<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02860507</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TGH015</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02860507</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Determine if Administration of Sugammadex Impacts Hospital Efficiency</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Blinded-assessor, Single Center Study to Determine if Administration of Sugammadex, When Used to Reverse Deep Neuromuscular Blockade (NMB) After Open Abdominal Surgery, Impacts Hospital Efficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of South Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of South Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of Sugammadex in rapidly reversing deep
      neuromuscular blockaded (induced by rocuronium)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants in the study group will receive a single bolus of Sugammadex (4.0mg/kg) prior to
      extubation. In the post-anesthesia care unit (PACU), a blinded safety-assessor will use the
      visual analog scale to clinically assess post-operative pain. Post-operative nausea and
      vomiting (PONV) will be assessed using a PONV rating scale every 30 minutes until PACU
      discharge. All patients will be monitored with continuous pulse-oximetry.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Operating room (OR) turnover time when using Sugammadex instead of combination of Neostigmine and Glycopyrrolate.</measure>
    <time_frame>through start of next surgery, average of 2 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients who experience postoperative nausea and vomiting, post-operative pain, and post-operative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>through discharge from hospital, average of 72 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuromuscular Blockade</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neostigmine + Glycopyrrolate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Neostigmine 0.06 mg/kg and Glycopyrrolate 0.04mg/kg iv</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sugammadex</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sugammadex 4mg/kg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sugammadex</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>sugammadex</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bridion</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neostigmine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Neostigmine + Glycopyrrolate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glycopyrrolate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Neostigmine + Glycopyrrolate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients scheduled for open ventral hernia repair or open colectomy

          -  ASA class I-III

          -  18 years and older

          -  Subjects with a body mass index (BMI) of &lt;45kg/m2 and weight less than 150kg

          -  Subjects who have given written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with medical conditions and/or undergoing surgical procedures that are not
             compatible with the use of the TOF-Watch® SX (e.g., injuries to the thumbs/distal
             forearms, bilateral ulnar nerve damage or subjects with cardiac pacemaker

          -  Subjects known or suspected to have neuromuscular disorders impairing neuromuscular
             blockade (e.g., subjects with myasthenia gravis)

          -  Subjects known or suspected to have significant renal dysfunction (e.g. creatinine
             clearance &lt; 30 mL.min-1

          -  Subjects known or suspected to have a (family)history of malignant hyperthermia; have
             significant hepatic dysfunction

          -  Subjects known or suspected to have an allergy to opiates/opioids, muscle relaxants or
             other medications used during general anesthesia;

          -  Subjects known or suspected to be hypersensitive to Sugammadex or other cyclodextrins
             or Rocuronium or any of its excipients

          -  Subjects who have a contraindication to, Rocuronium or Sugammadex

          -  Female subjects who are pregnant

          -  Morbidly obese subjects with a BMI &gt; 45 kg/m2 or weight more than 150 kg
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turner DA, Smith G. Evaluation of the combined effects of atropine and neostigmine on the lower oesophageal sphincter. Br J Anaesth. 1985 Oct;57(10):956-9.</citation>
    <PMID>4041322</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Proakis AG, Harris GB. Comparative penetration of glycopyrrolate and atropine across the blood--brain and placental barriers in anesthetized dogs. Anesthesiology. 1978 May;48(5):339-44.</citation>
    <PMID>646152</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chhibber AK, Lustik SJ, Thakur R, Francisco DR, Fickling KB. Effects of anticholinergics on postoperative vomiting, recovery, and hospital stay in children undergoing tonsillectomy with or without adenoidectomy. Anesthesiology. 1999 Mar;90(3):697-700.</citation>
    <PMID>10078669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tramèr MR, Fuchs-Buder T. Omitting antagonism of neuromuscular block: effect on postoperative nausea and vomiting and risk of residual paralysis. A systematic review. Br J Anaesth. 1999 Mar;82(3):379-86.</citation>
    <PMID>10434820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheng CR, Sessler DI, Apfel CC. Does neostigmine administration produce a clinically important increase in postoperative nausea and vomiting? Anesth Analg. 2005 Nov;101(5):1349-55.</citation>
    <PMID>16243993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naguib M, Brull SJ. Update on neuromuscular pharmacology. Curr Opin Anaesthesiol. 2009 Aug;22(4):483-90. doi: 10.1097/ACO.0b013e32832b8cff. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19384229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pühringer FK, Rex C, Sielenkämper AW, Claudius C, Larsen PB, Prins ME, Eikermann M, Khuenl-Brady KS. Reversal of profound, high-dose rocuronium-induced neuromuscular blockade by sugammadex at two different time points: an international, multicenter, randomized, dose-finding, safety assessor-blinded, phase II trial. Anesthesiology. 2008 Aug;109(2):188-97. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e31817f5bc7.</citation>
    <PMID>18648227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plaud B, Meretoja O, Hofmockel R, Raft J, Stoddart PA, van Kuijk JH, Hermens Y, Mirakhur RK. Reversal of rocuronium-induced neuromuscular blockade with sugammadex in pediatric and adult surgical patients. Anesthesiology. 2009 Feb;110(2):284-94. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e318194caaa.</citation>
    <PMID>19194156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hemmerling TM, Zaouter C, Geldner G, Nauheimer D. Sugammadex--a short review and clinical recommendations for the cardiac anesthesiologist. Ann Card Anaesth. 2010 Sep-Dec;13(3):206-16. doi: 10.4103/0971-9784.69052. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20826961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abad-Gurumeta A, Ripollés-Melchor J, Casans-Francés R, Espinosa A, Martínez-Hurtado E, Fernández-Pérez C, Ramírez JM, López-Timoneda F, Calvo-Vecino JM; Evidence Anaesthesia Review Group. A systematic review of sugammadex vs neostigmine for reversal of neuromuscular blockade. Anaesthesia. 2015 Dec;70(12):1441-52. doi: 10.1111/anae.13277. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26558858</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koyuncu O, Turhanoglu S, Ozbakis Akkurt C, Karcıoglu M, Ozkan M, Ozer C, Sessler DI, Turan A. Comparison of sugammadex and conventional reversal on postoperative nausea and vomiting: a randomized, blinded trial. J Clin Anesth. 2015 Feb;27(1):51-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinane.2014.08.010. Epub 2014 Dec 24.</citation>
    <PMID>25544263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sasaki N, Meyer MJ, Malviya SA, Stanislaus AB, MacDonald T, Doran ME, Igumenshcheva A, Hoang AH, Eikermann M. Effects of neostigmine reversal of nondepolarizing neuromuscular blocking agents on postoperative respiratory outcomes: a prospective study. Anesthesiology. 2014 Nov;121(5):959-68. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000000440.</citation>
    <PMID>25225821</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy GS, Szokol JW, Marymont JH, Greenberg SB, Avram MJ, Vender JS. Residual neuromuscular blockade and critical respiratory events in the postanesthesia care unit. Anesth Analg. 2008 Jul;107(1):130-7. doi: 10.1213/ane.0b013e31816d1268.</citation>
    <PMID>18635478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herbstreit F, Peters J, Eikermann M. Impaired upper airway integrity by residual neuromuscular blockade: increased airway collapsibility and blunted genioglossus muscle activity in response to negative pharyngeal pressure. Anesthesiology. 2009 Jun;110(6):1253-60. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e31819faa71.</citation>
    <PMID>19417617</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy GS, Szokol JW, Marymont JH, Greenberg SB, Avram MJ, Vender JS, Nisman M. Intraoperative acceleromyographic monitoring reduces the risk of residual neuromuscular blockade and adverse respiratory events in the postanesthesia care unit. Anesthesiology. 2008 Sep;109(3):389-98. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e318182af3b.</citation>
    <PMID>18719436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Butterly A, Bittner EA, George E, Sandberg WS, Eikermann M, Schmidt U. Postoperative residual curarization from intermediate-acting neuromuscular blocking agents delays recovery room discharge. Br J Anaesth. 2010 Sep;105(3):304-9. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeq157. Epub 2010 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20576632</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Della Rocca G, Pompei L, Pagan DE Paganis C, Tesoro S, Mendola C, Boninsegni P, Tempia A, Manstretta S, Zamidei L, Gratarola A, Murabito P, Fuggiano L, DI Marco P. Reversal of rocuronium induced neuromuscular block with sugammadex or neostigmine: a large observational study. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2013 Oct;57(9):1138-45. doi: 10.1111/aas.12155. Epub 2013 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23849107</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 9, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of South Florida</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Enrico Camporesi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Attending Anesthesiologist &amp; Director of Research, SE</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neostigmine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glycopyrrolate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

