<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02864238</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB #151566</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02864238</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Utility of Clinical Milestones Pathway in a Cardiovascular ICU</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Utility of an Electronic Based Milestone Pathway on the Care of Patients Undergoing Cardiac Valve Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vanderbilt University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The economic burden of health care is becoming a greater burden from year to year. Medicare
      spending, which represented 20 percent of national health spending in 2013, grew 3.4 percent
      to $585.7 billion, a slowdown from growth of 4.0 percent in 2012. This slowdown was
      attributed largely to slower enrollment growth and impacts of the Affordable Care Act (ACA)
      and sequestration. Per-enrollee spending in 2013 grew at about the same rate as 2012.

      The push to create Accountable Care Organizations (ACO) has taken these initiatives a step
      further. The goal would be to move away from a fee for service system and base reimbursement
      on quality of care. Clinical metrics, re-admissions, and patient satisfaction in categories
      of acute myocardial infarction, congestive heart failure, pneumonia, surgeries and healthcare
      associated infections will be the foci for 2013. Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services
      (CMS) has also initiated a valve bundled payment system that encompasses total patient care
      for 90 days, including readmissions.

      Leapfrog and the ACO movement along with the nonprofit group Institute for Health Care
      Improvement have placed quality and cost effectiveness into the spotlight for clinicians in
      the ICU and beyond. While clinicians have always been focused on evidence based therapies
      with little concern for cost, in the new era of healthcare understanding cost, value and
      effectiveness of therapies will be key for improved patient outcomes and institutional
      solvency in trying economic times.

      Vanderbilt elected to enroll in the CMS valve bundle trial. The Leadership team in the heart
      and vascular institute identified the importance of an electronic medical record that
      includes display and utilization of key drivers of quality and success across the continuum
      of care (Preoperative assessment to discharge up to 90 days) in the bundled payment model of
      care. A multidisciplinary team was developed in conjunction with nurses, midlevel providers,
      multi-specialty physicians, case managers, informatics specialists, and performance
      improvement representatives to develop an electronic pathway of care using evidence based and
      best practices for cardiac surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A multidisciplinary team consisting of physicians, pharmacists, nutritionists, social
      workers, bedside nurses, physical therapists, and mid-level providers developed the structure
      and key elements of the milestone pathway. The Vanderbilt University Informatics Team
      developed the electronic version of the consensus milestones. The pathway encompasses 17
      phases beginning with the pre-procedure evaluation and continuing through the perioperative
      period until the three-month follow-up post procedure. The nursing staff performed
      documentation of pathway stages during the index hospitalization, and the milestone stage was
      displayed on the door of the patient's room. The milestone stage was discussed on
      multi-disciplinary bedside rounds in the ICU, and if a patient could not progress to the next
      stage the nurse would document the reason for failure to progress.

      In this study, the investigators compared patients who underwent valve surgery with the
      milestone pathway in place, to patients who underwent valve surgery without the milestone
      pathway in place. Patients were adjusted according to baseline characteristics such as
      demographics, procedure, and proceduralist collected from the electronic medical record and
      Society of Thoracic Surgeons (STS) database.

      The investigators primary clinical outcome is mortality, and secondary clinical outcomes
      include the incidence of re-intubation within 48 hours, acute kidney injury as defined by
      Kidney Disease Improving Global Outcome (KDIGO) criteria, delirium, major adverse cardiac
      events (MACE), and infection rates for catheter and central line associated infections as
      well as sternal wound infection. In addition the investigators examined financial outcomes
      including variance in direct and total cost, and direct and total cost per patient.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Post operative day 0 to post operative day 7</time_frame>
    <description>mortality rate for patients during index hospitalization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Re-intubation rate within 48 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours of index procedure</time_frame>
    <description>re-intubation rate within 48 hours of index procedure for patients undergoing cardiac surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute Kidney Injury as defined by KDIGO (Kidney Disease Improving Global Outcomes) guidelines</measure>
    <time_frame>All time points occurring between post operative day 0 and Post operative day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of acute Kidney Injury as defined by KDIGO (Kidney Disease Improving Global Outcomes) guidelines during index hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>All time points occurring between post operative day 0 and Post operative day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of delirium as defined by Intensive Care Unit Confusion Assessment Method (ICU-CAM) scoring system during index hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>major adverse cardiac events</measure>
    <time_frame>All time points occurring between post operative day 0 and Post operative day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of major adverse cardiac events defined as death, need for re-operation, myocardial infarction during index hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infection rates</measure>
    <time_frame>All time points occurring between post operative day 0 and Post operative day 7</time_frame>
    <description>defined as Catheter Associated Urinary Tract Infection (CAUTI), Central Line Associated Blood Stream Infection (CLABSI), sternal wound infection during index hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Direct cost</measure>
    <time_frame>All time points occurring between post operative day 0 and Post operative day 7</time_frame>
    <description>summation of costs directly attributable to patient care during index hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>total cost</measure>
    <time_frame>All time points occurring between post operative day 0 and Post operative day 7</time_frame>
    <description>summation of costs directly attributable to patient care, as well as costs to the patient which are not directly attributable to patient care (unspecified charges to patient such as OR utilization fees, laboratory staff fees, etc.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>variance in cost</measure>
    <time_frame>All time points occurring between post operative day 0 and Post operative day 7</time_frame>
    <description>total and direct costs attributable to each patient undergoing cardiac valve surgery will be averaged for all patients undergoing cardiac valve surgery during the study period. Each individual patient's direct and total costs will then be compared to the averaged cost for all patients undergoing cardiac valve surgery hospitalization to obtain a variance in cost for each individual patient undergoing cardiac valve surgery. The investigators will then compare average variance between the two cohorts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2401</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiac Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre intervention</arm_group_label>
    <description>This cohort consists of patients who underwent cardiac valve surgery during calender year 2013 prior to the institution of the electronic milestone pathway</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>post intervention</arm_group_label>
    <description>This cohort consists of patients who underwent cardiac valve surgery during calender year 2014 after the electronic milestone pathway had been instituted</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>electronic milestone pathway</intervention_name>
    <description>an electronic based, clinical milestone driven pathway developed to guide the care of cardiac valve surgery patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>post intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients who underwent cardiac valve surgery at vanderbilt university medical center
        between 1/1/2013 and 12/31/2014
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Underwent cardiac valve surgery at vanderbilt university medical center between
             1/1/2013 and 12/31/2014

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lee Parmley, MD, JD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 13, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 10, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 10, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 12, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Vanderbilt University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adam Kingeter</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>electronic milestone pathway</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiac valve surgery</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

