<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02863770</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HS-15-00784</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02863770</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Contrast EUS of the Pancreas</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Controlled Trial of Contrast Enhanced Endoscopic Ultrasound for Evaluation of Pancreas Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Endoscopic Ultrasound (EUS) is the leading method to evaluate the pancreas but
      there may be difficulty characterizing small lesions, tumors which are not adenocarcinomas
      and neoplasia in the setting of pancreatitis.

      INTERVENTION: The innovation in this project will be the addition of intravenous contrast to
      standard EUS examination if the pancreas.

      PURPOSE: The aim is to determine if contrast enhances the ability of EUS to accurately
      diagnose lesions and target biopsies, and to define the quantitative features of this method.

      STUDY POPULATION:The population will include patients with pancreas cysts, masses, and
      inflammation presenting for EUS as part of standard clinical care.

      METHODOLOGY: This will be a prospective tandem trial involving conventional EUS, followed by
      EUS with contrast, followed by subsequent quantitative processing of contrast EUS imaging.

      ENDOINTS:Study endpoints will include the yield contrast EUS to evaluate pancreas cysts,
      masses, and inflammation. The impact of contrast EUS to better target the FNA of the chosen
      lesion will be assessed. Intra and interobserver variability will be assessed by comparing
      conventional EUS and contrast EUS of each case in a random order (intraobserver agreement)
      and among a group of blinded endosonographers (interobserver agreement).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      AIM Early detection of pancreas cancer and precursors lesions improves survival. The
      investigators aim is to gauge whether quantitative contrast endoscopic ultrasound (EUS)
      improves the evaluation of pancreas tumors and precursors lesions including cysts.

      DESIGN The study will be a prospective tandem contrast EUS trial. All EUS will be performed
      as part of standard clinical care.

      Conventional EUS Standard EUS will first be performed using the 180 series linear array
      echoendoscope (Olympus, Center Valley, PA). The alpha-10 image processor (Aloka America,
      Wallingford, CT) in B mode will be used to acquire images. A research coordinator will help
      to record key parameters. Thirty second cine clips of conventional EUS images will be
      captured to compare with contrast EUS clips and enable intra and interobserver variability
      comparison.

      Contrast Administration Definity contrast will be activated by 45 seconds of agitation
      (VialMix, Lantheus, North Billerica, MA) and injected through the intravenous peripheral line
      which is placed to administer fluids. The investigators will administer a bolus dose of
      10microliter (microL)/kg within 30-60 seconds followed by 10ml of saline flush. Up to 2 bolus
      injections will be administered during each case and doppler sonography will be used between
      them to induce microbubble destruction.

      Contrast EUS: Following contrast administration prospective assessment will be performed
      using the Olympus endoscope and images processed using the Alpha 10 system. Harmonic
      detection conversion software installed on the alpha 10 processor to enable detection. Core
      parameters for comparison to conventional EUS will be captured prospectively.

      Quantitative Processing: For each bolus 30 seconds of cine imaging will be captured for post
      processing and for comparison with conventional EUS imaging (intra and interobserver
      variability). Images of the lesion (5mm x 5mm region) and adjacent normal tissue (5mm x 5mm)
      regions will be captured to facilitate quantitative assessment. Quantitative analytic
      software will then be used to generate time intensity curves and associated values including
      peak intensity (PI), time to peak (TTP), wash-in-slope (WIS), rise time (RT), mean transit
      time (MTT), and time from peak to one-half (TPH).

      DRUG/DEVICE INFORMATION

      Definity: Definity is an intravenous contrast agent. It is comprised of 1.1-3.3um micropheres
      containing perflutren (octafluoropropane) which is cleared by respiration.

      The gas is encapsulated lipid shells which are metabolized to free fatty acids and
      hepatically cleared.

      The Olympus 180 linear echoendoscope will be used in all procedures which are being done for
      standard clinical indications. The Aloka SSD-Alpha 10-Processor will be used for image
      capture. Post EUS quantitative processing will be performed using QLAB quantification
      software (Philips Healthcare, Bothel, WA).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The yield of EUS versus contrast EUS to diagnose pancreas cystic lesions, mass lesion, and origin of pancreatitis.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The endoscopist will perform conventional EUS and classify the lesion as described below, this will be recorded by the research assistant prior to contrast EUS. Contrast will then be administered and the classification of contrast EUS recorded in real time. The gold standard to calculate the yields of the modality will be on pathology and clinical diagnosis at three and six months. Additionally we will assess whether contrast impacted assessment of size and diagnosis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Targeting of FINE NEEDLE ASPIRATION (FNA) of pancreas lesions.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>A) The decision to perform a FINE NEEDLE ASPIRATION of the lesion will be based solely on the standard EUS exam. After making the decision to perform the FNA contrast EUS will be performed. We will assess the degree to whether contrast administration helped to better target the FNA of the chosen lesion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitative Parameters of Pancreas Lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative parameters of pancreas mass lesions will be performed by comparing the quantitative parameters post processing of adenocarcinoma, neuroendocrine and other lesion, and chronic pancreatitis. The final diagnosis will be based on pathology and 3 and 6 month follow up. Comparison variables will include time to peak (SECONDS), rise time (SECONDS), mean transit time (SECONDS), and time from peak to one-half (SECONDS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatitis</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cyst</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Contrast EUS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Undergoing EUS for pancreatic indication (cyst, pancreatitis, mass)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EUS enhanced with contrast to evaluate pancreas</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive intravenous contrast during EUS to assess whether it increases diagnostic yield of the examination</description>
    <arm_group_label>Contrast EUS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients undergoing endoscopic ultrasound for standard pancreatic indications.

          -  Patients must have unexplained pancreatitis, pancreas mass(es), or pancreatic cystic
             lesions (&gt;1cm or worrisome features on imaging).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients &lt;18 years of age, pregnant women, and lactating mothers will be excluded.
             Subjects with unstable ischemic disease will be excluded. Additionally, those with
             known or suspected right-to-left, bi-directional, or transient right-to-left cardiac
             shunts will be excluded given theoretical (though clinically insignificant) risk of
             embolization.

          -  Patients with an allergy to Definity will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maria Trujillo</last_name>
    <phone>323 409 6939</phone>
    <email>mit@usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>James Buxbaum, MD</last_name>
    <phone>323 409 5371</phone>
    <email>jbuxbaum@usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles County Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James Buxbaum, MD</last_name>
      <phone>323-409-5371</phone>
      <email>jbuxbaum@usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Maria Trujillo</last_name>
      <phone>323 409 6939</phone>
      <email>mit@usc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Napoleon B, Alvarez-Sanchez MV, Gincoul R, Pujol B, Lefort C, Lepilliez V, Labadie M, Souquet JC, Queneau PE, Scoazec JY, Chayvialle JA, Ponchon T. Contrast-enhanced harmonic endoscopic ultrasound in solid lesions of the pancreas: results of a pilot study. Endoscopy. 2010 Jul;42(7):564-70. doi: 10.1055/s-0030-1255537. Epub 2010 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>20593334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kitano M, Kudo M, Yamao K, Takagi T, Sakamoto H, Komaki T, Kamata K, Imai H, Chiba Y, Okada M, Murakami T, Takeyama Y. Characterization of small solid tumors in the pancreas: the value of contrast-enhanced harmonic endoscopic ultrasonography. Am J Gastroenterol. 2012 Feb;107(2):303-10. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2011.354. Epub 2011 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>22008892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Săftoiu A, Vilmann P, Dietrich CF, Iglesias-Garcia J, Hocke M, Seicean A, Ignee A, Hassan H, Streba CT, Ioncică AM, Gheonea DI, Ciurea T. Quantitative contrast-enhanced harmonic EUS in differential diagnosis of focal pancreatic masses (with videos). Gastrointest Endosc. 2015 Jul;82(1):59-69. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2014.11.040. Epub 2015 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25792386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>King KG, Gulati M, Malhi H, Hwang D, Gill IS, Cheng PM, Grant EG, Duddalwar VA. Quantitative assessment of solid renal masses by contrast-enhanced ultrasound with time-intensity curves: how we do it. Abdom Imaging. 2015 Oct;40(7):2461-71. doi: 10.1007/s00261-015-0468-y. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26036794</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 1, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James Buxbaum</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Clinical Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>endosonography</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Cyst</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancrelipase</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

