<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02866435</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>25007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02866435</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Identifying the Brain Substrates of Hypoglycemia Unawareness in Type 1 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Identifying the Brain Substrates of Hypoglycemia Unawareness in Type 1 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate how the brain responds to low blood glucose in
      non-diabetic individuals. The ultimate goal is to understand the brain substrates of
      hypoglycemia unawareness, a condition that can occur in patients with type1 diabetes
      undergoing insulin treatment.In the present study, the investigators focus on differences
      between two groups of non-diabetic subjects: one group who experienced two episodes of
      hypoglycemia the day prior to the study (and supposedly developed some level of unawareness
      to hypoglycemia), and one group who did not. In this study, a 3 tesla MRI scanner is used to
      acquire brain images. The imaging system is identical to the ones used in hospitals.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypoglycemia, also called low blood glucose or low blood sugar, occurs when blood glucose
      drops below normal levels. When blood glucose starts to drop, the body reacts to this drop,
      trying to restore the blood glucose level. Symptoms of hypoglycemia are usually easily
      recognized. Hypoglycemia can be treated quickly and easily by eating or drinking a small
      amount of glucose-rich food. However some people with long history of diabetes can have an
      impaired response to hypoglycemia and therefore don't recognize the symptoms of hypoglycemia,
      condition called hypoglycemia unawareness. If not treated hypoglycemia can get worse and
      cause confusion, clumsiness, fainting etc. Currently, it is not fully understood which brain
      areas are involved in sensing the drop of glucose levels. Absence of such knowledge is a
      critical barrier to the design and monitoring of effective intervention strategies to avoid
      and/or reverse hypoglycemia unawareness. The purpose of this study is to investigate how the
      brain responds to low blood glucose in non-diabetic individuals. Specific focus is given to
      differences between two groups of non-diabetic subjects: one group who experienced two
      episodes of hypoglycemia the day prior to the study (and therefore supposedly developed some
      level of unawareness to hypoglycemia), and one group who did not.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline (i.e., normal glucose levels) functional connectivity, measured as a dimensionless correlation coefficient of MRI signals among brain areas, at hypoglycemia</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and immediately as hypoglycemia starts</time_frame>
    <description>Functional connectivity will be measured with MRI at 3 Tesla</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline (i.e., normal glucose levels) cerebral blood flow, measured in ml/min/100g, at hypoglycemia</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and immediately as hypoglycemia starts</time_frame>
    <description>Cerebral blood flow will be measured with MRI at 3 Tesla</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypoglycemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Euglycemia pre-conditioning</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will undergo two euglycemia (normal blood sugar) clamps (8-10 am and 1-3 pm) on day 1, where the target glucose during the clamp will be 95 mg/dl. For each clamp, participants will be given intravenous insulin for two hours and blood glucose will be maintained at target by the infusion of 20% dextrose, the rate of which will be adjusted based on measured blood glucose values collected every 5 minutes. Potassium phosphate will also be infused during each clamp. On next day (day 2), participants will undergo MRI session during experimental hypoglycemia, i.e., while their blood sugar is clamped from normal value to low value.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypoglycemia pre-conditioning</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will undergo two hypoglycemia (low blood sugar) clamps (8-10 am and 1-3 pm) on day 1, where target glucose during the clamp will be 50 mg/dl. For each clamp, participants will be given intravenous insulin for two hours and blood glucose will be maintained at target by the infusion of 20% dextrose, the rate of which will be adjusted based on measured blood glucose values collected every 5 minutes. Potassium phosphate will also be infused during each clamp. On next day (day 2), participants will undergo MRI session during experimental hypoglycemia, i.e., while their blood sugar is clamped from normal value to low value.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Insulin</intervention_name>
    <description>In each clamp, a small intravenous catheter is placed in participant's arm for infusion of insulin together with potassium phosphate and glucose. Insulin is a hormone that body makes naturally and it causes blood sugar to decrease. Insulin (and glucose) will be infused in calculated doses to maintain blood sugar level in the target range of 95 mg/dl or 50 mg/dl depending on the clamp.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Euglycemia pre-conditioning</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Hypoglycemia pre-conditioning</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Humulin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glucose</intervention_name>
    <description>Glucose is administered together with insulin and potassium phosphate during each clamp via the intravenous catheter. Glucose is a sugar and it is used to carefully regulate blood sugar level.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Euglycemia pre-conditioning</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Hypoglycemia pre-conditioning</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dextrose</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Potassium phosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Potassium phosphate is administered together with glucose and insulin during each clamp via the intravenous catheter. Potassium is a salt-like substance that is present in the blood.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Euglycemia pre-conditioning</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Hypoglycemia pre-conditioning</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>K Phos</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Participants will be included in the study, if they

          -  are non-diabetic

          -  are evaluated as not contraindicated (based on exclusion criteria)

          -  are age (within 5 years), gender, and body mass index (within 4 kg/m2) matched to
             patients with type 1 diabetes who have participated to a similar study which involved
             only the second part (day 2) of the current protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Participants will be excluded from the study, if they

          -  have any type of bio‐implant activated by mechanical, electronic, or magnetic means
             (e.g. cochlear implants, pacemakers, neurostimulators, bio stimulators, electronic
             infusion pumps)

          -  have any type of ferromagnetic bio‐implant that could potentially be displaced or
             damaged, such as aneurysm clips, metallic skull plates, etc

          -  have any retained metal in their body, either from a medical procedure or an injury

          -  have history of stroke, seizures, neurosurgical procedures, or arrhythmias

          -  are pregnant

          -  are currently using medication that can alter glucose metabolism or brain perfusion

          -  weight more than 300lbs (limit for MRI scanner)

          -  have concomitant medical problems that may prevent them from successfully completing
             the protocol

          -  lack capacity to consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Silvia Mangia, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anjali F Kumar, PA-C</last_name>
    <phone>612-624-0470</phone>
    <email>kumar045@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anjali F Kumar, PA-C</last_name>
      <phone>612-624-0470</phone>
      <email>kumar045@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth R Seaquist, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amir A Moheet, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Essa Yacoub, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lynn E Eberly, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cmrr.umn.edu/facultystaff/mangia/</url>
    <description>Description Profile of Principal Investigator</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mangia S, Tesfaye N, De Martino F, Kumar AF, Kollasch P, Moheet AA, Eberly LE, Seaquist ER. Hypoglycemia-induced increases in thalamic cerebral blood flow are blunted in subjects with type 1 diabetes and hypoglycemia unawareness. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2012 Nov;32(11):2084-90. doi: 10.1038/jcbfm.2012.117. Epub 2012 Aug 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22892724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bolo NR, Musen G, Simonson DC, Nickerson LD, Flores VL, Siracusa T, Hager B, Lyoo IK, Renshaw PF, Jacobson AM. Functional Connectivity of Insula, Basal Ganglia, and Prefrontal Executive Control Networks during Hypoglycemia in Type 1 Diabetes. J Neurosci. 2015 Aug 5;35(31):11012-23. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0319-15.2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26245963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wiegers EC, Becker KM, Rooijackers HM, von Samson-Himmelstjerna FC, Tack CJ, Heerschap A, de Galan BE, van der Graaf M. Cerebral blood flow response to hypoglycemia is altered in patients with type 1 diabetes and impaired awareness of hypoglycemia. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2017 Jun;37(6):1994-2001. doi: 10.1177/0271678X16658914. Epub 2016 Jan 1.</citation>
    <PMID>27389175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rooijackers HM, Wiegers EC, Tack CJ, van der Graaf M, de Galan BE. Brain glucose metabolism during hypoglycemia in type 1 diabetes: insights from functional and metabolic neuroimaging studies. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2016 Feb;73(4):705-22. doi: 10.1007/s00018-015-2079-8. Epub 2015 Oct 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26521082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 29, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 29, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoglycemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Unconsciousness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin, Globin Zinc</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Potassium phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

