<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02862925</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00070952</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R25TW009337</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02862925</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Introducing Fetal Scalp Stimulation as an Adjunct to Intermittent Auscultation in Low-Resource Settings.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Introducing Fetal Scalp Stimulation as an Adjunct to Intermittent Auscultation in Low-Resource Settings.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>John E. Fogarty International Center (FIC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fulbright</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a pilot study taking place in Moshi, Tanzania at the Kilimanjaro Christian
      Medical Centre (KCMC). The study aims to introduce fetal scalp stimulation into the
      intermittent auscultation protocols at KCMC, and to validate whether or not a handheld
      Doppler device can perform the fetal scalp stimulation test accurately.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Each year an estimated 2.6 million stillbirths occur globally. Nearly half, 1.2 million, of
      these occur intrapartum and an additional 650,000 children are born alive but die soon after
      birth due to birth asphyxia which is caused by hypoxia during labor. The vast majority of
      these deaths occur in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). In high-income countries,
      obstetric providers utilize electronic fetal monitoring (EFM) to monitor fetuses during
      labor, but controversy surrounds implementing this technology in LMICs. What observing EFM
      patterns has taught us is that fetuses that respond to scalp stimulation with a rise in their
      heart rate are essentially guaranteed to be well oxygenated. This physiologic phenomenon,
      known as the fetal scalp stimulation test (FSST), has potential to improve fetal monitoring
      in LMICs, but it has never been studied using Doppler technology. This study aims to collect
      information about the prevalence of fetal distress in an obstetric referral hospital, to test
      the sensitivity and specificity of FSST with a Doppler device, and to collect pilot data
      using FSST as an adjunct to improve fetal monitoring. The outcome of the study would be to
      identify a trend in cesarean delivery rate reduction, intrapartum stillbirth, and birth
      asphyxia.

      The vast majority of acute intrapartum-related morbidity and mortality occurs in low- and
      middle-income countries (LMIC) where the care of mothers and fetuses during labor remains
      under studied as is our understanding of how to implement and evaluate programs that address
      the delivery of quality care. Providing safe and effective obstetric care requires the
      development of processes that are appropriate for each clinical setting considering
      resources, burden of disease, and cultural factors as well as implementing those processes in
      an effective way so that they become standard practice over time. Internationally midwives
      employ intermittent auscultation (IA) to monitor fetuses with Pinard stethoscopes or Doppler
      devices. In high-resource settings providers rely on computerized electronic fetal monitoring
      (EFM) to identify signs of fetal acidosis, although this has not been shown superior to IA.
      Recently, the Federation International of Gynecology and Obstetrics published recommendations
      for adjunctive tests to fetal monitoring, but the recommendations were limited to the
      high-resource EFM paradigm. On this subject, an expert on fetal physiology from Nigeria
      stated, &quot;it is imperative that appropriate diagnostic and management modalities for fetal
      hypoxia be available and accessible. This is the only way the burden of perinatal morbidity
      and mortality can be reduced.&quot; Currently, fetal scalp stimulation (FSST) is the only
      low-cost, validated, adjunctive test that could be used to this end in the majority world,
      but it has not been studied for this purpose.

      STATEMENT OF THE PROBLEM Tanzania ranks as the 9th worst country for stillbirth globally
      experiencing 47,100 losses in 2015. Fetal monitoring at Kilimanjaro Christian Medical Center
      (KCMC) in Moshi, Tanzania, and countless labor wards around the world, is limited by the
      inability to accurately identify fetal acidosis in laboring patients. Misdiagnosis leads
      either to excess cesarean delivery (CD) or excess asphyxiated births. The study hypothesis is
      that implementing fetal scalp stimulation test (FSST) into labor protocols will reduce CD
      rates and improve neonatal outcomes leading to a reduction in maternal and neonatal
      mortality. Proving this will require a large randomized-controlled trial (RCT). The necessary
      first step is a proof-of-concept, feasibility study that will provide pilot data and inform
      future efforts.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility as measured by completion of all 3 study objectives</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Predicted fetal acidosis from cord blood pH (at thresholds of cord blood pH&lt;7.0, 7.1, and 7.2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is the sensitivity and specificity of the Doppler device to predict fetal acidosis based on the fetal scalp stimulation test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fetal distress rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators plan to define the fetal distress rate at a large referral center in Tanzania</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cesarean delivery rate</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, post introduction of fetal scalp stimulation (during labour)</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators plan to compare cesarean delivery rates before and after the introduction of fetal scalp stimulation to fetal monitoring protocols.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Birth asphyxia/stillbirth rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>NICU Admission Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">550</enrollment>
  <condition>Fetal Distress</condition>
  <condition>Stillbirth</condition>
  <condition>Birth Asphyxia</condition>
  <condition>Acidosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>A consecutive sample of 350 patients will be collected. After informed consent, data will be abstracted from the patient's record including day and time of delivery, method of delivery, parity, gestational age, meconium presence, heart rate abnormality and induction methods. For CD, the following data will be collected: decision-to-delivery time, Partogram adherence, time of each FSST, Apgar score, date and time of delivery and Comorbidities such as: Hypertension-spectrum disorders, Malaria, Postpartum Hemorrhage, Macrosomia, History of CD, Diabetes, Sickle Cell, and HIV status.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Post-intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study will take place on the labor ward at KCMC in Moshi, Tanzania. It will involve women who present to the labor ward in labor or who undergo an induction of labor. A consecutive sample of 350 patients will be collected. Study investigators will be present for 24 hours a day, 7 days a week on a rotating schedule during the enrollment period. All patients who fit inclusion and exclusion criteria will be approached if they are deemed medically stable.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fetal Scalp Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>During a routine vaginal exam, if there is concern for fetal distress based on local definitions, the midwife will gently stroke the fetal head with her finger. She will then observe for a rise in the fetal heart rate as observed by the Doppler monitor. A rise to above 15 beats per minute above the baseline is termed an &quot;acceleration&quot; and NEGATIVE test. Absence of an acceleration is a POSITIVE test and reason for intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Post-intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Gestational Age ≥ 37 weeks

          -  Singleton gestation

          -  Cephalic presentation

          -  First stage of labor

          -  Fetal distress diagnosed in the labor ward by either FHR &gt;160 or &lt;110, and/or grade
             2-3 meconium-stained liquor

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chorioamnionitis

          -  Known fetal anomaly

          -  Antepartum hemorrhage

          -  Eclampsia

          -  Other maternal/fetal factors precluding vaginal delivery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Schmitt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke UMC, Duke Global Health Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kilimanjaro Christian Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moshi</city>
        <state>Kilimanjaro</state>
        <country>Tanzania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Tanzania</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/topics</url>
    <description>Sustainable Development Goals &amp; Topics .:. Sustainable Development Knowledge Platform</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Visser GH, Ayres-de-Campos D; FIGO Intrapartum Fetal Monitoring Expert Consensus Panel. FIGO consensus guidelines on intrapartum fetal monitoring: Adjunctive technologies. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2015 Oct;131(1):25-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ijgo.2015.06.021.</citation>
    <PMID>26433402</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Omo-Aghoja L. Maternal and fetal Acid-base chemistry: a major determinant of perinatal outcome. Ann Med Health Sci Res. 2014 Jan;4(1):8-17. doi: 10.4103/2141-9248.126602. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24669324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark SL, Gimovsky ML, Miller FC. The scalp stimulation test: a clinical alternative to fetal scalp blood sampling. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1984 Feb 1;148(3):274-7.</citation>
    <PMID>6695974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark SL, Gimovsky ML, Miller FC. Fetal heart rate response to scalp blood sampling. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 1982 Nov 15;144(6):706-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7137256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skupski DW, Rosenberg CR, Eglinton GS. Intrapartum fetal stimulation tests: a meta-analysis. Obstet Gynecol. 2002 Jan;99(1):129-34.</citation>
    <PMID>11777523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rathore AM, Ramji S, Devi CB, Saini S, Manaktala U, Batra S. Fetal scalp stimulation test: an adjunct to intermittent auscultation in non-reassuring fetal status during labor. J Obstet Gynaecol Res. 2011 Jul;37(7):819-24. doi: 10.1111/j.1447-0756.2010.01442.x. Epub 2011 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>21410829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>fetal monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>cesarean delivery</keyword>
  <keyword>obstetrics</keyword>
  <keyword>midwifery</keyword>
  <keyword>developing countries</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acidosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Asphyxia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stillbirth</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Asphyxia Neonatorum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fetal Distress</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

