<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02863783</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HS-16-00032</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02863783</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>EUS Fiducial for Pancreas Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Trial of Endoscopic Ultrasound Guided Coil Placement to Facilitate Intraoperative Assessment of Pancreas Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Pancreas tumor localization makes minimally invasive surgical resection of
      pancreas tumors very challenging. Recently, an endoscopic ultrasound needle system has been
      developed which enables fiducial coils to be placed at the precise site of biopsy.

      INTERVENTION: At time of EUS guided biopsy the fine needle fiducial device will be used to
      place fiducials in the tumor. During surgery we will assess whether it improves tumor
      visualization.

      OBJECTIVES: We aim to determine the feasibility to use EUS guided fiducials placement to mark
      pancreas tumors in 20 patients and to assess whether the fiducials impact tumor visualization
      during pancreas surgery.

      STUDY POPULATION: Patients with pancreas adenocarcinoma or neuroendocrine lesions.

      STUDY ENDPOINTS: The main outcome will be to assess whether the coil may be successfully
      placed during EUS and whether they impact tumor visualization during surgery FOLLOW UP and
      ANALYSIS: Patients will be assessed at the time of EUS and surgery. This is a pilot analysis
      with the intention to assess feasibility and to gather data to power larger trials.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Minimally invasive pancreatic surgery diminishes the morbidity and mortality of the
      potentially curative procedures. However precise targeting of small adenocarcinomas and
      neuroendocrine tumors is challenging.

      Given safety, precision, and ease EUS guided pancreatic fiducial placement has emerged as a
      favored method to mark tumors for radiation therapy. The experimental aspect of this
      procedure is gauge whether EUS guided fiducial placement improves the intraoperative
      assessment of pancreas tumors. We will use the recently introduced (FDA approved) Beacon EUS
      guided fiducial system to perform placement. The fiducial will not alter the surgical plan in
      this study. However, the relative ability to detect the marker during standard pancreatic
      surgery will help to inform whether this strategy may be used in improve future approaches to
      pancreas surgery.

      The study will be a prospective trial. All EUS will be performed as part of standard clinical
      care.

      Conventional EUS+FNA The linear array echoendoscope will be used to identify the pancreas
      adenocarcinoma and neuroendocrine tumors. The Beacon EUS system/delivery sheath will be
      passed and fine needle aspiration performed to confirm cytology. This is required for
      standard clinical care. The delivery sheath will be left in place. The cytologist will
      perform bedside interpretation as is standard clinical care.

      EUS guided coil injection If adenocarcinoma or neuroendocrine tumor is confirmed by fine
      needle aspiration the fine needle fiducial accessory will be passed through the delivery
      sheath (whose position on the tumor is now &quot;biopsy confirmed&quot; and 1-3 fiducials (coil type)
      will be introduced into the lesion. This process will be guided by EUS which is being
      performed for standard clinical care. Fluoroscopy not be utilized.

      Pancreas Surgery: At time of surgery the experimental component is that it will be gauged
      whether the fiducial impacts the ability to assess the tumor relative to lesions of
      comparable size. Whether the fiducial improves or does not improve assessment will be scaled
      on a 1-10 scale where 5 is the standard ease of detection of similarly sized tumors (without
      fiducials) based on the attending surgeon's experience.

      However, the fiducial will not be used to target the lesion or alter the surgical plan. The
      surgical plan will be based on preoperative clinical imaging, intraoperative findings, and
      intraoperative ultrasound (standard clinical care). The research coordinator will be present
      during surgery to facilitate timely acquisition of data. In some cases patient are deemed to
      not be resection candidates at the time of surgery if for example unexpected metastasis are
      found. The EUS guided fiducial placement will have no bearing on whether resection is done or
      not.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 23, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Proportion of patients in which the fiducial was successfully placed/total patients in which fiducial attempted</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>the primary outcome will be to assess whether the coil may be successfully placed. This will be reported as the proportion of patients in which the fiducial was successfully placed/total patients in which fiducial attempted.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relative Ease of Detection of the Tumor with Fiducial</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>A co-primary outcome will be to assess whether the coil may detected at time of surgery. The proportion of patients in whom the fiducial may be easily detected will also be reported. The relative ease of detection of the tumor (with fiducial) will be compared to the ease of detection of similar sized tumors without the fiducial. A QUESTIONNAIRE will be used in which each of detection by the attending surgeon will be recorded with 5 being each of detection of similar (histology/size) tumor without fiducial.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pancreatitis, abdominal pain, infection, bleeding following placement.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>all complications including acute pancreatitis, abdominal pain, infection, bleeding following EUS guided fiducial placement will be recorded and reported. This will also be reported as the proportion of patients who develop a complication divided by total patients. Individual types of complications will be similarly reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fiducial Placement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>EUS with Fiducial Placement into Tumor</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EUS with Fiducial</intervention_name>
    <description>EUS will be used to place fiducial into pancreas tumor at time of biopsy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fiducial Placement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients undergoing endoscopic ultrasound for preoperative evaluation before planned
        pancreatic surgery for suspected adenocarcinoma and neuroendocrine tumors will be eligible.
        Rapid onsite evaluation is performed for all pancreas EUS as part of standard procedures.
        In this process the cytologist examines the cells and makes a determination whether the
        aspirate contains malignant or benign tissue. Fiducials will only be placed if cytologic
        confirmation of malignancy at the site is obtained.

        Tumors of sizes 5mm-4cm will be eligible as there may be benefit in marking small tumors
        given difficulty finding them with intraoperative ultrasound. Moderately large pancreas
        tumors may also cause fibrosis which makes identification for resection difficult. Coil
        placement in regions of cytologically confirmed malignant cells may be helpful. Fiducial
        markers will only be placed if the initial evaluation (abdominal computed tomography or
        magnetic resonance imaging) indicates resectability. If finding of nonresectability (i.e.
        liver metastasis) are seen on EUS then fiducials will not be placed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1) Patients with INR &gt;1.5 2) Platelet county &lt;100 3) Metal allergy 4) Pregnant 5) &lt;18
             years of age 6) Patients with pancreatic lymphoma will also be excluded as this is
             treated with chemotherapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jessica Serna</last_name>
    <phone>323 409 6939</phone>
    <email>Sernaj@usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>James Buxbaum, MD</last_name>
    <phone>323 409 5371</phone>
    <email>jbuxbaum@usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles County Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James Buxbaum, MD</last_name>
      <phone>323-409-5371</phone>
      <email>jbuxbaum@usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jessica Serna</last_name>
      <phone>323 409 6939</phone>
      <email>Sernaj@usc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Park WG, Yan BM, Schellenberg D, Kim J, Chang DT, Koong A, Patalano C, Van Dam J. EUS-guided gold fiducial insertion for image-guided radiation therapy of pancreatic cancer: 50 successful cases without fluoroscopy. Gastrointest Endosc. 2010 Mar;71(3):513-8. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2009.10.030.</citation>
    <PMID>20189509</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farrell JJ, Sherrod A, Parekh D. EUS-guided fine-needle tattooing for preoperative localization of early pancreatic adenocarcinoma. Gastrointest Endosc. 2009 Jan;69(1):176-7. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.03.1069. Epub 2008 Jul 2.</citation>
    <PMID>18599051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lennon AM, Newman N, Makary MA, Edil BH, Shin EJ, Khashab MA, Hruban RH, Wolfgang CL, Schulick RD, Giday S, Canto MI. EUS-guided tattooing before laparoscopic distal pancreatic resection (with video). Gastrointest Endosc. 2010 Nov;72(5):1089-94. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2010.07.023.</citation>
    <PMID>21034909</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 31, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James Buxbaum</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Clinical Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancrelipase</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

