<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02522715</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00011227</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2015-01103</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>11227</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CRS00001390</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>IRB00011227</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA069533</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02522715</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enzalutamide and Cabazitaxel in Treating Patients With Metastatic, Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Trial of Concurrent Chemohormonal Therapy Using Enzalutamide (MDV-3100) and Cabazitaxel in Patients With Metastatic Castration Resistant Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies the side effects and best dose of cabazitaxel when given
      together with enzalutamide in treating patients with prostate cancer that has spread to other
      places in the body (metastatic) and has not responded to treatment with hormones or no longer
      responds to treatment with hormones (hormone-resistant). Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as
      cabazitaxel, work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the
      cells, by stopping them from dividing, or by stopping them from spreading. Androgen can cause
      the growth of prostate cancer cells. Hormone therapy using enzalutamide may fight prostate
      cancer by blocking the use of androgen by the tumor cells. Giving cabazitaxel together with
      enzalutamide may work better in treating metastatic, hormone-resistant prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the safety and tolerability of combination treatment with enzalutamide and
      cabazitaxel (as determined by percent dose limiting toxicities [DLT], where DLT &lt; 17% is
      consistent with it being a tolerable combination).

      II. To determine the efficacy of treatment with the hormonal agent enzalutamide and the
      chemotherapy cabazitaxel in combination in men with metastatic castration-resistant prostate
      cancer (CRPC) (as determined by percent of patients achieving &gt;= 90% prostate specific
      antigen [PSA] declines following initiation of treatment).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To further define the anticancer effect and safety profile of the combination of
      enzalutamide and cabazitaxel.

      II. Collect toxicity data (description of adverse events). III. Determine PSA response
      (percent of patients who achieve &gt;= 50% PSA decline and &gt;= 30% PSA decline).

      IV. Examine pharmacokinetic (PK) data of cabazitaxel to characterize enzalutamide and
      cabazitaxel pharmacokinetic blood levels.

      V. Determine tumor response by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 for
      measurable disease and Prostate Cancer Working Group 2 criteria for non-measurable (bone)
      disease.

      VI. Determine overall survival.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine baseline (and at progression) biological tumor characteristics to evaluate
      for possible biomarkers indicative or predictive of response: apoptosis by cleaved caspase 3;
      androgen signaling axis (including but not limited to: androgen receptor expression, androgen
      receptor splice variants, and intratumoral androgen levels), and glucocorticoid receptor.

      II. To collect circulating tumor cells (CTCs) and determine the degree to which tumor
      characteristics (delineated above) are shared by the CTCs.

      III. To collect plasma and serum pre-treatment and at progression for assessment of
      circulating micro-ribonucleic acid (RNA)s and other circulating markers.

      IV. To collect buffy coat to evaluate for steroid transporters.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose de-escalation study of cabazitaxel.

      Patients receive cabazitaxel intravenously (IV) over 1 hour on day 1 and enzalutamide orally
      (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-21 (days 2-21 of course 1). Patients also receive prednisone
      PO twice daily (BID) as standard of care with cabazitaxel. Courses repeat every 21 days for
      6-10 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients may
      continue enzalutamide PO QD on days 1-28 in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 28 days and then every 6
      months for up to 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 28, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of dose limiting toxicities graded by National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 4.0 (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistical analysis will be conducted. The proportion estimate will be reported with 95% confidence interval using exact method.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PSA response 1, defined as &gt;= 90% PSA decline from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 28</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistical analysis will be conducted. The proportion estimate will be reported with 95% confidence interval using exact method. As an exploratory subgroup analysis, the various PSA response rates will be estimated in two subgroups that either received prior abiraterone or had not received prior abiraterone.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events graded by National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days after the last dose of study medication</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistical analysis will be conducted. The proportion estimate will be reported with 95% confidence interval using exact method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistical analysis will be conducted. The median overall survival will be estimated with 95% confidence interval (if available). Kaplan-Meier plot will be used to graphically illustrate the overall survival distribution.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters of cabazitaxel: Max plasma concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, and 24 hours after the start of cabazitaxel infusion of courses 1 and 2</time_frame>
    <description>Mean plasma concentration (Cmax) will be plotted over time for cabazitaxel (day 1, cycle 1) and cabazitaxel co-administered with enzalutamide (day1, cycle 2). Noncompartmental pharmacokinetic analysis will be performed on individual concentration-time data to calculate maximum concentration from 0 hours to last measureable concentration for cabazitaxel administered alone or coadministered with enzalutamide.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters of cabazitaxel: Mean Area Under the Curve (AUC).</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, and 24 hours after the start of cabazitaxel infusion of courses 1 and 2</time_frame>
    <description>Mean area under the curve (AUC) will be plotted over time for cabazitaxel (day 1, cycle 1) and cabazitaxel co-administered with enzalutamide (day1, cycle 2). Noncompartmental pharmacokinetic analysis will be performed on individual concentration-time data to calculate AUC from 0 hours to last measureable concentration for cabazitaxel administered alone or coadministered with enzalutamide.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters of cabazitaxel: Mean Cabazitaxel Half-Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, and 24 hours after the start of cabazitaxel infusion of courses 1 and 2</time_frame>
    <description>Mean cabazitaxel half-life will be plotted over time for cabazitaxel (day 1, cycle 1) and cabazitaxel co-administered with enzalutamide (day1, cycle 2). Noncompartmental pharmacokinetic analysis will be performed on individual concentration-time data to calculate half-life from 0 hours to last measureable concentration for cabazitaxel administered alone or coadministered with enzalutamide.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PSA response 2, defined as &gt;= 50% PSA decline from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 28</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistical analysis will be conducted. The proportion estimate will be reported with 95% confidence interval using exact method. As an exploratory subgroup analysis, the various PSA response rates will be estimated in two subgroups that either received prior abiraterone or had not received prior abiraterone.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PSA response 3, defined as &gt;= 30% PSA decline from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 28</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistical analysis will be conducted. The proportion estimate will be reported with 95% confidence interval using exact method. As an exploratory subgroup analysis, the various PSA response rates will be estimated in two subgroups that either received prior abiraterone or had not received prior abiraterone.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">39</enrollment>
  <condition>Castration Levels of Testosterone</condition>
  <condition>Castration-Resistant Prostate Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Prostate Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Prostate Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cabazitaxel, enzalutamide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive cabazitaxel IV over 1 hour on day 1 and enzalutamide PO QD on days 1-21 (days 2-21 of course 1). Patients also receive prednisone PO BID as standard of care with cabazitaxel. Courses repeat every 21 days for 6-10 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients may continue enzalutamide PO QD on days 1-28 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cabazitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cabazitaxel, enzalutamide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Jevtana</other_name>
    <other_name>RPR-116258A</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxoid XRP6258</other_name>
    <other_name>XRP-6258</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enzalutamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cabazitaxel, enzalutamide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ASP9785</other_name>
    <other_name>MDV3100</other_name>
    <other_name>Xtandi</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cabazitaxel, enzalutamide)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological Study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cabazitaxel, enzalutamide)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prednisone</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cabazitaxel, enzalutamide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>.delta.1-Cortisone</other_name>
    <other_name>1, 2-Dehydrocortisone</other_name>
    <other_name>Adasone</other_name>
    <other_name>Cortancyl</other_name>
    <other_name>Dacortin</other_name>
    <other_name>DeCortin</other_name>
    <other_name>Decortisyl</other_name>
    <other_name>Decorton</other_name>
    <other_name>Delta 1-Cortisone</other_name>
    <other_name>Delta-Dome</other_name>
    <other_name>Deltacortene</other_name>
    <other_name>Deltacortisone</other_name>
    <other_name>Deltadehydrocortisone</other_name>
    <other_name>Deltasone</other_name>
    <other_name>Deltison</other_name>
    <other_name>Deltra</other_name>
    <other_name>Econosone</other_name>
    <other_name>Lisacort</other_name>
    <other_name>Meprosona-F</other_name>
    <other_name>Metacortandracin</other_name>
    <other_name>Meticorten</other_name>
    <other_name>Ofisolona</other_name>
    <other_name>Orasone</other_name>
    <other_name>Panafcort</other_name>
    <other_name>Panasol-S</other_name>
    <other_name>Paracort</other_name>
    <other_name>PRED</other_name>
    <other_name>Predicor</other_name>
    <other_name>Predicorten</other_name>
    <other_name>Prednicen-M</other_name>
    <other_name>Prednicort</other_name>
    <other_name>Prednidib</other_name>
    <other_name>Prednilonga</other_name>
    <other_name>Predniment</other_name>
    <other_name>Prednisonum</other_name>
    <other_name>Prednitone</other_name>
    <other_name>Promifen</other_name>
    <other_name>Servisone</other_name>
    <other_name>SK-Prednisone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Metastatic CRPC with at least one biopsy-accessible metastasis

          -  Evidence of prostate cancer progression by any of the following criteria: radiographic
             or PSA criteria, or symptomatic progression related to prostate cancer

          -  Castrate testosterone levels (&lt; 50 ng/dL) achieved by orchiectomy or maintenance on a
             luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone (LHRH) agonist or antagonist

          -  Histologic confirmation of original prostate cancer diagnosis per institutional
             standard; life expectancy of greater than 6 months

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mm^3

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1,500/mm^3

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mm^3

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits (or &lt; 2 X the upper limit of normal
             in those with Gilbert?s disease)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)(serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT)(serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 1.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits OR creatinine clearance &gt;= 45
             mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

          -  Subject agrees to use a double barrier method of birth control during the course of
             study treatment period with enzalutamide and/or cabazitaxel treatment and for at least
             3 months after the study is discontinued

               -  A double-barrier method of contraception involves the use of a condom in
                  combination with 1 of the following: contraceptive sponge, diaphragm, or cervical
                  ring with spermicidal gel or foam

               -  Subject who has had a vasectomy at least 6 months prior to starting study
                  treatment period and those whose female sexual partner(s) are more than 55 years
                  of age and postmenopausal for at least 2 years or surgically sterile (tubal
                  ligation, hysterectomy, or bilateral oophorectomy) agree to use at least a condom

          -  Ability to understand, and the willingness to sign, a written informed consent
             document, as well as comply with study requirements

          -  Must have appropriate wash out (&gt; 6 half-lives) of androgen receptor antagonists, 5
             alpha reductase inhibitors or ketoconazole prior to the start of cycle 1; if the agent
             is not in the table below, the washout should be 2 weeks

               -  Bicalutamide; approximate half-life: 6 days; washout period: 36 days

               -  Flutamide; approximate half-life: 6 hours; washout period: 36 hours

               -  Nilutamide approximate half-life: 4 days; washout period: 24 days

               -  Finasteride; approximate half-life: 8 hours; washout period: 48 hours

               -  Aminoglutethimide; approximate half-life: 15 hours; washout period: 4 days

               -  Ketoconazole; approximate half-life: 8 hours; washout period: 48 hours

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior chemotherapy for mCRPC prostate cancer; chemotherapy given neoadjuvantly,
             adjuvantly, or for hormone sensitive metastatic disease is permitted as long as the
             cancer did not progress on chemotherapy AND &gt; 6 months have elapsed

          -  Patients may not have received any other investigational agents within the last 14
             days at the time of treatment start

          -  Patients may not have received enzalutamide or ARN-509 (another androgen receptor
             antagonist) in the past

          -  Patients may not have received cabazitaxel in the past

          -  Subject has clinical signs suggestive of high or imminent risks for pathological
             fracture, spinal cord compression and/or cauda equina syndrome

          -  History of severe hypersensitivity reaction (&gt;= grade 3) to docetaxel, polysorbate 80
             containing drugs, or any of the capsule components of enzalutamide, including
             Labrasol, butylated hydroxyanisole, and butylated hydroxytoluene

          -  Concurrent or planned treatment with strong inhibitors or strong inducers of
             cytochrome P450 family 3, subfamily A, polypeptide 4/5 (3A4/5); (a one-week wash-out
             period is necessary for patients who are already on these treatments)

          -  Uncontrolled, intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, uncontrolled diabetes, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable
             angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that
             would limit compliance with study requirements

          -  Subject has a history of seizure or any condition that may predispose to seizure
             including, but not limited to, underlying brain injury, stroke in the past 6 months,
             primary brain tumors, brain metastases, prior seizures

          -  Subject has a history of unexplained loss of consciousness or transient ischemic
             attack within 12 months of treatment start

          -  Subject is unwilling to stop using herbal supplements that can affect the PSA, such as
             saw palmetto or prostate cancer (PC)-SPES

          -  Subject has another active malignancy other than non-melanomatous skin cancer (unless
             it is metastatic) or superficial bladder cancer

          -  Must not have a gastrointestinal condition that would interfere with absorption

          -  Subjects may not be on other therapies that affect hormone levels, such as estrogens,
             testosterones, ketoconazole during this study; however, megestrol for hot flashes is
             permitted
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie Graff</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie N. Graff</last_name>
      <phone>503-220-8262</phone>
      <phone_ext>55688</phone_ext>
      <email>graffj@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julie N. Graff</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Portland Veterans Administration Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie N. Graff</last_name>
      <phone>503-220-8262</phone>
      <phone_ext>55688</phone_ext>
      <email>graffj@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julie N. Graff</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seattle Cancer Care Alliance</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heather H. Cheng</last_name>
      <phone>800-804-8824</phone>
      <email>hhcheng@u.washington.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Heather H. Cheng</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 11, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 13, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Julie Graff</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cortisone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cortisone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

