<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02529657</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12288113.1.0000.5511</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02529657</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Low Level Laser Therapy to Reduce Comorbidity in Spinal Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>LASPINE</acronym>
  <official_title>Analysis of Effect of Low Level Laser Therapy in Spinal Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Nove de Julho</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Nove de Julho</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Each year, more than one million individuals worldwide are submitted to laminectomies, with a
      failure rate higher than 40%. Postlaminectomy epidural adhesion is implicated as a main cause
      of ''failed back surgery syndrome'' and associated with increased risk of complications
      during revision surgery. The postoperative epidural scar can cause extradural compression or
      dural tethering, which results in recurrent radicular pain and physical impairment. Several
      studies in the literature are signalizing that Low-Level-Laser-Therapy (LLLT) is proven to be
      an effective tool to assist the inflammatory process and wound healing, as well to prevent
      infection. Thus, the objectives of this project are to delineate and evaluate the LLLT
      effects in spinal surgery. A prospective randomized, controlled trial with a total of 48
      patients who underwent laminectomy, were divided into 2 groups. In the first group, 25
      patients received LLLT during the surgical procedure over dura mater, over subcutaneous and
      on the skin, as well as 24h and 72h post surgery. In the second group, 23 patients were
      induced to think they will be getting the same treatment, although the laser is not
      operating. In those groups, C reactive protein, Lactate Dehydrogenase and Creatine kinase
      were evaluated in the second and fifth days after surgery, digital temperature will be
      measured and scores in visual analogue scale will be used, 5 minutes pre and 5 minutes post
      Laser application. The drainage output was collected in the first three days following
      surgery in both groups. Interleukins were evaluated in interstitial infiltrate drained in 24h
      and 48h. The data was evaluated for normality and subjected to appropriate statistical
      analysis, in order to seek representation, as same as the level of significance of the
      studied samples.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunochemistry to evaluate low level laser therapy anti-inflammatory mechanism 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Interstitial infiltrate obtained of Lumbar Drain collected 24 hours after surgery, interleukins IL-1, IL-4, IL-8, IL-10 and TNF alfa were measured through Immunochemistry, using ELISA.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunochemistry to evaluate low level laser therapy mechanism 48 hours after light delivery</measure>
    <time_frame>48h after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Interstitial infiltrate was obtained of Lumbar Drain collected 48 hours after surgery, in this infiltrate interleukins IL-1, IL-4, IL-8, IL10 and TNF alfa were measured through Immunochemistry, using ELISA.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Score in Visual Analogue Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes pre LLLT</time_frame>
    <description>Patient had to choose between 0 and 10 on the 11 point short pain scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Score in Visual Analogue Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes post LLLT</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in pain on the 11 point short pain scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Temperature of the skin in the healing scar</measure>
    <time_frame>pre and 1 minute post LLLT</time_frame>
    <description>Verified 1 minute before and 1 minute after LLLT</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Values of Creatine Kinase in the blood</measure>
    <time_frame>pre operative, 24h and 48h postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Obtained through patient blood.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Values of C reactive protein in the blood</measure>
    <time_frame>pre operative, 24h and 48h postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Obtained through patient blood pre operative, 24h and 48h postoperative</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Values of Lactate dehydrogenase in the blood</measure>
    <time_frame>pre operative, 24h and 48h postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Obtained through patient blood pre operative, 24h and 48h postoperative</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Failed Back Surgery Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>23 patients were induced to think they will be getting the same treatment, although the LLLT is not operating.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low level Laser Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>25 patients were submitted to spine surgery and have received low level laser therapy during surgery, 24 hours after surgery and 48 hours after surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low Level Laser Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>In 23 randomized patients, LLLT (B-Cure, Good Energies ®, Israel), with CW diode laser - semiconductor Gallium Arsenide and aluminum (GaAlAs) will be applied during surgery (λ = 804 nm ± 2 , total exposure time of 240 s, energy density of 2.48 J/cm2 , average power of 40 mW , spot area of 3,876 cm2), in contact mode, for 60 seconds on the laminectomy site, 60 seconds and 120 seconds in the subcutaneous tissue of the skin over the wound bed, respectively. In the first and second day post surgery, will be collected the drainage output for analysis of interleukin 1, 4, 6, 8 and 10 (IL- 1, IL-4, IL -6, IL-8 and IL -10 ) and tumor necrosis factor alpha ( TNF -alpha ).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low level Laser Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>In the operating room, lumbar laminectomy will be performed in 46 patients. During the surgery, 24 hours and 48 hours after surgery, the patients received the regular treatment after laminectomy and were induced to thing that were receiving low level laser therapy in their wound.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients undergoing to lumbar laminectomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active lumbar cancer

          -  Infectious disease

          -  Coagulation disorders

          -  Dural injury during the surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria Cristina Chavantes, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nove de Julho University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nove de Julho Universtiy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <state>São Paulo</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://aplicacao.saude.gov.br/plataformabrasil/visao/pesquisador/gerirPesquisa/gerirPesquisa.jsf</url>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farrokhi MR, Vasei M, Fareghbal S, Farrokhi N. The effect of methylene blue on peridural fibrosis formation after laminectomy in rats: an experimental novel study. Spine J. 2011 Feb;11(2):147-52. doi: 10.1016/j.spinee.2011.01.014.</citation>
    <PMID>21296299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yildiz KH, Gezen F, Is M, Cukur S, Dosoglu M. Mitomycin C, 5-fluorouracil, and cyclosporin A prevent epidural fibrosis in an experimental laminectomy model. Eur Spine J. 2007 Sep;16(9):1525-30. Epub 2007 Mar 27.</citation>
    <PMID>17387523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Temiz C, Temiz P, Sayin M, Ucar K. Effect of cepea extract-heparin and allantoin mixture on epidural fibrosis in a rat hemilaminectomy model. Turk Neurosurg. 2009 Oct;19(4):387-92.</citation>
    <PMID>19847760</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oehmichen M. Vitality and time course of wounds. Forensic Sci Int. 2004 Sep 10;144(2-3):221-31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15364394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah JM, Omar E, Pai DR, Sood S. Cellular events and biomarkers of wound healing. Indian J Plast Surg. 2012 May;45(2):220-8. doi: 10.4103/0970-0358.101282.</citation>
    <PMID>23162220</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang R, Ghahary A, Shen Q, Scott PG, Roy K, Tredget EE. Hypertrophic scar tissues and fibroblasts produce more transforming growth factor-beta1 mRNA and protein than normal skin and cells. Wound Repair Regen. 2000 Mar-Apr;8(2):128-37.</citation>
    <PMID>10810039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee JH, Lee SH. Clinical effectiveness of percutaneous adhesiolysis using Navicath for the management of chronic pain due to lumbosacral disc herniation. Pain Physician. 2012 May-Jun;15(3):213-21.</citation>
    <PMID>22622905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tao H, Fan H. Implantation of amniotic membrane to reduce postlaminectomy epidural adhesions. Eur Spine J. 2009 Aug;18(8):1202-12. doi: 10.1007/s00586-009-1013-x. Epub 2009 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>19404691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sobottke R, Schlüter-Brust K, Kaulhausen T, Röllinghoff M, Joswig B, Stützer H, Eysel P, Simons P, Kuchta J. Interspinous implants (X Stop, Wallis, Diam) for the treatment of LSS: is there a correlation between radiological parameters and clinical outcome? Eur Spine J. 2009 Oct;18(10):1494-503. doi: 10.1007/s00586-009-1081-y. Epub 2009 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19562386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandoval MA, Hernandez-Vaquero D. Preventing peridural fibrosis with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs. Eur Spine J. 2008 Mar;17(3):451-455. doi: 10.1007/s00586-007-0580-y. Epub 2008 Jan 3.</citation>
    <PMID>18172695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rochkind S, Drory V, Alon M, Nissan M, Ouaknine GE. Laser phototherapy (780 nm), a new modality in treatment of long-term incomplete peripheral nerve injury: a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled study. Photomed Laser Surg. 2007 Oct;25(5):436-42.</citation>
    <PMID>17975958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bae CS, Lim SC, Kim KY, Song CH, Pak S, Kim SG, Jang CH. Effect of Ga-as laser on the regeneration of injured sciatic nerves in the rat. In Vivo. 2004 Jul-Aug;18(4):489-95.</citation>
    <PMID>15369190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keskın F, Esen H. Comparison of the effects of an adhesion barrier and chitin on experimental epidural fibrosis. Turk Neurosurg. 2010 Oct;20(4):457-63. doi: 10.5137/1019-5149.JTN.3205-10.2.</citation>
    <PMID>20963694</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>LaRocca H, Macnab I. The laminectomy membrane. Studies in its evolution, characteristics, effects and prophylaxis in dogs. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1974 Aug;56B(3):545-50.</citation>
    <PMID>4421702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 22, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 18, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 30, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 30, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 2, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Nove de Julho</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Vanessa Milanesi Holanda</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, MS</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lower Level Laser Therapy (LLLT)</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>cytokines</keyword>
  <keyword>wound healing</keyword>
  <keyword>laminectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>clinical study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Failed Back Surgery Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

