<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02529748</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1506M73781</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02529748</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study to Assess the Quantitative Dermal Transfer Efficiencies of Solids for Multiple Transfer Pathways</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study to Assess the Quantitative Dermal Transfer Efficiencies of Solids for Multiple Transfer Pathways</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dermal transfer efficiency has been defined as the amount of material that moves from one
      surface to another following contact. The investigators propose to measure dermal transfer
      efficiency for the following pathways: (1) object to skin, (2) skin to skin, (3) skin to
      mouth, (4) clothing to skin, (5) gloves to skin, and (6) air to skin. First, the quantitative
      dermal transfer will be measured for the two selected test substances (lead, Tinopal) for
      each of these six pathways. The relative quantities of dermal transfer will also then be
      compared between the different transfer pathways (e.g., is skin to skin transfer greater or
      less than clothing to skin transfer?). And second, the pattern of transfer will be
      characterized semi-quantitatively (e.g., does dermal transfer occur consistently and evenly
      to the skin from different reservoirs?).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Each of the six transfer pathways will be tested and measured in a controlled, ventilated
      study chamber at the University of Minnesota's School of Public Health Industrial Hygiene
      Laboratory. To test each pathway, human volunteers will perform repeated contact activities
      using an identical protocol (e.g., identical number of contacts, type of material contacted,
      measured pressure of contact, measured time of contact, measured temperature and humidity) so
      that inter- and intra-individual variability can be characterized.

      The qualitative and quantitative sampling methods that will be used have been developed,
      tested, and published by researchers from the National Institute for Occupational Safety and
      Health (NIOSH) and other institutions such as ASTM. Specifically, quantitative transfer
      efficiencies will be measured using accepted wipe sampling protocols taken from several
      papers in the peer-reviewed literature. Semi-quantitative transfer patterns will be measured
      using fluorescent tracer intensity techniques that have also been presented in the
      peer-reviewed literature. The skin surface wipe samples will be sent to an accredited
      American Industrial Hygiene Association (AIHA) laboratory for analysis.

      These sampling results will allow the investigators to report the measured quantitative
      dermal transfer efficiencies of elemental metallic lead and Tinopal for each pathway in mass
      per square surface area of skin, and also calculate the relative transfer efficiencies in
      terms of percent transferred versus originally loaded. Fluorescent tracer maps will allow the
      investigators to demonstrate the patterns of transfer for each pathway using intensity of the
      tracer following transfer. Following this analysis, the investigators will then use the data
      to better inform the relative importance of the pathways in the conceptual model with respect
      to dermal exposure assessment and modeling efforts. These results are very important for
      improving the quality of workplace dermal exposure assessments and techniques. The current
      approaches are not well validated, and it is unknown if the results of existing dermal
      exposure models are accurate. It is expected that the results of this study will help to
      improve the protection of workers from certain dermal exposure hazards in the workplace by
      providing better inputs to the existing dermal exposure models, since it is not possible to
      collect exposure samples for each job task in the workplace.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitative mass of test substance per area of skin as measured through surface sampling</measure>
    <time_frame>Surface samples will be collected within an hour of contact or application</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will handle or touch the approved test substances or an intermediate transfer material such as a solid surface or clothing. Surface skin wipe sampling will then be conducted to measure the amount of material that has been transferred to or from the skin surface.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Environmental Exposure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants for Surface Skin Sampling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adult volunteers with healthy, intact skin will have surface skin wipe samples collected following contact with the approved test substances to measure the quantitative transfer of the test substances to and from the skin surface.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Participants for Surface Skin Sampling</intervention_name>
    <description>Skin wipe samples will be collected to quantify the amount of the test substances transferred to and from the surface of the participants' skin.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants for Surface Skin Sampling</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>No other names</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Elemental metallic lead</intervention_name>
    <description>Consumer product fishing tackle made of elemental lead will be handled by the participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants for Surface Skin Sampling</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>No other names</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tinopal</intervention_name>
    <description>Tinopal, a fluorescent tracer, will be handled by the participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants for Surface Skin Sampling</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>No other names</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult volunteers with healthy intact skin.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children will be excluded from the study.

          -  Adults with a past history of dermal sensitization, skin allergy, or dermal irritation
             or dermatitis because of the potential to have compromised barrier function in the
             skin.

          -  Adults who are unwilling to follow protocol requirements.

          -  Adults who have a documented history of lead poisoning.

          -  Adults who have a concurrent contagious illness or other stressor which in the opinion
             of the investigator may interfere with the subject's ability to perform the study's
             requirements.

          -  Adults who have open wounds or otherwise compromised skin integrity on their hands.

          -  Adults who are pregnant or nursing.

          -  Adults who lack the capacity to provide informed voluntary consent to participate in
             the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 11, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 19, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 19, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 19, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 20, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

