<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02522221</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLN-511</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02522221</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tecarfarin Anti-Coagulation Trial (TACT)</brief_title>
  <acronym>TACT</acronym>
  <official_title>A &quot;Real-World&quot;, Randomized, Open-Label, Study on the Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of Tecarfarin (ATI-5923) a Novel Vitamin K Antagonist, Versus Warfarin in Subjects Requiring Chronic Anticoagulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Espero Biopharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Espero Biopharma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      TACT is a &quot;real world&quot; randomized controlled trial of tecarfarin, a novel vitamin K
      antagonist, vs. warfarin. The quality of anticoagulation control will be compared for the two
      groups of subjects who require chronic oral anticoagulation for a broad panel of indications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a randomized, parallel-arm, open-label study comparing the safety and efficacy
      of tecarfarin and warfarin in approximately 1000 subjects who have an indication for chronic
      oral anticoagulation. The study will be fully enriched with subjects who are taking at least
      one CYP2C9-interacting medication and have either chronic kidney disease stage 3 or 4 and/or
      a genetic variant allele for CYP2C9. The study will be conducted at approximately 140 sites
      with experience in the management of anticoagulation subjects. Eligible subjects will be
      randomized to receive either tecarfarin or warfarin for a period ranging from 6 months to a
      maximum of approximately 24 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of time in the therapeutic range (TTR) for tecarfarin vs. warfarin for each treatment group in the randomized population</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization until study termination, up to 24 months (1st month not included)</time_frame>
    <description>Interpolated and observed TTR will be calculated for the two treatment groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage TTR for tecarfarin vs. warfarin in the sub-population of patients who are taking a CYP2C9-interacting medication and have a CYP2C9 genotype variant allele</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization until study termination, up to 24 months (1st month not included)</time_frame>
    <description>Interpolated and observed TTR will be calculated for the two treatment groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage TTR for tecarfarin vs warfarin for the sub-population of patients who are taking a CYP2C9-interacting medication and have chronic kidney disease stage 3 or 4 (eGFR ≥ 15 to &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m2)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization until study termination, up to 24 months (1st month not included)</time_frame>
    <description>Interpolated and observed TTR will be calculated for the two treatment groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with INR &gt; 4.0 for tecarfarin vs. warfarin</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization until study termination, up to 24 months (1st month not included)</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of observations of patients with INR &gt; 4.0 will be calculated for the two treatment groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with INR &gt; 5.0</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization until study termination, up to 24 months (1st month not included)</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of observations of patients with INR &gt; 5.0 will be calculated for the two treatment groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first embolic event for tecarfarin vs. warfarin</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization until study termination, up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time from enrollment until any embolic event (CVA, pulmonary embolism, peripheral embolism) while enrolled will be calculated for the two groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The primary safety endpoint of this study is the time to the first BARC category 3-5 bleeding event.</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization until study termination, up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>BARC category 3-5 bleeding events will be compared for the two treatment groups</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary safety endpoint of this study is the time to the first BARC category 2-5 bleeding event</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of randomization until study termination, up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>BARC category 2-5 bleeding events will be compared for the two treatment groups</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Thromboembolism</condition>
  <condition>Thrombosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tecarfarin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tecarfarin will be administered and dose adjusted by the investigator. Dose adjustments will be made in accordance with a target INR range pre-specified by the investigator.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Warfarin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Warfarin will be administered and dose adjusted by the investigator. Dose adjustments will be made in accordance with a target INR range pre-specified by the investigator.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Warfarin</intervention_name>
    <description>Warfarin is an oral vitamin K antagonist anticoagulant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Warfarin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Coumadin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>tecarfarin</intervention_name>
    <description>Tecarfarin is an oral vitamin K antagonist anticoagulant</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tecarfarin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ATI-5923</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        General Screening Inclusion Criteria

          1. Is male or female and at least 18 years of age.

          2. Is able and willing to sign an IRB-approved written informed consent.

          3. Is able and willing to follow instructions, to comply with protocol requirements, and
             to attend required study visits.

          4. Is taking a CYP2C9-interacting medication (inhibitor, substrate, or inducer; see list
             in Appendix A) at the time of randomization and is expected to receive this medication
             chronically for the duration of the trial.

          5. Has either

               1. Chronic kidney disease stage 3 or 4 (eGFR ≥ 15 to &lt;60 mL/min/1.73 m2 at Screening
                  based on central laboratory) and/or

               2. A CYP2C9 genotype variant allele

          6. (Only for warfarin experienced patients) Patient is considered poorly controlled on
             warfarin therapy as judged by the investigator, e.g. has at least 2 INR values out of
             target range within previous 12 months Anticoagulation-Related Inclusion Criteria

          7. Requires chronic anticoagulation therapy.

          8. Is willing to receive chronic anticoagulation investigational therapy for the duration
             of the study or, for warfarin-naïve DVT subjects, treating physician prescribed at
             least a 6-month treatment period with an oral anticoagulation agent.

          9. Has one or more of the following indications for chronic oral anticoagulation:

               1. Atrial fibrillation/flutter (paroxysmal, persistent or permanent), not due to a
                  reversible cause, documented by electrocardiography (ECG)

               2. Aortic and/or mitral prosthetic HV

               3. History of venous thromboembolic disease

               4. History of myocardial infarction or cardiomyopathy

               5. Any another indication for which warfarin is approved or recommended, with
                  Sponsor approval

         10. Conforms to the following restrictions regarding vitamin-K containing dietary
             supplements:

               1. If taking at Baseline (Visit 2), is willing to continue with consistent doses
                  throughout the study

               2. If not taking at Baseline (Visit 2), is willing to abstain from such supplements
                  throughout the study

        General Exclusion Criteria

          1. Is pregnant, nursing, or a woman of childbearing potential who cannot assure that they
             will not become pregnant for the duration of the study.

          2. Has been treated with an investigational drug within 30 days or 5 half-lives,
             whichever is longer, at time of screening.

             Safety-Related Exclusion Criteria

          3. Has a life expectancy &lt;1 year

          4. Is age &gt;85 years

          5. Has severe end-organ disease, such as:

               1. Estimated GFR (eGFR) &lt; 15 mL/min/1.73 m2 at Screening per the central laboratory

               2. Is on dialysis

               3. Is expected to be on dialysis or receive kidney transplant within 6 months of
                  screening

               4. Advanced pulmonary disease requiring home oxygen

               5. NYHA class IV heart failure

               6. Severe psychiatric disorder such as advanced dementia

          6. Has a history of ischemic stroke without residual neurologic deficit within the last 3
             months, prior major ischemic stroke with residual neurologic deficit, or any history
             of intracranial bleeding

          7. Is an ongoing alcohol or substance abuser

          8. Has anemia (screening hemoglobin &lt;9 g/dL) For subjects who have received a MHV within
             4 weeks of Screening, who have no active bleeding, and whose hemoglobin is stable, a
             Screening hemoglobin as low as 8 g/dL is allowed.

             For subjects with severe CKD (eGFR ≥ 15 to &lt;30 mL/min/1.73 m2), who have no active
             bleeding, and whose hemoglobin is stable, a Screening hemoglobin as low as 8 g/dL is
             allowed.

          9. Has thrombocytopenia (screening platelet count &lt;90,000 x 103/microL)

         10. Has a history of or presence of any illness or condition, which, in the judgment of
             the Investigator, may compromise the safety of the subject during Study Drug
             administration.

             Anticoagulation-related Exclusion Criteria

         11. Has active bleeding or lesions at risk of bleeding such as gastric ulceration, colonic
             or cerebral arterio-venous malformations, cerebral or aortic aneurysms, pericarditis
             or endocarditis

         12. Except for MHV replacement surgery and related or concurrent procedures, has recently
             (&lt;14 days from Screening) undergone non-thromboembolic surgery or other invasive
             procedures such as lumbar puncture.

         13. Has blood dyscrasias or inherited disorders of hemostasis.

         14. Has a history of hemorrhagic tendencies or prior serious hemorrhagic events such as
             hemorrhage within the cranium, eye, spinal cord, retroperitoneum.

         15. Has active gross hematuria or gastrointestinal bleeding

         16. Has a history of gross hematuria or gastrointestinal bleeding within the past 6 months
             prior to Screening. (Note: Investigators may enroll patients with such bleeding
             episodes if they are resolved at least 4 weeks prior to screening and if the benefits
             of anticoagulation outweigh the risks using accepted risk stratification methods such
             as HASBLED.)

         17. Has received concomitant therapy with other anticoagulant or antiplatelet agents, such
             as clopidogrel, prasugrel, ticlopidine, dipyridamole, heparin or low molecular weight
             heparin (LMWH), or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) that cannot be
             discontinued prior to initiating tecarfarin/warfarin dosing, unless use of such drugs
             is necessary as part of bridging/transitioning during the first several days of Study
             Drug administration.

             Daily use of 81 - 100 mg aspirin and intermittent or chronic use of the selective
             COX-2 inhibitors celecoxib and valdecoxib is allowed.

         18. Has congenital or acquired coagulant inhibitors present which would interfere with the
             use of the INR, eg:

               1. Antiphospholipid antibody syndrome or positive lupus anticoagulant

               2. Abnormally prolonged prothrombin time, in the absence of therapeutic
                  anticoagulation, due to an endogenous inhibitor
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 12, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 13, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic anticoagulation</keyword>
  <keyword>vitamin K antagonist</keyword>
  <keyword>mechanical heart valve</keyword>
  <keyword>CYP2C9</keyword>
  <keyword>warfarin</keyword>
  <keyword>tecarfarin</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic kidney disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin K</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Warfarin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

