<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00432107</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AP3003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00432107</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Assess APO866 for the Treatment of Advanced Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-centre, Two-stage, Open Label Phase II Study to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of APO866 in the Treatment of Patients With Advanced Melanoma.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Onxeo</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Onxeo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II study is designed to determine the efficacy and safety of APO866 for the
      treatment of patients with advanced cutaneous melanoma. APO866 has shown to induce growth
      inhibition in cultures of human melanoma cells as well as in animal models with
      subcutaneously implanted melanoma tumors. APO866 was considered to be safe and well tolerated
      in a phase I study that treated 24 patients with advanced cancer. In that study one of the
      two patients with advanced melanoma had a stable disease for 5 months with size reduction of
      some lesions. APO866 is administered by intravenous infusion continuously for 96 hours that
      is repeated every 4 weeks. Patients will receive 3 cycles of treatment and the primary
      efficacy endpoint will be assessed at Week 16. Patients will be follow-up for 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Advanced melanoma is one of the most chemo-resistant types of human cancers. The incidence
      increases by about 2.5% on an annual basis, with may partially be related to aging and growth
      of the population, as well as other environmental risk factors. Virtually no recent progress
      has been made in the treatment of patients with this disease. In the past 30 years, the FDA
      has approved only 2 agents, dacarbazine and interleukin-2, on the basis of overall response
      and response duration, respectively. However, these outcomes were not accompanied by a
      survival benefit. The most recent randomized study of Dacarbazine (DTIC) yielded an overall
      response rate of 7%, and to date, no other treatments, including combination therapies, have
      shown to improve survival when compared to DTIC alone. Hence, the mainstay of treatment for
      patients with advanced melanoma is DTIC-based therapy.

      APO866 is a novel drug that induces cell death by specifically inhibiting the biosynthesis of
      Niacinamide Adenine Dinucleotide (NAD+) from niacinamide, which is essential for the cellular
      metabolism, protein modification and messenger synthesis. APO866 is not subject to the
      commonly known mechanisms of multi drug resistance (MDR). Its activity is cell cycle
      independent. APO866 exerted high anti-tumor activity on a broad range of different tumor
      cells derived from both human solid cancers and leukemias in vitro and on a large number of
      human xenografts in nude mice, including melanoma, and rats in vivo. Hematologic cancer cells
      were highly sensitive to APO866. Lymphocytes are the most sensitive normal cells to APO866
      resulting in lymphocytopenia and reticulocytopenia in rats, monkeys. Furthermore, APO866 may
      have anti-angiogenic properties as shown in vivo.

      APO866 was investigated in 24 patients with advanced cancers in a phase I study aiming to
      determine the dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) and maximum tolerated dose (MTD). Treatment was
      well tolerated and safe. The unique DLT was thrombocytopenia. At dose levels higher than
      0.036 mg/m2/hr CTC grade III lymphocytopenia, not thought to be clinically relevant, preceded
      all other toxicities. The recommended dose for phase II studies of APO866 is 0.126 mg/m2/hr
      administered by civ infusion for 4 consecutive days evry 4 weeks. This dose was selected
      because of its safety profile, and the translational observation that Css of APO866 at MTD
      was similar or higher as compared to the concentrations at which efficacy was established in
      vitro and in vivo. In addition, a transient decrease of serum vascular endothelial growth
      factor (VEGF) levels, a surrogate marker of angiogenesis, was observed within 96 hrs after
      the start of treatment in 9 out of 11 patients treated at MTD and the 0.144 mg/m2/hr dose
      level of APO866.

      No objective tumor response was observed. However, 4 patients had stable disease for at least
      3 months: prostate cancer (4 months), melanoma (5 months), sarcomatoid mesothelioma (3
      months) and oropharyngeal cancer (5 months). In addition, lesion size reductions were
      observed in the melanoma patient (80% size reduction and stable size of other lesions) at an
      APO866 dose level of 0.072 mg/m2/hr, and in the mesothelioma patient (moderate size
      reductions of pleural lesions) at 0.108 mg/m2/hr.

      Treatment with APO866 was safe and well tolerated. The anti-tumor effect of APO866, in
      particular on melanoma cells in vitro and in vivo, and its anti-angiogenic propriety support
      the rationale to conduct a open phase II study of APO866 in patients with advanced melanoma.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the tumor response rate (according to Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) criteria) as the proportion of eligible patients with stage IV cutaneous melanoma or stage III not amenable to surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16 and 12 months follow-up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to response</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evolution of serum VEGF and interleukin-8 (IL-8) during treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 16</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2-stage mono therapy of APO866</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment period consists of 3 consecutive 28 day cycles. Each cycle starts with a 4 day continuous infusion of the study medication followed by a 24 day break</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>APO866</intervention_name>
    <description>APO866 is administered as 0.126 mg/m²/hr IV every 4 weeks for 4 consecutive days (96 hours) for a total of 3 cycles</description>
    <arm_group_label>2-stage mono therapy of APO866</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of melanoma

          -  Stage IV disease or stage III not amenable to surgery (AJCC, see Appendix A)

          -  Measurable disease, defined as at least 1 malignant lesion that could be accurately
             and serially measured in at least 1 dimension and for which the greatest diameter is &gt;
             or = 10 mm as measured by spiral computed tomography (CT) scan or magnetic resonance
             imaging (MRI), or &gt; or = 20 mm with conventional techniques. A caliper can be used for
             the measurement of superficial cutaneous metastases which are &gt; or = 10 mm.

          -  Patients must be able to undergo either contrast-enhanced CT-scan or contrast-enhanced
             MRI scan for tumor assessment

          -  Only one previous systemic treatment (excluding prior systemic treatment as
             postoperative adjuvant therapy) is allowed and should have been terminated &gt; 4 weeks
             before Study Day 1 (SD1).

          -  Lack of response or progression of disease after the most recent systemic therapy for
             advanced melanoma

          -  Patients must have recovered from the toxicity of any previously used treatment. All
             Adverse events of previous systemic treatment must have resolved to &lt; grade I Common
             Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTC v3.0, see Appendix)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status &lt; 1 (see Appendix C)

          -  Age &gt; 18 years, of either sex

          -  Female patients with childbearing potential must be using a hormonal contraceptive,
             intra uterine device, diaphragm with spermicide or condom with spermicide for the
             duration of the study. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum or
             urinary human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) pregnancy test within 7 days prior to Study
             Day 1 (SD1)

          -  Male patients, who are not surgically sterile, must use a condom with spermicide for
             the duration of the study and 3 months thereafter

          -  Have given written informed consent, prior to any study related procedure not part of
             the patient's normal medical care, with the understanding that consent may be
             withdrawn by the patient at any time without prejudice to future medical care.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have participated in any other investigational study or received an experimental
             therapeutic procedure considered to interfere with the study in the 4 weeks preceding
             SD1

          -  History of brain metastases or leptomeningeal disease

          -  Bone-only metastatic disease

          -  Use of prohibited medication due to Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) metabolism of APO866,
             as specified in Section 6.6.2. concomitant use of these drugs will not be allowed
             during the study.

          -  Use of biphosphonate drug during the 30 days preceding the APO866 infusion and during
             the treatment period will not be allowed

          -  Uncontrolled medical conditions, requiring surgical or pharmacological treatment
             (exceptions must be approved by the Medical Responsible of the study).

          -  Serious concomitant disease (e.g. significant cardiac disease)

          -  History of second cancer that was treated with curative intent and in complete
             remission for &lt; 5 years, with the exception of basal cell carcinoma or cervical cancer
             in situ

          -  Primary or acquired thrombocytopenia

          -  Inadequate bone marrow reserve: white blood cell (WBC) &lt; 3.5x10^9/L, neutrophils &lt;
             1.0x10^9/L, thrombocytes &lt; 100x10^9/L, Hb &lt; 10.0 g/dL or coagulation abnormalities

          -  Inadequate liver function: total bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal values (ULN),
             aspartate aminotransferase (AST), Alanine Amino Transferase (ALT), or alkaline
             phosphatase &gt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Have inadequate renal function, defined by serum creatinine &gt; 1.5x ULN

          -  Retinopathy, history of retinal laser surgery, or an ERG &lt; 50% of normal

          -  Pregnant of lactating female

          -  Abuse of alcohol or other recreational drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Uwe Trefzer, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Dermatology, Charité University Hospital, Schumannstrasse 20-21, 10117 Berlin, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Dermatology, Medical University Graz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Graz</city>
        <zip>8036</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Dermatology, Hopital Henri Modor</name>
      <address>
        <city>Créteil</city>
        <zip>94010</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Dermatologie, Hotel Dieu</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes</city>
        <zip>44093</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Dermatology, Charité University Hospital Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Clinic for Dermatology, Medical Faculty of Mannheim of the Heidelberg University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mannheim</city>
        <zip>68167</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Dermatology, University Hospital of Zürich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zürich</city>
        <zip>8091</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 6, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 7, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 28, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 28, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 29, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced cutaneous melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase II study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

