<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00439361</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2006-0527</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00439361</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Velcade Plus ICE for Patients With Relapsed Classical Hodgkin Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase-I Study of Bortezomib (VELCADE) Plus ICE (Ifosfamide, Carboplatin, Etoposide) for Patients With Relapsed Classical Hodgkin Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objectives:

        1. To determine the toxicity profile of multiple doses of bortezomib when given with ICE in
           patients with relapsed and refractory classical Hodgkin lymphoma (HL).

        2. To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of bortezomib when given in combination
           with ICE chemotherapy in patients with relapsed and refractory classical Hodgkin
           lymphoma (HL).

      Secondary Objectives:

      - To determine the overall response rate and complete response rate in patients with relapsed
      and refractory classical Hodgkin lymphoma (HL).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bortezomib is designed to block a protein that plays a role in cell function and growth,
      which may cause cancer cells to die.

      ICE is a combination of chemotherapy drugs that, together, may work more effectively at
      causing cancer cells to die by stopping cells from dividing.

      Mesna is a drug that protects bladder cells from damage by the chemotherapy drug ifosfamide.
      It is used to decrease the risk of bleeding in the bladder.

      Before you can start taking the drugs on this study, you will have &quot;screening tests.&quot; These
      tests will help the doctor decide if you are eligible to take part in this study. These tests
      may be performed within 28 days of starting the study drugs. If you have had some of these
      exams, tests, or procedures performed recently, they may not need to be repeated. This will
      be for your study doctor to decide. You will have a physical exam, including measurement of
      your vital signs (blood pressure, heart rate, temperature, and breathing rate), height, and
      weight. You will have x-rays and a bone marrow biopsy to check the status of the disease. To
      collect a bone marrow biopsy, an area of the hip or chest bone is numbed with anesthetic, and
      a small amount of bone marrow and bone is withdrawn through a large needle. You will have a
      computed tomography (CT) scan of your abdomen, chest, and pelvis and a positron emission
      tomography (PET) scan. Blood (about 2-3 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests. Women
      who are able to have children must have a negative blood (about 1 teaspoon) pregnancy test
      within 1 month before starting therapy on this study. Because taking part in this study
      requires that participants' ability to fight off infections be normal, you will have blood
      drawn (about 1-2 tablespoons) to be tested for HIV within 6 months before starting therapy on
      this study. If your HIV test results are found to be positive, you will not be able to take
      part in this study.

      All participants will receive bortezomib as a fixed dose, which will not change unless any
      intolerable side effects occur. At the start of this study, 3 participants will be given a
      dose of bortezomib. If this dose does not cause intolerable side effects, the dose will be
      increased as new participants take part in this study. There will be a total of 3 groups
      (with 3-6 participants per group) entered at increasing dose levels. The dose of bortezomib
      you receive will depend on when you join this study.

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will receive bortezomib plus
      ICE by vein. You will receive bortezomib, on Days 1 and 4, over 5 seconds. The ICE regimen
      will be given as a continuous infusion over different times as follows. On Day 1, you will
      receive ifosfamide and mesna over 24 hours. On Day 2, you will receive mesna over 12 hours
      and carboplatin over 1 hour. On Days 1-3, you will receive etoposide over 2 hours. This
      schedule for bortezomib plus ICE is considered 1 cycle (2 weeks) and will be repeated every
      14 days.

      You may have 3-6 cycles of the study drugs, depending on your tolerance of the drugs and the
      status of the disease. If the disease gets worse or you experience any intolerable side
      effects, you will be taken off this study.

      Blood (about 2-3 tablespoons) will be drawn once a week for routine tests. You will have a
      study visit before the start of each 2-week cycle. During these visits, you will have a brief
      questionnaire that will ask about specific side effects you might be experiencing. It should
      take about 5 minutes to complete this questionnaire.

      After completing 3 cycles, you will return for CT scans, bone marrow biopsies (if they were
      positive for disease before you began on this study), and a PET scan to check the status of
      the disease.

      After completing 3 cycles (if the disease did not worsen and intolerable side effects did not
      occur), you may continue on this study for 3 more cycles. During Cycles 4-6, you will have
      the same scans and blood tests as mentioned above.

      After completing this study, for every 3-4 months on an indefinite basis, you will have
      follow-up visits. During these visits, you will have blood drawn (about 2-3 tablespoons) for
      routine tests. You will also have the same scans that were performed during the screening
      visit.

      This is an investigational study. Bortezomib and ICE are FDA approved and commercially
      available. The combination of bortezomib plus ICE is considered investigational and
      authorized for use in research only.

      Up to 18 patients will take part in this study. All will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerable Dose (MTD) of Bortezomib when given in combination with ICE chemotherapy in participants with relapsed and refractory classical Hodgkin lymphoma (HL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-week cycle</time_frame>
    <description>MTD dose escalation stops either at the highest indicated dose of bortezomib (1.5 mg/m2), or when a Dose limiting toxicity (DLT) has been observed in at least one third of the patients at any dose level.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bortezomib + ICE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bortezomib + ICE (Ifosfamide, Carboplatin, Etoposide):
Bortezomib 1.0 mg/m^2 intravenous (IV) over 5 Seconds on Days 1 and 4; + ICE (Ifosfamide 5 Gm/m^2 IV continuous infusion on Day 1, Carboplatin 5 AUC IV over 1 Hour Day 1, Etoposide 100 mg/m^2 IV over 2 Hours Days 1-3) + Mesna 5 mg/m^2 IV continuous infusion Day 1; 2 Gm/m^2 IV continuous infusion over 12 Hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <description>1.0 mg/m^2 by Vein Over 5 Seconds on Days 1 and 4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bortezomib + ICE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Velcade</other_name>
    <other_name>LDP-341</other_name>
    <other_name>MLN341</other_name>
    <other_name>PS-341</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>5 AUC by Vein Over 1 Hour On Day 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bortezomib + ICE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Paraplatin®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoposide</intervention_name>
    <description>100 mg/m^2 By Vein Over 2 Hours On Days 1-3</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bortezomib + ICE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VePesid®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ifosfamide</intervention_name>
    <description>5 Gm/m^2 By Vein Continuous Infusion Over 24 Hours On Day 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bortezomib + ICE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mesna</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg/m^2 IV continuous Infusion over 24 Hours On Day 1; 2 Gm/m^2 IV continuous infusion over 12 hours starting after completion of Ifosfamide + Mesna 24 hour continuous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bortezomib + ICE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mesnex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed relapsed or refractory classical Hodgkin lymphoma (nodular
             sclerosis, mixed cellularity, or lymphocyte-rich classical HL).

          -  Patients must have failed front-line standard anthracycline-containing regimen, such
             as ABVD, Stanford V, or BEACOPP.

          -  Bidimensionally measurable disease with at least 1 lesion &gt;/= 2.0 cm in a single
             dimension

          -  Acceptable hematologic status: Hemoglobin &gt;/= 8.0 g/dL; Absolute neutrophil count &gt;/=
             1500 cells/mm^3; Platelet count &gt;/= 100,000 cells/mm^3

          -  Pre-study World Health Organization (WHO) performance status of 0, 1, or 2

          -  Age greater than or equal to 16 years

          -  Voluntary signed IRB approved consent informed before performance of any study-related
             procedure not part of normal medical care, with the understanding that consent may be
             withdrawn by the subject at any time without prejudice to future medical care.

          -  Patients of reproductive potential must follow accepted birth control methods during
             treatment and for 3 months after completion of treatment. Female subject is either
             post-menopausal or surgically sterilized or willing to use an acceptable method of
             birth control (i.e., a hormonal contraceptive, intra-uterine device, diaphragm with
             spermicide, condom with spermicide, or abstinence) for the duration of the study. Male
             subject agrees to use an acceptable method for contraception for the duration of the
             study. Female patients must not be pregnant or lactating.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lymphocyte predominant histology

          -  More than one prior chemotherapy regimen.

          -  Prior stem cell transplant

          -  Abnormal liver function:Bilirubin &gt; 2.0 mg/dL (26 µmol/L); Alkaline phosphatase &gt; 2 *
             upper limits of normal (ULN); AST (SGOT) &gt; 2 * ULN

          -  Serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 mg/dL (177 µmol/L) within 14 days before enrollment

          -  Presence of CNS involvement with Hodgkin lymphoma

          -  Presence of HIV infection or AIDS

          -  Patient has &gt;/= Grade 2 peripheral neuropathy within 14 days before enrollment.

          -  Patient has hypersensitivity to boron or mannitol.

          -  Prior bortezomib therapy.

          -  Another primary malignancy (other than squamous cell and basal cell carcinoma of the
             skin, in situ carcinoma of the cervix, or treated prostate cancer with a stable PSA)
             for which the patient has not been disease-free for at least 3 years

          -  Serious nonmalignant disease (e.g., congestive heart failure, hydronephrosis); active
             uncontrolled bacterial, viral, or fungal infections; or other conditions which would
             compromise protocol objectives in the opinion of the investigator and/or the sponsor.

          -  Myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to enrollment or has New York Heart
             Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure, uncontrolled angina, severe
             uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmias, or electrocardiographic evidence of acute
             ischemia or active conduction system abnormalities. Prior to study entry, any ECG
             abnormality at Screening has to be documented by the investigator as not medically
             relevant.

          -  Female subject is pregnant or breast-feeding. Confirmation that the subject is not
             pregnant must be established by a negative serum beta-human chorionic gonadotropin
             (beta-hCG) pregnancy test result obtained during screening. Pregnancy testing is not
             required for post-menopausal or surgically sterilized women.

          -  Patient has received other investigational drugs with 14 days before enrollment

          -  Serious medical or psychiatric illness likely to interfere with participation in this
             clinical study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michelle A. Fanale, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 5, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 5, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 9, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hodgkin Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>HL</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapsed Classical Hodgkin Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Nodular sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Mixed cellularity</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphocyte-rich classical HL</keyword>
  <keyword>Bortezomib</keyword>
  <keyword>Velcade</keyword>
  <keyword>LDP-341</keyword>
  <keyword>MLN341</keyword>
  <keyword>PS-341</keyword>
  <keyword>Carboplatin</keyword>
  <keyword>Paraplatin</keyword>
  <keyword>Etoposide</keyword>
  <keyword>VePesid®</keyword>
  <keyword>Ifosfamide</keyword>
  <keyword>Mesna</keyword>
  <keyword>Mesnex</keyword>
  <keyword>ICE</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isophosphamide mustard</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ifosfamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mesna</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

