<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00434499</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HP-00048859</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00434499</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of EGCG on the Body's Response to Insulin</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Exploratory Study to Evaluate the Ability of Epigallocatechin Gallate to Simultaneously Improve Metabolic and Cardiovascular Actions of Insulin in Healthy and Obese Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Maryland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Maryland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine whether epigallocatechin gallate (EGCG), a major component of green
      tea, affects how the body responds to insulin in healthy and obese people. Insulin is not as
      effective in people who are overweight, have high blood pressure or diabetes. This condition
      is known as insulin resistance. Laboratory studies suggest that green tea or EGCG treatment
      lowers blood pressure, lowers blood sugar and increases blood flow. This study will see if
      EGCG improves insulin resistance or insulin's effects on blood flow in people with insulin
      resistance.

      Healthy normal weight or overweight people between 21 and 65 years of age may be eligible for
      this study. Participants are randomly assigned to take EGCG or a placebo ( inactive dummy
      pill ) in two 4-week treatment phases with a 2-week period of no study medication before each
      treatment phase. After the first 4-week treatment, patients on placebo are switched to EGCG
      and those on EGCG are switched to placebo. In addition to treatment, participants undergo the
      following procedures during the study period:

        -  Screening, including medical history, physical examination and blood and urine tests,
           and finger-stick blood sugar measurement for patients with diabetes

        -  Complete a dietary and physical activity questionnaire and consult with a dietitian

        -  Blood and urine tests

        -  At-home and clinic blood pressure monitoring

        -  Glucose clamp test to measure how the body responds to insulin. This test is done three
           times during the study. A needle is placed in a vein in each of the subject's arms, one
           for sampling blood and the other for infusing insulin, glucose and potassium. Glucose
           and insulin levels, electrolytes, lipids, fatty acids, cytokines and epicatechin are
           measured.

        -  Forearm blood flow measurement with microbubbles and ultrasound. Before beginning the
           glucose clamp test, a test of how well the blood vessels relax is done. A device that
           measures the size of the artery in the upper arm is placed above the elbow. Blood flow
           in the muscle of the forearm is measured by ultrasound using a small infusion through a
           vein of microbubble contrast agent consisting of gas-filled bubbles the size of red
           blood cells. The contrast agent is infused over a 7- to 9-minute period at the beginning
           of the glucose clamp test and again 2 hours after the beginning of the test.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Green tea is a functional food whose consumption is associated with improved cardiovascular
      morbidity and mortality in several large epidemiological studies. One third of the solids in
      green tea are composed of the bioactive polyphenol epigallocatechin 3-gallate (EGCG). Studies
      in both cell- and animal-based models (from our lab and elsewhere) suggest that EGCG may
      mimic and/or augment beneficial metabolic, vascular, and anti-inflammatory actions of
      insulin. Indeed, we have recently shown that 3-week EGCG therapy of SHR rats (genetic model
      of hypertension with features of human metabolic syndrome including insulin resistance,
      hyperinsulinemia, endothelial dysfunction, and overweight) lowers blood pressure, improves
      endothelial dysfunction, increases insulin sensitivity, and raises adiponectin levels nearly
      as effectively as treatment with the conventional ACE-inhibitor enalapril. Obesity, type 2
      diabetes, and hypertension are all important interrelated public health problems that are
      characterized by reciprocal relationships between insulin resistance and endothelial
      dysfunction. Thus, therapies for these diseases that improve insulin resistance often
      simultaneously improve endothelial function and vice versa. Based on results from cellular,
      physiological, and epidemiological studies, we hypothesize that oral EGCG administration will
      simultaneously ameliorate insulin resistance and lower blood pressure in human subjects with
      obesity. To test these hypotheses, we will conduct a randomized, placebo-controlled,
      double-blind, cross-over study to evaluate potential beneficial effects of EGCG to modulate
      insulin sensitivity, blood pressure, vascular function, and inflammatory markers in two
      groups of subjects (lean healthy controls, obesity). After a 2-week EGCG-free run-in period,
      each subject will be randomized to receive EGCG or placebo capsules (400 mg p.o. B.I.D.) for
      4 weeks. This will be followed by a 2-week EGCG-free washout period after which subjects will
      cross-over to the other treatment arm. At baseline, and after each 4-week treatment period,
      we will assess insulin sensitivity (hyperinsulinemic isoglycemic glucose clamp technique) and
      vascular function. Regarding vascular function, we will measure basal and insulin-stimulated
      brachial artery blood flow (large conduit artery assessed by Doppler ultrasound) as well as
      capillary recruitment in forearm skeletal muscle (small nutritive arterioles assessed by
      ultrasound with microbubble contrast). Blood pressure will be measured weekly in the UMB GCRC
      throughout the duration of the study. EGCG pharmacokinetics will be measured at the beginning
      of each glucose clamp study day after oral administration of a single dose of EGCG or
      placebo. Finally, various plasma markers of inflammation will be measured at baseline and at
      the end of each treatment arm to evaluate potential changes that may be related to
      improvements in metabolic and/or vascular function. This study will explore whether EGCG, a
      single compound thought to be a major bioactive component of green tea, is effective at
      improving insulin resistance and lowering blood pressure in subjects with obesity. Results
      from this study may have important implications for understanding potential health benefits
      of functional foods that contain bioactive polyphenols including green tea, dark chocolate,
      and red wine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Not funded
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>February 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in insulin resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>measurements of insulin resistance prior to study drug, after 4 weeks of EGCG or placebo and at end of study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in endothelial dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>14 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>measurements of endothelial function prior to study drug, after 4 weeks of EGCG or placebo and at end of study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Insulin Resistance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo first</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo first then crossover to EGCG</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EGCG first</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>EGCG first then crossover to placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EGCG</intervention_name>
    <description>EGCG 400 mg by mouth twice/daily for 4 weeks duration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo first</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>EGCG first</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        HEALTHY SUBJECTS:

        Men and women in good general health with no significant underlying illnesses who are
        between the ages of 21-65 years of age with HbA(1C) less than 6.5%, fasting blood glucose
        less than 100 mg/dL, blood pressure less than 120/80, and BMI between 20-25 kg/m(2).
        Subjects should have never smoked tobacco or not smoked within the previous year.

        OBESE SUBJECTS:

        Men and women in good general health with no significant underlying illnesses except
        obesity who are between the ages of 21-65 years of age with HbA(1C) less than 6.5%, fasting
        blood glucose less than 110 mg/dl, blood pressure less than 140/90, and BMI between 30-40
        kg/m(2).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        ALL SUBJECTS:

        Subjects will be excluded from our study if they are pregnant , breastfeeding or if they
        plan pregnancy prior to the end of the study.

        In addition, subjects will be excluded if their age is greater than 65 yrs, BMI greater
        than or equal to 40 kg/m(2), or have liver disease (including liver transaminase levels
        greater than twice the upper limit of normal), pulmonary disease, renal insufficiency
        (serum creatinine greater than 2.0 mg/dl), coronary heart disease, heart failure (New York
        Heart Association heart failure Class III or IV), peripheral vascular disease,
        coagulopathy, major depressive disorder, actively smoking or used tobacco within the last
        year, history of cancer, in treatment for any form of cancer, positive tests for HIV,
        hepatitis B or C, or take systemic corticosteroids, thiazolidinediones (within 3 months),
        insulin, or anticoagulants, use food supplements that cannot be discontinued, regular
        intake of 8 or more cups of tea per week within 3 months prior to study entry, regular
        alcoholic beverage intake of more than two drinks per day (a drink corresponds to
        approximately 12 ounces of beer, 4 ounces of table wine, and between 1 and 1.5 ounces of
        80-proof spirits), poor compliance during run-in period or regular use of medications that
        affect insulin sensitivity, blood pressure or vascular function and that cannot be
        discontinued.

        In addition, history of any other medical disease, laboratory abnormalities, or
        psychological conditions that would make the subject (based upon the principal
        investigator's judgment) unsuitable for study enrollment.

        Subjects with known hypersensitivity to octafluoropropane, recent eye surgery, or with
        known cardiac shunts will also be excluded from participating because of potential adverse
        effects from microbubble contrast agent.

        Subjects will be excluded if they are unable to give informed consent for all procedures.

        Currently, type 2 diabetes is not rare in children, however children are excluded from this
        study because children do not typically take EGCG and do not typically have hypertension or
        type 2 diabetes mellitus.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kashif Munir, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Ward E, Hao Y, Thun M. Trends in the leading causes of death in the United States, 1970-2002. JAMA. 2005 Sep 14;294(10):1255-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16160134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Must A, Spadano J, Coakley EH, Field AE, Colditz G, Dietz WH. The disease burden associated with overweight and obesity. JAMA. 1999 Oct 27;282(16):1523-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10546691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fox CS, Coady S, Sorlie PD, Levy D, Meigs JB, D'Agostino RB Sr, Wilson PW, Savage PJ. Trends in cardiovascular complications of diabetes. JAMA. 2004 Nov 24;292(20):2495-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15562129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 10, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 10, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 13, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 28, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 28, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 29, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Maryland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kashif Munir</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Green Tea</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Endothelial Dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Nitric Oxide</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Overweight</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes Type 2</keyword>
  <keyword>High Blood Pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epigallocatechin gallate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

