<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00432133</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DK70553</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DK070553</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>DK70553</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00432133</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Individual and Environmental Mechanisms of PA Change</brief_title>
  <official_title>Behavioral 2X2 Randomized Controlled Trial to Determine Individual and Environmental Mechanisms of Physical Activity Behavior Change</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaiser Permanente</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The focus of this study is to determine the mechanisms that underlie Physical Activity
      behavior change. We have 2 primary objectives. One, to test the effectiveness of brief,
      practical interventions to promote and maintain Physical Activity among individuals who are
      referred to a treadmill stress test but do not present symptoms of cardiac disease. Two, to
      test the potential individual and environmental mediators and moderators of this effect.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is a dearth of information on the mechanisms, and potential moderators, of physical
      activity (PA) intervention effectiveness. Understanding the mechanisms of PA change will aid
      in successful intervention development while understanding moderators will allow a matching
      of intervention components to individual needs of particular populations. To definitively
      understand mechanisms and moderators of behavior change it is necessary to develop
      theory-based interventions that include specific strategies that target proposed mechanisms
      of change while monitoring the proposed mediating and moderating variables prior to and
      following intervention. This proposal highlights the use of the Ecological Model of Physical
      Activity (EMPA) as a theoretical guide to strategy development. The EMPA highlights the
      necessity to address individual (biological &amp; psychosocial) and environmental variables
      (e.g., PA resource accessibility) when developing and implementing interventions. Health care
      patients who have been referred for a treadmill cardiovascular stress test—but do not present
      abnormal ECG or chest pain during testing—will be will be stratified by diagnosis of low
      heart rate recovery, a potential biological moderator of intervention effectiveness. To
      detect the potential independent and combined effects of individual motivation and
      environmental accessibility we will conduct a randomized 2X2 factorial trial to test proposed
      mediators of effectiveness. Participants (n=500) will be randomized to an individual (I),
      environmental (E) , combination (I+E), or matched contact nutrition control. All intervention
      conditions will include a CD-ROM session, 3 tailored mail, and 3 tailored automated telephone
      follow-ups over a 6-month period. We will assess the reach, effectiveness, clinician
      adoption, and staff implementation of these interventions, individually, in combination, and
      when compared to controls among an understudied and high need population—individuals who are
      at an elevated risk, but have not yet suffered a serious cardiac event (approximately
      3,000,000 individuals/year in the US). The results of this project will identify the causal,
      and potentially additive, relationships of environmental and individual mediators of PA
      change and allow the examination of potential biological moderators of effectiveness. Because
      intervention typically effects decrease over time and studies do not address setting-related
      issues necessary to ensure sustainability of delivery at the organizational level we will
      determine the maintenance of intervention effects on causal mechanisms and PA, 6 &amp; 12 months
      following intervention. The interventions will be developed for delivery within the regular
      scope of treadmill stress testing by typical medical staff and cost of delivery will be
      assessed for each intervention condition. This project uniquely utilizes methods that will
      facilitate institutionalization of the intervention components following the successful
      completion of the trial and potential adoption of the intervention in other health care
      settings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity: CHAMPS self report measure and Actigraph Accelerometers</measure>
    <time_frame>6 &amp; 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dollar amounts to include cost of intervention delivery by condition.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart Rate Recovery.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">452</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <condition>Behavior Change</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Protection motivation theory-based tailored intervention to promote physical activity delivered via interactive technology (computer interactive session, automated telephone counseling, tailored newsletters).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Environmental access and awareness intervention to promote physical activity delivered via interactive technology (computer interactive session, automated telephone counseling, tailored newsletters).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combination intervention combining protection motivation and environmental intervention components to promote physical activity delivered via interactive technology (computer interactive session, automated telephone counseling, tailored newsletters).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Protection Motivation Theory-Based Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Targets perceptions of outcome severity and susceptibility, self-efficacy, response efficacy, response costs, and rewards of physical inactivity. One computer interactive session is followed by 3 automated telephone counseling sessions and 4 tailored newletters spread over a 6 month period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Environmenta</intervention_name>
    <description>Targets increased awareness and use of local parks and trials near the home and work environments. Targets increased access by providing membership to a local fitness facility for 12 months. One computer interactive session is followed by 3 automated telephone counseling sessions and 4 tailored newletters spread over a 6 month period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  No chest pains during stress testing

          -  Normal ECG During Stress Testing.

          -  Inactive or insufficiently active (&lt;150 moderate intensity PA/week)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age

          -  No access to telephone

          -  Not able to read or understand English.

          -  Home and Work address outside of 6-county area

          -  Have an active recreation center membership

          -  Any other contraindication to physical activity identified during stress testing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul A Estabrooks, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Permanente Colorado, Institute for Health Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80231</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 5, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 7, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 27, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavior Change</keyword>
  <keyword>Mechanism</keyword>
  <keyword>Environmental</keyword>
  <keyword>Ecological Model of Physical Activity</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

