<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02374996</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BPBIOPWSU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02374996</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacoepigenetics of Bipolar Disorder Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacoepigenetics of Second Generation Antipsychotic-Induced Insulin Resistance in Bipolar Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wayne State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wayne State University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Insulin is a hormone produced by the body to regulate blood sugar. Insulin resistance is a
      state when the body is not using insulin correctly, and more insulin is needed to maintain
      normal blood sugar. Insulin resistance is common in bipolar patients and even more common in
      bipolar patients treated with antipsychotics. Insulin resistance from antipsychotics can lead
      to type 2 diabetes, metabolic syndrome and cardiovascular disease and is known to lead to
      worse psychiatric outcomes (less mood stability) and lower life expectancies in bipolar
      disorder. Abnormal regulation of the folate cycle is known to play a role in
      antipsychotic-induced insulin resistance and the main endpoint to the folate cycle is the
      production of methyl donors for DNA methylation. DNA methylation is critical as it regulates
      how genes are expressed. Thus, changes in DNA methylation may play a role in the disease
      process of antipsychotic-induced insulin resistance. The purpose of this study is to examine
      the differences in the DNA methylation of candidate tissues known to have a role in the
      development of insulin resistance. The three groups of bipolar patients to be studied are 1)
      antipsychotic treated patients with impaired glucose tolerance, 2) antipsychotic treated
      patients with normal glucose tolerance and 3) lithium treated patients with normal glucose
      tolerance. Group 1 will be compared to groups 2 and 3 in order to assess how DNA methylation
      in the skeletal muscle and fat tissue changes due to medication effects (group 2 vs. 3) and
      medication side effects (group 1 vs. 2). Secondary analyses include the analysis of how fats
      are processed in skeletal muscle and fat tissue in relation to antipsychotic-induced insulin
      resistance and the correlation of DNA methylation across different tissues. The investigators
      hypothesize that antipsychotic-induced insulin resistance is to due changes in the way DNA is
      expressed (through epigenetic changes) which causes further changes in the way fats are
      processed in the body eventually leading to insulin resistance. This work is based on
      preliminary findings however further work is needed to identify the true mechanisms behind
      antipsychotic-induced insulin resistance and in particular, the main tissue in which this
      mechanism occurs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be composed of 2 visits. The first visit will be used as a screening visit
      for inclusion of the three groups of patients for the second visit where the outcomes will be
      collected (e.g., tissue samples for DNA methylation and lipidomic analysis).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DNA methylation in skeletal muscle and adipose tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The prevalence of DNA methylation of cytosine-phosphate-guanosine (CpG) Island 81 of the Fatty Acyl Coenzyme A Reductase gene will be compared amongst the groups. The is reported as % methylation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>shotgun Lipidomics in skeletal muscle and adipose tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>shotgun lipidomics will be ran via the a lipidomics core in both muscle and adipose tissue. The quantified lipid metabolites (over 1000 will be quantified) will compared amongst groups using multivariate analyses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>DNA methylation Across tissues</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the correlation of DNA methylation in the fatty acyl coa reductase gene correlation across tissues (muscle vs. adipose vs. buccal)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Antipsychotic Agents</condition>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>APIGT</arm_group_label>
    <description>Bipolar subjects treated with antipsychotics and having impaired glucose tolerance</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>APNGT</arm_group_label>
    <description>Bipolar subjects treated with antipsychotics and having normal glucose tolerance</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LINGT</arm_group_label>
    <description>Bipolar subjects treated with lithium and having normal glucose tolerance</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Bipolar patients treated with Lithium or an antipsychotic
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Aged 18-65 with a Bipolar Spectrum Diagnosis (Bipolar I, II or NOS)

          2. Currently treated with lithium or an antipsychotic as determined by a physician for at
             least 3 months at a stable dosage.

          3. Non- obese with BMI &lt; 30

          4. Able to communicate meaningfully with the investigator and legally competent to
             provide informed written consent.

          5. Females must be non-lactating, have a pregnancy test and be on acceptable birth
             control

        105 subjects will be studied in total from three groups:

          1. One group will consist of 35 bipolar patients currently stable on an antipsychotics
             with impaired glucose tolerance (2-hour postprandial plasma glucose of 140-199mg/dL).

          2. The second group will consist of 35 age, gender, and body composition matched bipolar
             patients currently stable on an antipsychotic with normal glucose tolerance (2-hour
             postprandial plasma glucose &lt;140mg/dL.

          3. The third group will consist of 35 age, gender and body composition matched bipolar
             subjects stable on lithium with normal glucose tolerance.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Currently diagnosed with diabetes (type I or II) or receiving treatment for diabetes.
             Any history of metabolic complications (weight gain, high cholesterol, high blood
             pressure) before taking an antipsychotic.

          2. Active diagnosis of alcohol or substance abuse.

          3. Primary relative diagnosed with type II diabetes.

          4. Treated with any of the following medications: a) Systemic glucocorticoids (more than
             2 weeks), antineoplastic agents, transplant medications, anti-retroviral medications
             within 6 months prior to screening.

               -  Start or change of hormonal replacement therapy within 3 months prior to
                  screening.

          5. History or presence of any of the following conditions

               -  Clinically significant heart disease (New York Heart Classification greater than
                  grade II; more than non-specific ST-T wave changes on the EKG)

               -  Peripheral vascular disease (history of claudication)

               -  Clinically significant pulmonary disease.

               -  Current uncontrolled hypertension (systolic BP&gt;160 mmHg, diastolic BP&gt;100 mmHg)

               -  History or presence of malignancy other than basal cell or squamous cell skin
                  cancer

               -  Clinically significant hematologic disease

          6. Any of the following abnormal laboratory values:

               -  Hematocrit &lt; 35 vol%

               -  Serum creatinine &gt; 1.6 mg/dl

               -  aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or Alkaline
                  phosphatase &gt; 2.5 times the upper limit of normal

               -  Prothrombin time (PT), Partial thromboplastin time (PTT) outside the normal
                  reference range

               -  thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) outside the normal reference range

               -  Triglycerides &gt; 400 mg/dl

               -  Platelet count &lt; 50,000

          7. Blood donation within 2 months prior to screening

          8. Engage in exercise with moderate to hard intensity for greater than 1 hour per day for
             5 or more days per week.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kyle J Burghardt, PharmD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wayne State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wayne State University Clinical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 2, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wayne State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kyle Burghardt</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antipsychotic Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

