<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02373774</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAO3705</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02373774</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultrasound vs Palpation for Infant Lumbar Puncture</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sonographic Visualization vs Palpation Technique for Infant Lumbar Puncture</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if performing an ultrasound to identify the space
      to insert the needle before performing a lumbar puncture will improve success of the
      procedure and patient safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators are conducting a single-center, prospective two-arm parallel group
      randomized clinical trial in an urban pediatric emergency department to determine if
      performing an ultrasound prior to lumbar puncture procedure improves success of the
      procedure.

      Patients will be block-randomized into two groups to receive procedural interspace selection
      via 1) standard anatomic palpation technique or 2) visualization with pre-procedural
      ultrasound (experimental group).

        1. Standard Anatomic Palpation Technique:

           Participants randomized to this group will receive standard of care treatment with
           providers using the palpation technique to select an interspace. As variations on the
           palpation technique exist, the investigators will provide a standardized educational
           cognitive aid that clinicians can use for this approach.

        2. Pre-Procedural Ultrasound:

      Clinicians will first use the standard palpation technique to select an interspace for
      ultrasound evaluation. A select group of pediatric emergency medicine attendings and fellows
      who have already trained to a mastery standard with the ultrasound protocol will then conduct
      the pre-procedural ultrasound. The clinicians performing the lumbar puncture will be provided
      the following information to conduct the lumbar puncture:

      i. Assessment for fluid at the level selected (and the number of interspaces above that have
      fluid without conus present)

      ii. Measurements of appropriate angle and depth

      iii. Evaluation of any overlying vasculature

      Post-Lumbar Puncture:

      After the lumbar puncture, infants randomized to both groups will receive a post-procedural
      ultrasound scan performed by one of the mastery trained ultrasound physicians.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lumbar Puncture Success - composite score including lab results and reported attempts</measure>
    <time_frame>Outcome measured on the same day of the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Our primary outcome of the clinical trial is binary, success or failure of lumbar puncture. Success is defined as obtaining a sample of cerebrospinal fluid on the first attempt that has a red blood cell count of &lt;1000 red blood cells per high-powered field.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Attempts- per direct observation</measure>
    <time_frame>Outcome measured at the time of the procedure (same day)</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the number of times a lumbar puncture needle is removed from skin and reinserted or a new needle is inserted.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Traumatic Lumbar Puncture- per lab results</measure>
    <time_frame>Outcome measured on the same day of the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as cerebrospinal fluid with greater than 1000 red blood cells per highpowered field. (will look for first attempt and for overall)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Initial Lumbar Interspace Selection- as measured during clip review</measure>
    <time_frame>Clip review for outcome will occur on average within one month of the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the lumbar interspace that the clinician performing the lumbar puncture initially inserts the lumbar puncture needle into, with the level determined by the post-procedural ultrasound by a blinded sonologist.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Highest Lumbar Interspace Selectionas-measured during clip review</measure>
    <time_frame>Clip review for outcome occurs on average within one month of the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the lumbar interspace that the lumbar puncture needle is inserted that is the most caudal (when more than one is performed), with level determined by the post-procedural ultrasound by a blinded sonologist.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lumbar Puncture Success - as per lab results ( &lt;1000 red blood cells per high powered field on any attempt)</measure>
    <time_frame>Outcome measured on the same day of the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Overall success will be defined as obtaining fluid with csf &lt;1000 rbcs by any practitioner on any attempt</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">81</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal; Puncture, Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Anatomic Palpation Technique</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to this group will receive standard of care treatment with providers using the palpation technique to select an interspace to perform lumbar puncture.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-Procedural Ultrasound</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to this group will receive an ultrasound of the interspace selected via the palpation method prior to performance of the lumbar puncture to determine measurements of appropriate angle and depth and evaluation of any overlying vasculature.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive an ultrasound prior to lumbar puncture procedure to help visualize and select spinal interspace.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-Procedural Ultrasound</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(Zonare Z1.pro and/or Sonosite Mturbo)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient is less than 90 days old.

          -  Patient is receiving a lumbar puncture

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient is clinically unstable

          -  Patient had a previous lumbar puncture in the past 24 hours

          -  An outside consultant (not working in ED) is performing the LP

          -  Patient has developmental delay or neurological impairment

          -  There is no legal guardian present

          -  The legal guardians speak neither English nor Spanish

          -  There is no ultrasound personnel available to enroll
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David O Kessler, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gerald Behr, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter S Dayan, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>NY</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alpern ER, Stanley RM, Gorelick MH, Donaldson A, Knight S, Teach SJ, Singh T, Mahajan P, Goepp JG, Kuppermann N, Dean JM, Chamberlain JM; Pediatric Emergency Care Applied Research Network. Epidemiology of a pediatric emergency medicine research network: the PECARN Core Data Project. Pediatr Emerg Care. 2006 Oct;22(10):689-99.</citation>
    <PMID>17047467</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jain S, Cheng J, Alpern ER, Thurm C, Schroeder L, Black K, Ellison AM, Stone K, Alessandrini EA. Management of febrile neonates in US pediatric emergency departments. Pediatrics. 2014 Feb;133(2):187-95. doi: 10.1542/peds.2013-1820. Epub 2014 Jan 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24470644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kessler DO, Arteaga G, Ching K, Haubner L, Kamdar G, Krantz A, Lindower J, Miller M, Petrescu M, Pusic MV, Rocker J, Shah N, Strother C, Tilt L, Weinberg ER, Chang TP, Fein DM, Auerbach M. Interns' success with clinical procedures in infants after simulation training. Pediatrics. 2013 Mar;131(3):e811-20. doi: 10.1542/peds.2012-0607. Epub 2013 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23439901</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nigrovic LE, Kuppermann N, Neuman MI. Risk factors for traumatic or unsuccessful lumbar punctures in children. Ann Emerg Med. 2007 Jun;49(6):762-71. Epub 2007 Feb 23.</citation>
    <PMID>17321005</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glatstein MM, Zucker-Toledano M, Arik A, Scolnik D, Oren A, Reif S. Incidence of traumatic lumbar puncture: experience of a large, tertiary care pediatric hospital. Clin Pediatr (Phila). 2011 Nov;50(11):1005-9. doi: 10.1177/0009922811410309. Epub 2011 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21622691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonadio W. Pediatric lumbar puncture and cerebrospinal fluid analysis. J Emerg Med. 2014 Jan;46(1):141-50. doi: 10.1016/j.jemermed.2013.08.056. Epub 2013 Nov 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24188604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duniec L, Nowakowski P, Kosson D, Łazowski T. Anatomical landmarks based assessment of intravertebral space level for lumbar puncture is misleading in more than 30%. Anaesthesiol Intensive Ther. 2013 Jan-Mar;45(1):1-6. doi: 10.5603/AIT.2013.0001.</citation>
    <PMID>23572300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Furness G, Reilly MP, Kuchi S. An evaluation of ultrasound imaging for identification of lumbar intervertebral level. Anaesthesia. 2002 Mar;57(3):277-80.</citation>
    <PMID>11892638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shekelle PG, Wachter RM, Pronovost PJ, Schoelles K, McDonald KM, Dy SM, Shojania K, Reston J, Berger Z, Johnsen B, Larkin JW, Lucas S, Martinez K, Motala A, Newberry SJ, Noble M, Pfoh E, Ranji SR, Rennke S, Schmidt E, Shanman R, Sullivan N, Sun F, Tipton K, Treadwell JR, Tsou A, Vaiana ME, Weaver SJ, Wilson R, Winters BD. Making health care safer II: an updated critical analysis of the evidence for patient safety practices. Evid Rep Technol Assess (Full Rep). 2013 Mar;(211):1-945. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24423049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coley BD, Shiels WE 2nd, Hogan MJ. Diagnostic and interventional ultrasonography in neonatal and infant lumbar puncture. Pediatr Radiol. 2001 Jun;31(6):399-402.</citation>
    <PMID>11436885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abo A, Chen L, Johnston P, Santucci K. Positioning for lumbar puncture in children evaluated by bedside ultrasound. Pediatrics. 2010 May;125(5):e1149-53. doi: 10.1542/peds.2009-0646. Epub 2010 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>20403933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lo MD, Parisi MT, Brown JC, Klein EJ. Sitting or tilt position for infant lumbar puncture does not increase ultrasound measurements of lumbar subarachnoid space width. Pediatr Emerg Care. 2013 May;29(5):588-91. doi: 10.1097/PEC.0b013e31828e630d.</citation>
    <PMID>23603648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Öncel S, Günlemez A, Anik Y, Alvur M. Positioning of infants in the neonatal intensive care unit for lumbar puncture as determined by bedside ultrasonography. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2013 Mar;98(2):F133-5. doi: 10.1136/archdischild-2011-301475. Epub 2012 Jun 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22684159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaikh F, Brzezinski J, Alexander S, Arzola C, Carvalho JC, Beyene J, Sung L. Ultrasound imaging for lumbar punctures and epidural catheterisations: systematic review and meta-analysis. BMJ. 2013 Mar 26;346:f1720. doi: 10.1136/bmj.f1720. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23532866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bruccoleri RE, Chen L. Needle-entry angle for lumbar puncture in children as determined by using ultrasonography. Pediatrics. 2011 Apr;127(4):e921-6. doi: 10.1542/peds.2010-2511. Epub 2011 Mar 28.</citation>
    <PMID>21444601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bailie HC, Arthurs OJ, Murray MJ, Kelsall AW. Weight-based determination of spinal canal depth for paediatric lumbar punctures. Arch Dis Child. 2013 Nov;98(11):877-80. doi: 10.1136/archdischild-2013-303793. Epub 2013 Aug 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23966025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilson DA, Prince JR. John Caffey award. MR imaging determination of the location of the normal conus medullaris throughout childhood. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 1989 May;152(5):1029-32.</citation>
    <PMID>2650477</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hill CA, Gibson PJ. Ultrasound determination of the normal location of the conus medullaris in neonates. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol. 1995 Mar;16(3):469-72.</citation>
    <PMID>7793365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolf S, Schneble F, Tröger J. The conus medullaris: time of ascendence to normal level. Pediatr Radiol. 1992;22(8):590-2.</citation>
    <PMID>1491937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sahin F, Selçuki M, Ecin N, Zenciroğlu A, Unlü A, Yilmaz F, Maviş N, Saribaş S. Level of conus medullaris in term and preterm neonates. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 1997 Jul;77(1):F67-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9279188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rozzelle CJ, Reed GT, Kirkman JL, Shannon CN, Chern JJ, Wellons JC 3rd, Tubbs RS. Sonographic determination of normal Conus Medullaris level and ascent in early infancy. Childs Nerv Syst. 2014 Apr;30(4):655-8. doi: 10.1007/s00381-013-2310-6. Epub 2013 Nov 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24178234</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tame SJ, Burstal R. Investigation of the radiological relationship between iliac crests, conus medullaris and vertebral level in children. Paediatr Anaesth. 2003 Oct;13(8):676-80.</citation>
    <PMID>14535904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kesler H, Dias MS, Kalapos P. Termination of the normal conus medullaris in children: a whole-spine magnetic resonance imaging study. Neurosurg Focus. 2007;23(2):E7.</citation>
    <PMID>17961006</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 27, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Kessler</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>infant</keyword>
  <keyword>lumbar puncture</keyword>
  <keyword>patient safety</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

