<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02376322</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ISCMPA01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02376322</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypofractionated Radiotherapy (16/2) for the Palliation of Complicated Bone Metastases in Patients With KPS</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Hypofractionated Radiotherapy (16 Gy in 2 Fractions With an Interval of One Week) for the Palliation of Complicated Bone Metastases in Patients With Poor Performance Status</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Santa Casa de Porto Alegre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Santa Casa de Porto Alegre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Literature has shown that hypofractionated radiotherapy regimens are efficacious in patients
      with complicated bone metastases and have a low potential for severe treatment-related
      toxicities. There is a clear need for hypofractionated schedules in the complicated bone
      metastases population, especially when considering the overarching aim of palliative
      radiotherapy and the clinical features of this patient population. As well, current research
      examining hypofractionated approaches in bone metastases patients with impending or
      pathologic fractures, neuropathic pain or accompanying soft tissue masses has been markedly
      scarce.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In response the the already commented on, the purpose of this one armed, phase II trial is to
      determine the efficacy and safety profile of a hypofractionated radiotherapy regimen, 16 Gy
      in 2 fractions with an interval of one week, for the palliation of complicated bone
      metastases in patients with poor performance status.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 30, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 30, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Radiotherapy</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall pain response at the site of treatment, which will be measured at two months post-treatment. Pain response will be measured using the International Consensus on Palliative Radiotherapy Endpoints Pain Response Categories.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months after the end of the second radiotherapy fraction</time_frame>
    <description>The general follow up will finish 1 year after each patient inclusion</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life as assessed by the EORTC QLQ PAL-15 and EORTC QLQ-BM22</measure>
    <time_frame>General follow up will be 1 year after each patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life assessed by these 2 questionnaries will follow composite information</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects of Radiotherapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>General follow up will be 1 year after each patient inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Nausea and vomiting, pain flare, skin rash, esophagitis, mucositis, diarrhea, spinal cord/cauda equina compression, pathologic fracture, re-irradiation rate).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Bone Metastases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Radiotherapy in bone metastases</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The purpose of this one armed, phase II trial is to determine the efficacy and safety profile of a hypofractionated radiotherapy regimen, 16 Gy in 2 fractions with an interval of one week, for the palliation of complicated bone metastases in patients with poor performance status.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Hypofractionated radiotherapy regimen, 16 Gy in 2 fractions in complicated bone metastases in patients with poor performance status</description>
    <arm_group_label>Radiotherapy in bone metastases</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically or cytologically proven malignancy.

          2. Patients aged 18 and above.

          3. Advanced cancer patients with at least one complicated bone metastasis. A complicated
             bone metastasis will be operationally defined as a bone metastasis that has an
             accompanying: soft tissue mass or extraosseous component penetrating the normal
             cortical boundary; neuropathic pain; post surgical intervention for bone fixation;
             impending fracture or high fracture risk in weight bearing long bone as defined by
             Harrington's criteria but not surgical candidate: lytic bone lesion involving more
             than ½ the diameter of the bone cortex , greater than 2.5 cm in greatest diameter, or
             in the intertrochanteric line (29).

          4. Patients with Karnofsky Performance Status (KPS) 30-60 at the time of baseline
             evaluation.

          5. Patients who are planned to receive radiation treatment to the complicated site(s)
             being followed for study.

          6. Patients who had surgery for complicated bone metastases.

          7. Patients who are currently taking any systemic therapy (i.e. chemotherapy, hormone
             therapy, or bone modifying agents) or planning to begin systemic therapy within two
             weeks of treatment will be allowed to participate in the study; study personnel will
             note any use of systemic therapy in the study records.

          8. Patients who are able to provide a worst pain score at the complicated site(s) being
             followed for study.

          9. Patients who are able and willing to fill out a daily diary.

         10. Patients who are able to provide informed consent prior to being enrolled to the
             study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with leukemia or Hodgkin's/non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.

          2. Patients who are surgical candidates with pathologic fractures or lesions at high risk
             for pathologic fracture in the humerus, radius, ulna, femur, tibia, or fibula. They
             will be eligible for post-operative hypofractionated radiotherapy.

          3. Patients with spinal cord compression or cauda equina syndrome.

          4. Patients who are currently receiving any radiopharmaceuticals.

          5. Patients who are unable to record a pain score, complete a daily diary or to
             communicate requested information to study personnel.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maurício F Silva, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical Doctor at Radiation Oncology Unit</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ISCMPA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <state>RS</state>
        <zip>90000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICESP</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>S. Maria Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Terni</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 10, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Santa Casa de Porto Alegre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mauricio F Silva</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor at Radiation Oncology Unity</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Marrow Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

