<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02379429</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>150087</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>15-C-0087</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02379429</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Care of the Urothelial Cancer Patient and Prospective Procurement of Urothelial Cancer Tissue</brief_title>
  <official_title>Care of the Urothelial Cancer Patient and Prospective Collection of Biospecimens From Healthy Volunteers and Urothelial Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Urothelial cancer is cancer of the bladder, ureter, and urethra. Researchers want to better
      understand what changes in a person s cells and genes cause this cancer to form. This may
      help them find new ways to treat it.

      Objective:

      - To perform DNA sequencing to help researchers learn the differences between normal tissue
      and tumor tissue. Also, to learn how molecular changes - including gene changes - might help
      predict the course of disease and how people respond to therapy.

      Eligibility:

      - Adults age 18 and older who have or are suspected of having urothelial cancer or an
      inherited disorder that raises their risk of getting bladder cancer.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam. Their medical records and tissue
           samples will be reviewed.

        -  Eligible participants will give tissue blocks of their original tumor. The blocks will
           be put in a tissue bank.

        -  Participants medical records may be reviewed.

        -  Participants may have a medical history and physical exam.

        -  Participants may have blood and urine tests. They may have imaging scans. They may give
           urine, blood, and saliva samples. These samples may be used in future research.

        -  If participants need surgery for their cancer, researchers will keep some of the tissue
           (both tumor and normal tissue). The tissue may be used in future research.

        -  Participants will go back to the Clinical Center in 6 months. They may give saliva,
           urine, and blood samples. After 6 months, they will be seen by their local doctor for
           standard post-surgical visits.

        -  Participants will be called every 6 months to give health updates.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Urothelial carcinoma, present as lower or upper urinary tract disease, is the most
           expensive malignancy to treat from diagnosis to death, and no major advances in drug
           therapy have taken place in the last two decades.

        -  Understanding the molecular mechanisms and genomic alterations that cause urothelial
           carcinoma will provide the foundation for the development of novel targeted therapeutic
           agents for this disease. Since 1982 investigators in the Urologic Oncology Branch have
           been studying the genetic basis of urologic cancers. The identification of the genes for
           cancer of the kidney has led to the approval by the FDA of a number of new agents for
           patients with advanced disease. Similarly, it is our goal to study the cancer biology
           (genomic, molecular, and cellular biology) of urothelial carcinoma in order to develop
           novel treatment strategies.

        -  Collection of patient tumor samples allows us to study molecular and biologic pathways
           and develop novel targeted therapies. Correlation of these samples with clinical
           outcomes in patients allows us to predict and understand clinical outcomes and possibly
           develop predictive and/or prognostic biomarkers.

        -  Collection of blood, urine and saliva from healthy volunteers will allow us to
           distinguish normal and inflammatory conditions from malignant diseases. Furthermore, the
           specimens will provide appropriate controls for comparison.

      Objective (Primary):

        -  Collect blood, urine, and benign and malignant tissue from patients with known or
           suspected urothelial cancer for the purpose of elucidating the molecular mechanisms of
           carcinogenesis in urothelial cancer and ultimately, identifying novel therapeutic
           targets.

        -  Collect blood, urine and saliva from healthy volunteers for the purpose of establishing
           controls for comparison with urothelial cancer specimens.

      Eligibility:

        -  Adults with biopsy-proven or suspected urothelial cancer who require diagnostic or
           therapeutic intervention as part of their diagnosis, standard of care treatment, or
           followup/surveillance for their neoplasm.

        -  Healthy volunteers from whom blood, saliva and urine samples are easily obtainable.

      Design:

        -  Care of the patient with urothelial carcinoma will be provided as per medically
           indicated standards and in the process, normal and malignant urothelial cancer tissues
           may be obtained at the time of clinically indicated diagnostic and/or therapeutic
           intervention.

        -  Blood, urine, and saliva samples for research may be obtained from patients and healthy
           volunteers at baseline. Additionally, blood and urine may be collected from patients at
           follow-up intervals.

        -  No investigational or experimental therapy will be given as part of this protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 20, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Collect samples for the purpose of studying the molecular mechanisms of carcinogenesis in urothelial cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>Collection of blood, urine, saliva, and/or benign and malignant tissue</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Collect detailed history, pathologic data, perioperative findings, and treatment data to better characterize the natural and clinical histories of urothelial cancer when feasible.</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>Collection of clinical histories of urothelial cancer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Develop stable urothelial / bladder cancer cell lines from procured tissue when feasible.</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>Generating cell lines</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perform molecular profiling and analysis to better characterizeurothelial cancer and identify novel targets.</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
    <description>Collection of blood, urine, saliva, and/or benign and malignant tissue</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Urinary Tract Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Urothelial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Adults with biopsy-proven or suspected urothelial cancer who require diagnostic or therapeutic intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy volunteers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Adults (&gt;= 18 years of age) with biopsy-proven or suspected urothelial cancer who
             require and are willing to undergo diagnostic or therapeutic intervention as part of
             their diagnosis, standard of care treatment, or follow-up/surveillance for their
             neoplasm.

          -  ECOG performance status of 0-3.

          -  Must be willing and able to provide informed consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Subjects who are pregnant.

          -  Subjects co-morbidities preclude diagnostic or therapeutic intervention.
             Co-morbidities include:

             --Ongoing treatment for another non-skin malignancy.

          -  History of hepatitis B/C or HIV.

        ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA FOR HEALTHY VOLUNTEERS (NCI ONLY)

        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        -Adults (greater than or equal to 18 years of age) and able to give informed consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Subjects who are pregnant.

          -  Diagnosis of cancer requiring treatment other than minor resection of basal cell or
             squamous cell skin cancers.

          -  Heart, lung, kidney disease, or other medical conditions as per Principal Investigator
             discretion.

          -  History of acute or chronic hepatitis B/C or HIV infection.

          -  Healthy volunteers who are family members with germline mutations.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Piyush K Agarwal, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sonia E Bellfield, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 760-6118</phone>
    <email>sonia.bellfield@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Piyush K Agarwal, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 760-6242</phone>
    <email>agarwalpk2@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2015-C-0087.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 15, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 5, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Specimen Collection</keyword>
  <keyword>Urine</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood</keyword>
  <keyword>Saliva</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

