<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02372409</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201502062</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02372409</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using MRI-Guided Laser Heat Ablation to Induce Disruption of the Peritumoral Blood Brain Barrier to Enhance Delivery and Efficacy of Treatment of Pediatric Brain Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Using MRI-Guided Laser Heat Ablation to Induce Disruption of the Peritumoral Blood Brain Barrier to Enhance Delivery and Efficacy of Treatment of Pediatric Brain Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      By employing a combination of advanced MRI techniques and correlative serum biomarkers of
      blood brain barrier (BBB) disruption, the investigators plan to develop a powerful, first of
      its kind clinical algorithm in pediatrics whereby the investigators can measure and identify
      the window of maximal BBB disruption post MLA to 1) allow for an alternative to surgery in
      incompletely resected tumors, 2) allow for optimal chemotherapeutic dosing to achieve the
      greatest benefits and the least systemic side effects and 3) distinguish subsequent tumor
      progression from long-term MLA treatment effects. Preliminary data in adult imaging studies
      have shown that the BBB disruption lasts for several weeks following treatment before
      returning to a low baseline. This pilot therapeutic study will provide preliminary validation
      in pediatric patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 14, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm A only: Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm A only: Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm B only: Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm B only: Quality of life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year from MLA</time_frame>
    <description>-Using Karnofsky or Lansky performance status in patients following MLA and in patients who receive doxorubicin and maintenance etoposide after MLA.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of MR imaging with peritumoral BBB disruption</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year from MLA</time_frame>
    <description>The linear regression model will used to investigate the correlation between MR imaging and peritumoral BBB disruption. To account for correlation among the repeated measures from the same patient, the longitudinal data will be analyzed with the use of linear generalized estimating equation (GEE). Whether the average measurements differ at the multiple time points will be evaluated through GEE model. Least-square means at each time points will be presented and standard errors will be calculated within the use of the GEE sandwich method when accounting for within-patient correlation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum biomarkers of peritumoral BBB disruption</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year from MLA</time_frame>
    <description>Since the investigators do not know which biomarkers will have better correlation with the Ktrans data from DCE and DSC-MRI and patients' survival outcome, the investigators plan to determine the levels of all 3 biomarkers in a blinded fashion. Once both the Ktrans and biomarker levels are available, the investigators will determine which biomarkers have the closest correlation that is statistically significant with the Ktrans. Pearson correlation coefficient (r) will be determined for each biomarker and Ktrans value. Biomarkers with higher correlation coefficient (r approaching 1) will be given higher priority.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Predictive value of the peritumoral permeability score for patient outcome as measured by PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Biomarkers with higher correlation coefficient (r approaching 1) will be given higher priority. A minimum r=0.5 is required for inclusion for further analysis and will be used as a peritumoral permeability score. This score will then be correlated with the patient outcome data (as measured by 6 month PFS rate) to determine whether it has a predictive value.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Pilocytic Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Anaplastic Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Mixed Oligoastrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Mixed Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Oligodendroglioma</condition>
  <condition>Optic Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Astrocytoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (MRI-guided laser ablation)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MLA is a minimally invasive laser surgery currently FDA approved for cytoreductive treatment of brain tumors, both primary and metastatic. MLA employs a small incision in the scalp and skull, through which a thin laser probe is inserted and guided by MR imaging to the core of a tumor mass where it delivers hyperthermic ablation from the core to the rim.
Participants will undergo DCE and DSC-MRI imaging at the following time points:
no more than 3 weeks prior to MLA (OPTIONAL)
within approximately 4 days after MLA
2-4 weeks after MLA
Every 12 weeks (+/- 7 days) for the first year or until disease progression</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (MRI-guided laser ablation, doxorubicin, etoposide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MLA is a minimally invasive laser surgery currently FDA approved for cytoreductive treatment of brain tumors, both primary and metastatic. MLA employs a small incision in the scalp and skull, through which a thin laser probe is inserted and guided by MR imaging to the core of a tumor mass where it delivers hyperthermic ablation from the core to the rim.
Within 7 days of MLA (range 2-14 days) doxorubicin will be given intravenously on an outpatient basis weekly for 6 weeks at a dose of 25 mg/m^2 over 5-30 minutes
Following the completion of doxorubin, etoposide 50 mg/m^2/day will be given orally for 21 days of each 28-day cycle (treatment can continue up to 24 cycles)
Participants will undergo DCE and DSC-MRI imaging at the following time points:
no more than 3 weeks prior to MLA (OPTIONAL)
within approximately 4 days after MLA
2-4 weeks after MLA
every 8 weeks (+/- 7 days) until 2 years have elapsed or disease progression, whichever comes first</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI-guided laser ablation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (MRI-guided laser ablation)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (MRI-guided laser ablation, doxorubicin, etoposide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MLA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Doxorubicin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (MRI-guided laser ablation, doxorubicin, etoposide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Adriamycin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etoposide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (MRI-guided laser ablation, doxorubicin, etoposide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Etoposide phosphate</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16</other_name>
    <other_name>Toposar</other_name>
    <other_name>Etopophos</other_name>
    <other_name>VePesid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dynamic contrast-enhanced (DCE) MRI</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (MRI-guided laser ablation)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (MRI-guided laser ablation, doxorubicin, etoposide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DCE-MRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dynamic susceptibility contrast (DSC) MRI</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (MRI-guided laser ablation)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (MRI-guided laser ablation, doxorubicin, etoposide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DSC-MRI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        ARM A

          -  Presumed pediatric gliomas (grades I-IV) on MRI that are determined to be candidates
             for MLA by the treating neurosurgeon

          -  Age 3 to ≤ 21

          -  Karnofsky/Lansky performance status ≥ 60%

        ARM B

          -  Recurrent pediatric brain tumors determined candidates for MLA as determined by the
             treating neurosurgeon.

          -  Unequivocal evidence of tumor progression by MRI

          -  There must be an interval of at least 12 weeks from the completion of radiotherapy to
             study registration except if there is unequivocal evidence for tumor recurrence per
             RANO criteria. When the interval is less than 12 weeks from the completion of
             radiotherapy, the use of PET scan is allowed to differentiate between evidence of
             tumor recurrence and pseudoprogression.

          -  Recurrent lesions with dimension and contour that are determined by the treating
             neurosurgeon to be appropriate for MLA.

          -  Age 3 to ≤ 21

          -  Karnofsky/Lansky performance status ≥ 60%

          -  Adequate cardiac function as determined by a shortening fraction ≥ 27% or left
             ventricular ejection fraction ≥ 50% by echocardiogram within the past 1 year prior to
             registration.

          -  Prior anthracycline therapy does not exceed 200 mg/m^2 total cumulative dose.

          -  Adequate bone marrow and hepatic function as defined below (must be within 7 days of
             MLA):

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1000/mcl (G-CSF is allowed)

               -  Platelets ≥ 100 K/cumm

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL (pRBC transfusion +/- ESA are allowed)

               -  ALT ≤ 3 x ULN

               -  AST ≤ 3 x ULN

               -  ALP ≤ 3 x ULN. If ALP is &gt; 3 x ULN, GGT must be checked and be ≤ 3 x ULN.

               -  Bilirubin ≤ 2 x ULN

          -  At the time of registration, patient must have recovered from the toxic effects of
             prior therapy to no more than grade 1 toxicity.

          -  At the time of registration, patient must be at least 4 weeks from other prior
             cytotoxic chemotherapy.

          -  Women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control, abstinence) prior to study entry and for
             the duration of study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is
             pregnant while participating in this study, she must inform her treating physician
             immediately.

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign an IRB approved written informed consent
             document (or that of legally authorized representative, if applicable).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        ARM A

          -  Currently receiving or scheduled to receive any other therapies intended to treat the
             newly diagnosed glioma prior to MLA and the first post-MLA blood collection for
             correlative studies.

          -  Multi-focal or metastatic disease.

          -  Pregnant and/or breastfeeding. Premenopausal women must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test within 14 days of study entry.

          -  Inability to undergo MRI due to personal or medical reasons.

          -  Known history of HIV or autoimmune diseases requiring immunosuppressant drugs.

        ARM B

          -  Prior treatment with bevacizumab within 12 weeks of study entry.

          -  Previous treatment with complete cumulative doses of daunorubicin, idarubicin, and/or
             other anthracyclines and anthracenediones that is equivalent to a total dose of &gt; 200
             mg/m2 doxorubicin.

          -  More than 2 prior relapses (not counting the current relapse being treated on this
             study).

          -  Currently receiving any other investigational agents that are intended as treatments
             of the relapsed tumor.

          -  Multi-focal or metastatic disease.

          -  A history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or
             biologic composition to doxorubicin or other agents used in the study.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, recent heart attack within the previous 12 months or severe heart
             problems, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Pregnant and/or breastfeeding. Premenopausal women must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test within 14 days of study entry.

          -  Inability to undergo MRI due to personal or medical reasons.

          -  Known history of HIV or autoimmune diseases requiring immunosuppressant drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Gauvain, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen Gauvain, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(314) 454-4457</phone>
    <email>gauvaink@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Gauvain, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>314-454-4457</phone>
      <email>gauvaink@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen Gauvain, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Limbrick, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joshua Shimony, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gavin Dunn, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joshua Rubin, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Allison King, M.D., M.P.H.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric Leuthardt, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holodny AI, Nusbaum AO, Festa S, Pronin IN, Lee HJ, Kalnin AJ. Correlation between the degree of contrast enhancement and the volume of peritumoral edema in meningiomas and malignant gliomas. Neuroradiology. 1999 Nov;41(11):820-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10602854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kassner A, Thornhill R. Measuring the integrity of the human blood-brain barrier using magnetic resonance imaging. Methods Mol Biol. 2011;686:229-45. doi: 10.1007/978-1-60761-938-3_10.</citation>
    <PMID>21082374</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hawasli AH, Ray WZ, Murphy RK, Dacey RG Jr, Leuthardt EC. Magnetic resonance imaging-guided focused laser interstitial thermal therapy for subinsular metastatic adenocarcinoma: technical case report. Neurosurgery. 2012 Jun;70(2 Suppl Operative):332-7; discussion 338. doi: 10.1227/NEU.0b013e318232fc90.</citation>
    <PMID>21869722</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gong W, Wang Z, Liu N, Lin W, Wang X, Xu D, Liu H, Zeng C, Xie X, Mei X, Lü W. Improving efficiency of adriamycin crossing blood brain barrier by combination of thermosensitive liposomes and hyperthermia. Biol Pharm Bull. 2011;34(7):1058-64.</citation>
    <PMID>21720013</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quick J, Gessler F, Dützmann S, Hattingen E, Harter PN, Weise LM, Franz K, Seifert V, Senft C. Benefit of tumor resection for recurrent glioblastoma. J Neurooncol. 2014 Apr;117(2):365-72. doi: 10.1007/s11060-014-1397-2. Epub 2014 Feb 15.</citation>
    <PMID>24535317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashley DM, Meier L, Kerby T, Zalduondo FM, Friedman HS, Gajjar A, Kun L, Duffner PK, Smith S, Longee D. Response of recurrent medulloblastoma to low-dose oral etoposide. J Clin Oncol. 1996 Jun;14(6):1922-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8656261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davidson A, Gowing R, Lowis S, Newell D, Lewis I, Dicks-Mireaux C, Pinkerton CR. Phase II study of 21 day schedule oral etoposide in children. New Agents Group of the United Kingdom Children's Cancer Study Group (UKCCSG). Eur J Cancer. 1997 Oct;33(11):1816-22.</citation>
    <PMID>9470839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fulton D, Urtasun R, Forsyth P. Phase II study of prolonged oral therapy with etoposide (VP16) for patients with recurrent malignant glioma. J Neurooncol. 1996 Feb;27(2):149-55.</citation>
    <PMID>8699237</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Law M, Young R, Babb J, Rad M, Sasaki T, Zagzag D, Johnson G. Comparing perfusion metrics obtained from a single compartment versus pharmacokinetic modeling methods using dynamic susceptibility contrast-enhanced perfusion MR imaging with glioma grade. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol. 2006 Oct;27(9):1975-82.</citation>
    <PMID>17032878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blyth BJ, Farhavar A, Gee C, Hawthorn B, He H, Nayak A, Stöcklein V, Bazarian JJ. Validation of serum markers for blood-brain barrier disruption in traumatic brain injury. J Neurotrauma. 2009 Sep;26(9):1497-1507. doi: 10.1089/neu.2008-0738.</citation>
    <PMID>19257803</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dunn GP, Dunn IF, Curry WT. Focus on TILs: Prognostic significance of tumor infiltrating lymphocytes in human glioma. Cancer Immun. 2007 Aug 13;7:12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17691714</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dunn GP, Fecci PE, Curry WT. Cancer immunoediting in malignant glioma. Neurosurgery. 2012 Aug;71(2):201-22; discussion 222-3. doi: 10.1227/NEU.0b013e31824f840d. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22353795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 26, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Astrocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oligodendroglioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Nerve Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposomal doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

