<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02372162</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>e:Med Tuebingen, Protocol #1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02372162</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fingerprint Characterization of Advanced HCC</brief_title>
  <acronym>e:Med-HCC-1</acronym>
  <official_title>Fingerprint Characterization of Advanced HCC to Optimize Treatment Decisions and Enable an Early Prediction of Therapy Resistance (HCC Multiscale Trial-1)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Tuebingen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Tuebingen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This single center, open-label, uncontrolled, non-randomized observational study in patients
      with advanced HCC. The patients qualify either to a local treatment with transarterial
      chemoembolization (TACE) or to a systemic treatment with the multikinase inhibitor sorafenib.
      The aim of this feasibility study is to get a comprehensive image and molecular fingerprint
      of individual tumors, with the intention to govern therapy decisions. Furthermore, to improve
      the care of patients that get progressive disease under treatment, the investigators have to
      improve the investigators understanding of the development of therapy resistance, which will
      improve patient care at the time point of progressive disease. Therefore, the data of 20
      patients in each group will be used to identify molecular and / or image patterns, that can
      be used to predict treatment responses and thus govern an optimized individual cancer
      treatment for patients with advanced HCC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A single-center, open-label, uncontrolled, non-randomized clinical trial. The two treatment
      groups to receive:

      Group A Transarterial Chemoembolization (TACE): 20 patients that are treated with TACE will
      get an image and molecular fingerprint of the tumor prior to the first treatment with TACE, a
      second image fingerprint between week 2 - 4 after the first treatment with TACE, and a third
      image and molecular fingerprint at the time point of progressive disease.

      Group B Sorafenib: 20 patients that are treated with Sorafenib will get an image and
      molecular fingerprint of the tumor prior to the first treatment, between week 2 and 3 after
      the start of treatment and at the time point of progressive disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Availability of comprehensive imaging and molecular fingerprint data of individual tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>Each patient will be evaluated within six months, the whole study outcome will need 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>The aim of this feasibility study is to get comprehensive image and molecular fingerprints of individual tumors that can be used for systems biology approaches to predict therapy outcome and govern therapeutic decisions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of turnaround time for image and molecular data availability</measure>
    <time_frame>Each patient will be evaluated within six months, the whole study outcome will need 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>To set-up and optimize the workflow of data gathering and analysis for molecular and image fingerprints.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Description of correlations between image and molecular data</measure>
    <time_frame>Each patient will be evaluated within six months, the whole study outcome will need 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of results from image and molecular fingerprints at one point of time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Description of correlations between image and molecular data</measure>
    <time_frame>Each patient will be evaluated within six months, the whole study outcome will need 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of either image or molecular fingerprints at three different time points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of molecular and image patterns of treatment failure</measure>
    <time_frame>Each individual patient will be evaluated within six months, the whole study outcome will need 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>To identify molecular and image patterns of early treatment failure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of molecular and image patterns of treatment success</measure>
    <time_frame>Each individual patient will be evaluated within six months, the whole study outcome will need 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>To identify molecular and image patterns of early treatment success</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of molecular and image pattern fingerprints in patients and animal models</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluation within 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare molecular and image patterns from HCC patients with respective patterns from different animal models which might identify suitable preclinical models for different clinical tumor patterns.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of early outcome prediction patterns</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluation within 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine ideal imaging methods for an early prediction of progressive disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To provide data for a molecular diagnostic board</measure>
    <time_frame>Each individual patient will be evaluated as soon as data sets are available within this feasibility study</time_frame>
    <description>To set up a molecular diagnostic board that checks for data-based tailored treatment options</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluation within 48 months</time_frame>
    <description>To identify clinical relevant biomarkers from tumor tissue or blood / urine analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - TACE</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with transarterial chemoembolization (TACE) will get an &quot;Image Fingerprint&quot; and &quot;Molecular Fingerprint&quot; for tumor characterization in vivo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - Sorafenib</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with Sorafenib treatment will get an &quot;Image Fingerprint&quot; and &quot;Molecular Fingerprint&quot; for tumor characterization in vivo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Image Fingerprint</intervention_name>
    <description>This is an observational study that uses in depth diagnostic procedures to characterize patients with a comprehensive Image Fingerprint that includes CT, MRI and PET diagnostics</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - TACE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - Sorafenib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Molecular Fingerprint</intervention_name>
    <description>This is an observational study that uses in depth diagnostic procedures to characterize patients with a Molecular Fingerprint that includes next-generation sequencing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A - TACE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B - Sorafenib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Biospecimens that will be investigated are tumor tissue and blood.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients aged ≥ 18, of both genders, with advanced stage hepatocellular carcinoma, for
        Group A BCLC class B (intermediate stage, performance status-ECOG 0, multinodular HCC), for
        Group B BCLC class B or C (advanced stage, performance status-ECOG 1-2, invasive tumor
        pattern (vascular invasion/extra hepatic spread)).

        Number: Up to 20 patients to receive therapy with TACE (Group A) and up to 20 patients to
        receive Sorafenib as first-line systemic therapy (Group B).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        All inclusion criteria must be met at the time of screening unless otherwise specified:

          1. Male or female ≥ 18 years.

          2. Written informed consent obtained prior to any trial specific procedure.

          3. Advanced stage hepatocellular carcinoma, BCLC class B for Group A and BCLC class B or
             C for Group B (refer to Appendix 3 for BCLC classification).

          4. Child-Pugh class A and B. Only patients with Child-Pugh index class B of not more than
             7 will be included. Patients with untreatable ascites or hepatic encephalopathy &gt;
             Grade 1 are excluded (see exclusion criteria; (refer to Appendix 4 for Child Pugh
             classification)).

          5. Indication for TACE or sorafenib treatment confirmed by an interdisciplinary tumor
             board.

          6. ECOG performance status 0, 1 or 2 (refer to Appendix 2 for definitions of ECOG
             grades).

          7. Life expectancy of 12 weeks or more.

          8. Adequate hematological parameters, as demonstrated by:

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dl (SI units: 5.6 mmol/l);

               -  WBC ≥ 3.0 x 109/l;

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥1,500/mm3;

               -  Platelets ≥ 75 x 109/l;

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 5 times
                  upper limit of normal range (ULNR);

               -  Bilirubin ≤ 3 mg/dl;

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg/dl (SI units: 132 µmol/l);

               -  Prothrombin Time (PT) International Normalized Ratio (INR) ≤ 1,5;

               -  Serum potassium, magnesium and calcium within normal range.

          9. Safe contraception in females of childbearing potential during the entire study using
             an established treatment with hormonal contraceptives for at least 2 months prior to
             start of screening.

         10. For females of child bearing potential (without using hormonal contraceptives for at
             least 2 months prior to start of screening) a double contraception method is requested
             during the entire study meeting the criteria for an effective method of birth control.
             That means at least two effective birth control methods such as condoms, diaphragms or
             intra-uterine devices must be used.

         11. Male patients with partners of child bearing potential are requested to use barrier
             contraception in addition to having their partner use another method of contraception
             during the trial and for 3 months after the last dose. Male patients will also be
             advised to abstain from sexual intercourse with pregnant or lactating women, or to use
             condoms.

         12. Able to comply with all the requirements of the protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients who meet any of the following criteria are not eligible for study participation:

          1. Renal failure requiring hemo- or peritoneal dialysis.

          2. Known central nervous system (CNS) tumors including symptomatic brain metastasis.

          3. Patients with no adequate treatment for gastrointestinal bleeding and esophagus
             varices within 14 days prior to study entry.

          4. Child-Pugh index class B in combination with more than slight ascites or hepatic
             encephalopathy &gt; Grade I (see Child-Pugh index, Appendix 4).

          5. History and current cardiovascular complications, including unstable angina pectoris,
             uncontrolled hypertension, congestive heart failure (NYHA Class III or IV) related to
             primary cardiac disease, a condition requiring anti arrhythmic therapy, ischemic or
             severe valvular heart disease, or a myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to the
             trial entry.

          6. Current evidence of any severe internal, psychiatric or neurologic disease.

          7. Altered mental status precluding understanding of the informed consent process and/or
             completion of the necessary studies.

          8. Pregnant or breastfeeding women.

          9. Active alcohol and/or drug abuse.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Bitzer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Clinic, Eberhard Karls University, Tübingen, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tuebingen</city>
        <state>BW</state>
        <zip>D-72076</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://im1-tuebingen.de</url>
    <description>Homepage University Tübingen, Department of Internal Medicine I</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 9, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 26, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital Tuebingen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Michael Bitzer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Deputy Director Department of Gastroenterology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular Diagnostics</keyword>
  <keyword>Sorafenib</keyword>
  <keyword>Therapeutic chemoembolization</keyword>
  <keyword>Next-generation sequencing</keyword>
  <keyword>Sequence analysis, DNA</keyword>
  <keyword>Sequence analysis, RNA</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolomics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

