<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02377167</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SETPOINT2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02377167</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Tracheostomy in Ventilated Stroke Patients 2</brief_title>
  <acronym>SETPOINT2</acronym>
  <official_title>Stroke-Related Early Tracheostomy Versus Prolonged Orotracheal Intubation in Neurocritical Care Trial 2</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Heidelberg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Maine Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Heidelberg</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with severe ischemic and hemorrhagic strokes, who require mechanical ventilation,
      have a particularly bad prognosis. If they require long-term ventilation, their orotracheal
      tube needs to be, like in any other intensive care patient, replaced by a shorter tracheal
      tube below the larynx. This so called tracheostomy might be associated with advantages such
      as less demand of narcotics and pain killers, less lesions in mouth and larynx, better mouth
      hygiene, safer airway, more patient comfort and earlier mobilisation. The best timepoint for
      tracheostomy in stroke, however, is not known. Preliminary data from a pilot study of early
      tracheostomy in patients with hemorrhagic or ischemic stroke suggest that such patients may
      also have improved survival and long-term functional outcomes, but a large, multicenter
      clinical trial is needed to confirm these findings.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: According to United States data from the National Inpatient Sample, about 1.3% of
      1.5 million patients (20,300) hospitalized with ischemic stroke from 2007-2009 underwent
      tracheostomy - while the number of tracheostomies performed for hemorrhagic stroke is
      unknown. Historically, mechanically ventilated patients with ischemic or hemorrhagic strokes
      have had poor functional outcomes, and care of such patients is extremely expensive.
      Effective interventions to improve survival, improve functional recovery, decrease costs, and
      increase cost-effectiveness are urgently needed. Early tracheostomy of selected medical and
      surgical patients allows for dramatically decreased sedation and analgesia, and is associated
      with improved outcomes. Preliminary data from a pilot study of early tracheostomy in patients
      with hemorrhagic or ischemic stroke suggest that such patients may also have improved
      survival and long-term functional outcomes, but a large, multicenter clinical trial is needed
      to confirm these findings.

      Method: SETPOINT 2 is a prospective, randomized, controlled, outcome observer-blinded,
      multicenter, two-armed, comparative trial. Patients are randomized 1:1 to either the
      experimental group - who undergo percutaneous tracheostomy (PDT) as soon as feasible and
      within 5 days after intubation (&quot;early tracheostomy&quot;) or to the control group (&quot;standard of
      care&quot; group), in which PDT is performed after day 10 from intubation if the application of an
      in-house weaning protocol did not lead to successful extubation. Otherwise, no differences in
      intensive care treatment are intended, and each participating institution's standard
      operating procedures will be applied to ensure uniform management decisions in fields such as
      weaning, ventilation, analgesia and sedation, transfusion, and neurological monitoring and
      management. Blinding to the treatment assignment is impossible for treating physicians,
      patients and legal representatives as well as for most of the investigators. However, the
      primary endpoint of long-term outcome and causes of mortality will be assessed by
      trial-independent adjudicators blinded to the timing of tracheostomy.

      The study started as an investigator initiated study which was conducted with limited
      external funding. Some funding (about 50 000 Euros) was provided from third party funds by
      the principal investigator and other foundations to provide for data management by the IMBI
      and other organizational aspects of the study. The principal investigator and the US
      co-principle investigator-David B. Seder, M.D.) together applied for research funding to
      several foundations and medical associations and in December 2016 received confirmation of
      funding from the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute (PCORI). Based on this award,
      some additional endpoints (e.g. neuromonitoring, patient and family experience) were added as
      secondary endpoints in this study. The core version of this study remained unchanged. There
      will be no industry funding of the SETPOINT 2 study. This is not an investigation of any
      specific medical products or medications.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Dichotomized functional outcome (a modified Rankin Scale (mRS) score of 0-4 (favorable outcome) vs 5,6 (poor outcome)) at 6 months after admission to ICU</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This secondary endpoint is assessed as time and type of death during the ICU-stay and 6 months after admission.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This secondary endpoint is assessed as days spent at the recruiting hospital from admission to discharge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 5 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This secondary endpoint is assessed as half-days on the ventilator until the patient is ventilator-independent for 24 h.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration and Quality of Weaning</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of weaning, an expected average of 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This secondary endpoint is assessed as half-days spent under the possible application of a weaning protocol, and spent within specific phases of such a protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of Analgosedation Dependence</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This secondary endpoint is assessed as half-days requiring the application of sedatives and analgesics which are also specified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of ICU dependence</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This secondary endpoint is assessed as days from admission to a pre-defined status that would allow discharge from ICU (absence of active infection, vasopressors, pulmonary and cardial instability etc.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vasopressor Dependence</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This secondary endpoint is assessed as half-days spent under vasopressors during ICU-stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and type of complications</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days post tracheostomy</time_frame>
    <description>This secondary endpoint is assessed as the number and types of complications arelated to tracheostomy (i.e. bleeding, mispositioning, malfunction, replacement demand,etc.).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>admission and discharge</time_frame>
    <description>This secondary endpoint is assessed as the modified Rankin Scale (mRS) at the above named timepoints.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Richmond Agitation Sedation Scale Score</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>evaluation of consciousness and sedation score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Riker Sedation-Agitation-Score</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>evaluation of consciousness and sedation score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Burden scale for Family caregivers BSFC-s</measure>
    <time_frame>at discharge and after 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>assessment of the caregiver burden at the time of discharge from the NCCU and after 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported outcome questions</measure>
    <time_frame>after 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>assessment of the patient and caregiver burden after 6 month</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">380</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemic and Hemorrhagic Stroke, Subarachnoid Hemorrhage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early Tracheostomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to early tracheostomy receive (preferably dilatative) tracheostomy within 5 days from intubation.
Intervention: Procedure: Early Tracheostomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prolonged Intubation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to this arm will be tried to wean off the ventilator and get (an) extubation trial(s) if regarded feasible. In case of failure or non-feasibility, they receive tracheostomy after intubation day 10.
Intervention: Procedure: Late Tracheostomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tracheostomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Tracheostomy is performed as percutaneous dilatative tracheostomy with tracheostomy kit by neurointensivists whenever possible. If anatomically or otherwise indicated, surgical tracheostomy is applied.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early Tracheostomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prolonged Intubation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 years or older

          -  informed consent from legal representative

          -  non-traumatic cerebrovascular disease

          -  Estimated ventilation need for at least 2 weeks

          -  The clinical judgement of the attending neurointensivist

          -  principle indication for tracheostomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Premorbid modified Rankin Score (mRS)&gt;1

          -  Artificial ventilation for more than 4 days

          -  Severe chronic pulmonary disease requiring supplemental oxygen, or evidence of CO2
             retention on admission serum analysis (HCO3≥30)

          -  Severe chronic cardiac disorder

          -  Any emergency situation compromising the patient's well-being or ability to undergo
             tracheostomy in the study time-frame

          -  Intracranial pressure (ICP) persistently &gt; 25cmH2O

          -  Difficult airway management, anticipated problems with extubation / re-intubation,

          -  Need for a permanent surgical tracheostomy

          -  Contraindications for a percutaneous tracheostomy (see below)

          -  High oxygenation requirements: Positive end-expiratory pressure &gt; 12, or fraction of
             inspired oxygen &gt; 0.6)

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Participation in any other interventional trial

          -  Life expectancy &lt; 3 weeks

          -  Patient/family unlikely to opt for at least 3 weeks of aggressive therapy prior to
             consideration of transition to comfort measures/discontinuation of life support
             measures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Silvia Schönenberger, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>0049/62215637549</phone>
    <email>silvia.schoenenberger@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UHHeidelberg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <zip>69120</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Silvia Schönenberger, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>0049/6221/5637549</phone>
      <email>silvia.schoenenberger@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Julian Bösel, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>0049/6221/5639145</phone>
      <email>julian.boesel@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bösel J, Schiller P, Hook Y, Andes M, Neumann JO, Poli S, Amiri H, Schönenberger S, Peng Z, Unterberg A, Hacke W, Steiner T. Stroke-related Early Tracheostomy versus Prolonged Orotracheal Intubation in Neurocritical Care Trial (SETPOINT): a randomized pilot trial. Stroke. 2013 Jan;44(1):21-8. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.112.669895. Epub 2012 Nov 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23204058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 28, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital Heidelberg</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Julian Boesel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. Julian Bösel, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Subarachnoid Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

