<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02374190</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LSEHE40914022015</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02374190</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Examining How Acute Treatment Contributes to Variations in AMI Mortality Across the English NHS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Examining How Acute Treatment Contributes to Variations in Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI) Mortality Across the English National Health Service (NHS): An Observational Study Using the Myocardial Ischaemia National Audit Project</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>London School of Economics and Political Science</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>London School of Economics and Political Science</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Globally, there is increasing focus on optimization of health system quality. International
      austerity, concerns regarding health care safety and effectiveness, and underlying
      aspirations to continually improve patient experience and outcomes are among the factors
      driving interest in measuring, rewarding, and optimizing quality of care. Care for
      cardiovascular diseases is of particular importance as a leading cause of premature death in
      the UK and across the world. With this as a backdrop, recent studies reveal the persistence
      of significant variations in risk‐adjusted health outcomes across English AMI populations,
      suggesting widespread application of ineffective care. In spite of this evidence, little is
      known on the extent to which modifiable, care‐related factors explain observed variations in
      risk‐adjusted AMI mortality rates. Set in this context, a recent conceptual model -
      emphasizing the influence of in‐hospital care on health outcomes - offers a new opportunity
      to 1) re‐examine the quality of acute treatment for AMI, and 2) reveal the extent to which
      care delivery influences and explains variations in mortality following acute admission. This
      study seeks to use data from the Myocardial Ischaemia National Audit Project (MINAP) within a
      retrospective, observational paradigm to examine the relationship between primary care,
      pre‐hospital patient status, acute clinical management and patient outcomes. Findings are
      expected to give a new perspective to quality of integrated AMI care in England.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-Based Measure of Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>In-Hospital (it is expected that this translates to 3 days of inpatient hospital care on average)</time_frame>
    <description>Aggregate mortality rate across hospital admitted patients. Based on in-hospital death from all causes. Cases are defined as cross-sectional episodes, capturing death between point of admission and final discharge or episode completion. Although the denominator is here defined in terms of completed index hospital episodes, it is expected that this translates to 3 days of inpatient hospital care on average.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-Based Measure of Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>30-Days Post-Discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Aggregate mortality rate across hospital admitted patients. Based on derived, patient-level all-cause mortality occurring within 30 days of discharge from acute hospital care for myocardial infarction. Mortality measures are patient-based, to capture death regardless of location.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-Based Measure of Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>1-Year Post-Discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Aggregate mortality rate across hospital admitted patients. Based on derived, patient-level all-cause mortality occurring within 1 year of discharge from acute hospital care for myocardial infarction. Mortality measures are patient-based, to capture death regardless of location.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600000</enrollment>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hospital Admitted AMI Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients admitted to hospital ('trust') for an acute coronary syndrome (ACS) within England and captured within the MINAP dataset. Final discharge diagnosis will be used to limit patient population to that with either a) an ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI), or b) a non-ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (NSTEMI). All patients captured within the MINAP dataset and meeting these inclusion/exclusion criteria will be included within this observational study (expected n = 60,000 / year).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Hospital Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Retrospective, observational analysis will be used to examine the relationship between pre‐admission patient characteristics (as available), acute clinical management and patient outcomes. Standard hospital care is here defined as interventional (e.g., primary angioplasty) and pharmaceutical (e.g., warfarin, beta-blockers) care provided to patients during index hospitalization for MI.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hospital Admitted AMI Patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Population of patients admitted to hospital (acute care trust) for myocardial infarction
        between 2005-2014 (or latest available data).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with discharge diagnosis of either a) an ST-segment elevation myocardial
             infarction (STEMI), or b) a non-ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (NSTEMI). .

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Those diagnosed at discharge as having had a) a threatened myocardial infarction, b)
             acute coronary syndrome (troponin negative), c) chest pain of uncertain cause, d)
             myocardial infarction (unconfirmed), e) other diagnosis, f) takotsubo cardiomyopathy,
             or g) percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) related MI will be excluded.

          -  Patients with a history of MI.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elias Mossialos, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>London School of Economics and Political Science</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Felix Cornehl, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>London School of Economics and Political Science</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 27, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

