<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02378298</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RTX -TAO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02378298</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rituximab (RTX) Therapy in Patients With Active TAO</brief_title>
  <official_title>Rituximab (RTX) Therapy in Steroid Resistant Patients or Patients Relapsing After Intravenous Steroids With Active TAO</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Göteborg University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Göteborg University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Thyroid Associated Ophthalmopathy is condition affecting the eyes of about 10% of patients
      with Graves disease. Its combination of protrusion affecting the looks of the patient and
      pain is often severely affecting the quality of life among these patients.

      The standard treatment for this illness today is intravenous glucocorticoids together with
      methotrexate. The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effect of rituximab on patients
      that do not respond to or relapse after conventional therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Diffuse autoimmune hyperthyroidism or Graves' disease (GD) is a common condition mainly
      affecting women with 2-3% prevalence The increased production of thyroid hormones in GD is
      driven by autoantibodies directed against the thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) receptor
      (TRab). In most cases, this autoimmunity will also affect other tissues, above all the
      orbital tissue by mechanisms not fully understood -Thyroid Associate Ophthalmopathy (TAO).
      Symptoms and signs can be mild (grittiness, dry eyes, periorbital swollen, chemosis,
      redness)-moderate (double eye vision, exophthalmia or severe (optic nerve compression,
      corneal ulcers). Serious-moderate ocular engagement in TAO is seen in approximately 10% of
      patients with GD.

      Not only has the hyperthyroidism a marked impact on mental health, but the presence of TAO
      has an additional negative impact on the well-being of these patients, even many years after
      successful treatment of the hyperthyroidism. It has been suggested that smoking and stress
      are negative prognostic factors for the course of TAO indicating that a vicious circle. MRI
      may detect earlier changes than CT that can be used to predict the course of TAO.

      The aims of treatment are to retain euthyroidism which can be achieved by anti thyrostatic
      drugs (ATD), radioiodine treatment or surgery (where patients are pre-treated with ATD) and
      to avoid TAO as long as possible. If moderate-severe TAO occurs, high dose if intravenous
      glucocorticoids (GC) are the gold standard considering the side effects. However, many
      patients are non-steroid responders and for them no treatment except for acute orbital
      decompression, retro bulbar irradiation and later reconstructive surgery can be offered. When
      patients relapse immediately after steroids often per oral steroids are given although not
      recommended from the literature.

      Rituximab (RTX) is a mouse-human chimeric antibody designed towards pre B and mature B
      lymphocytes and that blocks B-cells activation without affecting the regenerating of B cells
      from stem cells or the plasma cells immunoglobulin production. TAO is a B- lymphocyte
      mediated disease and in two studies RTX inhibits the active phase of TAO. In a study by
      Khanna et al a positive effect from RTX is observed in six steroid resistant patients with
      TAO with a decrease of the inflammation in the orbit, even though no effect on strabismus or
      proptosis was observed. In another study by Salvi et al , RTX treatment is compared with
      steroids as a first line treatment for TAO and after 30 weeks of follow up in an unrandomised
      study design. RTX decreased the activity and severity significantly compared to the steroid
      group. No relapse was observed in the RTX group but in the steroid group (10%). In the RTX
      all patients improved, but in the steroid group only 65%. There were more side-effects in the
      steroid group.

      Selection criteria All patients with indication for i.v GC will be evaluate for the study.
      The patients are recruited consecutively from the region as we are a tertial referral center
      and iv steroids for TAO is not given on local hospitals..

      Patients and study design All patients aged 18-70 years in the western region in Sweden with
      TAO and indication for iv GC (CAS ≥4) will be evaluated for this prospective open study with
      RTX+MTX to GC non-responders. If GC respondent but relapsing after 12 weeks of iv GC
      treatment, patients will be randomized to RTX+MTX or per oral GC+MTX. If non respondent after
      4 weeks of intravenous steroid infusion the patient will be eligible for RTX treatment
      Patients are seen for ophthalmological and endocrine investigations at baseline, 4, 12, 18,
      32, 44, 56 and 68 weeks. At similar occasions anthropometric measurements, immunological
      markers and measures of GC effects (ACTH test, body composition (not all occasions)) will be
      performed. At baseline and after 30 weeks high quality MRI and Gallium (GA)-PET is performed.
      Patients undergoing Ga-PET in another study focusing on pituitary imaging (principle
      investigator HFN) will serve as controls for orbital muscles. The aim of the RTX study is to
      recruit at least 10 patients in the RTX arm and probably 40-50 patients will be included.

      No study with this design has previously been published. The present situation does not offer
      the patients not responding to GC or with relapses after iv GC infusions any effective
      treatment. If the RTX proves safe and effective future non-respondent patients will be able
      to get this treatment. In small studies RTX have had a good effect in TAO, sometimes even
      better than GC and with less side-effects. It will also lay the ground for future studies
      that compare RTX and GC in a randomised study design as first line treatment. If GA-PET shows
      useful in the management of patients with TAO it may become a routine investigation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinical Activity Score (a composite measure of ophthalmological signs and symptoms) between arms</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4, 12, 18, 32 and 46 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measurement is the responder analysis in Clinical activity score (CAS) according to Mouritz et al and the consensus statement from European Group of Graves orbitopathy (EUGOGO) in the responder analysis. A responder is defined as an improvement in CAS ≥2 compared with before treatment. This can be analyzed at four occasions
At 4 weeks iv Steroid treatment compared to baseline
In the responder group 12 weeks compared to baseline
In the non-responder group 18 weeks compared to 4 weeks
In the relapse group at 32 and 46 weeks compared to 18 weeks</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Clinical Activity Score (a composite measure of ophthalmological signs and symptoms) between arms</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4, 12, 18, 32 and 46 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measurement is the responder analysis in Clinical activity score (CAS) according to Mouritz et al and the consensus statement from European Group of Graves orbitopathy (EUGOGO) in the responder analysis. A responder is defined as an improvement in CAS ≥2 compared with before treatment. This can be analyzed at four occasions
At 4 weeks iv Steroid treatment compared to baseline
In the responder group 12 weeks compared to baseline
In the non-responder group 18 weeks compared to 4 weeks
In the relapse group at 32 and 46 weeks compared to 18 weeks</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean/Median change in CAS (a composite measure of of ophthalmological signs and symptoms according to Mouritz et al and the EUGOGO</measure>
    <time_frame>12, 18, 32 and 46 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Mean/Median change in CAS is a secondary measurement outcome and can be evaluated at:
12 weeks in the responder group compared to baseline
18 weeks in the non-responder group compared to 4 weeks
In the relapse group at 32 and 46 weeks compared to 18 weeks in relapse RTX+MTX and po GC+MTX, respectively</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Adverse (a composite measure) events between arms</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4, 12, 18, 32 and 46 and 68 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events are recorded regarding symptoms and effects on glucose metabolism and body composition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of MRI attenuation of inflammation and CAS</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>MRI is performed at baseline and after 30 weeks to detect degree of inflammation. This will be compared to the CAS score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the change in the dynamic measure of standardized uptake values in PET of the orbital muscles to detect inflammation to that on MRI and CAS</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>PET of orbital muscles is performed at baseline and after 30 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Ophthalmopathy, Thyroid-Associated</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-responder RTX+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with moderate-severe TAO with an inflammatory CAS of ≥ 4 that do not respond to iv GC (deltaCAS &lt;2 compared to baseline after 4 weeks of iv GC ) or do relapse (deltaCAS ≥2 and total CAS ≥4) after steroid treatment compared to previous CAS measurement at 12 weeks. Rituximab (1000 mg iv with 2 weeks in between) is combined with methotrexate (15-20 mg once a week) to minimize the risk of antibody developement. MTX is always combined with RTX and is never given as a monotherapy in this study.
rituximab and methotrexate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Relapse RTX+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients that respond to iv GC (Methylprednisolone iv) but relapse after 6 weeks will be randomised to either RTX+MTX or per oral GC (po GC+MTX) rituximab and methotrexate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Relapse po GC+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients that respond to iv GC but relapse after 6 weeks will be randomised to either RTX+MTX or per oral GC (po GC+MTX) This is the conventional therapy arm.
methotrexate and methylprednisolone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Responders without relapse</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients that respond to iv GC and have no relapse at 18 weeks of study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Methylprednisolone iv</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients in the study have a 4 weeks period of 500 mg methylprednisolone iv/week. Depending of the response patiens are classified as non- responders (and are given RTX and MTX) or responders. The responders continue with intravenous infusion of Methylprednisolone 500 mg /week in 2 weeks and thereafter 250 mg iv/week in 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Rituximab (RTX) is a mouse-human chimeric antibody designed towards (CD20) pre B and mature B lymphocytes and that blocks B-cells activation without affecting the regenerating of B cells from stem cells or the plasma cells immunoglobulin production. Rituximab is used in the treatment of hematologic malignancies (B cells lymphoma, chronic lymphatic leukaemia, Waldenströms macroglobulinemia) and autoimmune diseases with B-cell involvement such as rheumatoid arthritis, thrombocytopenic purpura, SLE).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Non-responder RTX+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Relapse RTX+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mabthera</other_name>
    <other_name>Rituxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Zytux</other_name>
    <other_name>L01XC02</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Iv Methylprednisolone</intervention_name>
    <description>Solumedrol is an intravenous glucocorticoid that are the gold standard in TAO. All patients start with 500 mg/weeks for 4 weeks. The response is evaluated and patients are randomised to non-responders or responders. The responders continues with the gold standard treatment that is another 500 mg solumedrol/ week in 2 weeks and then 250 mg/ week in 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Methylprednisolone iv</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Solumedrol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>peroral methylprednisolone and Methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>Peroral GC (starting with 30 mg and tapering down) is combined with 15-20 mg MTX /week to reduce the needed dose of steroids</description>
    <arm_group_label>Relapse po GC+MTX</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Prednisolone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ◦Man or woman between 18-70 years TAO with CAS of ≥ 4 (less than 3 months).

          -  Euthyroid for at least 6 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Dysthyroid optic neuropathy (DON)

          -  Ulcerative Keratitis

          -  Previous treatment with steroids for TAO (do not include prophylaxis for TAO in
             connection with radio iodine treatment)

          -  Previous Treatment with Rituximab (MabThera®)

          -  Positive Hepatitis B or C serology.

          -  Receipt of a live vaccine within 4 weeks prior RTX+MTX to randomization

          -  History of recurrent significant infection or history of recurrent bacterial
             infections

          -  Patient who may not attend to the protocol according to the investigators opinion.

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  Significant cardiac, including significant or uncontrolled arrhythmia, or pulmonary
             disease (including obstructive pulmonary disease).

          -  Any other disease, metabolic dysfunction, physical examination finding, or clinical
             laboratory finding giving reasonable suspicion of a disease or condition that
             contraindicates the use of an investigational drug or that may affect the
             interpretation of the results or render the patient at high risk from treatment
             complications

          -  Concomitant malignancies or previous malignancies.

          -  Previous active tuberculosis

          -  Alcoholism

          -  Alcoholic related liver disease or other chronical liver disease

          -  Bone marrow depression with leukopenia, thrombocytopenia or significant anemia

          -  Rheumatoid or other significant pulmonary disease

          -  Allergy to the active substance or any other substance in the medications or murine
             proteins

          -  Active, severe infections (such as tuberculosis, sepsis or opportunistic infections)

          -  Patients with severe immunosuppression

          -  Severe cardiac failure or severe uncontrolled heart disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helena Filipsson, Ass Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mats O Holmberg, Phd student</last_name>
    <phone>+46705266365</phone>
    <email>mats@xnet.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Endocrinology and Metabolism, Sahlgrenska University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gothenburg</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ann-Charlotte Olofsson, Nurse</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MedTech West, Institute of Neuro Science and Physiology, Department for Clinical Neuro Science and Rehabilitation, Sahlgrenska Academy, University of Gothenburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gothenburg</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Ophthalmology, Sahlgrenska University Hospital/Mölndal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mölndal</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lena Sjödell, Dr</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Rheumatology, Sahlgrenska University Hospital/Mölndal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mölndal</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Radiology, Karolinska University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 20, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Eye Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Graves Ophthalmopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

