<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02374580</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VHT_041406</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02374580</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Partnership and Dignity: a Mixed-methods Survey on Supporting and Retaining Uganda's Village Health Teams</brief_title>
  <official_title>Partnership and Dignity: a Mixed-methods Survey on Supporting and Retaining Uganda's Village Health Teams</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>George Washington University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Makerere University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>George Washington University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For more than a decade, Uganda's Ministry of Health has led a community health worker program
      model in which Village Health Teams (VHTs), cadres of unpaid volunteers, are assigned the
      task of delivering preventative health services and education to their local communities.
      Studies have demonstrated the effectiveness of Uganda's VHTs in improving certain health
      outcomes; however it is known that VHTs are not optimally supported, and there has been VHT
      attrition in recent years. The Ministry of Health has recognized the inadequate support of
      VHTs thus far and is aiming to &quot;expand VHTs to all local governments and explore ways of
      sustaining VHTs.&quot; The objective of this study is to evaluate the extent to which material
      support is a deciding factor in the efficiency and durability of Uganda's VHT initiative.
      Material support may take the form of monetary stipends, regular payment, transportation
      assistance, or nonfinancial materials such as bicycles or mobile phone airtime. This study
      will review existing literature and gather novel data through surveys of VHT members and VHT
      stakeholders. The quantitative and qualitative survey data will be analyzed for trends that
      may point to a conclusion in the context of existing health policy discourse on community
      health worker remuneration. The purpose of this study is to strengthen the knowledge base on
      whether or not the current absence of material support significantly limits the potential for
      Uganda's VHTs to be sustained and expanded. This information can be used by governmental and
      non-governmental organizations in their work to strengthen and sustain VHTs throughout the
      country.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Predicted longevity related to support sufficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by asking VHTs to rate aspects of their current support. We will follow up those questions by asking how long they expect to be able to continue in their position as VHTs. The two results will be evaluated for possible trends connecting sufficiency of existing support with predicted longevity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Predicted longevity of minimum 10 years if current support does not increase</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 months</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by asking the VHTs if they predict being able to continue in their positions for at least 10 more years if their current support does not increase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">143</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <condition>Diarrhea</condition>
  <condition>Pneumonia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population will consist of at least 200 individual working VHT members, and at
        least 10 stakeholders, that is, program managers, administrators, district health officers,
        and policymakers. Almost all study subjects will be of Ugandan nationality. Some
        stakeholders may be expatriates.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        VHT subjects must have been actively working as a VHT member for at least 6 months.
        Stakeholders, that is, program managers, health administrators and policy makers, must be
        involved in managing, administrating, or guiding policy for VHT programs as part of their
        official job description. These persons must also have been acting in those roles for at
        least 6 months. All study subjects will be 18 years of age or older. All study subjects
        will be literate and able to be informed to give or withhold consent of participation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        There will be no exclusion or inclusion based on gender, race, tribal or ethnic
        affiliation, religion, or health status.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William S Schroth, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>George Washington University School of Medicine and Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The George Washington University School of Medicine and Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ministry of Health, Uganda, Education and Promotion Division. Village health team strategy and operational guidelines. 2010.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenner JL, Kabakyenga J, Kyomuhangi T, Wotton KA, Pim C, Ntaro M, Bagenda FN, Gad NR, Godel J, Kayizzi J, McMillan D, Mulogo E, Nettel-Aguirre A, Singhal N. Can volunteer community health workers decrease child morbidity and mortality in southwestern Uganda? An impact evaluation. PLoS One. 2011;6(12):e27997. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0027997. Epub 2011 Dec 14.</citation>
    <PMID>22194801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Okello D, Floyd K, Adatu F, Odeke R, Gargioni G. Cost and cost-effectiveness of community-based care for tuberculosis patients in rural Uganda. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2003 Sep;7(9 Suppl 1):S72-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12971657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalyango JN, Rutebemberwa E, Alfven T, Ssali S, Peterson S, Karamagi C. Performance of community health workers under integrated community case management of childhood illnesses in eastern Uganda. Malar J. 2012 Aug 20;11:282. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-11-282.</citation>
    <PMID>22905758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kayemba Nalwadda C, Guwatudde D, Waiswa P, Kiguli J, Namazzi G, Namutumba S, Tomson G, Peterson S. Community health workers - a resource for identification and referral of sick newborns in rural Uganda. Trop Med Int Health. 2013 Jul;18(7):898-906. doi: 10.1111/tmi.12106. Epub 2013 Apr 2.</citation>
    <PMID>23551394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ministry of Health Uganda. Annual Health Sector Performance Report: Financial Year 2012/2013. 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ministry of Health Uganda. The second national health policy. 2010.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perry, H, et al. How effective are community health workers? an overview of current evidence with recommendations for strengthening community health worker programs to accelerate progress in achieving the health-related millennium development goals. Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health. 2012.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lehmann U., Sanders D. Community health workers: what do we know about them? The state of the evidence on programmes, activities, costs and impact on health outcomes of using community health workers. (2007) Geneva: World Health Organization. Available at: &lt;http://www.who.int/hrh/documents/community_health_ workers.pdf&gt;</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 4, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 2, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 15, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 15, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 16, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

