<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02375932</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CN-13-1579</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DK099108</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02375932</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pre-Visit Prioritization for Complex Patients With Diabetes</brief_title>
  <acronym>PVP</acronym>
  <official_title>Pre-Visit Prioritization for Complex Primary Care Patients With Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaiser Permanente</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with type 2 diabetes are increasingly complex. Lack of time to address all patient
      and provider priorities during primary care visits represents a barrier to effective primary
      care. The investigators propose to design, implement, and evaluate in a randomized clinical
      trial a web-based tool linked to the electronic health record (EHR) that will enable complex
      patients to easily define care priorities for their upcoming visit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with type 2 diabetes are increasingly living with multiple concurrent conditions and
      complicated medical regimens. For these patients, diabetes management decisions and treatment
      goals must be addressed within the larger context of other competing health concerns. In
      parallel, clinical advances have led to a substantial increase in the number of tasks that
      primary care providers must perform during each visit. These twin trends present a formidable
      challenge to effective diabetes primary care. We hypothesize that among complex patients not
      meeting diabetes management goals, a web-based health IT tool to help patients explicitly
      prioritize all health issues (both related and unrelated to diabetes) and then submit these
      priorities directly into the electronic health record (EHR) for a scheduled visit with their
      primary care provider will result in more effective diabetes management over time. To test
      this hypothesis, we propose to design, implement, and evaluate in a randomized clinical trial
      a web-based tool linked to the EHR that will enable complex patients to easily define care
      priorities for their upcoming visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycemic Control (HbA1c control (% patients &lt; 7.0% and mean HbA1c levels)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>We will compare HbA1c control (% patients &lt; 7.0% and mean HbA1c levels) between intervention and control arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient assessment of visit communication (measures of communication quality using validated instruments)</measure>
    <time_frame>Shortly after visit with PCP</time_frame>
    <description>We will call a subset of patients in the intervention and control arms after attending a visit with their PCP to assess measures of communication quality using validated instruments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-Visit Tool</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients whose primary care physicians are allocated to the intervention arm will receive a secure electronic message shortly after scheduling an appointment with their provider asking them to complete a pre-visit prioritization survey using the kp.org patient portal</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients whose primary care physicians are allocated to the control arm will continue with usual care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pre-Visit Tool</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients receive a secure electronic message from their primary providers asking them to prepare for their visit by reviewing important areas of care and identifying their top priorities for discussion at a scheduled visit</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-Visit Tool</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients continue to receive usual care from their primary care provider</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Primary care physicians (PCPs) at Kaiser Permanente Northern California with potentially
        eligible patients (type 2 diabetes and HbA1c &gt; 8.0%) wil be recruited and consented to
        participate in this study. PCPs will review lists of potentially eligible patients of
        theirs (defined below). Patients approved by PCP's allocated to the intervention arm will
        be sent a secure message on the PCPs behalf asking them to review the Pre-Visit
        Prioritization Questionnaire to identify top priorities for discussion at the next
        scheduled visit.

        Patient Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Current adult member (&gt; 21 years old)

          -  Diagnosis of type 2 diabetes with most recent HbA1c &gt; 8.0%

          -  English as primary language

          -  Registered on kp.org.

        Patient Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Excluded by PCP, and/or: terminal illness, in hospice care or reside in a long-term
             care facility, severe mental illness (e.g. schizophrenia or personality disorder),
             currently or recently pregnant, and/or significant dementia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard W Grant, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Division of Research, Kaiser Permanente Northern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grant RW, Adams AS, Bayliss EA, Heisler M. Establishing visit priorities for complex patients: A summary of the literature and conceptual model to guide innovative interventions. Healthc (Amst). 2013 Dec;1(3-4):117-122.</citation>
    <PMID>24944911</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 24, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Electronic Medical Records</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Health Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

