<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00262496</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3216-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00262496</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Botulinum-A Toxin Injection for Detrusor Hyperreflexia in Spinal Cord Injury: A Non-Surgical Approach.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Botulinum-A Toxin Injection for Detrusor Hyperreflexia in Spinal Cord Injury: A Non-Surgical Approach.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determine whether Botulinum-A toxin injected in the bladder
      muscle will help prevent the frequency and degree of urinary incontinence in Spinal Cord
      Injured and Multiple Sclerosis patients. The proposed mechanism would be that the Toxin would
      allow the bladder to hold more urine at a lower pressure as determined by Urodynamics. The
      research will answer the question whether the dosages 300 units vs 400 units are either
      equally vs not equally effective in helping urinary incontinece and bladder storage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVE OF THE PROJECT The major aim of the present study is to use a double blind
      randomized clinical trial design to evaluate the long-term efficacy and safety of two
      different doses, 300 and 400 Units of Botulinum Toxin Type-A for the treatment of detrusor
      hyperreflexia (Neurogenic Bladder Overactivity). While also improving bladder capacity in
      spinal cord injured patients with refractory symptoms who have failed anticholinergic agents.

      RESEARCH PLAN Inclusion Criteria: Male and female subjects 18-80 years of age with
      suprasacral SCI refractory NBOA incontinence, and/or impaired detrusor compliance associated
      with a small bladder capacity will be eligible. Subjects will be recruited on the basis of
      incontinence symptoms and adverse urodynamic parameters including impaired bladder compliance
      less than 50ml/cm, H20 and bladder (cystometric) capacity less than 300 ml.

      Exclusion criteria: Allergy to Botulinum Toxin Type-A, pregnancy, breast-feeding women,
      active medical or psychiatric disorders, active urinary tract infection, coagulopathy,
      myasthenia gravis, upper urinary tract changes unrelated to lower tract dysfunction, and
      aminoglycoside use during the last three months. Furthermore, subjects with radiation
      cystitis (by history), vesico-ureteral reflux (by videofluoroscopy), bladder calculi (by
      cystoscopy) will be excluded.

      Evaluation will include history and physical examination, urine analysis, urine culture and
      sensitivity, 24-hour voiding diary for 3 consecutive days, urine pregnancy test in female
      subjects of reproductive age, validated questionnaires, multichannel videourodynamics (UDS),
      post-void residual volume at the time of UDS, and renal ultrasound.

      METHODOLOGY One week after the pre-intervention evaluation, endoscopic injection of Botulinum
      Toxin Type-A (300 Units or 400 Units) into the detrusor muscle will be performed. During the
      24 month duration of the study, participants will take and record their regular bladder
      medications as Dr. Gousse (or one of his assistants) decide necessary to control their
      urinary symptoms. Subjects will be scheduled to return at 2, 6, and 12 weeks after the first
      injection session, and every 3 months thereafter. At the 2-week visit we will assess untoward
      effects. At the 6-week visit and every subsequent visit a focused physical examination will
      be carried out, along with validated questionnaires.

      Participants with initial success, as defined by 50% improvement (voiding diary) in
      diminished leakage, improved cystometric capacity by greater than 100 ml, improved compliance
      by 15 ml/cm H20, 50% improvement in questionnaire scores, but who lose the initial
      therapeutic benefit will be considered candidates for re-injection every 6 months. Patients
      who continue to maintain therapeutic benefit pass 6 months after initial injection will not
      be re-injected and will be re-evaluated at every 3 months thereafter prior to possible
      re-injection. Pregnancy testing will be obtained prior to each injection session in
      appropriate female subjects in their reproductive years.

      Depending on the type of variable being analyzed different statistical techniques will be
      used for these comparisons including paired sample t-tests, Wilcoxon's signed rank tests,
      McNemar's tests, and Cochran's Q tests. Cross-sectional as well as longitudinal analyses will
      be performed to compare 300 vs. 400 Unit groups with respect to each of the variables
      ascertained at each time point, and also with respect to changes over time for the major
      study end points.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Overactive Bladder</condition>
  <condition>Urinary Incontinence</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Botox</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must be 18-80 years old with suprasacral spinal cord injury (SCI) or multiple
             sclerosis (MS) refractory Neurogenic bladder overactivity and/or detrusor compliance
             associated with small bladder capacity.· Impaired bladder compliance less than 50
             ml/cm, H2O and bladder (cystometric) capacity less than 300ml.-

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergy to Botulinum Toxin Type-A· Pregnancy· Breast-feeding women· Active medical or
             psychiatric disorders· Upper urinary tract changes unrelated to lower tract
             dysfunction· Aminoglycoside use during the last 3 months-
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angelo E Gousse, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Miami VA Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33125</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://sfvafre.org</url>
    <description>South Florida VA Foundation for Research</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.asia-spinalinjury.org</url>
    <description>American Spinal Injury Association</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schulte-Baukloh H, Weiss C, Schobert J, Stolze T, Stürzebecher B, Knispel HH. [Subjective patient satisfaction after injection of botulinum-a toxin in detrusor overactivity]. Aktuelle Urol. 2005 Jun;36(3):230-3. German.</citation>
    <PMID>16001338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schurch B, de Sèze M, Denys P, Chartier-Kastler E, Haab F, Everaert K, Plante P, Perrouin-Verbe B, Kumar C, Fraczek S, Brin MF; Botox Detrusor Hyperreflexia Study Team. Botulinum toxin type a is a safe and effective treatment for neurogenic urinary incontinence: results of a single treatment, randomized, placebo controlled 6-month study. J Urol. 2005 Jul;174(1):196-200.</citation>
    <PMID>15947626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Werner M, Schmid DM, Schüssler B. Efficacy of botulinum-A toxin in the treatment of detrusor overactivity incontinence: a prospective nonrandomized study. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2005 May;192(5):1735-40.</citation>
    <PMID>15902187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bagi P, Biering-Sørensen F. Botulinum toxin A for treatment of neurogenic detrusor overactivity and incontinence in patients with spinal cord lesions. Scand J Urol Nephrol. 2004;38(6):495-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15841785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grosse J, Kramer G, Stöhrer M. Success of repeat detrusor injections of botulinum a toxin in patients with severe neurogenic detrusor overactivity and incontinence. Eur Urol. 2005 May;47(5):653-9. Epub 2005 Jan 15.</citation>
    <PMID>15826758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 2, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 2, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 6, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 26, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Botox</keyword>
  <keyword>Overactive bladder</keyword>
  <keyword>Incontinence</keyword>
  <keyword>Spinal Cord Injury</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Incontinence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enuresis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder, Overactive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Reflex, Abnormal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins, Type A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>onabotulinumtoxinA</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>abobotulinumtoxinA</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

