<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00269997</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR005839</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00269997</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Safety and Effectiveness of Epoetin Alfa Versus Placebo in Patients With Persistent Anemia as a Result of Cancer Treatment With Cisplatin, a Platinum-containing Chemotherapy Drug</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Subcutaneous r-HuEPO in Patients With Chronic Anemia Secondary to Cisplatin Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of epoetin alfa versus
      placebo in the treatment of persistent anemia caused by advanced cancer and aggressive
      cisplatin chemotherapy. Epoetin alfa is a genetically engineered protein that stimulates red
      blood cell production.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients undergoing treatment with cisplatin-containing chemotherapy frequently develop
      significant anemia (hemoglobin &lt;= 10.5 grams/deciliter). Agents that can increase the amount
      of hemoglobin in cancer patients undergoing treatment with cisplatin-containing cyclic
      chemotherapy may improve the patients' reduced physical strength and reduced stamina
      resulting from anemia, increase the patients' ability to continue chemotherapy, and improve
      the patients' overall qualify of life. Epoetin alfa is a genetically engineered form of a
      natural hormone (erythropoietin) that is used to treat anemia by stimulating red blood cell
      production. This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel group,
      multicenter study. This study evaluates the safety and effectiveness of epoetin alfa in
      treating patients who develop persistent anemia as a result of treatment with aggressive
      cisplatin-containing cyclic chemotherapy (every 3 to 4 weeks) for any cancer type (except
      rapid and severe onset of leukemias and malignancies of the bone marrow and spleen). The
      study consists of a &lt;= 7 day screening period when patients' eligibility is determined, a
      12-week double-blind treatment period, and an optional open-label treatment period. Eligible
      patients will be randomly assigned to one of two treatment groups: epoetin alfa 150
      units/kilogram or a comparable volume of placebo, given by injection beneath the skin.
      Patients will be treated with study medication 3 times weekly for 12 weeks. Two of the 3
      weekly doses of study medication may be self-administered by the patient at home; the patient
      is visited by a health professional at least once weekly to administer the other dose(s). The
      dose of study medication may be increased or decreased at the discretion of the physician,
      based on the results of blood tests. Depending on the patient's chemotherapy cycle, he or she
      will return to the study site every 3 or 4 weeks for administration of study medication.
      During the open-label treatment period, patients who choose to continue will receive 3
      injections per week of epoetin alfa under the skin, until the completion of his or her
      chemotherapy treatments. Safety evaluations, including laboratory tests, vital signs,
      reporting of adverse events, physical examination, and electrocardiograms, are performed
      throughout the study. Effectiveness of the study drug will be determined by the number of
      transfusions patients require and by changes in blood test results (hemoglobin, hematocrit,
      and immature red blood cells) from before the start of the study to the end of the study. The
      study hypothesis is that epoetin alfa will, more effectively than placebo, stimulate adequate
      production of red blood cells to elevate the hemoglobin level in cancer patients who are
      anemic as a result of undergoing treatment with aggressive cisplatin-containing cyclic
      chemotherapy. Double-blind: Epoetin alfa 150 units/kilogram, or matching volume of placebo,
      injected beneath the skin 3 times weekly for 12 weeks. Open-label: Epoetin alfa at the dose
      received at the end of the double-blind study injected beneath the skin 3 times weekly for
      any remaining cycles of chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 1990</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of transfusions required; Changes in hemoglobin, hematocrit, and reticulocyte (immature red blood cells) levels from before the study to the end of the study</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life assessment; Physician's global evaluation; Performance score (ability to perform daily activities); Assessment of safety (laboratory tests, vital signs, and adverse events) from before the study to the end of the study</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>epoetin alfa</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with cancer (except for rapid onset of severe leukemia and malignancies of
             the bone marrow and spleen) and having anemia resulting from cisplatin-containing
             chemotherapy

          -  receiving cyclic chemotherapy for &lt;=5 consecutive days every 3 or 4 weeks (for 3
             cycles of chemotherapy)

          -  Performance score of 0, 1, 2, or 3 (grades assessing patients' ability to perform
             daily activities)

          -  having a life expectancy of at least 3 months

          -  having a hemoglobin level &lt;= 10.5 grams/deciliter, and signs and symptoms of physical
             stability for 1 month before the study (based on physical examination including vital
             signs, weight, and electrocardiogram)

          -  with an ability to administer self-injections

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a history of any blood disease

          -  having signs and symptoms of significant disease/dysfunction not caused by the
             underlying cancer

          -  receiving radiation therapy or surgery to decrease the number of cancer cells within
             30 days before the start of the study

          -  having a sudden and severe onset of illness within 7 days before the start of the
             study

          -  having cancer that has spread to the brain, a history of seizures, uncontrolled high
             blood pressure, or an iron, folate, or vitamin B12 deficiency
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L. C. Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_JNJ_6051&amp;studyid=672&amp;filename=CR005839_CSR.pdf</url>
    <description>A study to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of epoetin alfa given by injection beneath the skin to patients with persistent anemia as a result of cancer treatment with cisplatin, a platinum-containing anti-cancer drug</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 22, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 22, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 26, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 18, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>epoetin alfa</keyword>
  <keyword>epogen</keyword>
  <keyword>erythropoietin</keyword>
  <keyword>neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epoetin Alfa</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

