<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00268697</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TAK-475/EC303</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2005-002315-25</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1122-8322</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00268697</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Lapaquistat Acetate Alone and With Ezetimibe in Subjects With Primary Dyslipidemia.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-Blind, Double-Dummy, Randomized, Parallel Group, Multicenter, Phase 3 Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Lapaquistat Acetate 100 mg and Lapaquistat Acetate 100 mg Administered in Combination With Ezetimibe 10 mg vs Ezetimibe 10 mg in Subjects With Primary Dyslipidemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determine the efficacy of lapaquistat acetate, once daily
      (QD), taken with ezetimibe on cholesterol levels in subjects with primary dyslipidemia
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In humans, cholesterol is acquired from dietary sources and is produced de novo in the liver,
      intestine, and various other tissues. Normally, the balance among cholesterol synthesis,
      dietary intake, and degradation is adequate to maintain healthy cholesterol plasma levels;
      however, in subjects with hypercholesterolemia, elevation in low-density lipoprotein
      cholesterol leads to atherosclerotic deposition of cholesterol in the arterial walls
      (atherosclerosis) and subsequent coronary heart disease. Thus, it has been established that
      lowering the low-density lipoprotein cholesterol plasma concentrations effectively reduces
      cardiovascular morbidity and mortality. Additional lipid risk factors for coronary heart
      disease include elevated triglyceride, very low-density lipoprotein cholesterol and
      low-density lipoprotein cholesterol levels, and low levels of high-density lipoprotein
      cholesterol.

      Despite changes in lifestyle and the availability of potent lipid-lowering agents,
      cardiovascular disease continues to be the major cause of death in Western Europe and North
      America. Serum cholesterol levels exceeding 5 mmol/L (193 mg/dL) are common in adults in
      Britain and much of Europe, the United States, Australia, and New Zealand, representing a
      serious public health concern.

      Currently, 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl coenzyme A reductase inhibitors (ie, statins) are the
      first-line monotherapies prescribed for the treatment of dyslipidemia, after diet and
      therapeutic lifestyle changes alone fail to reduce low-density lipoprotein cholesterol to
      desired levels. Statins reduce low-density lipoprotein cholesterol and triglycerides,
      increase high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, and improve endothelial function. Treatment
      with statins reduces the risk of a vascular event by about 30% in subjects with and without
      symptoms of arteriosclerosis; however, many subjects fail to reach recommended levels of
      low-density lipoprotein cholesterol reduction after receiving low-dose statins as a
      monotherapy. Consequently, the dosage of statins is often increased or an additional
      treatment is added; the latter has become an important therapeutic option for achieving
      increasingly stringent lipid targets set forth by international therapeutic guidelines.

      Ezetimibe is a lipid-lowering compound that selectively inhibits intestinal absorption of
      cholesterol at the brush border of the small intestine, leading to a decrease in the delivery
      of intestinal cholesterol to the liver. Ezetimibe does not affect the absorption of
      triglycerides, fatty acids, bile acids, progesterone, ethinylestradiol, or fat-soluble
      vitamins A and D.

      TAK-475 (lapaquistat acetate) is a squalene synthase inhibitor currently under development at
      Takeda for the treatment of dyslipidemia. This study will evaluate the efficacy and safety of
      lapaquistat acetate taken with ezetimibe in subjects with hypercholesterolemia. Total
      participation time in this study is expected to be up to 24 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in fasting plasma Low Density Lipoprotein cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Triglycerides</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Total Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in High Density Lipoprotein cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Very Low Density Lipoprotein cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in apolipoprotein A1</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in apolipoprotein B</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in non- High Density Lipoprotein cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the ratio of Low Density Lipoprotein cholesterol/High Density Lipoprotein cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the ratio of Total Cholesterol/High Density Lipoprotein cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the ratio of apolipoprotein A1/apolipoprotein B</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in high-sensitivity C-reactive protein</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects who achieve Low Density Lipoprotein cholesterol concentrations less than 2.59 mmol/L (100 mg/dL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects who achieve Low Density Lipoprotein cholesterol concentrations less than 3.37 mmol/L (130 mg/dL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best corrected visual acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, and 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Laboratory Tests</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, and 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital Signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, and 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>12-lead Electrocardiogram</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 12 and 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Examination</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24 or Final Visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1267</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypercholesterolemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lapaquistat Acetate 100 mg QD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lapaquistat Acetate 100 mg QD + Ezetimibe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ezetimibe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lapaquistat acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>Lapaquistat acetate 100 mg, tablets, orally, once daily for up to 24 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lapaquistat Acetate 100 mg QD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TAK-475</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lapaquistat acetate and ezetimibe</intervention_name>
    <description>Lapaquistat acetate 100 mg, tablets, orally, once daily and stable ezetimibe therapy for up to 24 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lapaquistat Acetate 100 mg QD + Ezetimibe</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TAK-475</other_name>
    <other_name>Zetia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ezetimibe</intervention_name>
    <description>Lapaquistat acetate placebo-matching tablets, orally, once daily and stable ezetimibe therapy for up to 24 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ezetimibe</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zetia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Females of childbearing potential who are sexually active must agree to use adequate
             contraception from screening throughout the duration of the study and for 30 days
             following the last dose.

          -  Has a documented history of dyslipidemia with or without cardiovascular risk factors
             but without type 1 or 2 diabetes.

          -  At Randomization, participants must fulfill the above criteria and also have a mean
             fasting low density lipoprotein cholesterol levels greater than or equal to 3.36
             mmol/L and less than or equal to 5.6 mmol/L and mean triglyceride levels less than or
             equal to 4.52 mmol/L.

          -  Is willing and able to comply with the recommended, standardized diet.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has active liver disease or jaundice.

          -  Has a history of cancer, other than basal cell carcinoma, that had been in remission
             for less than 5 years prior to the first dose of study drug.

          -  Has an endocrine disorder, such as Cushing Syndrome, hyperthyroidism, or
             inappropriately treated hypothyroidism affecting lipid metabolism.

          -  Has a positive hepatitis B surface antigen or hepatitis C virus antibody, as
             determined by medical history and/or the subject's verbal report.

          -  Has a positive human immunodeficiency virus status or was taking antiretroviral
             medications, as determined by medical history and/or the subject's verbal report. .

          -  Has participated in any other clinical studies with lapaquistat acetate, was
             concurrently participating in another investigational study, had participated in an
             investigational study within the past 30 days or, for drugs with a long half-life,
             within a period of less than 5 times the drug's half-life.

          -  Has a known hypersensitivity or history of intolerance to lapaquistat acetate or
             ezetimibe.

          -  Has a history or presence of clinically significant food allergy that would prevent
             adherence to the specialized diet.

          -  Has a known heterozygous or homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia or known Type III
             hyperlipoproteinemia (familial dysbetalipoproteinemia).

          -  Has fibromyalgia, myopathy, rhabdomyolysis, or unexplained muscle pain and/or
             discontinuation of HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors due to myalgia at any time.

          -  Has uncontrolled hypertension despite medical treatment.

          -  Has inflammatory bowel or any other malabsorption syndrome or had had gastric bypass
             surgery or any other surgical procedure for weight loss.

          -  Has a history of drug abuse or a history of high alcohol intake within the previous 2
             years.

          -  Has any other serious disease or condition at Visit 1 or Randomization that might
             reduce life expectancy, impaired successful management according to the protocol, or
             make the participant unsuitable to receive study drug.

          -  Has a history of coronary heart disease or coronary heart disease-risk factors
             comprised of:

               -  Diabetes mellitus type 1 or 2

               -  History or presence of myocardial infarction, angina pectoris, unstable angina,
                  coronary angioplasty, coronary or peripheral arterial surgery (bypass graft),
                  aortic aneurysm, transient ischemic attacks, or cerebrovascular accident;

               -  Multiple risk factors that confer a 10-year risk of coronary heart disease
                  greater than 20% based on the Framingham risk score.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Tallinn</city>
        <country>Estonia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Tartu</city>
        <country>Estonia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Riga</city>
        <country>Latvia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Saratov</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Smolensk</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>St. Petersburg</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Tyumen</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kragujevac</city>
        <country>Serbia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Estonia</country>
    <country>Latvia</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Serbia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Former Serbia and Montenegro</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stein EA, Bays H, O'Brien D, Pedicano J, Piper E, Spezzi A. Lapaquistat acetate: development of a squalene synthase inhibitor for the treatment of hypercholesterolemia. Circulation. 2011 May 10;123(18):1974-85. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.975284. Epub 2011 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>21518985</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 22, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 24, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hyperlipidemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypercholesterolemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dyslipidemias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ezetimibe</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

