<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00267436</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDC-NCHSTP-U65/CCU523908</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U65/CCU523908-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00267436</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adopting and Demonstrating the Adaptation of Prevention Techniques: Community PROMISE PLUS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Adopting and Demonstrating the Adaptation of Prevention Techniques: Community PROMISE Positives Leading and Utilizing Strategies (ADAPT CP PLUS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Minneapolis Urban League;</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AIDS Action Committee of Massachusetts</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Fenway Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project will pilot test a step-by-step guide developed by CDC for organizations to
      engage in evidence-based adaptation of interventions previously shown to be effective in
      research settings for use in real world applications. The second purpose of the program is to
      evaluate the adapted intervention to determine if it is effective in changing behavior of
      HIV+ African American men who have sex with other men.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During the ADAPT project both sites will adapt the original Community Promise intervention to
      specifically address the HIV prevention needs of sero-positive, African American men who have
      sex with men (HIV+ AAMSM) in either Boston, MA or Minneapolis/St. Paul (MSP), MN. The adapted
      intervention will be referred to as Community PROMISE, Positives Leading and Utilizing
      Strategies (CP PLUS).

      In the first two months of the ADAPT project, the Boston and MSP sites will conduct formative
      evaluation activities (i.e., a comprehensive literature review, focus groups, and individual
      interviews) to assess the needs of the target population and organizational capacities to
      serve them. Results will be used to inform the adaptation of the original intervention to
      ensure that CP PLUS meet the expressed needs of the target population.

      Process data will also be collected from various sources throughout the life of the project.
      Process data will be collected through staff meetings, interviews with staff, focus groups
      with peer advocates, and an expert panel consultation. Process data will be extremely useful
      for ensuring program objectives are met, improving CP PLUS, and providing information for
      providers in other locales who may be interested in adapting this intervention to serve this
      target population.

      The Boston and MSP sites will also conduct outcome monitoring through collection of data
      concerning risk behaviors pre- and post-intervention implementation (follow-up at 6-8 months
      post and 11-13 months post [Boston only]) to determine if the adapted intervention has met
      its outcome objectives. Outcome monitoring will also be conducted for the &quot;parent&quot;
      intervention at both sites for HIV- or unknown status men who have sex with men.

      In addition to the project activities, the organization will be examining the utility of the
      CDC draft guidance. The Boston and MSP sites are two of five case studies throughout the
      United States that will detail the challenges, successes and lessons learned from adapting an
      intervention packaged by CDC's Replicating Effective Programs (REP) and disseminated by
      Diffusing Effective Behavioral Interventions (DEBI) to a specific population. These findings
      will help other community-based organizations and Health Departments effectively adapt and
      tailor group, individual and community-level interventions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sexual activities with main and casual partners in past 30 days to 6 months (i.e., unprotected insertive and receptive anal/vaginal sex and protected insertive and receptive anal/vaginal sex)</measure>
    <time_frame>7/2006-2/2007</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral intentions and attitudes for condom use; disclosure of HIV status; self reported STD diagnosis; medication adherence; links to care.</measure>
    <time_frame>7/2006-2/2007</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">574</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Prevention</condition>
  <condition>STD Prevention</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community PROMISE</intervention_name>
    <description>The Community PROMISE begins with a community assessment to identify HIV risk factors. Once risk factors have been identified, individuals from the targeted at-risk community are recruited and trained to be peer advocates. Trained peer advocates interview members of the community about their behavior. Role model stories are written based on the interviews. Role model stories are personal accounts from individuals in the target population which explain how and why they took steps to practice HIV risk-reduction behaviors and the positive effects the choice has had on their lives. Each week, peer advocates distribute role model stories and supplies, such as condoms, to 10 to 20 members of their social networks.</description>
    <other_name>AIDS Community Demonstration Project</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        HIV+ cohort

          -  Self-reports as HIV+ (for CP PLUS cohort)

          -  Self-report that they had sex with men in the past 3 years (MSP) or 1 year (Boston)

          -  Self-reports as a resident of the identified geographic areas.

          -  Identifies as African American

          -  18 years of age, or older.

        HIV- cohort

          -  HIV- or unknown status only, has engaged in risky sexual contact (defined as those who
             self-report engaging in unprotected anal or vaginal intercourse within the past year)

          -  Self-report that they had sex with men in the past 3 years (MSP) or 1 year (Boston)

          -  Identifies as African American (MSP); No racial/ethnic criteria however AA will be
             over-sampled and will be at least 20% of sample

          -  18 years of age, or older.

          -  Self-reports as a resident of the identified geographic areas.

          -  Engage in risky sex (defined as individuals who self-report engaging in unprotected
             anal or vaginal intercourse within the past year.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to complete informed consent process due to (a) substantial cognitive
             impairment. (b) non-English speaking; (c) under the influence of drugs or alcohol

          -  Under 18 years of age

          -  Plans to relocate within 12 months after baseline interview

          -  Anyone who does not meet inclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer S Galbraith</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AIDS Action Committee</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02118</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis Urban League</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 21, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 12, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 12, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 13, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Jennifer Galbraith/ Behavioral Scientist</name_title>
    <organization>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adaptation</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV positive</keyword>
  <keyword>evidence based interventions</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Seronegativity</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

