<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00802152</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1095618</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00802152</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Health Information Technology (HIT) to Improve Ambulatory Chronic Disease Care: Smart Device Substudy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Using Health Information Technology (HIT) to Improve Ambulatory Chronic Disease Care: Smart Device Substudy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Missouri-Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Missouri-Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In-home health monitoring devices have the potential to increase the speed and ease of
      modifying treatment for ambulatory patients living with chronic conditions. This study
      examines the implementation and effectiveness of remote data transmission from in-home
      devices (blood glucose meter/blood pressure machine) to the clinic on treatment outcomes in
      patients with diabetes who have out of range blood glucose (BG) or systolic blood pressure
      (BP) measurements. We test whether the short-term targeted use of in-home monitoring devices
      facilitates management for providers and improves outcome measures for patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the effectiveness of short-term targeted use of remote data transmission from
      in-home devices (blood glucose meter/blood pressure machine) to the clinic on treatment
      outcomes in patients with diabetes who have out of range blood glucose (BG) or systolic blood
      pressure (BP) measurements. Increased frequency of data transmission will provide the
      provider with &quot;real time&quot; data in order to make more timely adjustments in the treatment
      plan, resulting in improved glycemic control as measured by A1c values and hypertension as
      measured by systolic blood pressure (SBP).

      Subjects will be recruited from Family &amp; Community Medicine (FCM) and General Internal
      Medicine (GIM) clinics. We will randomly select patients from physicians with a minimum
      number of 5 eligible patients from the performance measurement list (A1c&gt;=8% or SBP&gt;130) to
      approach for the study. Patients who agree to enroll will be randomized to experimental and
      control using a block randomization approach stratified by age increments (18-40; 41-55;
      56-70; 71+). Subjects will be randomized using prepared sealed envelopes. A total of 200
      subjects (100 intervention subjects and 100 control subjects) will be enrolled over a period
      of one year. We will attempt to enroll equal numbers of FCM and GIM subjects.

      For all subjects, baseline data will be collected from the patient, including demographic
      data (age, gender, race, and years of formal education), payor status (private pay,
      insurance, Medicaid), number of co-morbid conditions, baseline blood pressure, and length of
      time diagnosed with diabetes (DM) and hypertension.

      Intervention patients will be instructed to test their BP and BG according to a minimum
      protocol of at least once daily and upload this clinical data at least every other day for
      the 3-month study duration, but this frequency could be further tailored by their provider,
      i.e., more than once daily. At least 2 of these BG readings each week should be fasting
      levels. Patient training will emphasize that this system is not an emergency response system,
      i.e., critical values should be treated in the usual manner.

      Control group patients (those who do not receive the device) will be asked to test their BP
      and BG at least once daily (in the same fashion as the intervention group). They will be
      instructed to bring these readings to their clinic visits, and again at the end of the study.
      We will collect these readings.

      Data from patients are downloaded to the website as they enter data. These data may be
      printed out for MD review or verbally communicated. APNs in FCM will make changes in patient
      treatment based on their currently established privileges, e.g., medication adjustments; RNs
      in GIM or FCM will review data with MDs for changes in treatment plans. All treatment changes
      will be individualized according to patient need, i.e., no standardized blood glucose
      management protocol will be employed. Communication of changes in therapy to the patient will
      be accomplished per usual clinic protocol, e.g., usually by a telephone call to the patient,
      with documentation of a telephone note in the medical record.

      After three months, all subjects will return to the clinic for an A1c and BP measure, and for
      post study surveys. Data collection will include achievement of clinical goals in blood
      glucose (A1c measure at end of 3 month intervention [+/- 2 weeks] and BP). If enrolled
      subjects have an available A1c and BP measure recorded in the record at the end of 6 months,
      we will collect these data to assess longer term effects of the intervention. Patient records
      will be reviewed for interventions provided to patient (i.e., documenting the process of
      medication changes, advice provided).

      Interview data will be collected from physicians and nurses re: perceptions of use of the
      data from the device; patient perceptions of the home-device application, and patient use
      rates of data upload (intervention), and frequency of BG and BP testing both before and
      during the intervention period (for both intervention and control patients).

      The primary outcome measure will be a comparison of A1c at three months following enrollment
      (i.e., patient met goal of &gt; 0.5% change in A1c or SBP &lt; 130). The proportion of patients who
      meet the blood glucose / BP goal three months after enrollment will be computed for both the
      intervention group and the control group. For each group, the denominator will be the number
      of patients enrolled in that group (and thus were not meeting the recommended goals at the
      time of enrollment). The numerator will be those patients who meet the recommended goals as
      determined during an office visit which occurs three months (+/- 14 calendar days) after
      enrollment.

      Changes in care processes will be categorized and described, and related to the patient
      entered data (daily blood glucose measures).

      Physician and nurse perception data will be analyzed using qualitative approaches.
      Intervention group patient perceptions and satisfaction with the home-device application will
      be measured using a short survey and analyzed descriptively.

      In the intervention group, patient use rates will be calculated to include the percent of
      readings submitted as the numerator and total expected as denominator (e.g., submitted 70
      readings/90 days = 78% use rate).

      RN time per week for data review &amp; follow up will be analyzed descriptively to assess the
      burden of responding to monitoring data.

      Data will be collected on the time for enrollment and patient training in order to estimate
      costs associated with the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) or Systolic blood pressure (SBP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in care (process), abstracted from patient's medical record</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months, 6 months following enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-entered device data</measure>
    <time_frame>All data over three months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">108</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>100 eligible subjects identified as (HbA1c &gt;= 8% OR SBP &gt; 130 mm Hg)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>100 eligible subjects identified as (HbA1c &gt;= 8% OR SBP &gt; 130 mm Hg)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>The subject will take their blood pressure or glucose measurements 1-4 times per day, depending on patient condition. They will upload these measurements using the device to a secure website at least every other day. Data will be reviewed at least 2 times per week Monday through Friday by the clinic nursing staff. Data indicating problems, e.g., critical out of range values, will be communicated to the patient's primary care physician after review by the nurse. The physician will then determine what is needed for follow up action based on the patient's condition and data (e.g., telephone call to patient home, scheduling a clinic appointment, etc).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MetrikLink, MediCompass, iMetrikus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  hemoglobin A1c (A1c) ≥8% OR systolic BP&gt; 130 on last measurement

          -  on oral medication or insulin

          -  Type 2 diabetes

          -  Diabetes and hypertension for at least one year

          -  using/owns a blood glucose meter (that is compatible with study equipment)

          -  followed by an attending MD

          -  private land phone line or computer with internet connection

          -  enrolled at Family &amp; Community Medicine (FCM) Green Meadows , FCM Woodrail or Fairview
             General Internal Medicine (GIM) clinic and anticipate receiving primary care for next
             12 months from MU primary care

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  newly diagnosed or Type 1 diabetes

          -  legally blind

          -  currently reside in a long-term care facility, including assisted living facility,
             residential care

          -  severe cognitive impairment (6-item cognitive screen via recruitment telephone call)

          -  family/household member enrolled in study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Mehr, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Missouri, School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Missouri, Dept. of Family and Community Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>65211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 2, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 3, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

