<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00806338</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MSI-1436C-102</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00806338</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Ascending Multi-Dose, Tolerance and Pharmacokinetic Study in Obese or Overweight Type 2 Diabetic Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Ascending IV Multiple Dose Tolerance and Pharmacokinetic Study of Trodusquemine (MSI-1436) in Obese or Overweight Type 2 Diabetic Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Genaera Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Genaera Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and tolerance of multiple intravenous
      (through a vein) doses of trodusquemine (MSI-1436) in obese or overweight, type 2 diabetics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Different amounts of trodusquemine (MSI-1436) will be given to each volunteer group
      throughout the study. Another purpose is to evaluate the pharmacokinetics (PK - the study of
      the way the drug enters and leaves the blood and tissues over time) of trodusquemine
      (MSI-1436). Finally, this study will also determine whether trodusquemine (MSI-1436) has any
      effect on appetite, mood or behavior, and selective biomarkers (substances in your blood that
      may change in response to the study drug).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerance of multiple intravenous doses of trodusquemine (MSI-1436) in obese or overweight type 2 diabetics. Safety will be evaluated by physical exams, vital signs assessments, 12-lead ECGs, clinical lab tests and adverse event profile.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on glucose tolerance or glucose/insulin relationships</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on appetite and food consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on behavior and mood</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on exploratory biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Trodusquemine (MSI-1436) 3mg/m2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Trodusquemine (MSI-1436) 6mg/m2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Trodusquemine (MSI-1436) 10mg/m2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trodusquemine (MSI-1436)</intervention_name>
    <description>A single dose of Trodusquemine (MSI-1436) will be administered every 72 hours on Days 0, 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18 and 21. Doses are 3mg/m2 in cohort 1, 6mg/m2 in cohort 2 and 10mg/m2 in cohort 3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Trodusquemine (MSI-1436) 3mg/m2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Trodusquemine (MSI-1436) 6mg/m2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Trodusquemine (MSI-1436) 10mg/m2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. male or female obese or overweight type 2 diabetic subjects, between 18 and 65 years
             old (inclusive) either treatment naïve or who are inadequately controlled on metformin
             alone;

          2. subjects receiving metformin should be on stable dose for at least two weeks prior to
             enrollment;

          3. have a fasting blood sugar of ≥ 100 mg/dL and hemoglobin A1C ≥ 7.5% (but ≤ 11.0%) at
             study entry;

          4. of any race who are in good health (based on medical history, physical examination,
             electrocardiograms [ECGs], and clinical laboratory tests);

          5. non-smokers (refrained from any tobacco or nicotine usage, including smokeless
             tobacco, nicotine patches, etc.,) for 6 months prior to Day 0 of the study. Subjects
             must have cotinine levels below those measured for smokers based on reference lab
             values;

          6. body mass index (BMI) of 27-40 kg/m2;

          7. able to execute informed written consent;

          8. willingness to remain in the clinic for the inpatient portion of the study and return
             for follow-up visits as required by the protocol and as deemed necessary by the
             Principal Investigator;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. likely allergy or sensitivity to any components of Trodusquemine (MSI-1436C) for
             Injection;

          2. any subject with a history of severe allergy or bronchial asthma;

          3. a clinically significant history of or current abnormality or disease of any organ
             system, including renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular (except
             hyperlipidemia or controlled hypertension), pulmonary (including chronic asthma),
             endocrine (except diabetes), central nervous, or hematologic systems, or recent
             clinically significant surgery;

          4. history of seizure, epilepsy, severe head injury, multiple sclerosis, or other known
             neurological conditions;

          5. abnormal pre-admission vital signs, physical examination, clinical laboratory, or any
             safety variable which is considered clinically significant for this population by the
             Principal Investigator or Sponsor (or designee). Subjects with an abnormal serum
             creatinine should not be enrolled. Subjects with AST (SGOT), ALT (SGPT), GGT, alkaline
             phosphatase, bilirubin, blood urea nitrogen (BUN), prothrombin time (PT), or activated
             partial thromboplastin time (aPPT) &gt;1.5 times above the upper limit of normal should
             not be enrolled;

          6. any subject with a clinically significant mental or physical illness within 1 year
             prior to the first dose, including a history of alcohol and/or drug abuse within 1
             year prior to the first dose of study medication;

          7. Insulin requiring diabetics;

          8. any subject who has received any known hepatic or renal clearance altering agents (eg,
             erythromycin, cimetidine, barbiturates, phenothiazines, St. John's Wort, etc.) within
             a period of 90 days prior to the first dose of study medication;

          9. any subject who has received any approved prescription anti-obesity drug or has taken
             any over-the-counter medication for weight loss or who has received a
             thiazolidinedione or exanatide within a period of 90 days prior to the first dose of
             study medication;

         10. ingestion or use of any investigational medication or device within 60 days prior to
             the first dose of study medication; ingestion or use of any investigational
             anti-obesity medication is prohibited within 3 months prior to the first dose of study
             medication;

         11. any subject with history of malignancy in last 5 years, with exception of basal and
             squamous cell carcinomas of the skin;

         12. any subject who is positive for HBsAG, Hepatitis C antibody, Hepatitis A IgM, or Human
             Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) Viral Serology tests at the screening visit;

         13. a positive qualitative urine drug or alcohol test at screening or at check-in;

         14. mental capacity is limited to the extent that the subject cannot provide legal consent
             or understand information regarding the study;

         15. any subject who has had a 10% weight loss in the past 3 months prior to the screening
             visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Kipnes, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>dgd Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gilbert Weiner, D.O. AOBFP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cetero Research, San Antonio</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cetero Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami Gardens</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33169</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>dgd Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 15, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Michael Gast, MD, PhD</name_title>
    <organization>Genaera Corporation</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

