<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00803426</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>07-0495-B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00803426</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultrasound Guided Popliteal Fossa Block. Does Blockade Distal to Sciatic Nerve Bifurcation Speed Onset Time? A Prospective, Randomized Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ultrasound Guided Popliteal Fossa Block. Does Blockade Distal to Sciatic Nerve Bifurcation Speed Onset Time? A Prospective, Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Sciatic nerve block is used routinely in ankle and foot surgery. It is applied often by a
      posterior approach at the popliteal fossa, near where the nerve divides into the common
      peroneal and tibial nerves. Due to the size of the sciatic nerve, the largest in the body,
      infiltration of anesthetic and onset of anesthesia can take a significant amount of time.
      This study hypothesizes that selectively blocking both the common peroneal and the tibial
      nerves distal to the bifurcation may result in a faster block onset than blockade of the
      sciatic nerve proximal to its bifurcation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sciatic nerve block (SNB) has been shown to reduce postoperative pain and opioid
      requirements, as well as improve patient satisfaction after outpatient foot and ankle
      surgery. The sciatic nerve divides into two terminal branches (the common peroneal and tibial
      nerves) in the popliteal fossa. Through these two branches it innervates the entire leg,
      ankle and foot except for the skin over the anterior-medial aspect of the leg, which is
      supplied by the saphenous nerve, a branch of the femoral nerve.

      Many approaches have been described to sciatic nerve blockade. High in the thigh or buttock
      are the classical posterior approach, the supine approach, and the anterior approach. In the
      popliteal fossa, a posterior, a lateral and a medial approach have been described. The
      popliteal fossa approaches are most commonly used to provide regional anesthesia and/or
      analgesia for major foot and ankle surgery.

      Traditional nerve localization techniques include seeking paresthesiae on needle to nerve
      contact, or alternatively seeking a muscle response to electrical nerve stimulation using a
      blunt insulated needle and a peripheral nerve stimulator. However, block results with
      traditional nerve localization techniques are highly variable, often requiring high local
      anesthetic doses, and a prolonged onset time. When a distal approach in the popliteal fossa
      is used (5-7 cm above the knee crease) with a nerve stimulator technique, a double motor
      response (both tibial and peroneal components) may be required to achieve consistent success.

      Recently, ultrasound guided techniques for SNB at the popliteal fossa have been described.
      Ultrasound guidance offers the unique advantages of real time anatomic assessment of the
      sciatic nerve itself, its site of bifurcation, and its relationship to surrounding muscles
      and the popliteal vessels. In a recent study we have shown that ultrasound guidance
      significantly improves the success rate of SNB at the popliteal fossa via a posterior
      approach.

      Despite these advantages, a prolonged onset time for complete blockade of up to 30-60 minutes
      (depending on the choice and dose of local anesthetic) is common. This may be a limitation to
      the widespread use of popliteal sciatic nerve blockade in a peri-operative environment, where
      a faster block onset may be preferable. This delayed onset has been attributed to the large
      size of the sciatic nerve. Therefore logically it should be faster to induce a block by
      depositing the local anesthetic after the sciatic nerve divides where the connective tissues
      decrease and the nerves are superficial. No exact mathematical data is available looking into
      onset times for nerves with varying diameter, as no previous studies are done in this area.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Onset time of anesthesia.</measure>
    <time_frame>every 5 minutes until start of surgery</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Block procedure time, complications, location of the sciatic nerve bifurcation, postoperative pain, patient satisfaction with pain control</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 days post-operative</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">55</enrollment>
  <condition>Ankle/Foot Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Local anesthetic will be injected above the division of the sciatic nerve.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Local anesthetic will be injected below the division of the sciatic nerve, around the common peroneal and tibial nerves.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sciatic nerve blockade for ankle/foot surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Injection of local anesthetic near the nerve to achieve anesthesia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. ASA physical status I-III

          2. 18-85 years of age, inclusive

          3. 50-120 kg, inclusive

          4. 150 cm of height or grater Scheduled for major elective foot or ankle surgery for
             which sciatic nerve block is indicated

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Contraindications to sciatic nerve block (e.g., allergy to local anesthetics,
             coagulopathy, malignancy or infection in the popliteal area)

          2. Significant peripheral neuropathy or neurological disorder affecting the lower
             extremity

          3. Pregnancy

          4. History of alcohol or drug dependency/abuse

          5. History of significant psychiatric conditions that may affect patient assessment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anahi Perlas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 2S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 4, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ultrasound-guided regional anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>nerve block</keyword>
  <keyword>popliteal fossa</keyword>
  <keyword>sciatic nerve</keyword>
  <keyword>common peroneal nerve</keyword>
  <keyword>tibial nerve</keyword>
  <keyword>onset time</keyword>
  <keyword>ankle surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>foot surgery</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics, Local</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

