<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00800982</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KOO - ENBREL-2008</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>H5939-31693-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00800982</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Open Label Study Etanercept's Maintenance Dose in Obese Patients With Moderate to Severe Plaque Type Psoriasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Center, Open-Label, Pilot Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Tolerability of Narrow Band UVB Phototherapy in Enhancing Etanercept's Maintenance Dose in Obese Patients With Moderate to Severe Plaque-Type Psoriasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, open-label, pilot study. A total of 30 subjects (15 in each study
      arm) will be enrolled in this 6 month study to evaluate whether the addition of narrow band
      UVB (NB-UVB) phototherapy can enhance the efficacy of etanercept's maintenance dose, 50 mg
      once a week, in obese psoriasis patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In Phase I, all subjects will receive etanercept's induction dose, 50 mg twice a week, for a
      total of 12 weeks. In Phase II, all subjects will receive etanercept's maintenance dose, 50
      mg once a week, during Weeks 12-24. Those subjects randomized to the treatment arm will
      receive NB-UVB phototherapy 3 times a week during Phase II. In order to ensure homogeneity
      between the NB-UVB arm and non-NB-UVB arm, subjects will be randomized according to their
      Body Mass Index (BMI). The Psoriasis Area Severity Index (PASI) score and Physician Global
      Assessment (PGA) will be calculated at each visit to determine the effectiveness of the
      etanercept and NB-UVB treatment during both phases of the study. The hypothesis is that the
      combination of NB-UVB phototherapy three times a week and etanercept maintenance dose (50 mg
      once a week) will enhance the efficacy of the maintenance dose alone in obese patients (BMI
      &gt;30) with moderate to severe psoriasis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psoriasis Area Severity Index. This Scale Ranges From 0-72, 0 Being no Disease, and 72 Being Most Severe. The Number of Patients Who Achieved 75% Improvement of Their Psoriasis at the End of 24 Weeks Are Indicated in the Outcomes Data Below.</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 12-24</time_frame>
    <description>Psoriasis area severity index was used to determine the number of patients in each treatment arm who had 75% improvement in their psoriasis. This scale uses the characteristics of the psoriasis, such as body surface area, redness, thickness, and scaling, to determine the severity score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1 (Etanercept only)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will only be treated with etanercept. This is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months. No UVB will be given. Sham UVB will not be used because the subjects are not blinded because they often know they are receiving sham UVB due to differences in light intensity and heat.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2 (Etanercept + nb-UVB)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive etanercept. This is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months.
In addition, for months 3-6, subjects will receive Narrow Band Ultraviolet B phototherapy three times a week for 12 weeks in addition to the etanercept maintenance dose. The safety and efficacy of the combination therapy will be evaluated by the registered phototherapy nurses at each phototherapy visit and by the study investigator at monthly visits. NB-UVB therapy will be adjusted according to the clinical judgment of the University of California San Francisco Psoriasis Treatment Center phototherapy staff.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Narrow band (310-312 nm) ultraviolet light B phototherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Narrow band (310-312 nm) ultraviolet light B phototherapy 3 times a week during Weeks 12-24. NB-UVB therapy will be adjusted according to the clinical judgment of the University of California San Francisco Psoriasis Treatment Center phototherapy staff</description>
    <arm_group_label>2 (Etanercept + nb-UVB)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>nb-UVB</other_name>
    <other_name>nbUVB</other_name>
    <other_name>narrowband UVB</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>etanercept</intervention_name>
    <description>Etanercept is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1 (Etanercept only)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2 (Etanercept + nb-UVB)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Enbrel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Nonimmunocompromised males or females 18 years of age or older.

          -  Must be able to read, understand, and speak basic English.

          -  Body Surface Area (BSA) involvement of greater than 10%.

          -  Psoriasis Area and Severity Index greater than 10.

          -  Obese defined as having a Body Mass Index greater than 30.

          -  Eligible for systemic therapy, particularly etanercept, and Narrow Band Ultraviolet B
             in the opinion of the investigator.

          -  Sign and date the appropriate written informed consent and Health Insurance
             Portability and Accountability Act authorization

          -  Negative urine pregnancy test within 7 days before the first dose of etanercept in all
             women (except those surgically sterile or at least 5 years postmenopausal).

          -  No evidence of active or latent tuberculosis based on a negative Purified Protein
             Derivative skin test. Patients with documentation of adequately treated tuberculosis
             may be enrolled.

          -  Sexually active subjects of childbearing potential must agree to use medically
             acceptable form of contraception during screening and throughout the study.

          -  Willing and able to self-administer subcutaneous injections or to have a qualified
             person available to administer subcutaneous injections

          -  Agrees to comply with protocol requirements, attend all regularly study visits and is
             considered to be a good study subject

          -  Meets concomitant medication washout requirements

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Erythrodermic, pustular, or guttate psoriasis

          -  Evidence of skin conditions other than psoriasis that would interfere with
             study-related evaluations of psoriasis.

          -  Known sensitivity to any component of the study medications.

          -  Evidence of active infections such as fevers, chills, sweats, or history of untreated
             Lyme disease and active severe infections within 4 weeks before screening visit, or
             between the screening and Week 0 visits.

          -  Evidence of latent or active hepatitis B infection as indicated by positive HBsAg test
             during the screening visit.

          -  Personal or first degree family history of neurologic disease.

          -  Poorly controlled medical condition including, but not limited to, unstable
             cardiovascular disease, poorly controlled diabetes, recent stroke, history of
             recurrent infections, or any other condition for which, in the opinion of the
             investigator, participation in the study would place the subject at risk.

          -  History of any Tumor Necrosis Factor-α inhibitor use including etanercept, infliximab,
             and adalimumab within 4 weeks of starting study drug.

          -  History of non-cutaneous malignancy within the past 5 years.

          -  History of drug or alcohol abuse. Substance abuse must clearly be documented so those
             patients with a remote and minor history of drug/alcohol use will still have an
             opportunity to participate in the study.

          -  Female subjects who are not postmenopausal for at least 1 year, surgically sterile, or
             willing to practice effective contraception during the study. Nursing mothers,
             pregnant women and women planning to become pregnant while on study are to be
             excluded.

          -  Plans to receive any live vaccines during the study.

          -  Evidence of photosensitivity disorder (i.e. polymorphous light eruption).

          -  Known photosensitivity or known sensitivity to any of the excipients or products to be
             administered during dosing.

          -  Current enrollment in another clinical study and treatment with another experimental
             drug or approved therapy for experimental use within 30 days prior to Week 0

          -  Cannot commit to all the assessments required by the protocol

          -  Any disorder that compromises the ability of the subject to give written informed
             consent and/or to comply with study procedures

          -  Considered by the investigator, for any reason, to be an unsuitable candidate for
             study participation.

          -  Cannot or do not wish to comply with the protocol washout requirements (please see
             section below entitled &quot;Washout Period Prior to Week 0).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Koo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCSF Psoriasis and Skin Treatment Center, Department of Dermatology, University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Psoriasis and Skin Treatment Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94118</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Park KK, Wu JJ, Koo J. A randomized, 'head-to-head' pilot study comparing the effects of etanercept monotherapy vs. etanercept and narrowband ultraviolet B (NB-UVB) phototherapy in obese psoriasis patients. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2013 Jul;27(7):899-906. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-3083.2012.04611.x. Epub 2012 Jun 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22702846</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 13, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 2, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>February 19, 2013</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>March 26, 2013</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">May 7, 2013</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 7, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obese patients (BMI&gt;30)</keyword>
  <keyword>Patients with moderate to severe psoriasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etanercept</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Dates of recruitment were July 2010 through June 2011. Recruitment was performed at the dermatologic medical clinic.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>The following treatments for psoriasis required wash-out before group assignment: any type of ultraviolet B phototherapy or topical therapy for 14 days; psoralen and ultraviolet A or any oral or systemic psoriasis treatment for 28 days; alefacept or ustekinumab for 12 weeks, Tumor Necrosis Factor-a inhibitor or monoclonal antibody for 4 weeks.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>1 (Etanercept Only)</title>
          <description>Subjects will only be treated with etanercept. This is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months. No Ultraviolet B will be given. Sham Ultraviolet B will not be used because the subjects are not blinded because they often know they are receiving sham Ultraviolet B due to differences in light intensity and heat.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>2 (Etanercept + Nb-UVB)</title>
          <description>Subjects will receive etanercept. This is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months.
In addition, for months 3-6, subjects will receive Narrow Band Ultraviolet B phototherapy three times a week for 12 weeks in addition to the etanercept maintenance dose. The safety and efficacy of the combination therapy will be evaluated by the registered phototherapy nurses at each phototherapy visit and by the study investigator at monthly visits. Narrow Band Ultraviolet B therapy will be adjusted according to the clinical judgment of the University of California San Francisco Psoriasis Treatment Center phototherapy staff.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="15"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="15"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="13"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="12"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lost to Follow-up</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Patient moved out of state</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>1 (Etanercept Only)</title>
          <description>Subjects will only be treated with etanercept. This is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months. No UVB will be given. Sham UVB will not be used because the subjects are not blinded because they often know they are receiving sham UVB due to differences in light intensity and heat.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>2 (Etanercept + Nb-UVB)</title>
          <description>Subjects will receive etanercept. This is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months.
In addition, for months 3-6, subjects will receive NB-UVB phototherapy three times a week for 12 weeks in addition to the etanercept maintenance dose. The safety and efficacy of the combination therapy will be evaluated by the registered phototherapy nurses at each phototherapy visit and by the study investigator at monthly visits. NB-UVB therapy will be adjusted according to the clinical judgment of the UCSF Psoriasis Treatment Center phototherapy staff.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="15"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="15"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="30"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="30"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="44.7" spread="1.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="43.8" spread="2.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="44.2" spread="1.9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="25"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="30"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Psoriasis Area Severity Index. This Scale Ranges From 0-72, 0 Being no Disease, and 72 Being Most Severe. The Number of Patients Who Achieved 75% Improvement of Their Psoriasis at the End of 24 Weeks Are Indicated in the Outcomes Data Below.</title>
        <description>Psoriasis area severity index was used to determine the number of patients in each treatment arm who had 75% improvement in their psoriasis. This scale uses the characteristics of the psoriasis, such as body surface area, redness, thickness, and scaling, to determine the severity score.</description>
        <time_frame>Weeks 12-24</time_frame>
        <population>All patients that completed the trial through week 24 were used for analysis.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>1 (Etanercept Only)</title>
            <description>Subjects will only be treated with etanercept. This is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months. No UVB will be given. Sham UVB will not be used because the subjects are not blinded because they often know they are receiving sham UVB due to differences in light intensity and heat.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>2 (Etanercept + Nb-UVB)</title>
            <description>Subjects will receive etanercept. This is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months.
In addition, for months 3-6, subjects will receive NB-UVB phototherapy three times a week for 12 weeks in addition to the etanercept maintenance dose. The safety and efficacy of the combination therapy will be evaluated by the registered phototherapy nurses at each phototherapy visit and by the study investigator at monthly visits. NB-UVB therapy will be adjusted according to the clinical judgment of the UCSF Psoriasis Treatment Center phototherapy staff.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Psoriasis Area Severity Index. This Scale Ranges From 0-72, 0 Being no Disease, and 72 Being Most Severe. The Number of Patients Who Achieved 75% Improvement of Their Psoriasis at the End of 24 Weeks Are Indicated in the Outcomes Data Below.</title>
          <description>Psoriasis area severity index was used to determine the number of patients in each treatment arm who had 75% improvement in their psoriasis. This scale uses the characteristics of the psoriasis, such as body surface area, redness, thickness, and scaling, to determine the severity score.</description>
          <population>All patients that completed the trial through week 24 were used for analysis.</population>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="13"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="12"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>1 (Etanercept Only)</title>
          <description>Subjects will only be treated with etanercept. This is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months. No UVB will be given. Sham UVB will not be used because the subjects are not blinded because they often know they are receiving sham UVB due to differences in light intensity and heat.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>2 (Etanercept + Nb-UVB)</title>
          <description>Subjects will receive etanercept. This is given at the standard FDA approved dosage of 50 mg twice weekly x 3 months then 50 mg once weekly x 3 months.
In addition, for months 3-6, subjects will receive NB-UVB phototherapy three times a week for 12 weeks in addition to the etanercept maintenance dose. The safety and efficacy of the combination therapy will be evaluated by the registered phototherapy nurses at each phototherapy visit and by the study investigator at monthly visits. NB-UVB therapy will be adjusted according to the clinical judgment of the UCSF Psoriasis Treatment Center phototherapy staff.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="15"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="15"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="15"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="15"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Of the 30 subjects enrolled, 3 were lost to follow-up, one moved out of state, and one voluntarily withdrew due to worsening of psoriasis.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr Ethan Levin</name_or_title>
      <organization>University of California San Francisco</organization>
      <phone>4154764019</phone>
      <email>levine@derm.ucsf.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

