<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01319955</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PR-09054</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>00002579</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01319955</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Flu Vaccine Against Childhood Pneumonia, Bangladesh</brief_title>
  <official_title>Influenza Vaccine Efficacy Against Childhood Pneumonia in an Urban Tropical Setting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pneumonia is the leading cause of child death worldwide. Data from Bangladesh indicates that
      influenza has a substantial association with pneumonia among children less than two years
      old. This study will use commercially available trivalent inactivated vaccine (killed
      vaccine) to see if it can prevent early childhood pneumonia among children less than two
      years old. The study will vaccinate children across three seasons (3 years), and look at the
      effect on the attack rate of pneumonia, as well as its effects on laboratory-confirmed
      influenza. It will also look at the effect on laboratory-confirmed influenza illness among
      the non-vaccinated household contacts of all ages of these children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pneumonia is the primary cause of child mortality worldwide. The global community is
      considering interventions to reduce pneumonia burden, including vaccines. Most attention is
      focused on bacterial vaccines. Influenza vaccine has not received attention due to lack of
      influenza burden data from high pneumonia endemic settings, and poor understanding of how
      influenza contributes, independently and with other pathogens, to childhood pneumonia burden.
      Data from Bangladesh indicate that influenza has a high incidence of over 10% per year among
      children &lt; 5 years, and that among children who get influenza infection, 28% develop
      pneumonia, including severe pneumonia. Influenza-infected children who develop pneumonia are
      significantly younger (&lt; 2y) than those who do not. Due to the high influenza incidence, and
      the high proportion of influenza-infected children who develop pneumonia, influenza is a
      major contributor to childhood pneumonia, not only in Bangladesh, but likely throughout the
      pneumonia endemic tropical and sub-tropical belt. Although trials have been conducted to
      examine influenza vaccine impact on influenza, none have been conducted specifically to
      determine the effect on childhood pneumonia, particularly among those &lt; 2 years who are at
      highest pneumonia risk. We propose to conduct such a trial.

      The project goal is to determine whether influenza vaccine (trivalent inactivated vaccine or
      TIV) can reduce childhood pneumonia burden including: influenza-associated, other
      aetiology-mediated, and overall pneumonia incidence. The specific objectives are to determine
      influenza vaccine efficacy on 1) early childhood pneumonia (children &lt; 2 years), 2)
      laboratory-confirmed influenza and 3) the rates of influenza-specific complications including
      severe disease, hospitalisation, and otitis media. Secondary objectives include determining
      the effect of influenza vaccine on household transmission and associated complications among
      all age groups, the effect on proven non-influenza viral and bacterial invasive diseases, the
      occurrence of adverse events associated with the vaccine, and to measure immune
      responsiveness to influenza vaccine in these young children.

      Critical milestones include comparison between vaccinated and vaccine-controlled children of
      1) pneumonia incidence (vaccine efficacy against pneumonia), 2) influenza incidence (vaccine
      efficacy against influenza) 3) rates of other clinical syndromes (vaccine efficacy against
      other childhood morbidity). Milestones related to secondary objectives include comparison
      between vaccinated and vaccine-controlled children of 1) rates of laboratory-confirmed
      infection and clinical illness among household contacts and 2) rates of other invasive
      bacterial and viral diseases, and 3) rates of adverse events. We will also measure childhood
      immune responsiveness to influenza vaccine and relate that to observed rates of infection and
      clinical illness.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical pneumonia</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Children who present with age-specific tachypnoea, cough with crepitations on auscultation will be determined to have clinical pneumonia. If this occurs ≥14 days post two doses of influenza vaccine, they will be considered fully vaccinated. Comparisons will be made between groups on the number of such episodes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory confirmed influenza infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Influenza infection will be determined by RT-PCR among children with signs and symptoms of febrile and/or respiratory symptoms, including pneumonia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Indirect effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months post-vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory-confirmed influenza will assessed by RT-PCR among household contacts who present with signs and symptoms of febrile and/or respiratory illness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of influenza infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months post vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>The epidemiological (seasonality and incidence) and clinical (important clinical syndromes, clinical course, complications and outcomes) characteristics of laboratory-confirmed influenza infection in this age group will be documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on non-influenza viral and bacterial invasive disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months post vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure the influenza vaccine effect on invasive disease by other pathogens, including pneumococcus, Haemophilus, and several respiratory viruses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 months of vaccine administration</time_frame>
    <description>We will obtain serum on a 20% subsample of children pre-dose 1, pre-dose 2 and 4 weeks post-dose 2 to determine the immune responsiveness to the vaccine.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events associated with the vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>Beginning Day 0 (day of vaccination) and for the next 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events will be monitored, beginning the day of vaccination and for the next 7 days (8 time points) using standardised questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3508</enrollment>
  <condition>Pneumonia</condition>
  <condition>Laboratory Confirmed Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Influenza vaccine (trivalent inactivated vaccine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inactivated polio vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trivalent inactivated influenza vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Two doses of 0.25 ml vaccine delivered IM at least 4 weeks apart.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Influenza vaccine (trivalent inactivated vaccine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Inactivated polio vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vaxigrip Junior</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children will be included if they are de jure residents 6 months to 23 months old at
             the time of first dose vaccination residing in households under surveillance.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children will be excluded if they have known chronic respiratory, cardiac, or
             neurological (including seizure disorders) illnesses, are severely malnourished or
             require hospitalisation for any other reason, are suspected of having tuberculosis
             (WHO guidelines) [83], are known to have egg allergy, or parents withhold consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>23 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>W. Abdullah Brooks, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICDDR,B</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dhaka</city>
        <zip>1000</zip>
        <country>Bangladesh</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Bangladesh</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brooks WA, Goswami D, Rahman M, Nahar K, Fry AM, Balish A, Iftekharuddin N, Azim T, Xu X, Klimov A, Bresee J, Bridges C, Luby S. Influenza is a major contributor to childhood pneumonia in a tropical developing country. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2010 Mar;29(3):216-21. doi: 10.1097/INF.0b013e3181bc23fd.</citation>
    <PMID>20190613</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 21, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 22, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pneumonia</keyword>
  <keyword>Influenza</keyword>
  <keyword>Child</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory</keyword>
  <keyword>Pathogen</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

