<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03275103</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GO39775</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03275103</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose-Escalation Study of BFCR4350A in Participants With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma (R/R MM)</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Multicenter, Phase I Trial Evaluating the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Escalating Doses of BFCR4350A in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Genentech, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I, multicenter, open-label, dose-escalation study of BFCR4350A administered
      as a single agent by IV infusion to participants with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma
      (R/R MM).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 19, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and Severity of Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is any unfavorable and unintended sign (including an abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a medical treatment or procedure that may or may not be considered related to the medical treatment or procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the maximum observed serum concentration of study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>OR is defined as percentage of participants with partial response (PR) or complete response (CR).
CR is defined as no evidence of initial monoclonal protein isotype(s) on immunofixation of the serum and urine, disappearance of any soft tissue plasmacytomas, and &lt;/= 5% plasma cells in bone marrow (BM).
PR is defined as &gt;/= 50% reduction of serum M-protein and reduction in 24-hour urine M-protein by &gt;/= 90% or to &lt; 200 milligrams (mg)/24 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time from first occurrence of OR (defined previously) to disease progression (PD) or death from any cause. PD: increase of &gt;/=25% from lowest response value in one of the following: serum M-protein (absolute increase &gt;/=0.5 grams per deciliter (g/dL); serum M-protein increase &gt;/=1g/dL, if lowest M component was &gt;/=5g/dL; urine M-protein (absolute increase &gt;/=200 mg/24 hours); no measurable serum and urine M-protein levels: difference between involved and uninvolved free light chain (FLC) levels (absolute increase &gt;10 mg/dL); no measurable serum and urine M-protein levels and no measurable disease by FLC: BM plasma cell % irrespective of baseline status (absolute % &gt;/=10%); new lesion(s) &gt;/=50% increase from lowest point in sum of the products of diameters of &gt; 1 lesion, or &gt;/=50% increase in longest diameter of a previous lesion &gt;1 centimeter (cm) in short axis; &gt;/=50% increase in circulating plasma cells (minimum 200 cells per microliter) if only measure of disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the Presence Anti-Drug Antibodies (ADAs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the immune response to the study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimum observed serum concentration (Cmin)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the minimum observed serum concentration of study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Concentration-Time Curve</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the total exposure of study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clearance (CL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the volume of plasma cleared of the drug per unit time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of Distribution at Steady State (Vdss)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the actual blood and tissue volume into which a drug is distributed and the relative binding of drug to protein in these spaces.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation for BFCR4350A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study drug will be administered intravenously on a 21-day cycle. Initially, cohorts will consist of 1 participant each. Subsequently will consist of at least 3 participants, unless dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) are observed in the first 2 prior to enrollment of a third participant. For each cohort, treatment with the first dose will be staggered such that the second participant enrolled in the cohort will receive study drug at least 72 hours after the first participant receives it to allow assessment of any severe and unexpected acute or subacute drug or infusion-related toxicities; dosing in subsequent participants in each cohort will be staggered by at least 24 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Expansion Phase for BFCR4350A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants exhibiting acceptable safety and evidence of clinical benefit will be administered study drug every 21 days up to a maximum of 17 cycles until objective disease progression is documented or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BFCR4350A</intervention_name>
    <description>BFCR4350A will be administered intravenously on a 21-day cycle, up to a total of 17 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dose Escalation for BFCR4350A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Expansion Phase for BFCR4350A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RO7187797</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0 or 1

          -  Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks

          -  Participants must have relapsed or refractory (R/R) multiple myeloma (MM) for which no
             established therapy for MM is appropriate and available or be intolerant to those
             established therapies

          -  Adverse events from prior anti-cancer therapy resolved to Grade &lt; or = 1, except any
             grade alopecia and/or peripheral sensory or motor neuropathy which must have resolved
             to Grade &lt; or = 2

          -  Measurable disease defined by laboratory test results

          -  Female participants of childbearing age must agree to remain abstinent or use reliable
             contraceptive methods during the treatment period, and at least 3 months after last
             dose of study drug

          -  Male participants must agree to refrain from donating sperm, to abstain or use a
             condom during the treatment period, and at least 60 days after last dose of study drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to comply with protocol-mandated hospitalization and activities restrictions

          -  Pregnant, lactating, or planning to become pregnant during the study and up to 3
             months after last dose of study drug

          -  Prior use of any monoclonal antibody, radioimmunoconjugate, or antibody-drug conjugate
             within 4 weeks before first infusion

          -  Prior treatment with systemic immunotherapeutic agents within 12 weeks or 5 half-lives
             of the drug, whichever is shorter, before first infusion

          -  Treatment-related, immune-mediated adverse events associated with prior
             immunotherapeutic agents

          -  Treatment with radiotherapy, any chemotherapeutic agent, or treatment with any other
             anti-cancer agent (investigational or otherwise) within 4 weeks or 5 half-lives of the
             drug, whichever is shorter, prior to first BFCR4350A infusion

          -  Autologous stem cell transplantation (SCT) within 100 days prior to first infusion

          -  Prior allogeneic SCT or solid organ transplantation

          -  Primary or secondary plasma cell leukemia

          -  History of autoimmune disease or of confirmed progressive multifocal
             leukoencephalopathy

          -  History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions to monoclonal antibody therapy
             (or recombinant antibody-related fusion proteins)

          -  History of other malignancy that could affect compliance with the protocol or
             interpretation of results

          -  Current or past history of central nervous system (CNS) disease, or CNS involvement by
             MM

          -  Significant cardiovascular disease or active pulmonary disease

          -  Known active bacterial, viral, fungal, mycobacterial, parasitic, or other infection
             (excluding fungal infections of nail beds) at study enrollment, or any major episode
             of infection requiring treatment with IV antibiotics within 4 weeks prior to first
             infusion

          -  Known or suspected chronic active Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) infection, acute or chronic
             hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection

          -  Positive serologic or polymerase chain reaction (PCR) test results for acute or
             chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection

          -  Recent major surgery within 4 weeks prior to first infusion

          -  Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) positive

          -  History of illicit drug or alcohol abuse within 12 months prior to screening

          -  Any medical condition or laboratory test abnormality that precludes the participant's
             safe participation in and completion of the study, or which could affect compliance
             with the protocol or interpretation of results
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Genentech, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Reference Study ID Number: GO39775 www.roche.com/about_roche/roche_worldwide.htm</last_name>
    <phone>888-662-6728 (U.S. only)</phone>
    <email>global-roche-genentech-trials@gene.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic Hospital - Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Denver</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarah Cannon Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alfred Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3004</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peter MacCallum Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Margaret Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1Z6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 5, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 5, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 7, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

