<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03272607</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MedSafer</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CIHR Application No. 365795</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03272607</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reducing Post-discharge Adverse Drug Events Amongst the Elderly: a Multi-centre Electronic Deprescribing Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Reducing Post-discharge Adverse Drug Events Amongst the Elderly: a Multi-centre Electronic Deprescribing Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McGill University Health Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Ottawa Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Foothills Medical Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kingston General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McGill University Health Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Reducing medications and associated side effects in older adults: an electronic
      hospital-based intervention
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Polypharmacy, or the concomitant use of 5 drugs or more, is a serious health concern and
      affects more than half of Canadians aged 65 years and older. It is the number one
      identifiable risk factor for adverse drug events (ADEs), which are responsible for 27,000
      hospital admissions annually in Canada and up to 20% of return visits to the hospital within
      30 days of discharge. Many ADEs are preventable or ameliorable through interventions to
      reduce inappropriate prescribing.

      MedSafer, the intervention software, applies an electronic set of criteria, previously
      designed and piloted on one thousand (1000) hospitalized patients by a group of Quebec and
      Ontario internists, geriatricians, palliative care doctors and pharmacists, to identify
      potentially inappropriate medications (PIMs) in the hospitalized elderly and generate
      instructions for the patient and physician for safe discontinuation. The current study seeks
      to partially automate the deprescribing process and to demonstrate the efficacy of this type
      of intervention on adverse drug events at 30-days post hospital discharge.

      At the time of hospitalization, the patient's medications, co-morbidities, and a measure of
      frailty will be entered into the MedSafer software which will output an individualized and
      prioritized deprescription plan for the most responsible physician's consideration. Any
      subsequent medication changes will be transmitted to relevant community physicians. The study
      will evaluate the impact of stopping PIMs on the occurrence of ADEs within 30 days of
      discharge, as compared to usual care.

      This study will take place on the clinical teaching units (CTUs) at 11 hospitals from seven
      university hospital centres across Canada. Based on historical data, the investigators
      estimate a combined 5200 eligible patients per year with nearly 50% taking ten or more
      medications. Many will have multiple medical co-morbidities such as diabetes, heart disease,
      and renal insufficiency. A large portion will meet criteria for geriatric syndromes such as
      frailty and will be at high risk for the development of delirium, falls and functional
      decline. This population is ideal for a generalizable deprescribing study.

      All patients aged 65 or older who meet inclusion/exclusion criteria will be enrolled. A
      trained research assistant will identify eligible patients and medications will be screened
      using MedSafer. A deprescribing plan will be generated for the CTU team containing the
      rationale for suggested medication changes and strategies for safe and successful
      deprescription. The CTU team will then decide, in conjunction with the patient/proxy and
      relevant consultants, whether to apply the suggested modifications.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 22, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The duration of the project will be a total of (approx.) 96 weeks. This is a stepped wedge cluster randomized trial study design (see PDF attachment entitled &quot;MedSafer, Figure 1&quot; - note start date will be August 2017 not July 2016). The intervention component will be administered sequentially to six (6) clusters (by city). A randomly selected single cluster will move from control data collection to intervention data collection every 200 patients or roughly every 12 weeks (96 total weeks), which will be followed by 12 weeks to complete follow up and another 36 to analyze data.
Please see PDF attachment entitled &quot;MedSafer, Figure 2&quot; which refers to both parts of the study (quality improvement and follow up components). It describes the follow up component of the study (a 30-day telephone follow-up to ascertain adverse drug events- please note the gray-shaded boxes refer to the Quality Improvement Project-Part 1).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Medical chart abstracts compiled at discharge (including any subsequent visits within 30 days) will be combined with the patient telephone interview into a case summary report which will be reviewed independently by two trained and blinded clinician reviewers who will be made up of pharmacists and physicians from each study site (but who will not adjudicate any patients from their own site).</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Drug Events within 30 days post-discharge (ascertained via telephone interviewer and adjudicated via clinician reviewers)</measure>
    <time_frame>Interview performed 30-35 days post-discharge.</time_frame>
    <description>Post-discharge telephone interview performed by trained personnel using a modification of the Australian two-step adverse reaction and drug event report.
Two trained and blinded clinician reviewers will independently use the Leape and Bates approach to assess whether an ADE was present (yes/no) and if so what was the nature of the injury resulting from it using a four-point Likert scale (definitely preventable, probably preventable, probably not preventable, and definitely not preventable), and assess the probability that an event was attributable to a specific drug that was newly started, changed or continued during hospitalization. In cases of disagreement, a third trained and blinded clinician will review and determine the final assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In-hospital falls</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>The research assistant will record any falls, the timing, and the presence or absence of trauma, throughout the index hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>through study completion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In-hospital mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>During the index hospitalization</time_frame>
    <description>Death in hospital</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of potentially inappropriate medications</measure>
    <time_frame>At hospital discharge and at 30-days post hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>The absolute number of potentially inappropriate medications at discharge among patients who were identified as having a potentially inappropriate medication at admission and for who a deprescribing opportunity was generated and presented to the treating team</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of potentially inappropriate medications</measure>
    <time_frame>At hospital discharge and at 30-days post hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of potentially inappropriate medications at discharge as compared to the total medications at discharge, relative to the proportion at admission, among patients who were identified as having a potentially inappropriate medication at admission and for who a deprescribing opportunity was generated and presented to the treating team as compared to those who did not have any deprescribing opportunities presented to the treating team (intervention vs. control).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality within 30-days post discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>30-days post hospital discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Death following hospital discharge</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8400</enrollment>
  <condition>Adverse Drug Event</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants in the control arm will receive medication reconciliation at admission and discharge, and identical follow up, but no prioritized deprescribing list will be generated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the intervention arm will be electronically screened using an electronic software &quot;MedSafer&quot; which will generate output of PIMs that will be brought to the attention of the CTU team via the unit pharmacist as &quot;deprescribing opportunities&quot;. (Note that in the case of multiple recommendations, they will be limited and prioritized so as to avoid overwhelming the treating team.) Based on their own expert medical judgement, in collaboration with the patient/caregiver and other relevant clinicians, a decision will be made to deprescribe if appropriate by the patient's in-hospital doctors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deprescribing opportunities</intervention_name>
    <description>An electronic intervention that identifies potentially inappropriate medications (PIMs) and generates instructions for safe discontinuation, which is presented to the treating physician for their consideration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients aged 65 years and older

          -  patients who take five or more medications in the community

          -  patients who are cognitively impaired or otherwise unable to provide consent will
             still be included as this subpopulation of patients may be at greatest risk of ADEs
             because of their communication problems.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients who take four or fewer medications in the community

          -  patients expected to die within 30 days or be transferred to a palliative care
             unit/another hospital

          -  patients without provincial health insurance or who normally live outside that
             province

          -  patients previously enrolled

          -  inability for patient or proxy to speak English or French

          -  no means of contacting patient or proxy post-discharge

        Patients discharged from non-study units will be excluded unless that unit is a
        transitional care, rehabilitation, or post-acute care unit which bridges the gap between
        acute medical hospitalization and community services.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Todd C Lee, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McGill University Health Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emily G McDonald, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
    <phone_ext>48488</phone_ext>
    <email>emily.mcdonald@mcgill.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Todd C Lee, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
    <phone_ext>34673</phone_ext>
    <email>todd.lee@mcgill.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kingston General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K7L 2V7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Johanna Murphy, MD</last_name>
      <phone>613-533-2056</phone>
      <email>johanna.murphy@queensu.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Titania Dixon-Luinenburg</last_name>
      <phone>613-869-8944</phone>
      <email>tdixo063@uottawa.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McGill University Health Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4A 3J1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emily G McDonald, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
      <phone_ext>48488</phone_ext>
      <email>emily.mcdonald@mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Carol Silas</last_name>
      <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
      <phone_ext>36134</phone_ext>
      <email>carol.silas@mail.mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 1, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 5, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>McGill University Health Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Emily McDonald</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr. Emily McDonald, Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adverse Drug Event</keyword>
  <keyword>Choosing Wisely Canada</keyword>
  <keyword>Deprescribing</keyword>
  <keyword>Elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>Frailty</keyword>
  <keyword>High value healthcare</keyword>
  <keyword>Medication rationalization</keyword>
  <keyword>Medication stewardship</keyword>
  <keyword>Polypharmacy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Drug-Related Side Effects and Adverse Reactions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We will keep a coded, completely anonymized, database that will be made available to other researchers upon request.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

