<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03270917</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL36215.068.11*</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03270917</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ORANGE SEGMENTS: Open Versus Laparoscopic Parenchymal Preserving Postero-Superior Liver Segment Resection</brief_title>
  <official_title>The ORANGE SEGMENTS - Trial: an International Multicentre Randomized Controlled Trial of Open Versus Laparoscopic Parenchymal Preserving Postero-superior Liver Segment Resection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Aachen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Queen Elizabeth Hospital Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universitair Ziekenhuis Brussel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Ghent</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jessa Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>General Hospital Groeninge</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aintree University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>King's College Hospital NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>San Raffaele University Hospital, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Newcastle-upon-Tyne Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Derriford Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital Southampton NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The international and multicentre ORANGE SEGMENTS - Trial is a prospective, double blinded,
      randomized controlled study comparing patients undergoing parenchymal preserving resection of
      postero-superior liver segments (involving one or two of segments 4a, 7, 8). All patients
      will be participating in an enhanced recovery programme.

      Primary outcome is time to functional recovery. Secondary study parameters include hospital
      length of stay, intraoperative blood loss, operation time, liver specific morbidity,
      readmission percentage, resection margin, quality of life, body image and cosmesis , reasons
      for delay of discharge after functional recovery, long term incidence of incisional hernias,
      hospital and societal costs during one year, time to adjuvant chemotherapy initiation,
      overall five-year survival.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Liver resection for colorectal metastasis is a potential curative therapy and has become the
      standard of care in appropriately staged patients, offering five-year survival rates ranging
      from 38 up to 61% in selected cases, with approximately 30% of patients surviving ten years
      or more, compared to five-year survival rates of less than 5% for patients not amenable to
      resection. Liver surgery is also a widely accepted treatment for symptomatic benign lesions
      and those of uncertain nature or large size. Whilst the figures are a vast improvement on the
      past, there is still a need to refine the treatment of these patients, including surgical
      technique.

      Open hepatectomy is the current standard of care for the management of primary and secondary
      tumours. The open postero-superior liver segment resection requires a large incision to
      achieve adequate access and proper control during resection. This has a significant impact on
      patient's recovery and, in cases of small resections, this access may represent the major
      component of surgical trauma. Advances in surgical technique and expertise now permit these
      operations to be performed with minor incisions by using the laparoscopic approach. Although
      the feasibility of laparoscopic hepatectomy has been established, only select centres use
      this technique as their primary modality.

      Laparoscopic liver resection was first reported in 1991. Over the past decades, the method
      has gained wide acceptance for various liver resection procedures. Multiple retrospective
      case series, patient cohorts, systematic reviews and meta-analyses have compared open with
      laparoscopic liver surgery and indicate the laparoscopic approach to be safely applicable for
      the resection of both malignant and benign liver lesions. Laparoscopic liver resection has
      been associated with shorter hospital length of stay, reduced intraoperative blood loss, less
      postoperative pain and earlier recovery. Despite this, concerns remain over operative times,
      the ability to control haemorrhage laparascopically and long-term oncological outcomes.

      Initially, the left lateral segments of the liver were chosen for anatomic laparoscopic
      resection, with good results. Many liver centres worldwide currently use laparoscopy for
      resection of the anterior liver segments. Whilst case control studies would now seem
      sufficient to allay such concerns in the context of minor liver resections and left lateral
      sectionectomies, the adoption and dissemination of laparoscopy by hepatobiliary oncologic
      surgeons for major hepatectomies and resections of postero-superior segments has been
      restricted. Besides the relatively low volume of patients, major laparoscopic liver
      resections are technically demanding, have a significant learning curve, are time consuming,
      are thought to hold an increased morbidity risk and lack in evidence.

      Nevertheless, a new impulse for the laparoscopic management of major liver lesions came after
      the first reports of laparoscopic hemihepatectomies, which demonstrated that in expert hands
      major anatomical laparoscopic liver resections are feasible with good efficacy and safety.
      When comparing surgical procedures, one of the easiest to measure and often used outcomes is
      the length of hospital stay; the time it takes for a patient to be discharged from the
      hospital after an operation. On the whole, a median hospital length of stay of 6.0 to 13.1
      days and 3.5 to 10.0 days have been observed after open and laparoscopic hepatic resections
      in European centres respectively. For major surgery in expert centres, median duration of
      hospital admission varied between 6 to 12.5 days for open surgery and 4 to 8.2 days for
      laparoscopic resections. Concentrating on postero-superior liver segment resections, the
      median hospital stay is 6 days (3-44 days) for those undergoing open compared with 4 days
      (1-11 days) for those having laparoscopic resections.

      Besides the immediate benefits to the patient, such as decreased intraoperative blood loss,
      diminished postoperative pain, earlier recovery and reduced hospital length of stay,
      laparoscopic liver surgery may also have the potential to improve outcomes in the longer term
      by reducing complications, enhancing quality of life, improving cosmesis, ensuring early
      commencement and completion of adjuvant therapies. However, level-1 evidence on all outcomes
      is still to be presented.

      Within the framework of optimized perioperative care, broader indications for hepatic surgery
      and further adoption of laparoscopic liver resections, there is a clear need for a randomized
      trial. Therefore, the multicentre and international ORANGE SEGMENTS - Trial has been designed
      to provide evidence on the merits of laparoscopic versus open parenchymal preserving
      postero-superior liver segment resection within an enhanced recovery programme in terms of
      time to functional recovery, hospital length of stay, intraoperative blood loss, operation
      time, resection margin, time to adjuvant chemotherapy initiation, readmission percentage,
      (liver specific) morbidity, quality of life, body image, reasons for delay of discharge after
      functional recovery, long term incidence of incisional hernias, hospital and societal costs
      during one year and overall five-year survival.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients will be randomised to either the open or the laparoscopic treatment arm.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>The patient, ward physician and research investigator are blinded to the treatment intervention. A large abdominal dressing will be used to cover the incision(s) until postoperative day 4. Obviously, the surgeon and anaesthesiology team can not be blinded.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to functional recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>expected average of 4-10 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time until a patient is functionally recovered</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Total length of hospital stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative blood loss</measure>
    <time_frame>during procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Net intraoperative blood loss</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operating time</measure>
    <time_frame>surgical time from incision until closure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>(Liver specific) morbidity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Composite endpoint of liver specific morbidity (intra-abdominal bleeding, intra-abdominal abcess, ascites, postresectional liver failure, intra-operative mortality, bile leakage)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readmission percentage</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Total percentage of patients being readmitted</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resection margin</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Residual tumor cells in resection border</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The physical, social and emotional well-being of the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body image and cosmesis</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The aesthetic appearance of the scars associated with the operation and its influence on the patient self-view</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reasons for delay of discharge after functional recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>All reasons that may cause delay in discharge after the patient has recovered functionally, such as administrative reasons, patient confidence, logistics problems, etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incisional herniation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Cicatricial hernia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital and societal costs</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>All costs that are associated with the operation, including in-hospital costs and out of hospital costs, such as home care, work absence, etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to adjuvant chemotherapy initiation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The time it takes to start adjuvant chemotherapy after the patient has been operated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall five-year survival</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Five-year survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Open</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Open liver surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Laparoscopic liver surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Parenchymal preserving postero-superior liver segment resection</intervention_name>
    <description>Parenchymal preserving liver segment resection of one or two of the postero-superior liver segments (4A, 7 or 8).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Open</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients requiring a parenchymal sparing liver resection (including wedge resections
             and full segmentectomies) involving one or two of segments 4a/7/8 for accepted
             indications . A segment 6/7 resection would also be eligible.

          -  Able to understand the nature of the study and what will be required of them.

          -  Men and non-pregnant, non-lactating women, aged 18 years and older.

          -  BMI between and including 18-35 kg/m2

          -  Patients with ASA physical status I-II-III.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to give (written) informed consent.

          -  Patients requiring other liver surgery than a parenchymal sparing resection involving
             one or two of segments 4a, 7, 8.

          -  Patients requiring parenchymal sparing liver resection involving segment 1. This is
             due to the high level of technical difficulty.

          -  Patients with hepatic lesion(s), that are located with insufficient margin from
             vascular or biliary structures to be operated laparoscopically.

          -  Patients with ASA physical status IV-V.

          -  Repeat hepatectomy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohammed Abu Hilal, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Southampton NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Primrose, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Southampton NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark Halls, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+447872641673</phone>
    <email>mark.halls@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Zina Eminton</last_name>
    <phone>+447973551272</phone>
    <email>z.b.eminton@soton.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Erasmus Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>V. Lucidi, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>V. Lucidi, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>G. Katsanos, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jessa Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hasselt</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>G. Sergeant, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>G. Sergeant, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General Hospital Groeninge</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kortrijk</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>M. D'Hondt, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M. D'Hondt, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Aachen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aachen</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>U.P. Neumann, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>U.P. Neumann, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>F. Ulmer, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Raffaele Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>L. Aldrighetti, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>L. Aldrighetti, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>F. Ratti, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Academic Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>M.G. Besselink, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M.G. Besselink, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht University Medical Center+</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>R.M. van Dam, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>R.M. van Dam, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Oslo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Å.A. Fretland, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>B.E. Edwin, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Å.A. Fretland, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aintree University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aintree</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>v Díaz-Nieto, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>R. Díaz-Nieto, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>R. Sutcliffe, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>R. Sutcliffe</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>P. Marudanayagam</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. James's University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>P. Lodge, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>P. Lodge, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>R. Prasad, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>King's College Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>K.V. Menon, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>K.V. Menon, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>A. Ayers, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Freeman Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>S. White, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>S. White, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>S. Robinson, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oxford University Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Z. Soonawalla, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Z. Soonawalla, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M. Silva, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Derriford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plymouth</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>S. Aroori, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>S. Aroori, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>C. Briggs, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Southampton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Southampton</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>M. Halls, MD PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M. Abu Hilal, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>J. Primrose, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M. Halls, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>S. Pugh, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>A.S. Takhar, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>T.H. Armstrong, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Z.R. Hamady, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Norway</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://orangetrial.eu</url>
    <description>The ORANGE - Trials consortium webpage</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coles SR, Besselink MG, Serin KR, Alsaati H, Di Gioia P, Samim M, Pearce NW, Abu Hilal M. Total laparoscopic management of lesions involving liver segment 7. Surg Endosc. 2015 Nov;29(11):3190-5. doi: 10.1007/s00464-014-4052-2. Epub 2015 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25582963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cipriani F, Shelat VG, Rawashdeh M, Francone E, Aldrighetti L, Takhar A, Armstrong T, Pearce NW, Abu Hilal M. Laparoscopic Parenchymal-Sparing Resections for Nonperipheral Liver Lesions, the Diamond Technique: Technical Aspects, Clinical Outcomes, and Oncologic Efficiency. J Am Coll Surg. 2015 Aug;221(2):265-72. doi: 10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2015.03.029. Epub 2015 Mar 27.</citation>
    <PMID>25899733</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scuderi V, Barkhatov L, Montalti R, Ratti F, Cipriani F, Pardo F, Tranchart H, Dagher I, Rotellar F, Abu Hilal M, Edwin B, Vivarelli M, Aldrighetti L, Troisi RI. Outcome after laparoscopic and open resections of posterosuperior segments of the liver. Br J Surg. 2017 May;104(6):751-759. doi: 10.1002/bjs.10489. Epub 2017 Feb 13.</citation>
    <PMID>28194774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zheng B, Zhao R, Li X, Li B. Comparison of laparoscopic liver resection for lesions located in anterolateral and posterosuperior segments: a meta-analysis. Surg Endosc. 2017 Nov;31(11):4641-4648. doi: 10.1007/s00464-017-5527-8. Epub 2017 Apr 7.</citation>
    <PMID>28389796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 31, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 1, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 16, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 16, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parenchymal preserving</keyword>
  <keyword>Postero-superior</keyword>
  <keyword>Laparoscopy</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Extracts</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

