<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03279731</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>827450</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03279731</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Binge Eating Liraglutide Intervention</brief_title>
  <acronym>BELIEVE</acronym>
  <official_title>Liraglutide 3.0mg/d for the Treatment of Binge Eating Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kelly Allison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novo Nordisk A/S</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is a 17-week, single-center, double-blind, parallel-group, randomized placebo
      controlled trial that will test the efficacy of liraglutide 3.0 mg/d as compared to placebo
      in reducing the number of binge episodes per week, achieving remission from binge episodes,
      and in changes in body weight, global BED symptom improvement, cognitive restraint of food
      intake, dietary disinhibition, perceived hunger, quality of life, and depressed mood at
      treatment end.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All applicants will be initially screened by phone and/or electronically to determine whether
      they potentially meet eligibility criteria. Those who appear to meet eligibility criteria and
      remain interested in the trial will be scheduled for an in-person interview.

      The in-person interview will be conducted by a psychologist or Masters' level staff member,
      who will obtain informed consent and evaluate subjects' behavioral eligibility (i.e.,
      willingness and appropriateness to participate) using structured and semi-structured clinical
      interviews including: an examination of the applicants' BED symptoms, their mood,
      suicidality, and other general psychopathology. Participants will also be asked to complete
      questionnaires assessing eating behavior, demographic characteristics, frequency of specific
      eating behaviors related to loss of control, risk of substance dependence with the
      consumption of high fat/sugar foods, alexithymia, night eating syndrome, sleep patterns and
      quality, and attitudes towards food cravings.

      Subjects who remain interested and pass this portion of the assessment will proceed to meet
      with the study physician or nurse practitioner, who will obtain a medical history and conduct
      a physical examination to determine medical eligibility. Subjects will also have an
      electrocardiogram (EKG), fasting blood test, and a urine pregnancy test (for females of child
      bearing age) to confirm eligibility.

      Upon successful completion of the screening visit, subjects will be asked to eat as they
      normally would for 2 weeks. Once per week over these two weeks they will receive a brief
      survey through REDcap to assess their binge eating episodes for eligibility.

      Subjects who continue to meet eligibility criteria assessed at the screening visit and during
      the run-in period will be scheduled for a randomization visit at the Center within 3 weeks of
      their screening.

      Subjects will be randomly assigned to the two interventions in equal numbers (i.e., 1:1
      ratio). The subject's weight, blood pressure, and pulse will then be measured. Following
      randomization, all subjects will have a medical visit with the study physician or nurse
      practitioner who will instruct them in the use of liraglutide 3.0 (as described later) and
      provide the first month's supply of medication.

      After randomization, subjects will return at week 1 to assess rate of response. Subjects will
      return for study visits every two weeks thereafter, at weeks 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 13, 15, and 17.

      These study visits include a brief medical visit (10-15 minutes) with a physician or nurse
      practitioner to monitor their response to the medication or any changes in health. Vitals and
      weight will be taken. Additionally, binge episodes, mood, suicidality, and symptom
      improvement will be assessed by the psychologist or Masters' level trained study staff.
      Participants will be asked also to complete questionnaires assessing quality of life,
      obsessions related to food, and food cravings prior to each treatment visit for the secondary
      outcomes:

      In summary, study visits will consist of the medical visit, completion of written surveys,
      review of structured interviews with the study staff and review of medication adverse events.
      These visits are expected to last about 30-40 minutes. The study assessments at week 17 will
      consist of the previously listed procedures and measures in addition to the questionnaires
      and blood tests conducted at baseline.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 29, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 20, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single-center, double-blind, randomized placebo-controlled trial with parallel groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Novo Nordisk's Clinical Services (CS) will label, package, and ship the labelled study drugs to the Penn's Investigational Drug Service (IDS). Dr. Rockwell from Penn's IDS service will generate the randomization code using a 1:1 randomization scheme of liraglutide and placebo. The first subject to meet the treatment criteria will be assigned the first number in the sequence; each subsequent subject to meet treatment criteria will be assigned the next number in the sequence. Unblinding of the treatment codes will occur after all data have been verified and deemed clean by the data managers and statistician, and right before analysis of the data occurs.
The code for a particular subject may be broken in a medical emergency if knowing the identity of the treatment allocation would influence the treatment of the subject or if demanded by the subject. Whenever a code is broken, the staff-member breaking the code will record the time, date and reason.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Binge Episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>change in binge episodes per week from randomization (week 0) to study end (week 17)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Remission from binge-eating</measure>
    <time_frame>17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>the proportion of participants who have achieved remission from binge-eating (no binge episodes between weeks 13 - 17)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of improvement of binge eating symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>week 17 rating on the interviewer-based Clinical Global Impression of Improvement Scale for global assessment of BED symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in body weight measured in kilograms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Report cognitive restraint from the Eating Inventory Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>self-report measure of cognitive restraint will be measured from the Eating Inventory questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Report dietary disinhibition of from the Eating Inventory Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>self-report measure of dietary disinhibition will be measured from the Eating Inventory questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Report perceived hunger from the Eating Inventory Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>self-report measure of perceived hunger will be measured from the Eating Inventory questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Report Measure of Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self report measure of quality of life will be measured using the Quality of Life, Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Report Measures of Mood</measure>
    <time_frame>17 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Score from the Patient Health Questionnaire 9-Item version (PHQ-9) will be used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">152</enrollment>
  <condition>Binge-Eating Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Liraglutide (Saxenda) 6Mg/Ml Inj Pen 3Ml</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pre-filled, multi-dose pen that delivers doses of 0.6 mg, 1.2 mg, 1.8 mg, 2.4 mg, or 3 mg via subcutaneous injection. Matching the recommended dosage and administration guidelines of the FDA-approved labeling for the use of liraglutide (Saxenda), the medication will be initiated at 0.6 mg daily for 1 week, and then increased by 0.6 mg/day in weekly intervals until a dose of 3.0 mg/day is achieved. Liraglutide is a glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) receptor agonist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pre-filled, multi-dose pen that delivers doses of 0.6 mg, 1.2 mg, 1.8 mg, 2.4 mg, or 3 mg of placebo via subcutaneous injection. The placebo will be initiated at 0.6 mg daily for 1 week, and then increased by 0.6 mg/day in weekly intervals until a dose of 3.0 mg/day is achieved.The inactive ingredients include: disodium phosphate dihydrate, 1.42 mg; propylene glycol, 14 mg; phenol, 5.5 mg; and water for injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liraglutide (Saxenda) 6Mg/Ml Inj Pen 3Ml</intervention_name>
    <description>subcutaneous injection, pre-filled, multi-dose pen that delivers doses of 0.6 mg, 1.2 mg, 1.8 mg, 2.4 mg, or 3 mg (6 mg/mL, 3 mL). Matching the recommended dosage and administration guidelines of the FDA-approved labeling for the use of liraglutide (Saxenda), the medication will be initiated at 0.6 mg daily for 1 week, and then increased by 0.6 mg/day in weekly intervals until a dose of 3.0 mg/day is achieved.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Liraglutide (Saxenda) 6Mg/Ml Inj Pen 3Ml</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>subcutaneous injection, pre-filled, multi-dose pen that delivers doses of 0.6 mg, 1.2 mg, 1.8 mg, 2.4 mg, or 3 mg (6 mg/mL, 3 mL). It is designed to be identical to the pen used for liraglutide (Saxenda). Placebo product inactive ingredients: disodium phosphate dihydrate, 1.42 mg; propylene glycol, 14 mg; phenol, 5.5 mg; and water for injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. BMI &gt; 30 kg/m2 or BMI ≥ 27 - 29.9 kg/m² in the presence of at least one weight-related
             comorbid condition, such as binge eating disorder, hypertension, or dyslipidemia.
             There is no upper BMI limit for this trial.

          2. Age ≥ 21 years and ≤ 70 years

          3. Meet full DSM 5 criteria for BED

               1. Recurrent episodes of binge eating characterized by both consuming an abnormally
                  large amount of food in a short period of time compared with what others might
                  eat in the same amount of time under the same or similar circumstances and
                  experiencing a loss of control over eating during the episode.

               2. These episodes feature at least 3 of the following:

             i. consuming food more rapidly than normal; ii. eating until uncomfortably full; iii.
             consuming large amounts of food when not hungry; iv. consuming food alone due to
             embarrassment; v. feeling disgusted, depressed, or guilty after eating a large amount
             of food. c. Significant distress about the binge episodes is present. d. Binge
             episodes must occur, on average, at least once per week for 3 months.

          4. All races and ethnicities are included

          5. Eligible female subjects will be:

               -  non-pregnant, evidenced by a negative urine dipstick pregnancy test

               -  non-lactating

               -  surgically sterile or postmenopausal, or they will agree to continue to use an
                  accepted method of birth control during the study

          6. Ability to provide informed consent before any trial-related activities

          7. Subjects must:

               -  have a primary care provider (PCP) who is responsible for providing routine care

               -  have reliable telephone or Internet service to communicate with study staff

               -  understand and be willing to comply with all study-related procedures and agree
                  to participate in the study by giving written informed consent

               -  plan to remain in the Philadelphia area for the next 6 months or more

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or nursing, or plans to become pregnant in the next 6 months, or not using
             adequate contraceptive measures

          2. Personal or family history of medullary thyroid cancer or multiple endocrine neoplasia
             syndrome type 2

          3. Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic blood pressure ≥ 160 mm Hg or diastolic blood
             pressure ≥ 100 mm Hg)

          4. Type 1 diabetes

          5. Type 2 diabetes

          6. A combination of fasting glucose ≥ 126 mg/dl, combined with an HbA1c &gt;6.5, will be
             used to indicate the presence of diabetes, an exclusion criterion

          7. Recent history of cardiovascular disease (e.g., myocardial infarction or stroke within
             the past 6 months), congestive heart failure, or heart block greater than first degree

          8. Clinically significant hepatic or renal disease

          9. Thyroid disease, not controlled

         10. History of malignancy (except for non-melanoma skin cancer) in past 5 years

         11. The presence of current anorexia nervosa or bulimia nervosa

         12. Current major depressive episode, active suicidal ideation, or lifetime history of
             suicide attempts. We will exclude participants who have a Patient Health
             Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) [31] score &gt; 15, or a score of &gt; 1 on the suicidal ideation
             item, as well as any risk of suicidality as measured by a score of 4 or 5 on the
             Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)[32].

         13. Psychiatric hospitalization within the past 6 months

         14. Self-reported alcohol or substance abuse within the past 12 months, including at-risk
             drinking (current consumption of ≥ 14 alcoholic drinks per week)

         15. Diagnosis of bipolar disorder or current or past psychosis

         16. Use in past 3 months of medications known to treat BED (such as lisdexamfetamine),
             induce significant weight loss (i.e., prescription weight loss medications), or induce
             weight gain (e.g., chronic use of oral steroids, second generation antipsychotics)

         17. Currently receiving behavioral or pharmacological treatment for BED

         18. Loss of ≥ 10 lb of body weight within the past 3 months

         19. Known or suspected allergy to trial medication(s), excipients, or related products

         20. Hypersensitivity to liraglutide or any product components

         21. The receipt of any investigational drug within 6 months prior to this trial

         22. Previous participation in this trial (e.g., randomized and failed to participate)

         23. History of pancreatitis

         24. History of gastrointestinal surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Madelyn R Ruggieri, MS</last_name>
    <phone>215-573-5502</phone>
    <email>mrugg@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kelly C Allison, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>215-898-2823</phone>
    <email>kca@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennyslvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19140</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kelly C Allison, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>215-898-2823</phone>
      <email>kca@mail.med.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Madelyn Ruggieri, MS</last_name>
      <phone>215-573-5502</phone>
      <email>mrugg@mail.med.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kelly C Allison, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas A Wadden, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Berkowitz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 12, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kelly Allison</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>eating disorder, pharmacotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Feeding and Eating Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bulimia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Binge-Eating Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liraglutide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan to make individual participant data available to other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

