<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02737579</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3879</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Internal Bridge Funding</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02737579</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>XFM: (X-ray Fused With MRI) Guided Cardiac Catheterization</brief_title>
  <official_title>XFM: (X-ray Fused With MRI) Guided Cardiac Catheterization</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Joshua Kanter</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the use of x-ray fused with MR images as an imaging tool to help
      guide catheter tools during diagnostic and therapeutic cardiac catheterization procedures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cardiovascular interventional procedures are currently conducted under the guidance of X-ray
      fluoroscopy. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) can provide increased soft tissue information
      about the cardiovascular system. By combining the familiar X-ray environment with superior
      magnetic resonance imaging, the investigator hopes to enhance and expand the capabilities of
      cardiac catheterization techniques.

      The investigator will conduct cardiac catheterization procedures using XFM guidance in
      pediatric research patients who are undergoing medically necessary procedures. The
      investigator aims to decrease the exposure of these patients to the routine hazards of
      ionizing radiation and contrast exposure compared to the standard of care approach.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiation exposure measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of each catheterization procedure through study completion,up to 8 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Comparisons with data from historical controls undergoing matched invasive cardiology procedures at Children's National Medical Center</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fluoroscopy time measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of each catheterization procedure through study completion,up to 8 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Comparisons with data from historical controls undergoing matched procedures at Children's National Medical Center</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Contrast volume measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of each catheterization procedure through study completion, up to 8 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Comparisons with data from historical controls undergoing matched invasive cardiology procedures at Children's National Medical Center will be examined.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedure time measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of each catheterization procedure through study completion,up to 8 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Comparisons with data from historical controls undergoing matched procedures at Children's National Medical Center</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Congenital Heart Defect</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>XFM guidance</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>X-ray fused cardiac MRI images used for guidance tool to perform cardiac catheterization procedure</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>XFM guidance</intervention_name>
    <description>X-ray images and MRI roadmaps are aligned, during the medically indicated catheterization procedure, both conventional X-ray and investigational XFM images are displayed side-by-side. The operator may choose to be guided by either.</description>
    <arm_group_label>XFM guidance</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Children and adults of any age

          2. Undergoing clinically-indicated cardiovascular catheterization

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Cardiovascular instability precluding baseline medially-necesary MRI

          2. Women who are pregnant

          3. Women who are nursing and who do not plan to discard breast milk for 24 hours

          4. All patients who are medically judged to have contraindication(s) to MRI scanning.
             Contraindications include implanted metal devices which are contraindicated for MRI
             scanning
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joshua Kanter, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's National Hospital System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joshua Kanter, MD</last_name>
    <phone>202-476-2020</phone>
    <email>jkanter@childrensnational.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laura Olivieri, MD</last_name>
    <phone>202-476-2020</phone>
    <email>lolivieri@childrensnational.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's National Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joshua Kanter, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Russell Cross, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laura Olivieri, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Silva R, Gutiérrez LF, Raval AN, McVeigh ER, Ozturk C, Lederman RJ. X-ray fused with magnetic resonance imaging (XFM) to target endomyocardial injections: validation in a swine model of myocardial infarction. Circulation. 2006 Nov 28;114(22):2342-50. Epub 2006 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>17101858</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gutiérrez LF, Silva Rd, Ozturk C, Sonmez M, Stine AM, Raval AN, Raman VK, Sachdev V, Aviles RJ, Waclawiw MA, McVeigh ER, Lederman RJ. Technology preview: X-ray fused with magnetic resonance during invasive cardiovascular procedures. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2007 Nov 15;70(6):773-82.</citation>
    <PMID>18022851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Faranesh AZ, Kellman P, Ratnayaka K, Lederman RJ. Integration of cardiac and respiratory motion into MRI roadmaps fused with x-ray. Med Phys. 2013 Mar;40(3):032302. doi: 10.1118/1.4789919.</citation>
    <PMID>23464334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>George AK, Sonmez M, Lederman RJ, Faranesh AZ. Robust automatic rigid registration of MRI and X-ray using external fiducial markers for XFM-guided interventional procedures. Med Phys. 2011 Jan;38(1):125-41.</citation>
    <PMID>21361182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gutiérrez LF, Ozturk C, McVeigh ER, Lederman RJ. A practical global distortion correction method for an image intensifier based x-ray fluoroscopy system. Med Phys. 2008 Mar;35(3):997-1007.</citation>
    <PMID>18404935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kleinerman RA. Cancer risks following diagnostic and therapeutic radiation exposure in children. Pediatr Radiol. 2006 Sep;36 Suppl 2:121-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16862418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andreassi MG, Ait-Ali L, Botto N, Manfredi S, Mottola G, Picano E. Cardiac catheterization and long-term chromosomal damage in children with congenital heart disease. Eur Heart J. 2006 Nov;27(22):2703-8. Epub 2006 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>16717079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beels L, Bacher K, De Wolf D, Werbrouck J, Thierens H. gamma-H2AX foci as a biomarker for patient X-ray exposure in pediatric cardiac catheterization: are we underestimating radiation risks? Circulation. 2009 Nov 10;120(19):1903-9. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.109.880385. Epub 2009 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>19858412</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwartz GJ, Haycock GB, Edelmann CM Jr, Spitzer A. A simple estimate of glomerular filtration rate in children derived from body length and plasma creatinine. Pediatrics. 1976 Aug;58(2):259-63.</citation>
    <PMID>951142</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kiringoda R, Thurm AE, Hirschtritt ME, Koziol D, Wesley R, Swedo SE, O'Grady NP, Quezado ZM. Risks of propofol sedation/anesthesia for imaging studies in pediatric research: eight years of experience in a clinical research center. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2010 Jun;164(6):554-60. doi: 10.1001/archpediatrics.2010.75.</citation>
    <PMID>20530306</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haustein J, Laniado M, Niendorf HP, Louton T, Beck W, Planitzer J, Schöffel M, Reiser M, Kaiser W, Schörner W, et al. Triple-dose versus standard-dose gadopentetate dimeglumine: a randomized study in 199 patients. Radiology. 1993 Mar;186(3):855-60.</citation>
    <PMID>8430199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niendorf HP, Alhassan A, Geens VR, Clauss W. Safety review of gadopentetate dimeglumine. Extended clinical experience after more than five million applications. Invest Radiol. 1994 Jun;29 Suppl 2:S179-82.</citation>
    <PMID>7928222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niendorf HP, Dinger JC, Haustein J, Cornelius I, Alhassan A, Clauss W. Tolerance data of Gd-DTPA: a review. Eur J Radiol. 1991 Jul-Aug;13(1):15-20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1889423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niendorf HP, Haustein J, Cornelius I, Alhassan A, Clauss W. Safety of gadolinium-DTPA: extended clinical experience. Magn Reson Med. 1991 Dec;22(2):222-8; discussion 229-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1812350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niendorf HP, Haustein J, Louton T, Beck W, Laniado M. Safety and tolerance after intravenous administration of 0.3 mmol/kg Gd-DTPA. Results of a randomized, controlled clinical trial. Invest Radiol. 1991 Nov;26 Suppl 1:S221-3; discussion S232-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1808134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dillman JR, Ellis JH, Cohan RH, Strouse PJ, Jan SC. Frequency and severity of acute allergic-like reactions to gadolinium-containing i.v. contrast media in children and adults. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2007 Dec;189(6):1533-8.</citation>
    <PMID>18029897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sundgren PC, Leander P. Is administration of gadolinium-based contrast media to pregnant women and small children justified? J Magn Reson Imaging. 2011 Oct;34(4):750-7. doi: 10.1002/jmri.22413. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21928308</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deo A, Fogel M, Cowper SE. Nephrogenic systemic fibrosis: a population study examining the relationship of disease development to gadolinium exposure. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2007 Mar;2(2):264-7. Epub 2007 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>17699423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joshua Kanter</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Joshua Kanter, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cardiac catheterization</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiac MRI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Defects, Congenital</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

