<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02739087</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3860</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Internal Bridge funding</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02739087</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Radiation-Free Heart Catheterization Using MRI</brief_title>
  <official_title>Radiation-Free Heart Catheterization Using MRI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Joshua Kanter</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Currently catheters used in heart catheterization procedures are guided throughout the heart
      chambers and blood vessels by pictures taken by x-rays. This technology exposes patients to
      radiation. With this study protocol the investigators will use MRI technology to take
      real-time pictures to navigate catheters throughout heart chambers. MRI uses electromagnetic
      energy; therefore, it does not expose participants to radiation energy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants undergo general anesthesia, and vascular access is obtained in the x-ray
      catheterization lab. Next the participant is transferred into the MRI scanner where a focused
      MRI examination is performed. Catheters are then guided into the heart chambers using
      real-time MRI guidance to perform conventional cardiac catheterization steps. If time allows,
      additional research MRI is performed before the participant is returned to the x-ray
      catheterization lab. If any MRI guided catheterization steps are unsuccessful, the clinically
      indicated step is performed after the participant returns to the x-ray catheterization lab
      using conventional x-ray guided pictures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Test the feasibility of navigating catheters into right heart structures using real-time MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of each catheterization procedure through study completion,up to 5 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Heart catheterization usually uses X-ray guidance. Using commercially available MRI-compatible catheters, the right heart catheterization procedure will be done using real-time magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). MRI guidance does not use X-ray radiation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants whose MRI cardiac catheterization procedure was prematurely terminated</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of each catheterization procedure through study completion,up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Premature termination will occur under the following circumstances:
Hemodynamic or other clinical instability
Technical failure of catheter procedure such as being unable to navigate the catheters to the heart chamber
Equipment malfunction
Any other circumstance that in the opinion of the Principal Investigator poses hazard to the research subject</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of radiation exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>End of study, 5 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of radiation exposure in this cohort of subjects to historical controls undergoing matched invasive cardiology procedure at CNMC.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Aortic Coarctation</condition>
  <condition>Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Septal Defect</condition>
  <condition>Aortic Stenosis</condition>
  <condition>Post Heart Transplant Catheter Procedure</condition>
  <condition>Patent Ductus Arteriosus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MRI guided cardiac catheterization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Magnetic resonance imaging will be used to guide cardiac catheterization procedures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI guided cardiac catheterization</intervention_name>
    <description>Magnetic resonance imaging will be used to guide cardiac catheterization procedures whenever possible to avoid or minimize x-ray radiation exposure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MRI guided cardiac catheterization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic resonance imaging</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MRI guided cardiac catheterization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Undergoing a medically necessary cardiovascular catheterization

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cardiovascular instability including hemodynamic instability (such as requiring
             significant vasoactive infusion support) or mechanical hemodynamic support.

          -  Women who are pregnant

          -  Women who are nursing and who do not plan to discard breast milk for 24 hours

          -  Patients with a contraindication to MRI scanning will be excluded. These
             contraindications include patients with the following devices:

               1. Central nervous system aneurysm clips

               2. Implanted neural stimulator

               3. Implanted cardiac pacemaker or defibrillator which are not MR safe or MR
                  conditional according to the manufacturer

               4. Cochlear implant

               5. Ocular foreign body (e.g. metal shavings)

               6. Implanted Insulin pump

               7. Metal shrapnel or bullet

        Exclusion criteria for Gadolinium (contrast agent)

        1. Renal disease with estimated glomerular filtration rate &lt; 30 ml/min/1.73 m2 body surface
        area
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joshua Kanter, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joshua Kanter, MD</last_name>
    <phone>202-476-2020</phone>
    <email>jkanter@childrensnational.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laura Olivieri, MD</last_name>
    <phone>202-476-2020</phone>
    <email>lolivieri@childrensnational.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's National Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joshua Kanter, MD</last_name>
      <phone>202-476-2020</phone>
      <email>jkanter@childrensnational.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laura Olivieri, MD</last_name>
      <phone>202-476-2020</phone>
      <email>lolivieri@childrensnational.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joshua Kanter, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Russell Cross, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laura Olivieri, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saikus CE, Lederman RJ. Interventional cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging: a new opportunity for image-guided interventions. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2009 Nov;2(11):1321-31. doi: 10.1016/j.jcmg.2009.09.002. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19909937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ratnayaka K, Faranesh AZ, Guttman MA, Kocaturk O, Saikus CE, Lederman RJ. Interventional cardiovascular magnetic resonance: still tantalizing. J Cardiovasc Magn Reson. 2008 Dec 29;10:62. doi: 10.1186/1532-429X-10-62. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19114017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guttman MA, Lederman RJ, Sorger JM, McVeigh ER. Real-time volume rendered MRI for interventional guidance. J Cardiovasc Magn Reson. 2002;4(4):431-42. Erratum in: J Cardiovasc Magn Reson. 2003;5(2):407.</citation>
    <PMID>12549231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guttman MA, Kellman P, Dick AJ, Lederman RJ, McVeigh ER. Real-time accelerated interactive MRI with adaptive TSENSE and UNFOLD. Magn Reson Med. 2003 Aug;50(2):315-21.</citation>
    <PMID>12876708</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peters DC, Lederman RJ, Dick AJ, Raman VK, Guttman MA, Derbyshire JA, McVeigh ER. Undersampled projection reconstruction for active catheter imaging with adaptable temporal resolution and catheter-only views. Magn Reson Med. 2003 Feb;49(2):216-22.</citation>
    <PMID>12541240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guttman MA, Dick AJ, Raman VK, Arai AE, Lederman RJ, McVeigh ER. Imaging of myocardial infarction for diagnosis and intervention using real-time interactive MRI without ECG-gating or breath-holding. Magn Reson Med. 2004 Aug;52(2):354-61.</citation>
    <PMID>15282818</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peters DC, Guttman MA, Dick AJ, Raman VK, Lederman RJ, McVeigh ER. Reduced field of view and undersampled PR combined for interventional imaging of a fully dynamic field of view. Magn Reson Med. 2004 Apr;51(4):761-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15065249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Silva R, Gutiérrez LF, Raval AN, McVeigh ER, Ozturk C, Lederman RJ. X-ray fused with magnetic resonance imaging (XFM) to target endomyocardial injections: validation in a swine model of myocardial infarction. Circulation. 2006 Nov 28;114(22):2342-50. Epub 2006 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>17101858</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guttman MA, Ozturk C, Raval AN, Raman VK, Dick AJ, DeSilva R, Karmarkar P, Lederman RJ, McVeigh ER. Interventional cardiovascular procedures guided by real-time MR imaging: an interactive interface using multiple slices, adaptive projection modes and live 3D renderings. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2007 Dec;26(6):1429-35.</citation>
    <PMID>17968897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kocaturk O, Kim AH, Saikus CE, Guttman MA, Faranesh AZ, Ozturk C, Lederman RJ. Active two-channel 0.035'' guidewire for interventional cardiovascular MRI. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2009 Aug;30(2):461-5. doi: 10.1002/jmri.21844.</citation>
    <PMID>19629968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kocaturk O, Saikus CE, Guttman MA, Faranesh AZ, Ratnayaka K, Ozturk C, McVeigh ER, Lederman RJ. Whole shaft visibility and mechanical performance for active MR catheters using copper-nitinol braided polymer tubes. J Cardiovasc Magn Reson. 2009 Aug 12;11:29. doi: 10.1186/1532-429X-11-29.</citation>
    <PMID>19674464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>George AK, Derbyshire JA, Saybasili H, Saikus CE, Kocaturk O, Guttman MA, McVeigh ER, Lederman RJ, Faranesh AZ. Visualization of active devices and automatic slice repositioning (&quot;SnapTo&quot;) for MRI-guided interventions. Magn Reson Med. 2010 Apr;63(4):1070-9. doi: 10.1002/mrm.22307.</citation>
    <PMID>20373408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saybasili H, Derbyshire JA, Kellman P, Griswold MA, Ozturk C, Lederman RJ, Seiberlich N. RT-GROG: parallelized self-calibrating GROG for real-time MRI. Magn Reson Med. 2010 Jul;64(1):306-12. doi: 10.1002/mrm.22351.</citation>
    <PMID>20577983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Derbyshire JA, Herzka DA, McVeigh ER, Lederman RJ. Efficient implementation of hardware-optimized gradient sequences for real-time imaging. Magn Reson Med. 2010 Dec;64(6):1814-20. doi: 10.1002/mrm.22211.</citation>
    <PMID>20878764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sampath S, Raval AN, Lederman RJ, McVeigh ER. High-resolution 3D arteriography of chronic total peripheral occlusions using a T1-W turbo spin-echo sequence with inner-volume imaging. Magn Reson Med. 2007 Jan;57(1):40-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17152076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guttman MA, Raval AN, Lederman RJ, McVeigh ER. Real-time catheter-directed MRA with effective background suppression and persistent rendering. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2008 Aug;28(2):538-42. doi: 10.1002/jmri.21409.</citation>
    <PMID>18666149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lederman RJ, Guttman MA, Peters DC, Thompson RB, Sorger JM, Dick AJ, Raman VK, McVeigh ER. Catheter-based endomyocardial injection with real-time magnetic resonance imaging. Circulation. 2002 Mar 19;105(11):1282-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11901036</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dick AJ, Guttman MA, Raman VK, Peters DC, Pessanha BS, Hill JM, Smith S, Scott G, McVeigh ER, Lederman RJ. Magnetic resonance fluoroscopy allows targeted delivery of mesenchymal stem cells to infarct borders in Swine. Circulation. 2003 Dec 9;108(23):2899-904. Epub 2003 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>14656911</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arepally A, Karmarkar PV, Weiss C, Rodriguez ER, Lederman RJ, Atalar E. Magnetic resonance image-guided trans-septal puncture in a swine heart. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2005 Apr;21(4):463-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15779027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raman VK, Karmarkar PV, Guttman MA, Dick AJ, Peters DC, Ozturk C, Pessanha BS, Thompson RB, Raval AN, DeSilva R, Aviles RJ, Atalar E, McVeigh ER, Lederman RJ. Real-time magnetic resonance-guided endovascular repair of experimental abdominal aortic aneurysm in swine. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2005 Jun 21;45(12):2069-77.</citation>
    <PMID>15963411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raval AN, Telep JD, Guttman MA, Ozturk C, Jones M, Thompson RB, Wright VJ, Schenke WH, DeSilva R, Aviles RJ, Raman VK, Slack MC, Lederman RJ. Real-time magnetic resonance imaging-guided stenting of aortic coarctation with commercially available catheter devices in Swine. Circulation. 2005 Aug 2;112(5):699-706. Epub 2005 Jul 25.</citation>
    <PMID>16043639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raval AN, Karmarkar PV, Guttman MA, Ozturk C, Sampath S, DeSilva R, Aviles RJ, Xu M, Wright VJ, Schenke WH, Kocaturk O, Dick AJ, Raman VK, Atalar E, McVeigh ER, Lederman RJ. Real-time magnetic resonance imaging-guided endovascular recanalization of chronic total arterial occlusion in a swine model. Circulation. 2006 Feb 28;113(8):1101-7. Epub 2006 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>16490819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raval AN, Karmarkar PV, Guttman MA, Ozturk C, Desilva R, Aviles RJ, Wright VJ, Schenke WH, Atalar E, McVeigh ER, Lederman RJ. Real-time MRI guided atrial septal puncture and balloon septostomy in swine. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2006 Apr;67(4):637-43.</citation>
    <PMID>16532499</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elagha AA, Kocaturk O, Guttman MA, Ozturk C, Kim AH, Burton GW, Kim JH, Raman VK, Raval AN, Wright VJ, Schenke WH, McVeigh ER, Lederman RJ. Real-time MR imaging-guided laser atrial septal puncture in swine. J Vasc Interv Radiol. 2008 Sep;19(9):1347-53. doi: 10.1016/j.jvir.2008.05.007. Epub 2008 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>18725098</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dick AJ, Raman VK, Raval AN, Guttman MA, Thompson RB, Ozturk C, Peters DC, Stine AM, Wright VJ, Schenke WH, Lederman RJ. Invasive human magnetic resonance imaging: feasibility during revascularization in a combined XMR suite. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2005 Mar;64(3):265-74.</citation>
    <PMID>15736247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ratnayaka K, Faranesh AZ, Hansen MS, Stine AM, Halabi M, Barbash IM, Schenke WH, Wright VJ, Grant LP, Kellman P, Kocaturk O, Lederman RJ. Real-time MRI-guided right heart catheterization in adults using passive catheters. Eur Heart J. 2013 Feb;34(5):380-9. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehs189. Epub 2012 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>22855740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kleinerman RA. Cancer risks following diagnostic and therapeutic radiation exposure in children. Pediatr Radiol. 2006 Sep;36 Suppl 2:121-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16862418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andreassi MG, Ait-Ali L, Botto N, Manfredi S, Mottola G, Picano E. Cardiac catheterization and long-term chromosomal damage in children with congenital heart disease. Eur Heart J. 2006 Nov;27(22):2703-8. Epub 2006 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>16717079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niendorf HP, Dinger JC, Haustein J, Cornelius I, Alhassan A, Clauss W. Tolerance data of Gd-DTPA: a review. Eur J Radiol. 1991 Jul-Aug;13(1):15-20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1889423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niendorf HP, Haustein J, Cornelius I, Alhassan A, Clauss W. Safety of gadolinium-DTPA: extended clinical experience. Magn Reson Med. 1991 Dec;22(2):222-8; discussion 229-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1812350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niendorf HP, Haustein J, Louton T, Beck W, Laniado M. Safety and tolerance after intravenous administration of 0.3 mmol/kg Gd-DTPA. Results of a randomized, controlled clinical trial. Invest Radiol. 1991 Nov;26 Suppl 1:S221-3; discussion S232-5.</citation>
    <PMID>1808134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kiringoda R, Thurm AE, Hirschtritt ME, Koziol D, Wesley R, Swedo SE, O'Grady NP, Quezado ZM. Risks of propofol sedation/anesthesia for imaging studies in pediatric research: eight years of experience in a clinical research center. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2010 Jun;164(6):554-60. doi: 10.1001/archpediatrics.2010.75.</citation>
    <PMID>20530306</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwartz GJ, Haycock GB, Edelmann CM Jr, Spitzer A. A simple estimate of glomerular filtration rate in children derived from body length and plasma creatinine. Pediatrics. 1976 Aug;58(2):259-63.</citation>
    <PMID>951142</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beels L, Bacher K, De Wolf D, Werbrouck J, Thierens H. gamma-H2AX foci as a biomarker for patient X-ray exposure in pediatric cardiac catheterization: are we underestimating radiation risks? Circulation. 2009 Nov 10;120(19):1903-9. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.109.880385. Epub 2009 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>19858412</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haustein J, Laniado M, Niendorf HP, Louton T, Beck W, Planitzer J, Schöffel M, Reiser M, Kaiser W, Schörner W, et al. Triple-dose versus standard-dose gadopentetate dimeglumine: a randomized study in 199 patients. Radiology. 1993 Mar;186(3):855-60.</citation>
    <PMID>8430199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niendorf HP, Alhassan A, Geens VR, Clauss W. Safety review of gadopentetate dimeglumine. Extended clinical experience after more than five million applications. Invest Radiol. 1994 Jun;29 Suppl 2:S179-82.</citation>
    <PMID>7928222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dillman JR, Ellis JH, Cohan RH, Strouse PJ, Jan SC. Frequency and severity of acute allergic-like reactions to gadolinium-containing i.v. contrast media in children and adults. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2007 Dec;189(6):1533-8.</citation>
    <PMID>18029897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sundgren PC, Leander P. Is administration of gadolinium-based contrast media to pregnant women and small children justified? J Magn Reson Imaging. 2011 Oct;34(4):750-7. doi: 10.1002/jmri.22413. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21928308</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deo A, Fogel M, Cowper SE. Nephrogenic systemic fibrosis: a population study examining the relationship of disease development to gadolinium exposure. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2007 Mar;2(2):264-7. Epub 2007 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>17699423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tello R, Mitchell PJ, Melhem ER, Witte D, Thomson KR. Interventional catheter magnetic resonance angiography with a conventional 1.5-T magnet: work in progress. Australas Radiol. 1999 Nov;43(4):435-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10901954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paetzel C, Zorger N, Seitz J, Völk M, Nitz WR, Herold T, Feuerbach S, Lenhart M. Intraarterial contrast material-enhanced magnetic resonance angiography of the aortoiliac system. J Vasc Interv Radiol. 2004 Sep;15(9):981-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15361566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paetzel C, Zorger N, Völk M, Herold T, Seitz J, Nitz WR, Feuerbach S, Hamer O, Lenhart M. Intra-arterial magnetic resonance angiography of the iliac arteries: clinical experience using two different protocols. Acta Radiol. 2005 May;46(3):250-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15981721</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schulte AC, Bongartz G, Huegli R, Aschwanden M, Jaeger KA, Ostheim-Dzerowycz W, Jacob AL, Bilecen D. Intraarterial versus IV gadolinium injections for MR angiography: quantitative and qualitative assessment of the infrainguinal arteries. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2005 Sep;185(3):735-40.</citation>
    <PMID>16120927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bozlar U, Norton PT, Turba UC, Hagspiel KD. Novel technique for evaluating complex pelvic arteriovenous malformations with catheter-directed subtracted MR angiography. J Vasc Interv Radiol. 2007 Jul;18(7):920-3.</citation>
    <PMID>17609455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmitt B, Steendijk P, Lunze K, Ovroutski S, Falkenberg J, Rahmanzadeh P, Maarouf N, Ewert P, Berger F, Kuehne T. Integrated assessment of diastolic and systolic ventricular function using diagnostic cardiac magnetic resonance catheterization: validation in pigs and application in a clinical pilot study. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2009 Nov;2(11):1271-81. doi: 10.1016/j.jcmg.2009.09.007.</citation>
    <PMID>19909930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larose E, Yeghiazarians Y, Libby P, Yucel EK, Aikawa M, Kacher DF, Aikawa E, Kinlay S, Schoen FJ, Selwyn AP, Ganz P. Characterization of human atherosclerotic plaques by intravascular magnetic resonance imaging. Circulation. 2005 Oct 11;112(15):2324-31. Epub 2005 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>16203910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Razavi R, Hill DL, Keevil SF, Miquel ME, Muthurangu V, Hegde S, Rhode K, Barnett M, van Vaals J, Hawkes DJ, Baker E. Cardiac catheterisation guided by MRI in children and adults with congenital heart disease. Lancet. 2003 Dec 6;362(9399):1877-82.</citation>
    <PMID>14667742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miquel ME, Hegde S, Muthurangu V, Corcoran BJ, Keevil SF, Hill DL, Razavi RS. Visualization and tracking of an inflatable balloon catheter using SSFP in a flow phantom and in the heart and great vessels of patients. Magn Reson Med. 2004 May;51(5):988-95.</citation>
    <PMID>15122681</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muthurangu V, Taylor A, Andriantsimiavona R, Hegde S, Miquel ME, Tulloh R, Baker E, Hill DL, Razavi RS. Novel method of quantifying pulmonary vascular resistance by use of simultaneous invasive pressure monitoring and phase-contrast magnetic resonance flow. Circulation. 2004 Aug 17;110(7):826-34. Epub 2004 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>15302793</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuehne T, Yilmaz S, Steendijk P, Moore P, Groenink M, Saaed M, Weber O, Higgins CB, Ewert P, Fleck E, Nagel E, Schulze-Neick I, Lange P. Magnetic resonance imaging analysis of right ventricular pressure-volume loops: in vivo validation and clinical application in patients with pulmonary hypertension. Circulation. 2004 Oct 5;110(14):2010-6. Epub 2004 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>15451801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuehne T, Yilmaz S, Schulze-Neick I, Wellnhofer E, Ewert P, Nagel E, Lange P. Magnetic resonance imaging guided catheterisation for assessment of pulmonary vascular resistance: in vivo validation and clinical application in patients with pulmonary hypertension. Heart. 2005 Aug;91(8):1064-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16020598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paetzel C, Zorger N, Bachthaler M, Hamer OW, Stehr A, Feuerbach S, Lenhart M, Völk M, Herold T, Kasprzak P, Nitz WR. Magnetic resonance-guided percutaneous angioplasty of femoral and popliteal artery stenoses using real-time imaging and intra-arterial contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance angiography. Invest Radiol. 2005 May;40(5):257-62.</citation>
    <PMID>15829822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kee ST, Ganguly A, Daniel BL, Wen Z, Butts K, Shimikawa A, Pelc NJ, Fahrig R, Dake MD. MR-guided transjugular intrahepatic portosystemic shunt creation with use of a hybrid radiography/MR system. J Vasc Interv Radiol. 2005 Feb;16(2 Pt 1):227-34.</citation>
    <PMID>15713923</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krueger JJ, Ewert P, Yilmaz S, Gelernter D, Peters B, Pietzner K, Bornstedt A, Schnackenburg B, Abdul-Khaliq H, Fleck E, Nagel E, Berger F, Kuehne T. Magnetic resonance imaging-guided balloon angioplasty of coarctation of the aorta: a pilot study. Circulation. 2006 Feb 28;113(8):1093-100. Epub 2006 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>16490822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muthurangu V, Atkinson D, Sermesant M, Miquel ME, Hegde S, Johnson R, Andriantsimiavona R, Taylor AM, Baker E, Tulloh R, Hill D, Razavi RS. Measurement of total pulmonary arterial compliance using invasive pressure monitoring and MR flow quantification during MR-guided cardiac catheterization. Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol. 2005 Sep;289(3):H1301-6. Epub 2005 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>15879483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huegli RW, Aschwanden M, Kos S, Rasmus M, Jaeger K, Jacob AL, Bilecen D. Diagnostic pitfalls in postinterventional intraarterial magnetic resonance angiography after recanalization of femoropopliteal arterial occlusions. Acta Radiol. 2008 Dec;49(10):1129-36. doi: 10.1080/02841850802508942.</citation>
    <PMID>19031180</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tzifa A, Krombach GA, Krämer N, Krüger S, Schütte A, von Walter M, Schaeffter T, Qureshi S, Krasemann T, Rosenthal E, Schwartz CA, Varma G, Buhl A, Kohlmeier A, Bücker A, Günther RW, Razavi R. Magnetic resonance-guided cardiac interventions using magnetic resonance-compatible devices: a preclinical study and first-in-man congenital interventions. Circ Cardiovasc Interv. 2010 Dec;3(6):585-92. doi: 10.1161/CIRCINTERVENTIONS.110.957209. Epub 2010 Nov 23.</citation>
    <PMID>21098745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sommer P, Grothoff M, Eitel C, Gaspar T, Piorkowski C, Gutberlet M, Hindricks G. Feasibility of real-time magnetic resonance imaging-guided electrophysiology studies in humans. Europace. 2013 Jan;15(1):101-8. doi: 10.1093/europace/eus230. Epub 2012 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>22849974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nordbeck P, Beer M, Köstler H, Ladd ME, Quick HH, Bauer WR, Ritter O. Cardiac catheter ablation under real-time magnetic resonance guidance. Eur Heart J. 2012 Aug;33(15):1977. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehs139. Epub 2012 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22677138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nazarian S, Kolandaivelu A, Zviman MM, Meininger GR, Kato R, Susil RC, Roguin A, Dickfeld TL, Ashikaga H, Calkins H, Berger RD, Bluemke DA, Lardo AC, Halperin HR. Feasibility of real-time magnetic resonance imaging for catheter guidance in electrophysiology studies. Circulation. 2008 Jul 15;118(3):223-9. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.742452. Epub 2008 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>18574048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Manke C, Nitz WR, Djavidani B, Strotzer M, Lenhart M, Völk M, Feuerbach S, Link J. MR imaging-guided stent placement in iliac arterial stenoses: a feasibility study. Radiology. 2001 May;219(2):527-34.</citation>
    <PMID>11323483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hofmann LV, Liddell RP, Eng J, Wasserman BA, Arepally A, Lee DS, Bluemke DA. Human peripheral arteries: feasibility of transvenous intravascular MR imaging of the arterial wall. Radiology. 2005 May;235(2):617-22.</citation>
    <PMID>15858101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Araki T, Aoki S, Ishigame K, Kumagai H, Nanbu A, Hori M, Ueki J, Komiyama T, Araki T. MR-guided intravascular catheter manipulation: feasibility of both active and passive tracking in experimental study and initial clinical applications. Radiat Med. 2002 Jan-Feb;20(1):1-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12002598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joshua Kanter</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>radiation free cardiac catheterization</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Valve Stenosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ductus Arteriosus, Patent</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Septal Defects</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Coarctation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Septal Defects, Atrial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

