<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02739555</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P140909</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-001698-41</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02739555</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zoledronic Acid Compared to Percutaneous Treatment in Osteoid Osteoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>BISPHOO</acronym>
  <official_title>Non-inferiority Trial of Three Cycles of Zoledronic Acid Versus Percutaneous Thermal Ablation in Osteoid Osteoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Osteoid osteoma (OO) is a benign osteogenic tumor occurring in children and young adults,
      responsible for intense bone pain, which has a tendency to spontaneously heal with
      mineralization of the nidus, but extremely slowly. This healing may be accelerated in
      patients taking NSAIDs regularly during a few years. The long delay for healing and intense
      pain, explain why patients are quickly directed to surgeons or specialized radiology
      departments for tumor ablation. But percutaneous treatment or surgical excision destruction
      can expose the patient to a substantial risk in terms of neurologic or joint damages,
      depending on the location. Bisphosphonates treatment may be an effective alternative to
      percutaneous treatment by accelerating the natural history of OO.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Osteoid osteomas (OOs) are small, benign but painful bone tumors, mainly observed in children
      and young adults. Pain, almost universal, is characteristically greater at night. Pain is
      well relieved by NSAIDs but resolution is not always complete and pain reappears a few hours
      after the last dose. Also long-term consumption of NSAID can lead to serious adverse events.
      Therefore OOs are usually cured shortly after diagnosis, mainly by means of percutaneous
      treatment (PT) under computed tomography (CT) (radiofrequency coagulation or interstitial
      laser ablation).

      The clinical success rate using these techniques is 96% at 6-month, 94% at 24-month. However,
      the technique is not distributed everywhere since it is performed by highly specialized
      interventional radiologists. The PT is performed under general, spinal or regional
      anesthesia. General anesthesia is used in most cases, especially in children. When the OO is
      located in close proximity to the skin, cartilage, vessels and nerves, severe complications
      may occur and additional procedures such as infusion of saline or injection of CO2 at the
      interface between the OO and the vulnerable structure are done. Also few anatomic locations
      are not accessible to a PT.

      The natural history of OOs remains poorly understood. However investigators in small series
      of conservatively treated OOs suggested a spontaneous healing of the lesion with
      mineralization of the nidus and resolution of pain (mean duration of pain in patients with
      NSAID treatment: 33 months NSAID).

      The efficacy of bisphosphonates on pain related to benign (Langherhans cell histiocytosis,
      fibrous dysplasia, Paget disease) or malignant bone lesions has been widely reported. The
      investigators observed such efficacy in a small series of 20 patients with percutaneously
      hard-to-reach or recurrent OO using one to three infusions of zoledronate. The clinical
      efficacy assessed on pain relief was accompanied by a significantly increased mineralization
      of the nidus. The investigators postulated that bisphosphonates had accelerated the natural
      history of OO.

      Our hypothesis is that three infusions of zoledronate (4mg) repeated monthly in patients with
      symptomatic OO is non-inferior to percutaneous treatment on the efficacy, measured by pain
      relief at Visual Analogical Scale (VAS).

      The main objective of this randomized study is to demonstrate that in patients with OO,
      treatment with three intravenous cycles of 4mg of zoledronic acid administered monthly, is
      non-inferior to treatment with percutaneous thermal ablation on the efficacy measured by the
      percentage of pain relief between baseline and end of treatment.

      NB: Patients for whom the OO would not be percutaneously accessible (that is to say when the
      percutaneous treatment or surgical excision destruction expose the patient to a substantial
      risk in terms of neurologic or joint damages) will be offered to participate in a cohort,
      only in Lariboisière and Cochin hospital in Paris. In the cohort, the clinical follow-up will
      be conducted as it is currently proposed in Laribosisière hospital (no act added by the
      research). Objectives of the register will be explained to the patient. It consists in
      collecting anonymized medical data after a bisphosphonate treatment to statuate on the
      efficacy of the bisphosphonates to relieve pain due to osteoid osteoma.

      Study design of the randomized study:

        -  Selection / Inclusion visit: verification of eligibility, randomization and recollection
           of patient consent.

        -  Intervention:

             -  percutaneous thermal ablation at V1 visit (i.e. maximum one month after the
                selection / inclusion visit)

             -  or three zoledronic acid infusions at V1, V2 (one month after v1) and V3 visits
                (one month after V2)

        -  V4 visit at 4 months (end of treatment, evaluation of the main outcome) and V7 visit at
           16 months (end of study, evaluation of the secondary outcomes).

        -  Option: One to 3 additional visits (V4, V5 and V6) for zoledronic acid infusion can be
           proposed to the patient, depending on the efficacy of the previous infusion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 23, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 23, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of decrease in bone pain measured on a visual analog scale (VAS) between baseline and the end of treatment larger or equal to 70%.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of decrease in bone pain measured on a visual analog scale (VAS) between baseline and the end of treatment larger or equal to 70%. End of treatment is set at one month after the third administration of bisphosphonates and three months after the percutaneous thermal destruction (ie 4 months after inclusion visit = V4 visit, for both groups).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1, 2, 3, 7, 10 and 16 months</time_frame>
    <description>arm1 : only at 16 months
arm 2 : assessed by Visual Analog Scale as an average over the past 48 hours, at V1 (1 month +/- 5 days), V2 (2 months +/- 5 days), V3 (3 months +/- 5 days), V7 visits (16 months +/- 1 month) and, in case of additional infusions, at V5 (7 months +/- 15 days) and V6 (10 months +/- 15 days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient'Global Impression of change (PGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2, 3, 7, 10 and 16 months</time_frame>
    <description>arm1 : only at 16 months
arm 2 : assessed by Visual Analog Scale as an average over the past 48 hours, at V2 (2 months +/- 5 days), V3 (3 months +/- 5 days), V7 visits (16 months +/- 1 month) and, in case of additional infusions, at V5 (7 months +/- 15 days) and V6 (10 months +/- 15 days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Consumption of analgesic and NSAIDs</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 10 and 16 months</time_frame>
    <description>To this end, patient will be asked to note any analgesic and NSAIDs medication in a CRJ during the whole study arm1 : only at inclusion, 1, 4 and16 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nidus mineralization on CT scan images</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surface of bone marrow edema on MR images</measure>
    <time_frame>at 4 and 16 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events of bisphosphonates and percutaneous treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>at inclusion, 1, 2, 3, 4, 7, 10 and 16 months</time_frame>
    <description>Tolerance and adverse events of bisphosphonates and percutaneous treatment. To this end, patient will be asked to note any adverse event in a CRJ during the whole study.
arm1 : only at inclusion, 1, 4 and16 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoid Osteoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1: Percutaneous treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Percutaneous treatment of OO is a thermal tumor destruction by radiofrequency or laser photocoagulation performed under CT control with strict aseptic approach and most often under general anesthesia. The introductive needle is inserted toward the nidus. Then the optic fiber or the radiofrequency probe is inserted in the nidus center and thermal destruction of the tumor is obtained.When the distance between the nidus and a nerve or the skin is less than 10 mm, infusion of normal saline or CO2 is introduced as spacing agent. When the nidus is in the subchondral bone, cold normal saline is introduced in the joint to protect the cartilage. In addition, a thermocouple is placed in the epidural or foraminal space to continuously monitor the temperature. A procedure typically required between 1 and 2 h from the time the patient entered the CT unit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2: Bisphosphonate treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment consists of 3 infusions of zoledronic acid administered at a monthly interval. Bisphosphonate treatment is considered finished 1 month after the third bisphosphonate infusion (V4 visit). In few cases, the analgesic efficacy provided by 3 bisphosphonate infusions cannot be sufficient: 1 to 3 additional infusions could be proposed to the patient.
Zoledronic acid is supplied as a 4 mg/100 ml solution for infusion. It will be administered as infusion over 30 minutes under the supervision of a nurse. Adults will receive intravenous infusion of 4 mg of zoledronic acid. Children will receive infusion of 0.025 mg/kg of zoledronic acid.
The solution for infusion will be diluted in a specific volume of an injectable solution of sodium chloride 9 mg / ml (0.9%). The investigators propose abacus corresponding to zoledronic acid volume to sample and volume of sterile sodium chloride for dilution and infusion during 30 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thermal destruction with radiofrequency or laser</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>1: Percutaneous treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acide Zoledronique MEDAC</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>2: Bisphosphonate treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age superior or equal to 10 years

          -  Patient with a typical osteoid osteoma diagnosed on clinical and radiological criteria
             (MRI and scanner), validated by a binomial clinician / radiologist.

          -  OO never treated or in treatment failure, or recurrent OO.

          -  OO percutaneously accessible

          -  Pain intensity is superior or equal to 40 mm on a VAS at inclusion visit.

          -  Written informed consent signed by the patient or his representative (for minors,
             agreement of the child and signature of the two mandatory parents).

          -  Patient affiliated to the social security.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with other diseases or receiving treatment that may impact on bone tissue or
             its metabolism.

          -  Patients suffering from renal failure (i.e. lower than 60 ml/min according to the
             Cowcroft equation).

          -  Patients with severe hepatocellular insufficiency (TP&lt;50%).

          -  Patients with a history of iritis or uveitis.

          -  Patient with untreated rickets or osteomalacia.

          -  Patient with untreated dental infection or planed dental surgery during the study
             period.

          -  Patient with untreated infection of the external auditory canal (ex: furuncle, eczema
             superinfection)

          -  Patient already treated by bisphosphonates.

          -  Patients with hypersensitivity to the active substance, to other bisphosphonates or to
             any of the excipients (List of excipients: mannitol (E421), sodium citrate (E331),
             water for injections).

          -  Patient enrolled in another biomedical research protocol and during the whole study

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women, or planning pregnancy during the course of the study

          -  Women of child bearing potential (women following menarche and until post-menopause)
             and sexually active, without an effective contraceptive measure during the period of
             treatment (hormonal contraception or mechanical contraception)*

             * Oral contraceptive methods include:

          -  combined (oestrogen and progestogen containing) hormonal contraception associated with
             inhibition of ovulation (oral, intravagina or transdermal)

          -  progestogen-only hormonal contraception associated with inhibition of ovulation (oral,
             intravagina or transdermal).

               -  Mechanical methods of contraception include intrauterine device and intrauterine
                  hormone-releasing system.Patient enrolled in another biomedical research protocol
                  and during the whole study

        Patients who would not meet the inclusion criteria &quot;OO percutaneously accessible&quot; will be
        offered to participate in a register, only in Lariboisière hospital. This register will
        target specifically children aged of at least 12 years old and adults.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Valérie BOUSSON, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Valérie BOUSSON, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+331 4995 6180</phone>
    <email>valerie.bousson@aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital LARIBOSISIERE - Service radiologie ostéo-articulaire</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75010</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Valérie BOUSSON, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+331 4995 6180</phone>
      <email>valerie.bousson@aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 29, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteoid osteoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Bisphophonates</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoma, Osteoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Zoledronic acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diphosphonates</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

