<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02734472</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XJTU1AF-CRF-2015-006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02734472</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blood Pressure Follow-up Study in Two Chinese Cohorts(C-BPCS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>C-BPCS</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of the Interaction Between Environmental Factors and Genetic Predisposition on Long-term Blood Pressure in Chinese Population</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>First Affiliated Hospital Xi'an Jiaotong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>First Affiliated Hospital Xi'an Jiaotong University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Essential hypertension is a complex trait which results from interaction between
      environmental factors and genetic factors. The aim of this study is to investigate the
      effects of interaction between environmental factors and genetic factors on long-term blood
      pressure (BP) based on two established cohorts including &quot;the cohort of Hanzhong adolescent
      hypertension study&quot; and &quot;the cohort of Mei county adult salt-sensitive hypertension study&quot;.
      Firstly, the Hanzhong cohort-based follow-up study is designed to observe the track of BP
      during the whole life time, and to explore the effects of many risk factors (such as
      salt-sensitivity, obesity et al) on long-term BP and the occurrence of hypertension, and also
      to analyze the relationship of different polymorphisms of sodium and potassium
      metabolism-related gene with BP changes and target organ damages. In addition, by using DNA
      samples collected from subjects of &quot;Mei county adult salt-sensitive hypertension study&quot;in
      which all participants had completed a chronic salt loading and potassium intervention trial,
      we attempt to examine the single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) of sodium and potassium
      metabolism-related genes, as well as the relationship between these SNPs and BP responses to
      dietary sodium/potassium intervention, long-term BP change, the risk of hypertension and
      target organ damages were analyzed. This study would enable us to further explore the
      etiology of essential hypertension as well as to identify new genetic markers for predicting
      early hypertension and target organ damage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a longitudinal cohort follow-up study. The main contents
      include:(1)Questionnaire design: questionnaire is designed according to the research contents
      and purposes. The standard questionnaires will be used to collect the general information,
      dietary habits, lifestyle, medical history and family history etc.(2)Anthropometric
      measurements: blood pressure, height, body weight,waist and hip, pulse will be acquired by
      medical practitioners who received professional trainings based on World Health Organization
      (WHO) standards, and passed relevant examinations.(3) Blood and urine samples collection:
      morning fasting blood, nocturia, and 24-hour urine specimen will be collected by medical
      staffs, and blind tubes will be set up according to 5% of the total samples. Blood
      biochemistries including serum total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol, LDL cholesterol,
      triglycerides, fasting glucose, creatinine and hsCRP can be measured using automatic
      biochemical analyzer. The sodium and potassium concentrations in the urine will be measured
      by flame photometry. The total sodium and potassium excretions in urine in 24h were
      calculated by multiplying the concentration and 24-h volume of urine. (4) Auxiliary
      examinations: Auxiliary examinations including carotid intima-media thickness,
      endothelium-dependent vasodilation (FMD), measurements of brachial-ankle pulse wave velocity
      (baPWV) and electrocardiographic parameters. The measurement will be done in hospitals by
      medical practitioners who received professional trainings and passed relevant examinations.
      (5) Single nucleotide polymorphisms detection: based on our previous studies, sodium and
      potassium metabolism-related gene polymorphisms will be detected using MassARRAY technology.
      (6) Data processing and statistics: we should input the data to the database, and utilize
      softwares such as SPSS, STATA, Haploview and FBAT to analyze. (7) Quality control: ①
      Questionnaire is strictly designed and amended by epidemiologist and clinical experts. ② A
      standardized &quot;Investigator Handbook&quot; will be stipulated according to the guidelines. ③ Staff
      members are required to do a rigorous training and pass the exam. ④ The investigation process
      will be strictly supervised by the principal investigator. ⑤ Data entry use the parallel
      double entry method. ⑥ During laboratory testing, blank control and blind detection are
      applied to ensure the quality. ⑦ Data analysis is performed by 2-3 postgraduates,
      inconsistent data need to be double checked.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>blood pressure value(mmHg)</measure>
    <time_frame>First day of the three-day follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>The follow-up study of these two cohorts will last approximately 18 months (Jul 2016 to Dec 2017). During this period, each subject will receive a three-day follow-up examination. Three BP(mmHg) measurements will be obtained using a mercury sphygmomanometer on the first day of the three-day follow-up period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular hypertrophy（g/m^2）</measure>
    <time_frame>During the three-day follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>The follow-up study of these two cohorts will last approximately 18 months (Jul 2016 to Dec 2017). During this period, each subject will receive a three-day follow-up examination. Left ventricular mass index (LVMI,g/m^2）will be measured using echocardiography during the three-day follow-up period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increased arterial stiffness（mm/s）</measure>
    <time_frame>During the three-day follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>The follow-up study of these two cohorts will last approximately 18 months (Jul 2016 to Dec 2017).During this period, each subject will receive a three-day follow-up examination. Brachial-ankle pulse wave velocity（baPWV,mm/s）will be measured with Noninvasive automatic waveform analyzer during the three-day follow-up period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Carotid artery wall thickening（mm）</measure>
    <time_frame>During the three-day follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>The follow-up study of these two cohorts will last approximately 18 months (Jul 2016 to Dec 2017).During this period, each subject will receive a three-day follow-up examination. Carotid Intima media thickness (IMT,mm）will be measured using Color Doppler Ultrasound Diagnostic System during the three-day follow-up period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Microalbuminuria（mg/24h）</measure>
    <time_frame>Second day of the three-day follow-up period</time_frame>
    <description>The follow-up study of these two cohorts will last approximately 18 months (Jul 2016 to Dec 2017).During this period, each subject will receive a three-day follow-up examination. On the second day,24-hour urinary will be collected and the concentrations of microalbuminuria in the urine sample will be measured with Hitachi biochemical analyzer.The 24-h microalbuminuria（mg/24h）of each subject is calculated as the concentration of microalbuminuria multiplied by the 24-h urine volume of each individual.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5298</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hanzhong cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>A total of 4623 adolescents aged 6-15 years old in Hanzhong rural areas were recruited in 1987.During the follow-up period, the information about the incidence and risk factors of hypertension will be collected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mei county cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>A total of 675 individuals from 126 families were recruited in this family-based dietary intervention study. A community-based BP screening was conducted among adults aged 18-60 years in the study villages. The probands who had a mean systolic BP (SBP) between 130-160 mmHg and/or a diastolic BP (DBP) between 85-100 mmHg and no use of antihypertensive medications and their parents, siblings, spouses, and offspring were recruited in this study. During the follow-up period, the information about the incidence and risk factors of hypertension will be collected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Incidence and risk factors of hypertension</intervention_name>
    <description>During the follow-up period,General information(age, sex, BMI, blood pressure, the history of drink and smoke, medical history, etc).Blood biochemistry parameters（Lipid, hsCRP levels, etc）and other laboratory examination parameters(arterial stiffness,IMT, FMD) will be collected.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hanzhong cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mei county cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Meixian county adult salt-sensitive hypertension study is a family-based dietary
      interventional study. Whole blood specimen was collected from each participant who underwent
      a chronic salt load and potassium supplementation trial.Genomic DNA was extracted from whole
      blood specimen using the GOLDMAG Whole Blood Genomic DNA Purification Kit.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        In March and April, 1987, investigators established the cohort of Hanzhong Adolescent
        Hypertension Study. A total of 4,623 adolescents aged 6-15 years old in over 20 schools of
        three towns (Qili, Laojun and Shayan) in Hanzhong, Shaanxi, China were recruited.

        In 2003-2004, investigators established the cohort of Mei county adult salt sensitive
        hypertension Study. This study was a family-based dietary intervention study conducted in a
        Han Chinese population from rural areas of northern China. A total of 675 subjects from 126
        families were recruited in this cohort.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Hanzhong cohort of Adolescent Hypertension Study:

               -  adolescents aged 6-15 years old in over 20 schools of three towns (Qili, Laojun
                  and Shayan) in Hanzhong, Shaanxi, China.

          2. Mei county cohort of adult salt-sensitive hypertension study:

               -  Han individuals in rural northern China

               -  adults aged 18-60 years

               -  individuals who had a mean systolic BP (SBP) between 130-160 mmHg and/or a
                  diastolic BP (DBP) between 85-100 mmHg and no use of antihypertensive medications
                  were identified as the proband

               -  the probands'parents,siblings, spouses, and offspring were recruited for the
                  study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        During the follow-up period, the exclusion criteria are as follows:

          -  Secondary hypertension

          -  a history of severe cardiovascular disease

          -  chronic kidney disease or liver disease

          -  unable to complete the examination

          -  unable/refuse to sign the informed consent form
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jianjun Mu, doctor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>First Affiliated Hospital Xi'an Jiaotong University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jianjun Mu, doctor</last_name>
    <phone>0086-029-85323804</phone>
    <email>mujjun@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Chao Chu, master</last_name>
    <phone>0086-029-85323800</phone>
    <email>iaacd@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>First Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Xi'an</city>
        <state>Shaanxi</state>
        <zip>710061</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jianjun Mu, doctor</last_name>
      <phone>0086-029-85323804</phone>
      <email>mujjun@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Chao chu, master</last_name>
      <phone>0086-029-85323800</phone>
      <email>iaacd@163.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mu J, Zheng S, Lian Q, Liu F, Liu Z. Evolution of blood pressure from adolescents to youth in salt sensitivies: a 18-year follow-up study in Hanzhong children cohort. Nutr J. 2012 Sep 14;11:70. doi: 10.1186/1475-2891-11-70.</citation>
    <PMID>22978814</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Liu F, Zheng S, Mu J, Chu C, Wang L, Wang Y, Xiao H, Wang D, Cao Y, Ren K, Liu E, Yuan Z. Common variation in with no-lysine kinase 1 (WNK1) and blood pressure responses to dietary sodium or potassium interventions- family-based association study. Circ J. 2013;77(1):169-74. Epub 2012 Oct 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23059770</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 12, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>blood pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypertrophy, Left Ventricular</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular Stiffness</keyword>
  <keyword>Proteinuria</keyword>
  <keyword>Carotid Artery Diseases</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The achievements will be evaluated by papers published in specialized journals with a peer-reviewed system, and the original dates can be disclosed according to requirements.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

