<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02736890</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 14-2212</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02736890</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Injecting Botulinum Toxin A Underneath the Skin to Treat Spinal Cord Pain in Patients With Spinal Cord Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>Subcutaneous Injection of Botulinum Toxin A for At--Level Back Pain in Patients With Spinal Cord Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Back pain is a common secondary condition of both acute and chronic spinal cord injury (SCI).
      Current existing treatment including both pharmacologic and non-pharmacologic are limited by
      marginal efficacy or intolerable side effects. The purpose of this study is to evaluate the
      potential of subcutaneous injections of botulinum toxin A to provide pain relief in spinal
      cord injury patients with back pain near the level of injury in the spine. Botulinum toxin A
      has been shown in both pre-clinical and clinical studies to help with nerve pain. The
      researchers propose a double blinded placebo controlled crossover study to study the effects
      of subcutaneous botulinum injections to at--level SCI back pain in patients with spinal cord
      injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this study, there will be 2 procedure performed. The first procedure will be named P1 and
      consists of subcutaneous injection of either placebo or Botulinum Toxin A. The second
      procedure will be the cross-over procedure named P2. For the cross-over procedure, the
      subjects who had initially received Botulinum Toxin A will receive placebo and the subjects
      who had initially received placebo will receive Botulinum Toxin A. This is a Randomized
      Double-Blinded Placebo Controlled Trial. Recruited subjects will be consented, enrolled and
      evaluated immediately prior to P1 (or during a visit prior to the visit for P1). After the
      initial pre-treatment evaluation, subjects will randomly receive either placebo or Botulinum
      Toxin A subcutaneously (P1). A telephone follow-up (or e-mail follow up) will be performed at
      2 weeks and 8 weeks post- P1. An onsite follow up will be performed 4 weeks post P1 and 12
      weeks post P1.

      Cross-over Study: After the 3rd month on-site evaluation (12 weeks post P1), during the same
      visit, the subject will proceed to the cross-over study. At this time, the patient will have
      the option to receive a repeat subcutaneous injection of the cross-over agent. If they desire
      one, a subcutaneous injection of the cross-over agent will be performed at that same visit.
      If they wish to defer the repeat injection, they will be contacted and asked every 4 weeks -
      between 12 weeks and 24 weeks post P1 (no subject will receive P2 after week 24) if they
      would like to have the subcutaneous injection of the cross-over agent. If they desire one, a
      repeat injection will be scheduled for the following week.

      The rationale for a variable length of time after the initial Botulinum Toxin A/Placebo
      injection (P1) is to document the variability of individuals' pain response after Botulinum
      Toxin A. It has been reported in literature, of the subjects that respond to subcutaneous
      Botulinum Toxin A injections for pain, most will return to their base-line pain score in
      12--24 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric pain rating scale (NPRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks post--injection</time_frame>
    <description>Participant rated pain intensity from 0-10.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>7-Point Guy/Farrar Patient Global Impression of Change</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks post--injection</time_frame>
    <description>This scale measures the global treatment effect from very much improved to very much worse. Subjects will be asked to rate the treatment's effect at each reevaluation. In this investigation, the PGIC rating will take the form of, &quot;Taking into account your pain level and how it affects your life, are you feeling better, the same or worse than when you started treatment ?&quot; If the individual states that there is no change, then the rating is complete. If he or she is worse or better, the individual is asked to quantify the magnitude of the change as 1-very much better; 2--better; 3--somewhat better; or 5- somewhat worse; 6--worse; 7-very much worse. The PGIC will be a secondary outcome measure of treatment effect. The PGIC one of the recommended scales for measuring the global treatment effect and can be used to complement the one- dimensional pain intensity scales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>International Basic Pain Dataset</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks post--injection</time_frame>
    <description>The International Basic Pain Dataset is an assessment tool which includes several components including: location of pain, temporal qualities of the pain, type of pain, pain interference measures of activity, sleep, and mood. It has been shown to be valid in an interview/self -report format. This will be collected for up to 3 pains localized to the back which can be differentiated as unique pains. These pains may or may not be neuropathic.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Static Mechanical Allodynia testing</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks post--injection</time_frame>
    <description>Mechanical allodynia is a characteristic of evoked pain in subjects with neuropathic pain. Static allodynia to mechanical stimuli will be defined as a sensation of pain evoked by the pressure of the end of a wooden stick. The end of a wooden stick will touch the affected region with enough pressure to indent the skin, for 10 seconds. Afterwards, the subject will be asked to rate the perceived pain on an 11-point NRS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dynamic Mechanical Allodynia testing</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks post--injection</time_frame>
    <description>Dynamic allodynia will be tested by stroking the affected region gently with a cotton swab, 4 times at a rate of 3-5cm per second over an area of 5cm. If there is an evoked clear sensation of pain, the subject is asked to rate the intensity of dynamic allodynia using the 11-point NRS. The region of static and dynamic allodynia, if present, will be marked and recorded</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuropathic Back Pain</condition>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Botulinum Toxin A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each vial of botulin toxin (100U, BOTOX, Allergan) will be reconstituted with 4ml non-preserved saline solution (0.9%) as recommended by the manufacturer (concentration of 5 units Botulinum Toxin A/0.2ml). Each injection will be 0.2mL (BOTOX, 5 units), administered through a 25 gauge needle. The marked area will have subcutaneous injections, each separated by a radius of 1 cm, from the other injections into the marked area,(maximum of 80 injections, 400 Units).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo consists of 0.9% normal saline. Each injection will be 0.2mL, administered with a 25 gauge needle subcutaneously into the affected area. The marked area will have subcutaneous injections (maximum of 80) each separated from the surrounding ones by a radius of 1 cm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Botulinum Toxin A</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive subcutaneous Botulinum Toxin A injections into the marked painful region. The syringes will be prepared by a third party prior to the injection and the administrator of the procedure will be blinded to syringe content. This physician will be performing the injections under sterile conditions. Local anesthesia, EMLA (lignocaine/prilocaine eutectic mixture) cream, up to 4 grams, will be applied topically for local anesthesia. After 50 minutes, the cream will be cleaned off. Overlying skin will be sterilized with either betadine or alcohol solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Botulinum Toxin A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Botox</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive subcutaneous placebo injections into the marked painful region. The syringes will be prepared by a third party prior to the injection and the administrator of the procedure will be blinded to syringe content. This physician will be performing the injections under sterile conditions. Local anesthesia, EMLA (lignocaine/prilocaine eutectic mixture) cream, up to 4 grams, will be applied topically for local anesthesia. After 50 minutes, the cream will be cleaned off. Overlying skin will be sterilized with either betadine or alcohol solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between the ages of 18 and 80 years old

          -  Diagnosed with traumatic spinal cord injury

          -  Target pain is considered by the physician as at-level SCI in nature to a high degree
             of certainty (4 or 5 using a Likert confidence scale ranging from 0-5 where 0 is
             &quot;purely a guess&quot; and 5 is &quot;absolutely certain&quot;)

          -  Able to give written informed consent

          -  Target pain that has been continuously present for at least one month

          -  Target pain is of at least moderate average intensity over the past week, e.g.,
             greater than or equal to 4/10 on a numeric rating scale, the cutoff point for moderate
             pain in an SCI population.

          -  Target pain is localized within the dermatome which identifies the NLI or within 3
             levels below the NLI

          -  Subject has been on a stable dose of analgesic mediation (or not on analgesic
             medication) for at least 3 weeks and is agreeable to remaining on current regimen for
             the duration of the study (previous prescribed breakthrough analgesics will be
             allowed)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  History of intolerance, hypersensitivity or known allergy to botulinum toxin or its
             preservatives

          -  History of intolerance, hypersensitivity or known allergy to EMLA cream
             (lignocaine/prilocaine eutectic mixture) which is used as an analgesic during BoNT
             injection

          -  Recent history of administration of botulinum toxin (within previous 6 months)

          -  Contraindications to botulinum toxin (myasthenia gravis or other disease of the
             neuromuscular junction)

          -  Coagulation disorder

          -  Current infection

          -  Insufficient command of English to complete self-report instruments.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Bryce, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ajax Yang, MD, MPT</last_name>
    <phone>857-222-2264</phone>
    <email>ajax.yang@mountsinai.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Thomas Bryce, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-241-6321</phone>
    <email>thomas.bryce@mountsinai.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas Bryce, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-6321</phone>
      <email>thomas.bryce@mountsinai.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alan Kozolwski, PhD</last_name>
      <email>alan.kozolwski@mountsinai.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miguel Escalon, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ajax Yang, MD, MPT</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siddall PJ, McClelland JM, Rutkowski SB, Cousins MJ. A longitudinal study of the prevalence and characteristics of pain in the first 5 years following spinal cord injury. Pain. 2003 Jun;103(3):249-57.</citation>
    <PMID>12791431</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardenas DD, Bryce TN, Shem K, Richards JS, Elhefni H. Gender and minority differences in the pain experience of people with spinal cord injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2004 Nov;85(11):1774-81.</citation>
    <PMID>15520972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rintala DH, Loubser PG, Castro J, Hart KA, Fuhrer MJ. Chronic pain in a community-based sample of men with spinal cord injury: prevalence, severity, and relationship with impairment, disability, handicap, and subjective well-being. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1998 Jun;79(6):604-14.</citation>
    <PMID>9630137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen MP, Hoffman AJ, Cardenas DD. Chronic pain in individuals with spinal cord injury: a survey and longitudinal study. Spinal Cord. 2005 Dec;43(12):704-12.</citation>
    <PMID>15968299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vogel LC, Krajci KA, Anderson CJ. Adults with pediatric-onset spinal cord injury: part 2: musculoskeletal and neurological complications. J Spinal Cord Med. 2002 Summer;25(2):117-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12137215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McColl MA, Charlifue S, Glass C, Lawson N, Savic G. Aging, gender, and spinal cord injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2004 Mar;85(3):363-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15031818</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knútsdóttir S. Spinal cord injuries in Iceland 1973-1989. A follow up study. Paraplegia. 1993 Jan;31(1):68-72.</citation>
    <PMID>8446450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samuelsson KK. Back pain and spinal Deformity—Common among wheelchair users with spinal cord injuries. Scandinavian journal of occupational therapy. 1996 -01;3(1):28-32.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waisbrod H, Hansen D, Gerbershagen HU. Chronic pain in paraplegics. Neurosurgery. 1984 Dec;15(6):933-4.</citation>
    <PMID>6514167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hardcastle P, Bedbrook G, Curtis K. Long-term results of conservative and operative management in complete paraplegics with spinal cord injuries between T10 and L2 with respect to function. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 1987 Nov;(224):88-96.</citation>
    <PMID>3665258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walter JS, Sacks J, Othman R, Rankin AZ, Nemchausky B, Chintam R, Wheeler JS. A database of self-reported secondary medical problems among VA spinal cord injury patients: its role in clinical care and management. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2002 Jan-Feb;39(1):53-61. Erratum in: J Rehabil Res Dev. 2002 Sep-Oct;39(5):623.</citation>
    <PMID>11926327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rintala DH, Hart KA, Priebe MM. Predicting consistency of pain over a 10-year period in persons with spinal cord injury. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2004 Jan-Feb;41(1):75-88.</citation>
    <PMID>15273900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardenas DD, Jensen MP. Treatments for chronic pain in persons with spinal cord injury: A survey study. J Spinal Cord Med. 2006;29(2):109-17.</citation>
    <PMID>16739554</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cardenas DD, Warms CA, Turner JA, Marshall H, Brooke MM, Loeser JD. Efficacy of amitriptyline for relief of pain in spinal cord injury: results of a randomized controlled trial. Pain. 2002 Apr;96(3):365-73.</citation>
    <PMID>11973011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levendoglu F, Ogün CO, Ozerbil O, Ogün TC, Ugurlu H. Gabapentin is a first line drug for the treatment of neuropathic pain in spinal cord injury. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2004 Apr 1;29(7):743-51.</citation>
    <PMID>15087796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Norrbrink C, Lundeberg T. Tramadol in neuropathic pain after spinal cord injury: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Clin J Pain. 2009 Mar-Apr;25(3):177-84. doi: 10.1097/AJP.0b013e31818a744d.</citation>
    <PMID>19333166</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elia AE, Filippini G, Calandrella D, Albanese A. Botulinum neurotoxins for post-stroke spasticity in adults: a systematic review. Mov Disord. 2009 Apr 30;24(6):801-12. doi: 10.1002/mds.22452. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19224614</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Novak I, Campbell L, Boyce M, Fung VS; Cerebral Palsy Institute. Botulinum toxin assessment, intervention and aftercare for cervical dystonia and other causes of hypertonia of the neck: international consensus statement. Eur J Neurol. 2010 Aug;17 Suppl 2:94-108. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-1331.2010.03130.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20633181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sheean G, Lannin NA, Turner-Stokes L, Rawicki B, Snow BJ; Cerebral Palsy Institute. Botulinum toxin assessment, intervention and after-care for upper limb hypertonicity in adults: international consensus statement. Eur J Neurol. 2010 Aug;17 Suppl 2:74-93. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-1331.2010.03129.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20633180</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olver J, Esquenazi A, Fung VS, Singer BJ, Ward AB; Cerebral Palsy Institute. Botulinum toxin assessment, intervention and aftercare for lower limb disorders of movement and muscle tone in adults: international consensus statement. Eur J Neurol. 2010 Aug;17 Suppl 2:57-73. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-1331.2010.03128.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20633179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piovesan EJ, Teive HG, Kowacs PA, Della Coletta MV, Werneck LC, Silberstein SD. An open study of botulinum-A toxin treatment of trigeminal neuralgia. Neurology. 2005 Oct 25;65(8):1306-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16247065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xiao L, Mackey S, Hui H, Xong D, Zhang Q, Zhang D. Subcutaneous injection of botulinum toxin a is beneficial in postherpetic neuralgia. Pain Med. 2010 Dec;11(12):1827-33. doi: 10.1111/j.1526-4637.2010.01003.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21134121</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu CJ, Lian YJ, Zheng YK, Zhang HF, Chen Y, Xie NC, Wang LJ. Botulinum toxin type A for the treatment of trigeminal neuralgia: results from a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Cephalalgia. 2012 Apr;32(6):443-50. doi: 10.1177/0333102412441721. Epub 2012 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22492424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yuan RY, Sheu JJ, Yu JM, Chen WT, Tseng IJ, Chang HH, Hu CJ. Botulinum toxin for diabetic neuropathic pain: a randomized double-blind crossover trial. Neurology. 2009 Apr 28;72(17):1473-8. doi: 10.1212/01.wnl.0000345968.05959.cf. Epub 2009 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>19246421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jabbari B, Maher N, Difazio MP. Botulinum toxin a improved burning pain and allodynia in two patients with spinal cord pathology. Pain Med. 2003 Jun;4(2):206-10.</citation>
    <PMID>12873271</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bryce TN, Budh CN, Cardenas DD, Dijkers M, Felix ER, Finnerup NB, Kennedy P, Lundeberg T, Richards JS, Rintala DH, Siddall P, Widerstrom-Noga E. Pain after spinal cord injury: an evidence-based review for clinical practice and research. Report of the National Institute on Disability and Rehabilitation Research Spinal Cord Injury Measures meeting. J Spinal Cord Med. 2007;30(5):421-40.</citation>
    <PMID>18092558</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bryce TN, Biering-Sørensen F, Finnerup NB, Cardenas DD, Defrin R, Ivan E, Lundeberg T, Norrbrink C, Richards JS, Siddall P, Stripling T, Treede RD, Waxman SG, Widerström-Noga E, Yezierski RP, Dijkers M. International Spinal Cord Injury Pain (ISCIP) Classification: Part 2. Initial validation using vignettes. Spinal Cord. 2012 Jun;50(6):404-12. doi: 10.1038/sc.2012.2. Epub 2012 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22310319</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bryce TN, Ragnarsson KT. Pain after spinal cord injury. Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am. 2000 Feb;11(1):157-68. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10680163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vranken JH, Hollmann MW, van der Vegt MH, Kruis MR, Heesen M, Vos K, Pijl AJ, Dijkgraaf MG. Duloxetine in patients with central neuropathic pain caused by spinal cord injury or stroke: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Pain. 2011 Feb;152(2):267-73. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2010.09.005.</citation>
    <PMID>21078545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lis AM, Black KM, Korn H, Nordin M. Association between sitting and occupational LBP. Eur Spine J. 2007 Feb;16(2):283-98. Epub 2006 May 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16736200</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Nieuwenhuyse A, Fatkhutdinova L, Verbeke G, Pirenne D, Johannik K, Somville PR, Mairiaux P, Moens GF, Masschelein R. Risk factors for first-ever low back pain among workers in their first employment. Occup Med (Lond). 2004 Dec;54(8):513-9. Epub 2004 Sep 22.</citation>
    <PMID>15385649</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adams MA, McNally DS, Chinn H, Dolan P. The clinical biomechanics award paper 1993 Posture and the compressive strength of the lumbar spine. Clin Biomech (Bristol, Avon). 1994 Jan;9(1):5-14. doi: 10.1016/0268-0033(94)90052-3.</citation>
    <PMID>23916072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Panjabi MM, Andersson GB, Jorneus L, Hult E, Mattsson L. In vivo measurements of spinal column vibrations. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 1986 Jun;68(5):695-702.</citation>
    <PMID>3722226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scannell JP, McGill SM. Lumbar posture--should it, and can it, be modified? A study of passive tissue stiffness and lumbar position during activities of daily living. Phys Ther. 2003 Oct;83(10):907-17.</citation>
    <PMID>14519062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Claus AP, Hides JA, Moseley GL, Hodges PW. Is 'ideal' sitting posture real? Measurement of spinal curves in four sitting postures. Man Ther. 2009 Aug;14(4):404-8. doi: 10.1016/j.math.2008.06.001. Epub 2008 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18793867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dunk NM, Kedgley AE, Jenkyn TR, Callaghan JP. Evidence of a pelvis-driven flexion pattern: are the joints of the lower lumbar spine fully flexed in seated postures? Clin Biomech (Bristol, Avon). 2009 Feb;24(2):164-8. doi: 10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2008.12.003. Epub 2009 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19138810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Carvalho DE, Soave D, Ross K, Callaghan JP. Lumbar spine and pelvic posture between standing and sitting: a radiologic investigation including reliability and repeatability of the lumbar lordosis measure. J Manipulative Physiol Ther. 2010 Jan;33(1):48-55. doi: 10.1016/j.jmpt.2009.11.008.</citation>
    <PMID>20114100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dolan P, Adams MA, Hutton WC. Commonly adopted postures and their effect on the lumbar spine. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 1988 Feb;13(2):197-201.</citation>
    <PMID>3406840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lord MJ, Small JM, Dinsay JM, Watkins RG. Lumbar lordosis. Effects of sitting and standing. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 1997 Nov 1;22(21):2571-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9383867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Callaghan JP, McGill SM. Low back joint loading and kinematics during standing and unsupported sitting. Ergonomics. 2001 Feb 20;44(3):280-94.</citation>
    <PMID>11219760</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harrison DD, Harrison SO, Croft AC, Harrison DE, Troyanovich SJ. Sitting biomechanics part I: review of the literature. J Manipulative Physiol Ther. 1999 Nov-Dec;22(9):594-609. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10626703</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hedman TP, Fernie GR. Mechanical response of the lumbar spine to seated postural loads. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 1997 Apr 1;22(7):734-43.</citation>
    <PMID>9106313</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reeve A, Dilley A. Effects of posture on the thickness of transversus abdominis in pain-free subjects. Man Ther. 2009 Dec;14(6):679-84. doi: 10.1016/j.math.2009.02.008. Epub 2009 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>19443261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Claus AP, Hides JA, Moseley GL, Hodges PW. Different ways to balance the spine: subtle changes in sagittal spinal curves affect regional muscle activity. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2009 Mar 15;34(6):E208-14. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0b013e3181908ead.</citation>
    <PMID>19282726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Sullivan PB, Dankaerts W, Burnett AF, Farrell GT, Jefford E, Naylor CS, O'Sullivan KJ. Effect of different upright sitting postures on spinal-pelvic curvature and trunk muscle activation in a pain-free population. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2006 Sep 1;31(19):E707-12.</citation>
    <PMID>16946644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Francisco GE, Tan H, Green M. Do botulinum toxins have a role in the management of neuropathic pain?: a focused review. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 2012 Oct;91(10):899-909. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22660369</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lu DW, Lippitz J. Complications of botulinum neurotoxin. Dis Mon. 2009 Apr;55(4):198-211. doi: 10.1016/j.disamonth.2009.01.001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19286054</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Argoff CE. A focused review on the use of botulinum toxins for neuropathic pain. Clin J Pain. 2002 Nov-Dec;18(6 Suppl):S177-81. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12569966</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Matak I, Bach-Rojecky L, Filipović B, Lacković Z. Behavioral and immunohistochemical evidence for central antinociceptive activity of botulinum toxin A. Neuroscience. 2011 Jul 14;186:201-7. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2011.04.026. Epub 2011 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>21539899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Foster L, Clapp L, Erickson M, Jabbari B. Botulinum toxin A and chronic low back pain: a randomized, double-blind study. Neurology. 2001 May 22;56(10):1290-3.</citation>
    <PMID>11376175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Apalla Z, Sotiriou E, Lallas A, Lazaridou E, Ioannides D. Botulinum toxin A in postherpetic neuralgia: a parallel, randomized, double-blind, single-dose, placebo-controlled trial. Clin J Pain. 2013 Oct;29(10):857-64. doi: 10.1097/AJP.0b013e31827a72d2.</citation>
    <PMID>23370074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ranoux D, Attal N, Morain F, Bouhassira D. Botulinum toxin type A induces direct analgesic effects in chronic neuropathic pain. Ann Neurol. 2008 Sep;64(3):274-83. doi: 10.1002/ana.21427. Erratum in: Ann Neurol. 2009 Mar;65(3):359.</citation>
    <PMID>18546285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bach-Rojecky L, Salković-Petrisić M, Lacković Z. Botulinum toxin type A reduces pain supersensitivity in experimental diabetic neuropathy: bilateral effect after unilateral injection. Eur J Pharmacol. 2010 May 10;633(1-3):10-4. doi: 10.1016/j.ejphar.2010.01.020. Epub 2010 Feb 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20123097</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bach-Rojecky L, Lacković Z. Central origin of the antinociceptive action of botulinum toxin type A. Pharmacol Biochem Behav. 2009 Dec;94(2):234-8. doi: 10.1016/j.pbb.2009.08.012. Epub 2009 Sep 2.</citation>
    <PMID>19732788</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kharkar S, Ambady P, Venkatesh Y, Schwartzman RJ. Intramuscular botulinum toxin in complex regional pain syndrome: case series and literature review. Pain Physician. 2011 Sep-Oct;14(5):419-24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21927045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Birthi P, Sloan P, Salles S. Subcutaneous botulinum toxin A for the treatment of refractory complex regional pain syndrome. PM R. 2012 Jun;4(6):446-9. doi: 10.1016/j.pmrj.2011.12.010.</citation>
    <PMID>22732156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fabregat G, Asensio-Samper JM, Palmisani S, Villanueva-Perez VL, De Andres J. Subcutaneous botulinum toxin for chronic post-thoracotomy pain. Pain Pract. 2012 Jun 21.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang T, Adatia A, Zarin W, Moitri M, Vijenthira A, Chu R, Thabane L, Kean W. The efficacy of botulinum toxin type A in managing chronic musculoskeletal pain: a systematic review and meta analysis. Inflammopharmacology. 2011 Feb;19(1):21-34. doi: 10.1007/s10787-010-0069-x. Epub 2010 Nov 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21076878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Argoff C. The emerging use of botulinum toxins for the treatment of neuropathic pain. Pain Med. 2010 Dec;11(12):1750-2. doi: 10.1111/j.1526-4637.2010.00997.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21134116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lew HL, Lee EH, Castaneda A, Klima R, Date E. Therapeutic use of botulinum toxin type A in treating neck and upper-back pain of myofascial origin: a pilot study. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2008 Jan;89(1):75-80. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2007.08.133.</citation>
    <PMID>18164334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jabbari B, Machado D. Treatment of refractory pain with botulinum toxins--an evidence-based review. Pain Med. 2011 Nov;12(11):1594-606. doi: 10.1111/j.1526-4637.2011.01245.x. Epub 2011 Sep 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21958302</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jabbari B, Ney J, Sichani A, Monacci W, Foster L, Difazio M. Treatment of refractory, chronic low back pain with botulinum neurotoxin A: an open-label, pilot study. Pain Med. 2006 May-Jun;7(3):260-4.</citation>
    <PMID>16712627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McMahon HT, Foran P, Dolly JO, Verhage M, Wiegant VM, Nicholls DG. Tetanus toxin and botulinum toxins type A and B inhibit glutamate, gamma-aminobutyric acid, aspartate, and met-enkephalin release from synaptosomes. Clues to the locus of action. J Biol Chem. 1992 Oct 25;267(30):21338-43.</citation>
    <PMID>1356988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Welch MJ, Purkiss JR, Foster KA. Sensitivity of embryonic rat dorsal root ganglia neurons to Clostridium botulinum neurotoxins. Toxicon. 2000 Feb;38(2):245-58.</citation>
    <PMID>10665805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Durham PL, Cady R, Cady R. Regulation of calcitonin gene-related peptide secretion from trigeminal nerve cells by botulinum toxin type A: implications for migraine therapy. Headache. 2004 Jan;44(1):35-42; discussion 42-3.</citation>
    <PMID>14979881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meng J, Wang J, Lawrence G, Dolly JO. Synaptobrevin I mediates exocytosis of CGRP from sensory neurons and inhibition by botulinum toxins reflects their anti-nociceptive potential. J Cell Sci. 2007 Aug 15;120(Pt 16):2864-74. Epub 2007 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>17666428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Planells-Cases R, Garcìa-Sanz N, Morenilla-Palao C, Ferrer-Montiel A. Functional aspects and mechanisms of TRPV1 involvement in neurogenic inflammation that leads to thermal hyperalgesia. Pflugers Arch. 2005 Oct;451(1):151-9. Epub 2005 May 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15909179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morenilla-Palao C, Planells-Cases R, García-Sanz N, Ferrer-Montiel A. Regulated exocytosis contributes to protein kinase C potentiation of vanilloid receptor activity. J Biol Chem. 2004 Jun 11;279(24):25665-72. Epub 2004 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>15066994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antonucci F, Rossi C, Gianfranceschi L, Rossetto O, Caleo M. Long-distance retrograde effects of botulinum neurotoxin A. J Neurosci. 2008 Apr 2;28(14):3689-96. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0375-08.2008.</citation>
    <PMID>18385327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Restani L, Antonucci F, Gianfranceschi L, Rossi C, Rossetto O, Caleo M. Evidence for anterograde transport and transcytosis of botulinum neurotoxin A (BoNT/A). J Neurosci. 2011 Nov 2;31(44):15650-9. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2618-11.2011.</citation>
    <PMID>22049408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naumann M, Jankovic J. Safety of botulinum toxin type A: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Curr Med Res Opin. 2004 Jul;20(7):981-90. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15265242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naumann M, Albanese A, Heinen F, Molenaers G, Relja M. Safety and efficacy of botulinum toxin type A following long-term use. Eur J Neurol. 2006 Dec;13 Suppl 4:35-40. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17112348</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li M, Goldberger BA, Hopkins C. Fatal case of BOTOX-related anaphylaxis? J Forensic Sci. 2005 Jan;50(1):169-72.</citation>
    <PMID>15831014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Forchheimer MB, Richards JS, Chiodo AE, Bryce TN, Dyson-Hudson TA. Cut point determination in the measurement of pain and its relationship to psychosocial and functional measures after traumatic spinal cord injury: a retrospective model spinal cord injury system analysis. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2011 Mar;92(3):419-24. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2010.08.029.</citation>
    <PMID>21353824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hanley MA, Jensen MP, Ehde DM, Robinson LR, Cardenas DD, Turner JA, Smith DG. Clinically significant change in pain intensity ratings in persons with spinal cord injury or amputation. Clin J Pain. 2006 Jan;22(1):25-31.</citation>
    <PMID>16340590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>BEECHER HK. The powerful placebo. J Am Med Assoc. 1955 Dec 24;159(17):1602-6.</citation>
    <PMID>13271123</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Widerström-Noga E, Biering-Sørensen F, Bryce T, Cardenas DD, Finnerup NB, Jensen MP, Richards JS, Siddall PJ. The international spinal cord injury pain basic data set. Spinal Cord. 2008 Dec;46(12):818-23. doi: 10.1038/sc.2008.64. Epub 2008 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>18521092</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen MP, Widerström-Noga E, Richards JS, Finnerup NB, Biering-Sørensen F, Cardenas DD. Reliability and validity of the International Spinal Cord Injury Basic Pain Data Set items as self-report measures. Spinal Cord. 2010 Mar;48(3):230-8. doi: 10.1038/sc.2009.112. Epub 2009 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>19786975</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruta DA, Garratt AM, Leng M, Russell IT, MacDonald LM. A new approach to the measurement of quality of life. The Patient-Generated Index. Med Care. 1994 Nov;32(11):1109-26.</citation>
    <PMID>7967852</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruta DA, Garratt AM, Russell IT. Patient centred assessment of quality of life for patients with four common conditions. Qual Health Care. 1999 Mar;8(1):22-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10557665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tugwell P, Bombardier C, Buchanan WW, Goldsmith CH, Grace E, Hanna B. The MACTAR Patient Preference Disability Questionnaire--an individualized functional priority approach for assessing improvement in physical disability in clinical trials in rheumatoid arthritis. J Rheumatol. 1987 Jun;14(3):446-51.</citation>
    <PMID>3305931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wright JG, Young NL. The patient-specific index: asking patients what they want. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 1997 Jul;79(7):974-83.</citation>
    <PMID>9234873</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Thomas N. Bryce</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Rehabilitation Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Botulinum Toxin A</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuropathic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Spinal cord injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain management</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins, Type A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>onabotulinumtoxinA</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>abobotulinumtoxinA</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The following will be shared: demographic information, pain response to interventions, adverse events and functional outcomes. The above information will be obtain in the forms of questionnaires and surveys. The data will be available when the study concludes.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

