<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02738463</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SHMS1985</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02738463</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Maternal Serum Ferritin and Low Neonatal Birth Weight</brief_title>
  <acronym>LBW</acronym>
  <official_title>Role of Maternal Serum Ferritin in the Prediction of Low Neonatal Birth Weight</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ain Shams Maternity Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ain Shams University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ain Shams Maternity Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Intrauterine growth restriction ( IUGR )is defined as fetal growth slower than the normal
      growth potential of a specific fetus because of genetic or environmental factors. Recently
      several studies have highlighted the role of many biomolecules as markers for IUGR.
      Measurement of maternal serum ferritin has also been used as a predictive marker for
      increased risk of IUGR. Iron deficiency has its known deleterious effect in pregnancy but
      iron loading may be associated with oxidative damage to cells and tissues. It has been shown
      in various studies that lower level of transferritin receptor expression in placenta is
      associated with preeclampsia and IUGR. This can lead to decrease extraction of iron by
      placenta from maternal serum leading to increase maternal serum ferritin. This fetal iron
      deficiency leads to increase in fetal corticotropins and fetal cortisol, causing inhibition
      of fetal growth
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR) is defined as fetal growth slower than the normal
      growth potential of a specific fetus because of genetic or environmental factors. IUGR is
      associated with a high incidence of perinatal morbidity and mortality. IUGR neonates have a
      greater risk of hypoxic ischemic encephalopathy, intraventricular hemorrhage and necrotizing
      enterocolitis with longer hospital stay and higher health care costs. Incidence of a fetus
      developing a small size for gestational age is about 8%. Fetal growth is regulated by the
      balance between fetal nutrient demand and maternal placental nutrient supply. Intrauterine
      growth restriction may be caused by maternal, placental, or fetal factors. Nearly one-third
      of IUGRs are due to genetic causes, and two-thirds are related to the fetal environment. In
      the developing world, IUGR is likely to be a consequence of poor maternal nutritional status
      prior to or during pregnancy.

      There are two general patterns of growth abnormalities: symmetric and asymmetric. Symmetric
      growth inhibition arises during the first half of gestation, when fetal growth occurs
      primarily through cellular division and produces an undersized fetus with fewer cells of
      normal size. Asymmetric growth inhibition occurs during the second half of gestation and is
      usually the consequence of an inadequate availability of substrates for fetal metabolism. To
      prevent the previously mentioned complications of IUGR, it is important to establish markers
      which can identify pregnancies at risk of IUGR early enough. Recently several studies have
      highlighted the role of many bio-molecules as markers for IUGR like leptin, adiponectin,
      endothelin-1, lactate dehydrogenase, s-endoglin, pregnancy associated plasma protein,
      metastin. Apart from being expensive, laboratories at majority of centers are not equipped
      with facilities of measurement of these markers. Measurement of maternal serum ferritin has
      also been used as a predictive marker for increased risk of IUGR in one previous study on a
      limited number (seventeen) of cases. Ferritin is an intracellular protein consisting of 24
      heavy and light sub-units surrounding a core that can store up to 4,500 iron atoms. The two
      sub-units are highly conserved during evolution, but only the heavy sub-unit has ferroxidase
      activity. Ferritin is released by infiltrating leukocytes, in response to acute and chronic
      infection. Ferritin as an acute phase reactant is well known for its intracellular iron
      sequestration and storage abilities during immune activation. Serum ferritin concentration is
      positively correlated with the amount of total body iron stores in the absence of
      inflammation. Serum ferritin is considered a valuable bio-marker for body iron status in
      healthy subjects.Iron deficiency has its known deleterious effect in pregnancy but iron
      loading may be associated with oxidative damage to cells and tissues. It has been shown in
      various studies that lower level of transferritin receptor expression in placenta is
      associated with preeclampsia and IUGR. This can lead to decrease extraction of iron by
      placenta from maternal serum leading to increase maternal serum ferritin. This fetal iron
      deficiency leads to increase in fetal corticotropins and fetal cortisol, causing inhibition
      of fetal growth.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>2 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>maternal serum ferritin (microg/L)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ferritin values will be estimated by immunometric testing for quantitative determination in human serum at Olympus analyzers using the Olympus ferritin reagent. Reference ranges from 10.00 to 30.00 microgram/L</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fetal weight (gm)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>birth weight less than 10th percentile will be adjusted for small for gestational age</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal hemoglobin (g/L)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>estimation will be done from hemolysate of the obtained blood samples with the addition of sodium ferricyanide and sodium cyanide. Cyanmet -hemoglobin formed in the solution will be estimated by spectro photometry at the wave length of 540 nm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal hematocrit (x10^12/L)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>The level will be also estimated by spectro photometry and calculated using the following formula: Hematocrit = blood cells volume/volume of blood sample × 100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apgar score</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>will be estimated by cardiac action, respiration of the newborn, muscle tone, skin color and reaction of the newborn will be estimated by 0, 1 or 2 summed up and compared. Apgar score can vary from 0 to 10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal total leucocytic count (x10^9/L)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>will be also estimated also by spectro photometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>IUGR</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 case</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will include 32 pregnant females whose fetuses show intrauterine growth restriction at full term ( the 32 neonates with birth weight less than 10th percentile for corresponding gestational age will be included as small for gestational age and the investigator will thaw their maternal frozen samples for detection of serum ferritin level)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 control</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will include at least 32 pregnant females whose fetuses are appropriate for gestational age at full term ( the 32 neonates with birth more than or equal to the 10th percentile for corresponding gestational age will be included as average for gestational age and the investigator will thaw their maternal frozen samples for detection of serum ferritin level)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      serum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study will include women, who attend the Obstetrics Department, in Ain Shams University
        Hospital, and fulfill the inclusion criteria, after taking an informed consent
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Older than 20 years of age

          -  Pregnant with singleton intrauterine pregnancy

          -  30th-32nd weeks of gestation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a history of anemia due to any causes.

          -  Patients with history of iron supplementation, Clinical and/or laboratory evidence of
             hepatic, renal, hematologic, cardiovascular abnormalities.

          -  History of acid-peptic disorders, esophagitis, or hiatal hernia.

          -  Family history of thalassemia, sickle cell anemia, or malabsorption syndrome.

          -  Antepartum hemorrhage.

          -  Allergies to milk proteins / hypersensitivity to iron preparations.

          -  Patients with acute infection, positive CRP, raised TLC count.

          -  Congenital malformation and fetuses with chromosomal or genetic syndrome.

          -  Recent blood transfusion.

          -  Refusal to participate in the study.

          -  BMI &lt;18.

          -  Placental abnormalities like velamentous insertion.

          -  Multiple pregnancies.

          -  Smoking during pregnancy

          -  Preterm births.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hassan A Bayoumyi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Ain Shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sherif A Ashoush, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ain Shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Haitham AM ElSabaa, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ain Shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ain Shams Maternity Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <zip>11566</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>outpatient clinics in the Obstetrics and Gynecology Department Ain Shams Maternity Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <zip>11566</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/261226-overview</url>
    <description>Ross MG. Fetal growth restriction, 2008</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arosio P, Ingrassia R, Cavadini P. Ferritins: a family of molecules for iron storage, antioxidation and more. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2009 Jul;1790(7):589-99. doi: 10.1016/j.bbagen.2008.09.004. Epub 2008 Sep 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18929623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bindal N, Godha Z, Kohli R, Kadam VK. Role of maternal serum ferritin as a predictive marker in intrauterine growth restriction. Int J Reprod Contracept Obstet Gynecol. 2015 Jun;4(3):804-808</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Milman N. Iron Deficiency and Anaemia in Pregnant Women in Malaysia - Still a Significant and Challenging Health Problem. J Preg Child Health 2015, 2:3</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moh W, Graham JM Jr, Wadhawan I, Sanchez-Lara PA. Extrinsic factors influencing fetal deformations and intrauterine growth restriction. J Pregnancy. 2012;2012:750485. doi: 10.1155/2012/750485. Epub 2012 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22888434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murki S and Sharma D. Intrauterine Growth Retardation - A Review Article. Murki and Sharma, J Neonatal Biol 2014, 3:3</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nandini M D, Shetty HV, Rupakala BV, Usha S M R, Priyadarshini KS, Manjula HS and Victoria Ksh. Study of serum ferritin levels in preterm labor. International Journal of Recent Trends in Science and Technology, ISSN 2277-2812 E-ISSN 2249-8109, Volume 14, Issue 2, 2015 pp 477-480</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muhammad T, Khattak AA, Shafiq-ur-Rehman, Khan MA, Khan A, Khan MA. Maternal factors associated with intrauterine growth restriction. J Ayub Med Coll Abbottabad. 2010 Oct-Dec;22(4):64-9.</citation>
    <PMID>22455264</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Višnjevac N, Segedi LM, Ćurčić A, Višnjevac J, Dragan Stajić. Blood ferritin levels in pregnant women and prediction of the development of fetal intrauterine growth restriction. J Med Biochem. 2011;30:m317-22</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang CN, Chang SD, Peng HH, Lee YS, Chang YL, Cheng PJ, Chao AS, Wang TH, Wang HS. Change in amniotic fluid levels of multiple anti-angiogenic proteins before development of preeclampsia and intrauterine growth restriction. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2010 Mar;95(3):1431-41. doi: 10.1210/jc.2009-1954. Epub 2010 Jan 15.</citation>
    <PMID>20080845</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang S, Regnault TR, Barker PL, Botting KJ, McMillen IC, McMillan CM, Roberts CT, Morrison JL. Placental adaptations in growth restriction. Nutrients. 2015 Jan 8;7(1):360-89. doi: 10.3390/nu7010360. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25580812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 31, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 11, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 11, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ain Shams Maternity Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Shaimaa Mahmoud salem</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ferritin LBW</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Birth Weight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_type>Individual Participant Data Set</doc_type>
      <doc_url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed</doc_url>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

