<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02737007</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>204853</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02737007</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Microdose Study in Healthy Subjects to Describe Intravenous Pharmacokinetics of GSK3191607</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Microdose Study to Describe the Intravenous Pharmacokinetics of GSK3191607 in Healthy Male Subjects Following Administration of [14C]-GSK3191607</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hammersmith Medicines Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label, single-centre, non-randomized study to investigate the
      pharmacokinetics of GSK3191607, administered as a single intravenous (IV) dose in healthy
      male subjects.

      Six subjects will be administered an IV microdose of radio-labeled [14C]-GSK3191607. The
      study will provide an early readout on human pharmacokinetic parameters. The results of this
      study will be used to estimate the potential duration of anti-parasite effect in humans,
      define predicted clinical oral doses, and hence inform about the compound's potential safety
      margin.

      Each subject will participate in the study for up to 8 weeks, and will have a screening
      visit, one treatment period, eight outpatient visits, and a follow-up visit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 18, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 12, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 12, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed concentration (Cmax) of GSK3191607 in plasma following a single intravenous (IV) microdose</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal phase half life (t1/2) of GSK3191607 following a single IV microdose</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of occurrence of Cmax (tmax) of GSK3191607 following a single IV microdose</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-t) of GSK3191607 following a single IV microdose</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>AUC(0-t) is the area under the concentration-time curve from time zero (pre-dose) to last time of quantifiable concentration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-infinity) of GSK3191607 following a single IV microdose</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>AUC(0-infinity) is the area under the concentration-time curve from time zero (pre-dose) extrapolated to infinite time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Systemic clearance (CL) of GSK3191607 following a single IV microdose</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>GSK3191607 volume of distribution at steady state (Vss)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax of radioactive drug-related material (RDM) in plasma following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>RDM is a measure of total radioactivity. Cmax of RDM will be compared with that of the parent drug (GSK3191607).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>T1/2 of RDM following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>T1/2 of RDM will be compared with that of the parent drug.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax of RDM following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax of RDM will be compared with that of the parent drug.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-t) of RDM following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>AUC(0-t) of RDM will be compared with that of the parent drug.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-infinity) of RDM following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>AUC(0-infinity) of RDM will be compared with that of the parent drug.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of RDM excreted in urine (Ae) following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0-24 hours and 24-48 hours after the start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will be asked to void their bladders before study treatment administration. A blank urine sample will be collected pre-dose.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole-Blood:Plasma ratio of Cmax of RDM following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax of RDM in whole blood will be compared with that of RDM in plasma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole-Blood:Plasma ratio of tmax of RDM following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax of RDM in whole blood will be compared with that of RDM in plasma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole-Blood:Plasma ratio of t1/2 of RDM following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>T1/2 of RDM in whole blood will be compared with that of RDM in plasma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole-Blood:Plasma ratio of AUC(0-t) of RDM following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>AUC(0-t) of RDM in whole blood will be compared with that of RDM in plasma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole-Blood:Plasma ratio of AUC(0-infinity) of RDM following a single IV microdose of [14C]-GSK3191607</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose; and 0.25, 0.75, 1.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 168, 216, 264, 312, and 336 hours following start of infusion</time_frame>
    <description>AUC(0-infinity) of RDM in whole blood will be compared with that of RDM in plasma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of infusion until follow-up (up to Day 25)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with clinically significant abnormal laboratory parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -1, Day 1, Day 2, and follow-up (up to Day 25)</time_frame>
    <description>Hematology, clinical chemistry, and urinalysis parameters will be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with clinically significant abnormal 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, Day 1, Day 2, and follow-up (up to Day 25)</time_frame>
    <description>12-lead ECGs will be obtained at each time point during the study using an ECG machine that automatically calculates the heart rate and measures PR, QRS, QT, and QT duration corrected for heart rate by Bazett's formula (QTcB) intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with clinically significant abnormal vital signs parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, Day 1, Day 2, Day 3, and follow-up (up to Day 25)</time_frame>
    <description>Vital signs will be measured in a semi-supine position after 5 minutes rest and will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure and pulse rate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria, Falciparum</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>[14C]-GSK3191607 IV Microdose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single microdose of 100 micrograms (mcg) of [14C]-GSK3191607 by intravenous infusion over 15 minutes on Day 1 of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[14C]-GSK3191607</intervention_name>
    <description>[14C]-GSK3191607 is a solution to be administered intravenously as a single dose infusion over 15 minutes. It is a radio-labeled product; 100 mcg of [14C]-GSK3191607 contains approximately 7.4 kilobecquerel (kBq) of [14C] radioactivity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>[14C]-GSK3191607 IV Microdose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between 18 and 55 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the informed consent.

          -  Healthy as determined by the investigator or medically qualified designee based on a
             medical evaluation including medical history, physical examination, vital signs,
             laboratory tests, and cardiac monitoring. A subject with a clinical abnormality or
             laboratory parameter(s) which is/are not specifically listed in the inclusion or
             exclusion criteria, outside the reference range for the population being studied may
             be included only if the investigator agrees and documents that the finding is unlikely
             to introduce additional risk factors and will not interfere with the study procedures.

          -  Body weight &gt;= 50 kg and body mass index (BMI) within the range 19.0-31.0 kilograms
             per meter squared (kg/m^2) (inclusive).

          -  Male.

          -  Subjects with female partners of child bearing potential must use a condom from the
             time of first dose of study medication until follow-up.

          -  Capable of giving signed informed consent, which includes compliance with pre-defined
             requirements and restrictions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and bilirubin &gt;1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN)
             (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5 times ULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and
             direct bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary abnormalities
             (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones).

          -  Mean QT duration corrected for heart rate by Fridericia's formula (QTcF) &gt; 450
             milliseconds (msec).

          -  Any clinically relevant abnormality identified at the screening medical assessment
             (physical examination/medical history), clinical laboratory tests, or 12-lead
             electrocardiogram (ECG).

          -  At screening, a mean supine blood pressure (BP) that is higher (triplicate
             measurements at least 2 minutes apart) than 140/90 millimeters of mercury (mmHg).

          -  At screening, a supine mean pulse rate outside the range 40-90 beats per minute (BPM).

          -  Subject is mentally or legally incapacitated.

          -  Use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, including vitamins, herbal and dietary
             supplements (including St John's Wort) within 7 days (or 14 days if the drug is a
             potential enzyme inducer) or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) before the first dose
             of study medication, unless in the opinion of the investigator and GlaxoSmithKline
             (GSK) Medical Monitor the medication will not interfere with the study procedures or
             compromise subject safety.

          -  Smoking or use of tobacco products. Urinary cotinine levels indicative of use of
             tobacco products or nicotine-containing products.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study, defined as an
             average weekly intake of &gt;21 units. One unit is equivalent to 8 grams (g) of alcohol:
             a half pint (~240 milliliters [mL]) of beer, 1 glass (125 mL) of wine or 1 (25 mL)
             measure of spirits.

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medication or its components, or a history
             of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or medical monitor,
             contraindicates the subject's participation.

          -  Presence of hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), positive hepatitis C antibody test
             result at screening or within 3 months before first dose of study treatment.

          -  A positive pre-study drug/alcohol screen.

          -  A positive test for Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

          -  Participation in a clinical trial involving administration of 14C-labelled compound(s)
             within the last 12 months before dosing. A subject's previous effective dose will be
             reviewed by the medical investigator to ensure there is no risk of
             contamination/carryover into the current study.

          -  Subjects who have received a total body radiation dose of greater than 5.0
             millisieverts (mSv) (upper limit of World Health Organization [WHO] category II) or
             exposure to significant radiation (for example, serial x ray or Computed Tomography
             (CT) scans, barium meal, etc.) in the 12 months before dosing.

          -  Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or blood products
             in excess of 500 mL within a 90 day period.

          -  Unable to refrain from consumption of red wine, Seville oranges, grapefruit or
             grapefruit juice from 7 days before the first dose of study medication until the last
             study visit.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period before the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months before the first
             dosing day.

          -  An occupation which requires monitoring for radiation exposure, nuclear medicine
             procedures or excessive x-rays within the past 12 months before dosing.

          -  Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures outlined in the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW10 7EW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.gsk-clinicalstudyregister.com/study/204853?search=study&amp;b'search_terms=204853'#rs</url>
    <description>Results for study 204853 can be found on the GSK Clinical Study Register.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 31, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 7, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malaria</keyword>
  <keyword>Microdose</keyword>
  <keyword>GSK3191607</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Falciparum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

