<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02738684</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>pfnaegmt-023</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02738684</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Predict Gefitinib' s Efficacy for Lung Cancer by Plasma Free Nucleic Acids EGFR Gene Mutation Test</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Small Sample Exploratory Study to Predict Gefitinib' s Efficacy for Late Stage Lung Adenocarcinoma Patients by Plasma Free Nucleic Acids EGFR Gene Mutation Test</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Southwest Hospital, China</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Southwest Hospital, China</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project aims to do a small sample exploratory study, to predict EGFR-TKI targeted
      therapy gefitinib' s efficacy in late stage lung adenocarcinoma patients (phase IIIB or IV),
      who have negative tissue EGFR gene mutation, positive plasma free nucleic acid EGFR gene.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Results of the study will clarify that if the circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) EGFR mutation
      could be used as a screening method for EGFR-TKI targeted therapy for late stage lung cancer
      patients, as well as a standard for the therapy efficacy. This study can be used as a
      standard to assess gefitinib' s efficacy after 8 weeks of treatment in IIIB or stage IV lung
      cancer through tumor tissue negative, ctDNA positive EGFR mutation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>RECIST 1.1 Efficacy assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Categorisation of objective tumour response assessment at each visit will be based on the RECIST 1.1 criteria of response: CR, PR, SD and PD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>lung cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>A small sample exploratory study to predict gefitinib' s efficacy for late stage lung adenocarcinoma patients by plasma free nucleic acids EGFR gene mutation test</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      predict gefitinib' s efficacy for late stage lung adenocarcinoma patients by plasma free
      nucleic acids EGFR gene mutation test
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants in this research must meet the following criteria: histologic diagnosed of
        lung adenocarcinoma. Late stage (stage IIIB or IV) lung adenocarcinoma according to the
        International Union against cancer (UICC) the latest version of standard cancer TNM
        staging.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants in this research must meet the following criteria: histologic diagnosed
             of lung adenocarcinoma.

          -  Late stage (stage IIIB or IV) lung adenocarcinoma according to the International Union
             against cancer (UICC) the latest version of standard cancer TNM staging.

          -  tumor tissue EGFR mutation negative, and ctDNA EGFR mutation positive correlated with
             EGFR TKI sensitivity.

          -  Participants should have signed and dated on the official informed consent.

          -  Not less than 18 years old.

          -  At least 1 lesion can be exactly measured.

          -  Patients whose plasma free nucleic acids EGFR mutation test were positive, and willing
             to use gefitinib for therapy by their own expense.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Patients already received EGFR-TKI treatment previously.

          -  Patients have pressure on the spinal cord or brain metastases, no symptom, conditions
             stabled, do not need to use steroid medications for 4 weeks before the start of the
             study.

          -  Patients with clinical evidence of any symptoms of severe or uncontrolled
             hypertension, for example, researchers believe that patients with uncontrolled
             hypertension and active bleeding will affect the study reliability.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled nausea or vomiting, chronic gastrointestinal disease,
             unable to swallow drugs or underwent major bowel resection may affect the full
             absorption of gefitinib.

          -  Patients meet any one of the following heart standard: in static State, 3 times ECG
             check shows average correction QT period (QTc) &gt;470 msec; clinical abnormal symptom of
             rhythm, conduction, and static ECG, for example completely left beam conduction block,
             III degrees conduction block, II degrees conduction block, PR period &gt;250 msec,
             various factors with risks of extended QTc or rhythm disorders, for example,
             congestive heart failure, low potassium blood syndrome, congenital long QT Syndrome,
             direct relatives has long QT syndrome or sudden unexplained death in less than 40
             years old, drug combination that may prolong the QT interval.

          -  Patients Have the following history: ILD, drug-induced ILD, radiation Pneumonitis
             require steroid treatment, clinically active interstitial lung disease.

          -  Abnormal marrow reservation or organ function.

          -  Women who are breastfeeding.

          -  Fertile male or female, who did not taken effective contraceptive measures, women have
             been pregnant or breast feeding, or positive pregnancy test prior to study (urine or
             serum).

          -  Patients don't agree with the study processes, constraints and requirements, and were
             evaluated by researchers that can't participate in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>DAI X T, doctor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Respiratory Diseases, Souty West Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>WANG H J, doctor</last_name>
    <phone>+86-23-65221360</phone>
    <email>cslz.fwjt@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Southwest Hospital, China</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>XIAOTIANDAI</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Department of Respiratory Diseases</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>EGFR</keyword>
  <keyword>plasma free nucleic acids</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gefitinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

