<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02734576</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AP-003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02734576</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Venous Sinus Stenting To Treat Intractable Pulsatile Tinnitus Caused By Venous Sinus Stenosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Venous Sinus Stenting To Treat Intractable Pulsatile Tinnitus Caused By Venous Sinus Stenosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There have been few published studies that examine the efficacy and safety of endovascular
      treatments on patients with pulsatile tinnitus with venous stenosis. Despite the limited
      experience with venous sinus stenting to treat pulsatile tinnitus, preliminary results show
      that venous sinus stenting could represent a viable alternative for refractory pulsatile
      tinnitus patients with venous sinus stenosis. The purpose of our study is to evaluate the
      safety and efficacy of this procedure in a controlled fashion, using strict inclusion and
      exclusion criteria, and long-term clinical and imaging follow-up. The investigators hope to
      provide robust data regarding the safety and efficacy of venous sinus stenting for patients
      with pulsatile tinnitus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      WHAT IS INVOLVED IN THE STUDY?

      A. Screening process - not experimental:

      Patients with pulsatile tinnitus, evidence of narrowing of the large veins of the brain, and
      failure of prior conservative treatment will be considered for enrollment. All patients will
      undergo the standard of care evaluation for tinnitus by a specialist physician for diseases
      of the ear (Ear, Nose and Throat [ENT] physician or otorhinolaryngologist). If it is
      determined that the narrowing of the large veins of the brain (&quot;dural venous sinuses&quot;) is the
      most likely etiology for the tinnitus, then the possibility of enrollment in the trial will
      be discussed. Imaging studies of the head and temporal bone will be performed in order to
      further confirm venous sinus stenosis as the etiology of the pulsatile tinnitus and to rule
      out other possible causes. Additionally, patients will answer the questions listed on the
      Tinnitus Handicap Inventory questionnaire.

      During the screening process, we will review the results of tests that are not experimental
      and are performed as part of your routine care. In other words, these tests are performed
      regardless of your participation in the study and are termed &quot;standard procedures&quot;.

      B. Participating in the study:

      Participating in the trial means that the participants will undergo an experimental procedure
      called &quot;venous sinus stenting&quot; to open up the narrowing in the vein that is causing the
      tinnitus. This procedure requires taking two blood thinners called aspirin and Plavix. Both
      blood thinners will be initiated 1 week prior to the procedure and continued for 1 month
      after the procedure. At that time the Plavix will be stopped and aspirin will be continued
      for 11 more months (total of 12 months).

      - Direct Retrograde Cerebral Venography (DRCV) and Manometry: A DRCV is a non-experimental
      procedure to look at the veins of the brain. This procedure is done by inserting a catheter
      (soft plastic tube) through a vein in the groin (upper leg) and guide it though the veins all
      the way to the neck. It is done under local anesthetic and moderate sedation. After placing
      the catheter in the neck, a special dye (contrast) is injected through this catheter into the
      veins, while X-ray cameras take multiple pictures of the veins. Then, a smaller catheter is
      further advanced to the area of narrowing and by this catheter we will measure the blood
      pressure at that point. This helps us to identify the severity of the narrowing. If the
      pressure before and after the narrowing is significantly different, than we will continue
      with the placement of the stent in order to reopen the narrowing.

      - Venous Sinus Stenting (experimental): Venous sinus stenting is the experimental procedure
      being tested in this protocol and consists of placing a stent into the narrowed veins of the
      brain. The participants will be placed under general anesthesia because it is important that
      you do not move at all during the procedure. A catheter will be inserted through the upper
      part of the leg (groin area) and guided through the veins all the way to neck. Then, a
      balloon will be advanced through the catheter and positioned across the stenosis. The balloon
      will be carefully inflated for a few seconds. This process is called angioplasty and will
      partially re-open the narrowing, making placement of the stent easier. The balloon will be
      removed and then the stent will be advanced through the catheter in neck across the stenosis
      and carefully deployed.

      - Post-procedure Care: After the procedure, you will stay in the intensive care unit for 24
      hours for observation.

      C. Follow-up period:

      There will be no experimental procedure or test during the follow-up period. The following
      office visits and standard tests will be performed to evaluate the effects of the study
      intervention.

      - Office visits: Office visits and neurological evaluation will be performed at 1, 6, 12, and
      24 months after study intervention. At this time, patients will also fill the Tinnitus
      Handicap Inventory Questionnaire. The visits will be about 45min.

      - Audiometric assessment: An audiometric assessment will be performed at 3 months after the
      stenting procedure in order to assess inner ear function.

      - Non-invasive imaging studies: Magnetic Resonance Venogram (MRV) is a special Magnetic
      Resonance Imaging (MRI) scan with injection of a dye through a vein in the arm that will
      allow us to check whether the stent is still open without new narrowing. It will be performed
      12 months after the venous sinus stenting procedure. If there is clinical concern about stent
      patency, an expedited or intermediate MRV will be performed. If MRV is contraindicated,
      Computed Tomographic Venogram (CTV) will be performed instead.

      D. Medications:

      For the purpose of the study, the participants need to take antiplatelet drugs (&quot;blood
      thinners&quot;) that are necessary to prevent formation of clot in the stent. This is a standard
      precaution for every stent procedure. The participants will take two drugs (called aspirin
      and Plavix) for 1 month and then aspirin alone for 11 more months (total time on aspirin is
      12 months). It is essential that the drugs are taken every day as prescribed. As these drugs
      are dangerous during pregnancy, if the participant is a woman of childbearing age, then
      should discuss this issue with her physician, and avoid becoming pregnant during the 12
      months that you need these drugs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Grade on the Tinnitus Handicap Inventory Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedure related and device related complications</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Tinnitus</condition>
  <condition>Pulsatile Tinnitus</condition>
  <condition>Venous Sinus Stenosis</condition>
  <condition>Dural Sinus Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Venous Sinus Stenting</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Venous sinus stenting is the experimental procedure being tested in this protocol and consists of placing a stent into the narrowed veins of the brain. Under general anesthesia, a catheter will be inserted through a vein the upper part of the leg (groin area) and guided through the veins all the way to neck and the head. Then, a balloon will be advanced through the catheter and positioned across the stenosis. The balloon will be carefully inflated for a few seconds. This process is called angioplasty and will partially re-open the narrowing, making placement of the stent easier. The balloon will be removed and then the stent will be advanced through the catheter in neck across the stenosis and carefully deployed. After the procedure, the participants will stay in the intensive care unit for 24 hours for observation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Venous Sinus Stenting</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Venous Sinus Stenting</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe or catastrophic venous pulsatile tinnitus defined as Grades 4 or 5 on Tinnitus
             Handicap Inventory

          -  50% or more stenosis of the lateral venous sinus on Magnetic Resonance Venogram (MRV)
             or Computed Tomographic Venogram (CTV_, ipsilateral to the side of more severe
             tinnitus

          -  Failure of conservative or non-surgical therapies (including sound therapy, sound
             masking, hearing aids, tinnitus retraining (desensitization) therapy. Failure is
             defined as Grades 4 or 5 on the Tinnitus Handicap Inventory despite prior treatments
             that have lasted for at least 3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-pulsatile tinnitus

          -  Contra-indication to iodinated contrast

          -  Contra-indication to antiplatelet therapy

          -  Contra-indication to general anesthesia

          -  Pregnancy or plans for immediate pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Athos Patsalides, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Athos Patsalides, MD MPH</last_name>
    <phone>2127462821</phone>
    <email>atp9002@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Oscar Lleva</last_name>
    <phone>2127462821</phone>
    <email>osl9003@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York Presbyterian Hospital/ Weill Cornell Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Oscar Lleva, MD MPH</last_name>
      <phone>212-746-2821</phone>
      <email>osl9003@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 5, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 12, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Athos Patsalides MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Radiology in Neurological Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Venous Sinus Stenting</keyword>
  <keyword>Dural Sinus Stenting</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tinnitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

