<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02736747</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Cryotherapy_LAFIN</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02736747</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Cryotherapy on Ankle Movements and Gait of Spastic Hemiparetic Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immediate Effects of Cryotherapy on Neuromuscular Performance of Ankle Joint and on Gait Pattern of Chronic Spastic Hemiparetic Subjects Post-Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carolina Carmona de Alcântara</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Federal de Sao Carlos</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The stroke has been described as the third cause of death and main cause of disability in the
      worldwide population. About 60% of the survivors are able to walk following the
      rehabilitation process, however deficits on lower limbs functions often persists in most
      cases, affecting the gait and functional mobility. In this sense, several interventions are
      applied in the clinical practice to optimize the functional performance. Cryotherapy is one
      of the most used techniques aiming to reduce spasticity temporarily, allowing the training of
      functional tasks, such as walking. The aim of the present study is to evaluate the immediate
      effects of cryotherapy (ice pack) on neuromuscular performance, proprioception, passive
      resistance of dorsiflexors and plantarflexors muscles, and also on gait performance in
      chronic post-stroke subjects. Eighteen chronic hemiparetic subjects will participate in this
      crossover placebo-controlled trial. The order of intervention (cryotherapy or placebo) will
      be randomized. Fifteen days of washout period will be considered. The cryotherapy/placebo
      will be applied on the posterior area of the leg for 20 minutes. Initially Fugl Meyer will be
      applied. All other assessments will be performed before and after intervention: spasticity
      level, classified according to Modified Ashworth Scale; temporo-spatial and angular
      parameters for trunk, hip, knee and ankle during gait, using a motion analysis system
      (Qualysis AB, Gothenburg, Sweden); the proprioception (joint position sense), passive
      resistance to stretching, isometric and isokinetic torques during contractions of
      plantarflexors and dorsiflexors of the ankle, evaluated through isokinetic dynamometer.
      Concomitantly, bilateral activation of soleus, gastrocnemius, tibialis anterior and peroneus
      will be assessed by electromyography during isokinetic dynamometer assessment and gait. The
      following electromyographic variables will be analyzed: maximum activation amplitude, muscle
      onset, coactivation index between agonists and antagonists. For statistical analysis,
      normality (Shapiro Wilk) and homogeneity (Levene) tests will be applied. If the variables
      have a distribution considered normal and homogeneous, Two-way ANOVA with repeated measures
      will be applied. Otherwise, non-parametric statistics (Friedman test) will be applied. A
      significance level of 0.05 will be considered for all statistical tests.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in spasticity level</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 20 minutes (immediately post-application of cryotherapy or placebo)</time_frame>
    <description>Spasticity level of plantarflexors and dorsiflexors will be classified according to Modified Ashworth Scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in angular kinematic variables during gait</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 20 minutes (immediately post-application of cryotherapy or placebo)</time_frame>
    <description>The post-evaluation will be performed immediately after the end of the intervention (cryotherapy or placebo, applied for 20 minutes). A motion analysis system (Qualysis AB, Gothenburg, Sweden) will be used for kinematic data collection during gait. Passive reflective markers will be placed on the anatomical landmarks (anatomical markers) according to the International Society of Biomechanics. In addition, clusters will be placed on T4, L2 and bilaterally on the lateral portion of the thighs and legs. Following markers and clusters placement, a static posture (duration: 10 seconds) will be performed with the subjects in orthostatic position. Then dynamic data will be collected during walking in the self-selected comfortable speed (10 trials). The displacement (°) of the joints of the trunk, hip, knee and ankle during heel strike, stance phase and balance phase will be calculated during gait.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in linear kinematic variables during gait</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 20 minutes (immediately post-application of cryotherapy or placebo)</time_frame>
    <description>The post-evaluation will be performed immediately after the end of the intervention (cryotherapy or placebo, applied for 20 minutes). A motion analysis system (Qualysis AB, Gothenburg, Sweden) will be used for kinematic data collection during gait. Passive reflective markers will be placed on the anatomical landmarks (anatomical markers) according to the International Society of Biomechanics. In addition, clusters will be placed on T4, L2 and bilaterally on the lateral portion of the thighs and legs. Following markers and clusters placement, a static posture (duration: 10 seconds) will be performed with the subjects in orthostatic position. Then dynamic data will be collected during walking in the self-selected comfortable speed (10 trials) and linear kinematic variables during gait will be analyzed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in joint sense position (proprioception) during plantarflexion and dorsiflexion</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 20 minutes (immediately post-application of cryotherapy or placebo)</time_frame>
    <description>The post-evaluation will be performed immediately after the end of the intervention (cryotherapy or placebo, applied for 20 minutes). The joint position sense (proprioception) test will be performed on an isokinetic dynamometer. The participants will be seated and blindfolded. Initially, the dynamometer will move the foot toward references angles (for dorsiflexion or plantarflexion). Then, subjects will be allowed to sense the reference angle for 10 seconds before the ankle is returned passively to the start position. Subsequently, the foot will be moved passively by the dynamometer toward the reference position (for dorsiflexion or plantarflexion), and subjects will press a button in their hand that will stop the machine when they feel the position has been reached. The absolute error (in degrees) will be calculated as the difference between the indicated and reference positions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in passive resistance of plantarflexors and dorsiflexors</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 20 minutes (immediately post-application of cryotherapy or placebo)</time_frame>
    <description>The post-evaluation will be performed immediately after the end of the intervention (cryotherapy or placebo, applied for 20 minutes). The assessment of passive resistance for plantarflexion and dorsiflexion muscles will be performed on an isokinetic dynamometer. The equipment will passively move the foot in a series of 6 repetitions in the movements of dorsiflexion and plantar flexion. Both responses to slow and fast passive stretching will be evaluated. Passive torque peak (N.m) of plantarflexors and dorsiflexors of the ankle will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in torque during isometric contractions</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 20 minutes (immediately post-application of cryotherapy or placebo)</time_frame>
    <description>The post-evaluation will be performed immediately after the end of the intervention (cryotherapy or placebo, applied for 20 minutes). The isometric active torques (N.m) generated during plantarflexion and dorsiflexion contractions will be assessed using an isokinetic dynamometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in torque during concentric contractions</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 20 minutes (immediately post-application of cryotherapy or placebo)</time_frame>
    <description>The post-evaluation will be performed immediately after the end of the intervention (cryotherapy or placebo, applied for 20 minutes). The active torques generated (N.m) during plantarflexion and dorsiflexion movements will be assessed using an isokinetic dynamometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in torque during eccentric contractions</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 20 minutes (immediately post-application of cryotherapy or placebo)</time_frame>
    <description>The post-evaluation will be performed immediately after the end of the intervention (cryotherapy or placebo, applied for 20 minutes). The active torques generated (N.m) during plantarflexion and dorsiflexion movements will be assessed using an isokinetic dynamometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in electromyography assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 20 minutes (immediately post-application of cryotherapy or placebo)</time_frame>
    <description>The post-evaluation will be performed immediately after the end of the intervention (cryotherapy or placebo, applied for 20 minutes). Bilateral activation of soleus, gastrocnemius, tibialis anterior and peroneus will be assessed by electromyography concomitantly with isokinetic dynamometer and gait assessments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Muscle Spasticity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cryotherapy (ice pack)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A pack with 1000g of crushed ice without air will be placed for 20 consecutive minutes on a pre-delimited rectangular area with dimensions of 25 x 35 cm and will be fixed with a non-compressive elastic band. One strip of plastic paper will encompass the paretic leg of the subjects, avoiding direct contact from the skin with the ice pack.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (sand pack)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>For placebo application, the pack will be filled with 1000g of thin sand, in environmental temperature, so that the pressure exerted will be the same as the ice pack. All other experimental procedures will follow the same protocol as &quot;cryotherapy application&quot;.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cryotherapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cryotherapy (ice pack)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (sand pack)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic stroke (last episode of stroke occurred more than 6 months ago)

          -  Ischemic stroke

          -  Minimum score on the Mini Mental State Examination, according to the subject's
             educational level

          -  Spasticity level between 1 and 4 according to Modified Ashworth Scale for the
             plantarflexors

          -  Locomotion capacity of 2 to 4 according to Functional Ambulation Category (FAC).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diabetic peripheral neuropathy

          -  Adverse reactions to cold

          -  Intolerance to cold application

          -  Absence of sensibility to cold

          -  Diagnostic of Raynaud syndrome

          -  Ulcers or skin lesions

          -  Severe cardiovascular or peripheral vascular diseases (heart failure, arrhythmias,
             angina pectoris, and acute myocardial infarction)

          -  Other neurological or orthopedic diseases

          -  Toxin bothulinium injection 4 months or sooner

          -  Cognitive impairments

          -  Any history of joint or muscle injuries of the lower limbs

          -  Body mass index (BMI) greater than 28 kg/m²

          -  Pain during the any experimental procedure.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thiago L. Russo, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universidade Federal de Sao Carlos</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidade Federal de São Carlos</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Carlos</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>13565-905</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Federal de Sao Carlos</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carolina Carmona de Alcântara</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle Spasticity</keyword>
  <keyword>Cryotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Gait</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle Weakness</keyword>
  <keyword>Proprioception</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscle Spasticity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

