<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00894894</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SGI-0470-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00894894</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study to Determine the Maximum Tolerated Dose, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Oral MP470, a Multitargeted Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor, in Patients With Solid Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety Study to Determine the Maximum Tolerated Dose, Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics of Oral MP470, a Multitargeted Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor, in Patients With Solid Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Astex Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Astex Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multicenter, open-label, dose-ranging study in two parts: maximum tolerated dose (MTD)
      segment (the first 28-day course of MP 470) followed by long-term safety segment.

      MTD segment: follows standard oncology phase-I design; within-patient dose level adjustments
      prohibited; each patient participates in one of three stages:

        1. Accelerated Titration Stage

        2. Dose Escalation/De-Escalation Stage

        3. Dose Confirmation Stage
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Multicenter, open-label, dose-ranging study in two parts: MTD Segment (the first 28-day
      course of MP 470) followed by Long-Term Safety Segment

      MTD Segment: follows standard oncology phase-I design; within-patient dose level adjustments
      prohibited; each patient participates in one of three stages:

      Accelerated Titration Stage: 1 patient per dose level; first patient receives MP 470 at 100
      mg/day; subsequent patients assigned higher dose levels based on modified Fibonacci sequence;
      stage stops when any first-course DLT is observed or when grade-2 or greater MP 470-related
      toxicity is observed at 2 dose levels; dosing next patient prohibited until previous
      patient's MTD-Segment result is confirmed Dose Escalation/De-Escalation Stage: 3 patients per
      cohort; two additional patients enrolled to receive last dose level studied during
      Accelerated Titration Stage (first 3-patient cohort); subsequent 3-patient cohorts assigned
      dose level conditional on number of patients with first-course DLT in previous cohort; new
      cohorts enrolled until MTD is defined; dosing next cohort prohibited until previous cohort's
      MTD-Segment results are confirmed Dose Confirmation Stage: an additional 6-10 patients
      enrolled to receive MP 470 at the established MTD; patient accrual stops following Dose
      Confirmation Long-Term Safety Segment: patients continue receiving 28-day courses of MP 470
      until experiencing unmanageable toxicity or disease progression; within-patient dose level
      adjustments based on toxicity; DLT during preceding 28-day course mandates one-level dose
      reduction; one-level dose increase possible in absence of grade-3 or greater MP 470-related
      AEs during preceding 28-day course
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MP-470</intervention_name>
    <description>escalating daily doses of amuvatinib</description>
    <other_name>amuvatinib</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>amuvatinib (MP-470)</intervention_name>
    <description>escalating doses of daily amuvatinib</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The patient has a histological or cytological diagnosis of unresectable or metastatic
             solid-tumor cancer that is refractory to standard therapies or for which no standard
             therapy exists. Patients with refractory lymphoma (Hodgkin's or NHL) are also
             permitted to participate.

          2. The patient must read, understand and sign the IRB-approved informed consent form
             (ICF) confirming his or her willingness to participate in this trial.

          3. The patient is willing and able to participate in all of the required evaluations and
             procedures described in this study protocol, including swallowing MP 470 capsules.

          4. The patient is at least 18 years old.

          5. The patient is capable of fasting for 6 hours.

          6. The patient has Karnofsky Performance Status ≥ 70 (see Appendix 5).

          7. The patient has adequate bone marrow function evidenced, at minimum, by Hgb ≥ 9 g/dL,
             ANC ≥ 1.5 x 109/L and platelet count ≥ 100 x 109/L.

          8. The patient has normal renal and hepatic function evidenced, at minimum, by total
             serum bilirubin ≤ 2 mg/dL; AST and ALT ≤ 2.5 x ULN (upper limit of normal for the
             clinical laboratory), but ≤ 5 x ULN is acceptable if due to hepatic metastases; serum
             albumin ≥ 2 g/dL; and serum creatinine ≤ 2 mg/dL.

          9. The patient has normal cardiac function in the opinion of the investigator and
             supported by left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) 50% or greater on the screening
             echocardiogram, no significant abnormalities on the screening ECG (eg, left bundle
             branch block, III degree AV block, acute myocardial infarction or QTc interval &gt; 450
             msec) and no history of additional risk factors for torsade de pointes (eg, heart
             failure, hypokalemia or family history of Long QT Syndrome).

         10. The patient has recuperated from any prior surgical procedures including at least 4
             weeks rest since a major surgery.

         11. The patient does not have childbearing potential or has had a negative serum pregnancy
             test within the past 14 days.

         12. The patient does not have reproductive potential or has agreed to use and will use an
             approved method of contraception during the study and for 3 months following the last
             dose of MP 470.

         13. The patient is not lactating.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The patient has a life-threatening illness, medical condition or organ system
             dysfunction which, in the investigator's opinion, could compromise the patient's
             safety, interfere with the absorption or metabolism of oral MP 470, or put the study
             outcomes at risk.

          2. The patient has any serious, uncontrolled active infection that requires systemic
             treatment.

          3. The patient has a history of significant cardiovascular disease such as uncontrolled
             or symptomatic arrhythmias, congestive heart failure and/or myocardial infarction.

          4. The patient has received any anticancer agent(s) within the past 3 weeks, including
             investigational agents, chemotherapy (6 weeks for nitrosoureas or mitomycin),
             immunotherapy, biologic or hormonal therapy other than LHRH agonists.

          5. The patient has received radiation therapy within the past 4 weeks.

          6. The patient has a grade-2 or more severe toxicity (other than alopecia) continuing
             from prior anticancer therapy.

          7. The patient has active CNS metastases (primary brain tumors are permitted).

          8. The patient requires treatment with immunosuppressive agents other than
             corticosteroids that have been at stable doses for at least 2 weeks.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Translation Genomics Research Institute (TGen)/Scottsdale Clin.Researc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85258</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>So. Texas Accelerated Research Therapeutics-START</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 5, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 6, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 7, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 1, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 1, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 2, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MP470</keyword>
  <keyword>MP-470</keyword>
  <keyword>SuperGen</keyword>
  <keyword>Tyrosine</keyword>
  <keyword>Kinase</keyword>
  <keyword>Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid Malignancies</keyword>
  <keyword>Oncology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

