<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00891787</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>090135</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>09-CC-0135</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00891787</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Probiotic Ingestion and Isoagglutinin Titers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Probiotic Ingestion and Isoagglutinin Titers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Probiotics are oral food supplements containing live bacteria that may be beneficial to
           a person s digestion or general health. Probiotics are available as tablets, powder, or
           liquid supplements and are frequently used to supplement yogurt. They are available for
           purchase without prescription in most supermarkets.

        -  The bacteria in probiotic supplements commonly express sugar substances on their
           surface. These sugar substances are similar to group A and B blood group sugars, called
           antigens. These antigens determine a person s blood group. Researchers are studying the
           effect of probiotic supplements on the amount of blood group antibodies that are present
           in a person s blood.

      Objectives:

        -  To determine whether taking oral probiotic supplements increases anti-A and anti-B
           isoagglutinins (antibodies that cause red blood cells to clump together) in healthy
           subjects.

        -  To study the frequency of these effects and determine whether there is a dose-response
           relationship with probiotics and isoagglutinin titers.

      Eligibility:

        -  Healthy adults, 18 years or older, with type A, B, or O blood.

        -  Female participants need to have undergone menopause or have had a hysterectomy.

        -  Individuals are ineligible if they currently donate platelets; have a history of
           ulcerative colitis or Crohn s disease; have had major bowel surgery; are pregnant or
           capable of becoming pregnant; have a bleeding or clotting disorder; have a history of a
           blood disorder or immune deficiency; have a history of high-risk behaviors for exposure
           to HIV or hepatitis B or C; have diabetes; have received vaccinations in the past 2
           months, with the exception of the flu vaccine; are currently taking immunosuppressive
           medications; are currently taking antibiotics; or have taken probiotic supplements
           within the last 12 months.

      Design:

        -  Researchers will conduct the following tests throughout the 28-week study:

             -  Blood samples will be drawn every 2 weeks to measure the quantity of isoagglutinin
                titers.

             -  Depending on individual results, continued blood testing may be done every 3 months
                for 1 year, then every 6 to 12 months for up to 5 years.

        -  Study subjects will take a probiotic supplement at a dose of 1 to 3 caplets per day for
           18 consecutive weeks according to the following schedule:

             -  During the first 6-week period, the subject will take one probiotic tablet daily.

             -  During the second 6-week period, the subject will take one probiotic tablet twice
                daily.

             -  During the third 6-week period, the subject will take one probiotic tablet three
                times daily.

        -  Control group subjects will be followed in a similar manner but will not take probiotic
           supplements.

        -  The outcome measure is the percent of probiotic ingestors (the study subjects) versus
           control group subjects who experience a fourfold or greater rise in isoagglutinin titer.

        -  Study subjects will receive the following financial compensation: $10 per blood sample,
           for a maximum of $240 if all 24 samples are collected; $100 after completing the first
           6-week period; $150 after completing the second 6-week period; and $200 after completing
           the third 6-week period.

        -  Control subjects will receive $10 per blood sample, for a maximum of $150 if all 15
           samples are collected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Probiotics are over-the-counter dietary supplements which contain live bacteria. These
      bacteria are normally present in the gastrointestinal tract and may provide health benefits
      when added to a regular diet. Common reasons for taking probiotic supplements include
      repopulating the gut with lactobacilli after taking antibiotics and aiding in the treatment
      of inflammatory bowel disease, lactose intolerance, and gastrointestinal infections.

      The gut of neonates is sterile and becomes colonized with bacteria during the first few
      months of life. Many of these bacteria possess terminal sugar structures on their membrane
      components that are chemically similar to A and B blood group substances present on red
      cells. Antibodies to A and B blood group substances are not present at birth. Early in life,
      infants lacking A or B antigens on their red cells recognize the corresponding antigens on
      bacteria and form antibodies against bacterial sugars that cross react with the corresponding
      red cell antigen. These antibodies are known as anti-A and anti-B isoagglutinins. They do not
      cause disease, but are important in the transfusion of compatible blood units.

      Prior studies have suggested that probiotics consumed in large doses may provoke the
      formation of high titer isoagglutinins. This has relevance for transfusion of platelet
      components, in that, since ABO-matching of platelets is not necessary, minor
      ABO-incompatibility between donor and recipient is present in 10-20% of plateletpheresis
      components transfused nationwide. Plateletpheresis components derived from donors taking
      probiotics might contain high titer isoagglutinins, which could cause hemolytic reactions in
      group A and B recipients.

      The objectives of this study are (1) to determine whether taking oral probiotic supplements
      increases anti-A and anti-B isoagglutinins in healthy subjects, (2) to study the frequency of
      these effects and determine whether there is a dose-response relationship with probiotics and
      isoagglutinin titers.

      Study subjects will be asked to take a probiotic supplement at a dose of 1-3 caplets per day
      for 18 weeks. Blood samples will be drawn every 2 weeks during that time. Depending on
      individual results, continued blood testing may be done every 3 months for a year, then every
      6-12 months for up to 5 years. A group of control subjects will be followed in a similar
      manner, but will not take probiotic supplements. The outcome measure is the percent of
      probiotic ingestors versus controls who experience a four-fold or greater rise in
      isoagglutinin titer in association with a final titer of at least 128.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 28, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 6, 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 6, 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in isoagglutinin titer</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-response relationship between probiotic dose and peak change in isoagglutinin titer.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Isoagglutinin-Mediated Hemolysis</condition>
  <condition>Probiotic Toxicity</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Probiotic Supplement</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Subjects must be healthy

               2. Subjects must be greater than or equal to 18 and less than or equal to 70 years
                  of age

               3. Subjects must have an ABC blood group of A, B or O

               4. Laboratory values within established guidelines for participation in clinical
                  studies:

                  AST/ALT less than or equal to 2 times ULN; creatinine less than or equal to ULN;
                  hemoglobin greater than or equal to 12.5 g/dL (males and females)

               5. Subjects must be willing to sign consent to participate in the protocol

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. ABO blood group of AB

          2. Current apheresis platelet donor in the NIH DTM

          3. Current or past history of gastrointestinal disease or surgery including: Crohn s
             disease, ulcerative colitis, celiac disease, irritable bowel syndrome, gastric bypass
             or banding, esophagectomy, gastrectomy, small bowel resection, colectomy, and any
             history of gastrointestinal malignancy including pancreatic carcinoma

          4. Vaccination within the last 2 months, with the exception of the influenza vaccine

          5. A history of high risk behaviors for exposure to HIV, HBV, HCV, HTLV (no intravenous
             drug use in past 5 years, no male sex with males in last 5 years)

          6. Confirmed positive test result for anti-HIV-1/2, anti-HCV, anti-HTLV I/Il,
             anti-T.pallidum, or H BsAg.

          7. History of bleeding or clotting disorders

          8. History of hematologic malignancy

          9. History of inherited or acquired immune deficiency

         10. Diabetes mellitus (type I or II)

         11. Women of child-bearing potential

        I) Subjects currently taking immunosuppressive medications

        m) Subjects who have taken probiotic supplements within the last 12 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan F Leitman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snelling AM. Effects of probiotics on the gastrointestinal tract. Curr Opin Infect Dis. 2005 Oct;18(5):420-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16148529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>SPRINGER GF, HORTON RE, FORBES M. [Origin of anti-human blood group B agglutinins in white Leghorn chicks]. J Exp Med. 1959 Aug 1;110(2):221-44. Undetermined Language.</citation>
    <PMID>13673136</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>SPRINGER GF, ANSELL N, BRANDES W, NORRIS RF. Relation of blood group specific substances from bacilli and a higher plant to hemagglutinin formation. Bibl Haematol. 1958;7:190-5.</citation>
    <PMID>13499259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 10, 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 1, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Probiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>Isoagglutinins</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-A</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-B</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemolysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemolysis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

