<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01832402</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-1169</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00961</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01832402</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fentanyl Pectin Nasal Spray (FNPS) for Exercise-Induced Breakthrough Dyspnea</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Preliminary Study of Prophylactic Fentanyl Pectin Nasal Spray (FPNS) for Exercise-Induced Breakthrough Dyspnea</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Depomed</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if fentanyl nasal spray can help to
      control shortness of breath in patients who have been treated or are being treated for
      cancer.

      Fentanyl is commonly used for treatment of cancer pain. It may help patients with their
      shortness of breath as well.

      In this study, fentanyl will be compared to a placebo. A placebo is not a drug. It looks like
      the study drug but is not designed to treat any disease or illness. It is designed to be
      compared with a study drug to learn if the study drug has any real effect.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Groups:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be randomly assigned (as
      in the flip of a coin) to receive either fentanyl or placebo. You will have an equal chance
      of being assigned to either group. Neither you nor the study staff will know to which group
      you have been assigned. However, if needed for your safety, the study staff will be able to
      find out what you are receiving.

      Study Drug/Placebo Administration:

      Before you receive the study drug/placebo, you will walk back and forth in an indoor hallway
      for up to 6 minutes. You may feel out of breath or become exhausted. You may slow down, stop,
      and rest at any time you need to.

      After that, you will sit down and rest (for about 30 minutes).

      You will then be given the study drug/placebo by a nasal spray. You will then wait for
      another 20 minutes and repeat the walking test.

      After that, you will sit down and rest (for about 30 minutes).

      You will then be given the study drug/placebo again by a nasal spray. You will then wait for
      another 20 minutes and repeat the walking test for a third time.

      Study Visit:

      During your study visit, the study staff will collect information from your medical record
      about your age, sex, race, disease type, your performance status, any drugs you are taking,
      and possible causes of shortness of breath.

      Before each walk test, you will complete the questionnaires about your symptoms.

      Before and after each walk test, the study staff will record your heart rate, breathing rate,
      and the level of oxygen in your blood using a measuring device that will be clipped onto your
      finger. The study staff will also ask you 3 questions about how hard it is to catch your
      breath and your level of tiredness.

      During each walk test, you will be asked 6 times how hard it is to catch your breath. The
      distance you walked and how often and for how long you stopped will be recorded.

      Before and after the second and third walk tests, the study staff will ask you about any side
      effects from the study drug/placebo that you may be having.

      During the rest period between the walk tests, you may be asked several times how hard it is
      to catch your breath.

      After each walk test, you will also be asked to complete 4 tests of your mental abilities,
      including finger tapping, simple mathematics questions (addition, subtraction,
      multiplication, division), recall of numbers, and recall of objects. It should take 15
      minutes to complete these tests.

      At the end of the study visit, you will complete 1 questionnaire that asks if you think the
      study drug/placebo is helping you, and how satisfied you are with the study. It should take
      about 5 minutes to complete the questionnaire.

      Length of Study:

      You will be on this study for up to 3 hours. You will be taken off study if intolerable side
      effects occur during the study.

      This is an investigational study. Fentanyl is FDA approved and commercially available for the
      treatment of pain. Its use to help with shortness of breath is investigational.

      Up to 25 patients will be enrolled in this study. All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of Prophylactic Fentanyl Pectin Nasal Spray (FPNS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The main goal of this study is to determine the effect size for both fentanyl pectin nasal spray (FPNS) and placebo arm. Comparisons within arms performed using paired t-tests or signed rank tests. Summary descriptive statistics will be provided for demographics, outcomes, and other collected variables and will include proportions, medians, means, 95% confidence intervals, and other simple statistics as appropriate for the measure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Cancers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl Pectin Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fentanyl pectin nasal (FPNS) dose equivalent to 15-25% of the morphine equivalent daily dose (MEDD). FPNS administered intranasally 20 minutes before the second 6-minute walk test. Same dose repeated at least 30 minutes after the first dose and 20 minutes prior to the third and final 6 minute walk test. Walk test administered before first dose of FPNS. Participant will rest for 30 minutes after walk test. FPNS administered, then participant will wait 20 minutes before repeating second 6 minute walk test. After second walk test, participant will rest for 30 minutes. FPNS administered for second time, then participant will wait for 20 minutes. Walk test administered again for 6 minutes. Questionnaires completed at baseline, before each walk test, and at end of final walk test. Four mental ability tests administered after each walk test to include finger tapping, simple mathematics questions, recall of numbers, and recall of objects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo nasal spray administered intranasally 20 minutes before the second 6-minute walk test. Same dose repeated at least 30 minutes after the first dose and 20 minutes prior to the third and final 6 minute walk test. Walk test administered before first dose of placebo nasal spray. Participant will rest for 30 minutes after walk test. Placebo nasal spray administered, then participant will wait 20 minutes before repeating second 6 minute walk test. After second walk test, participant will rest for 30 minutes. Placebo nasal spray administered for second time, then participant will wait for 20 minutes. Walk test administered again for 6 minutes. Questionnaires completed at baseline, before each walk test, and at end of final walk test. Four mental ability tests administered after each walk test to include finger tapping, simple mathematics questions, recall of numbers, and recall of objects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fentanyl Pectin Nasal Spray</intervention_name>
    <description>Fentanyl pectin nasal (FPNS) dose equivalent to 15-25% of the morphine equivalent daily dose (MEDD) administered intranasally 20 minutes before the second 6-minute walk test. Same dose repeated at least 30 minutes after the first dose and 20 minutes prior to the third and final 6 minute walk test.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl Pectin Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Nasal Spray</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo nasal spray administered intranasally 20 minutes before the second 6-minute walk test. Same dose repeated at least 30 minutes after the first dose and 20 minutes prior to the third and final 6 minute walk test.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Walk Test</intervention_name>
    <description>Walk test administered before first dose of drug/placebo nasal spray. Participant will rest for 30 minutes after walk test. Drug/placebo nasal spray administered, then participant will wait 20 minutes before repeating second 6 minute walk test. After second walk test, participant will rest for 30 minutes. Drug/placebo nasal spray administered for second time, then participant will wait for 20 minutes. Walk test administered again for 6 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl Pectin Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>Questionnaires completed at baseline, before each walk test, and at end of final walk test.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl Pectin Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surveys</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mental Ability Tests</intervention_name>
    <description>Four mental ability tests administered after each walk test to include finger tapping, simple mathematics questions, recall of numbers, and recall of objects.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl Pectin Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of cancer

          2. Breakthrough dyspnea, defined in this study as dyspnea on exertion with an average
             intensity level &gt;=3/10 on the numeric rating scale

          3. Outpatient at MD Anderson Cancer Center seen by the Supportive Care Service or
             Thoracic Medical Oncology

          4. Ambulatory and able to walk with or without walking aid

          5. On strong opioids with morphine equivalent daily dose of 80-500 mg, with stable (i.e.
             +/- 30%) regular dose over the last 24 hours

          6. Karnofsky performance status &gt;=50%

          7. Age 18 or older

          8. Able to complete study assessments

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Dyspnea at rest &gt;=7/10 at the time of enrollment

          2. Supplemental oxygen requirement &gt;6 L per minute

          3. Delirium (i.e. Memorial delirium rating scale &gt;13)

          4. History of unstable angina or myocardial infarction 1 month prior to study enrollment

          5. Resting heart rate &gt;120 at the time of study enrollment

          6. Systolic pressure &gt;180 mmHg or diastolic pressure &gt;100 mmHg at the time of study
             enrollment

          7. History of active opioid abuse within the past 12 months

          8. History of allergy to fentanyl

          9. Unwilling to provide informed consent

         10. Patients who currently have no evidence of disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Hui, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 10, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 16, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced Cancers</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise-Induced Breakthrough Dyspnea</keyword>
  <keyword>Shortness of breath</keyword>
  <keyword>Fentanyl pectin nasal spray</keyword>
  <keyword>Placebo nasal spray</keyword>
  <keyword>Walk test</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>Surveys</keyword>
  <keyword>Mental ability tests</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyspnea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pectin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

