<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01839656</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ISIS 396443-CS3A</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-000621-12</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01839656</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Assess the Efficacy, Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Nusinersen (ISIS 396443) in Infants With Spinal Muscular Atrophy (SMA)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Assess the Efficacy, Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of Multiple Doses of ISIS 396443 Delivered Intrathecally to Patients With Infantile-Onset Spinal Muscular Atrophy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Biogen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Biogen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective is to examine the clinical efficacy of multiple doses of nusinersen
      (ISIS 396443) administered intrathecally to participants with Infantile-Onset Spinal Muscular
      Atrophy (SMA). The secondary objectives are to examine the safety and tolerability of
      multiple doses of nusinersen administered intrathecally to participants with infantile-onset
      SMA and to examine the cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) and plasma Pharmacokinetics (PK) of
      multiple doses of nusinersen administered intrathecally to participants with infantile-onset
      SMA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study was conducted and the protocol was registered by Ionis Pharmaceuticals, Inc.. In
      August 2016, sponsorship of the trial was transferred to Biogen.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 31, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 21, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 21, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>Yes</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of Participants Who Achieved Improvement in Motor Milestones as Assessed by Section 2 of the HINE at the Last Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1352 or Early Termination</time_frame>
    <description>Section 2 of HINE consists of 8 independent milestone categories. Within each of these categories, participants can progress from complete absence of a motor ability (the lowest level in each category) through multiple milestones (2 to 4 levels in each category) to the highest level within the category. Overall, there are a total of 26 milestones that can be achieved across the 8 categories. Improvement was defined as any of the following: 1. An increase from baseline of 2 milestones or more, or the achievement of pincer grasp in the voluntary grasp category 2. An increase from baseline of 2 milestones or more, or achievement of touching toes in the ability to kick category 3. An increase from baseline of 1 milestone or more in any of the remaining 6 categories: head control, rolling, sitting, crawling, standing, or walking.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free Survival at the End of Study</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 1638</time_frame>
    <description>Event-free survival was defined as the percent of participants who were alive and did not require permanent ventilatory support (defined as tracheostomy or the need for ≥16 hours ventilation/day continuously for at least 2 weeks in the absence of an acute reversible illness) Event-free survival was estimated using Kaplan-Meier methodology.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of Participants With Improved Motor Function at the Last Visit as Assessed by the CHOP-INTEND Motor Function Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 1352 or Early Termination</time_frame>
    <description>The CHOP-INTEND test includes 16 items structured to move from easiest to hardest with the grading including gravity eliminated (lower scores) to antigravity movements (higher scores). All item scores range from 0 (worst) to 4 (best). Total scores range from 0 to 64, with higher scores indicating better movement functioning. Improvement was defined as an increase in total CHOP INTEND score ≥4 points from baseline as of the last study visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in Neuromuscular Electrophysiology at the Last Visit as Assessed by the Change From Baseline in CMAP Amplitude</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 1072</time_frame>
    <description>CMAP is an electrophysiological technique that can be used to determine the approximate number of motor neurons in a muscle or group of muscles. A positive change from Baseline indicates that the number of motor neurons increased.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Experiencing Adverse Events (AEs) and/or Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 1352</time_frame>
    <description>AE: any unfavorable and unintended sign, symptom, or disease temporally associated with the study or use of investigational drug product, whether or not the AE is considered related to the investigational drug product. SAE: any AE that in the view of either the Investigator or Sponsor, meets any of the following criteria: results in death; is life threatening: that is, poses an immediate risk of death at the time of the event; requires in-patient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization; results in a persistent or significant incapacity or substantial disruption of the ability to conduct normal life functions; results in congenital anomaly or birth defect in the offspring of the subject (whether male or female); is an important medical event in the opinion of the Investigator or Sponsor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) Parameters of Nusinersen in CSF: Maximum Observed Drug Concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK Parameters of Nusinersen in Plasma: Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK Parameters of Nusinersen in Plasma: Time to Reach Cmax (Tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK Parameters of Nusinersen in Plasma: Area Under the Plasma Concentrations Time Curve From the Time of the IT Dose to Four Hours After Dosing (AUC0-4)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Muscular Atrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 (n=4)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 (n=4-16)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nusinersen</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered by intrathecal (IT) injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 (n=4)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 (n=4-16)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ISIS 396443</other_name>
    <other_name>Spinraza</other_name>
    <other_name>BIIB058</other_name>
    <other_name>IONIS SMN Rx</other_name>
    <other_name>ISIS SMNRx</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Genetic documentation of 5q SMA (homozygous gene deletion or mutation)

          -  Onset of clinical signs and symptoms consistent with SMA at ≥ 21 days and &lt;6 months
             (180 days) of age

          -  At study entry, receiving adequate nutrition and hydration (with or without
             gastrostomy), in the opinion of the Site Investigator

          -  Body weight &gt;5th percentile for age using Center of Disease Control and Prevention
             (CDC) guidelines

          -  Medical care meets and is expected to continue to meet guidelines set out in the
             Consensus Statement for Standard of Care in SMA (Wang et al. 2007), in the opinion of
             the Site Investigator

          -  Gestational age of 35 to 42 weeks and gestation body weight ≥2 kg

          -  Reside within approximately 9 hours ground-travel distance from a participating study
             center for the duration of the study. Residence &gt;2 hours ground-travel distance from a
             study center must obtain clearance from the Site Investigator and the study Medical
             Monitor

          -  Able to complete all study procedures, measurements and visits and parent or
             guardian/participant has adequately supportive psychosocial circumstances, in the
             opinion of the Site Investigator

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hypoxemia (O2 saturation awake &lt;96% or O2 saturation asleep &lt;96%, without ventilation
             support)

          -  Presence of an untreated or inadequately treated active infection requiring systemic
             antiviral or antimicrobial therapy at any time during the screening period

          -  History of brain or spinal cord disease that would interfere with the lumbar puncture
             (LP) procedures, CSF circulation, or safety assessments

          -  Presence of an implanted shunt for the drainage of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) or an
             implanted central nervous system (CNS) catheter

          -  History of bacterial meningitis

          -  Clinically significant abnormalities in hematology or clinical chemistry parameters,
             as assessed by the Site Investigator, at screening that would render the participant
             unsuitable for inclusion

          -  Treatment with another investigational drug (e.g., albuterol, riluzole, carnitine,
             creatine, sodium phenylbutyrate, salbutamol, valproate, hydroxyurea etc), biological
             agent, or device within 90 days prior to enrollment or anytime during the study. Any
             history of gene therapy or cell transplantation

          -  The participants parent(s) or legal guardian(s) is unable to understand the nature,
             scope, and possible consequences of the study, or does not agree to comply with the
             protocol defined schedule of assessments

          -  Ongoing medical condition that according to the Site Investigator would interfere with
             the conduct and assessments of the study. Examples are medical disability other than
             SMA that would interfere with the assessment of safety or would compromise the ability
             of the participant to undergo study procedures NOTE: Other protocol defined
             Inclusion/Exclusion criteria may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>210 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Biogen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nemours Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32827</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Hospital for Sick Children (SickKids)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1X8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.curesma.org</url>
    <description>Cure SMA</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://mda.org/disease/spinal-muscular-atrophy</url>
    <description>Muscular Dystrophy Association</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.rarediseases.org</url>
    <description>National Organization for Rare Diseases</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 22, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 22, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 25, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spinal Muscular Atrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>SMA</keyword>
  <keyword>SMN</keyword>
  <keyword>SMNRx</keyword>
  <keyword>ISIS-SMNRx</keyword>
  <keyword>ISIS 396443</keyword>
  <keyword>IONIS-SMNRx</keyword>
  <keyword>Spinraza</keyword>
  <keyword>Nusinersen</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Atrophy, Spinal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

