<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01832532</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CIN001Pilot 2GLP</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UL1RR026314</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01832532</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Study of the Effects on Sleep Disordered Breathing (SDB) When Using the Drug Liraglutide for 4 Weeks</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot 2: Glucagon-like Peptide-1 in Sleep Disordered Breathing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Research Resources (NCRR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, controlled study.

      The investigators are studying if the FDA approved diabetes medicine liraglutide (Victoza®)
      can improve sleep apnea in adults. This study is testing liraglutide in 20 adults without
      diabetes that are diagnosed with sleep apnea.The treatment group will be compared to a
      control group of 10 adults without diabetes who have sleep apnea but will not use
      liraglutide. Both groups will continue receiving standard of care for their sleep apnea as
      prescribed by their managing sleep physician throughout their study participation.

      Everyone in the study will have two study visits and one overnight sleep study for research.
      Subjects who have not had a recent sleep study but otherwise qualify for the study, will have
      an additional research sleep study to determine the baseline severity of their sleep apnea.
      The study visits include fasting blood samples and breathing tests (pulmonary function test
      and hypercapnic challenge). There will be weekly phone visits that include a questionnaire on
      sleepiness. The group that takes liraglutide will check their blood sugar two times a day
      while on the medicine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study aimed at measuring the change in obstructive apnea/hypopnea index in
      non-diabetic patients being treated for the first time with the glucagon-like peptide-1
      (GLP-1) agonist, Liraglutide. Sleep disordered breathing (SDB) consists of nocturnal alveolar
      hypoventilation and / or obstructive sleep apnea which result from abnormalities in upper
      airway tone and ventilation during sleep. The development of a new pharmacological treatment
      for sleep disordered breathing (SDB) could bring a breakthrough discovery that will impact a
      rapidly growing population of children and adults with this disorder. The investigators
      hypothesize that GLP-1 plays a central role in the improvement of SDB and that the
      administration of GLP-1 receptor agonist to patients with OSA will correct or improve SDB.

        -  Hypothesis 1: Administration of Liraglutide to patients with severe OSA defined as apnea
           hypopnea index ≥ 8 /hr. will result in a mean reduction in the index by a minimum of 50%
           after 4 weeks.

        -  Hypothesis 2: Administration of Liraglutide will result in significant increase in
           Orexin level, decrease in leptin, decrease in Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) score and
           increase in carbon dioxide (CO2) chemosensitivity.

      This is an open label, non-randomized, controlled pilot study. Subjects are heavy to obese
      non-diabetic adults that are diagnosed with sleep apnea. 20 subjects will be treated with
      liraglutide for 4 weeks and compared to 10 untreated controls.

      Study time points are baseline and 4 weeks post treatment. Study procedures include pre and
      post treatment: fasting blood for glucose, hemoglobin A1C (HbA1C), Orexin and leptin; ESS
      questionnaire; pulmonary function test and hypercapnic challenge. The procedures also include
      a post treatment overnight research sleep study to measure change in apnea index from
      diagnostic sleep study done previous to study enrollment or if needed, the baseline research
      sleep study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in apnea hypopnea index (AHI) from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4 week endpoint</time_frame>
    <description>Decrease of AHI at end of study in treatment group</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Disordered Breathing</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment group- liraglutide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment group- liraglutide daily use of drug. Titrated up from 0.6mg/day to 1.8mg/day or highest tolerated dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>liraglutide</intervention_name>
    <description>daily use of drug. Titrated up from 0.6mg/day to 1.8mg/day or highest tolerated dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment group- liraglutide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Other name- Victoza</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-60 years

          -  Diagnosis of severe obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) AHI ≥ 8 /hour of sleep

          -  Ability and willingness to comply with all protocol procedures e.g. correct handling
             of trial product, compliance to visit schedule

          -  BMI of ≥ 27

          -  For Cohort 1: If female of childbearing capacity, willing to use acceptable birth
             control during use of study drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A major medical condition such as renal or hepatic failure

          -  Treatment with glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) receptor agonists, dipeptidyl
             peptidase-4 inhibitors or insulin within the last 3 months prior to screening

          -  Diagnosis of type 1 or type 2 diabetes per judgment of the investigator

          -  BMI &lt; 27

          -  History of glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) equal to or above 6.5%

          -  Significant craniofacial abnormalities that may cause OSA

          -  Respiratory and neuromuscular diseases that could interfere with the results of the
             trial in the opinion of the investigator

          -  Use of central stimulants, hypnotics, mirtazepine, opioids, trazodone or drugs in the
             incretin family within the previous 3 months prior to screening

          -  Previous surgical treatment for obesity

          -  Familial or personal history of Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia type 2 or familial
             Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma

          -  Personal or immediate family history of thyroid cancer

          -  History of chronic pancreatitis or idiopathic acute pancreatitis

          -  History of Major Depressive Disorder or suicide attempts

          -  Systolic blood pressure equal to or above 160 mmHg and/or diastolic blood pressure
             equal to or above 100 mmHg

          -  History of alcoholism

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raouf Amin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 12, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 16, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sleep Apnea</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep Disordered Breathing</keyword>
  <keyword>liraglutide</keyword>
  <keyword>glucagon-like peptide-1 agonist</keyword>
  <keyword>Orexin</keyword>
  <keyword>leptin,</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Aspiration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liraglutide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucagon-Like Peptide 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucagon</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Manuscript is in progress.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

