<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03506646</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UNOmaha2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03506646</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dietary Nitrate Supplementation and Thermoregulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dietary Nitrate Supplementation and Thermoregulation During Exercise</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Nebraska, Omaha</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Nebraska, Omaha</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a double-blinded, randomized, crossover design study to assess the effects of dietary
      nitrate supplementation (beetroot juice) on peripheral artery disease (PAD) patients (ages
      50-85) diagnosed with Fontaine stage I or II PAD (as determined by vascular surgeon, Dr.
      Pipinos at UNMC). Exclusion criteria include: 1) experience severe claudication (leg pain) at
      rest or tissue loss due to PAD (Fontaine stage III and IV), 2) have limited walking capacity
      due to conditions other than PAD, 3) are already supplementing with a form of dietary
      nitrate, or 4) have an allergy to beetroot juice.

      Subjects will be required to visit the lab 3 times and will be randomized to receive either
      the supplement or the placebo for the 2nd and 3rd visits. There will be a washout period of
      14 days between the 2nd and 3rd visits. Visit 1 will take approximately 2 hours and the
      2nd/3rd visits will take approximately 1.5 hours. Total experimentation period will last
      approximately 15 days.

      Visit 1 will consist of non-invasive baseline testing including assessment of endothelial
      function (flow-mediated dilation by ultrasound imaging), maximal walking capacity (Gardner
      treadmill protocol), leg function (near-infrared spectroscopy, time to onset claudication,
      blood flow to lower extremities), and body core temperature (rectal thermometer). Visits 2
      and 3 will require consumption of either the supplement or placebo. The same tests from the
      baseline measurements will be performed for visits 2 and 3. There will be a recommended
      fourth visit, albeit not required, to review study results.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background and rationale The vast majority of the research involving dietary nitrate
      supplementation, namely beetroot juice, has been performed mostly on samples of healthy
      populations. A few clinical populations have been studied, including heart failure with
      preserved ejection fraction, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), and peripheral
      artery disease (PAD). In various populations, beetroot juice (BRJ) has been shown to decrease
      overall blood pressure, increase blood flow, increase muscle tissue oxygenation, improve body
      core temperature regulation, and increase exercise tolerance while decreasing the oxygen cost
      of exercise.

      Blood pressure BRJ supplementation has been shown to have an immediate effect on reducing
      blood pressure, with the most substantial decreases recorded within approximately 2.5-3 hours
      following supplement consumption [1, 2]. Systolic, diastolic, and mean arterial blood
      pressures showed decreases of 10.4±3 mmHg, 8.1±2.1 mmHg, and 8.0±2.1 mmHg, respectively, in
      healthy volunteers [2]. During exercise in healthy individuals, systolic blood pressure
      remained lower throughout varying exercise intensities [1]. Blood pressure was also reduced
      in heart failure with preserved ejection fraction patients. After an acute dose of BRJ,
      resting systolic blood pressure significantly decreased when compared to placebo conditions
      (BRJ 127 ± 14 mmHg; placebo134 ± 14 mmHg) [3]. A slight reduction in systolic blood pressure
      during exercise may be beneficial to PAD patients. Hypertension, or high blood pressure, is a
      major risk factor for the development of PAD [4]. Decreasing overall blood pressure and
      slightly decreasing systolic blood pressure in response to light activity would result in a
      decrease in unnecessary stress placed on the cardiovascular system at rest and during
      exercise.

      In a study involving PAD patients where 7 of the 8 participants were classified as either
      hypertensive or prehypertensive, BRJ consumption caused a significant reduction in diastolic
      blood pressure during rest that was maintained during exercise testing [5]. The study
      concludes that their data suggest that BRJ supplementation reduces blood pressure in PAD
      patients and this effect is maintained throughout exercise [5].

      Oxygen delivery and muscle tissue oxygenation Oxygen demand of working muscle increases as
      activity level increases the efficiency of oxygen delivery and oxygen utilization is crucial
      to muscle function, as well as a necessary increase in blood flow. This is especially
      important in PAD patients; increasing oxygenation to areas of skeletal muscle ischemia may
      increase physical function. By using near-infrared spectroscopy, muscle tissue oxygenation
      can be examined. During cycling in healthy males supplementing with BRJ, the right vastus
      lateralis muscle oxyhemoglobin concentrations were greater than that of the placebo condition
      [6]. While cycling at a moderate intensity, the male cyclists had a 13% reduction in
      deoxyhemoglobin concentration amplitude post-supplementation, which indicated a reduction in
      fractional oxygen extraction in the right vastus lateralis muscle [6]. These results suggest
      that BRJ supplementation may promote a better balance between localized oxygen delivery and
      utilization as an index of muscle fractional oxygen extraction [6]. Overall, BRJ
      supplementation has been shown to increase working muscle tissue oxygenation during exercise.

      In PAD patients, the oxygenation of the gastrocnemius with the worst PAD symptoms was
      monitored during a walking cardiopulmonary exercise test. Subjects showed a 48% reduction in
      deoxyhemoglobin concentration amplitude following BRJ supplementation, which indicated that
      fractional oxygen extraction was reduced [5]. During the exercise protocol, deoxyhemoglobin
      amplitude measures for the BRJ supplementation group at 100 and 200 seconds into exercise
      were reduced by 44% and 53%, respectively [5]. This response implies that BRJ supplementation
      in PAD patients improves a balance between local oxygen delivery and utilization as an index
      of muscle fractional oxygenation extraction by the working muscle. Increasing oxygenation to
      areas of skeletal muscle ischemia in PAD patients may increase physical function, but in
      order for this to be as efficient as possible, a dose-response relationship must be
      determined.

      Blood flow and thermoregulatory response Increases in activity and oxygen demand of working
      skeletal muscle necessitate increases in blood flow. In PAD patients, increasing blood flow
      to working muscle becomes difficult due to atherosclerotic occlusions in the lower extremity
      arteries. Research in healthy populations showed significant increases in forearm blood flow
      during hand grip exercise in hypoxic conditions following an acute dosage of BRJ in
      comparison to placebo (BRJ 373 ± 38 mL/min; placebo 343 ± 32 mL/min).

      Nitric oxide signals smooth muscle within the blood vessels (endothelium) to relax, which in
      turn increases blood flow to the localized area of vasodilation. In healthy populations,
      dietary nitrate supplementation increases vasodilation near the surface of the skin [7]. This
      increase in vasodilatory capacity and blood flow would create a stronger temperature gradient
      at the level of the skin, which would facilitate more efficient heat exchange as blood is
      cooled at the level of the skin (sweat evaporative, conductive, and convective cooling),
      causing decreased strain on the body.

      In PAD patients, nitrite-related nitric oxide signaling showed to increase peripheral blood
      flow to hypoxic tissue, which is supported by a decrease in gastrocnemius deoxygenation and a
      decrease in blood pressure [5]. However, during brachial artery flow mediated dilation, peak
      dilation did not significantly change (BRJ 42.6 ± 10.6 seconds; placebo 41.0 ± 10.39
      seconds), which suggested that endothelial production of nitric oxide did not change [5]. The
      unchanging vasodilatory response is likely due to the study not examining a BRJ dose-response
      relationship and its effects on vasodilation.

      Exercise tolerance and oxygen cost BRJ supplementation has been shown to decrease oxygen cost
      during low-intensity and moderate-intensity exercise. In trained populations supplementing
      with BRJ, significant decreases in oxygen cost during the beginning stages of exercise have
      been detected [8, 9]. Oxygen cost during walking was shown to decrease by approximately 12%
      following BRJ supplementation [8]. BRJ supplementation showed a 20% decrease in oxygen cost
      during moderate-intensity cycling in recreationally trained men [10]. This reduction in
      oxygen cost implies an increase in exercise efficiency in light-to-moderate level exercise,
      which in turn increases exercise tolerance. In high-intensity exercise,
      time-to-exercise-failure increased by 15% following BRJ supplementation, which is also
      suggestive of an increase in exercise tolerance [8].

      BRJ supplementation in clinical populations has also shown to improve exercise tolerance. In
      heart failure with preserved ejection fraction patients, submaximal endurance exercise
      improved by 24% following BRJ supplementation in comparison to placebo conditions (BRJ 449 ±
      180 seconds; placebo 363 ± 125 seconds) [3]. In patients with COPD, walking distance
      increased by 11% and time to exercise fatigue increased by 6% [11]. In PAD patients, BRJ
      supplementation showed an 18% (32 second) increase to onset claudication pain and a 17% (65
      seconds) increase peak walking time in comparison to placebo conditions [5]. These results in
      PAD patients show a substantial acute response to BRJ supplementation (~2 hours of
      consumption) during exercise testing.

      In various populations, BRJ supplementation has shown to decrease blood pressure, improve
      blood flow, increase muscle tissue oxygenation, safely maintain core temperature, and
      increase exercise tolerance. The effects of BRJ specifically in PAD patients showed decreases
      in blood pressure, increases in time to onset claudication and exercise tolerance, but did
      not show a significant effect on endothelial function. Examining a dose-response relationship
      is necessary to determine the responses to BRJ supplementation (endothelial function, leg
      function, and blood vessel oxygen carrying capacity) in PAD patients.In this study, a higher
      dose of nitrate (280 mL, 16.8 mmol nitrates) will be examined [12]. BRJ supplementation has
      shown reductions in blood pressure, increased muscle tissue oxygenation, blood flow, and
      thermoregulatory response. These mechanisms all contribute to improving overall
      cardiovascular function. If these results are observed during this study, PAD patients may
      experience less claudication pain as well as better tolerance to daily physical activities
      and exercise.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>1:1 randomized, cross-over, double-blinded</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Endothelial Function</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <description>Endothelial function will be assessed using flow mediated dilation to measure vasodilation in the brachial artery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Leg Blood Flow</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <description>Femoral and popliteal artery blood flow will be measured in both legs before and 40 minutes after supplementation by an ultrasound imaging system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle Tissue Oxygenation</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <description>Muscle tissue oxygenation will be assessed by using near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) during a maximal walking protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Walking Capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>maximum of 14 minutes each day for 2 days</time_frame>
    <description>Physical walking capacity will be measured during the Gardner treadmill protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thermoregulation</measure>
    <time_frame>maximum of 30 minutes each day for 2 days</time_frame>
    <description>Body core temperature will be monitored during the maximal walking protocol by using a rectal thermometer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Peripheral Arterial Disease</condition>
  <condition>Peripheral Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Beetroot juice-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be tested on two different days. The first day will be beetroot juice and the second day will be a placebo. Testing will take place approximately one hour after intake. There will be a 14 day washout period between testing days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo-Beetroot juice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be tested on two different days. The first day will be a placebo and the second day will be beetroot juice. Testing will take place approximately one hour after intake. There will be a 14 day washout period between testing days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Beetroot juice</intervention_name>
    <description>Beetroot juice serves as a mode of dietary nitrate supplementation. This will be a double-blinded, randomized, cross-over design to examine the effects of beetroot juice on endothelial function, leg function, and thermoregulation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Beetroot juice-Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo-Beetroot juice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. be able to give written, informed consent

          2. demonstrate positive history of chronic claudication

          3. have a history of exercise-limiting claudication

          4. have an ankle/brachial index &lt; 0.90 at rest

          5. have a stable blood pressure regimen, stable lipid regimen, stable diabetes regimen
             and risk factor control for 6 weeks.

          6. be between 50-85 years old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. pain at rest (severe claudication) and/or tissue loss due to PAD (Fontaine stage III
             and IV)

          2. acute lower extremity ischemic event secondary to thromboembolic disease or acute
             trauma

          3. limited walking capacity due to other conditions other than PAD

          4. a form of nitrate supplementation already included in their diet/regimen

          5. an allergy to beetroot juice
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vanhatalo A, Bailey SJ, Blackwell JR, DiMenna FJ, Pavey TG, Wilkerson DP, Benjamin N, Winyard PG, Jones AM. Acute and chronic effects of dietary nitrate supplementation on blood pressure and the physiological responses to moderate-intensity and incremental exercise. Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol. 2010 Oct;299(4):R1121-31. doi: 10.1152/ajpregu.00206.2010. Epub 2010 Aug 11.</citation>
    <PMID>20702806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Webb AJ, Patel N, Loukogeorgakis S, Okorie M, Aboud Z, Misra S, Rashid R, Miall P, Deanfield J, Benjamin N, MacAllister R, Hobbs AJ, Ahluwalia A. Acute blood pressure lowering, vasoprotective, and antiplatelet properties of dietary nitrate via bioconversion to nitrite. Hypertension. 2008 Mar;51(3):784-90. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.107.103523. Epub 2008 Feb 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18250365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eggebeen J, Kim-Shapiro DB, Haykowsky M, Morgan TM, Basu S, Brubaker P, Rejeski J, Kitzman DW. One Week of Daily Dosing With Beetroot Juice Improves Submaximal Endurance and Blood Pressure in Older Patients With Heart Failure and Preserved Ejection Fraction. JACC Heart Fail. 2016 Jun;4(6):428-37. doi: 10.1016/j.jchf.2015.12.013. Epub 2016 Feb 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26874390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Selvin E, Erlinger TP. Prevalence of and risk factors for peripheral arterial disease in the United States: results from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey, 1999-2000. Circulation. 2004 Aug 10;110(6):738-43. Epub 2004 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>15262830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kenjale AA, Ham KL, Stabler T, Robbins JL, Johnson JL, Vanbruggen M, Privette G, Yim E, Kraus WE, Allen JD. Dietary nitrate supplementation enhances exercise performance in peripheral arterial disease. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2011 Jun;110(6):1582-91. doi: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00071.2011. Epub 2011 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>21454745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bailey SJ, Varnham RL, DiMenna FJ, Breese BC, Wylie LJ, Jones AM. Inorganic nitrate supplementation improves muscle oxygenation, O₂ uptake kinetics, and exercise tolerance at high but not low pedal rates. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2015 Jun 1;118(11):1396-405. doi: 10.1152/japplphysiol.01141.2014. Epub 2015 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25858494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boegli Y, Gremion G, Golay S, Kubli S, Liaudet L, Leyvraz PF, Waeber B, Feihl F. Endurance training enhances vasodilation induced by nitric oxide in human skin. J Invest Dermatol. 2003 Nov;121(5):1197-204.</citation>
    <PMID>14708626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lansley KE, Winyard PG, Fulford J, Vanhatalo A, Bailey SJ, Blackwell JR, DiMenna FJ, Gilchrist M, Benjamin N, Jones AM. Dietary nitrate supplementation reduces the O2 cost of walking and running: a placebo-controlled study. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2011 Mar;110(3):591-600. doi: 10.1152/japplphysiol.01070.2010. Epub 2010 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21071588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsen FJ, Weitzberg E, Lundberg JO, Ekblom B. Effects of dietary nitrate on oxygen cost during exercise. Acta Physiol (Oxf). 2007 Sep;191(1):59-66. Epub 2007 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>17635415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bailey SJ, Winyard P, Vanhatalo A, Blackwell JR, Dimenna FJ, Wilkerson DP, Tarr J, Benjamin N, Jones AM. Dietary nitrate supplementation reduces the O2 cost of low-intensity exercise and enhances tolerance to high-intensity exercise in humans. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2009 Oct;107(4):1144-55. doi: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00722.2009. Epub 2009 Aug 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19661447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leong P, Basham JE, Yong T, Chazan A, Finlay P, Barnes S, Bardin PG, Campbell D. A double blind randomized placebo control crossover trial on the effect of dietary nitrate supplementation on exercise tolerance in stable moderate chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. BMC Pulm Med. 2015 May 2;15:52. doi: 10.1186/s12890-015-0057-4.</citation>
    <PMID>25934631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wylie LJ, Kelly J, Bailey SJ, Blackwell JR, Skiba PF, Winyard PG, Jeukendrup AE, Vanhatalo A, Jones AM. Beetroot juice and exercise: pharmacodynamic and dose-response relationships. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2013 Aug 1;115(3):325-36. doi: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00372.2013. Epub 2013 May 2.</citation>
    <PMID>23640589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Nebraska, Omaha</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Song-Young Park</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

