<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03501823</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16/0248</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03501823</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development of Photoacoustic Tomography</brief_title>
  <official_title>Photoacoustic Tomography of Normal and Abnormal Vasculature: Feasibility of in Vivo Measurements.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College, London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cancer is one of the leading causes of death internationally. When planning treatment for
      most cancers, it is important to know how far it has spread, including whether or not the
      cancer has spread to the local lymph nodes (LNs) because this affects the treatment strategy.
      This is termed &quot;staging&quot;, and can be achieved by medical imaging, such as by ultrasound,
      computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans. However, these are
      imperfect, and sometimes incorrect treatment decisions are made because of errors in staging
      by imaging. Improved accuracy would be of great clinical value for almost all solid organ
      tumours. An emerging technique to address this is photoacoustic tomography (PAT), a
      non-invasive, safe modality that relies on light and sound to generate images. Laser light is
      applied to the area to be imaged; this is absorbed, and causes the illuminated tissue to emit
      ultrasound waves. These can be detected and turned into an image by post-processing
      techniques similar to those used in conventional diagnostic ultrasound. By changing the
      wavelength of light used, the technique can be adjusted to optimise detection of various body
      components, including fat, water and both oxygenated and deoxygenated blood. This means the
      images can represent tissue composition and function rather than just anatomical structure.
      Hitherto, most work on PAT has been on healthy volunteers, and has focused on imaging the
      vasculature. We would like to see whether we are able to generate images of deeper structures
      inside the body. Initially we will focus on patients with vascular disease, whom we expect to
      have abnormal blood vessels; and subsequently we will attempt to image tumours and LNs in
      patients with cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cancer affects nearly 50% of individuals in the UK, and accounts for around 30% of all
      deaths. For almost all cancers, both prognosis and treatment fundamentally depend on the
      degree of spread at diagnosis i.e. tumour stage. For example, early stage bowel (colorectal)
      cancer confined to the bowel wall has a cure rate of nearly 95% whereas it is lower than 50%
      by the time it has spread to the lymph nodes (LNs). Similarly, patients with LN involvement
      from breast cancer may require more extensive surgery to remove the affected node, and have
      poorer long-term survival than patients without LN disease, even with small volumes of nodal
      tumour. The same is true for most other solid organ malignancies. So, as a general
      oncological principle, patients with advanced disease often require more aggressive treatment
      such as pre-operative (neo-adjuvant) chemotherapy, radiotherapy or both; and usually need
      more extensive surgery / radiotherapy when definitive treatment is instituted.

      Such therapeutic decision-making depends fundamentally on the advance knowledge of whether or
      not a particular patient has disease spread. This, in turn, requires a battery of tests
      designed to accurately pinpoint the extent and anatomical location of cancer dissemination
      throughout the body. This is typically achieved via a combination of medical imaging tests
      (such as ultrasound, computed tomography [CT], magnetic resonance imaging [MRI] and nuclear
      medicine techniques e.g. positron emission tomography [PET]) and tissue sampling (biopsy).
      Unfortunately, these techniques are imperfect, both for local staging of the primary cancer
      and its spread to local LNs. For example, in some cancers, over 50% of malignant LNs measure
      less than 10mm, the most commonly-used cut-off to define an abnormal lymph node using
      conventional medical imaging[9]. Therefore, for many tumours it is common practice to treat
      the entire regional LN group, either by surgical removal or radiotherapy. This strategy risks
      overtreatment for many and introduces the adverse effects associated with such extensive
      tissue damage. Regarding primary tumours, the precise extent of local tumour spread can
      determine whether or not a limited, local resection can be achieved rather than a more
      radical excision. A rapid, non-invasive, well-tolerated test that could improve local and
      regional nodal cancer staging would be of great clinical value, since it would immediately
      permit more accurate individualized treatment strategies.

      Photoacoustic tomography (PAT) is a relatively novel technology that may be able to help
      address this urgent clinical need. PAT relies upon the absorption of laser-generated light of
      specific wavelengths (often in the infra-red spectrum) by intrinsic components of the imaged
      tissue. Such absorption results in emission of sound waves, which are ultrasonic (i.e. very
      high frequency). Images can then be reconstructed in a similar manner to that employed by a
      clinical ultrasound scanner. By imaging at multiple wavelengths, tissue distribution of
      water, lipid (fat) and haemoglobin (in red blood cells and therefore blood vessels) can be
      mapped with extremely high resolution (~100 microns), raising the possibility that PAT can
      depict the small volume tumour that existing techniques cannot.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of PAT acquisitions in which the target lymph node is visible, as judged by the mean of both readers' qualitative scores</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Mean score of 2 or above</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dimension of smallest blood vessels resolvable by PAT</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Using full-width at half maximum, FWHM, to define the margins of a resolvable vessel</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">27</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peripheral vascular disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>All adult patients (aged 18 years and above) proven or highly suspected to have peripheral arterial or venous disease.
Ultrasound to be performed first in order to correct Photoacoustic tomography positioning.
Photoacoustic tomography to be performed after ultrasound</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oncology</arm_group_label>
    <description>All adult patients (ages 18 years and above) proven or highly suspected to have solid organ malignancy Ultrasound to be performed first in order to correct Photoacoustic tomography positioning.
Photoacoustic tomography to be performed after ultrasound</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Photoacoustic tomography</intervention_name>
    <description>A non-invasive, safe modality that relies on light and sound to generate images.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peripheral vascular disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Oncology</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Potentially eligible participants will be identified by the direct care clinical team at
        outpatient clinics, who will inform potential participants of the existence of the study
        and its broad rationale. Those who wish to consider participation in the study will be
        provided with a patient information sheet which includes the contact details of the
        research team.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Peripheral vascular disease:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults (aged over 18 years)

          -  Suspected or proven to have peripheral arterial or venous disease on the basis of
             physical examination, imaging or ankle-brachial pressure index.

          -  Able to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 17 or under

          -  Unable to provide informed consent (e.g. due to dementia or severe mental illness)

          -  Skin condition precluding safe and/or comfortable placement of an ultrasound or PAT
             probe (e.g. active infection, ulcerating tumour)

        Oncology Cohort All adult patients with either (a) superficial primary tumours or (b) solid
        organ tumours with a propensity to spread to superficial lymph nodes will be potentially
        eligible. These include head and neck cancers, breast cancers, skin cancers including
        melanoma, low rectal and anal cancer, lung cancer and cancers of the upper gastrointestinal
        tract.

          -  Adults (aged over 18 years)

          -  have either a proven diagnosis of malignancy or be under active investigation for
             malignant disease.

          -  Able to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shankar Kumar, BSc (hons) MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>020 3447 9070</phone>
    <email>shankar.kumar@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrew Plumb, BA, BMBCh, PhD, MRCP, FRCR</last_name>
    <email>andrew.plumb@nhs.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University College London Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW1 2PG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shankar Kumar, BSc, MBBS</last_name>
      <email>shankar.kumar@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Andrew Plumb, BA, BMBCh, PhD, MRCP, FRCR</last_name>
      <email>andrew.plumb@nhs.net</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen SL, Hoehne FM, Giuliano AE. The prognostic significance of micrometastases in breast cancer: a SEER population-based analysis. Ann Surg Oncol. 2007 Dec;14(12):3378-84. Epub 2007 Sep 26.</citation>
    <PMID>17899293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zackrisson S, van de Ven SMWY, Gambhir SS. Light in and sound out: emerging translational strategies for photoacoustic imaging. Cancer Res. 2014 Feb 15;74(4):979-1004. doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-13-2387. Epub 2014 Feb 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24514041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guggenheim JA, Allen TJ, Plumb A, Zhang EZ, Rodriguez-Justo M, Punwani S, Beard PC. Photoacoustic imaging of human lymph nodes with endogenous lipid and hemoglobin contrast. J Biomed Opt. 2015 May;20(5):50504. doi: 10.1117/1.JBO.20.5.050504.</citation>
    <PMID>26008874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moulding FJ, Roach SC, Carrington BM. Unusual sites of lymph node metastases and pitfalls in their detection. Clin Radiol. 2004 Jul;59(7):558-72. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15208061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang E, Laufer J, Beard P. Backward-mode multiwavelength photoacoustic scanner using a planar Fabry-Perot polymer film ultrasound sensor for high-resolution three-dimensional imaging of biological tissues. Appl Opt. 2008 Feb 1;47(4):561-77.</citation>
    <PMID>18239717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

