<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03501901</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UR14-004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03501901</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Urinary Tract Infections Caused by ESBL-producing Enterobacteria</brief_title>
  <official_title>Characteristics of Hospital- and Community-acquired Urinary Tract Infections Caused by ESBL-producing Enterobacteria in a Tertiary-care Hospital</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad Autonoma de Nuevo Leon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad Autonoma de Nuevo Leon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study was to compare the etiologic agents, the antimicrobial resistance
      rates, and the risk factors associated with a HA-UTI and CA-UTI among complicated and
      uncomplicated UTI patients in a tertiary-care hospital in Mexico. This study was performed
      according to the principles expressed in the Declaration of Helsinki with the approval of the
      Local Ethics Committee of the School of Medicine of the Universidad Autónoma de Nuevo León
      (UR14-004). All patients with a UTI and a positive urine culture (&gt; 100,000 UFC/mL) from
      March to October 2015 were included. The study was carried out at the Hospital Universitario
      &quot;Dr. José Eleuterio González&quot; hospital, a tertiary-care teaching hospital in Monterrey,
      Mexico. Identification and susceptibility antibiotic assays were performed to all isolates
      from positive urine culture.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study was to compare the etiologic agents, the antimicrobial resistance
      rates, and the risk factors associated with a HA-UTI and CA-UTI among complicated and
      uncomplicated UTI patients in a tertiary-care hospital in Mexico.

      This study was performed according to the principles expressed in the Declaration of Helsinki
      with the approval of the Local Ethics Committee of the School of Medicine of the Universidad
      Autónoma de Nuevo León (UR14-004).

      All patients with a UTI and a positive urine culture (&gt; 100,000 UFC/mL) from March to October
      2015 were included. The study was carried out at the Hospital Universitario &quot;Dr. José
      Eleuterio González&quot; hospital, a tertiary-care teaching hospital in Monterrey, Mexico. This
      hospital has 500 beds, serves a population of approximately 5 million people, and has an
      average of 250,000 medical consultations and 22,000 hospitalizations annually.

      A UTI was defined as the presence of symptoms related to the urinary tract, pyuria (≥10
      leucocytes per high-power field) and a positive urine culture (≥105 CFU/mL) of one
      uropathogen according to the guidelines of the Infectious Diseases Society of America (IDSA)
      and the European Association of Urology (EAU). Patients with urine cultures with
      significative counts of two or more bacterial species were excluded.

      Patients' charts were reviewed for clinical and demographic characteristics. The
      classification of UTIs as either complicated or uncomplicated, and hospital-acquired or
      community-acquired, was based on the IDSA and EAU criteria. Cases which could not be
      classified due to insufficient clinical information were excluded.

      Urine cultures were performed according to standard protocols. Species identification of all
      isolates was performed using MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry (Microflex, Bruker Daltonics,
      Billerica, MA). The drug resistance profile of all E. coli isolates was determined using the
      broth microdilution method for gentamicin, amoxicillin-clavulanic acid, aztreonam,
      ceftriaxone, ertapenem, ciprofloxacin, levofloxacin, nitrofurantoin,
      trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole, and colistin; except fosfomycin, in which the agar dilution
      method was used. The results were interpreted according to the Clinical and Laboratory
      Standards Institute (CLSI) criteria.

      Multidrug resistance (MDR) was defined as non-susceptibility to at least one agent in three
      or more antimicrobial categories. All isolates with resistance to at least one
      third-generation cephalosporin were evaluated for production of ESBL in E. coli using the
      double-disc test according to the CLSI.

      Categorical variables were expressed as frequencies and percentages. Numerical variables were
      expressed as a mean and standard deviation. Clinical and demographic characteristics were
      analyzed using the χ2 test for categorical variables and the t-test (or Mann-Whitney test in
      the absence of normal distribution) for continuous variables. Statistical significance was
      set at p &lt;0.05. Statistical analysis was performed with the SPSS software version 20.0 (IBM
      Corp, Armonk, NY).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 31, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>7 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibiotic resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>7 month</time_frame>
    <description>Antibiotic resistance test were perfomed to all Escherichia coli isolates</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">353</enrollment>
  <condition>Urinary Tract Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Antibiotic susceptibility test</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Strains of enterobacteria
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients with a UTI and a positive urine culture (&gt; 100,000 UFC/mL) from March to
        October 2015 were included. The study was carried out at the Hospital Universitario &quot;Dr.
        José Eleuterio González&quot; hospital, a tertiary-care teaching hospital in Monterrey, Mexico.
        This hospital has 500 beds, serves a population of approximately 5 million people, and has
        an average of 250,000 medical consultations and 22,000 hospitalizations annually.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients (&gt; 18 years old) with a UTI and a positive urine culture (&gt; 100,000
             UFC/mL) from March to October 2015 were included

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad Autonoma de Nuevo Leon</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Soraya Mendoza-Olazarán</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ESBL-producing enterobacteria</keyword>
  <keyword>hospital- and community-acquired urinary tract infections</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Tract Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

