<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03508206</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUAI2017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03508206</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Acute Effect of a Standardized Botanical Blend Rich in Polyphenols on Cognitive Functions in Healthy Students</brief_title>
  <official_title>Acute Effect of a Standardized Botanical Blend Rich in Polyphenols on Cognitive Functions in Healthy Students: Randomized, Placebo-controlled, Double-blind, Cross-over Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Activ'inside</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CIC SANPSY (USR CNRS 3413), Hôpital Pellegrin, Bordeaux, FRANCE</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital St André, Bordeaux, FRANCE</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Activ'inside</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Available literature suggests that flavanols-rich foods, and more especially monomeric
      flavanols-rich foods such as grape, can have an acute effect on cognitive functions via
      different mechanisms such as cerebral blood flow improvement.

      The objective of this study is to investigate the effect of a Standardized botanical blend
      rich in polyphenols (SBRP), on cognitive functions, together with endothelial function in
      healthy students. Moreover, in order to provide supportive evidence on the mechanisms and
      biological plausibility to the clinical effects of the product, appropriate biological
      parameters and circulating metabolites will be assayed.

      The study design will be a double-blind, randomised, placebo controlled, crossover study. A
      total of 30 healthy volunteers will be included. Each participant will receive a single dose
      of SBRP and placebo capsules, during 2 separate experimental visits and in a counterbalanced
      order. There will be a 1 week washout period between the 2 experimental visits. During each
      experimental visit, after a training battery volunteers will be administered a cognitive test
      battery (COMPASS) before product intake (baseline, B0) and 6 times after product intake (B1
      to B6, from 90 min post-dose to 160 min post-dose).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoint is the change (difference B4-B0) in the number of correct answers during the Serial Three Subtraction task (Serial Three) between the baseline battery (B0) and the 4th repetition of the battery after product intake (B4).</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B4=120 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>The Serial Three task will be administered through the computerized COMPASS battery (&quot; Computerised Mental Performance Assessment System &quot;). Serial subtraction tasks rely on working memory (executive function).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the number of correct responses from the Serial Three Subtraction task between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions N°1, 2, 3, 5 and 6 of the battery after product intake</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the number of errors from the Serial Three Subtraction task (Serial Three, COMPASS battery) between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions of the battery after product intake (B1 to B6);</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the number of correct responses from the Serial Sevens Subtraction task (Serial Sevens, COMPASS battery) between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions of the battery after product intake (B1 to B6);</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the number of errors from the Serial Sevens Subtraction task (Serial Sevens, COMPASS battery) between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions of the battery after product intake (B1 to B6);</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the reaction time from the RVIP test (&quot; Rapid Visual Information Processing &quot;, COMPASS battery), in milliseconds (ms) between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions of the battery after product intake (B1 to B6);</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the percentage of correct responses from the RVIP test (COMPASS battery) between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions of the battery after product intake (B1 to B6);</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min-dose to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the number of false alarms from the RVIP test (COMPASS battery) between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions of the battery after product intake (B1 to B6);</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min-dose to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the score of mental fatigue (COMPASS battery self-assessment using a Visual Analogue Scale) between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions of the battery after product intake (B1 to B6);</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min-dose to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the score of anxiety (COMPASS battery, VAS) between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions of the battery after product intake (B1 to B6);</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the score of vigilance/ alertness (COMPASS battery, VAS) between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions of the battery after product intake (B1 to B6);</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the score of cognitive performances (COMPASS battery, VAS) between the baseline battery (B0) and each of the repetitions of the battery after product intake (B1 to B6);</measure>
    <time_frame>B0= baseline (before product administration); B1 to B6: test battery repeated 6 times from 90 min to 160 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Differences B1-B0, B2-B0, B3-B0, B5-B0 and B6-B0;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of correct responses at the immediate free recall test before the first repetition of the test battery (B1) ;</measure>
    <time_frame>85-90 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Number of words properly recalled, among a list of 20 words, with no clue</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of correct responses at the delayed free recall test, after the last repetition of the test battery (B6) ;</measure>
    <time_frame>165-170 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Number of words properly recalled, among a list of 20 words, with no clue</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of correct responses at the delayed recognition task, after the last repetition of the test battery (B6) ;</measure>
    <time_frame>165-170 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Number of words properly recognized among a list of 20 words containing 10 words from the original list and 10 distractors</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes between the values measured in fasting conditions and those measured after the end of the cognitive assessments in flow-mediated dilation (FMD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Before product administration; 180 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Post-ischemic increase of brachial artery diameter, in % of the pre-ischemic diameter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes between the values measured in fasting conditions and those measured after the end of the cognitive assessments (i.e. 3 hours after product intake) in basal diameter of brachial artery;</measure>
    <time_frame>Before product administration; 180 min post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>Pre-ischemic diameter of brachial artery (mm)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SBRP arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Food supplement in hard gelatin capsule form containing a Standardized botanical blend rich in polyphenols (SBRP)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hard gelatin capsule form containing maltodextrin, with the same appearance as SBRP capsules</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SBRP</intervention_name>
    <description>SBRP capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>SBRP arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PLACEBO</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Graduate students (being either at the University or high school), with exam at least
             every 6 months and attending courses at the equivalent of at least 2 full days each
             week;

          -  Male and female subjects (at least 25% of each gender);

          -  Subjects aged 18 - 25 years (limits included);

          -  French native speaker;

          -  Healthy, and especially not suffering from the following diseases, either medically
             controlled or not:

               -  depression,

               -  anxiety disorders,

               -  diabetes (type I or type II),

               -  dyslipidemia,

               -  hypertension,

               -  any other cardiovascular disease,

               -  disorder of the thyroid function.

          -  Not consuming any food supplements (at time of V0 visit) and agreeing not to consume
             any food supplements until the end of the study;

          -  No consumption within the last 30 days (30 days before the V0 visit) of drug or food
             supplement likely to affect the studied parameters,

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) &lt; 30 kg/m2;

          -  Non-smoker;

          -  No use of narcotics nor cannabis within the last 7 days (the 7 days preceding the V0
             visit) and agreeing not to consume such products until the end of the study. The
             compliance with this criteria will be confirmed by a urine TetraHydroCannabinol (THC)
             test at the beginning of the testing visits (V1 and V2);

          -  Subjects capable of and willing to comply with the protocol and to give their written
             informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exam during the study period;

          -  Systolic blood pressure &gt; 140 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure &gt; 90 mmHg during the V0
             visit;

          -  Currently suffering from or personal history of psychiatric or neurologic disorders
             (examples: schizophrenia, depression, generalized anxiety disorder, epilepsia)
             according to the subject's self-declaration;

          -  Neuroleptic, hypnotic, anxiolytic or antidepressant treatment (whatever the reason)
             ongoing or stopped since less than 3 months;

          -  Anti-hypertensive, blood thinner or anticoagulant treatment (eg aspirin &gt; 325mg / day
             and prescribed as anticoagulant) ongoing or stopped since less than 3 months;

          -  Venotonic treatment or vasodilator treatment ongoing or stopped since less than 3
             months;

          -  Any other treatment (administered systemically or locally) that may affect the
             endothelial function (example: statins);

          -  History of moderate to severe traumatic brain injury and / or intracranial surgery;

          -  Personal history of Cerebrovascular Accident (CVA);

          -  Inflammatory bowel disease (examples: Crohn disease, coeliac disease, irritable bowel
             syndrome) likely to affect the intestinal absorption of the study product components;

          -  Progressive disease ongoing or resolved since less than one year;

          -  General anesthesia in the last 7 days or planned in the next 2 weeks;

          -  Restrictive or unbalanced diet (hypocaloric diet aiming at weight loss, vegan, …)
             according to the subject's self-declaration at V0;

          -  Excessive alcohol consumption : more than 2 glasses per day every day;

          -  Documented food allergy to one of the components of the study product;

          -  Psychological or linguistic incapability to sign the informed consent;

          -  Under legal protection (guardianship, wardship) or deprived from his rights following
             administrative or judicial decision;

          -  Participation in another biomedical study or during the exclusion period of a previous
             study;

          -  Having received, during the last 12 months, indemnities for clinical trial higher or
             equal to 4500 Euros.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wilfrid MAZIER, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33(0)5 35 54 56 73</phone>
    <email>w.mazier@activinside.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SANPSY (CHU Pellegrin)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <zip>33076</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Students, cognitive functions, memory</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

