<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03506828</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MFM-IRB, MD/17.11.08</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03506828</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phenol With Fluoroscopy Guided Radiofrequency Ablation of T2-T3in Palmar Hyperhidrosis.</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Adding Phenol With Fluoroscopy Guided Radiofrequency Ablation of T2-T3 Versus Thoracoscopic Sympathectomy in Palmar Hyperhidrosis.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mansoura University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mansoura University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary hyperhidrosis is a disorder characterized by excessive and chronic sweating in the
      absence of a sweating trigger. The disorder can be severe and interfere with normal daily
      activities of the patients.

      The gold-standard treatment in severe cases of hyperhidrosis is thoracoscopic sympathectomy
      betweenT2 and T4. These procedures are regularly performed in surgical units under general
      anaesthesia which needs special anesthetic considerations which is complex and associated
      with a lot of complications.

      Radiofrequency ablation of the sympathetic chain for treatment of hyperhidrosis is considered
      alternative to thoracoscopic sympathectomy. The procedure is safe, inexpensive and done under
      sedation with local anaesthesia in an outpatient setting, but its success rate is still
      significantly lower than endoscopic sympathectomy.

      The purpose of this study is to determine whether adding phenol 6% in a mixture with glycerin
      will increase the efficacy of fluoroscopy guided radiofrequency ablation of T2, T3
      sympathetic ganglia in hyperhidrosis in comparison to surgery without significant side
      effects to provide safe and effective method rather than surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary hyperhidrosis is a disorder characterized by excessive, chronic sweating in the
      absence of a sweating trigger. This condition must be differentiated from secondary
      hyperhidrosis, which is due to a lot of stimuli as infection, malignancy, drugs, anxiety,
      neurological and endocrine disorders.

      Primary hyperhidrosis is caused by hyperactivity of the sympathetic system. The etiology of
      the disease is unknown and appears simultaneously. It affects patients between 15 and 40
      years of age and may cause serious damage to their quality of life.

      The first line of treatment of hyperhidrosis is non-surgical methods as topical
      antiperspirants, anti-cholinergic and Botox, but the disadvantages of this treatment are
      short term relieve, so repetition of this treatment is required.

      Thoracoscopic Sympathectomy of the sympathetic chain between T2 and T4 is considered the
      gold-standard treatment in severe cases of hyperhidrosis. These procedures are performed in
      surgical units under general anaesthesia which needs special anesthetic considerations in the
      form of double lumen tube and one lung ventilation.

      Complications like pneumothorax, surgical emphysema, lung injury, lobar collapse,
      atelectasis, pleural effusion; bleeding, Horner's syndrome and neuritis have been described.
      Postoperative pain is more severe which can occasionally require opiate analgesia.

      Radiofrequency ablation of the sympathetic chain is considered alternative to thoracoscopic
      sympathectomy for hyperhidrosis. The procedure is safe, inexpensive and done under sedation
      with local anaesthesia in an outpatient setting, but its success rate is still significantly
      lower than endoscopic sympathectomy.

      McCormack et al. concluded that there are anatomical variations in the position of
      sympathetic trunk which are thought to be one of the main causes of failure and patient
      dissatisfaction after thoracic sympathetic neurolysis in hyperhidrosis.

      Previous studies tried to increase the efficacy of radiofrequency ablation of T2, T3
      sympathetic ganglia in hyperhidrosis via adding alcohol 100% to cover the anatomical
      variations of the sympathetic trunk. Alcohol is intensely painful during injection, so large
      volume of local anaesthetics is injected prior to alcohol. Also, it is hypobaric, water
      soluble and spread rapidly from the injection site, so large volume is required. In addition,
      the incidence of neuritis is very high with its injection.

      Phenol is primarily a local anesthetic at lower concentrations and becomes more neurolytic at
      higher concentration. Unlike alcohol, it is not painful on injection. It is prepared in a
      mixture with glycerin so it is highly soluble and hyperbaric and diffuses slowly into the
      local tissues.

      In this study, the effect of adding phenol 6% with percutaneous fluoroscopy guided
      radiofrequency ablation of T2, T3 sympathetic ganglia in hyperhidrosis will be evaluated. The
      study hypothesizes that adding phenol 6% in a mixture with glycerin will increase the
      efficacy of radiofrequency ablation of T2, T3 sympathetic ganglia in hyperhidrosis in
      comparison to surgery without significant side effects to provide safe and effective method
      rather than surgery for hyperhidrosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Single blind (Investigator) study</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Temperature of the ipsilateral palm of the hand</measure>
    <time_frame>For six months after the procedure</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative pain scores</measure>
    <time_frame>For 24 hours after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>The level of pain based on visual analog scale (VAS) (where 0= no pain and 10= worst pain) will be assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>postoperative cumulative analgesic consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>For 24 hours after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Total amount of post-operative analgesics (ketorolac and fentanyl) will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of pneumothorax</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be transferred to the PACU and chest x ray will be done to exclude pneumothorax.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of compensatory hyperhidrosis</measure>
    <time_frame>For six months after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Compensatory hyperhidrosis defined as excessive sweating after the procedures in areas of the body that previously did not sweat mainly in axilla, back, and lower limbs and will be assessed and classified into 4 degrees Not present, Mild Sometimes noticeably sweaty and sometimes not sweaty, Moderate Always aware but not troublesome, or troublesome but controlled by clothing, and Sever Causes embarrassment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>For six months after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction with their procedure will be measured with a four-grade scale: 0 (not satisfied), 1 (slightly satisfied), 2 (satisfied) and 3 (very satisfied)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">82</enrollment>
  <condition>Excessive Sweating of the Hands</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical sympathectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients in this group will have standard surgical procedure</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Radiofrequency ablation with phenol injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>patient will receive radiofrequency ablation of T2 and T3 sympathetic ganglia + phenol 6% (0.5ml) injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgical sympathectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>thoracoscopic sympathectomy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical sympathectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiofrequency ablation with phenol injection</intervention_name>
    <description>All patient in this group will have radiofrequency ablation of T2 and T3 sympathetic ganglia with phenol injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Radiofrequency ablation with phenol injection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status grades I and II

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient refusal.

          -  Hepatic impairement.

          -  Renal impairment.

          -  Neuromuscular diseases.

          -  History of opioid abuse.

          -  Coagulopathies.

          -  Cardiovascular diseases.

          -  Respiratory diseases.

          -  Previously failed cases either after percutaneous or thoracoscopic sympathectomy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gamal M El Morsy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Professor of Anesthesia and Surgical Intensive Care</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mansoura University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mansourah</city>
        <state>DK</state>
        <zip>05</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperhidrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Phenol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

