<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03506100</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ESE IPCB_01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03506100</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Water Walking on Spirometry Values</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Swimming and Swimming Complemented With Water Walking on Spirometry Values</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Instituto Politécnico de Castelo Branco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Instituto Politécnico de Castelo Branco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study was verify if there are differences in spirometry values in
      children aged between 6 and 12 years who practice swimming complemented with water walking at
      the end of each session and those who only practice swimming.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Spirometry is a standard pulmonary function test that measures how an individual inhales or
      exhales volumes of air as a function time. It is the most important and most frequently
      performed pulmonary function testing procedure, having become indispensable for the
      prevention, diagnosis and evaluation of various respiratory impairments. However, there have
      been only a few studies addressing the effect of physical activity on pulmonary function test
      results and investigating the association between body composition and respiratory parameters
      in sports activities [1,2,3]. The objective of this study was verify if there are differences
      in spirometry values in children aged between 6 and 12 years who practice swimming
      complemented with water walking at the end of each session and those who only practice
      swimming. In this study participated 28 subjects (mean age, 7.68 ± 1.16 years) and was
      divided into two groups: swimming group (SG) (N=9) and swimming complemented with water
      walking group (SWWG) (N=19). The study was performed in 12 weeks with 3 moments of evaluation
      (M1, M2 and M3) , with two sessions per week of 45 minutes each, we wanted to identify the
      benefits in pulmonary function - Forced Vital Capacity (FVC), Forced Expiratory Volume in 1
      second (FEV1) and Peak Expiratory Flow (PEF). The water walking activity occurred in the end
      of each session for 6 minutes, performed in straight line with the water level at the
      children's chest. The spirometry tests were realized with the microQuark Spirometer®. For the
      analysis of the results, we used descriptive statistics, the Shapiro Wilk test for testing
      the normality of the sample and for the inferential statistics the Mann-Whitney tests,
      Friedman's Anova, and d-Cohen for the magnitude of effect.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 17, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 21, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>spirometric values</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The spirometry tests were realized with the microQuark Spirometer®.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Influence of Water Walking in Spirometric Values</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>water walking in spirometric values</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental: practice swimming complemented with water walking</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Water Walking</intervention_name>
    <description>Practice swimming complemented with water walking at the end of each session and those who only practice swimming. In this study participated 28 subjects (mean age, 7.68 ± 1.16 years) and was divided into two groups: swimming group (SG) (N=9) and swimming complemented with water walking group (SWWG) (N=19). The study was performed in 12 weeks with 3 moments of evaluation (M1, M2 and M3) , with two sessions per week of 45 minutes each, we wanted to identify the benefits in pulmonary function - Forced Vital Capacity (FVC), Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 second (FEV1) and Peak Expiratory Flow (PEF). The water walking activity occurred in the end of each session for 6 minutes, performed in straight line with the water level at the children's chest. The spirometry tests were realized with the microQuark Spirometer®.</description>
    <arm_group_label>water walking in spirometric values</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  classes of the level of adaptation to the aquatic environment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Students who did not belong to this age group, that is, less than 6 years old or over
             12, who attended classes only once a week, were athletes at a competitive level, and
             children with a 6 months and / or more than 12 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pedro Mendes, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Instituto Politécnico de Castelo Branco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Instituto Politécnico de Castelo Branco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pedro Alexandre Duarte Mendes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spirometry</keyword>
  <keyword>swimming</keyword>
  <keyword>water walking</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

