<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03505983</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB #01603</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Award Number W81XWH-17-2-0014</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03505983</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Criteria for Advanced Prosthetic Foot Prescription</brief_title>
  <official_title>Criteria for Advanced Prosthetic Foot Prescription</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA New York Harbor Healthcare System</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>James A. Haley Veterans Administration Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VA Puget Sound Health Care System</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA New York Harbor Healthcare System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to develop criteria for prosthetic foot prescription for
      Veterans and Service Members with transtibial limb loss. The objectives are to: 1) Determine
      the appropriate functional outcome tests and measures to support the prescription of a type
      of Energy Storing and Returning (ESR) non-articulating, articulating or active plantarflexion
      prosthetic ankle-foot for a Veteran or Service Member with transtibial limb loss. 2)
      Correlate patient goals and subjective measures with objective data to determine the
      appropriate prosthetic ankle-foot category that will facilitate the greatest overall function
      to the user. 3) Develop criteria for the appropriate prescription of non-articulating ESR,
      articulating ESR, and active plantar flexion ESR ankle-foot units.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 6-min walk distance for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The 6-minute walk test measures the distance an individual can walk in 6 minutes without help or encouragement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in TUG times for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The TUG measures the time taken by an individual to stand up from a standard arm chair, walk a distance of 10 feet, turn, walk back to the chair, and sit down.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 4SST times for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The four-square step test is a higher order complex task assessing dynamic balance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in AmpPRO for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The AmpPro is a 21-item instrument designed to measure basic prosthetic mobility of individuals with lower extremity amputation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Stair Assessment Index (SAI) for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The SAI is a rated qualitative scale on how an individual with lower limb amputation negotiates up and down a staircase.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hill Assessment Index (HAI) for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The HAI is a rated qualitative scale on how an individual with lower limb amputation negotiates up and down a ramp.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Gait Evaluation for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Biomechanical evaluation of gait.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Prosthetic Evaluation Questionnaire (PEQ) score for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The PEQ is a self-report Visual Analog Scale questionnaires for persons with lower limb amputations who use a prosthesis. It consists of 9 validated subscales. They are used to evaluate the prosthesis and life with the prosthesis. Most questions in the PEQ use a visual analog scale format. Each visual analog scale is scored as a continuous numerical variable measured as the distance in millimeters from the left endpoint of the line to the point at which the respondent's mark crosses the line. Each line is 100 mm long and is always measured from the left (0-100). The questions are all worded so that a higher number (toward the right) will correspond with a more positive response. Subscale scores are calculated by computing the average (arithmetic mean) of all the questions which make up that particular scale. Only subscales are calculated. A total combined score is not calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Short Form (SF)-12 for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-12 is a questionnaire used to measure the relationship between physical and mental health functioning and the social determinants of health. It is a self-reported questionnaire, on a rating scale, called a Likert Scale. The participant taking this questionnaire will check one response box per question. Physical and Mental Health Composite Scores (PCS &amp; MCS) are computed using the scores of twelve questions and range from 0 to 100, where a zero score indicates the lowest level of health measured by the scales and 100 indicates the highest level of health. Age-specific mean difference score (difference score) is calculated and is the amount by which a person's score differs from their age group's mean score. By looking at difference scores, it is clear whether a person is more or less healthy than other persons in his or her comparison group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in OPUS for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>OPUS is a set of self-report instruments that assess functional status, quality of life, and satisfaction with devices and services that can be used in an orthotics and prosthetics clinic. The OPUS Health Quality of Life Score is the sum of the scores for the 23 items (0 - 92). The OPUS lower extremity total score is the sum of the scores for the 20 items (0 - 80). OPUS Satisfaction With Device Score is the sum of the scores for items 1-11 (11 - 55). Satisfaction With Services Score is the sum of the scores for items 12-21 (10 - 50). A higher score indicates a better outcome for all measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Final Visit Guided Interview</measure>
    <time_frame>Administered one time at Final Visit, which will occur 7 weeks after enrollment.</time_frame>
    <description>Final Visit questionnaire to evaluate subjective preferences. This is a free response questionnaire, in which the participant can answer in open-ended format.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in responses to Prosthetic Evaluation Questionnaire-Addendum (PEQ-A) for each prosthetic foot type</measure>
    <time_frame>Once per week, at Week 1, Week 2, and Week 3 after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>The PEQ-A is a free response 2-question questionnaire, in which the participant is asked whether and how many times they had experienced a fall or near-fall in the previous week using the particular prosthetic foot.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Prosthesis User</condition>
  <condition>Amputation; Traumatic, Limb, Lower</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ESR Prosthetic Foot First</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subject will start with an energy storing and returning (ESR) prosthetic foot first for 1 week, then will complete an additional week with an articulating ESR prosthetic foot, and a powered prosthetic foot for 1 week. During the final 4 weeks of the study, all prosthetic feet will be available and subjects can self-select which foot to use.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Articulating ESR Prosthetic Foot First</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will start with an Articulating ESR prosthetic foot first for 1 week, then will complete an additional week with the ESR prosthetic foot, and a powered prosthetic foot for 1 week.The final 4 weeks, all prosthetic feet will be available for use and subjects will self-select which foot to use for daily activities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Powered Prosthetic Foot First</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will start with a powered prosthetic foot first for 1 week, then will complete an additional week with an articulating ESR prosthetic foot and an ESR prosthetic foot for 1 week. The final 4 weeks, all prosthetic feet will be available for use and subjects will self-select which foot to use for daily activities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ESR Prosthetic Foot First</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will start with an ESR foot first for 1 week, then will complete an additional week with an articulating ESR foot and a powered foot for 1 week. The final 4 weeks of the study, all prosthetic feet will be available and subjects can self-select which foot to use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ESR Prosthetic Foot First</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Articulating ESR Prosthetic Foot First</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will start with an articulating ESR foot first for 1 week, then will complete an additional week with an articulating ESR foot and a powered foot for 1 week. The final 4 weeks of the study, all prosthetic feet will be available and subjects can self-select which foot to use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Articulating ESR Prosthetic Foot First</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Odyssey (College Park)</other_name>
    <other_name>Elan (Endolite)</other_name>
    <other_name>MotionFoot (Fillauer)</other_name>
    <other_name>Proflex (Ossur)</other_name>
    <other_name>Echelon (Endolite)</other_name>
    <other_name>Tribute (College Park)</other_name>
    <other_name>Proprio (Ossur)</other_name>
    <other_name>TruStep (College Park)</other_name>
    <other_name>Kinterra (Freedom Innovations)</other_name>
    <other_name>Flex Foot Balance with DP Flexion (Ossur)</other_name>
    <other_name>Raize (Fillauer)</other_name>
    <other_name>Echelon VT (Endolite)</other_name>
    <other_name>Triton Smart Ankle (Otto Bock)</other_name>
    <other_name>Venture (College Park)</other_name>
    <other_name>Kinnex (Freedom Innovations)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Powered Prosthetic Foot First</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will start with a powered prosthetic foot first for 1 week, then will complete an additional week with an articulating ESR foot and an ESR foot for 1 week. The final 4 weeks of the study, all prosthetic feet will be available and subjects can self-select which foot to use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Powered Prosthetic Foot First</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>emPOWER (Otto Bock)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  DEERS eligible Veteran or Service Member with unilateral transtibial amputation

          -  Currently using an Energy Storing and Returning prosthetic foot with a well-fitting
             socket as a primary or back-up prosthesis

          -  Achieved a &quot;No Helper&quot; score of 5, 6, or 7 on the Functional Independence Measure
             (FIM) for the locomotion mobility items

          -  Has a minimum clearance of 8 ¾ inches to accommodate all feet

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has active wounds/ulcers or significant musculoskeletal comorbidities on their intact
             limb that would impair their ability to participate in all functional outcome measures

          -  Has any comorbidity that results in rapid limb volume changes (i.e. end stage renal
             disease with dialysis),

          -  Weighs more than 275 pounds, the maximum product weight load

          -  Is unable or unwilling to comply with all research visits

          -  Has cognitive deficit(s) or mental health pathology limiting a subject's ability to
             participate fully in the study

          -  Women who are pregnant. This will be determined by asking the participant if they are
             pregnant or if they believe that they may be pregnant. This question will only be
             asked at inclusion, as biomechanical changes will only be impacted if the woman is in
             the 2nd or 3rd trimester, and will not be impacted if the participant becomes pregnant
             while in the study.

          -  Poorly fitting socket

          -  Potential participants with knee flexion contracture &gt; 5 degrees

          -  Vision loss that requires use of an assistive device for gait

          -  Upper Limb Amputation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jason Maikos, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Director, VISN 2 Gait and Motion Analysis Laboratory</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Hyre, MS</last_name>
    <phone>212-951-3339</phone>
    <email>michael.hyre@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA New York Harbor Healthcare System</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Hyre, MS</last_name>
      <phone>212-951-3339</phone>
      <email>michael.hyre@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jason Maikos, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>VA New York Harbor Healthcare System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jason Maikos</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, VISN 2 Gait and Motion Analysis Laboratory</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prosthetic Limb Design</keyword>
  <keyword>Prosthesis Fitting</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amputation, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leg Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

