<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03504007</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-001404</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03504007</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Registry of Patients Prescribed Anticoagulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mayo Clinic Registry of Patients Prescribed Anticoagulation for Acute Venous Thromboembolic</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Gonda Vascular Center- Thrombophilia Clinic at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota
      utilizes a standardized, guideline-directed, yet patient-oriented approach for treating
      patients diagnosed with venous thrombo embolism (VTE).

      The rates of VTE recurrence, major bleeding, clinically relevant non-major bleeding (CRNMB)
      and survival in patients treated with anticoagulation for acute VTE are assessed during
      prospective observation. VTE cases include an acute deep vein thrombosis (DVT) of lower or
      upper extremities, splanchnic veins, gonadal, renal, cerebral veins thrombosis and pulmonary
      embolism (PE). Therapy includes the whole spectrum of FDA approved anticoagulants such as
      &quot;classic&quot; agents: warfarin and heparinoids and the newer direct oral anticoagulants (DOACs)
      such as rivaroxaban, dabigatran, apixaban, and edoxaban.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      When a patient has positive testing for acute VTE the radiologist interpreting the study
      contacts the Thrombophilia Center and the patient is immediately evaluated. Standardized
      information about guidelines endorsed anticoagulation therapy is provided in a uniform
      fashion with a standardized script for providers and a short summary table for the patient.
      This initial review also includes patient-specific cost information by contacting a pharmacy
      service phone-line. Patients with cancer-related VTE are counselled regarding the guideline
      endorsed use of low molecular heparin (LMWH) as the preferred option of anticoagulation and
      available data on DOACs. After the shared decision making is complete, the prescription is
      promptly filled at the pharmacy located within the same building, with the first dose
      administered within the ensuing hour. For patients with acute VTE diagnosed after hours,
      evaluation is accomplished in the Emergency Department; one dose of LMWH is administered and
      the patient is referred the next day to the Thrombophilia Clinic.

      Patients with symptomatic PE or extensive symptomatic iliofemoral DVT are referred for prompt
      hospitalization. While in the hospital, they are consulted by a Vascular Medicine service and
      an appropriate follow up visit at the Thrombophilia Clinic is arranged. For patients with
      asymptomatic or minimally symptomatic pulmonary embolism (simplified Pulmonary Embolism
      Severity Index (PESI) score of 0), outpatient management is offered. All patients with
      cancer-associated PE are referred for lower extremity duplex ultrasound, and if symptomatic
      or if a central venous catheter is in place, also for upper extremity venous assessment.

      Demographic and clinical data are entered into a REDCap. The registry is maintained on
      institutional servers, which are backed-up nightly and protected in controlled computer room
      with uninterrupted power supplies, data will never reside on a desktop computer system.
      Transfer of registry data will occur inside the Mayo Clinic firewall via our integrated high
      speed network. Analysis will be done using the most current version of SAS® software.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of symptomatic, recurrent VTE. Incidence of major bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Recurrent VTE clearly new compared to previous VTE. Major bleeding by ISTH definition</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Deep Vein Thrombosis</condition>
  <condition>Acute Pulmonary Embolism</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Mayo Clinic patients prescribed anticoagulation for treatment of acute DVT or PE. Treatment
        with all FDA-approved anticoagulants are captured in the database
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        • VTE seen at Thrombophilia Clinic and treatment with anti-coagulant is started within 14
        days of VTE diagnosis date.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients already on anticoagulation for other reasons or enrolled into anticoagulation
             clinical trials.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Waldemar E Wysokinski, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dalene M Bott Kitslaar, APRN CNP</last_name>
    <phone>507-266-3964</phone>
    <email>Bottkitslaar.Dalene@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Waldemar E Wysokinski, MD</last_name>
    <phone>507-266-1970</phone>
    <email>Wysokinski.Waldemar@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Waldemar Wysokinski, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <phone>507-266-1970</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Waldemar Wysokinski, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janczak DT, Mimier MK, McBane RD, Kamath PS, Simmons BS, Bott-Kitslaar DM, Lenz CJ, Vargas ER, Hodge DO, Wysokinski WE. Rivaroxaban and Apixaban for Initial Treatment of Acute Venous Thromboembolism of Atypical Location. Mayo Clin Proc. 2018 Jan;93(1):40-47. doi: 10.1016/j.mayocp.2017.10.007. Epub 2017 Dec 6.</citation>
    <PMID>29217335</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bott-Kitslaar DM, Saadiq RA, McBane RD, Loprinzi CL, Ashrani AA, Ransone TR, Wolfgram AA, Berentsen MM, Wysokinski WE. Efficacy and Safety of Rivaroxaban in Patients with Venous Thromboembolism and Active Malignancy: A Single-Center Registry. Am J Med. 2016 Jun;129(6):615-9. doi: 10.1016/j.amjmed.2015.12.025. Epub 2016 Jan 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26797081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 12, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Waldemar E. Wysokinski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Deep Vein Thrombosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Embolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Apixaban</keyword>
  <keyword>Rivaroxaban</keyword>
  <keyword>Dabigatran</keyword>
  <keyword>Edoxaban</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

