<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03502291</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4896</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03502291</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Live Attenuated Inactivated Influenza Vaccine on Experimental Human Pneumococcal Carriage Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>LAIV/EHPC</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of Live Attenuated Inactivated Influenza Vaccine on Experimental Human Pneumococcal Carriage Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Royal Liverpool and Broadgreen University Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sponsor GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Royal Liverpool and Broadgreen University Hospitals NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators are interested in examining the effect of the Live Attenuated Influenza
      (flu) Vaccine (LAIV) upon nasal carriage of bacteria called Streptococcus pneumoniae (also
      known as pneumococcus). The nasal spray is a live attenuated vaccine which means that it has
      weakened virus that does not cause disease. This vaccine is licenced in the United Kingdom
      for children and adolescents from 2 to 18 years of age.

      Pneumococcus can commonly be found harmlessly inhabiting the nose where it does not cause any
      problem (pneumococcal colonisation). About 10% of adults carry pneumococcus at any one time,
      and almost all adults experience an episode of carriage at least once per year. Carriage acts
      as a natural vaccine, boosting immunity against pneumococcal infection in adults and
      children.

      During influenza there is an increase in the burden of pneumococcal pneumonia. We have
      studied the effects of pneumococcus for many years and have developed a programme in which we
      can nasally inoculate healthy participants with a dose of pneumococcus and achieve a
      reproducible carriage rate. The investigators would now like to use this model to investigate
      the effects of the nasal influenza vaccine upon pneumococcal carriage and to better
      understand how influenza infections lead to increased susceptibility to pneumonia.

      Pneumococcal disease in young adults is rare - less than 10 cases per 100,000 people per
      year. When pneumococcus does cause problems, usually in young children or elderly people, it
      can be very serious as it is responsible for diseases such as pneumonia, sepsis and
      meningitis, which kill millions of children around the world each year.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Secondary bacterial infections such as pneumococcal pneumonia are a leading cause of death
      during influenza endemics. Individuals recently infected with influenza become more
      susceptible to pneumonia, an effect associated with increased density of pneumococcal
      carriage in the nose and uncontrolled inflammatory immunological responses. The interaction
      of influenza virus and pneumococcus has been known and well documented. Recent works have
      shown that the Live Attenuated Influenza Vaccine (LAIV) enhances pneumococcal carriage in
      murine models. These results highlighted the potential effect of mass immunization of
      children with LAIV on pneumococcal carriage. Increased carriage could lead to increased
      pneumococcal disease in LAIV-vaccinated individuals as well as increased bacterial
      transmission within the population. LAIV has been licensed for use in children since 2011 in
      Europe, and has been increasingly administered in children and adults in the USA. There is an
      urgent need for a clinical trial that will determine the effect of LAIV on pneumococcal
      carriage dynamics.

      The investigators have developed a safe and reproducible experimental human pneumococcal
      carriage (EHPC) model. The investigators will use EHPC to define the effect of antecedent and
      concurrent LAIV on pneumococcal carriage acquisition, density and duration. The investigators
      will perform two double - blinded Randomised Controlled Trials (RCT) to compare LAIV with
      Quadrivalent Inactivated Influenza Vaccine (QIV). The investigators will compare clinical
      symptoms, pneumococcal carriage density and duration associated with both vaccines
      administered antecedent to or concurrently with EHPC inoculation. Changes in the
      nasopharyngeal microbiome, inflammatory responses in the nasal mucosal and lung cellular
      immunity associated with influenza virus and pneumococcus interaction will be investigated.
      This project may provide some reassurance regarding the impact of mass immunization with LAIV
      on carriage or, if carriage is increased, will provide knowledge of how a natural carriage
      episode might develop into pneumonia in susceptible subjects during pandemic influenza.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>DBRCT performed as two studies over two flu seasons. 2 arms to each study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Physical blind folds worn by participant. Unblinded research nurses to deliver the vaccines</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection of pneumococcal bacteria in the nasal wash sample</measure>
    <time_frame>within 6 weeks of inoculation per patient</time_frame>
    <description>Primary outcome: detection of pneumococcal bacteria in the nasal wash sample at any time point after inoculation by classical microbiology. 130 participants will complete the study (65 in each arm) to achieve 80% power to detect 50% increase in colonisation rates induced by antecedent LAIV compared to control</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">324</enrollment>
  <condition>Pneumonia</condition>
  <condition>Influenza, Human</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study One: LAIV + Inoculation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>LAIV Nasal Spray: Inoculation (FLUMIST or FLUENZ) plus intramuscular placebo then inoculation with pneumococci bacteria</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study One: Placebo + inoculation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Quadrivalent Inactivated Influenza Vaccine Intramuscular (Fluarix Tetra) plus nasal placebo then inoculation with pneumococci bacterial</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Two: Inoculation + LAIV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Inoculation with pneumococci bacteria then Live attenuated Influenza Vaccine Nasal Spray (FLUMIST or FLUENZ) plus intramuscular placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Two: Inoculation + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Inoculation with pneumococci bacteria then Quadrivalent Inactivated Influenza Vaccine Intramuscular (Fluarix Tetra) plus nasal placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Study one: LAIV + Inoculation</intervention_name>
    <description>Pneumococci bacteria nasal inoculation following vaccination with LAIV and intramuscular placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study One: LAIV + Inoculation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FLUMIST or FLUENZ AstraZeneca</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Study one: Placebo + Inoculation</intervention_name>
    <description>Pneumococci bacteria nasal inoculation following vaccination QIV with nasal placebo spray</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study One: Placebo + inoculation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fluarix Tetra GlaxoSmithKline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Study two: Inoculation + LAIV</intervention_name>
    <description>Pneumococci bacteria nasal inoculation prior to vaccination with LAIV and intramuscular placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Two: Inoculation + LAIV</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FLUMIST or FLUENZ AstraZeneca</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Study two: Inoculation + placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Pneumococci bacteria nasal inoculation prior to vaccination QIV with nasal placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Two: Inoculation + placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fluarix Tetra GlaxoSmithKline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  have capacity to give informed consent

          -  aged 18-50 yrs - ages chosen to minimise the risk of pneumococcal infection

          -  speak fluent English- to ensure a comprehensive understanding of the research project
             and their proposed involvement, in order to minimise any communication issues to
             maximise participant safety.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  currently involved in another study unless observational or in follow-up phase
             (non-interventional)

          -  received any influenza vaccine in the last 2 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jamie Rylance</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Liverpool Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <state>Merseyside</state>
        <zip>L7 8XP</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Human challenge models</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunity</keyword>
  <keyword>Streptococcus pneumoniae</keyword>
  <keyword>Live Attenuated Influenza Vaccine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tetracycline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

