<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00063232</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>030233</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-DK-0233</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00063232</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treating Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH) With Metformin</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis With Metformin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH) is associated with progressive liver disease, fibrosis,
      and cirrhosis. Although the cause of NASH is unknown, it is often associated with obesity,
      type 2 diabetes, and insulin resistance. At present, there are no approved treatments for
      NASH patients, but an experimental approach has focused on improving their insulin
      sensitivity. Metformin is one of the most commonly used medications for the treatment of
      diabetes.

      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the medical problems of NASH patients,
      specifically liver damage, improves when their insulin sensitivity is enhanced with
      metformin.

      The study will last 3 to 5 years and will enroll up to 30 patients. Participants will undergo
      a complete medical examination, a series of lab tests, and a liver biopsy. They will then
      start taking a single 500-mg tablet of metformin once a day for 2 weeks, then the same dosage
      twice a day for 2 more weeks, if they tolerate the first dosage. The dosage will increase to
      1,000 mg twice a day for the remaining 44 weeks of the study. After 1 year, participants will
      undergo a repeat medical examination and liver biopsy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) represents a spectrum of diseases ranging from
      simple fatty liver (steatosis) to steatosis with inflammation and necrosis to cirrhosis, that
      occurs in persons who drink little or no alcohol. Nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH)
      represents the more severe end of this spectrum and is associated with progressive liver
      disease, fibrosis and cirrhosis. The etiology of NASH is unclear, but it is often associated
      with obesity, type 2 diabetes, hyperlipidemia and insulin resistance. We have recently
      conducted a study of a 48-week course of pioglitazone in 21 non-diabetic patients with NASH.
      Serum aminotransferase levels and liver histology improved in most patients and the
      improvements correlated with changes in insulin sensitivity. These results are promising, but
      pioglitazone is associated with significant weight gain, is quite expensive, and its
      long-term safety is yet to be proven. In contrast, metformin is inexpensive, extremely well
      tolerated, and of proven long-term safety in patients with diabetes and pre-diabetes.

      In this study, we propose to treat 20 non-diabetic patients with NASH with metformin for
      48-weeks. After an initial evaluation for insulin sensitivity, fat distribution and liver
      biopsy, patients will receive gradually increasing doses of metformin orally to a maximum of
      2000 mg daily. Patients will be monitored at regular intervals for symptoms of liver disease,
      side effects of metformin and serum biochemical and metabolic indices. At the end of
      48-weeks, patients will have a repeat medical evaluation and liver biopsy. Pre and post
      treatment liver histology, fat distribution and insulin sensitivity will be compared. The
      primary end point of successful therapy will be improvement in hepatic histology as
      determined by reduction of at least three points in NASH activity score. Secondary end points
      will be improvement in insulin sensitivity, body fat distribution, and liver biochemistry.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Histological NASH Activity Index at 48 Weeks Compared With Baseline (Number of Participants in Each Change Category)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 48 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Patients under went liver biopsy, metabolic profiling and imaging studies before and at the end 48 weeks of metformin (2000 mg/day) therapy. The primary endpoint is a three point improvement in the histological NASH activity index with a decrease in at least two of the component scores and no worsening of fibrosis or increase in Mallory bodies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Serum Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) Levels From Baseline (Number of Participants in Each Change Category)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Alanine transaminase &lt;42 U/L is considered normal</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Insulin Sensitivity (Glucose Tolerance, Homeostatic Model Assessment of Insulin Resistence (HOMA-IR)) From Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>HOMA-IR is calculated from Fasting Glucose and Fasting Insulin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>After complete medical evaluation and liver biopsy, patients who qualified for therapy were started on metformin in an initial dose of 500 mg once daily. After 2 weeks, the dose was increased to 500 mg twice daily and after 4 weeks to the full dose of 1000 mg twice daily. Subsequent dose reductions were carried out based on tolerance, with particular attention to gastrointestinal upset and abdominal bloating. Patients were seen in the out-patient clinic, had a brief medical history and examination and routine blood tests at 2 and 4 weeks after enrolment and every 4 weeks thereafter. The oral and intravenous glucose tolerance tests were repeated after 40 and 44 weeks respectively and liver biopsy and imaging tests at 48 weeks. Metformin was discontinued after 48 weeks in patients without diabetes on the pre-treatment evaluation.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Age at entry at least 18 years.

               2. Serum alanine (ALT) or aspartate (AST) aminotransferase activities that are above
                  the upper limits of normal.

               3. Evidence of steatohepatitis on liver biopsy done within the previous 12 months
                  with a NASH activity score of at least 4 (of a total possible score of 16)
                  including a score of at least 1 each for steatosis, hepatocellular injury and
                  parenchymal inflammation. Histological criteria of steatohepatitis include: (1)
                  macrovesicular steatosis, (2) acinar zone 3 hepatocellular injury (ballooning
                  degeneration), (3) parenchymal and (4) portal inflammation. Additionally helpful,
                  but not required, features include the presence of (5) Mallory's hyaline and (6)
                  pericellular and/or sinusoidal fibrosis that predominantly involves zone 3.

               4. Written informed consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Evidence of another form of liver disease.

               1. Hepatitis B as defined as presence of hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg).

               2. Hepatitis C as defined by presence of hepatitis C virus (HCV) RNA in serum.

               3. Autoimmune hepatitis as defined by anti-nuclear antibody (ANA) of 1:160 or
                  greater and liver histology consistent with autoimmune hepatitis or previous
                  response to immunosuppressive therapy.

               4. Autoimmune cholestatic liver disorders as defined by elevation of alkaline
                  phosphatase and anti-mitochondrial antibody of greater than 1:80 or liver
                  histology consistent with primary biliary cirrhosis or elevation of alkaline
                  phosphatase and liver histology consistent with sclerosing cholangitis.

               5. Wilson disease as defined by ceruloplasmin below the limits of normal and liver
                  histology consistent with Wilson disease.

               6. Alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency as defined by alpha-1-antitrypsin level less than
                  normal and liver histology consistent with alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency.

               7. Hemochromatosis as defined by presence of 3+ or 4+ stainable iron on liver biopsy
                  and homozygosity for C282Y or compound heterozygosity for C282Y/H63D.

               8. Drug-induced liver disease as defined on the basis of typical exposure and
                  history.

               9. Bile duct obstruction as shown by imaging studies.

          2. History of excess alcohol ingestion, averaging more than 30 gm/day (3 drinks per day)
             in the previous 10 years, or history of alcohol intake averaging greater than 10
             gm/day (1drink per day: 7 drinks per week) in the previous one year.

          3. Contraindications to liver biopsy: platelet counts less than 75,000/mm(3) or
             prothrombin time greater than 16 seconds.

          4. Decompensated liver disease, Child-Pugh score greater than or equal to 7 points.

          5. History of gastrointestinal bypass surgery or ingestion of drugs known to produce
             hepatic steatosis including corticosteroids, high-dose estrogens, methotrexate,
             tetracycline or amiodarone in the previous 6 months.

          6. Presence of diabetes mellitus as defined by: fasting plasma glucose of greater than or
             equal to 126 mg/dl on two separate occasion, or diabetic symptoms with a random plasma
             glucose of greater than or equal to 200 mg/dl (34).

          7. Use of anti-diabetic drugs, including insulin, biguanides, sulfonylureas, or
             thiazolidinediones in the previous 6 months.

          8. Significant systemic or major illnesses other than liver disease, including congestive
             heart failure, coronary artery disease, cerebrovascular disease, pulmonary disease
             with hypoxia, renal failure, organ transplantation, serious psychiatric disease,
             malignancy that, in the opinion of the investigator would preclude treatment with
             metformin and adequate follow up.

          9. Positive test for anti-HIV.

         10. Active substance abuse, such as alcohol, inhaled or injection drugs within the
             previous one year.

         11. Pregnancy or inability to practice adequate contraception in women of childbearing
             potential.

         12. Evidence of hepatocellular carcinoma: alpha-fetoprotein levels greater than 200 ng/ml
             and/or liver mass on imaging study that is suggestive of liver cancer.

         13. Any other condition, which, in the opinion of the investigators would impede
             competence or compliance or possibly hinder completion of the study.

         14. History of hypersensitivity reactions to metformin.

         15. Serum creatinine greater than 1.5 mg/dl in men and greater than 1.4 mg/dl in women.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caldwell SH, Oelsner DH, Iezzoni JC, Hespenheide EE, Battle EH, Driscoll CJ. Cryptogenic cirrhosis: clinical characterization and risk factors for underlying disease. Hepatology. 1999 Mar;29(3):664-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10051466</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 23, 2003</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 23, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>March 14, 2011</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>June 21, 2011</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">July 20, 2011</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 20, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Jay Hoofnagle, M.D./National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</name_title>
    <organization>National Institutes of Health</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Insulin</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatty Liver</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Cirrhosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Metformin</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>NASH</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>28 adult patients with biopsy-proven NASH were enrolled in the study and 26 completed the 48 weeks of therapy and underwent follow-up metabolic testing, imaging and repeat liver biopsy. 2 patients dropped out were not included in analyses.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>The two drop-outs included a 26-year-old woman who stopped therapy after 12 weeks because she had moved and her employment did not allow time for travel for outpatient visits and a 53-year-old woman who stopped therapy after 24 weeks because of desire to pursue other treatments.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Metformin</title>
          <description>Participants will undergo a complete medical examination, a series of lab tests, and a liver biopsy. They will then start taking a single 500-mg tablet of metformin once a day for 2 weeks, then the same dosage twice a day for 2 more weeks, if they tolerate the first dosage. The dosage will increase to 1,000 mg twice a day for the remaining 44 weeks of the study. After 1 year, participants will undergo a repeat medical examination and liver biopsy.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="26"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="26"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Metformin</title>
          <description>Participants will undergo a complete medical examination, a series of lab tests, and a liver biopsy. They will then start taking a single 500-mg tablet of metformin once a day for 2 weeks, then the same dosage twice a day for 2 more weeks, if they tolerate the first dosage. The dosage will increase to 1,000 mg twice a day for the remaining 44 weeks of the study. After 1 year, participants will undergo a repeat medical examination and liver biopsy.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="26"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="44" spread="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race/Ethnicity, Customized</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Non-Hispanic White</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Hispanic White</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Asian</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>African-American</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="26"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Body Mass Index</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Overweight (BMI=25-30 kg/m^2)</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Obese (BMI=30-40 kg/m^2)</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Severely Obese (BMI greater than 40 kg/m^2)</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Glucose tolerance</title>
          <description>Impaired glucose tolerance is defined by fasting glucose 110–125 or &gt;=160 mg⁄ dL after 2-h glucose load</description>
          <units>partcipants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>impaired</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>not impaired</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="18"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Diabetes</title>
          <description>Diabetes is defined by a fasting glucose greater or equal to 125 or greater or equal to 200 mg per dL aftera 2-h glucose load.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Yes</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>No</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Change in the Histological NASH Activity Index at 48 Weeks Compared With Baseline (Number of Participants in Each Change Category)</title>
        <description>Patients under went liver biopsy, metabolic profiling and imaging studies before and at the end 48 weeks of metformin (2000 mg/day) therapy. The primary endpoint is a three point improvement in the histological NASH activity index with a decrease in at least two of the component scores and no worsening of fibrosis or increase in Mallory bodies.</description>
        <time_frame>from baseline to 48 Weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Metformin</title>
            <description>Participants will undergo a complete medical examination, a series of lab tests, and a liver biopsy. They will then start taking a single 500-mg tablet of metformin once a day for 2 weeks, then the same dosage twice a day for 2 more weeks, if they tolerate the first dosage. The dosage will increase to 1,000 mg twice a day for the remaining 44 weeks of the study. After 1 year, participants will undergo a repeat medical examination and liver biopsy.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in the Histological NASH Activity Index at 48 Weeks Compared With Baseline (Number of Participants in Each Change Category)</title>
          <description>Patients under went liver biopsy, metabolic profiling and imaging studies before and at the end 48 weeks of metformin (2000 mg/day) therapy. The primary endpoint is a three point improvement in the histological NASH activity index with a decrease in at least two of the component scores and no worsening of fibrosis or increase in Mallory bodies.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="26"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>improved (reduced) by greater or equal to 3 points</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>improved (reduced) by 1-2 points</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>no change</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>worsen (increased)</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>self-controlled comparison of NASH activity index at 48 weeks and baseline. Null hypothesis is &quot;no change&quot;.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>&lt;0.001</p_value>
            <method>paired t-test</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Serum Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) Levels From Baseline (Number of Participants in Each Change Category)</title>
        <description>Alanine transaminase &lt;42 U/L is considered normal</description>
        <time_frame>from baseline to 48 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Metformin</title>
            <description>Participants will undergo a complete medical examination, a series of lab tests, and a liver biopsy. They will then start taking a single 500-mg tablet of metformin once a day for 2 weeks, then the same dosage twice a day for 2 more weeks, if they tolerate the first dosage. The dosage will increase to 1,000 mg twice a day for the remaining 44 weeks of the study. After 1 year, participants will undergo a repeat medical examination and liver biopsy.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Serum Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) Levels From Baseline (Number of Participants in Each Change Category)</title>
          <description>Alanine transaminase &lt;42 U/L is considered normal</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="26"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>changed to normal from abnormal</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>unchanged (normal at beginning)</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>unchanged (abnormal at beginning)</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>changed to abnormal from normal</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>self-controlled comparison of serum aminotransferase levels at 48 weeks and baseline. Null hypothesis: No change</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.04</p_value>
            <method>Fisher Exact</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Insulin Sensitivity (Glucose Tolerance, Homeostatic Model Assessment of Insulin Resistence (HOMA-IR)) From Baseline</title>
        <description>HOMA-IR is calculated from Fasting Glucose and Fasting Insulin</description>
        <time_frame>from baseline to 48 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Metformin</title>
            <description>Participants will undergo a complete medical examination, a series of lab tests, and a liver biopsy. They will then start taking a single 500-mg tablet of metformin once a day for 2 weeks, then the same dosage twice a day for 2 more weeks, if they tolerate the first dosage. The dosage will increase to 1,000 mg twice a day for the remaining 44 weeks of the study. After 1 year, participants will undergo a repeat medical examination and liver biopsy.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Insulin Sensitivity (Glucose Tolerance, Homeostatic Model Assessment of Insulin Resistence (HOMA-IR)) From Baseline</title>
          <description>HOMA-IR is calculated from Fasting Glucose and Fasting Insulin</description>
          <units>unit</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="26"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-3.3" spread="3.2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.04</p_value>
            <method>paired t-test</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Metformin</title>
          <description>Participants will undergo a complete medical examination, a series of lab tests, and a liver biopsy. They will then start taking a single 500-mg tablet of metformin once a day for 2 weeks, then the same dosage twice a day for 2 more weeks, if they tolerate the first dosage. The dosage will increase to 1,000 mg twice a day for the remaining 44 weeks of the study. After 1 year, participants will undergo a repeat medical examination and liver biopsy.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="21" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Weight loss</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="21" subjects_affected="21" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Jay Hoofnagle, M.D.</name_or_title>
      <organization>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</organization>
      <phone>3014961333</phone>
      <email>hoofnaglej@extra.niddk.nih.gov</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

