<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00067418</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>030270</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-N-0270</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00067418</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Light Scattering Spectroscopy to Determine Brain Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Spectroscopic Determination of Brain Tumor Cells</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will use light scattering spectroscopy (LSS) to analyze brain tissue removed from
      patients during brain surgery to determine if this new technology can be used to
      differentiate between normal and cancerous cells. LSS focuses light on cells or tissues, and
      the way that light is reflected back from the tissues provides information about the size of
      cells and the density of the cell nuclei (the part of the cell that contains the genes).

      Patients between 18 and 75 years of age with a known or suspected brain tumor and patients
      with temporal lobe epilepsy that does not respond to medication may be eligible for this
      study. (Examination of tissue from patients with epilepsy will allow comparison of tumor and
      non-tumor brain cells.) All patients must require surgery to treat their condition.

      Participants will be admitted to the Clinical Center for 3 to 10 days for physical and
      neurological examinations, blood and urine tests, and other tests needed to prepare for
      surgery. They will then undergo surgery. A small amount of tissue removed during surgery for
      pathological review will be collected for use in this study.

      Half of the tissue will be examined using LSS to help determine the size of the cell and its
      nucleus. Studies will be done to measure how many of the cells are actively dividing and
      which proteins are expressed more often in tumor cells compared with normal cells. This
      information may shed light on how tumor cells are different from normal cells.

      Participants may be contacted for up to 3 years to follow their health status.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Optical spectroscopy for detection of brain tumors and tumor margins has been shown to be of
      use in distinguishing gliomas and metastatic tumor cells from surrounding white matter.
      Optical spectroscopy has the potential to provide immediate and accurate diagnostic
      information about the nature and quantity of neoplastic cells, in a minimally-or non-invasive
      fashion. We propose to use a new method of optical spectroscopy, polarized light-scattering
      spectroscopy (LSS), which permits discrimination of malignant cancer cells from normal brain
      cells by virtue of alterations in the cytoplasmic and nuclear ratios of these cells.

      Patients suspected of having, or with prior biopsy proof of, a WHO grade II-IV central
      nervous system (CNS) glial tumor(s); those with metastatic brain tumor; or patients with
      medically-refractory temporal lobe epilepsy with a presumed hippocampal source of seizures,
      who are seen in the Surgical Neurology Branch, NINDS, will be considered for entry into this
      study. Tissue samples of tumor or normal lateral temporal neocortex resected as part of
      standard care will be collected at surgery and utilized for research.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 2004</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>50</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy, Temporal Lobe</condition>
  <condition>Temporal Lobe</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Radiographic evidence of primary glial neoplasm of the CNS (WHO grade II-IV) or any
             patient with a known primary neoplasm of the CNS; patients with a known or with
             radiographic evidence of resectable metastatic brain tumor(s); or patients with
             temporal lobe epilepsy (TLE) in whom resective surgery, which will include the lateral
             termporal neocortex, is indicated.

          2. Informed consent from patients age 18 or older.

          3. No racial or ethnic group or gender is excluded.

          4. Pregnant women who require brain surgery may participate in this study.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Inability to provide informed consent prior to surgery.

          2. Medical conditions that cannot be corrected prior to surgery that would be standard
             contraindications for neurosurgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lacroix M, Abi-Said D, Fourney DR, Gokaslan ZL, Shi W, DeMonte F, Lang FF, McCutcheon IE, Hassenbusch SJ, Holland E, Hess K, Michael C, Miller D, Sawaya R. A multivariate analysis of 416 patients with glioblastoma multiforme: prognosis, extent of resection, and survival. J Neurosurg. 2001 Aug;95(2):190-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11780887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Louis DN, Pomeroy SL, Cairncross JG. Focus on central nervous system neoplasia. Cancer Cell. 2002 Mar;1(2):125-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12086870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silbergeld DL, Chicoine MR. Isolation and characterization of human malignant glioma cells from histologically normal brain. J Neurosurg. 1997 Mar;86(3):525-31.</citation>
    <PMID>9046311</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2004</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 18, 2003</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 18, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Spectroscopy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy, Temporal Lobe</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

