<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00062946</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>030104</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-M-0104</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00062946</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PET Imaging of Dopamine in Healthy Study Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>PET Imaging of Dopamine D2 Receptors and Extracellular Dopamine With (18F)Fallypride, D-amphetamine, and Alpha-Methyl-Para-Tyrosine in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to measure molecules on or in cells that interact with a
      chemical in the nervous system, called dopamine. Investigators will obtain two kinds of
      images of the brain-a position emission tomography (PET) scan and a magnetic resonance
      imaging (MRI) scan.

      Thirty-eight participants aged 18 to 45 will be enrolled in this study. They must have no
      history of medical or psychiatric illness, including substance abuse. Participants will have
      four appointments at NIH. On the first visit, they will undergo a physical exam, a medical
      history, and lab tests. The second and third visits will involve PET scans and the fourth
      visit will involve an MRI scan.

      Participants will be compensated up to $430 for their involvement in this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Abnormalities of dopaminergic function have been implicated in a number of neurological and
      psychiatric illnesses, including Parkinson's disease, schizophrenia, and psychostimulant
      dependence syndromes. Functional imaging with positron emission tomography (PET) and single
      photon emission computed tomography (SPECT) have demonstrated the feasibility of in vivo
      measurement of the distribution and the density of dopamine (DA) D1 and D2 receptors in
      humans. Besides simple measurement of receptor density, it has been shown that the
      competition between endogenous neurotransmitters and radiolabeled tracers might provide a
      tool to estimate extracellular levels of neurotransmitters. However, most of those studies
      have been confined to the striatum. In this protocol using a PET tracer (18F)fallypride, we
      will estimate both stimulant-induced DA release and baseline DA levels in the striatum and
      extrastriatal regions by comparing baseline scans and those after d-amphetamine or
      alpha-methyl-para-tryosine (AMPT) adminstration. In addition, to explore genetic factors that
      determine synaptic DA levels, allelic variations of two genes that regulate DA levels,
      catechol-O-methyltransferase and dopamine transporter, will be studied.

      A recent study showed that oral administration of d-amphetamine induced displacement of (11C)
      raclopride in a similar way as the commonly used method of i.v. administration. The current
      protocol will be performed in two steps. First, the method of d-amphetamine administration
      will be determined by studying effects of oral d-amphetamine on the binding of (18F)
      fallypride binding. If oral administration effectively displaces the radioligand binding,
      this method will be applied in the subsequent study of examining effects of each of
      d-amphetamine and AMPT in individual subjects.

      If this study successfully detects the influence of DA levels on (18F)fallypride binding, the
      same design will be applied to the studies of patients with psychiatric and neurological
      disorders.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 17, 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date>August 15, 2007</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>45</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>(18F)fallypride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Age 18-45, inclusive

        In good general health on basis of history and physical examination

        Normal screening laboratory studies including thyroid function tests, blood count, serum
        electrolytes, liver and kidney function, and urinalysis

        Normal ECG at a resting condition

        Normal blood pressure

        No illegal drug use based on urine drug screen

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Pregnancy/Nursing

        Evidence of active mental or neurological illness

        Medically significant biochemical or hematological abnormality on screening laboratory
        studies

        Abnormal ECG

        High Blood Pressure (above 140 systolic and/or above 90 dystolic pressure)

        History of myocardial infarction or angina pectoris

        Positive urine drug screen or use of alcohol within one week prior to each PET study

        History of substance abuse or dependence within 6 months

        Presence of ferromagnetic metal in the body or heart pacemaker

        Body weight more than 93 kg to limit AMPT dose to 4 g/ day (only for subjects having four
        PET scans and d-amphetamine and AMPT administration)

        Claustrophobia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anand A, Verhoeff P, Seneca N, Zoghbi SS, Seibyl JP, Charney DS, Innis RB. Brain SPECT imaging of amphetamine-induced dopamine release in euthymic bipolar disorder patients. Am J Psychiatry. 2000 Jul;157(7):1108-14.</citation>
    <PMID>10873919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 15, 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 17, 2003</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 17, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 18, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Thalamus</keyword>
  <keyword>Cerebral Cortices</keyword>
  <keyword>Quantification</keyword>
  <keyword>Reproducibility</keyword>
  <keyword>Dopamine Release</keyword>
  <keyword>(18F) Fallypride</keyword>
  <keyword>D-Amphetamine</keyword>
  <keyword>Alpha-Methyl-Para-Tyrosine (AMPT)</keyword>
  <keyword>PET</keyword>
  <keyword>Dopamine D2 Receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dopamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amphetamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dopamine Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dextroamphetamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>alpha-Methyltyrosine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

