<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00060372</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2009-00042</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>040749</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P-6082</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-6082</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000301644</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA093891</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00060372</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ipilimumab After Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant in Treating Patients With Persistent or Progressive Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>CTLA-4 Blockade With MDX-010 to Induce Graft-Versus-Malignancy Effects Following Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial is studying how well ipilimumab works after allogeneic stem cell
      transplant in treating patients with persistent or progressive cancer. Monoclonal antibodies
      can locate cancer cells and either kill them or deliver cancer-killing substances to them
      without harming normal cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the dose of MDX-010 (ipilimumab) that can safely be administered to patients
      with persistent or progressive malignancy following allo-HCT.

      II. To determine the pharmacokinetics of different doses of MDX-010 administered as a single
      dose to patients with persistent or progressive malignancy following allo-HCT.

      III. By assessment of aims 1 and 2, to determine the best dosing regimen for further study of
      CTLA-4 blockade in conjunction with escalating dose donor-leukocyte infusions (DLI) in
      patients with evidence of residual or progressive malignancy following allo-HCT.

      IV. To assess if there is preliminary evidence of efficacy following the administration of
      MDX-010 in this population.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive ipilimumab intravenously (IV) over 90 minutes.

      Cohorts of 3-6 patients receive escalating doses of ipilimumab until the maximum tolerated
      dose (MTD) is determined. The MTD is the dose preceding that at which 2 of 3 or 2 of 6
      patients experience dose-limiting toxicity.

      Patients with persistent or progressive disease at 60 days after ipilimumab administration
      and no evidence of graft-versus-host disease receive donor lymphocyte infusions every 60 days
      for a total of 3 infusions.

      Patients are followed at 4, 5, 6, 9, and 12 months and then annually thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2003</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of grade 3 and 4 acute GVHD based on NCI CTC</measure>
    <time_frame>60 days following administration of ipilimumab</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of graft rejection following ipilimumab defined as the percentage of patients entered who demonstrate =&lt; 10% donor T-cell chimerism</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-infusion day 60</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Autoimmune reaction defined as &gt;= grade 3 dysfunction of a vital organ or the graft</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Polyclonal T-cell activation monitored by clinical assessment and laboratory evidence (anti CD3, CD4, CD8) and markers of activation (anti CD69, CD25, CD44 and MHC class II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of extensive stage chronic GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-infusion day 360</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 360 post ipilimumab infusion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 360 following antibody infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Kaplan- Meier estimates of probability will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 360 days post-infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Kaplan- Meier estimates of probability will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With 11q23 (MLL) Abnormalities</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With Inv(16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(15;17)(q22;q12)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(16;16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia With t(8;21)(q22;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Atypical Chronic Myeloid Leukemia, BCR-ABL1 Negative</condition>
  <condition>Childhood Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia, BCR-ABL1 Positive</condition>
  <condition>Disseminated Neuroblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Choriocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Embryonal Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Immature Teratoma</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Mature Teratoma</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Mixed Germ Cell Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Monodermal and Highly Specialized Teratoma</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Polyembryoma</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Yolk Sac Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Previously Treated Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Burkitt Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Diffuse Mixed Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Immunoblastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Lymphoblastic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Grade 3 Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Malignant Testicular Germ Cell Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Neuroblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Ovarian Epithelial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Ovarian Germ Cell Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Relapsing Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Ovarian Epithelial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Malignant Testicular Germ Cell Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Ovarian Epithelial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Ovarian Epithelial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Choriocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Choriocarcinoma and Embryonal Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Choriocarcinoma and Seminoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Choriocarcinoma and Teratoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Choriocarcinoma and Yolk Sac Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Embryonal Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Embryonal Carcinoma and Seminoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Embryonal Carcinoma and Teratoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Embryonal Carcinoma and Teratoma With Seminoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Embryonal Carcinoma and Yolk Sac Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Embryonal Carcinoma and Yolk Sac Tumor With Seminoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Teratoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Yolk Sac Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Yolk Sac Tumor and Teratoma</condition>
  <condition>Testicular Yolk Sac Tumor and Teratoma With Seminoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ipilmumab and donor lymphocyte infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive ipilimumab IV over 90 minutes. Cohorts of 3-6 patients receive escalating doses of ipilimumab until the MTD is determined. The MTD is the dose preceding that at which 2 of 3 or 2 of 6 patients experience dose-limiting toxicity. Patients with persistent or progressive disease at 60 days after ipilimumab administration and no evidence of graft-versus-host disease receive donor lymphocyte infusions every 60 days for a total of 3 infusions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ipilmumab and donor lymphocyte infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>anti-cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated antigen-4 monoclonal antibody</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-010</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-CTLA-4</other_name>
    <other_name>monoclonal antibody CTLA-4</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>therapeutic allogeneic lymphocytes</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (ipilmumab and donor lymphocyte infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ALLOLYMPH</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of persistent or progressive hematologic malignancy or solid tumor after
             allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (AHSCT)

          -  Patients are eligible for study entry at any time between post-transplantation day 90
             and 3 years after withdrawal of immunosuppressive therapy

          -  Acute myeloid leukemia (AML) or acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) that meets any of
             the following criteria: hematologic relapse by standard criteria, hematologic
             persistence evidenced by bone marrow blasts &gt; 10% after day 30 post-AHSCT

          -  Cytogenetic progression as evidenced by an increase in the percentage of Philadelphia
             chromosome (Ph)1-positive metaphases (or Ph1-positive cells by fluorescent in situ
             hybridization) from complete cytogenetic response (0% Ph1-positive cells) to partial
             response (1-34% Ph1-positive cells); PR to minor response (35-94% Ph1-positive cells);
             or MR to no response (95-100% Ph1-positive cells)

          -  Resistance to imatinib mesylate, defined as disease progression (hematologic,
             cytogenetic, or molecular) during OR failure to respond to (i.e., lack of complete
             hematologic response after 3 months, lack of partial cytogenetic response after 6
             months, or lack of complete cytogenetic response after 12 months) prior imatinib
             mesylate therapy

          -  Myelodysplastic syndromes that meet any of the following criteria:

        Hematologic relapse by standard criteria, cytogenetic relapse evidenced by recurrence of
        clonal abnormality in patients who achieved CCR after AHSCT, hematologic persistence
        evidenced by cytopenias not attributable to other post-transplant causes accompanied by
        characteristic morphological changes more than 90 days after AHSCT

          -  OR; Hematologic persistence evidenced by cytopenias not attributable to other
             post-transplant causes accompanied by characteristic morphological changes more than
             90 days after AHSCT, or cytogenetic persistence evidenced by persistence of clonal
             abnormality more than 90 days after AHSCT

          -  Chronic lymphocytic leukemia that meets any of the following criteria:

        greater than 25% increase in absolute lymphocytosis of &gt; 5,000/mm3, greater than 25%
        increase in measurable lymphadenopathy, persistence of absolute lymphocytosis of &gt;
        5,000/mm3 at day 90 or later after AHSCT, persistence of lymphadenopathy of ≥ 3 cm in
        diameter at day 90 or later after AHSCT

          -  Aggressive non-Hodgkin's lymphoma (e.g., diffuse large cell lymphoma, lymphoblastic
             lymphoma, mantle cell lymphoma, or peripheral T cell lymphoma), Hodgkin's lymphoma, OR
             solid tumor that meets any of the following criteria: greater than 50% increase in
             measurable or evaluable disease, persistence of measurable lesions &gt; 3.0 cm in
             diameter at day 90 or later after AHSCT OR;

          -  Persistence of malignancy by biopsy or positron emission tomography scan unless there
             is clear evidence of progression

          -  Multiple myeloma with demonstrated resistance to or intolerance of prior thalidomide
             and bortezomib unless these agents are contraindicated (e.g., due to peripheral
             neuropathy) and meeting any of the following criteria: greater than 25% increase in
             paraprotein band, abnormal quantitative immunoglobulin level, or urine protein
             excretion OR

          -  Greater than 25% increase in percent of plasma cells in the bone marrow (if &gt; 15%),
             presence of new lytic bone lesions, new extramedullary lesions OR ≥ 25% enlargement of
             existing extramedullary lesions, persistence of paraprotein band, abnormally elevated
             quantitative immunoglobulin level, or bone marrow plasmacytosis &gt; 15% for a period of
             at least 90 days after AHSCT

          -  At least 1 bidimensionally measurable lesion ≥ 1.5 cm in diameter

          -  Evaluable disease is defined as disease that is assessable for response (e.g., pleural
             effusion, elevated serum tumor)

          -  Bone metastases that can be assessed by CT scan or MRI considered evaluable

          -  Leukemia is considered evaluable disease

          -  Patients who met criteria for persistence or progression with AML, ALL, CML, or
             aggressive NHL AND are currently in complete remission after reinduction therapy do
             not require measurable or evaluable disease to be eligible

          -  At least 50% donor chimerism in the T-cell lineage OR full (≥ 90%) donor chimerism in
             unseparated blood on last assessment within 3 months before study entry

          -  No evidence on consecutive testing of &gt; 10% decline in T-cell chimerism beyond the
             error of the test

          -  ECOG 0-2

          -  Life expectancy: More than 3 months

          -  No prior grade 3 or 4 acute graft-vs-host disease

          -  No concurrent autoimmune diseases requiring the chronic use of immunosuppressive
             medications, active connective tissue disease, CNS disease including multiple
             sclerosis or demyelinating disease, inflammatory bowel disease, autoimmune hepatitis

          -  No ongoing serious infection

          -  Negative pregnancy test

          -  Fertile patients must use effective contraception during and for at least 4 months
             after study therapy

          -  No other serious ongoing medical condition that would preclude study participation

          -  No other malignancy within the past 5 years

          -  No psychological or psychiatric condition that would preclude study participation

          -  No prior anti-cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated antigen-4 monoclonal antibody
             (MDX-010)

          -  At least 6 weeks since prior immunosuppressive agents

          -  At least 2 weeks since prior imatinib mesylate

          -  No concurrent imatinib mesylate

          -  At least 6 weeks since prior and no concurrent immunosuppressive agents for clinically
             active graft-versus-host disease (GVHD) prophylaxis or treatment

          -  No other concurrent investigational agents

          -  OR Cytogenetic persistence evidenced by any Ph1-positive metaphases in bone marrow
             after day 90 post-AHSCT
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ewa Carrier</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Scripps Clinic - La Jolla</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Diego</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093-0960</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Blood and Marrow Transplant Group of Georgia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30342</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northside Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30342</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Harvard Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2003</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 6, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 7, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 27, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Follicular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Mantle-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Burkitt Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large-Cell, Immunoblastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Plasmablastic Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Germ Cell and Embryonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Glandular and Epithelial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Germinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testicular Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Teratoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Embryonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endodermal Sinus Tumor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Seminoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Choriocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Chronic, Atypical, BCR-ABL Negative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermoid Cyst</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

