<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00066183</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>030254</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-D-0254</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00066183</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Studying Phosphorus Metabolism</brief_title>
  <official_title>Studies in Phosphorus Metabolism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phosphorus and phosphate irons play critical roles in bone structure and essential cellular
      functions.

      The purpose of this study is to learn more about the factors and hormones that regulate
      phosphorus in the body by collecting blood and urine samples from patients with disorders of
      phosphate control.

      Both children and adults will be enrolled in this study. Researchers will collect blood and
      urine samples from participants on multiple occasions (2 to 6 times). Some blood specimens
      will be taken after an overnight fast and participants may be asked to collect all their
      urine during a 24-hour period. Researchers will analyze these blood and urine samples to
      better understanding how the body handles phosphorus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phosphorus and phosphate ions play an important role in cellular metabolism as well as bone
      structure. Scientific evidence suggests that, in addition to Vitamin D and PTH systems, novel
      factors, such as Fibroblast Growth Factor 23 (FGF-23) and Matrix extracellular
      phosphoglycoprotein (MEPE), may play an important role in phosphorus regulation. These
      factors have been best studied in rare genetic and acquired phosphate wasting disorders such
      as tumor induced osteomalacia (TIO), X linked hypophosphatemia (XLH) and autosomal dominant
      hypophosphatemic rickets (ADHR). Patients with other abnormal phosphate regulating states
      such as hyperparathyroidism and hypoparathyroidism, pseudohypoparathyroidism etc. undergoing
      phosphorus-altering interventions may provide important insight into the role of these
      hormones.

      We are proposing an observational study with collection of blood and urine samples to study
      both established (e.g. mineral ions, bone markers, PTH-Vit D system, TMP-GFR) and novel (e.g.
      FGF-23 and MEPE) constituents of the phosphorus metabolism pathway. Patients with abnormal
      phosphorus regulating states will be enrolled and we will study the natural history of their
      disease and the effects of specific interventions that are likely to change phosphorus
      balance.

      The outcome will potentially aid understanding of this new field of mineral regulating
      hormones and generate both interest and research in phosphorus metabolism. It is hoped that
      this will also encourage clinical trials in treatment of phosphate wasting disorders.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 2005</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>100</enrollment>
  <condition>Phosphorus Metabolism</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients of any age, gender or ethnicity who will help fulfill the objectives laid out in
        Section II.

        We propose to study patients primarily enrolled in other clinical center protocol(s). They
        will continue to receive treatment/ interventions per the original protocols.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients with significant cognitive impairment who are unable to give informed consent or
        patients having other significant mineral disturbances that could confound the parameters
        being studied will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Dental And Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murer H, Forster I, Hernando N, Lambert G, Traebert M, Biber J. Posttranscriptional regulation of the proximal tubule NaPi-II transporter in response to PTH and dietary P(i). Am J Physiol. 1999 Nov;277(5 Pt 2):F676-84. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10564230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cai Q, Hodgson SF, Kao PC, Lennon VA, Klee GG, Zinsmiester AR, Kumar R. Brief report: inhibition of renal phosphate transport by a tumor product in a patient with oncogenic osteomalacia. N Engl J Med. 1994 Jun 9;330(23):1645-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8177270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jonsson KB, Mannstadt M, Miyauchi A, Yang IM, Stein G, Ljunggren O, Jüppner H. Extracts from tumors causing oncogenic osteomalacia inhibit phosphate uptake in opossum kidney cells. J Endocrinol. 2001 Jun;169(3):613-20.</citation>
    <PMID>11375132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2003</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 4, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Fibroblast Growth Factor 23</keyword>
  <keyword>FGF-23</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypophosphatemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Phosphaturia</keyword>
  <keyword>Phosphorus</keyword>
  <keyword>Phosphorus Metabolism</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

