<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00063076</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DM02-164</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00063076</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Randomized Bilateral Comparison of Topical Targretin Gel 1% in Alopecia Areata</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Two Stage Phase II Randomized Bilateral Comparison of Topical Targretin® Gel 1% in Alopecia Areata</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ligand Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to find the most effective dose of Targretin®
      (bexarotene) Gel 1% that can be given to patients as a treatment for alopecia areata. The
      safety and tolerability of this drug will also be studied.

      Objectives:

        1. Determine the safety and tolerability of Targretin® Gel 1% in the treatment of patients
           with alopecia areata.

        2. Determine the efficacy of Targretin® Gel 1% in the treatment of patients with alopecia
           areata.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Targretin® (bexarotene) Gel 1% a synthetic vitamin A compound that is approved for the
      topical treatment and oral treatment of cutaneous T cell lymphoma (CTCL). Vitamin A compounds
      can influence the growth of skin cells, and can cause the death of T-cells. Researchers hope
      that the bexarotene may get rid of T-cells around the hair follicles in AA (alopecia areata)
      lesions.

      Before treatment starts, patients will have a complete medical history and a brief physical
      exam. Researchers will ask about alopecia disease history, date of first diagnosis, and
      earlier treatments and responses. Blood test (about 4 teaspoons) will be performed before and
      after the end of treatment. Additional blood tests will be done if needed. Women able to have
      children must have a negative blood pregnancy test within 7 days before the start of
      treatment. Blood pregnancy test must be repeated once a month while receiving treatment.

      Participants in this study will be randomly assigned (as in the toss of a coin) to treat
      alopecia areata lesions on only one half of their head. Half of the participants will have
      the left side treated while the other half will have the right side treated. Sealed envelopes
      will be given to participants, telling them which side of the head to treat. The other half
      of the head will remain untreated and serve as the control.

      Patients will treat alopecia lesions on one-half of the head including facial hair as
      designated by the investigator. The other half of the head will have control (untreated)
      alopecia lesions. Up to 5 index lesions for treatment and 5 control lesions will be
      designated at baseline to follow and measure during the study. Patients will be treated with
      Targretin® gel 1% in a dose escalation regimen starting at once every day. At the start of
      Week 3 patients will begin applications of twice a day applications if tolerated. Patients
      will continue BID dosing, if tolerated, unless the investigator determines a further increase
      in application frequency may benefit the patient and the patient agrees to comply.

      Patients will be seen at baseline and at weeks 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24 and at a 4-week
      follow-up. Telephone evaluations will be done at week 1 and as needed.

      Study visits for evaluation of safety and efficacy will be made at Week 2 and 4 after the
      start of treatment and then every 4 weeks up until Week 24. Telephone safety evaluations will
      also be made at Week 1 and other times as needed.

      Skin irritation or changes in health during the study may require participants to stop
      treatment or withdraw from the study.

      At withdrawal from the study, about 4 teaspoons of blood will be drawn. The total study
      duration is 24 Weeks with a 4-week follow-up period. At the 4-week follow-up visit, a
      physical exam, including measurement of vital signs and weight will be performed. An
      evaluation of both treated and untreated sides of the head will be performed.

      Patients who show a response at 6 months (24 weeks) will be given the option to continue
      therapy for an additional 6 months and will be able to apply the medication to both sides of
      the head. Patients will come every 2 months (3 additional visits) and will have the same
      examination as they have had during the study with evaluation of irritation, hair loss, hair
      thickness, measurement of lesions, and the physician's global assessment, which is the
      evaluation of hair re-growth. The same dose adjustment and withdrawal from treatment will be
      applied during this 6-month period. Every 2 months, blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn
      for pregnancy tests and to look at your triglycerides (fat) levels and complete blood cell
      counts.

      This is an investigational study. Targretin® Gel 1% is commercially available and approved by
      the FDA for use in the treatment of cutaneous lesions in patients with CTCL. Initially up to
      42 participants will be enrolled in the study. All will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response and toxicity of Targretin Gel 1% treatment for alopecia areata</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at weeks 2,4,8,12,16,20,24 and at a 4-week follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>&quot;Response&quot; defined as hair growth at PGA grade 3 or 4, and &quot;toxicity&quot; as vesiculation grade 3 or ulceration at grade 4 using design of Thall, Simon and Estey (1995, 1996). To monitor response and toxicity, four possible elementary outcomes are: 1 = [no toxicity, no response], 2 = [no toxicity, response], 3 = [toxicity, no response] , 4 = [toxicity, response].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Alopecia Areata</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Targretin®</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Targretin® (bexarotene) Gel 1%, treat half head</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Half head untreated as control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Targretin Gel 1%</intervention_name>
    <description>Alopecia lesions on one-half of the head including facial hair treated, and other half on head serves as control (untreated). Starting dose once every day till Week 3 then escalate to twice a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Targretin®</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Targretin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Clinical diagnosis of alopecia areata, alopecia totalis, or alopecia universalis.

          2. Patients must be 18 years of age to participate.

          3. Patients with alopecia areata must have at least two distinct alopecia areata patches
             &gt;1.0 cm diameter, one located on the right and left sides each of the scalp. Patients
             with alopecia totalis or universalis will not have distinct alopecia patches but will
             have complete or total alopecia on both the sides of the scalp. Patients with alopecia
             totalis or universalis will have one side of the scalp treated. The patient must agree
             to treat only one side of the scalp with drug, to have photos taken, and to return for
             follow-up visits.

          4. They must also agree to practice two reliable forms of contraception (hormonal, IUD,
             double barrier) to be used simultaneously unless abstinence is the chosen method
             during the entire period of treatment and for at least one month after treatment is
             discontinued.

          5. Men with sexual partners who are of childbearing potential or pregnant must use
             condoms during sexual intercourse during Targretin® gel therapy and for one month
             after the last application.

          6. Patients will be asked to voluntarily contribute pre- and post biopsies for research
             studies (3 mm punch biopsies for hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) staining and
             immunohistochemistry of T-cells). However, failure to consent to biopsies will not
             exclude them from the study.

          7. Patients have signed the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Must be off other topical treatment for alopecia areata or PUVA (psoralen + UVA)
             therapy for at least two weeks.

          2. Must have discontinued intralesional steroids or any systemic therapies that are
             immunosuppressive or that may affect alopecia areata for at least four weeks. Patients
             who are on chronic oral steroids are not eligible for the study.

          3. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding are excluded. The pregnancy test will be
             sensitive to at least 25 mlU/ml.

          4. Patients with hepatitis, HIV or other serious infections are excluded.

          5. Known hypersensitivity to Targretin® drug or to any retinoid or to any ingredient in
             the study medication.

          6. Patients must not have participated in any other investigational drug study within 4
             weeks of entry.

          7. Patients with Hbg &lt; 9.5 g/dL, WBC &lt; 2,500 K/ul, Platelets &lt; 100 K/ul, TSH &gt; 5.5 or &lt;
             0.5 mcU/mL, T4 &lt; 0.9 or &gt; 1.8 g/dl, or fasting triglyceride level &gt; 350 mg/dl will not
             be eligible to participate in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Madeleine Duvic, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2003</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 20, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 2, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alopecia Areata</keyword>
  <keyword>Alopecia Totalis</keyword>
  <keyword>Alopecia Universalis</keyword>
  <keyword>Targretin Gel</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alopecia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alopecia Areata</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bexarotene</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

