<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00060580</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>030156</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-EI-0156</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00060580</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Raman Scattering Spectroscopy to Measure Macular Pigment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Measurement of Macular Pigment With Resonant Raman Backscattering Spectroscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the ease and reliability of Raman scattering spectroscopy, a new
      technique to measure the amount of the pigment lutein in the retina, the light-sensitive
      tissue lining the back of the eye. The highest concentrations of lutein are in the center of
      the retina, called the macula, which is the area most important for fine, detailed vision.
      The functions of lutein are not fully known. Besides absorbing blue light, it may help
      protect against abnormal changes in the retina, such as age-related macular degeneration.
      Until recently, lutein was measured using long, cumbersome, and difficult tests. This study
      will evaluate a new instrument that provides faster measurements. It will be tested under
      different conditions, such as wearing or not wearing glasses or contact lenses, or dilating
      or not dilating the pupil of the eye.

      Healthy normal volunteers between 20 and 65 years of age may be eligible for this study,
      which involves two visits to the NIH Clinical Center, as follows:

      Visit 1 - Screening

        -  Medical history and physical examination, including measurement of vital signs (blood
           pressure, pulse, temperature, and breathing rate), and examination of the head and neck,
           heart and lungs, and arms and legs.

        -  Eye examination, including eye chart test, eye pressure measurement, examination of
           pupils and eye movements, and examination of the retina (back part of the eye) using a
           strong light and magnifying lens after dilation of the pupils.

        -  Raman scattering spectroscopy to measure lutein. For this test, the subject looks with
           one eye at a brief, bright flash of bluish light (similar to a flashbulb light) from a
           laser. This is repeated several times. Subjects who wear glasses or contact lenses for
           distance vision will be tested without them and then again with a lens in front of the
           eye. Subjects who do not wear glasses or contact lenses will be tested before and after
           dilation of the pupil.

        -  Contrast sensitivity to assess ability to identify an object from the background and to
           see everyday objects. The subject looks at and identifies a variety of objects of
           different shapes and sizes.

        -  Color vision to determine the ability to identify different shades of color. The subject
           arranges a line of colorful discs, similar to checkers, in order of similar shades.

      Visit 2 - Repeat Spectroscopy

      Subjects return 1 week after the screening visit for a repeat Raman scattering spectroscopy
      to evaluate the precision of the measurements.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the degree of variability in retinal
      measurements of lutein, a carotenoid macular pigment of human retina in normal volunteers,
      with a new and novel technique of resonant Raman scattering spectroscopy. This technique is
      generally more objective than psychophysical techniques used for lutein measurements, such as
      heterochromatic flicker photometry. Raman scattering spectroscopy is non-invasive and the
      levels of ocular exposure to argon laser light used in this technique are well below the
      safety limits recommended by the American National Standards Institute.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>40</enrollment>
  <condition>Raman Spectroscopy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Raman scattering spectroscopy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Men and women between 18 and 75 years of age.

          2. Corrected visual acuity of 20/30 or better.

          3. Ability to understand and sign an informed consent form prior to enrollment.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Ocular disease, including significant explained or unexplained visual field loss.

          2. Ocular media opacities.

          3. History of epilepsy or light-triggered convulsions.

          4. A maximal pupillary dilation of less than 7 mm.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Eye Institute (NEI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bone RA, Landrum JT, Tarsis SL. Preliminary identification of the human macular pigment. Vision Res. 1985;25(11):1531-5.</citation>
    <PMID>3832576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Landrum JT, Bone RA, Joa H, Kilburn MD, Moore LL, Sprague KE. A one year study of the macular pigment: the effect of 140 days of a lutein supplement. Exp Eye Res. 1997 Jul;65(1):57-62.</citation>
    <PMID>9237865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seddon JM, Ajani UA, Sperduto RD, Hiller R, Blair N, Burton TC, Farber MD, Gragoudas ES, Haller J, Miller DT, et al. Dietary carotenoids, vitamins A, C, and E, and advanced age-related macular degeneration. Eye Disease Case-Control Study Group. JAMA. 1994 Nov 9;272(18):1413-20. Erratum in: JAMA 1995 Feb 22;273(8):622.</citation>
    <PMID>7933422</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2003</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 8, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Retinal Measurements</keyword>
  <keyword>Lutein in Vivo</keyword>
  <keyword>Raman Spectroscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinal Measurements of Lutein in Vivo in the Human Eye</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

