<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01200043</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UCSF-2845</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DK089216</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01200043</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Metabolic Impact of Fructose Restriction in Obese Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>SUCRE</acronym>
  <official_title>Metabolic Impact of Fructose Restriction in Obese Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Touro University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The sugar fructose has been implicated not just as a cause of obesity, but as a cause of the
      metabolic diseases that go along with obesity, termed &quot;metabolic syndrome&quot;. Obese children
      with metabolic disease will be studied before and after 10 days of a fructose restricted
      diet. The question is whether their co-morbidities will improve, even if weight remains
      constant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent studies suggest that specific types of macronutrients in the diet may have selective
      effects on nutrient absorption, insulin sensitivity, and lipid metabolism. Elucidation of the
      metabolic impact of specific dietary components may well result in improved efficacy of
      lifestyle approaches to reduce obesity and metabolic diseases. Despite similar fructose
      consumption, the phenotype of co-morbidities is different between African Americans and
      Latinos. Latino and Caucasian children manifest worsened dyslipidemia and non-alcoholic fatty
      liver disease (NAFLD), while African American children manifest worsened insulin resistance
      and hypertension. We have also documented in adults that a reduction in de novo lipogenesis
      (DNL; production of new lipids) in the liver and liver fat content, and improvement in
      hepatic insulin sensitivity were achieved by substitution of complex carbohydrate for
      fructose; but these changes appeared less dramatic in African American compared to Latino or
      Caucasian subjects. These divergent findings suggest ethnic and race-specific differences of
      fructose metabolism and disposition.

      To determine whether fructose is a contributor to metabolic co-morbidity in children, we will
      conduct a convenience cohort within-subject intervention with repeated measures, stratified
      by racial/ethnic group (Latinos vs. African Americans vs. Caucasians). The intervention will
      consist of restricting fructose ingestion only to naturally-occurring fructose in fruits and
      vegetables (approximately 15 gm/day for 10 days), by substituting complex carbohydrate for
      excess dietary fructose, while maintaining neutral energy balance. We anticipate fructose
      restriction to differentially improve co-morbidities in different racial/ethnic groups.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 1, 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>intrahepatic fat content</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days</time_frame>
    <description>We anticipate fructose restriction to reduce intrahepatic fat, exclusive of calories</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>insulin resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days</time_frame>
    <description>We anticipate fructose restriction will improve insulin sensitvity exclusive of calories</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>fructose restriction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Isocaloric fructose restricted diet for 10 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fructose restriction diet</intervention_name>
    <description>fruits and vegetables only</description>
    <arm_group_label>fructose restriction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  African-American, Latino, and Caucasian boys and girls. Ethnicity is to be determined
             by self-report. Utilizing the US Census Bureau procedures, participants will be asked
             two questions, the first regarding ethnicity and the second on race. Subjects will be
             given the opportunity to select more than one racial category.

          -  Ages 8 to 18 yr. The minimum age cutoff is due to our desire not to sedate younger
             children for the magnetic resonance spectroscopy scan or magnetic resonance scan (MRS,
             MRI). We chose to study these groups because they are most affected by metabolic
             syndrome and manifest the greatest morbidities; yet their presentations are different
             from each other.

          -  The following criteria are modified from the National Cholesterol Education Program's
             Adult Treatment Panel and the World Health Organization definition of metabolic
             syndrome. Waist circumference is not an adequate predictor of visceral adiposity in
             children. Also, no normative values have been developed nor is this measurement
             consistent between racial and ethnic groups. Body mass index (BMI), however,
             correlates strongly with both visceral lipid depot and blood pressure. The definition
             of hypertension is greater than the 95th percentile for sex and age as designated in
             the 1996 Task Force Report on High Blood Pressure in Children and Adolescents.

               1. Obesity, as defined by BMI z-score of 2.0 or greater, or above the 97th
                  percentile for age and sex; and weight ≥40 kg.

               2. Hyperinsulinemia (fasting insulin &gt;15 µU/mL), or insulin resistant (HOMA &gt; 4.3).
                  See details below.

               3. At least one of the following: systolic blood pressure above the 95th percentile
                  for age and sex, or triglyceride level above the 95th percentile for age, sex and
                  race or ethnic group as established by the 1998 National Heart, Lung, and Blood
                  Institute Growth and Health Study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of disorders other than obesity that may affect insulin levels, such as
             Cushing's syndrome, diabetes mellitus, or depression.

          -  Medications that may affect insulin sensitivity or hepatic lipid content, e.g.
             metformin, steroids, atypical antipsychotics, anti depressants, statins, Vitamin E,
             thyroid medications, anti-hypertensives, weight loss medications, oral contraceptives.

          -  Pregnancy or lactation.

          -  Surgical procedures for obesity.

          -  History consistent with obstructive sleep apnea.

          -  Implants including intracranial surgical clips, pacemakers, and other metals or
             implants that preclude MR scanning.

          -  Claustrophobia.

          -  Inability to fit within the MR bore: shoulder to shoulder width of greater than 58 cm
             or anterior-posterior length greater than 35 cm (magnet bore size limitation).

          -  Weight greater than 320 pounds (MRS table weight limitation).

          -  Eating disorders.

          -  Smoking or alcohol use. Subjects will answer the two questions on the Alcohol Query
             Form. Any consumption of more than 2 drinks per month will

          -  Vegan diet.

          -  All subjects with known diabetes mellitus according to the 1997 ADA criteria will be
             excluded. However, subjects with known impaired glucose tolerance (fasting glucose
             101-125, and 2-hour post-prandial glucose level between 141-200) can remain eligible.

          -  Syndromic patients (e.g. Prader-Willi, Bardet-Biedl) will be excluded, as it is likely
             that the reasons for their obesity may be neurologic or single-point mutations, and
             are likely to be different from those causing the Metabolic Syndrome.

          -  Subjects who are found to be hypothyroid by clinical exam or by evaluation of thyroid
             function tests on first visit to the WATCH Clinic will receive L-thyroxine for three
             months, with documentation of adequate replacement, prior to enrollment in the
             protocol.

          -  Subjects with a history of hepatitis will be excluded from the study. However,
             patients with NAFLD, as determined by Dr. P. Rosenthal (Ped. Hepatology, UCSF), may
             participate. Upper cutoffs for AST and ALT will be 5 times the upper limit of normal
             for the UCSF laboratory.

          -  Subjects with any history of renal disease will be excluded.

          -  Subjects who have a fever or an active infection will be postponed until their
             infection remits.

          -  Emancipated minors will be excluded, as there will be no parental supervision and
             monitoring over the subject's diet during the 9 days of fructose restriction.

          -  Females who have achieved menarche will have a urine pregnancy test at the time of
             their DEXA scans. A positive pregnancy test will lead to exclusion of the data from
             further analysis. Results of a positive pregnancy test will be transmitted to the
             minor only, and the parents will be told only that the subject does not qualify for
             the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Lustig, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 9, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 13, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Childhood obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolic syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>insulin resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>intrahepatic fat</keyword>
  <keyword>hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome X</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

