<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01209676</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UPCC 03610</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01209676</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>IMCgp100 in Advanced Unresectable Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 0, Exploratory Study of the Pharmacodynamics of a Single Intratumoral Dose of IMCgp100, a Monoclonal Receptor Anti-CD3 scFv Fusion Protein, in Subjects With Advanced Unresectable Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A phase 0, exploratory study of the pharmacodynamics of a single intratumoral dose of
      IMCgp100, a monoclonal T cell receptor anti-CD3 scFv fusion protein, in subjects with
      advanced unresectable melanoma to assess the safety and pharmacodynamic properties of single
      intratumoral doses of IMCgp100 in the setting of advanced unresectable melanoma. Six patients
      will be enrolled to complete the study over approximately 12-15 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will test the safety effect of a single dose of the investigational drug IMCgp100
      when administered directly into the metastatic melanoma lesion in patients with advanced
      metastatic melanoma. IMCgp100 is a drug made up of two components. The first is the T cell
      receptor designed to bind specifically and tightly with protein found at high levels on the
      surface of melanoma cancer cells and second is an anti-CD3 fragment that is meant to bind to
      and activate the T cells. There will be two stage dose regimens each enrolling 3 patients.
      Stage 1 dose will 0.00017 mg IMCgp100 and Stage 2 dose will be 0.0017 mg IMCgp100. Inclusion
      Criteria: 1. Histologically confirmed dx of advanced unresectable melanoma not requiring
      immediate treatment and/or in a window between treatments 2. Two or more cutaneous or
      subcutaneous melanoma metastatic lesions 7 to 15 mm in at least one dimension and amenable to
      subsequent biopsy 3. Greater or equal to 18 years of age 4. ECOG PS 0-2 5.

      Able to provide informed consent and willing to comply with protocol requirements 6. Female
      patients must not be of childbearing potential or must have negative serum pregnancy test 48
      hours prior to receiving investigational drug 7. Male patients must agree to use reliable
      form of birth control throughout study 8. Must have adequate organ system function Exclusion
      Criteria: 1. Received any other chemo, immune, radiation or investigational therapy agents
      within 2 weeks prior to study treatment 2. Cutaneous metastasis that have received prior
      local therapy 3. Pregnant or breastfeeding 4.

      History of autoimmune disease 5. Current treatment with steroid or other immunosuppressive
      meds 6. Active uncontrolled infection 7. Known HIV infection 8. Uncontrolled seizures 9.
      Known delayed wound healing 10. On full dose anticoagulation therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2010</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the safety and pharmacodynamic properties of single intratumoral doses of IMCgp100 in the setting of advanced unresectable melanoma.
Tumor Lesions, peripheral blood pre- and post-injection will be used to determine the safety and pharmacodynamic properties of single intratumoral doses of IMCgp100 in the setting of advanced unresectable melanoma</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be used to determine the safety and tolerability of IMCgp100 at subtherapeutic doses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>will be used to determine the safety and tolerability of IMCgp100 at subtherapeutic doses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PE examinations findings</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>will be used to determine the safety and tolerability of IMCgp 100 at subtherapeutic doses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peripheral blood samples</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>will be used to examine peripheral cytokine measurements as evidence of product immunoactivity and peripheral T and NK cell numbers, phenotype and activation marker status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Advanced Disease</condition>
  <condition>Unresectable</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IMCgp100</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>IMCgp100 will be injected cutaneously or subcutaneously into the metastasis, and peritumoral area if applicable</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IMCgp100 injection</intervention_name>
    <description>a monoclonal T cell receptor anti-CD3scFv fusion protein</description>
    <arm_group_label>IMCgp100</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Histologically confirmed diagnosis of melanoma, with advanced unresectable disease
             not currently requiring immediate treatment and/or in a window between treatments.

          -  2. Two or more cutaneous or subcutaneous melanoma metastatic lesions 7-15 mm in at
             least one dimension and amenable to subsequent biopsy.

          -  3. Age 18 years

          -  4. ECOG performance status 0-2

          -  5. Able to understand and to provide written informed consent and willingness to
             comply with all protocol requirements;

          -  6. Female patients who are not be of childbearing potential as documented by medical
             history (e.g., tubal ligation or hysterectomy), or be post menopausal with a minimum 1
             year without menses or have a negative serum beta human chorionic gonadotropin (HGC)
             pregnancy test within 48 hours prior to receiving the intratumoral injection and agree
             to use an acceptable form of birth control, defined as abstinence or use of an
             intrauterine device (IUD), oral contraceptive, barrier and spermicide, or hormonal
             implant throughout the study period;

          -  7. Male patients who must agree to use an acceptable form of birth control throughout
             the study period.

          -  8. Adequate organ system function as evidenced by laboratory values: -Absolute
             neutrophil count (ANC) greater than or equal to 1.0 X 109/L -Hemoglobin greater than
             or equal to 9 g/dL -Platelets greater than or equal to 75 X 109/L -Total bilirubin
             less than or equal to 1.5 mg/dL -AST and ALT less than or equal to 2.5 X ULN ( 2.5 X
             ULN in the presence of liver metastasis.) -Creatinine less than or equal to 2 mg/dL
             -TSH within normal limits -INR/PT and PTT less than or equal to 1.3 X ULN

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Receive any chemotherapy, immunotherapy, radiation therapy, or other
             investigational agents (agents part of a research protocol or not approved by the FDA)
             within 2 weeks prior to injection. A minimum of 14 days is required between last
             therapy and injection on this study. In addition, any clinically significant
             drug-related toxicity should have recovered to grade 1 or less (excluding alopecia)

          -  2. Patients without cutaneous or subcutaneous metastatic lesions;

          -  3. Cutaneous metastases that have received prior local therapy, such as radiation or
             isolated limb perfusion.

          -  4. Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  5. History of autoimmune disease (excluding vitiligo or controlled thyroid disease) or
             immunodeficiency.

          -  6. Current treatment with steroids (inhaled, topical or systemic) or other
             immunosuppressive medications within 2 weeks of injection;

          -  7. Active uncontrolled infection;

          -  8. Known HIV positivity;

          -  9. Uncontrollable seizures;

          -  10. Known delayed wound healing;

          -  11. Full dose anticoagulation with heparin, warfarin, or any other anticoagulant
             within 2 weeks of injection ;

          -  12. History of acute coronary syndromes (including unstable angina), coronary
             angioplasty, or stenting, stroke or TIA within the past 24 weeks.;

          -  13. Known hypersensitivity of IMCgp100 or any of its components (ie, Tween) ;

          -  14. Class II, III, or IV heart failure as defined by the New York Heart Association;

          -  15. Any psychological, familial, sociological, or geographical conditions that do not
             permit compliance with the protocol.

          -  16. Any other condition that in the investigators opinion would jeopardize compliance
             with the protocol ;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giorgos Karakousis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 22, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 24, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 27, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 11, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 11, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>melanoma, with advanced unresectable</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

