<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01203033</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WVU 1910</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01203033</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Pilot Study of Bone Marrow and Peripheral Blood Samples From AML Patients to Characterize the Biologic Heterogeneity of the Disease Using Single Cell Network Profiling (SCNP)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Pilot Study of Bone Marrow and Peripheral Blood Samples From Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) Patients to Characterize the Biologic Heterogeneity of the Disease Using Single Cell Network Profiling (SCNP)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>West Virginia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>West Virginia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Treatment options and clinical outcomes for acute myeloid leukemia (AML) have not improved
      for more than 40 years. AML patients are still suffering from receiving costly, ineffective
      chemotherapy treatments with very high chances of bad side effects. The purpose of this study
      is to take a look at leukemia cells to see if the investigators can learn what makes them up
      and makes them aggressive and hard to treat. We want to use this information to create new
      treatments that the investigators hope are more effective and less harmful for AML patients.

      Newly diagnosed, relapsed or refractory (post induction therapy) AML patients that are 18
      years of age or older will have bone marrow and blood samples taken for their regular AML
      treatment. When these tests are done during their treatment the investigators will need to
      get some extra blood and bone marrow to do this research. The patients will not be asked to
      have an extra needle stick or bone marrow biopsy to get these samples. The patients will have
      the same number of blood and bone marrow tests whether they participate in this study or not.
      We will only need to get about two teaspoons of blood and two teaspoons of bone marrow each
      time the patient has these tests during their regular AML treatment. The research the
      investigators do with these sample will not decide or change the care the patients get for
      their AML.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study will be an open-label prospective investigation using fresh bone marrow
      and paired peripheral blood samples obtained from patients with AML starting at the time of
      diagnosis and including samplings at times of response assessment (CR and NR) continuing
      through relapse for responders and for other subsequent treatments including salvage therapy
      after resistance/relapse. Approximately 100 AML patients are expected to be enrolled. There
      is no extra marrow and blood sampling taken from patients who enroll into this study because
      we only study their marrow and blood when they undergo such sampling for routine medical
      needs. The SCNP results will not be used to guide or adjust current, or future, treatment for
      patients enrolled in this study and they will not be contacted regarding the study results.

      Fresh whole bone marrow (5-10ml) and paired peripheral blood (5-10ml) will be collected from
      AML patients at participating institutions when these patients need marrow/blood tests prior
      to initiation of therapy, post each induction, post consolidation, at relapse and/or
      refractory, which is according to their standard care. When marrow cannot be obtained it is
      acceptable to collect only peripheral blood from the patient. Patient's demographic
      information, diagnosis, treatment option, outcome will be de-identified by the study PI.
      Samples must be collected in a standard 10 ml green top heparinized vacutainer labeled with
      sample de-identified ID, time, and date of collection. Samples will then be shipped to
      Nodality Inc. via FedEx in ambient temperature shipping kits on the same day. Nodality Inc.
      personnel will process the sample for study within 36 hours from collection. Leukemic blast
      SCNP will be conducted under the supervision of the researchers at Nodality Inc. and at
      facilities owned by Nodality Inc. Samples will be fractionated into bone marrow mononuclear
      cells (BMMC) or peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) and then aliquoted. All but one of
      these fractionated aliquots will be cryopreserved. The fresh, fractionated aliquot will be
      incubated with cytokines (e.g. interleukins, Flt3L), growth factors (e.g. SCF, GM-CSF and
      G-CSF), chemotherapeutic agents (e.g. cytarabine, ara- C, etoposide), and other modulators.
      Cells will then be fixed, permeabilized, and stained with antibodies that recognize
      extracellular markers (i.e. surface phenotypic markers such as clusters of differentiation,
      drug transporters, and receptors) in conjunction with intracellular activation-state specific
      epitopes (readouts) of designated signaling molecules. Subsequently, cells will be processed
      by multiparametric flow cytometry for SCNP. Blast populations will be defined by using
      combination of surface markers (CD33, CD34, CD38, CD45, CD11b) and approximately 30 different
      signaling nodes (paired modulator/readout e.g. Flt3L → phospho-Erk), depending on sample cell
      number (ideally 5-6 million; minimum 3 million). Signaling readouts will be evaluated in the
      total blast population, as well as within individual subpopulations, defined by CD33, CD34,
      CD 38, CD45, CD11b, and Side Scatter (SSC). Signaling readouts will be analyzed for each
      signaling node (univariate analysis) as well as a combination of nodes when the data set
      allows for multivariate analyses. In the &quot;bridging&quot; assay, cell surface markers and signaling
      readouts will be compared between fresh and cryopreserved AML samples including BMMC and PBMC
      when available in addition to BM samples.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize the biologic phenotypes of leukemic blast cells in bone marrow and peripheral blood samples collected from AML patients during the natural history of the disease.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To &quot;bridge&quot; assay performance between fresh and cryopreserved bone marrow and peripheral blood samples from AML patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AML patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>newly diagnosed or relapsed AML patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      whole blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Newly diagnosed or relapsed AML patients at the Mary Babb Randolph Cancer Center
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Newly diagnosed, relapsed, or refractory (post induction therapy) AML patients age &gt;
             18

          -  For relapsed AML patients, previous treatment regimens received do not limit their
             eligibility to this study

          -  Patients enrolled will have no limitation as to the type of treatment they receive for
             their disease.

          -  Patient is able to give consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  AML-M3 patients

          -  AML patients age &lt; 18

          -  AML patients in clinical remission

          -  AML patients who will not be able to receive diagnostic blood and marrow work up for
             any reason

          -  Patients who received allogeneic stem cell transplantation or autologous stem cell
             transplantation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Tse, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>WVUCI - Mary Babb Randolph Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MBRCC, West Virginia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morgantown</city>
        <state>West Virginia</state>
        <zip>26506</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 15, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 16, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acute myeloid leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>single cell network profiling</keyword>
  <keyword>AML</keyword>
  <keyword>SCNP</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

