<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01207921</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201010719</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01207921</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lenalidomide Maintenance Therapy Post Autologous Transplant for Hodgkins Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Lenalidomide Maintenance Therapy Following Autologous Stem Cell Transplantation in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Hodgkin Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study to evaluate the feasibility of lenalidomide maintenance therapy in
      patients with relapsed Hodgkin lymphoma after autologous transplant
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objectives

      -To evaluate the feasibility of lenalidomide maintenance therapy in patients with relapsed
      Hodgkin lymphoma after autologous stem cell transplant, as measured by dropout rate.

      Secondary Objectives

        -  To assess overall survival, event free survival, and progression free survival.

        -  To establish the adverse event profile of long-term maintenance therapy with
           lenalidomide in this patient population.

        -  To assess the conversion of partial response/stable disease post-ASCT to complete
           response.

        -  To evaluate changes in immune cell number and function and plasma proteins before,
           during, and after lenalidomide therapy (correlative studies).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 28, 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 19, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the feasibility of lenalidomide maintenance therapy in patients with relapsed Hodgkin lymphoma after ASCT, as measured by dropout rate.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be described by the proportion of patients who drop out of the study for drug-related reasons at or before 12 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse event profile</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of treatment through 30 days following completion of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To establish the adverse event profile of long-term maintenance therapy with lenalidomide in this patient population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Conversion of partial response/stable disease post-ASCT to complete response.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the conversion of partial response/stable disease post-autologous stem cell transplant to complete response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate immune response</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 30 days after end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate changes in immune cell number and function and plasma proteins before, during, and after lenalidomide therapy (correlative studies).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival (EFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Hodgkin Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lenalidomide 15 mg/day Cycle 1 (28 days).
If no unacceptable side effects Cycle 2 (28 days) will be lenalidomide 20 mg/day.
If no unacceptable side effects Cycles 3 thru 18 (28 days for each cycle) will be lenalidomide 25 mg/day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Revlimid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient must have histologically documented classical Hodgkin lymphoma that is
             recurrent or refractory to standard chemotherapy.

          -  Core biopsies are acceptable if they contain adequate tissue for primary diagnosis and
             immunophenotyping. If the original diagnostic specimen is not available, relapsed or
             refractory specimens may be used. Bone marrow biopsies as the sole means of diagnosis
             are not acceptable; however, they may be used in conjunction with nodal biopsies. Fine
             needle aspirates (FNA) are not acceptable. Pathology reports must be submitted with
             the appropriate CRFs, and the actual biopsy specimens are not requested for central
             review. Patients with cHL have one of the following WHO subtypes:

               -  Nodular sclerosis Hodgkin lymphoma

               -  Lymphocyte-rich Hodgkin lymphoma

               -  Mixed cellularity Hodgkin lymphoma

               -  Lymphocyte-deplete Hodgkin lymphoma cHL patients without one of these subtypes
                  designated cHL not otherwise specified are also eligible.

        NOTE: Patients with nodular lymphocyte-predominant HL are not eligible.

          -  Patient must have undergone autologous stem cell transplant (ASCT) between 60 and 90
             days prior to study registration.

          -  Patient must be ≥ 18 years old.

          -  Patient must have an ECOG performance status of ≤ 2 at study entry.

          -  Patient must have adequate hematologic, renal, and hepatic function as defined by:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1000 / μL

               -  Platelets ≥ 30,000 / μL

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 X institution upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 mg/dL

               -  AST (SGOT) and ALT (SGPT) ≤ 3 x ULN (if not attributed to cHL)

          -  Patient must be disease free of prior malignancies for ≥ 5 years with exception of
             currently treated basal cell, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or carcinoma &quot;in
             situ&quot; of the cervix or breast.

          -  Patient must understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent form.

          -  Patient must be able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol
             requirements.

          -  If a female of childbearing potential (FCBP), patient must agree to use two reliable
             forms of contraception simultaneously or to practice complete abstinence from
             heterosexual intercourse during the following time periods related to this study: 1)
             for at least 28 days before starting study drug; 2) while participating in the study;
             and 3) for at least 28 days after discontinuation from the study. The two methods of
             reliable contraception must include one highly effective method (i.e. intrauterine
             device (IUD), hormonal [birth control pills, injections, or implants], tubal ligation,
             partner's vasectomy) and one additional effective (barrier) method (i.e. latex condom,
             diaphragm, cervical cap). FCBP must be referred to a qualified provider of
             contraceptive methods if needed

          -  A FCBP is defined as a sexually mature woman who: 1) has not undergone a hysterectomy
             or bilateral oophorectomy; or 2) has not been naturally postmenopausal for at least 24
             consecutive months (i.e., has had menses at any time in the preceding 24 consecutive
             months).

          -  A FCBP must have two negative pregnancy tests (sensitivity of at least 50 mIU/mL)
             prior to starting study drug. The first pregnancy test must be performed within 10-14
             days prior to the start of study drug and the second pregnancy test must be performed
             within 24 hours prior to prescribing the study drug. The subject may not receive study
             drug until the Investigator has verified that the results of these pregnancy tests are
             negative.

          -  If male, patient must agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact with FCBP
             while participating in the study and for at least 28 days following discontinuation
             from the study even if he has undergone a successful vasectomy.

          -  Patient must be able to take aspirin (81 or 325 mg) daily as prophylactic
             anticoagulation (patients intolerant to ASA may use warfarin or low molecular weight
             heparin).

          -  Patient must be registered into the mandatory Revlimid REMS® program and be willing
             and able to comply with the requirements of Revlimid REMS®.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient who has undergone allogeneic stem cell transplantation.

          -  Patient who shows evidence of progressive disease during salvage chemotherapy or
             following ASCT.

          -  Patient has any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric
             illness that would prevent him/her from signing the informed consent form.

          -  Patient has any condition, including the presence of laboratory abnormalities, which
             places him/her at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in the study or
             confounds the ability to interpret data from the study.

          -  Patient has used any other anti-cancer drug or therapy, including experimental, within
             30 days of initiation of lenalidomide treatment (radiation therapy is allowed within
             30 days).

          -  Patient has known hypersensitivity to thalidomide.

          -  Patient developed erythema nodosum if characterized by a desquamating rash while
             taking thalidomide or similar drugs.

          -  Patient has any prior use of lenalidomide.

          -  Patient is known to be positive for HIV or infectious hepatitis, type A, B, or C.

          -  Patient is pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Patient has concurrent use of other anti-cancer agents or treatments.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Todd Fehniger, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bartlett NL. Modern treatment of Hodgkin lymphoma. Curr Opin Hematol. 2008 Jul;15(4):408-14. doi: 10.1097/MOH.0b013e328302c9d8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18536581</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fehniger, T.A., et al., A Phase II Multicenter Study of Lenalidomide in Relapsed or Refractory Classical Hodgkin Lymphoma. ASH Annual Meeting Abstracts, 2009. 114(22): p. 3693-.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Böll B, Borchmann P, Topp MS, Hänel M, Reiners KS, Engert A, Naumann R. Lenalidomide in patients with refractory or multiple relapsed Hodgkin lymphoma. Br J Haematol. 2010 Feb;148(3):480-2. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2141.2009.07963.x. Epub 2009 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19863533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Attal, M., et al., Lenalidomide After Autologous Transplantation for Myeloma: First Analysis of a Prospective, Randomized Study of the Intergroupe Francophone Du Myelome (IFM 2005 02). ASH Annual Meeting Abstracts, 2009. 114(22): p. 529-.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheson BD, Pfistner B, Juweid ME, Gascoyne RD, Specht L, Horning SJ, Coiffier B, Fisher RI, Hagenbeek A, Zucca E, Rosen ST, Stroobants S, Lister TA, Hoppe RT, Dreyling M, Tobinai K, Vose JM, Connors JM, Federico M, Diehl V; International Harmonization Project on Lymphoma. Revised response criteria for malignant lymphoma. J Clin Oncol. 2007 Feb 10;25(5):579-86. Epub 2007 Jan 22.</citation>
    <PMID>17242396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 22, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 23, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

