<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00464191</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EudraCT 2005-004357-94</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Lundbeck 10968</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NPS 2005-1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00464191</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Escitalopram in Bipolar Depression: a Placebo-controlled Study of Acute and Maintenance Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Escitalopram in Bipolar Depression: a Placebo-controlled Study of Acute and Maintenance Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nordfjord Psychiatric Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>H. Lundbeck A/S</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nordfjord Psychiatric Centre</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Funding: An investigator-initiated trial funded by H. Lundbeck AS.

      Study design: Prospective, randomised, placebo-controlled parallel-group multicenter study.

      Aim: To investigate efficacy and side effects (especially mood switches) of escitalopram,a
      selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor, in the acute and maintenance treatment of bipolar
      depression.

      Hypotheses:

        1. Escitalopram, given in addition to mood stabilising medications, is significantly more
           efficacious, measured by response and remission rates than placebo in bipolar depression
           (the acute phase study).

        2. Continuation therapy with escitalopram gives significantly longer mean time to
           depressive relapse and fewer depressive relapses compared to placebo (the continuation
           study).

        3. The incidence of &quot;mood switching&quot; (defined as development of mixed episodes, mania, or
           hypomania according to DSM-IV criteria) do not differ significantly between escitalopram
           and placebo in either the acute or the continuation phases.

      Patients: In- and outpatients receiving care in the specialised psychiatric services of
      Western Norway. The population is intended to be representative of the patients treated for
      bipolar depression in ordinary specialist care. Patients must have a MADRS score of at least
      20 at baseline. Patients with ongoing substance abuse or dependence, organic mental illness,
      and non-affective psychotic symptoms are excluded.

      Medication: Escitalopram 10-20 mg daily or placebo in addition to mood stabilisers. The dose
      of mood stabilisers must have been constant for the last six weeks prior to randomisation.

      Method: Phase 1 is a eight-week acute treatment trial with six clinical assessments. Patients
      treated with escitalopram who have not responded after eight weeks (defined by at least 50%
      reduction of MADRS score compared to baseline) leave the study. Placebo non-responders are
      treated openly with escitalopram and repeat phase 1. Responders are re-randomised to 32 weeks
      of maintenance treatment (phase 2). Phase 2 has nine clinical assessments. Patients who
      develop hypomania, mania or depressive episodes (defined as episodes meeting DSM-IV criteria
      for Major Depressive Episode with MADRS scores of at least 20 points) leave the study in this
      phase. Patients leaving the study prematurely will be offered alternative treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aims

      The study has two main aims:

        1. To compare the efficacy and the risk of &quot;mood switching&quot; of escitalopram and placebo in
           the acute phase treatment of bipolar depression in patients already taking mood
           stabilising medication.

        2. To compare the efficacy of escitalopram and placebo in continuation phase therapy for
           bipolar depression using a placebo-controlled discontinuation design. The study will
           compare the occurrence of syndromal and subsyndromal relapses, mixed states, mania,
           hypomania, and &quot;rapid cycling&quot; in a seven months' maintenance study following response
           to acute phase treatment.

      Hypotheses

        1. Escitalopram, given in addition to mood stabilising medications, is significantly more
           efficacious, measured by response and remission rates than placebo in bipolar depression
           (the acute phase study).

        2. Continuation therapy with escitalopram gives significantly longer mean time to
           depressive relapse and fewer depressive relapses compared to placebo (the continuation
           study).

        3. The incidence of &quot;mood switching&quot; (defined as development of mixed episodes, mania, or
           hypomania according to DSM-IV criteria do not differ significantly between escitalopram
           and placebo in either the acute or the continuation phases.

      Design This is a multi-center RCT with parallel-group design. The study compares the efficacy
      of placebo and escitalopram, given as add-on to mood stabilising medications in patients with
      bipolar depression without non-affective psychotic symptoms according to DSM-IV, and with a
      baseline MADRS score of ≥ 20 points.

      The study has two phases. The acute phase study lasts for eight weeks and compares the
      efficacy of escitalopram and placebo on depressive symptoms in bipolar depression. Response
      is defined as at least 50% improvement on the MADRS compared to the baseline score.
      Responders to escitalopram are re-randomised to escitalopram or placebo for the continuation
      phase while placebo responders continue taking placebo for the continuation phase. Patients
      on escitalopram who do not respond in the acute phase leave the study, whereas placebo
      non-responders are treated openly with escitalopram and repeat phase 1. Responders to this
      open-label treatment are then re-randomised double blind to escitalopram or placebo for the
      continuation study.

      The continuation phase study lasts for 32 weeks. Patients who responded to placebo in the
      acute phase continue placebo and their usual mood stabilising medication for the remainder of
      the study. Those who responded to escitalopram are re-randomised to continue taking placebo
      or escitalopram in unchanged doses. Patients who develop new mood episodes (DSM-IV-defined
      major depressive episode, mania, hypomania, or mixed episodes) or MADRS score ≥ 20 points
      leave the study.

      Method Screening includes sociodemographic variables, medical and psychiatric history,
      diagnosis made on the basis of clinical interview and verified by the MINI, symptom intensity
      measured by the MADRS,), results of medical examination and laboratory tests (ECG, height,
      weight, blood pressure and blood tests). Sociodemographic variables include age, gender,
      previous and concomitant disorders, course and treatment of mental disorders, bipolar
      disorder type (I or II), age of onset and history of psychotropic medication use.

      Study procedure As soon as the blood samples are analysed, eligible patients can be
      randomised. They are rated on the MADRS, Clinical Global Impressions (CGI), Inventory of
      Depressive Symptoms - Self Report (IDS-SR), Medical Outcomes Study Short Form 12 (SF-12),
      Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF) and Sheehan Disability Inventory (SDI) at the baseline
      visit. Study medication is dispensed. The patients will return to further visits as shown
      below. Patients will receive study medication for a maximum of 40 weeks. Adverse events and
      concomitant medications are recorded.

      Assessments

      The following assessments will be carried out::

        1. MADRS, GAF, IDS-RS, and CGI-I at week 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 9, 10, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 34 and
           40

        2. SDI and QLDS at week 8 and 40

        3. Diagnostic criteria for Mania and Hypomania at week 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 9, 10, 12, 16, 20,
           24, 28, 34 and 40

        4. Diagnostic criteria for Major Depressive Episode at week 8, 9, 10, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28,
           34 and 40

      For the acute study, response and remission rates as assessed by the MADRS are the primary
      outcome measures. CGI-Improvement and IDS-SR are secondary outcome measures. In the
      continuation study, primary outcome measures include emergence of major depressive episodes
      and mania/hypomania, while time spent at different depressive symptom levels as assessed by
      the DSM-IV diagnostic criteria are secondary outcome measures.

      Definitions Response: at least a 50% reduction of the baseline MADRS score at the end of
      phase 1 if the patient has completed at least four weeks of the study. CGI-I 1 or 2 at the
      end of phase 1.

      Remission: MADRS score of 12 or less at the end of the acute phase if the patient has
      completed at least four weeks of the study.

      New episode: A patient who has previously responded to treatment meets the DSM-IV criteria
      for Major Depressive Episode. The patient must score at least 15 points on the MADRS and have
      a CGI-S score of 3 or more during this episode.

      Mania and hypomania: by DSM-IV criteria.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    The study has been terminated because too few patients have been recruited
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1:</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>response rates</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>remission rates</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2:</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>emergence of major depressive episodes</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>emergence of mania, hypomania, and mixed states.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1:</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CGI-Improvement</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change on the IDS-SR</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2:</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time spent at different depressive symptom levels as assessed by the DSM-IV diagnostic criteria.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>escitalopram</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with bipolar disorder in major depressive episode according to DSM-IV

          -  MADRS score of at least 20 points at screening and baseline

          -  18-70 years of age

          -  Unchanged dose of mood stabilising medication for at least six weeks prior to
             inclusion

          -  Voluntary, informed and written consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-affective psychotic symptoms at screening

          -  Pregnancy or breast-feeding

          -  Fertile women without appropriate contraception (the pill, IUD, or contraceptive
             injection)

          -  Substance dependence during the last three months prior to baseline

          -  Mental retardation and organic brain disorders

          -  Suicide risk that mandates specific measures

          -  Novel (within three months) or unstable medical conditions

          -  Clinically significant abnormal results on medical examination or blood samples

          -  Exposure to escitalopram during the last three months

          -  Allergic reactions to citalopram or escitalopram

          -  Anorexia nervosa with body mass index below 18

          -  Formal psychotherapy started within six weeks of screening

          -  Electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) during the current episode of depression

          -  Patients who are unlikely to be reliable and compliant with study procedures

          -  Patients who are not fluent in Norwegian
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Trond F. Aarre, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nordfjord Psychiatric Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nordfjord Psychiatric Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nordfjordeid</city>
        <zip>6770</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 20, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 20, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 23, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 19, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 19, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>bipolar depression</keyword>
  <keyword>SSRI</keyword>
  <keyword>escitalopram</keyword>
  <keyword>bipolar disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>antidepressant</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment trial</keyword>
  <keyword>RCT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Citalopram</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexetimide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

