<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00461461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AOM04-108</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00461461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>a Multifaceted Program for Improving Quality of Care in ICU</brief_title>
  <official_title>IATROREF III: a Multifaceted Program for Improving Quality of Care in Critically Ill Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Outcomerea Group for Intensive Care Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>the Regional Direction of Clinical Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>the High Health Authority</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Medical errors that affect patient safety have generated huge concern since the publication
      of &quot;To Err Is Human&quot; 6 years ago [1]. Given the complexity of management in the intensive
      care unit (ICU) and the nature of human activities, critically ill patients are exposed to
      adverse events (AEs) induced by medical errors. A large number of studies have focused on AEs
      and medical errors in ICUs [2-6], one of their main goals being to identify strategies for
      preventing AEs and thereby improving patient outcomes. Choosing the best AE to serve as an
      indicator for the risk of medical error is challenging. In 2005, our group conducted a
      systematic literature review and presented the results to 30 national experts with clinical
      backgrounds in internal, emergency, and intensive care medicine. Using the Delphi technique,
      these experts selected 14 AEs that had the following characteristics: high frequency, easy
      and reproducible definition, association with morbidity and mortality, and ease of reporting
      without fear of punishment (Iatroref I study) (ref abstract). These AEs were used in a French
      multicenter study (75 ICUs) for a weeklong incidence evaluation (Iatroref II study) (ref
      abstract). Preliminary evaluation of the results allowed us to choose the following AEs for
      the current Iatroref III study: error in insulin administration, error in anticoagulant
      administration, error in anticoagulant prescription, unplanned extubation, and unplanned
      removal of central venous catheter. Evidence suggests that guidelines alone without
      reinforcing strategies may be insufficient to change provider behavior and that the most
      effective interventions may be multifaceted rather than single-component strategies ([7]).
      This study will test a composite intervention program. The objectives of the study are to
      determine whether the introduction of a composite intervention program decreases the
      predefined AEs.

      Study hypothesis: The intervention program will decrease the incidence of the predefined AEs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design and methods Definition of adverse events

        1. Error in insulin administration Insulin not given exactly as prescribed (including in
           the written protocol used in the ICU). The error may be a planning error or an
           implementation error regarding the nature of the insulin, dosage, preparation
           modalities, or administration modalities. Insulin therapy requires monitoring of
           capillary blood glucose levels.

        2. Error in anticoagulant prescription Non respect of the recommendations about
           indications, dosages, administration modalities, contraindications, drug-drug
           interactions, and laboratory monitoring using the VIDAL (French Drug Compendium),
           learned societies, ICU protocols, and local drug committees. Either unfractionated
           heparin or low-molecular-weight heparin may be involved

        3. Error in anticoagulant administration Anticoagulant not given exactly as prescribed. The
           error may be a planning error or an implementation error regarding the nature of the
           anticoagulant, dosage, preparation modalities, administration modalities, dosing times,
           or dosing intervals. Either unfractionated heparin or low-molecular-weight heparin may
           be involved.

        4. Unplanned catheter removal Unplanned complete removal of a central venous catheter by
           the patient or by staff while caring for the patient.

        5. Unplanned extubation Extubation not planned by the physicians. Unplanned extubations can
           be categorized as self-extubation by the patient, or accidental extubation for technical
           reasons (porosity, section of the balloon, poorly secured tube), and during patient care
           (bathing, taking radiographs, transportation, care).

      Randomization procedure We will use a multicenter cluster randomized design to assess the
      effectiveness of a multifaceted intervention. Our statistician will randomly assign each unit
      to compliance with ICU guidelines as usual or implementation of the multifaceted intervention
      to prevent one of the AEs. Randomization will occur at the ICU level. Units that do not use
      the intervention program will serve as controls. The randomization procedure will be repeated
      every 2 1/2 months for a total of four 21/2-month periods in 2007-2008. During the month of
      January, the study will be prepared at each site, where a clinical research assistant will be
      trained in the use of RheaTM data collection software (http://outcomerea.org/rhea/install).

      In the Iatroref II study, anticoagulant prescription or administration errors occurred in
      59/1377 (about 6%) patients, insulin administration errors in more than 20% of patients, and
      unplanned catheter or endotracheal tube removal in 4% of patients. For this study, we
      collapsed unplanned catheter removal and unplanned extubation into a single group and
      administration error and prescription error of anticiagulant in another single group.
      Assuming that more than 2400 patients will be admitted to the four study ICUs during the
      study period, the study would have greater than 80% power for detecting a 4% absolute
      decrease in anticoagulant errors, a 3% absolute decrease in unplanned catheter or
      endotracheal tube removal, and a 10% absolute decrease in insulin treatment errors. We will
      use the two-sided score test for comparisons (Farrington and Manning). P levels ≤0.05 will be
      considered statistically significant.

      Interventions In each study ICU, a physician trained in clinical research and a a clinical
      research assistant will prepare the study during the two weeks preceding randomization. The
      intervention for each AEs will include three components: meeting with the ICU nurses and
      physicians, distribution of educational materials including a pocket card showing the
      recommendations about prevention of each AE, and quality improvement sessions twice a month.
      At each site, the physician trained in clinical research and the clinical research assistant
      will lead feedback meetings with the ICU staff every 2 weeks 1) to provide feedback about AEs
      that occurred in the last 2 weeks, 2) to review compliance with recommendations on the pocket
      card, and 3) to analyze the causes of AEs and suggest practice changes if appropriate. A
      report on each meeting will be drafted.

      Intervention for insulin administration errors

        1. Meeting with the ICU staff to discuss the epidemiology of patients admitted with
           diabetes mellitus outside the ICU, the pathophysiology of insulin resistance in ICU
           patients, and clinical studies of glycemic control and mortality in wards and ICUs.

        2. Pocket card showing how and why to control blood glucose and giving the guidelines for
           controlling blood glucose levels with insulin infusions according to the protocol in
           each study ICU.

        3. Feedback meeting twice a month on insulin administration errors in the unit,
           preventability, and appropriate changes in insulin treatment procedures.

      Intervention for anticoagulant administration errors

        1. Meeting with the ICU staff to discuss the pathophysiology of anticoagulants (heparin and
           HBPM), indications, AEs, and specific problems in the ICU (e.g., use during dialysis and
           in patients with renal failure).

        2. Pocket card showing the nature of the anticoagulants, AEs, route of administration (IV
           or enteral), specific problems in the ICU (e.g., use during dialysis and in patients
           with renal failure).

        3. Feedback meeting twice a month on anticoagulant administration errors in the unit,
           causes of noncompliance with prescriptions, and preventability.

      Intervention for anticoagulant prescription errors

        1. Meeting with the ICU staff to discuss the pathophysiology of anticoagulants (heparin and
           HBPM), indications, AEs, and specific problems in the ICU (e.g., use during dialysis and
           in patients with renal failure).

        2. Pocket cards with the nature of the anticoagulants, indications, dosage, route of
           administration, and Aes, as recommended by the French Society for Anesthesiology in 2005
           in a consensus conference.

        3. Feedback meeting twice a month on anticoagulant prescription errors in the unit, causes
           of noncompliance with recommendations, and preventability.

      Intervention for unplanned extubation and catheter removal

        1. Meeting with the ICU staff to discuss the epidemiology, risk factors, mortality, and
           prevention of unplanned extubation and catheter

        2. Pocket card showing methods for securing catheters and endotracheal tubes, the sedation
           protocol, and the weaning protocol of each ICU.

        3. Feedback meeting twice a month on occurrence of these AEs in the unit, causes, and
           preventability

      Study population All patients admitted to the four study ICUs after January, 2007 will be
      included. No patients will be excluded. The study has been submitted to the appropriate
      ethics committee.

      Data collection Patients Data are collected in the Outcomerea database. For each patient, the
      clinical research assistant will complete a case-report form on a computer using data capture
      software (Rhea) then will import all records to the Outcomerea database. The following
      information will be recorded prospectively: demographic characteristics (age, sex, and body
      mass index); underlying diseases using the Knaus classification [8]; admission category
      (medical, scheduled surgery, or unscheduled surgery), invasive procedures (arterial or venous
      central catheter, Swan-Ganz catheter, and endotracheal intubation), nosocomial infections
      (ventilator-associated pneumonia, nosocomial bacteremia, urinary tract infections, surgical
      site infections, and sinusitis), and decisions to withhold and/or withdraw life-sustaining
      treatments. The location of the patient prior to ICU admission will be recorded, with
      transfer from wards being defined as admission to the same hospital or another hospital
      before ICU admission. Severity of illness will be recorded at admission and once a day
      thereafter. Day 1 is the interval from admission to 8 A.M. on the next day; all other days
      are calendar days from 8 A.M. to 8 A.M. The Simplified Acute Physiology Score (SAPS II) [9]
      at admission and the Logistic Organ Dysfunction (LOD) [10] score are computed using the worst
      physical and laboratory data during the first 24 hours in the ICU. Duration of stays in the
      ICU and acute-care hospital and vital status at ICU and hospital discharge will be recorded.

      Adverse events All AEs will be collected during all four periods, regardless of the
      intervention being implemented. For each AE, Rhea software will be used to collect the date
      and time of occurrence, clinical consequences (from a predefined list), therapeutic
      consequences (from a predefined list), preventability, severity, and relation with death on a
      five-item scale (excluded, very less unlikely, less unlikely, unlikely, likely, certainly).
      An open box will be available for description of the AEs if needed.

      Statistical analysis A hierarchical (patients/center) logistic model will be used to evaluate
      the impact of each intervention. The intervention, as well as interactions between periods
      and specific interventions, will be taken into account.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>decreased of occured of iatrogenic event in ICU</measure>
    <time_frame>one month</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>severity of iatrogenic event</measure>
    <time_frame>one month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>preventability of iatrogenic event</measure>
    <time_frame>one month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2117</enrollment>
  <condition>Adverse Event</condition>
  <condition>Indicator</condition>
  <condition>Intensive Care Units</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>meeting nurses / physicians, quality improvement sessions</intervention_name>
    <description>For each iatrogenic indicator, the interventions are:
Meeting with the ICU staff to discuss the epidemiology of patients on each theme.
Pocket card with guidelines on the theme and ICU protocol in each study ICU.
Feedback meeting twice a month on errors in the unit, preventability, and appropriate changes in procedures on the subject.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients hospitalised in ICU

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  age under 18 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Soufir Lilia, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Garrouste Maité, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timsit Jean Francois, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Unité INSERM U 823 - Equipe &quot;Epidémiologie des cancers et affections graves&quot;</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Intensive Care Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38043</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical and surgical Intensive Care unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75014</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Intensive Care Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Denis</city>
        <zip>93200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.outcomerea.org</url>
    <description>Outcomerea association</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 17, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 18, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 24, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 24, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 25, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

