<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00461955</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHUBX 2000/04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00461955</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Injection of ex Vivo Amplified G-CSF Mobilised Autologous Peripheral Blood Stem Cell Transplantation</brief_title>
  <acronym>Expansion</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot Clinical Trial of Injection of ex Vivo Amplified G-CSF Mobilised Autologous Peripheral Blood Stem Cell Transplantation in Adult Patients With Multiple Myeloma in First Response</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Bordeaux</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Bordeaux</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hematopoietic reconstitution defined by a neutrophils number &gt; 500/mm3 at day 7 after
      injection of ex vivo amplified graft and by a platelets number &gt; 20000/mm3, at day 15 after
      the injection of ex vivo amplified graft, without transfusion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To check that injection of autologous peripheral blood stem cell CD34(+) &quot;amplified ex vivo
      in the presence of SCF, G-CSF and TPO in HP01 Maco pharma medium culture. &quot;: Allows to obtain
      a hematopoietic reconstitution:

        1. Rapid : 7 days or less after the injection, regarding neutrophils and 15 days or less
           regarding platelets

        2. Complete: numbers neutrophils and platelets respectively higher than 500/mm3 and
           20000/mm3 within the times mentioned

        3. Stable: no secondary neutropenia or thrombocytopenia during the year following the
           injection, in the absence of recurence of the myeloma.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematopoietic reconstitution defined by a neutrophils number &gt; 500/mm3 at day 7 after injection of in vitro amplified graft and by a platelets number &gt; 20000/mm3, at day 15 after the injection of in vitro amplified graft, without transfusion.</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 7 (neutrophils) and day 15 (platelets) after injection of in vitro amplified graft</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immediate Toxicity of the injection of the amplified graft ;</measure>
    <time_frame>just after the injection of the amplified graft</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitative immunological Reconstitution</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 30, 100, 180, 270, 360 after the injection and then every 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stability of the hematopoiesis in the long term</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after the graft</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absence of cytogenetics abnormalities not related to the multiple myeloma in the long term.</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after the injection</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>autologous peripheral blood stem cell transplantation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>autologous peripheral blood stem cell transplantation, ex vivo amplified</intervention_name>
    <description>autologous peripheral blood stem cell transplantation, ex vivo amplified</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient between 18 and 65 years of age

          -  Diagnosis of Multiple Myeloma, requiring a treatment, including high dose Melphalan
             whith autologous peripheral blood stem cell transplantation

          -  Performance status: &lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt; 70%)

          -  Anticipated survival &gt; 3 month

          -  Collection of a minimum of 10x106 cells (CD34+)/Kg of autologous G-CSF mobilised
             peripheral blood stem cells in 2 to 3 pheresis.

          -  Signed and dated informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Multiple Myeloma not requiring a treatment

          -  Another cancer in the 5 years preceding the diagnosis or evolutive psychiatric
             affection

          -  Positive serology for HIV, hepatitis C or hepatitis B

          -  Hepato cellular insufficiency

          -  Severe renal insufficiency defined by a creatine clearance &lt; 30 ml/mn

          -  Women pregnant or nursing, or effective absence of contraception

          -  Antecedent of serious cardiac disease in the last 6 months.

          -  Allergy known to the products derived from Escherichia Coli
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Noel MILPIED, MS, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Bordeaux</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Haut-Leveque</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac</city>
        <zip>33604</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernstein ID, Andrews RG, Zsebo KM. Recombinant human stem cell factor enhances the formation of colonies by CD34+ and CD34+lin- cells, and the generation of colony-forming cell progeny from CD34+lin- cells cultured with interleukin-3, granulocyte colony-stimulating factor, or granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor. Blood. 1991 Jun 1;77(11):2316-21.</citation>
    <PMID>1710148</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bodine DM, Crosier PS, Clark SC. Effects of hematopoietic growth factors on the survival of primitive stem cells in liquid suspension culture. Blood. 1991 Aug 15;78(4):914-20.</citation>
    <PMID>1714328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boiron JM, Marit G, Fabéres C, Cony-Makhoul P, Foures C, Ferrer AM, Cristol G, Sarrat A, Girault D, Reiffers J. Collection of peripheral blood stem cells in multiple myeloma following single high-dose cyclophosphamide with and without recombinant human granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (rhGM-CSF). Bone Marrow Transplant. 1993 Jul;12(1):49-55.</citation>
    <PMID>8104070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brandt J, Srour EF, van Besien K, Briddell RA, Hoffman R. Cytokine-dependent long-term culture of highly enriched precursors of hematopoietic progenitor cells from human bone marrow. J Clin Invest. 1990 Sep;86(3):932-41.</citation>
    <PMID>1697607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brugger W, Heimfeld S, Berenson RJ, Mertelsmann R, Kanz L. Reconstitution of hematopoiesis after high-dose chemotherapy by autologous progenitor cells generated ex vivo. N Engl J Med. 1995 Aug 3;333(5):283-7. Retraction in: Kanz L, Brugger W. N Engl J Med. 2001 Jul 5;345(1):64.</citation>
    <PMID>7541111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haylock DN, To LB, Dowse TL, Juttner CA, Simmons PJ. Ex vivo expansion and maturation of peripheral blood CD34+ cells into the myeloid lineage. Blood. 1992 Sep 15;80(6):1405-12.</citation>
    <PMID>1381625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iscove NN, Shaw AR, Keller G. Net increase of pluripotential hematopoietic precursors in suspension culture in response to IL-1 and IL-3. J Immunol. 1989 Apr 1;142(7):2332-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2784460</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ivanovic Z, Duchez P, Dazey B, Hermitte F, Lamrissi-Garcia I, Mazurier F, Praloran V, Reiffers J, Vezon G, Boiron JM. A clinical-scale expansion of mobilized CD 34+ hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells by use of a new serum-free medium. Transfusion. 2006 Jan;46(1):126-31.</citation>
    <PMID>16398741</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kobayashi M, Imamura M, Gotohda Y, Maeda S, Iwasaki H, Sakurada K, Kasai M, Hapel AJ, Miyazaki T. Synergistic effects of interleukin-1 beta and interleukin-3 on the expansion of human hematopoietic progenitor cells in liquid cultures. Blood. 1991 Oct 15;78(8):1947-53.</citation>
    <PMID>1717075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moore MA. Review: Stratton Lecture 1990. Clinical implications of positive and negative hematopoietic stem cell regulators. Blood. 1991 Jul 1;78(1):1-19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2070044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moore MA. Hematopoietic reconstruction: new approaches. Clin Cancer Res. 1995 Jan;1(1):3-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9815881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muench MO, Moore MA. Accelerated recovery of peripheral blood cell counts in mice transplanted with in vitro cytokine-expanded hematopoietic progenitors. Exp Hematol. 1992 Jun;20(5):611-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1587307</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muench MO, Schneider JG, Moore MA. Interactions among colony-stimulating factors, IL-1 beta, IL-6, and kit-ligand in the regulation of primitive murine hematopoietic cells. Exp Hematol. 1992 Mar;20(3):339-49.</citation>
    <PMID>1373685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reiffers J, Marit G, Vezon G, Cony-Makhoul P, Boiron JM, Montastruc M, Rice A, Broustet A. Autologous blood stem cell grafting in hematological malignancies. Present status and future directions. Transfus Sci. 1992;13(4):399-405. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10147738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reiffers J, Faberes C, Boiron JM, Marit G, Foures C, Ferrer AM, Cony-Makhoul P, Puntous M, Bernard P, Vezon G, et al. Peripheral blood progenitor cell transplantation in 118 patients with hematological malignancies: analysis of factors affecting the rate of engraftment. J Hematother. 1994 Fall;3(3):185-91.</citation>
    <PMID>7530133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rice A, Boiron JM, Barbot C, Dupouy M, Dubsoc-Marchenay N, Dumain P, Lacombe F, Reiffers J. Cytokine-mediated expansion of 5-FU resistant peripheral blood stem cells and bone marrow: self-renewal and commitment capacity. J Hematother. 1994 Summer;3(2):135-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7522897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shih JP, Ogawa M. Monoclonal antibody J11d.2 recognizes cell cycle-dormant, primitive hematopoietic progenitors of mice. Blood. 1993 Mar 1;81(5):1155-60.</citation>
    <PMID>8443377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith C, Gasparetto C, Collins N, Gillio A, Muench MO, O'Reilly RJ, Moore MA. Purification and partial characterization of a human hematopoietic precursor population. Blood. 1991 May 15;77(10):2122-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1709369</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 17, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 18, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 3, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 3, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Jean-Pierre LEROY / Clinical Research and Innovation Director</name_title>
    <organization>University Hospital, Bordeaux</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Symptomatic Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>first line treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>first autologous Stem Cell Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>ex vivo amplified autologous peripheral blood stem cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

