<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00467272</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2006-0958</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00467272</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Catheter Related - Gram Positive Bloodstream Infections</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II, Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Daptomycin in the Treatment of Catheter-Related Gram Positive Bloodstream Infections</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cubist Pharmaceuticals LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective:

      -Evaluate the clinical efficacy and safety of Daptomycin given for treatment of
      catheter-related bloodstream infections (CRBSI) due to gram positive bacteremia in the
      context of standard of care antimicrobial therapy consisting mainly of Vancomycin with or
      without initial treatment with beta lactam antibiotics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      THE STUDY DRUG:

      Daptomycin is an antibiotic designed to treat a variety of bacterial infections that are
      difficult to treat.

      SCREENING TESTS:

      Before you can start treatment on this study, you will have what are called &quot;screening
      tests.&quot; These tests will help the doctor decide if you are eligible to take part in this
      study.

        -  You will be asked about your medical/surgical history.

        -  You will be asked about any medications that you may have taken in the past 2 weeks. You
           should tell the study doctor or study staff about any medications or therapies you may
           be taking while on this study)

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your vital signs (heart rate,
           temperature, breathing rate, and blood pressure).

        -  You will have blood drawn (about 1 tablespoon) for routine tests and to check for
           bacterial infection. This routine blood sample may be drawn from the CVC, if the CVC is
           still in place.

        -  Your CVC exit site (where the CVC will be removed from) will be examined.

        -  You may have an echocardiogram (a test that uses sound waves to make pictures of your
           heart, which helps show how well your heart pumps blood). This test will only be
           performed if you have a specific type of infection (to make sure you do not have
           inflammation in the lining of the heart). Your primary doctor and/or your study doctor
           will decide if you will have this test. If you are found to have this inflammation, you
           will not be able to take part in this study.

        -  Women who are able to have children must have a negative blood (about 1 teaspoon) or
           urine pregnancy test.

      STUDY TREATMENT:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be given daptomycin by
      vein over 30 minutes every 24 hours for at least 7-14 days, depending on the type of bacteria
      that you have.

      The CVC will either be removed, or it will be exchanged over a guide wire. The decision to
      remove or exchange the CVC and timing of the placement of the CVC will be decided by your
      primary physician and the willingness of you to remove or exchange your infected CVC. This
      will be done within 96 hours after your first positive blood culture (first blood drawn that
      showed bacteria). A CVC is a sterile flexible tube that will be placed into a large vein
      while you are under local anesthesia. Your doctor will explain this procedure to you in more
      detail, and you will be required to sign a separate consent form for this procedure.

      If the study doctor and/or your primary doctor suspects that you have a mixed infection (2 or
      more certain types of bacteria) or pneumonia, you will also be treated with different types
      of antibiotics, by vein or mouth, in combination with the study drug. These antibiotics may
      include aztreonam, cefepime, imipenem, meropenem, ciprofloxacin hydrochloride, bactrim,
      and/or amoxicillin/clavulanate (a combination antibiotic).

      If you are discharged from the hospital before completing the study medication, arrangements
      will be made to provide infusions on an outpatient basis (by a nurse, yourself, or a family
      member). You and/or a family member will be taught (by a nurse) how to take the study
      medication at home. Before you are discharged from the hospital, you will receive the kits
      that include enough supplies for you and/or a family member to give daptomycin by vein. If
      medication will be given at home, a prescription will be given to you to pick up your
      medication from the pharmacy before you discharge from the hospital. If possible, your
      primary doctor may arrange for you to receive medication at the M. D. Anderson outpatient
      treatment center, or a nurse will be scheduled to visit you at home to give you the
      medication.

      STUDY TESTS/PROCEDURES:

      During each week of treatment, you will have the following exams/procedures performed once a
      week.

        -  You will have blood drawn (about 1 tablespoon) for routine tests. It may be drawn from
           the CVC, if the CVC is still in place. The CVC exit site will be examined at each visit
           until you have no more signs or symptoms of infection.

        -  You will also have blood drawn (about 1 tablespoon) for a blood culture every other day
           until it no longer shows signs of infection.

        -  You will be asked about any symptoms or illnesses that you may have experienced since
           your last visit.

      LENGTH OF STUDY:

      Participation on this study will last for no more than 60 days (about 2 months).

      You will be taken off this study if the infection gets worse or any intolerable side effects
      occur.

      END-OF-STUDY VISIT AND FOLLOW-UP VISIT:

      The end-of-study visit will occur within 7 days after your last dose of the study drug.

      The follow-up visit will occur about 32 days (about 1 month) after your last dose of the
      study drug. At each of these visits, you will have the following exams/procedures performed.

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your vital signs.

        -  You will have blood drawn (about 1 tablespoon) for routine tests and to check for
           bacterial infection. The blood sample may be drawn from the CVC, if the CVC is still in
           place. The CVC exit site will be examined.

        -  You will be asked about any symptoms or illnesses that you may have experienced since
           your last visit.

        -  You will be asked about any medications or therapies that you may be taking.

      This is an investigational study. Daptomycin is FDA approved and commercially available for
      the treatment infections of the skin and soft tissue. Its use in this study is
      investigational and authorized for use in research only. Up to 40 patients will take part in
      this study. All will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2007</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To find out if daptomycin can help to control CRIs with or without exchange of the central venous catheter (CVC) over a guide wire.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The safety of this treatment will also be studied.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Bloodstream Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Daptomycin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Daptomycin 6 mg/kg IV every 24 hours for at least 7-14 days, depending on the type of bacteria.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Daptomycin</intervention_name>
    <description>6 mg/kg IV every 24 hours for at least 7-14 days, depending on the type of bacteria.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Daptomycin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cubicin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or non-pregnant, non-lactating females with an age of greater than or equal to 18
             years.

          -  The suspected culprit on exchangeable central venous catheter (CVC) is tunneled or
             non-tunnel (including ports and PICC) and antibiotic or non-antibiotic coated catheter
             inserted in the subclavian, jugular, peripheral or femoral vein.

          -  Patients must have at least two signs of sepsis from the list below, in any
             combination, within 48 hours prior to Daptomycin therapy and no other source for the
             bacteremia other than CVC: a. Core temperature =/&gt;38.0 degrees C or =/&lt;36.0 degrees C,
             measured orally, rectally, tympanic ally or via a central catheter. If auxiliary add
             0.5 degrees C to the measured temperature; b. Pulse rate =/&gt; 100 beats/min.; c.
             Respiratory rate =/&gt; 20/min.; d. WBC count =/&gt;12,000/mm^3 or =/&lt;4,000/mm^3
             differential count showing &gt;10% band forms; e. Systolic blood pressure =/&lt;90 mm Hg.

          -  Patients with probable or definite diagnosis of uncomplicated CVC-related gram
             positive bacteremia that includes at least one positive blood culture for CNS, SA,
             Enterococci, Corynebacterium, and Propionibacterium (If the positive blood culture is
             drawn through the CVC for skin flora such as CNS, Corynebacterium, Propionibacterium,
             Micrococcus and Bacillus, then at least &gt;15 colonies/ml will be required or the time
             of positive (DTP) of CVC at least 2 hours earlier than the peripheral culture).

          -  Signed informed consent.

          -  No apparent source for the clinical manifestation of bacteremia other than the
             catheter (may have local signs and symptoms at the catheter site).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Estimated Serum Creatinine Clearance &lt;30 mL/min (according to Cock-Gault-formula)at
             the time gram positive bacteremia was diagnosed unless the patient is on dialysis.

          -  Bilirubin &gt;4x the upper limit of normal at the time gram positive bacteremia was
             diagnosed.

          -  Treatment with an antibiotic, such as vancomycin, linezolid, tigecycline or
             daptomycin, effective against resistant gram positive bacterial infections, such as
             methicillin resistant staphylococci, for more than 48 hours within 72 hours of study
             medication initiation, unless treatment failed that is defined as a persistent fever,
             leukocytosis, and/or repeated positive blood cultures (CVC and peripheral) for 72
             hours or longer of appropriate antibiotics treatment other than Daptomycin.

          -  Documented gram positive bacteremia within last 1 month due to source other than CVC.

          -  Patients who have participated in another investigational anti-infective study within
             30 days.

          -  History of hypersensitivity to lipopeptides.

          -  Presence of additional source of infection with same organism cultured from blood, eg.
             endocarditis (as evidenced by vegetations on an echocardiogram), septic thrombosis.

          -  Conditions with markedly decreased albumin in plasma (&lt;1.5 g/dl), e.g., cirrhosis,
             nephritic syndrome, end-stage renal disease.

          -  Prosthetic valve.

          -  Oliguria defined as urine output of &lt;20 cc/hour averaged over 24 hours.

          -  Possible complicated CRBSI with persistent bacteremia for more than 48 hours on active
             antimicrobial therapy (such as osteomyelitis, endocarditis, and septic thrombosis).

          -  Patients with diagnosis of pneumonia that is due to S. aureus organism, e.g, S. aureus
             from sputum or bronchial cultures.

          -  CPK &gt;10X max-normal in asymptomatic patients and CPK &gt;5 max-normal in symptomatic
             patients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Issam Raad, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>MD Anderson Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 26, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 27, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 30, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 18, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 18, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 19, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Catheter-Related Bloodstream Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Bloodstream Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Daptomycin</keyword>
  <keyword>Cubicin</keyword>
  <keyword>CRBSI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Daptomycin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

