<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00120978</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SC0100141</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>SC0100141</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00120978</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Can Advair and Flovent Reduce Systemic Inflammation Related to Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)? A Multi-Center Randomized Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Advair - CRP Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Large population-based studies suggest that patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary
      disease (COPD) are 2 to 3 times at risk for cardiovascular mortality, which accounts for a
      large proportion of the total number of deaths. How COPD increases the risk of poor
      cardiovascular outcomes is largely unknown. However, there is growing evidence that
      persistent low-grade systemic inflammation is present in COPD and that this may contribute to
      the pathogenesis of atherosclerosis and cardiovascular disease among COPD patients.
      Inflammation and more specifically, C-reactive protein (CRP), has been linked with all stages
      of atherosclerosis, including plaque genesis, rupture and subsequent thrombo-fibrosis of
      vulnerable vessels. Recently, our group has demonstrated in a relatively small study that
      short-term inhaled corticosteroid (ICS) therapy can repress serum CRP levels in stable COPD
      patients. Conversely, withdrawal of ICS leads to a marked increase in serum CRP levels.
      Although very promising, these data cannot be considered definitive because the study was
      small in size and scope (N=41 patients). Additionally, this study did not address the
      potential effects of combination therapy with ICS and long-acting β2 agonists (LABA). This is
      an important short-coming because combination therapy of ICS and LABA have been shown to
      produce improved clinical outcomes over ICS monotherapy and is commonly used by clinicians in
      the treatment of moderate to severe COPD. We hypothesize that inhaled fluticasone (Flovent®)
      reduces systemic inflammation and that combination therapy (Advair®) is more effective than
      steroids alone in reducing systemic inflammation in COPD. In this proposal, we will implement
      a randomized controlled trial to determine whether ICS by themselves or in combination with
      LABAs can:

        1. reduce CRP levels in stable COPD patients and

        2. reduce other pro-inflammatory cytokines, which have been linked with cardiovascular
           morbidity and mortality such as interleukin-6 (IL-6) and monocyte chemoattractant
           protein-1 (MCP-1)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      What is the problem to be addressed? Patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
      (COPD) are at increased risk of cardiovascular events. Indeed, ischemic heart disease is one
      of the leading causes of mortality and hospitalization among patients with mild to moderate
      COPD. For every 10% decrease in forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1), cardiovascular
      mortality increases by ~28%, and nonfatal coronary event increases by ~20% in mild to
      moderate COPD. How COPD increases the risk of poor cardiovascular outcomes is largely
      unknown. However, there is growing evidence that persistent low-grade systemic inflammation
      is present in COPD and that this may contribute to the pathogenesis of atherosclerosis and
      cardiovascular disease among COPD patients. Circulating levels of C-reactive protein (CRP),
      which has been strongly linked with poor cardiovascular outcomes in the general population,
      has been demonstrated to be elevated in COPD. Moreover, an elevated level of CRP has been
      associated with myocardial injury in COPD. Reduction in the level of CRP, on the other hand,
      has been shown to be associated with improved outcomes in various populations. Other
      cytokines such as interleukin-6 (IL-6) and monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1), which
      are potent regulators of CRP, have also been associated with cardiovascular events. If this
      linkage between systemic inflammation and atherosclerosis holds true for COPD, then systemic
      inflammation and/or its markers may provide a new and very important therapeutic target for
      COPD management. Corticosteroids (CS) can reduce CRP and other circulating inflammatory
      cytokine levels in acute pro-inflammatory states. They can also down-regulate certain
      inflammatory cells and cytokine expression in the airways of COPD patients and attenuate
      airway hyperresponsiveness related to COPD. More importantly, in large clinical studies, they
      have been shown to reduce clinical exacerbations, improve health status and may even reduce
      mortality in COPD. The mechanism by which such improvement occurs is not known. Recently, our
      group has demonstrated in a relatively small study that short-term inhaled corticosteroid
      (ICS) therapy can repress serum CRP levels in stable COPD patients. Conversely, withdrawal of
      ICS leads to a marked increase in serum CRP levels. Although very promising, these data
      cannot be considered definitive because the study was small in size and scope (N=41
      patients). Additionally, this study did not address the potential effects of combination
      therapy with ICS and long-acting β2 agonists (LABA).This is an important short-coming because
      combination therapy has been shown to produce improved clinical outcomes over ICS monotherapy
      and is commonly used by clinicians in the treatment of moderate to severe COPD. In-vitro
      studies suggest that steroids and LABAs may “synergistically” down-regulate inflammation in
      COPD. Whether this occurs in-vivo remains largely unknown and untested.

      What is the proposed trial design:

      This trial will be a double blind, placebo-controlled multi-center study comparing the
      effects of Advair, Flovent and placebo on serum CRP in COPD. All study participants will
      first undergo a run-in phase during which all will be treated with Flovent 500 mcg bid. This
      will be followed by a withdrawal phase wherein all participants will be FREE of any ICS or
      LABAs for 4 weeks. After the withdrawal phase, the participants will be randomly assigned
      (using a computer generated algorithm) to one of three arms: placebo; Flovent; or Advair
      Run-In Phase (4 weeks): The use of ICS, theophyllines, and leukotriene modifiers, LABA will
      be prohibited and subjects will be maintained on Flovent 500 mcg bid. Regular use of
      tiotropium and as needed use of short-acting β2 (salbutamol) and/or anti-cholinergic
      (Atrovent) will be allowed.

      Why is this phase needed? Management of COPD is variable. Because of the controversy
      surrounding the use of ICS and LABAs, some patients at enrollment will be taking these
      medications, while others will not. This phase is to ensure uniformity of therapy (and in
      particular to the use of ICS in the same dose) for all study participants.

      Withdrawal Phase (4 weeks): Flovent will be discontinued and participants will also not be
      taking any other ICS, theophyllines, LABAs or leukotriene modifiers during this period.
      Regular use of tiotropium and as needed use of short-acting β2 (salbutamol) and/or
      anti-cholinergic (Atrovent) will be allowed.

      Why is this phase needed? There are two principal reasons why this phase is needed. One way
      of “proving” that ICS modifies serum CRP levels is to demonstrate that withdrawal of ICS
      increases CRP levels and their re-introduction of ICS suppresses CRP levels. The Second
      reason is that in the researchers' pilot study it was found that serum CRP levels were
      highest when patients were off ICS for 4 weeks. To achieve the necessary statistical power
      for this study, a reasonably high serum CRP signal is desirable at the beginning of the
      randomization period.

      Active Treatment Phase (4 weeks): Subjects will be randomized to one of 3 arms, placebo,
      Advair, or Flovent. Rescue medications (anti-cholinergics and short-acting β2) will be
      allowed. Participants will not be taking any other inhaled corticosteroids, theophyllines,
      leukotriene modifiers or LABAs during this period.

      Why is this phase only 4 weeks? Exacerbations and infections can elevate CRP levels by 2 to
      10 fold. The rate of normalization of CRP levels after these episodes is variable; complete
      normalization may not take place for several weeks after the resolution of the infective or
      exacerbation episode. To reduce the risk that the study participants will experience
      clinically apparent infections or exacerbations, we have made this phase of the study
      relatively short (4 weeks). The short treatment period will also reduce the effects of non or
      suboptimal compliance of treatment medications on CRP levels. We believe that 4 weeks of
      therapy will be sufficient to demonstrate the suppressive effects of Flovent and Advair,
      given the fact that in the pilot study, an effect of Flovent on CRP after only 2 weeks of
      therapy was observed.

      What are the proposed practical arrangements for allocating participants to trial groups?
      Patients will be randomized (1:2:2) to placebo, Advair, or Flovent. Patients will first be
      stratified based on study site to minimize the potential impact of variation in patient care
      across the study sites on the endpoint of interest. We have hired an external statistician
      (Ms. Lieling Wu) who will prepare computer-generated randomization lists blocked by study
      site using permuted blocks of six. The lists will be inputted into a randomization computer.
      When a site coordinator has identified an eligible, consented patient, he/she will contact
      the central co-ordinating site at St. Paul’s Hospital (SPH) for a randomization number. The
      randomization computer will then issue a study identification number to the study coordinator
      and to GlaxoSmithKline (Mississauga) for delivery of the appropriate treatment package (that
      contains one Flovent canister and one “unknown” puffer) to the appropriate study site within
      two business days. The open-labeled Flovent will be used for the “run-in” phase, while the
      “unknown” puffer (either placebo, Flovent or Advair) will be dispensed at the start of the
      “active treatment phase.”

      What are the proposed methods for protecting against other sources of bias ? All research
      personnel will all be blinded to the treatment group except for the study biostatistician,
      who will be responsible for the randomization computer. Only he will have access to the
      master file, which can link patient identifiers to the randomization number. This computer
      will be locked away in a secure space at the James Hogg iCAPTURE Centre in SPH and will have
      a password protection that only he (or his designate) can access. The study medications and
      placebo will be packaged and delivered identically as a diskus.

      What is the proposed duration of treatment period? 4 weeks of run-in; 4 weeks of withdrawal
      phase and 4 weeks of active treatment phase (i.e RCT).

      What is the frequency and duration of followup? Participants will be seen at enrollment,
      after the completion of each phase of the study and with exacerbations or infections (as
      defined above).

      What are the proposed primary and secondary outcome measures?

      Primary: The difference in CRP from start of the active treatment phase to the end of the
      trial between the 3 groups

      Secondary: measurements of MCP-1 and IL-6; St. George’s Respiratory Questionnaire, SGRQ,76
      scores; FEV1

      How will the outcome measures be measured at follow-up?

      Blood Collection: During every visit, study personnel will take two 10 ml collection of blood
      from participants through venipuncture (using standard techniques). Samples will be
      centrifuged and the serum component will be aliquoted into special tubes (provided by the
      coordinating site) that contain anti-proteases. They will then be shipped (Fedexed) in
      regular ice immediately to the Study Coordinating Center (to arrive within 24 hours of blood
      collection) where they will be frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored in -70ºC freezers until
      analysis. To avoid delays, no samples will be taken on a Friday or a day preceding holidays.
      A high-sensitive solid phase enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) to measure serum CRP
      will be used. The investigators have measured over 4,000 serum samples from the Lung Health
      Study with this technique. In comparison with nephelometry, another commonly used technique,
      CRP levels with high-sensitivity ELISA is excellent. The coefficient of variation for CRP in
      the researchers' laboratory is ~5%. IL-6 and MCP-1 will also be measured using
      high-sensitivity ELISA assays. The researchers' laboratory has also experience performing
      these assays using serums collected from COPD patients. The investigators have previously
      shown that the coefficient of variation for the IL-6 assay to be 4.7% (median; interquartile
      range, 1.8% to 11.2%) and the MCP-1 assay to be 3.2% (median; interquartile range, 1.5% to
      5.9%).

      Spirometry: Spirometry will be performed in accordance with guidelines from the American
      Thoracic Society during each visit. At the first visit, pre and post-bronchodilator
      measurements will be done. For follow-up visits, only pre-bronchodilator values will be
      measured.

      Health Status Measurements: During each visit, study participants will complete the SGRQ in
      person. The SGRQ was chosen because it has excellent internal consistency (Cronbach’s alpha
      coefficient ≥ 0.76), reliability (intraclass correlation coefficient of ~85% of responses
      measured 6 months apart), and is an independent predictor of future risk of exacerbations and
      mortality in COPD. Clinically relevant thresholds for SGRQ are considered to be score changes
      of ≥ 4.0 units.

      What is the proposed sample size? In the pilot study (described above), it was found that
      after 2 weeks, compared with the placebo group, those assigned to fluticasone experienced a
      significant decrease in CRP levels from baseline, after adjustments for baseline FEV1, age,
      and sex of participating patients (57.1% decrease relative to placebo; p=0.042). The
      (geometric) mean of CRP for this cohort was 4.9 mg/L (95% CI, 3.3 to 7.1). Sample sizes of
      200 participants combined in Flovent and Advair group (100 in each) and 50 in the placebo
      group will be needed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>December 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date>August 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in serum C-reactive protein levels over 3 months between treatment groups.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes in serum interleukin levels; quality of life; FEV1 between treatment groups</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>250</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Advair</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Flovent</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients must have a clinical diagnosis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
             according to Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) guidelines.

          -  Patients must have a cigarette smoking history of more than 10 pack-years

          -  Patients must be clinically stable and at least 4 weeks from last acute exacerbation
             (and return to baseline level of symptoms)

          -  Patients must have an FEV1 of less than 80% of predicted values with FEV1 to FVC ratio
             of less than 0.70 (post-bronchodilator values)

          -  Men or women ≥ 45 years of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Don Sin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Roxanne Rousseau, BS</last_name>
    <phone>604-977-9791</phone>
    <email>RRousseau@mrl.ubc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Don D Sin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>604-806-8395</phone>
    <email>dsin@mrl.ubc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Calgary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2V 1P9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gladys Wolters, BS</last_name>
      <phone>403-943-3292</phone>
      <email>Gladys.Wolters@CalgaryHealthRegion.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gordon Ford, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Cowie, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Links Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T5G 3G6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jill Edwards, BS</last_name>
      <phone>780-913-4240</phone>
      <email>jilledwards@shaw.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Warren Ramesh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alberta Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2B7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Heidi Haupt, BS</last_name>
      <phone>(780) 407-7591</phone>
      <email>hhaupt@ualberta.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric Wong, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grey Nuns Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6L 5X8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Barchard, BS</last_name>
      <phone>780.450.7178</phone>
      <email>JBarchar@cha.ab.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lyle Melenka, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lethbridge Regional Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lethbridge</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T1J 1W5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathy Duce, BS</last_name>
      <phone>403-388-6031</phone>
      <email>kduce@mail.chr.ab.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric Wilde, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wetaskiwin Lung Laboratory</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wetaskiwin</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T9A 3B8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teena Rossiter, BS</last_name>
      <phone>780.352.7085</phone>
      <email>teena@incentre.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ernest York, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lion's Gate Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>North Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V7L 2N3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anju Mainra, BS</last_name>
      <phone>: 604.649.5852</phone>
      <email>mainra@shaw.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raj Mainra, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vancouver General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 3J5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Linda Hui, BS</last_name>
      <phone>604.875.5697</phone>
      <email>lindahui@interchange.ubc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Fitzgerald, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Paul' Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6Z 1Y6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roxanne Rousseau, BS</last_name>
      <phone>604-977-9791</phone>
      <email>RRousseau@mrl.ubc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Man, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Don Sin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal University Hospita</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saskatoon</city>
        <state>Saskatchewan</state>
        <zip>S7N 0W8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Janet Baron, BS</last_name>
      <phone>306.966.7871</phone>
      <email>janetbaron@shaw.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Darcy Marciniuk, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Reid, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sin DD, Man SF, Marciniuk DD, Ford G, FitzGerald M, Wong E, York E, Mainra RR, Ramesh W, Melenka LS, Wilde E, Cowie RL, Williams D, Rousseau R; ABC (Advair, Biomarkers in COPD) Investigators. Can inhaled fluticasone alone or in combination with salmeterol reduce systemic inflammation in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease? Study protocol for a randomized controlled trial [NCT00120978]. BMC Pulm Med. 2006 Feb 6;6:3.</citation>
    <PMID>16460562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 11, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 19, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 9, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Clinical Trial; C-reactive protein; fluticasone; salmeterol</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone Propionate, Salmeterol Xinafoate Drug Combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

