<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02029053</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>67709</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02029053</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preliminary Study of a Vaginal Lubrication Ring to Treat the Symptoms of Vaginal Dryness</brief_title>
  <official_title>VR101: A Pilot Study to Evaluate the Preliminary Feasibility and Safety of a Lubricating Intravaginal Ring to Relieve the Symptoms of Vaginal Dryness</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>J3 Bioscience, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>J3 Bioscience, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study, assessing the ability and safety of the use of VR101 intravaginal ring
      to relieve the symptoms of vaginal dryness, in peri and post-menopausal women. VR1010 is
      designed to release glycerol. The study will assess the duration of lubrication/
      moisturization of the vagina with the VR101 intravaginal ring in place (up to 7 days) and
      participant satisfaction of the device.

      Study participants will insert the intravaginal ring and leave it in place for an initial 7
      days and then repeat this process a 2nd time. Participants will respond to questionnaires,
      complete a daily diary and come in for 4 separate study visits. Each study visit will involve
      a brief vaginal exam.

      Upon removal of the initially inserted device (7 days after first study visit), participants
      will insert a second device for an additional 7 days and undergo the same evaluation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Vaginal dryness affects many women, although they frequently do not bring up the topic with
      their doctors. Vaginal dryness can dramatically affect women's lifestyle, in particular their
      sexual activity and relationship with their partner. Since we believe that living with
      uncomfortable vaginal dryness does not have to be part of aging, we intend to conduct this
      study to evaluate a lubricating vaginal ring developed to ease symptoms caused by vaginal
      dryness.

      The objectives of this study are to obtain preliminary data on the ability of the VR101
      intravaginal ring to relieve the symptoms of vaginal dryness in peri- and post-menopausal
      women. Effectiveness will be measured in two ways:

        1. Vaginal health index scoring assessed by a member of the research team

        2. Participant answers to questionnaires

      Study objectives will assess the following:

        1. Successful placement of VR101 intravaginal ring into the vagina

        2. Ease of insertion and removal

        3. Comfort and fit

        4. Lubrication/ moisturization of the vagina
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vaginal lubrication/moisturization</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of patient reported vaginal lubrication/moisturization while the intravaginal ring is inserted.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comfort and fit of intravaginal ring</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of patient satisfaction with the comfort and fit of the intravaginal ring during the study period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Successful vaginal placement and removal</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of patient ability to self-insert and self-remove the intravaginal ring at the initial study visit as well as throughout the 14 day time period of the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Menopausal and Perimenopausal Disorder, Unspecified</condition>
  <condition>Atrophic Vaginitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm Study</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vaginal Lubrication Ring for Vaginal Dryness</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vaginal Lubrication Ring for Vaginal Dryness</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be asked to complete 4 study visits and one final follow-up phone call. Each study visit will include a brief vaginal exam where vaginal fluid levels and pH levels are checked and questionnaires are completed. Daily diaries will be completed at home and returned to the study staff at subsequent visits.
Participants will self-insert the Intravaginal ring on the 1st study visit. The 2nd study visit will occur 3-4 days later.
The 3rd study visit will occur approximately 7 days after the 1st visit. Participants will remove the device and self-insert a new intravaginal ring.
The 4th study visit will occur approximately 14 days after the first visit. Participants will remove the intravaginal ring and undergo a final vaginal exam.
Participants will be called approximately 7 days after the last visit and will be asked about their current vaginal dryness symptoms and how they felt about the device during the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm Study</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VR101</other_name>
    <other_name>Intravaginal Ring</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed informed consent

          -  Females over 35 years of age at the time of enrollment

          -  Willing to comply with study visit schedule

          -  Self-reported peri- or post-menopausal women with self-reported vaginal dryness

          -  Willing to abstain from vaginal intercourse while in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of hormone therapy

          -  Undergoing any vulvar or vaginal procedures (biopsies, radiation in the last 3 months)

          -  Active vulvar or vaginal injections/lesions or complaints, as well as undiagnosed
             abnormal genital bleeding

          -  History of chronic pelvic pain, interstitial cystitis, vulvar vestibulitis, pelvic
             inflammatory disease within the past 12 weeks

          -  Known current clinically evident cervical or vaginal infection

          -  Postpartum or post-abortion endometritis, unless symptoms resolved at least 12 weeks
             prior to study entry

          -  Current persistent, abnormal vaginal bleeding

          -  History of inability to place an IVR

          -  History of any abnormality of the vagina resulting in distortion of the vaginal canal
             or incompatible with IVR placement

          -  Body habitus, or history of lower genital tract abnormalities or prior surgeries,
             which may not allow the vagina to be appropriately accessed

          -  Known or suspected allergy or hypersensitivity to polyurethane or glycerol

          -  Known current alcohol or illicit drug abuse

          -  Participants who have not recovered from adverse events due to chemotherapy or
             radiation treatment for cancer

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator or study staff that would
             constitute contraindications to participation in the study or would compromise ability
             to comply with the study protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Margit Janat-Amsbury, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Utah</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah Health Sciences Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84132</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palacios S. Managing urogenital atrophy. Maturitas. 2009 Aug 20;63(4):315-8. doi: 10.1016/j.maturitas.2009.04.009. Epub 2009 Jun 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19493638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vaginal atrophy. Managing vaginal dryness and irritation. Mayo Clin Health Lett. 2012 Oct;30(10):6.</citation>
    <PMID>23133861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woods NF. An overview of chronic vaginal atrophy and options for symptom management. Nurs Womens Health. 2012 Dec;16(6):482-93; quiz 494. doi: 10.1111/j.1751-486X.2012.01776.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23253575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andelloux M. Products for sexual lubrication: understanding and addressing options with your patients. Nurs Womens Health. 2011 Jun-Jul;15(3):253-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1751-486X.2011.01642.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21672177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bond S, Horton LS. Management of postmenopausal vaginal symptoms in women. J Gerontol Nurs. 2010 Jul;36(7):3-7. doi: 10.3928/00989134-20100527-96. Epub 2010 Jul 8.</citation>
    <PMID>20608584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 3, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 3, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 7, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 14, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 14, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vaginal dryness</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaginal lubrication</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-menopausal symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Peri-menopausal symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Urogenital atrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>Dyspareunia</keyword>
  <keyword>Painful intercourse</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaginitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrophic Vaginitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

