<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02027298</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CC-Yao-2012001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02027298</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Abatacept for Patients With Inflammatory Arthritis Associated With Sjögren's Syndrome: an Open-Label Phase II Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Abatacept for Patients With Inflammatory Arthritis Associated With Sjögren's Syndrome: an Open-Label Phase II Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Cleveland Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Cleveland Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this pilot study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of Abatacept
      in subjects with Sjogren's Syndrome (SS). This clinical trial study will enroll and treat 15
      subjects with active moderate and severe inflammatory arthritis associated with primary
      Sjogren's syndrome (pSS) and secondary Sjogren's sybdrine (sSS) with Rheumatoid Arthrits
      (RA). All subjects will receive Abatacept weekly by Subcutaneous (SC) dosing. Subjects will
      receive Abatacept by SC injection of 125 mg on day 1 and followed by 125 mg SC weekly
      thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sjogren's Syndrome (SS) is a common systemic autoimmune disease, including primary and
      secondary form. About 30% of RA are associated with sSS (1) Tumor necrosis factor alpha
      inhibitors (TNFa-Is) have been tried in this population without success. Abatacept (CTLA4-Ig)
      is comprised of the ligand-binding domain of CTLA4 plus human immunoglobulin and represents a
      novel therapeutic costimulation blocker that modulates the signal required for full T cell
      activation. Studies have shown that activated CD4 T cells play a role in the pathogenesis of
      SS, indicating Abatacept might be a useful therapeutic intervention in SS. Subjects who are
      receiving non-biologic immunosuppressive medications consisting of hydroxychloroquine,
      methotrexate (MTX), sulfasalazine, or leflunomide, at the time of enrollment will remain on
      these medications without dosage alteration. Efficacy and Safety data will be collected at
      the time of each clinic visit. The treatment closing date will occur 6 months after
      enrollment of each subject. Subjects will be followed at 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 months.
      Laboratory studies associated with the clinical trial will test potential autoantibody
      production for systemic autoimmune diseases.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    No Enrollment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of Abatacept in patients with inflammatory arthritis and Sjogren's Syndrome</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the efficacy for inflammatory arthritis of Abatacept in patients with both pSS and sSS. The primary efficacy endpoint for determining the efficacy is the proportion of patients meeting the ACR 20% improvement criteria at month 6.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase or change in autoantibody profile</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 3, 6 and 3 month follow up</time_frame>
    <description>A secondary endpoint is to assess autoantibody production as measured by Bioplex2200, including antinuclear antibodies (ANA), anti-ENA (Sm, RNP, SSA, SSB, chromatin, Scl70 and centromere) antibodies, anti-dsDNA antibodies, Complement 3 (C3)/Complement 4 (C4), immunoglobulin (Ig), erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) and C-reactive protein (CRP).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Explore the potential efficacy of Abatacept in the exocrine glandular function</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 1, 3 and 6</time_frame>
    <description>The last efficacy endpoint is to explore the efficacy of Abatacept in the exocrine glandular function including assessment of xerophthalmia and xerostomia using 0-100 mm visual analog scale (VAS)(29) and functional measurement of salivary gland and lacrimal gland.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Sjogren's Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Secondary Sjogren's Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Inflammatory Arthritis</condition>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Abatacept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Abatacept by SC injection of 125 mg weekly for 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abatacept</intervention_name>
    <description>by SC injection of 125 mg weekly for 6 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Abatacept</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Orencia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of Sjogren's Syndrome

          2. Patients are at least 18 years or older

          3. Patients should have either pSS and/or sSS associated with RA, and must have active
             moderate to severe inflammatory arthritis as defined by painful joint counts (≥5) and
             swollen joint counts (≥5), or DAS28 scores&gt;3.2.

          4. One non-biologic DMARD will be permitted.

          5. These patients will be willing and able to comply with treatment and follow-up
             procedures.

          6. These patients will be willing and able to provide written informed consent.

          7. Both women and men of child bearing age must be willing to use an effective means of
             birth control while receiving treatment throughout participation in this study.
             Effective contraception methods include abstinence, oral contraceptives (birth control
             pills), IUD, diaphragm, Norplant, approved hormone injections, condoms, or medical
             sterilization.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients will be excluded if they have a concomitant disorder requiring systemic
             glucocorticoid (GC) therapy (prednisone &gt;10 mg daily or GC equivalent), have
             organ-threatening features, and have any investigational drug including biologics
             within 28 days of study entry.

          2. History of cancer or diabetes mellitus

          3. Use of tricyclic antidepressants or anticholinergics

          4. Evidence of active infection or chronic infection including human immunodeficiency
             virus (HIV), tuberculosis (TB), hepatitis C, or a positive hepatitis B surface
             antigen.

          5. Patients with latent TB if not treated with isoniazid for at least 4 weeks prior to
             receiving the study drug

          6. Radiographic evidence of COPD, emphysema, and/or interstitial lung disease.

          7. Subjects who are pregnant or who are nursing infants

          8. Patients with cytopenia: platelet count &lt;80,000/mm3, absolute neutrophil
             count&lt;1500/mm3, hematocrit &lt; 20%.

          9. Patients with renal insufficiency defined by a serum creatinine of greater than or
             equal to 2.0 mg/dL or creatinine clearance of less than or equal to 35 ml/min.

         10. Use of illegal drugs.

         11. A live vaccination fewer than 4 weeks before enrollment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Qingping Yao, MD, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Cleveland Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Abatacept</keyword>
  <keyword>Sjogren's Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Rheumatoid Arthritis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sjogren's Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Abatacept</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

