<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02021721</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-00058 [JIRB]</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12195/12</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02021721</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Next Generation DNA Sequencing in Patients With Idiopathic Male Infertility</brief_title>
  <official_title>Next Generation DNA Sequencing in Patients With Idiopathic Male Infertility</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hamad Medical Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Weill Cornell Medical College in Qatar</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hypothesis: To identify new gene mutations that can be related to patients with idiopathic
      male factor infertility.

      Primary Objective: To detect possible genetic abnormalities in families with more than one
      sibling with male infertility.

      Secondary Objective: To evaluate using next generation DNA sequencing in cases of infertility
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Infertility involves about 15% of couples who attempt to conceive and the male factor
      accounts for about half of the cases. Idiopathic, azoospermia, or oligozoospermia, which may
      be genetically based, constitute a significant number of male infertility cases.In the recent
      years, there is increasing recognition of the genetic abnormalities as a cause of male
      infertility. Genetic factors contribute up to 15 - 30% of male infertility cases. These
      abnormalities may be numerical chromosomal abnormality; the most common is Klinefelter
      syndrome, or structural e.g. Y-chomosome microdeletion, DNA mutations or mitochondrial DNA
      mutations. They account for 5%-10% cases of oligozoospermia, to 15%-25% cases with
      non-obstructive azoospermia. In azoospermia, sex chromosome abnormalities are predominant.
      However, autosomal structural chromosomal abnormalities are the chief genetic cause of
      oligozoospermia and may be balanced or unbalanced. In a substantial proportion of cases (32%
      of infertile men, or 1.5% of the male population), the underlying causes are unknown
      (idiopathic infertility). While cytogenetic studies have been successful in revealing some
      causes most non-obstructive azoospermic men are still idiopathic. They are believed to carry
      unknown autosomal mutations based on studies of familial male infertility that often involves
      two or more siblings.Regulation of the complex process of spermatogenesis depends on the
      cooperation of many genes which are expressed at various stages of differentiation, where
      mitotic, meiotic cell divisions, and postmeiotic development finally lead to the spermatozoa.
      Identification of genes playing a crucial role in spermatogenesis is mainly based on the
      observations of rodents, particularly the mouse model. In humans, such identification remains
      largely unavailable because of the difficulty in gaining access to tissue samples from a male
      gonad and the limited possibilities of functional verification in humans. Hence the genetic
      causes of male infertility have not yet been well recognized. Next-generation sequencing
      (NGS) is an effective tool for Mendelian gene identification. So far, more than 30 Mendelian
      disease genes have been identified using NGS, including recessive and dominant diseases. NGS
      data can also be used to discover linkage and homozygosity intervals, as well as determine
      copy number number of specific intervals (Becker et al. 2011, Krawitz et al. 2010). 15, 16
      The two major branches of next-generation DNA sequencing are whole-exome (WE) and whole
      genome (WG) sequencing. While WGS is more comprehensive and useful for population genetics or
      for diseases in which complex non-exonic inheritance is suspected, WES remains a more
      powerful, cost-effective tool for detecting rare mutations within a patient population. Our
      use of WGS or WES will depend on the nature of the patients recruited for the study. In cases
      where depth of coverage requirements are high, WES would be better-suited as it allows for
      4-6 exomes to be covered at such depth for the same cost of 1 genome at 30X. This would aid
      in sampling rarer alleles within the population and discovering novel mutations in patients
      that are not present in their unaffected family members. This is especially useful in cases
      of diseases where wide allelic heterogeneity may exist, as patients who test negative for the
      most common mutations may have a novel mutation that would otherwise have been undetectable
      by traditional methods. Multiple members of the same family may be affected by infertility
      with similar or different presentations of testicular failure with different
      histopathologies. In the presence of normal karyotyping and Y-chromosome microdeletion, we
      are usually left with unknown genetic abnormality. Genetic causes of male factor infertility
      can be broadly assumed to be a result of either de novo mutations inherited by the patient
      from one of his parents or from polymorphisms circulating in the population. In both cases, a
      search for potential genetic causes for infertility must rely on comparison of the DNA
      sequence of the patient with a controlled fertile member of his family.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Family-Based</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Next generation sequencing</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Use next generation sequencing to discover novel genes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects who fulfill the inclusion criteria will be pre-identified by consultation with their attending physicians and by thorough review of the literature to establish that the disease is indeed genetic and unsolved.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with be recruited from HMC infertility clinic.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The study will include male patients diagnosed with infertility, fitting one of the
             following categories:

          -  More than one family member complaining of male infertility

          -  All ethnicities will be included in this study

          -  Family members will be invited to join the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients in whim infertility is suspected to be caused by environmental factors more
             than genetic factors

          -  Patients whose cause of infertility has already been determined by other clinical
             testing

          -  Patients fulfilling the inclusion criteria but the other affected family member could
             not be recruited or did not approve of being included in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ronald Crystal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Haitham El Bardisi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hamad Medical Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Grace Mammen, BA, CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>6469622672</phone>
    <email>gwm2004@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Amal Robay, PhD, CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>+974-4492-8494</phone>
    <email>amr2018@qatar-med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hamad Medical Corporation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Doha</city>
        <country>Qatar</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alya Al-Shakaki</last_name>
      <phone>+974-492-8445</phone>
      <email>aaa2017@qatar-med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amal Robay, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Qatar</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 22, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 19, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 27, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infertility, Male</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

