<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02021422</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>013-018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02021422</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot, Prospective, Non-randomized Evaluation of the Safety of Anakinra Plus Standard Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot, Prospective, Non-randomized Evaluation of the Safety of Anakinra Plus Standard Chemotherapy Regimens in Metastatic Pancreatic Ductal Adenocarcinoma Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study's overall objectives are to evaluate the safety of anakinra in combination with
      standard chemotherapy regimens in patients with pancreatic ductal adenocarinoma, as well as
      to collect preliminary immune modulation and clinical activity information, overall survival,
      and serious adverse events related to the study drug.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Kineret (anakinra) is a FDA-approved drug indicated for rheumatoid arthritis. Anakinra is a
      recombinant, nonglycosylated form of the human interleukin-1 receptor antagonist (IL-1Ra).
      Anakinra blocks the biologic activity of IL -1 by competitively inhibiting IL-1 binding to
      the interleukin-1 type I receptor (IL-1RI), which is expressed in a wide variety of tissues
      and organs. IL-1 production is induced in response to inflammatory stimuli and mediates
      various physiologic effects including inflammatory and immunological responses.

      This is a pilot, prospective, non-randomized, consecutive enrollment study that will enroll
      up to 12 subjects who meet the study defined inclusion and exclusion criteria.

      Subjects will undergo standard of care chemotherapy treatment/regimens (i.e., modified
      FOLFIRINOX). Subjects will be dispensed a 2 weeks supply of anakinra the day they begin
      chemotherapy. They will be instructed to begin self-administering the anakinra (study drug)
      injections the day after their first dose of chemotherapy.

      They will have a blood sample collected at baseline and 6 months follow up. If they have
      surgery for their disease, they may have a tissue sample collected for later analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Number of Participants with SAEs and AEs.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Test the safety of Anakinra in combination with standard chemotherapy in patients with metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) as evidenced by the Number of Participants with serious adverse events (SAEs) and adverse events (AEs).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall Survival (OS) rate as defined by the percentage of people who are alive for a certain period of time after diagnosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events associated with injection site reactions and the incidence of infections</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events associated with injection site reactions and the incidence of infections</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Data Collection: tumor measurements by CT scans</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Data Collection: tumor measurements by CT scans</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gather preliminary information on the immune modulation and clinical activity of this therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Blood transcriptional profiling
Composition of white blood cells
Assessment of PDAC antigen--specific T cell repertoire in the blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreas Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anakinra with Modified Folfirinox</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>8-weeks of anakinra and modified FOLFIRINOX regimen (refer to Appendix 9 for regimen) as follows
Kineret (anakinra) Dosage Route Administration 100 mg SC Every Other Day
Modified FOLFIRINOX Drug Dose Administration Oxaliplatin 85 mg/m2 2-4 hours Irinotecan 180 mg/m2 90 minutes fluorouracil 2400 mg/m2 48 hours</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>anakinra</intervention_name>
    <description>Dosage Route Administration 100 mg SC Every Other Day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anakinra with Modified Folfirinox</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kineret</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxaliplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Oxaliplatin 85 mg/m2 2-4 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anakinra with Modified Folfirinox</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Irinotecan</intervention_name>
    <description>Irinotecan 180 mg/m2 90 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anakinra with Modified Folfirinox</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Camptosar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorouracil</intervention_name>
    <description>fluorouracil 2400 mg/m2 48 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anakinra with Modified Folfirinox</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5 FU</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Male or non-pregnant and non-lactating female

          -  Confirmed metastatic/inoperable metastatic pancreas cancer and/or
             Histologically/cytologically confirmed metastatic adenocarcinoma of pancreas

          -  Patients' blood counts and blood chemistry levels at baseline must be not clinically
             significant (NCS) as determined by the enrolling investigator.

          -  Patient has Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group( ECOG ) Performance Status 0 to 2
             (refer to Appendix 5):

          -  Signed study consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt;18 years of age

          -  Pregnant or lactating female

          -  Patient has islet cell neoplasms

          -  Active secondary malignancies (2nd cancer not treated/present)

          -  Active, uncontrolled bacterial, viral, or fungal infection(s) requiring systemic
             therapy

          -  Known infection with hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or cirrhosis

          -  Major surgery or vascular device placement (excluding ports for IV
             medication/chemotherapy) within 2 weeks prior to Day 1 of treatment in study

          -  History of allergy or hypersensitivity to the study drugs

          -  Patient is enrolled in any concurrent-outside (outside Baylor University Medical
             Center or Texas Oncology) clinical protocol or investigational trial

          -  Significant cardiac disease as defined as New York Heart Association (NYHA)
             classification III or IV, uncontrolled CHF, or prior MI last 6-months

          -  Any prior gastrointestinal (GI) disease or history of prior pelvic or abdominal
             radiation which in the opinion of the investigator may place the patient at increased
             risk

          -  Peripheral sensory neuropathy ≥ to grade 2 at baseline

          -  Significant co-morbidities deemed by investigator as unsuitable for
             participation/enrollment

          -  Study consent form not signed
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos Becerra, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor Sammons Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor Sammons Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75246</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allantaz F, Chaussabel D, Stichweh D, Bennett L, Allman W, Mejias A, Ardura M, Chung W, Smith E, Wise C, Palucka K, Ramilo O, Punaro M, Banchereau J, Pascual V. Blood leukocyte microarrays to diagnose systemic onset juvenile idiopathic arthritis and follow the response to IL-1 blockade. J Exp Med. 2007 Sep 3;204(9):2131-44. Epub 2007 Aug 27. Erratum in: J Exp Med. 2009 Sep 28;206(10):2299. Smith, Elisabeth [added].</citation>
    <PMID>17724127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aspord C, Pedroza-Gonzalez A, Gallegos M, Tindle S, Burton EC, Su D, Marches F, Banchereau J, Palucka AK. Breast cancer instructs dendritic cells to prime interleukin 13-secreting CD4+ T cells that facilitate tumor development. J Exp Med. 2007 May 14;204(5):1037-47. Epub 2007 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>17438063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beatty GL, Chiorean EG, Fishman MP, Saboury B, Teitelbaum UR, Sun W, Huhn RD, Song W, Li D, Sharp LL, Torigian DA, O'Dwyer PJ, Vonderheide RH. CD40 agonists alter tumor stroma and show efficacy against pancreatic carcinoma in mice and humans. Science. 2011 Mar 25;331(6024):1612-6. doi: 10.1126/science.1198443.</citation>
    <PMID>21436454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennett L, Palucka AK, Arce E, Cantrell V, Borvak J, Banchereau J, Pascual V. Interferon and granulopoiesis signatures in systemic lupus erythematosus blood. J Exp Med. 2003 Mar 17;197(6):711-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12642603</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chaussabel D, Quinn C, Shen J, Patel P, Glaser C, Baldwin N, Stichweh D, Blankenship D, Li L, Munagala I, Bennett L, Allantaz F, Mejias A, Ardura M, Kaizer E, Monnet L, Allman W, Randall H, Johnson D, Lanier A, Punaro M, Wittkowski KM, White P, Fay J, Klintmalm G, Ramilo O, Palucka AK, Banchereau J, Pascual V. A modular analysis framework for blood genomics studies: application to systemic lupus erythematosus. Immunity. 2008 Jul 18;29(1):150-64. doi: 10.1016/j.immuni.2008.05.012.</citation>
    <PMID>18631455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coussens LM, Zitvogel L, Palucka AK. Neutralizing tumor-promoting chronic inflammation: a magic bullet? Science. 2013 Jan 18;339(6117):286-91. doi: 10.1126/science.1232227. Review. Erratum in: Science. 2013 Mar 29;339(6127):1522.</citation>
    <PMID>23329041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Monte L, Reni M, Tassi E, Clavenna D, Papa I, Recalde H, Braga M, Di Carlo V, Doglioni C, Protti MP. Intratumor T helper type 2 cell infiltrate correlates with cancer-associated fibroblast thymic stromal lymphopoietin production and reduced survival in pancreatic cancer. J Exp Med. 2011 Mar 14;208(3):469-78. doi: 10.1084/jem.20101876. Epub 2011 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21339327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalos M, Levine BL, Porter DL, Katz S, Grupp SA, Bagg A, June CH. T cells with chimeric antigen receptors have potent antitumor effects and can establish memory in patients with advanced leukemia. Sci Transl Med. 2011 Aug 10;3(95):95ra73. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3002842.</citation>
    <PMID>21832238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuraishy A, Karin M, Grivennikov SI. Tumor promotion via injury- and death-induced inflammation. Immunity. 2011 Oct 28;35(4):467-77. doi: 10.1016/j.immuni.2011.09.006. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22035839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>La Torre M, Nigri G, Ferrari L, Cosenza G, Ravaioli M, Ramacciato G. Hospital volume, margin status, and long-term survival after pancreaticoduodenectomy for pancreatic adenocarcinoma. Am Surg. 2012 Feb;78(2):225-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22369834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laheru D, Jaffee EM. Immunotherapy for pancreatic cancer - science driving clinical progress. Nat Rev Cancer. 2005 Jun;5(6):459-67. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15905855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee HC, Ziegler SF. Inducible expression of the proallergic cytokine thymic stromal lymphopoietin in airway epithelial cells is controlled by NFkappaB. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Jan 16;104(3):914-9. Epub 2007 Jan 9.</citation>
    <PMID>17213320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maker AV, Katabi N, Qin LX, Klimstra DS, Schattner M, Brennan MF, Jarnagin WR, Allen PJ. Cyst fluid interleukin-1beta (IL1beta) levels predict the risk of carcinoma in intraductal papillary mucinous neoplasms of the pancreas. Clin Cancer Res. 2011 Mar 15;17(6):1502-8. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-10-1561. Epub 2011 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>21266527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palucka AK, Gatlin J, Blanck JP, Melkus MW, Clayton S, Ueno H, Kraus ET, Cravens P, Bennett L, Padgett-Thomas A, Marches F, Islas-Ohlmayer M, Garcia JV, Banchereau J. Human dendritic cell subsets in NOD/SCID mice engrafted with CD34+ hematopoietic progenitors. Blood. 2003 Nov 1;102(9):3302-10. Epub 2003 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>12869510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palucka AK, Ueno H, Connolly J, Kerneis-Norvell F, Blanck JP, Johnston DA, Fay J, Banchereau J. Dendritic cells loaded with killed allogeneic melanoma cells can induce objective clinical responses and MART-1 specific CD8+ T-cell immunity. J Immunother. 2006 Sep-Oct;29(5):545-57.</citation>
    <PMID>16971810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Palucka K, Banchereau J. Cancer immunotherapy via dendritic cells. Nat Rev Cancer. 2012 Mar 22;12(4):265-77. doi: 10.1038/nrc3258. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22437871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pascual V, Allantaz F, Arce E, Punaro M, Banchereau J. Role of interleukin-1 (IL-1) in the pathogenesis of systemic onset juvenile idiopathic arthritis and clinical response to IL-1 blockade. J Exp Med. 2005 May 2;201(9):1479-86. Epub 2005 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>15851489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pedroza-Gonzalez A, Xu K, Wu TC, Aspord C, Tindle S, Marches F, Gallegos M, Burton EC, Savino D, Hori T, Tanaka Y, Zurawski S, Zurawski G, Bover L, Liu YJ, Banchereau J, Palucka AK. Thymic stromal lymphopoietin fosters human breast tumor growth by promoting type 2 inflammation. J Exp Med. 2011 Mar 14;208(3):479-90. doi: 10.1084/jem.20102131. Epub 2011 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21339324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramilo O, Allman W, Chung W, Mejias A, Ardura M, Glaser C, Wittkowski KM, Piqueras B, Banchereau J, Palucka AK, Chaussabel D. Gene expression patterns in blood leukocytes discriminate patients with acute infections. Blood. 2007 Mar 1;109(5):2066-77. Epub 2006 Nov 14.</citation>
    <PMID>17105821</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sebens Müerköster S, Werbing V, Sipos B, Debus MA, Witt M, Grossmann M, Leisner D, Kötteritzsch J, Kappes H, Klöppel G, Altevogt P, Fölsch UR, Schäfer H. Drug-induced expression of the cellular adhesion molecule L1CAM confers anti-apoptotic protection and chemoresistance in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma cells. Oncogene. 2007 Apr 26;26(19):2759-68. Epub 2006 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>17086212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vence L, Palucka AK, Fay JW, Ito T, Liu YJ, Banchereau J, Ueno H. Circulating tumor antigen-specific regulatory T cells in patients with metastatic melanoma. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Dec 26;104(52):20884-9. Epub 2007 Dec 18.</citation>
    <PMID>18093940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu CI, Gallegos M, Marches F, Zurawski G, Ramilo O, García-Sastre A, Banchereau J, Palucka AK. Broad influenza-specific CD8+ T-cell responses in humanized mice vaccinated with influenza virus vaccines. Blood. 2008 Nov 1;112(9):3671-8. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-05-157016. Epub 2008 Aug 19.</citation>
    <PMID>18713944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 27, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC)</keyword>
  <keyword>pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>pancreas cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>pancreatic adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic pancreas cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin 1 Receptor Antagonist Protein</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

