<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02028351</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VVS 001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02028351</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vision Measured by the Vimetrics CVA Compared With Chart Testing Under Similar Luminance and Contrast Conditions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Vision Measured by the Vimetrics Central Vision Analyzer With That Measured by logMAR Acuity Chart Testing Under Similar Conditions of Luminance and Contrast</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sinclair Technologies, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sinclair Technologies, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose of The Study:

      The purpose of this study is the following:

      A)To gather age-related normative visual acuity data for the Vimetrics Central Vision
      Analyzer (CVA, Vimetrics, LLC, Media, Pa) B)To gather visual acuity data for patients with
      known ocular problems, including cataract and maculopathy.

      C)To correlate and compare the CVA visual acuity findings with the acuity measured with
      standard LogMAR acuity charts viewed under similar conditions of contrast and lighting
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The measurement of visual acuity involves the determination of the smallest high contrast
      target that can be resolved by the patient. Classically, this has been approached by the use
      of letter style optotypes, each having successively smaller stroke and gap resolution. More
      recently, the arrangements of letter charts have been redesigned with a logarithmic scale and
      with attention being paid to the uniformity of other effects such as crowding or of the
      choice of optotype. The resultant Ferris-Bailey-Lovie chart has become a standard for acuity
      testing, especially for clinical research. The letters of such acuity charts have a 0.1
      logMAR step progression (1.26 X) between lines and have 5 letters per line. It has been noted
      that the logMAR chart could have greater resolution with finer steps between the lines and
      with improved repeatability by converting to a letter-by-letter scoring system.

      While these advances have improved the resolution and reliability of acuity measures, they
      require relatively cumbersome wall charts and do not provide any of the advantages of an
      interactive program that would enable a threshold to be approached by stimulus presentation
      on both the seeing as well as non-seeing sides.

      The Vimetrics CVA is an interactive computer device that measures threshold visual acuity by
      presenting a Landolt-C with the gap randomly tumbled in one of 4 positions to which the
      patient responds with a response pad. The threshold is approached in a logarithmic, staircase
      fashion to define the test subject's acuity threshold with a resolution similar to letter by
      letter scoring in chart testing but with the ability to rapidly test under a number of
      conditions of luminance and contrast that simulate activities of daily living.

      The CVA determination of visual acuity under six conditions of contrast and lighting will be
      compared with that acquired by logMAR chart testing under similar conditions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of monocular Visual Acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>Upon recruitment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Refractive Error</condition>
  <condition>Cataract</condition>
  <condition>Maculopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal</arm_group_label>
    <description>No Intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cataract</arm_group_label>
    <description>No intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Maculopathy</arm_group_label>
    <description>No Intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Primary Eye Clinic
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        General Exclusion Criteria:

        those individuals whom the examiner determines cannot read the ETDRS letter chart to define
        vision and those individuals whom the examiner determines cannot respond to the computer
        presentation of the tumbled Landolt C by pressing one of the 4 buttons arranged in a
        diamond or by deflecting the joystick on the response pad held in the lap.

        Normals:

        Systemic Disease Exclusion Criteria: Persons with systemic disease that would interfere
        with vision will be excluded under the normal classification. Such diseases that would
        exclude a subject from this category would include diabetes, and other systemic diseases
        such as neurological disorders that the examiner determines may interfere with the vision
        of an eye.

        Ocular Inclusion criteria:

        For inclusion in the normal group an eye would have an ocular examination within three
        months that, in the least, included the following:

        A visual acuity measured of 20/30 or better for which on examination the refractive error
        alone is determined to define the vision.

        For individuals 65 years or greater, lens nuclear opalescence and brunescence that is less
        than or equal to NO3, NC3 according to the LOCS III grading system.

        For individuals less than 65 years, lens nuclear opalescence and brunescence that is less
        than or equal to NO2, NC2, according to the LOCS III grading system.

        Ocular Exclusion Criteria:

        Media opacity or retinal or optic nerve pathology that the examiner determines would affect
        the measured vision.

        For individuals aged 65 or greater, eyes with nuclear opalescence and brunescence,
        according to the LOCS III grading system greater than NO3, NC3 or with other opacities will
        be excluded.

        Eyes with Cataracts:

        General Inclusion Criteria:

        Persons without systemic disease that would interfere with vision will be enrolled. Such
        diseases that would exclude a subject from this category would include diabetes, and other
        systemic diseases such as neurological disorders that the examiner determines may interfere
        with the vision of an eye.

        Ocular Inclusion Criteria:

        For inclusion an eye would have had an ocular examination within three months as per the
        stated protocol.

        A visual acuity worse than 20/30. The determination on examination by the examiner that the
        lens opacity alone defines the vision. For individuals less than age 65 the nuclear
        cataract will be denser than NO2, NC2 or contain other components (posterior cortical or
        posterior sub capsular) that will be documented. For individuals 65 years of age or older,
        the nuclear cataract will be greater than NO3, NC3 or contain other components that define
        the vision.

        Ocular Exclusion Criteria:

        Eyes in which retinal or optic nerve pathology that the examiner determines would affect
        the measured vision.

        Eyes with a best refracted chart acuity of 20/100 or worse because in such eyes the
        examiner will be prevented by the media opacity from adequately examining the fundus to
        determine if there is co-existent macular pathology.

        Eyes with Maculopathy:

        General Inclusion Criteria:

        It is recognized that many individuals within this group will have diabetes or hypertension
        that may be the cause of the maculopathy or aggravate the maculopathy. However, such
        systemic diseases will not necessarily exclude such persons, unless the examiner determines
        that such diseases cause reduced vision in the eye that is not defined by the maculopathy.

        Ocular Inclusion Criteria:

        For inclusion an eye would have had an ocular examination within three months with
        components according to the protocol as stated.

        A visual acuity with chart testing worse than 20/30 for which on examination the
        maculopathy alone is determined to define the vision.

        Ocular Exclusion Criteria:

        Eyes with a chart acuity of 20/400 or worse. Eyes having lens or optic nerve pathology that
        the examiner determines would affect the measured vision.

        Eyes with dense cataract in which an adequate examination of the macula is prevented.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen H Sinclair, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sinclair Technologies, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennsylvania College of Optometry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Elkins Park</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gutstein Optik</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arditi A, Cagenello R. On the statistical reliability of letter-chart visual acuity measurements. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1993 Jan;34(1):120-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8425819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bourne RR, Rosser DA, Sukudom P, Dineen B, Laidlaw DA, Johnson GJ, Murdoch IE. Evaluating a new logMAR chart designed to improve visual acuity assessment in population-based surveys. Eye (Lond). 2003 Aug;17(6):754-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12928690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hazel CA, Elliott DB. The dependency of logMAR visual acuity measurements on chart design and scoring rule. Optom Vis Sci. 2002 Dec;79(12):788-92.</citation>
    <PMID>12512687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raasch TW, Bailey IL, Bullimore MA. Repeatability of visual acuity measurement. Optom Vis Sci. 1998 May;75(5):342-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9624699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bailey IL. New procedures for detecting early vision losses in the elderly. Optom Vis Sci. 1993 Apr;70(4):299-305. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8502458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carkeet A. Modeling logMAR visual acuity scores: effects of termination rules and alternative forced-choice options. Optom Vis Sci. 2001 Jul;78(7):529-38.</citation>
    <PMID>11503943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 29, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 3, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 7, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 7, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sinclair Technologies, LLC</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stephen H. Sinclair, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief Medical Officer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>visual acuity</keyword>
  <keyword>contrast sensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>cataract</keyword>
  <keyword>maculopathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Refractive Errors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

