<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02021149</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-0614</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02021149</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enhancing Psychotherapy for Mood Disorders With Whole Body Hyperthermia</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charles (Chuck) Raison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arizona</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      According to the 2005 National Comorbidity Survey-Replication study, approximately 20.9
      million American adults, or 9.5 percent of the population over the age of 18 suffer from mood
      disorders including major depressive disorder, chronic, mild depression and bipolar disorder.
      Major depressive disorder (MDD) is predicted to be the second leading cause of disability
      worldwide by the year 2020; sub-clinical mood disturbances impact many additional people and
      are a major reason people seek psychotherapy services. The economic burden of depression in
      the United States is significant: $83.1 billion in 2000 and increasing. Much of this burden
      comes from the high rate of sub-optimal treatment outcomes associated with the disorder.
      Indeed, only 50% of MDD patients recover in less than 12 weeks with adequate treatment, and
      up to 20% of patients will fail to adequately respond to all currently available
      interventions. Moreover, current treatments come at the cost of significant central nervous
      system (CNS) side effects, further highlighting the need for more effective treatments with
      fewer side effects. To address these pressing clinical issues, the investigators will conduct
      a placebo controlled, clinical trial to determine if Whole Body Hyperthermia (WBH) enhances
      the effects of psychotherapy compared to psychotherapy alone in medically healthy patients
      with moderate to severe mood disorders. The investigators plan to recruit a sample of 24
      medically healthy individuals with mood problems who will be randomized to examine whether
      WBH enhances the effects of psychotherapy. To determine acute and sustained effects of WBH
      +psychotherapy on mood disorders, the study will include basic psychiatric
      questionnaire-based assessments at three therapy sessions prior to a single session conducted
      while receiving one of two intensities of WBH treatment. Subjects who elect not to conduct a
      therapy session in the WBH chamber will still be able to complete study questionnaires at all
      therapy sessions. This study challenges the existing paradigm by determining if peripheral
      afferent sensory pathways can be accessed to enhance the treatment of mood disorders and thus
      avoid problems of exposing all of the brain to non-selective drugs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our research group has observed in an open trial that a single session of whole body
      hyperthermia (WBH) induced rapid antidepressant effects that persisted for at least a week in
      patients with major depression (MDD) severe enough to warrant inpatient hospitalization. In
      addition to reducing depression, the single session of WBH induced a prolonged reduction in
      mean core body temperature, consistent with basic science data from our group suggesting that
      hyperthermia activates a skin-to-brain pathway that targets specific serotonergic nuclei in
      the raphe. In animal models, these nuclei have been shown to be important for mood and body
      temperature regulation. Consistent with this known anatomy in our preliminary study in
      depressed patients, reductions in core body temperature were highly correlated with
      reductions in depressive symptoms over the same time period (one week post WBH). Moreover,
      patients with higher mean core body temperature prior to treatment had enhanced
      antidepressant effects. Because increased body temperature is an outcome of poor functioning
      in the skin-to-brain pathway activated by WBH our data suggests that WBH may actually
      sensitize this pathway in ways that promote changes in brain functioning known to promote
      emotional well-being. The results of our first open trial have encouraged us to conduct a
      larger, more rigorous placebo-controlled, double blind study of WBH for MDD, which is
      currently underway at the University of Arizona Medical School.

      In addition to impacting depressive symptoms and body temperature, The investigators have
      observed that WBH induces striking increases in prosocial and self-disclosing behavior in
      many individuals. This effect initiates in the heating phase of the treatment and culminates
      at maximum body temperature. Importantly, our observations thus far suggest that this
      prosociality only occurs when the person in the hyperthermia box is accompanied by someone
      he/she knows to at least some degree. For example, a recent subject was silent during his
      initial WBH treatment in which he was attended by one of our staff that he had never met. He
      elected to get a repeat WBH session. The same &quot;attendant&quot; was present for this second WBH
      session, and during this session the patient became strikingly talkative and without
      prompting self-disclosed a range of very intimate personal issues related to his depression,
      such as a previously undisclosed history of childhood sexual abuse.

      The goal of the current proposal is to conduct a pilot study to evaluate whether this
      observed prosocial effect of WBH might be employed to accelerate and deepen the formation of
      therapeutic alliance in patients undergoing an 8-12 session course of cognitive behavioral
      psychotherapy (CBT). Our study design will also more rigorously test our clinical observation
      about the prosocial effects of WBH. In addition to potentially enhancing psychotherapeutic
      outcomes, the current study may provide data relevant to larger issues related to the near
      universal use of hyperthermia in indigenous cultures around the world for spiritual and
      health purposes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Investigator transferred to the University of Wisconsin - Madison
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depression scores over time [Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology—Self Report (IDS-SR)]</measure>
    <time_frame>Intake Session and at therapy sessions every week thereafter (Weeks 2-12), including the session that occurs during the WBH/WBH-control intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage change in scores between baseline and subsequent assessments will be assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Therapeutic bond / alliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Intake Session and at therapy sessions every week thereafter (Weeks 2-12).</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage change over time in the therapeutic alliance between patients and their therapists.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depression scores over time (OQ-45 Measurement)</measure>
    <time_frame>Intake Session and at therapy sessions every week thereafter (Weeks 2-12), including the session that occurs during the WBH/WBH-control intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in scores between baseline and subsequent assessments will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Vitality</measure>
    <time_frame>Intake Session and at therapy sessions every week thereafter (Weeks 2-12), including the session that occurs during the WBH/WBH-control intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in scores between baseline and subsequent assessments will be assessed using a vitality scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Positive and Negative Affect</measure>
    <time_frame>Intake Session and at therapy sessions every week thereafter (Weeks 2-12), including the session that occurs during the WBH/WBH-control intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Percent change in positive and negative affect will be assessed between baseline and subsequent assessments using the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule (PANAS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in relationship with psychotherapist</measure>
    <time_frame>Intake Session and at therapy sessions every week thereafter (Weeks 2-12), including the session that occurs during the WBH/WBH-control intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will use qualitative coding of psychotherapy sessions recorded at each psychotherapy session to assess whether WBH + psychotherapy affects and strengthens the ways in which patients relate to their psychotherapist and determined whether or not it enhances psychotherapy treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Psychotherapy and Questionnaire Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will have their regular psychotherapy sessions with their psychotherapist and will, prior to each session, fill out study related questionnaires.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High intensity whole-body infrared heating and Psychotherapy.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will have weekly psychotherapy sessions and fill out study questionnaires. The participant's 4th psychotherapy session will be conducted while the patient undergoes the WBH intervention where subjects will be induced to levels of heat that increases core body temperature to approximately 37.5-38.5 °C.temperature.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low intensity whole-body infrared heating and Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will have weekly psychotherapy sessions and fill out study questionnaires. The participant's 4th psychotherapy session will be conducted while the patient undergoes WBH-control where subjects will be induced to levels of heat that causes only a minor increase in body temperature.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High intensity whole-body infrared heating</intervention_name>
    <description>The Whole Body Hyperthermia system uses water-filtered infrared-A (wIRA) heat radiation. The rise in the body's core temperature is correspondingly rapid and well-tolerated. There are two phases of the thermal challenge, 1) Irradiation phase during which the patient lies recumbent with his/her head positioned outside the tent. The wIRA irradiators are arranged above the exposed upper part of the body; and 2) Heat retention phase during which the patient lies in the chamber with the walls of the tent positioned to retain heat. Core body temperatures will be raised to those comparable to a mild fever 37.8-38.5°C.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High intensity whole-body infrared heating and Psychotherapy.</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly psychotherapy using cognitive behavioral therapy sessions with a therapist.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Psychotherapy and Questionnaire Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High intensity whole-body infrared heating and Psychotherapy.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low intensity whole-body infrared heating and Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly questionnaires to assess changes in mood, perceptions of self and perceptions of effectiveness of the therapist/patient bond will be administered.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Psychotherapy and Questionnaire Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High intensity whole-body infrared heating and Psychotherapy.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low intensity whole-body infrared heating and Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low intensity whole-body infrared heating</intervention_name>
    <description>Attenuated heating using only heating coils at the bottom of the Heckel device. This results in only a minor increase in skin temperature and no increase in core body temperature. The participant will still feel heat and will see similar lighting and hear similar sounds as those occurring during actual WBH, and will be in the chamber for the same period of time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low intensity whole-body infrared heating and Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria for Psychotherapy and Questionnaire Group:

        - The only inclusion criteria for this group is that they are deemed eligible to receive
        psychotherapy at the Psychology Department Clinic, are fluent in English and are interested
        in participating in the study. There are no specific exclusion criteria for this study
        group.

        Inclusion Criteria for WBH Psychotherapy Group:

          -  Male or female outpatients aged 18-65.

          -  Able to understand the nature of the study and able to provide written informed
             consent prior to conduct of any study procedures.

          -  Able to communicate in English with study personnel.

          -  For women of child-bearing potential (i.e., one who is biologically capable of
             becoming pregnant), must be willing to use a medically acceptable form of birth
             control or practice abstinence for the duration of her participation in the trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any of the following diagnoses, as identified by the intake evaluation conducted or
             study assessments:

          -  A diagnosis claustrophobia severe enough that it would impair ability to be in the
             Heckel HT3000 hyperthermia device

          -  A current (or within 12 months prior to the Screening visit) diagnosis of Anorexia
             Nervosa or Bulimia Nervosa

          -  Subject has a medical condition or disorder that:

          -  Is unstable and clinically significant, or:

          -  Could interfere with the accurate assessment of safety or efficacy of treatment,
             including:

          -  individuals who are using prescription drugs that may impair thermoregulatory cooling,
             including diuretics, barbiturates, and beta-blockers, or antihistamines,

          -  individuals with cardiovascular conditions or problems (uncontrolled hypertension,
             congestive heart failure, or documented evidence of coronary artery disease)

          -  individuals with chronic conditions/diseases associated with a reduced ability
             initiate thermoregulatory cooling, including Parkinson's, multiple sclerosis, central
             nervous system tumors, and diabetes with neuropathy,

          -  hemophiliacs/individuals prone to bleeding,

          -  individuals with a fever the day of study intervention,

          -  individuals with hypersensitivity to heat,

          -  individuals with recent acute joint injury,

          -  individuals with enclosed infections, be they dental, in joints, or in any other
             tissues,

          -  Clinically significant, in the investigator's opinion, abnormal findings on screening
             laboratory tests or physical exam as presented to the research team.

          -  Use of any psychotropic medications for 2 weeks (8 weeks for fluoxetine) prior to
             initiation of the study, with the exception of hypnotic medications (zolpidem,
             zaleplon, eszopiclone).

          -  Need for any non-protocol psychotropic medication during the trial, with the exception
             of hypnotics used up to four nights per week.

          -  Women who are pregnant (HCG pregnancy test at screening, or lactating, or who plan to
             become pregnant during the study.

          -  Current participation in any clinical trial that might impact results of this one,
             which includes participation in another clinical trial for depression, as well as drug
             trials with agents that might affect mood or regulation of body temperature.

          -  Reasonable likelihood for non-compliance with the protocol for any other reason, in
             the opinion of the Investigator, prohibits enrollment of subject into the study.

          -  Obesity and overall size of subject. It will be up to the PI's discretion will
             consider BMI, waist circumference, and body fat composition when determining
             eligibility and safety of the individual.

          -  History of peripheral circulatory disease, for example peripheral vascular disease,
             deep vein thrombosis (DVT), or lymphedema.

          -  History of a cerebral vascular accident

          -  History of stroke, epilepsy or cerebral aneurisms

          -  Cancer in the last five years.

          -  Diabetes mellitus types I or II

          -  Any clinically significant autoimmune disease (compensated hypothyroidism allowed)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Raison, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arizona, Department of Psychiatry, College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Sbarra, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arizona</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85741</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 26, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 19, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 27, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 27, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Arizona</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Charles (Chuck) Raison</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, Department of Psychiatry (College of Medicine) and the Norton School of Family and Consumer Sciences</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Whole Body Hyperthermia</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Therapist and patient alliance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

