<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00752349</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200702029R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00752349</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Evaluate Oral Phase Swallowing Function Using Submental Ultrasound</brief_title>
  <official_title>To Evaluate Oral Phase Swallowing Function Using Submental Ultrasound</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Taiwan University Hospital</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Ultrasound is widely applied in many fields of medicine but less commonly used in the
      evaluation of tongue movement and swallowing abnormality. Fuhrman RAW reported the usefulness
      of using ultrasound to evaluate poor tongue coordination [1]. Peng CL stated that ultrasound
      could provide excellent quantitative and qualitative bases of tongue movement during
      swallowing using cushion-scan technique [2]. Videofluoroscopic swallowing study (VFSS) is
      widely accepted as the gold standard of evaluating swallowing abnormality because it is able
      to evaluate the whole swallowing procedure without interference of pharyngeal contraction and
      foreign body sensation when swallowing is examined by using a fiber-optic laryngoscope. One
      of the most important information that VFSS can provide is the detection of subclinical
      silent aspiration. The decision and management of many patients with swallowing abnormalities
      are usually based on the VFSS findings [3]. As shown in many reports, our experiences showed
      that VFSS provided extremely important information of understanding the pathophysiologic
      change of dysphagia due to variable etiologies, such as in patients with nasopharyngeal
      cancer suffering from radiation therapy [4] and in patients with stroke [5]. Using the
      findings of VFSS, physicians and medical staffs can make important decision whether oral
      feeding should be given, which safety swallowing maneuver works and what is the appropriate
      choices of food consistency safe to dysphagic patients. The difficulties of VFSS are usually
      in the transportation of paraplegic and hemiplegic patients from ward to the examining chair.
      The frequency and examination duration of VFSS is usually limited for avoiding unnecessary
      radiation exposure. Hence, ultrasound provides a role in evaluating oral condition with the
      benefits of convenience of transportation and availability as well as no radiation exposure.
      Therefore, validation of the value of ultrasound for the oral swallowing with correlation of
      VFSS is important to test the clinical feasibility.

      Peng CL et al reported their experiences of using real-time ultrasound in the evaluation of
      intrinsic tongue movement [2, 6, 7]. The findings of submental ultrasound are quite different
      from the findings of VFSS which provides the surface information of the tongue in the
      swallowing of radiopaque barium sulfate bolus. Combined real-time B mode and M mode
      ultrasound, it was reported the potential of digital data analysis of oral phase swallowing.
      Kuhl V et al reported the usefulness of ultrasound in the evaluation of laryngeal elevation
      in patients with dysphagia [8]. They found significant decrease of laryngeal elevation in
      patients diagnosed as neurogenic dysphasia [8]. Casas et al successfully combined ultrasound
      examination and plethysmography to evaluate the swallowing condition of children with
      cerebral palsy [9]. The results of these studies explained the potential of ultrasound in
      oral swallowing and dynamic laryngeal movement.

      Our experiences of VFSS showed the usefulness VFSS in diagnosing and management of patients
      with swallowing problem or dysphagia [4, 5, 10, 11]. To our knowledge, there was little
      experience of comparing between ultrasound and VFSS in patients with swallowing problem.
      Therefore, we conducted this study to correlate submental ultrasound and VFSS findings and
      tried to find out the clinical feasibility and usefulness.

      Purposes: This study was to evaluate the usefulness of submental ultrasound (SM US) in oral
      phase swallowing in correlation with videofluoroscopic study (VFSS).

        1. To compare normal volunteers and patients with swallowing abnormality with submental
           ultrasound.

        2. To evaluate and compare patients with swallowing problem using submental ultrasound and
           VFSS.

      Type of study: Retrospective. Time of study: Jan 2004 - July 2006.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Available</overall_status>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Dysphagia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>To evaluate oral phase swallowing function using submental ultrasound</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  &gt;= 20 yers

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chang Yeun-Chung, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>886-2-23123456</phone>
    <phone_ext>65566</phone_ext>
    <email>ycc5566@ntu.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>September 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 10, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 12, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 12, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Yeun-Chung Chang/ Department of medical imaging</name_title>
    <organization>National Taiwan University Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Videofluoroscopic</keyword>
  <keyword>swallowing</keyword>
  <keyword>study</keyword>
  <keyword>(VFSS)</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

