<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01521715</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>iOM-605</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2011-001138-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01521715</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>First Line Pazopanib in Poor Risk Patients With Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>FLIPPER</acronym>
  <official_title>A Single Arm Multicentre Study Evaluating Pazopanib in First-line Treatment of Poor-risk Patients With Locally Advanced or Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>iOMEDICO AG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>iOMEDICO AG</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with advanced renal cell carcinoma (RCC) are classified according to Memorial
      Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center (MSKCC) criteria in three risk-groups: favourable, intermediate
      and poor. To our knowledge there is only one study which examined the poor risk group (Hudes
      et al.), which led to the approval of temsirolimus in this population. However temsirolimus
      demonstrated a low response rate of 8.6% according to Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid
      Tumor (RECIST) criteria and a Progression free Survival (PFS) of 5.5 months and not all
      patients are suitable for temsirolimus treatment.

      Thus, in clinical routine high-risk patients are also treated with multi Tyrosinkinase
      Inhibitors (mTKI). To date, a prospective data acquisition and control of effectiveness of a
      mTKI-treatment in high-risk patients has not been conducted.

      Pazopanib was recently approved for the first-line treatment of advanced renal cell carcinoma
      in Europe and the USA. In the pivotal Phase III trial only nine patients in the pazopanib
      group were poor risk according to MSKCC risk criteria and no analysis of this subgroup was
      performed. Therefore further data in this group of patients with high medical need is needed.

      Currently there are no well-established predictive or prognostic biomarkers in RCC-mTKI
      treatment. This is one of the most important scientific questions in this field. In addition
      to the clinical endpoints in this study, the comprehensive biomarker program seeks to
      evaluate biomarker candidates and will help to learn more about the effects of pazopanib on
      the human organism.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 24, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 31, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of poor risk patients as defined by the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center (MSKCC) criteria who are free of disease progression at 6 months after start of first line treatment with pazopanib.</measure>
    <time_frame>from registration until progression of disease or death, assessed up to 6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival of poor risk patients treated with pazopanib.</measure>
    <time_frame>from registration until death of any cause assessed up 24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number, characteristics and severity of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>from first dose of pazopanib until 30 days after last dose, death or end of study, whichever came first</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival of patients treated with pazopanib</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 20 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate and duration of response according to Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 20 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relation between biomarkers and clinical outcome (response, stable disease, progression of disease)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 20 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Locally Advanced and/or Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</condition>
  <condition>Clear-cell Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pazopanib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>800 mg (2x400mg) pazopanib per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pazopanib</intervention_name>
    <description>800 mg (2x400mg) pazopanib per day should be taken orally without food at least one hour before or two hours after a meal until progression or occurrence of intolerable toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pazopanib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Votrient</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed metastatic or locally advanced (defined as non operable
             tumor), predominantly clear cell renal cell carcinoma.

          -  At least three of the following five predictors of short survival are required:

               -  Lactate Dehydrogenase (LDH) &gt; 1.5 x Upper Limit of Normal (ULN)

               -  Hemoglobin &lt; Lower Limit of Normal (LLN)

               -  corrected serum calcium level &gt; 10 mg/dl (2.5 mmol/l)

               -  time from initial diagnosis of renal-cell carcinoma to occurrence of metastases
                  of less than 1 year

               -  Karnofsky Status of 60 or 70

          -  Karnofsky Status ≥ 60

          -  Age ≥ 18 years or legal age of consent if greater than 18 years

          -  Dated and signed written informed consent prior to performance of study-specific
             procedures or assessments

          -  Patients with at least one measurable disease, as defined by RECIST 1.1

          -  Fresh or archived tumor tissue should be provided for all subjects for biomarker
             analysis before or during treatment with pazopanib.

          -  Adequate organ system function as defined as:

          -  Subjects may not have had a transfusion within 7 days of screening assessment.

          -  Subjects receiving anticoagulant therapy are eligible if their International
             Normalized Ratio (INR) is stable and within the recommended range for the desired
             level of anticoagulation.

          -  Concomitant elevations in bilirubin and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT) above 1.0 x ULN are not permitted. Patients with Gilbert's
             disease and elevation of indirect bilirubin only can be considered like patients with
             normal bilirubin.

          -  Compliance of the patient

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other malignancy. (Patients who have undergone prior radical or partial nephrectomy
             for RCC are allowed). Subjects who have had another malignancy and have been
             disease-free for five years, or subjects with a history of completely resected
             non-melanomatous skin carcinoma or successfully treated in situ carcinoma are
             eligible.

          -  Prior systemic treatment for renal cell carcinoma. (NB: all treatments, neo-adjuvant,
             adjuvant or for locally advanced or metastatic RCC are not permitted.)

          -  History or clinical evidence of central nervous system (CNS) metastases or
             leptomeningeal carcinomatosis, except for individuals who have previously-treated CNS
             metastases, are asymptomatic, and have had no requirement for steroids or anti-seizure
             medication for 6 months prior to first dose of study drug. Screening with CNS imaging
             studies (computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is required only
             if clinically indicated or if the subject has a history of CNS metastases.

          -  Clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may increase the risk for
             gastrointestinal bleeding

          -  Clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may affect absorption of
             investigational product including, but not limited to: Malabsorption syndrome, major
             resection of the stomach or small bowel.

          -  Presence of uncontrolled infection (&gt; grade 2 NCI-CTCAE Version 4.03).

          -  Corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 480 msecs using Bazett's formula

          -  History of any one or more of the following cardiovascular conditions within the past
             6 months:

               -  Myocardial infarction

               -  Cardiac angioplasty or stenting

               -  Unstable angina

               -  Coronary artery bypass graft surgery

               -  Symptomatic peripheral vascular disease

               -  Class III or IV congestive heart failure, as defined by the New York Heart
                  Association (NYHA)

          -  Poorly controlled hypertension

          -  History of cerebrovascular accident including transient ischemic attack (TIA),
             pulmonary embolism or untreated deep venous thrombosis (DVT) within the past 6 months.
             Note: Subjects with recent DVT who have been treated with therapeutic anti-coagulating
             agents for at least 6 weeks are eligible

          -  Prior major surgery or trauma within 28 days prior to first dose of study drug and/or
             presence of any non-healing wound, fracture, or ulcer.

          -  Evidence of active bleeding or bleeding diathesis.

          -  Known endobronchial lesions or lesions infiltrating major pulmonary vessels

          -  Hemoptysis in excess of 2.5 ml (or one half teaspoon ) within 8 weeks prior to first
             dose of study drug

          -  Any serious or unstable pre-existing medical, mental, or other condition, medical,
             social or mental impairment or drug abuse that could comprise or interfere with the
             subject's safety, provision of informed consent, or compliance to study procedures.

          -  Unable or unwilling to discontinue use of prohibited medications for at least 14 days
             or five half-lives of a drug (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of study
             drug and for the duration of the study.

          -  Simultaneous participation in another clinical drug study

          -  Known infection with Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) or chronic hepatitis B or C

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding women. Female subjects of childbearing potential need to be
             negatively tested prior and as close to the start of therapy as possible, at least
             within 14 days. Women participating in this trial are required to use adequate
             contraception. Female subjects who are lactating should discontinue nursing prior to
             the first dose of study drug and should refrain from nursing throughout the treatment
             period and for 14 days following the last dose of study drug

          -  Subjects who are unable to take oral medication

          -  Known hypersensitive reaction to any of the components of study treatments
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Staehler, PD MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München, Klinikum Grosshadern</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Urolog. Klinik im Waldkrankenhaus St. Marien, Friedrich-Alexander-Universität</name>
      <address>
        <city>Erlangen</city>
        <zip>91054</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Essen, Klinik f. Urologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <zip>45122</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Med. Klinik II, Johann-Wolfgang-Goethe-Universität</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt</city>
        <zip>60590</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinisches Versorgungszentrum (MVZ) Osthessen GmbH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fulda</city>
        <zip>36043</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsmedizin Greifswald</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greifswald</city>
        <zip>17475</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Hochschule Hannover</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hannover</city>
        <zip>30625</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität (LMU) München, Klinikum Grosshadern</name>
      <address>
        <city>München</city>
        <zip>81377</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Münster</name>
      <address>
        <city>Münster</city>
        <zip>48149</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 21, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

