<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01527877</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2011-0828-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01527877</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of BKM120 in Advanced Squamous Cell Carcinoma of Head and Neck</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label, Single Arm, Multicenter Phase II Study of BKM120 in Patients With Recurrent or Metastatic Squamous Cell Carcinoma of Head and Neck Who Failed to Respond to Platinum-based Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yonsei University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yonsei University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to evaluate disease control rate (DCR) at 8 weeks of BKM120 administered as
      therapy for patient with recurrent/metastatic head and neck squamous cell carcinoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      One promising approach to the treatment of cancer is inhibition or modulating the crucial
      signal transduction pathway of PI3K-Akt-mTOR. Several PI3K inhibitors are being tested in the
      clinical trials for cancer treatment but not for the head and neck cancer yet. BKM120 is a
      specific Pan-class I PI3K inhibitor. We suggest multicenter single arm phase II study to
      determine anti-tumor effects of BKM120 in patients with recurrent and/or metastatic SCCHN who
      failed to prior platinum-based chemotherapy regimens.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Eight weeks after administration of the drug</time_frame>
    <description>The disease control rate (DCR) is defined as the proportion of randomized patients achieving a best overall response of PR or CR or SD, defined by RECIST criteria (version 1.1), relative to the total number of patients in the considered analysis population (ITT).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 8 weeks from date of first treatment until date of last treatment up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall objective response rate (ORR) is the best response rate stipulated as complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) (target lesion and tumor response defined according to RECIST guideline version 1.1) and identified as percentage of the confirmed patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity profile</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 4 weeks from date of first treatment until date of last treatment up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>From C1D1 to 1 months after the last dose adminitration
Overall safety profile verified as relevance of adverse events and laboratory abnormality in the study and grades granted based on (USA National Cancer Center) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events such as the type, frequency and severity (CTCAE), v4.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 8 weeks from date of first treatment until the date of death from any cause, assessed approximately up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>From C1D1 to death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 8 weeks from date of first treatment until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed approximately up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>From C1D1 until confirmed disease progression or death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 4 weeks from date of first treatment until the date of death from any cause, assessed approximately up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life assessment will be performed using FACT-HN&amp; questionnaire
FACT-H&amp;N questionnaire includes physical well-being (PWB), social/family well-being (SWB), emotional well-being (EWB), functional well-being (FWB), and head &amp; neck cancer subscale (HNCS).
Patients will be evaluation on baseline, day 1 of every cycle (4 weeks), and end of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 8 weeks from date of first treatment until the date of first documented progression, assessed approximately up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>From C1D1 until confirmed disease progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Head Neck Cancer Squamous Cell Metastatic</condition>
  <condition>Head Neck Cancer Squamous Cell Recurrent</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BKM120</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BKM120</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be instructed to take BKM120 orally at a dose of 100 mg with a glass of water once daily, in a fasting state or with a light fat-free meal, and as close as possible to the same time each day. The patient will be dosed on a flat scale of mg/day and not be adjusted to body weight or body surface area. If vomiting occurs no attempt should be made to replace the dose.
• BKM120 should be taken 1-hour following a light meal. Please note that patients must avoid consumption of Seville orange (and juice), grapefruit or grapefruit juice, grapefruit hybrids, pummelos and exotic citrus fruits from 7 days prior to the first dose of study drug and during the entire study treatment period due to potential CYP3A4 interaction. Regular orange juice is allowed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BKM120</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NVP-BKM120</other_name>
    <other_name>BKM-120</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed recurrent or metastatic squamous-cell
             carcinoma of head and neck (SCCHN), except nasopharyngeal carcinoma

          -  Disease not amenable to curative treatment (surgery or radiation for curative intent)

          -  20 years of age or older

          -  Progressive disease defined as follows

               -  after one or two prior chemotherapy regimens including platinum-based
                  chemotherapy given for palliation

               -  within 6 months after concurrent chemoradiotherapy (including induction
                  chemotherapy) delivered as part of primary treatment.

          -  Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks

          -  At least one measurable lesion according to the RECIST 1.1 criteria.

          -  ECOG performance score of 0 ~ 2

          -  Adequate organ function

               -  Absolutely Neutrophil Count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 109/L, Platelets ≥ 100 x 109/L,
                  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL

               -  Serum Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               -  Adequate liver function (total bilirubin ≤ 2.0 x ULN, AST and ALT ≤ 2.0 x ULN or
                  &lt; 5.0 x ULN if liver metastases are present)

          -  Availability of tissue samples (archival tissue or rebiopsied tissues) for molecular
             analysis (representative paraffin block or unstained sections from tumor diagnostic
             specimen are mandatory)

          -  Patients who have will and ability to comply with the scheduled visits, the treatment
             plan, laboratory tests and any other trial procedures

          -  Patient's informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Nasopharyngeal carcinoma

          -  More than two prior lines of chemotherapy in the palliative setting.

          -  Uncontrolled, untreated brain metastasis Patients with controlled and asymptomatic CNS
             metastases may participate in this trial. The patient must have completed any prior
             treatment for CNS metastases ≥ 28 days (must include radiotherapy and/or surgery) and,
             if on corticosteroid therapy, should be receiving a stable low dose (e.g.
             dexamethasone 4 mg or equivalent dose of another corticosteroid for at least 14 days
             before start of study treatment)

          -  Surgery, chemotherapy or irradiation within 4 weeks of study entry

          -  Prior treatment with any investigational drug within the preceding 4 weeks

          -  Concomitant chemotherapy, hormonal therapy or immunotherapy

          -  Previous or concomitant malignant disease, except adequately treated basal cell cancer
             of the skin or cervical cancer in situ, superficial bladder tumors (Ta, Tis &amp; T1) or
             any cancer curatively treated &gt; 5 years prior study entry

          -  Patient who cannot take the oral drug

          -  Patient is pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the
             state of a female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed
             by a positive hCG laboratory test (&gt; 5 mIU/mL).

          -  Clinically significant psychological disorders including mood and anxiety disorders
             judged by psychiatry physician

          -  Patient who have not recovered to grade 1 or better from any adverse events (except
             alopecia) related to previous antineoplastic therapy before screening procedures are
             initiated

          -  Severe acute or chronic medical condition or laboratory abnormality that may increase
             the risk associated with trial participation or investigational product administration
             or may interfere with the interpretation of trial results and, in the judgment of the
             investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into this trial.

               -  Patient has poorly controlled diabetes mellitus (HbA1c&gt; 8 %)

               -  Patient has history of cardiac dysfunction including history of documented
                  congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association functional classification
                  III-IV) and documented cardiomyopathy

               -  Patient is currently receiving treatment with medication that has a known risk to
                  prolong the QT interval or inducing Torsades de Pointes. * Active infection,
                  inflammatory bowel disease

               -  Inadequate liver function (total bilirubin ≥ 2.0 x ULN, AST and ALT ≥ 2.0 x ULN
                  or ≥ 5.0 x ULN if liver metastases are present)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Byoung Chul Cho, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yonsei University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Byoung Chul Cho, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>82-2-2228-8126</phone>
    <email>cbc1971@yuhs.ac</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Severance Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Byoung Chul Cho, MD</last_name>
      <phone>82-2-2228-8126</phone>
      <email>cbc1971@yuhs.ac</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Byoung Chul Cho, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 26, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 6, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 7, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 4, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 4, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 8, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Yonsei University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Byoung Chul Cho</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>BKM120</keyword>
  <keyword>head and neck cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>squamous cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

