<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01521741</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>08-540</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA139118</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01521741</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Analysis of Symptoms and Lymphedema in Patients Following Treatment for Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Analysis of Symptoms, Functionality and Quality of Life Questionnaires to Evaluate Lymphedema in Patients Following Treatment for Breast Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to determine the level of symptoms, functional disability, and
      changes in quality of life that breast cancer patients experience from changes in their
      arm(s) during and after treatment for breast cancer. These problems are often associated with
      transient or chronic lymphedema, numbness, reduced shoulder flexibility, and an altered
      ability to use the arm for functional activities of daily living. The goal of this study is
      to collect data to support the hypothesis that swelling and other impairments in the upper
      extremities, causes a significant level of symptoms, functional disability and diminished
      quality of life for patients. Furthermore the investigators hope to evaluate how symptoms in
      the upper extremity (such as decreased functionality, sensory changes, pain or stiffness) are
      related to early, low volume lymphedema.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The method that we propose for this trial is to administer a condensed form of the Lymphedema
      and Breast Cancer Questionnaire (LBCQ) , Disabilities of the Arm Shoulder and Hand (DASH) and
      Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy- Breast quality of life instrument (FACT-B) as
      surveys/questionnaires within the clinic. This combined questionnaire is called the
      lymphedema evaluation following treatment for breast cancer (LEFT-BC). All patients who
      present for a baseline (pre-operative) arm measurement will be offered the opportunity to
      participate in this trial. At that point the purpose of the trial will be explained. Any
      patient that wishes to participate will be provided the questionnaires to complete and return
      (by mail or in person) to the study coordinator prior to surgery. During follow-up visits,
      questionnaires will be collected prior to perometer measurements and will be analyzed in
      conjunction with the measurements taken on the same day. We will utilize the questionnaires
      to evaluate their symptoms, functionality and quality of life (QOL). The perometer is a
      well-validated instrument and considered the gold standard today for quantifying volume in a
      limb. It is accurate to within a percent and far more accurate than circumferential
      measurement using a tape measure. It has been a regular part of the standard of care for MGH
      breast cancer patients. Patients are routinely measured at diagnosis, after surgery, after
      chemotherapy, after radiation, at four to six-month follow-up visits that continue for years,
      and anytime a patient reports with new symptoms of swelling or arm discomfort outside of
      these time frames.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Upper extremity changes following treatment for breast cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>During and following treatment for breast cancer patients' experience a variety of changes in their upper extremities. The subject responses to the LEFT-BC questionnaire obtained at the mandated study points will be analyzed in conjunction with a arm volume measurement. This will allow for the correlation between quantifiable limb volume changes and subject documented changes in arm use and functionality and quality of life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2500</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphedema</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Breast Cancer</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Newly diagnosed breast cancer patients.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of breast cancer

          -  No metastatic disease in the cervical or thoracic regions

          -  No bulky disease in the thoracic or cervical region

          -  No history of primary Lymphedema

          -  No prior surgery to the head, neck, upper limb or trunk

          -  No prior radiation to the head, neck, upper limb or trunk

          -  No evidence of axillary lymph node malignancy causing Lymphedema due to recurrence

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  metastatic or other locally advanced disease in the cervical or thoracic regions

          -  known brain metastases

          -  history of primary Lymphedema

          -  history of prior surgery or radiation to the head, neck, upper limb or trunk

          -  axillary lymph node malignancy causing Lymphedema (per physician discretion)

          -  current case of cellulitis

          -  history of a different malignancy except for the following: History of other
             malignancies if they are disease-free for 5+ years and deemed by the PI to be at low
             risk for recurrence OR &lt;5 years of diagnosis and treatment for cervical cancer in
             situ, basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin.

          -  Will not be returning routinely for follow-up at MGH or DFHCC
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alphonse G Taghian, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02134</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alphonse G Taghian, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>617-726-6050</phone>
      <email>ataghian@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alphonse G Taghian, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ancukiewicz M, Miller CL, Skolny MN, O'Toole J, Warren LE, Jammallo LS, Specht MC, Taghian AG. Comparison of relative versus absolute arm size change as criteria for quantifying breast cancer-related lymphedema: the flaws in current studies and need for universal methodology. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2012 Aug;135(1):145-52. doi: 10.1007/s10549-012-2111-8. Epub 2012 Jun 19. Erratum in: Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2012 Nov;136(2):623.</citation>
    <PMID>22710706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ancukiewicz M, Russell TA, Otoole J, Specht M, Singer M, Kelada A, Murphy CD, Pogachar J, Gioioso V, Patel M, Skolny M, Smith BL, Taghian AG. Standardized method for quantification of developing lymphedema in patients treated for breast cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2011 Apr 1;79(5):1436-43. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2010.01.001. Epub 2010 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20605339</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 6, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alphonse Taghian, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief of Breast Service</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphedema</keyword>
  <keyword>symptoms</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphedema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

