<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01523002</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SP-C-014-11</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01523002</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Drug Interaction Study of Pyronaridine-artesunate and Metoprolol and Pyronaridine-artesunate Re-dosing Study in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open-label, Drug Interaction Study of Pyramax (Pyronaridine:Artesunate) and Metoprolol in Healthy Volunteers and Pyramax Re-dosing Study in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medicines for Malaria Venture</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shin Poong Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medicines for Malaria Venture</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pyronaridine: artesunate (Pyramax) is an antimalarial fixed-dose combination therapy which
      has been demonstrated to be well tolerated and effective treatment in patients with
      Plasmodium falciparum and vivax malaria.

      This open-label Phase I study has two parts: a drug-drug interaction part intended to
      investigate the interaction of Pyramax in the pharmacokinetics of the CYP2D6 probe metoprolol
      and a re-dosing evaluation part intended to investigate the differences on the changes in
      liver enzymes induced by Pyramax in a first and in a second treatment course and the effect
      of the redosing interval on the changes in liver enzymes induced by Pyramax in a first and in
      a second treatment course.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Healthy subjects will be randomised to either arm A (sequential metoprolol single dose and
      Pyramax 3 days course + metoprolol on the last day starting 7 days after Pyramax single dose
      followed by Pyramax redosing with another 3 days course 90 days later) or arm B (2 courses of
      3-days Pyramax separated by 60 days). Each arm will include 22 subjects.

      Subjects will be followed for tolerability and pharmacokinetics for 42 days following each
      start of Pyramax dosing period.

      Subjects will be considered to have completed the study at Day 140 (arm A) or at Day 103 (arm
      B).

      Any adverse event ongoing at the time of study completion will be followed until resolution
      unless no further change is expected according to the investigator.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Profile of Pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>140 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area Under Curve (AUC)0-t, AUC0-∞, Cmax, Tmax, and halflife.
Plasma samples for determination of metoprolol and alphahydroxymetoprolol: pre-dose and 0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4,6, 8, 10, 12, and 24 h post-dose.
Plasma samples for determination of artesunate and dihydroartemisinin: pre-dose and 1, 3, and 6 h post-dose.
Blood samples for determination of pyronaridine:pre-dose and 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 12, and 24 h and 2, 3, 5, 12, 19, 26, 33, and 40 days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of re-treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>140 days</time_frame>
    <description>Pyramax Re-dosing sub-study (Arm A and Arm B):Peak ALT and peak AST values following the first and the second three day Pyramax administration.
Safety assessments include monitoring of:
Adverse events, Laboratory parameters, Vital signs, clinical signs and symptoms and physical examination, including changes from baseline, ECG evaluation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Metoprolol DDI and Pyramax 90-day re-dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will take 1 day of metoprolol followed by a 7 day wash out period; then 2 days of Pyramax followed by 1 day of Pyramax + metoprolol and then a 87 day follow-up period. Subjects will then receive Pyramax once daily for three days followed by a 40 day follow-up period and a study completion evaluation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Pyramax 60-day re-dosing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will take Pyramax once daily for 3 days, followed by a 57 day follow-up period. Subjects will then take Pyramax once daily for 3 days followed by a 40 day follow-up period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metoprolol and Pyronaridine : artesunate</intervention_name>
    <description>On Day 1, subjects will receive a single oral 100 mg dose of metoprolol tartrate. On Day 8 and Day 9, subjects will receive a once daily oral dose of Pyramax as follows:
55 - &lt; 65 kg: 3 tablets (180:60 mg pyronaridine:artesunate)
≥ 65 kg: 4 tablets (180:60 mg pyronaridine:artesunate)
On Day 10, a 100 mg dose of metoprolol will be coadministered with Pyramax at the above dose.
On Days 98 - 100, subjects will receive Pyramax once daily at the same dose described above.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Metoprolol DDI and Pyramax 90-day re-dosing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pyronaridine:artesunate</intervention_name>
    <description>In the first period, subjects will receive 3 days of Pyramax as follows:
55 - &lt; 65 kg: 3 tablets (180:60 mg pyronaridine:artesunate)
≥ 65 kg: 4 tablets (180:60 mg pyronaridine:artesunate) followed by a 57 day follow-up period. In the second period, subjects will receive 3 days of Pyramax at the dose described above.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Pyramax 60-day re-dosing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female subjects between the ages of 18 and 55 years with a body weight between
             50 and 90 kg and a body mass index calculated using Quetelet's Index - weight
             (kg)/height2 (m2) between 18.5-30.0

          2. Signed and dated a written informed consent form before undergoing any study related
             activities

          3. Medically normal subjects with no significant abnormal findings at the screening
             physical examination as evaluated by the investigator

          4. Strictly normal values of ALT, AST, and total bilirubin and normal or abnormal and
             clinically insignificant results of the other blood and urine laboratory parameters at
             screening.

          5. Female subjects of non-childbearing potential (i.e., physiologically incapable of
             becoming pregnant, including any female who was post-menopausal (i.e., one year
             without menses) or who has undergone sterilization (via hysterectomy or bilateral
             tubal ligation)

          6. Female subjects of childbearing potential with a negative urine pregnancy test at
             screening confirmed at Day -1 by a serum pregnancy test and who agreed to one of the
             following methods:

               -  Double barrier method of contraception for 2 weeks before first study drug
                  administration and throughout the entire study follow up period

               -  Partner(s) who had undergone vasectomy and has been negative for sperm for at
                  least 6 months

          7. The ability to understand the requirements of the study and willingness to comply with
             all study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known history or evidence of clinically significant disorders such as cardiovascular
             (including arrhythmia, acute QTc interval greater or equal to 450 mseconds),
             respiratory (including active tuberculosis), hepatic, renal, gastrointestinal,
             immunological (including active HIV-AIDS), neurological (including auditory),
             endocrine, infectious, malignancy, psychiatric or other abnormality (including head
             trauma)

          2. Known history of hypersensitivity, allergic or adverse reactions to pyronaridine or
             artesunate or other artemisinins or metoprolol.

          3. Other contraindications to pyronaridine use

          4. Other contraindications to metoprolol use including second or third degree
             atrioventricular block, heart rate below 50 beats per minute, uncompensated heart
             failure or need for treatment with inotropic agents, clinically apparent hypotension,
             sinus bradycardia or sick sinus syndrome, peripheral arterial disease,
             pheochromocytoma, asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, depression and any
             other condition with in the opinion of the Investigator may be worsened by
             administration of metoprolol.

          5. Known active Hepatitis A IgM (HAV-IgM), Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) or
             Hepatitis C antibody (HCV Ab)

          6. Seropositive HIV antibody

          7. Previous participation in any clinical study with pyronaridine:artesunate (Pyramax)

          8. Presence or recent history (last two years) of tobacco abuse (≥10 cigarettes/day)

          9. Known or suspected alcohol abuse or illicit drug use 10 years before the study start
             or positive findings on urine drug screen

         10. Intake of alcoholic beverages within 72 hours before study drug administration or
             caffeine-containing food or beverages, such as coffee, tea, chocolate, or cola, 48
             hours before study drug administration

         11. Gilbert's disease

         12. Administration of any systemic medication or herbal product within 14 days before the
             first dose of study drug. If the investigator considers that the specific product
             would not interfere with the safety of the subject or the objectives of the study,
             topical treatments as well as vitamins and mineral supplements not containing other
             substances are allowed until 4 days before each dose. Ibuprofen at doses of at most
             1200 mg per day for no more than 3 consecutive days or 6 non-consecutive days is
             allowed until 24h before the first dose of study drug.

         13. Plasma donation 3 months before the study start

         14. Blood donation of 500 mL or more 3 months before the study start

         15. Participation in any clinical study in last 3 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rolf Pokorny, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Covance Research Unit AG</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Covance Clinical Research Unit AG</name>
      <address>
        <city>Allschwil</city>
        <state>Basel</state>
        <zip>4123</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 27, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 31, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 1, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metoprolol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artesunate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemisinins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pyronaridine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

