<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01529060</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-28463</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01529060</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phenylbutyrate Therapy for Maple Syrup Urine Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>MSUD</acronym>
  <official_title>A Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Trial of Phenylbutyrate in the Treatment of Maple Syrup Urine Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brendan Lee</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators have learned in past research that the drug phenylbutyrate can decrease the
      amounts of branched chain amino acids and their byproducts in the bloodstreams of healthy
      volunteer patients and also patients with certain disorders of protein breakdown including
      maple syrup urine disease. Through this study, the investigators will try to find out how
      well phenylbutyrate (NaPBA), also known by name brand &quot;Buphenyl-TM&quot;, decreases BCAA and
      branched chain keto chain acids in the blood of patients with MSUD. The investigators hope is
      that through this research the investigators will be better able to treat these patients.

      Subjects with MSUD will take phenylbutyrate (NaPBA) in powder form for a two-week treatment
      period and powder placebo, a substance with no effect on the body, for a two-week treatment
      period. They will be given the same amount of powder and undergo the same laboratory testing
      during both of the two-week treatment periods. The results will be compared once the study is
      over.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Maple syrup urine disease is a severe inborn error of amino acid metabolism caused by
      deficiency of the mitochondrial branched-chain alpha-ketoacid dehydrogenase complex (BCKDC)
      resulting in the accumulation of branched-chain amino acids (BCAA) (isoleucine, leucine, and
      valine) and their corresponding branched-chain alpha-ketoacids (BCKA)
      [alpha-keto-beta-methylvalerate (KMV), alpha-ketoisocaproate (KIC), and
      alpha-ketoisovalerate(KIV)] in tissues and plasma. The disorder typically manifests with
      potentially lethal episodes of intoxication presenting with acute neurological deterioration,
      feeding problems, weight loss, and a maple syrup odor to the urine. Current treatment is
      based on dietary manipulations with protein restriction and a synthetic formula with reduced
      BCAA content. However, mental and social impairment are still present in the majority of
      these patients in spite of dietary management.

      Our study seeks to investigate the potential small molecule inhibition of the kinase that
      regulates BCKDC by applying a novel activity of sodium phenylbutyrate (NaPBA), in MSUD.
      Sodium phenylbutyrate is has been used to treat patients with urea cycle disorders (UCDs). In
      our extensive studies with UCDs, we noted that patients on therapy with NaPBA had decreased
      plasma levels of BCAA. This led us to hypothesize that NaPBA has effects on BCAA metabolism.

      This will be a single-site, randomized, active-controlled, double-blind, cross-over study
      designed to enroll subjects with MSUD. Subjects will be randomly assigned to receive either
      sodium phenylbutyrate (PB) or placebo for 2 weeks, and then crossed over to receive the other
      treatment for 2 weeks.

      If study findings show sodium phenylbutyrate lowers BCAA and BCKA levels in these patients,
      it may prove to be an effective adjunct treatment for these patients. A treatment option that
      could prevent or decrease the accumulation of BCAA and BCKA during states of catabolism
      induced by fasting or intercurrent illnesses, and thereby minimize or prevent the neurologic
      sequelae and loss of human potential that result, would greatly benefit society.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax and Area Under the Curve (AUC)for BCAA and BCKA</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 2hrs, 4hrs, 8hrs, 12hrs, 16hrs, 20hrs and 24hrs post-dose</time_frame>
    <description>On the last study day of each intervention period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Maple Syrup Urine Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phenylbutyrate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study Drug</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inactive Powder</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo powder</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phenylbutyrate</intervention_name>
    <description>Dosage of phenylbutyrate powder will be 500 mg/kg/day in patients weighing less than 20kg and 10 g/m2/day in larger patients in four divided doses per day, the standard UCD dose studied in our preliminary studies, for 14 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phenylbutyrate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Buphenyl-TM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo powder</intervention_name>
    <description>Dosage of inactive placebo powder will be 500 mg/kg/day in patients weighing less than 20kg and 10 g/m2/day in larger patients in four divided doses per day for 14 days. Subjects will receive the same amount of powder for each arm of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inactive Powder</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be 3 years or older at enrollment.

          -  Must have a diagnosis of maple syrup urine disease (MSUD) confirmed by the presence of
             plasma alloisoleucine (&gt;5 micromol/L) and/or genetic testing showing mutations in both
             alleles of any subunit of BCKDHA (E1alpha subunit gene, MSUD type 1A), BCKDHB (E1beta
             subunit gene, MSUD type 1B), or DBT (E2 subunit gene, MSUD type 2).

          -  Participants must have a history of compliance to diet and treatment.

          -  Signed informed consent by subject and/or subject's legally acceptable representative.

          -  Must be capable of completing study procedures, including taking oral or G- tube
             medication.

          -  Negative pregnancy test for all females of childbearing potential.

          -  All females of childbearing potential and all sexually active males must agree to use
             an acceptable method of contraception throughout the study. Appropriate contraceptive
             methods include hormonal contraceptives (oral, injected, implanted, or transdermal),
             tubal ligation, intrauterine device, hysterectomy, vasectomy, or double barrier
             methods. Abstinence is an acceptable form of birth control, though appropriate
             contraception must be used if the subject becomes sexually active.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  May not have used sodium phenylbutyrate within 30 days of Visit 1.

          -  May not have an active infection (viral or bacterial) or any condition which may
             exacerbate their MSUD causing metabolic decompensation.

          -  Cannot have any clinical or laboratory abnormality of Grade 3 or greater according to
             the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v3.0 (CTCAE) (or for conditions not
             covered by the CTCAE, a severe or life-threatening toxicity).

          -  May not have taken any medications known to significantly affect renal clearance or to
             increase protein catabolism within the 24 hours prior to Visit 1.

          -  May not participate if they have a known hypersensitivity to phenylacetate or
             phenylbutyrate or creatinine levels 1.5 times or more ULN.

          -  Since a total of 53 mL will be drawn over Days 14 and 15 of both treatment periods,
             only subjects weighing more than 30 pounds can be enrolled.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brendan Lee, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bcm.edu/genetics/</url>
    <description>Dr. Lee's BCM Department of Molecular and Human Genetics Faculty Page</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bcm.edu/</url>
    <description>Baylor College of Medicine Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 8, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 1, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brendan Lee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Molecular and Human Genetics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>phenylbutyrate</keyword>
  <keyword>MSUD</keyword>
  <keyword>Buphenyl-TM</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Maple Syrup Urine Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>4-phenylbutyric acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>September 18, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>October 16, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>January 26, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>February 23, 2018</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

