<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03355469</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19364</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01HL130296-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03355469</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exercise Dose and Metformin for Vascular Health in Adults With Metabolic Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exercise Dose and Metformin for Vascular Health in Adults With Metabolic Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Virginia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Virginia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Health organizations recommend exercise in an intensity based manner to promote
      cardiovascular adaptation and prevent disease. Metformin is a common anti-diabetes medication
      that reduces future type 2 diabetes and cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk. However, the
      optimal dose of exercise to be combined with metformin for vascular health remains unknown.
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate whether combining high or low intensity exercise
      with metformin has the potential to outperform either exercise intensity alone on blood flow
      across the arterial tree as well as impact insulin action in individuals with metabolic
      syndrome. Identification of such outcomes will indicate 1) whether and how metformin should
      be combined with physical activity for CVD prevention, 2) provide the first indication of
      whether exercise intensity reduces CVD risk via multi-level vasculature function vs.
      metabolic insulin action, and 3) provide a rational early treatment for people with metabolic
      syndrome to prevent/treat type 2 diabetes and CVD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 7, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Each subject will be randomly assigned to receive low intensity exercise training + placebo, high intensity exercise training + placebo, or these exercise programs with metformin.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Flow Mediated Dilation of brachial artery</measure>
    <time_frame>At 0 and 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of blood flow</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Metabolic Insulin Sensitivity by the Euglycemic Clamp</measure>
    <time_frame>At 0 and 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of glucose metabolism</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Post Ischemic Flow Velocity in brachial artery</measure>
    <time_frame>At 0 and 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of blood flow</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Contrast Enhanced Ultrasound</measure>
    <time_frame>At 0 and 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of Microvascular blood flow</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pulse Wave Velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>At 0 and 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of Arterial Stiffness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Augmentation Index</measure>
    <time_frame>At 0 and 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of Arterial Stiffness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Ambulatory Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>At 0 and 16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of Vascular health</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Metabolic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LoEx+placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will participate in 3 supervised training sessions and 2 unsupervised training sessions and receive placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HiEx+placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will participate in 3 supervised training sessions and 2 unsupervised training sessions and receive placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LoEx+metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>If subjects are assigned to this group they will participate in the same LoEx exercise program as outlined above. But, here they will be provided metformin. Metformin is a common medication routinely used to treat high blood sugar and has secondary effects on vascular health. Subjects will not be able to find out if you are on metformin until the study is done. If their doctor needs to know, the people doing this study can find out.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HiEx+metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>If subjects are assigned to this group you will participate in the same HiEx exercise program and receive metformin as outlined above.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LoEx+Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>Low Intensity exercise (LoEx) measured by a percentage of maximal heart rate in combination with metformin.</description>
    <arm_group_label>LoEx+metformin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HiEx+Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>High Intensity exercise (HiEx) measured by a percentage of maximal heart rate in combination with metformin.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HiEx+metformin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LoEx+Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Low Intensity exercise (LoEx) measured by a percentage of maximal heart rate in combination with placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>LoEx+placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HiEx+Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>High Intensity exercise (HiEx) measured by a percentage of maximal heart rate in combination with placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HiEx+placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female &gt;40 and &lt;70 years old.

          -  Have a body mass index &gt;30 and &lt;45 kg/m2.

          -  Not diagnosed with Type 2 diabetes.

          -  Not currently engaged in &gt; 60 min/wk of exercise

          -  Meet at least 3 of 5 National Cholesterol Education Adult Treatment Panel III

        Metabolic Syndrome criteria:

          1. Increased waist circumference (≥102 cm in men; ≥88 cm in women)

          2. Elevated triglycerides (≥150 mg/dl)

          3. Reduced HDL-cholesterol (&lt;40mg/dl in men, &lt;50 mg/dl in women)

          4. High blood pressure (≥130 mmHg systolic or ≥85mmHg diastolic)

          5. Elevated fasting glucose (≥100 mg/dl)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Morbidly obese patients (BMI &gt;45 kg/m2) and overweight/lean patients (BMI &lt;30 kg/m2)

          -  Evidence of type 1 diabetes and diabetics requiring insulin therapy.

          -  Subjects who have not been weight stable (&gt;2 kg weight change in past 6 months)

          -  Subjects who have been recently active (&gt;30 min of moderate/high intensity exercise, 2
             times/week).

          -  Subjects who are smokers or who have quit smoking &lt;5 years ago

          -  Subjects prescribed metformin or have taken metformin within 1 year.

          -  Subjects with abnormal estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR).

          -  Hypertriglyceridemic (&gt;400 mg/dl) and hypercholesterolemic (&gt;260 mg/dl) subjects

          -  Hypertensive (&gt;160/100 mmHg)

          -  Subjects taking vasoactive medications (i.e. Ca++ channel blockers, ACEI, ARB,
             nitrates, alpha- or beta-blockers).

          -  Subjects with a history of significant metabolic, cardiac, congestive heart failure,
             cerebrovascular, hematological, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, liver, renal, or
             endocrine disease or cancer that in the investigator's opinion would interfere with or
             alter the outcome measures, or impact subject safety.

          -  Pregnant (as evidenced by positive pregnancy test) or nursing women

          -  Subjects with contraindications to participation in an exercise training program

          -  Known hypersensitivity to perflutren (contained in Definity)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven K Malin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Virginia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Applied Metabolism and Physiology Lab</last_name>
    <phone>434-243-8677</phone>
    <email>slm4ps@virginia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22904</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephanie Miller, M.S.Ed.</last_name>
      <phone>434-243-8677</phone>
      <email>slm4ps@virginia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emily Heiston, M.S.Ed</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Monique Francois, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven K Malin, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laurent S, Katsahian S, Fassot C, Tropeano AI, Gautier I, Laloux B, Boutouyrie P. Aortic stiffness is an independent predictor of fatal stroke in essential hypertension. Stroke. 2003 May;34(5):1203-6. Epub 2003 Apr 3.</citation>
    <PMID>12677025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grundy SM, Cleeman JI, Daniels SR, Donato KA, Eckel RH, Franklin BA, Gordon DJ, Krauss RM, Savage PJ, Smith SC Jr, Spertus JA, Fernando Costa. Diagnosis and management of the metabolic syndrome: an American Heart Association/National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute scientific statement: Executive Summary. Crit Pathw Cardiol. 2005 Dec;4(4):198-203.</citation>
    <PMID>18340209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeFronzo RA, Abdul-Ghani M. Assessment and treatment of cardiovascular risk in prediabetes: impaired glucose tolerance and impaired fasting glucose. Am J Cardiol. 2011 Aug 2;108(3 Suppl):3B-24B. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.03.013. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21802577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bateman LA, Slentz CA, Willis LH, Shields AT, Piner LW, Bales CW, Houmard JA, Kraus WE. Comparison of aerobic versus resistance exercise training effects on metabolic syndrome (from the Studies of a Targeted Risk Reduction Intervention Through Defined Exercise - STRRIDE-AT/RT). Am J Cardiol. 2011 Sep 15;108(6):838-44. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.04.037. Epub 2011 Jul 7.</citation>
    <PMID>21741606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malin SK, Nightingale J, Choi SE, Chipkin SR, Braun B. Metformin modifies the exercise training effects on risk factors for cardiovascular disease in impaired glucose tolerant adults. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2013 Jan;21(1):93-100. doi: 10.1002/oby.20235.</citation>
    <PMID>23505172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malin SK, Niemi N, Solomon TP, Haus JM, Kelly KR, Filion J, Rocco M, Kashyap SR, Barkoukis H, Kirwan JP. Exercise training with weight loss and either a high- or low-glycemic index diet reduces metabolic syndrome severity in older adults. Ann Nutr Metab. 2012;61(2):135-41.</citation>
    <PMID>23036993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Potteiger JA, Claytor RP, Hulver MW, Hughes MR, Carper MJ, Richmond S, Thyfault JP. Resistance exercise and aerobic exercise when paired with dietary energy restriction both reduce the clinical components of metabolic syndrome in previously physically inactive males. Eur J Appl Physiol. 2012 Jun;112(6):2035-44. doi: 10.1007/s00421-011-2174-y. Epub 2011 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>21947428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mestek ML, Westby CM, Van Guilder GP, Greiner JJ, Stauffer BL, DeSouza CA. Regular aerobic exercise, without weight loss, improves endothelium-dependent vasodilation in overweight and obese adults. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2010 Aug;18(8):1667-9. doi: 10.1038/oby.2009.467. Epub 2010 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>20057377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips SA, Mahmoud AM, Brown MD, Haus JM. Exercise interventions and peripheral arterial function: implications for cardio-metabolic disease. Prog Cardiovasc Dis. 2015 Mar-Apr;57(5):521-34. doi: 10.1016/j.pcad.2014.12.005. Epub 2014 Dec 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25529367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tjønna AE, Lee SJ, Rognmo Ø, Stølen TO, Bye A, Haram PM, Loennechen JP, Al-Share QY, Skogvoll E, Slørdahl SA, Kemi OJ, Najjar SM, Wisløff U. Aerobic interval training versus continuous moderate exercise as a treatment for the metabolic syndrome: a pilot study. Circulation. 2008 Jul 22;118(4):346-54. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.108.772822. Epub 2008 Jul 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18606913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malin SK, Gerber R, Chipkin SR, Braun B. Independent and combined effects of exercise training and metformin on insulin sensitivity in individuals with prediabetes. Diabetes Care. 2012 Jan;35(1):131-6. doi: 10.2337/dc11-0925. Epub 2011 Oct 31.</citation>
    <PMID>22040838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gokce N, Keaney JF Jr, Hunter LM, Watkins MT, Nedeljkovic ZS, Menzoian JO, Vita JA. Predictive value of noninvasively determined endothelial dysfunction for long-term cardiovascular events in patients with peripheral vascular disease. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2003 May 21;41(10):1769-75.</citation>
    <PMID>12767663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vlachopoulos C, Aznaouridis K, Stefanadis C. Prediction of cardiovascular events and all-cause mortality with arterial stiffness: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2010 Mar 30;55(13):1318-27. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2009.10.061. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20338492</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eggleston EM, Jahn LA, Barrett EJ. Early microvascular recruitment modulates subsequent insulin-mediated skeletal muscle glucose metabolism during lipid infusion. Diabetes Care. 2013 Jan;36(1):104-10. doi: 10.2337/dc11-2399. Epub 2012 Sep 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22961574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu Z, Liu J, Jahn LA, Fowler DE, Barrett EJ. Infusing lipid raises plasma free fatty acids and induces insulin resistance in muscle microvasculature. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2009 Sep;94(9):3543-9. doi: 10.1210/jc.2009-0027. Epub 2009 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>19567533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vincent MA, Clerk LH, Lindner JR, Price WJ, Jahn LA, Leong-Poi H, Barrett EJ. Mixed meal and light exercise each recruit muscle capillaries in healthy humans. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2006 Jun;290(6):E1191-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16682488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barrett EJ, Wang H, Upchurch CT, Liu Z. Insulin regulates its own delivery to skeletal muscle by feed-forward actions on the vasculature. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2011 Aug;301(2):E252-63. doi: 10.1152/ajpendo.00186.2011. Epub 2011 May 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21610226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clerk LH, Vincent MA, Jahn LA, Liu Z, Lindner JR, Barrett EJ. Obesity blunts insulin-mediated microvascular recruitment in human forearm muscle. Diabetes. 2006 May;55(5):1436-42.</citation>
    <PMID>16644702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keske MA, Clerk LH, Price WJ, Jahn LA, Barrett EJ. Obesity blunts microvascular recruitment in human forearm muscle after a mixed meal. Diabetes Care. 2009 Sep;32(9):1672-7. doi: 10.2337/dc09-0206. Epub 2009 Jun 1.</citation>
    <PMID>19487636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu J, Jahn LA, Fowler DE, Barrett EJ, Cao W, Liu Z. Free fatty acids induce insulin resistance in both cardiac and skeletal muscle microvasculature in humans. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2011 Feb;96(2):438-46. doi: 10.1210/jc.2010-1174. Epub 2010 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21047922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson TJ, Charbonneau F, Title LM, Buithieu J, Rose MS, Conradson H, Hildebrand K, Fung M, Verma S, Lonn EM. Microvascular function predicts cardiovascular events in primary prevention: long-term results from the Firefighters and Their Endothelium (FATE) study. Circulation. 2011 Jan 18;123(2):163-9. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.953653. Epub 2011 Jan 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21200002</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cruickshank K, Riste L, Anderson SG, Wright JS, Dunn G, Gosling RG. Aortic pulse-wave velocity and its relationship to mortality in diabetes and glucose intolerance: an integrated index of vascular function? Circulation. 2002 Oct 15;106(16):2085-90.</citation>
    <PMID>12379578</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Donley DA, Fournier SB, Reger BL, DeVallance E, Bonner DE, Olfert IM, Frisbee JC, Chantler PD. Aerobic exercise training reduces arterial stiffness in metabolic syndrome. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2014 Jun 1;116(11):1396-404. doi: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00151.2014. Epub 2014 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>24744384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green DJ, Eijsvogels T, Bouts YM, Maiorana AJ, Naylor LH, Scholten RR, Spaanderman ME, Pugh CJ, Sprung VS, Schreuder T, Jones H, Cable T, Hopman MT, Thijssen DH. Exercise training and artery function in humans: nonresponse and its relationship to cardiovascular risk factors. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2014 Aug 15;117(4):345-52. doi: 10.1152/japplphysiol.00354.2014. Epub 2014 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24947027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swift DL, Weltman JY, Patrie JT, Saliba SA, Gaesser GA, Barrett EJ, Weltman A. Predictors of improvement in endothelial function after exercise training in a diverse sample of postmenopausal women. J Womens Health (Larchmt). 2014 Mar;23(3):260-6. doi: 10.1089/jwh.2013.4420. Epub 2013 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24299160</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mather KJ, Verma S, Anderson TJ. Improved endothelial function with metformin in type 2 diabetes mellitus. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2001 Apr;37(5):1344-50.</citation>
    <PMID>11300445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vitale C, Mercuro G, Cornoldi A, Fini M, Volterrani M, Rosano GM. Metformin improves endothelial function in patients with metabolic syndrome. J Intern Med. 2005 Sep;258(3):250-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16115299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patel C, Ghanim H, Ravishankar S, Sia CL, Viswanathan P, Mohanty P, Dandona P. Prolonged reactive oxygen species generation and nuclear factor-kappaB activation after a high-fat, high-carbohydrate meal in the obese. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2007 Nov;92(11):4476-9. Epub 2007 Sep 4.</citation>
    <PMID>17785362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malin SK, Braun B. Impact of Metformin on Exercise-Induced Metabolic Adaptations to Lower Type 2 Diabetes Risk. Exerc Sport Sci Rev. 2016 Jan;44(1):4-11. doi: 10.1249/JES.0000000000000070. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26583801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Selvin E, Bolen S, Yeh HC, Wiley C, Wilson LM, Marinopoulos SS, Feldman L, Vassy J, Wilson R, Bass EB, Brancati FL. Cardiovascular outcomes in trials of oral diabetes medications: a systematic review. Arch Intern Med. 2008 Oct 27;168(19):2070-80. doi: 10.1001/archinte.168.19.2070. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18955635</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Virginia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Steven K. Malin, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome X</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

