<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03358771</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00065003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03358771</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>COPD Discharge Bundle Delivered Alone or Enhanced Through a Care Coordinator</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRIHS</acronym>
  <official_title>Effectiveness and Cost-effectiveness of a COPD Discharge Bundle Delivered Alone or Enhanced Through a Care Coordinator</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Calgary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alberta Health Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alberta Innovates Health Solutions</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a common, chronic progressive lung disease
      that is characterized by shortness of breath, activity limitation, and a predisposition to
      flare-ups resulting in frequent emergency department (ED) visits and hospitalizations. COPD
      flare-ups increase risks of disease progression and mortality and account for the greatest
      proportion of preventable hospitalizations among major chronic diseases.

      Evidence show that timely integrated disease management can prevent future COPD flare-ups and
      readmissions, but recent data indicate that appropriate follow-up after a COPD
      hospitalization is limited. To reduce this care gap, the investigators developed a discharge
      care bundle to help a patient that are being discharged from hospital or ED after COPD
      flare-up transition to community care.

      The aim of this study is to assess how effective and cost-effective is such bundle delivered
      alone or supported by the dedicated care manager. The investigators will be assessing
      reduction of ED and hospital readmission.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction/Significance

      Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a common, chronic progressive lung disease
      that is characterized by shortness of breath, activity limitation, and a predisposition to
      acute exacerbations resulting in frequent emergency department (ED) visits and
      hospitalizations. COPD exacerbations account for the greatest proportion of preventable
      hospitalizations among major chronic diseases. In Alberta, a recent report from the COPD
      Working Group of the Respiratory Health Strategic Clinical Network (RHSCN) found that, with
      an average length of stay of 12.9 days, COPD hospitalizations result in an estimated total
      inpatient cost of $112 million annually. In addition to increasing the risk of disease
      progression and mortality, COPD exacerbations are a major risk factor for subsequent COPD
      exacerbations, resulting in additional ED visits and hospitalizations. Approximately 35% of
      COPD patients who are discharged from the ED have a subsequent revisit within 30 days of
      initial ED discharge. National data indicate that 18% of hospitalized COPD patients are
      readmitted within one year after the index hospitalization while 14% are admitted twice
      within the year. Analysis of Alberta Health Services (AHS) administrative data shows that the
      30-day hospital readmission rates for COPD in Alberta during 2012 (18.8%) and 2013 (19.5%)
      were well above the national 30-day readmission rate for all hospital admissions (8.4%).

      The Canadian Thoracic Society (CTS) has developed evidence-based management guidelines for
      optimizing COPD care and preventing exacerbations and has recommended that COPD patients
      should be seen by their primary care provider within 14 days following an exacerbation.
      Further, the Global Initiative for Obstructive Lung Disease has proposed a list of items to
      review with the patient at discharge and recommends follow-up at 4-6 weeks after discharge.
      Despite evidence from systematic reviews that timely integrated disease management can
      prevent future COPD exacerbations and readmissions, recent Alberta data indicate that
      appropriate follow-up after a COPD hospitalization is limited. An audit at the University of
      Alberta hospital found that only 43% of COPD patients received appropriate medication
      prescriptions at discharge; only 10% of eligible patients were referred to a rehabilitation
      program while only 58% of smokers received instructions on smoking cessation interventions.
      To overcome these care gaps in COPD, previously published work has supported the introduction
      of clinical bundles and case management for follow-up after discharge, suggesting promising
      results to reduce readmissions and minimize health care utilization costs. Clinical bundles
      support the translation of clinical guidelines into local protocols and their subsequent
      standardization and application to clinical practice, enhance integrated care, and optimize
      patient outcomes while maximizing clinical efficiency and containing costs.

      A recently completed systematic review of the scientific literature on the effectiveness of
      COPD discharge care bundles showed that COPD discharge care bundles reduced hospital
      readmission rates (Risk Ratio [RR]=0.8; 95% Confidence Interval [CI] [0.65, 0.99]); they did
      not, however, significantly reduce long-term mortality (RR=0.74; CI [0.43; 1.28]) nor
      improved quality of life after acute care discharge (Mean Difference=1.84; CI [-5.23, 5.80])

      COPD discharge care bundle

      In view of the promising results from systematic reviews that indicate that integrated care
      bundles can be effective for conditions with relatively predictable trajectories of care such
      as COPD, the investigators want to assess whether a COPD discharge bundle adapted to local ED
      and hospital settings is a relevant, feasible and cost-effective alternative within the
      Alberta health care system, and whether the addition of a care coordinator to the bundle
      further reduces ED and hospital readmissions while containing health care costs.

      To assure that the care bundle is relevant to the local practice and applicable in the
      Alberta health system, the research team developed a COPD discharge care bundle through an
      evidence-based consultation-driven process. During this process, the researchers consulted
      patients and expert clinicians from Alberta and Canada. The development of the bundle has
      been a part of 3-year PRIHS project titled &quot;Developing and assessing the effectiveness of a
      post-discharge care pathway to reduce emergency department revisits and hospital re-admission
      rates for patients with COPD&quot;. The process of bundle development involved several steps:

        -  Systematic review - to identify evidence-based components incorporated in COPD discharge
           care bundles in the scientific literature;

        -  2-step Delphi technique with field experts and patients to reach consensus on the
           evidence-based individual components of discharge care bundles;

        -  A face-to-face Consensus Meeting with practitioners and experts from Alberta and to
           finalize components of the bundle and identify practical issues for bundle
           implementation;

        -  Targeted focus groups with patients and health professionals who work within hospitals,
           emergency units and/or primary care settings to recognize barriers and facilitators for
           care bundle implementation.

      As a result, the investigators developed the COPD discharge care bundle that includes 7
      action items (see Table 2). The list constitutes a single intervention (COPD discharge care
      bundle). The bundle has subsequently been integrated into the new provincial AHS COPD Order
      Set by the AHS pathway development team. The current study will specifically examine the
      efficacy of this new discharge care bundle, and whether the addition of a case manager will
      improve care. Currently, the research team is conducting the needs and readiness assessments
      within the five hospitals that are part of the project to determine the best implementation
      strategies.

      Study objectives

      This study aims to assess the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of an evidence-based COPD
      discharge care bundle, delivered alone or facilitated by a dedicated care coordinator, to
      reduce ED and hospital readmissions, and improve patient-centered and economic outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ED revisits</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after discharge</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after discharge</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ED revisits</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ED revisits</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ED revisits</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital readmission</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital readmission</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital readmission</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first physician visit and total visits</measure>
    <time_frame>in the first 30 days after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first physician visit and total visits</measure>
    <time_frame>in the first 6 months after discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Experience - inpatient</measure>
    <time_frame>45-60 days after discharge</time_frame>
    <description>For a randomly selected sample of patients, Patient Experience Survey - Inpatient Care</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Experience - ED</measure>
    <time_frame>45-60 days after discharge</time_frame>
    <description>For a randomly selected sample of patients, Patient Experience Survey - Emergency Department</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Economic evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after termination of the trial (April 2020)</time_frame>
    <description>E.g. cost per readmission prevented; Cost of intervention; Cost of healthcare use (MD visits, ED visits, medication use, hospitalizations)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the initial stepped wedge phase, all sites will receive usual care. There is currently no standardized discharge care bundle for COPD in Alberta. Some electronic patient information sheets do exist; however, their content is general and use is limited. It is expected that a vast majority of patients will transition to the community on a sub-optimal medication regimen, with limited referral to additional outpatient programs and no formal follow-up organized with a primary care provider (e.g., &quot;F/U prn&quot; or &quot;F/U with Fam MD&quot;).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COPD discharge care bundle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>COPD discharge care bundle:
Ensure patient has demonstrated adequate inhaler technique
Send discharge summary to family physician office and arrange follow-up
Optimize and reconcile prescription of respiratory medications
Provide a written discharge management plan, and assess patient's and care giver's comprehension of discharge instructions
Refer to pulmonary rehabilitation
Screen for frailty and comorbid condition(s)
Assess smoking status, provide counseling and refer to smoking cessation program, where appropriate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COPD discharge care bundle &amp; coordinator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>COPD discharge care bundle as listed for active comparator arm enhanced with care coordinator support.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>COPD discharge care bundle</intervention_name>
    <description>As a part of RHSCN quality improvement initiative, the elements of the COPD discharge bundle were integrated into a standardized COPD admission order set and are being implemented province-wide. The discharging physician/team will complete the COPD bundle (with reminders facilitated by clinical decision support tools) prior to patient discharge. A copy of the bundle is retained in the patient's medical record, and another copy is sent to the patient's primary care provider detailing the components of the bundle that were completed prior to discharge, and those still needing to be addressed. The patient will also receive a patient-focused discharge checklist detailing discharge bundle items</description>
    <arm_group_label>COPD discharge care bundle</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>COPD discharge care bundle &amp; coordinator</intervention_name>
    <description>The coordinator will be health professional associated with a Primary Care Network, ED or AHS with access to patient information. Patients will be informed that care coordinator may contact them for follow up after discharge. At 48-72 hours after hospital/ED discharge and then at intervals to be determined, the care coordinator will contact the patient by phone. The care coordinator will identify specific needs or problems that patient may have encountered after discharge, which could potentially affect the successful transition from acute to community care setting. Specifically, the care coordinator will seek information on any follow up with family doctor visit, pulmonary rehabilitation and smoking cessation referrals</description>
    <arm_group_label>COPD discharge care bundle &amp; coordinator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical diagnosis of COPD;

          -  Male or female, 50 years of age and over, admitted to ED or hospital for an
             exacerbation of COPD. The age limit is imposed to reduce the chances of enrolling
             patients with asthma.

          -  Any stage of severity;

          -  Not being treated previously under the COPD care bundle

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a diagnosis other than COPD will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael K Stickland, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marta Michas, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>780-248-1761</phone>
    <email>marta.michas@ualberta.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michael K Stickland, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>780-492-3995</phone>
    <email>michael.stickland@ualberta.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Foothills Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rockyview General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Alexandra Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alberta Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Red Deer Regional Hospital Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Red Deer</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T4N 4E7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael K Stickland, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>780-492-3995</phone>
      <email>michael.stickland@ualberta.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alberta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Stickland</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>COPD</keyword>
  <keyword>AECOPD</keyword>
  <keyword>Discharge care bundle</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient Care Bundles</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

