<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03356496</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO00030057</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03356496</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preoperative Self-managed Respiratory Therapy for Reduction of Postoperative Pulmonary Complications</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRESMART</acronym>
  <official_title>Preoperative Self-managed Respiratory Therapy for Reduction of Postoperative Pulmonary Complications After Non-cardiothoracic Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative pulmonary complications (PPCs) are a source of much morbidity and mortality.
      Rates of PPCs exceed 30% in patients with multiple risk factors. Several studies have
      demonstrated reduced PPCs in patients who underwent preoperative inspiratory muscle training.
      These studies largely focused on cardiothoracic surgery and required the use of respiratory
      therapists. The investigators hypothesize that preoperative, self-administered respiratory
      therapy would reduce PPCs in patients with risk factors for PPCs undergoing any
      non-cardiothoracic surgery. This study is a randomized, controlled trial comparing
      preoperative use of an oscillating positive expiratory pressure (OPEP) device with usual care
      in patients undergoing non-emergent, non-cardiothoracic surgical procedures under general
      anesthesia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative pulmonary complications account for &gt;50% of all adverse postoperative events
      and are more costly and carry greater comorbidity than cardiac complications. Much research
      has been performed to identify potential risk reduction strategies for PPCs. Until recently
      all of these focused on intraoperative and postoperative interventions, including
      lung-protective mechanical ventilation, lung expansion techniques, and use of regional
      anesthesia and analgesia. In the last few years several studies have investigated the
      potential role of preoperative interventions to improve respiratory status. These studies
      have demonstrated benefit from preoperative inspiratory muscle training (IMT). A recent
      systematic review found that any preoperative intervention, such as education, IMT, exercise
      training or relaxation reduced PPC rates. However, these studies have focused on
      cardiothoracic and abdominal surgery, and almost all have utilized respiratory
      therapist-directed interventions. Likely due to the additional costs and difficulty of
      arranging respiratory therapy on an outpatient basis, this promising new risk mitigation
      strategy has yet to be adopted on a large scale. Oscillating positive expiratory pressure
      (OPEP) devices offer a potentially easier and less costly preoperative respiratory
      intervention. OPEPs are a drug-free, easy to use, hand-held device with a
      pressure-oscillation dynamic that provides intermittent resistance and creates positive
      pressure and oscillations simultaneously. It opens weak or collapsed airways to mobilize and
      assist mucociliary clearance to the upper airways where it can be coughed out. This study
      evaluates the hypothesis that providing preoperative, patient self-directed respiratory
      therapy with use of an OPEP device will reduce the incidence of PPCs in patients with
      increased pulmonary risk undergoing any major, non-cardiothoracic surgery with general
      anesthesia.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative pulmonary complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Composite of hypoxemia (documentation of pulse oximetry &lt;88% with provision of oxygen therapy beyond 24 hours after surgery); bronchospasm (documentation of new wheezing or bronchospasm with provision of bronchodilator therapy); hypercarbia (documentation of serum bicarbonate or arterial or end-tidal carbon dioxide level above reference range treated with provision of mechanical ventilation [invasive or noninvasive]); atelectasis (radiographic evidence of atelectasis plus documentation of respiratory symptoms or abnormal lung exam findings); pneumonia (radiologic evidence of pulmonary infiltrate plus administration of antibiotics with documented indication of pneumonia); pleural effusion (radiographic evidence of pleural effusion and performance of thoracentesis); pneumothorax (radiographic evidence of pneumothorax); and ventilatory failure (replacement of endotracheal tube or mechanical ventilation for &gt;48 hours postoperatively)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Patient death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length-of-stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days of hospitalization after index surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readmission</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of rehospitalization after index surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unanticipated hospital admissions</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of inpatient admission after index surgery that was planned as outpatient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unanticipated hospital observation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of admission for observation for recovery after index surgery planned as outpatient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unanticipated intensive care unit utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of intensive care admission after index surgery not planned for intensive care unit admission</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">394</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Respiratory Complication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient provided with instructions and video for the use of oscillating positive expiratory pressure (OPEP) device. Patient instructed to use OPEP device set at the median resistance at least 4 times daily for at least 20 breathing cycles for 1-3 weeks before surgery. Patient instructed to record usage and any physical complaints in a diary.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient receives only usual care as provided by perioperative healthcare providers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oscillating positive expiratory pressure (OPEP) device</intervention_name>
    <description>OPEP device provides both lung expansion through positive expiratory pressure (PEP) and mucociliary clearance through the oscillating nature of the PEP.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aerobika</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Intermediate or high risk for postoperative pulmonary complications as defined by
             ARISCAT score &gt;25

          -  Undergoing non-cardiothoracic surgery scheduled at least 7 days in the future

          -  Planned general anesthesia (alone or in combination with regional or neuraxial
             anesthesia)

          -  Personal internet access

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active bronchospasm during preoperative clinic visit

          -  History of pneumothorax

          -  History of tracheal stoma or ventilator dependency

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Chronic oxygen requirement

          -  Deficient motor and/or visual function that will prohibit utilization of the device or
             instructional video and handout

          -  Lack of English language proficiency

          -  Inability to consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kurt J Pfeifer, MD</last_name>
    <phone>414-805-0520</phone>
    <email>kpfeifer@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hari Paudel, MD</last_name>
    <phone>414-805-6250</phone>
    <email>hpaudel@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Canet J, Gallart L, Gomar C, Paluzie G, Vallès J, Castillo J, Sabaté S, Mazo V, Briones Z, Sanchis J; ARISCAT Group. Prediction of postoperative pulmonary complications in a population-based surgical cohort. Anesthesiology. 2010 Dec;113(6):1338-50. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181fc6e0a.</citation>
    <PMID>21045639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katsura M, Kuriyama A, Takeshima T, Fukuhara S, Furukawa TA. Preoperative inspiratory muscle training for postoperative pulmonary complications in adults undergoing cardiac and major abdominal surgery. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015 Oct 5;(10):CD010356. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD010356.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26436600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 28, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hari Paudel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

