<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03359291</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AC-055-122</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03359291</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Study to Investigate the Effect of Macitentan on the Concentrations of Rosuvastatin in the Blood of Healthy Male Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-center, Open-label, One-sequence, Two-treatment Study to Investigate the Effect of Macitentan at Steady State on the Pharmacokinetics of Rosuvastatin in Healthy Male Subjects.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Actelion</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Actelion</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this Phase 1 trial is to study a potential drug-drug interaction between
      macitentan and rosuvastatin, a model substrate of various transporter proteins (e.g. in the
      gut).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rosuvastatin is a substrate of various transporter proteins including breast cancer
      resistance protein (BCRP) and organic anion-transporting polypeptides (OATP). It is unknown
      to which extent macitentan has an effect, if any, on BCRP transporters, especially intestinal
      BCRP. The primary purpose of this Phase 1 study is to investigate the effect of macitentan on
      the pharmacokinetics of rosuvastatin, a model BCRP substrate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 4, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 4, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>All subjects will receive rosuvastatin alone (treatment A) or with macitentan at steady state (treatment B). A fixed sequence design was selected to avoid a lengthy washout period and unnecessary prolongation of subjects' participation in the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-inf) of rosuvastatin following administration of rosuvastatin alone (treatment A) and in combination with macitentan (treatment B)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to Day17 (treatment A: from Day1-Day5 and treatment B: from Day10-Day17)</time_frame>
    <description>AUC(0-inf) is the area under the plasma concentration-time curves of rosuvastatin, calculated from time zero to the extrapolated infinite time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax of rosuvastatin following administration of rosuvastatin alone (treatment A) and in combination with macitentan (treatment B)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to Day17 (treatment A: from Day1-Day5 and treatment B: from Day10-Day17)</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax is the maximum observed plasma concentration and is directly derived from the individual plasma concentration time curves of rosuvastatin</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>tmax of rosuvastatin following administration of rosuvastatin alone (treatment A) and in combination with macitentan (treatment B)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to Day17 (treatment A: from Day1-Day5 and treatment B: from Day10-Day17)</time_frame>
    <description>The time to reach maximum plasma concentration (tmax) of rosuvastatin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>t½ of rosuvastatin following administration of rosuvastatin alone (treatment A) and in combination with macitentan (treatment B)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to Day17 (treatment A: from Day1-Day5 and treatment B: from Day10-Day17)</time_frame>
    <description>t½ is the terminal half-life of rosuvastatin and corresponds to the period of time required for the concentration levels of rosuvastatin to be reduced by one-half</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-t) of rosuvastatin following administration of rosuvastatin alone (treatment A) and in combination with macitentan (treatment B)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to Day17 (treatment A: from Day1-Day5 and treatment B: from Day10-Day17)</time_frame>
    <description>AUC(0-t) is the area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to time t of the last measured concentration above the limit of quantification of rosuvastatin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trough plasma concentrations of macitentan and its metabolite ACT-132577</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day5 to Day17</time_frame>
    <description>Trough concentrations of macitentan and ACT-132577 are measured before oral administration of macitentan</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in supine blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to end-of-study visit (Day 26-28)</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline to each time point of measurement during study period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in pulse rate</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to end-of-study visit (Day 26-28)</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline to each time point of measurement during study period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in heart rate (HR)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to end-of-study visit (Day 26-28)</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline to each time point of measurement during study period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in ECG variables</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to end-of-study visit (Day 26-28)</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline to each time point of measurement during study period in ECG variables: PR, QRS, QT, RR, and QT corrected for Bazett's and Fridericia's formulae (QTcB and QTcF, respectively)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline to end-of-study (EOS) in body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to end-of-study visit (Day 26-28)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in body weight measured in kg during study period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in clinical laboratory tests</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to end-of-study visit (Day 26-28)</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline to each time point of measurement during study period for clinical laboratory tests (hematology, clinical chemistry, serology)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence rate of treatment-emergent treatment-emergent adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day1 to follow-up period (Day46-48)</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence rates of treatment-emergent AEs including abnormalities in ECG variables during each treatment as well as AEs leading to the discontinuation of study treatment. A treatment-emergent AE is any AE temporally associated with the use of a study treatment, whether or not considered related to the study treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Subjects</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence AB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects participate in two study periods: During the first period (treatment A), they receive a single oral dose of rosuvastatin on Day 1. During the second period (treatment B), they receive a single oral loading dose of macitentan on Day 5 and oral doses of macitentan from Day 6 to Day 16 (i.e., 11 doses). Subjects receive a single oral dose of 10 mg rosuvastatin concomitantly with macitentan in the morning of Day 10.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rosuvastatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Single oral dose of 10 mg rosuvastatin (film-coated tablet) on Day 1 and Day 10</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence AB</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Macitentan</intervention_name>
    <description>Single oral dose of 30 mg macitentan (film-coated tablet) on Day 5 and 10 mg macitentan administered orally from Day 6 to Day 16</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence AB</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ACT-064992</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Principal Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed informed consent in the local language prior to any study-mandated procedure.

          -  Healthy male subjects aged between 18 and 55 years (inclusive) at screening.

          -  No clinically significant findings on the physical examination at screening.

          -  Body mass index of 18.0 to 30.0 kg/m2 (inclusive) at screening.

          -  Systolic blood pressure 100−140 mmHg, diastolic blood pressure 60−90 mmHg, and pulse
             rate 50−90 beats per minute (inclusive), measured on the dominant arm, after 5 min in
             the supine position at screening.

          -  12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) without clinically relevant abnormalities, measured
             after 5 min in the supine position at screening.

          -  Hematology and clinical chemistry test results not deviating from the normal range to
             a clinically relevant extent at screening.

          -  Negative results from urine drug screen and alcohol breath test at screening and Day
             −1.

          -  Ability to communicate well with the investigator, in the local language, and to
             understand and comply with the requirements of the study.

        Principal Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known allergic reactions or hypersensitivity to macitentan, rosuvastatin, any drug of
             the same classes, or any of their excipients.

          -  Any contraindication for rosuvastatin treatment.

          -  History or clinical evidence of myopathy.

          -  Subjects of Asian race.

          -  Known hypersensitivity or allergy to natural rubber latex.

          -  Values of hepatic aminotransferase (alanine aminotransferase and aspartate
             aminotransferase) outside of the normal range at screening.

          -  Hemoglobin or hematocrit outside of the normal range at screening.

          -  History or clinical evidence of any disease and/or existence of any surgical or
             medical condition, which might interfere with the absorption, distribution, metabolism
             or excretion of the study treatment(s) (appendectomy and herniotomy allowed,
             cholecystectomy not allowed).

          -  Previous history of fainting, collapse, syncope, orthostatic hypotension, or vasovagal
             reactions.

          -  Veins unsuitable for intravenous puncture on either arm (e.g., veins that are
             difficult to locate, access or puncture, veins with a tendency to rupture during or
             after puncture).

          -  Previous exposure to macitentan.

          -  Previous exposure to rosuvastatin.

          -  Treatment with another investigational drug within 3 months prior to screening or
             participation in more than 3 investigational drug studies within 1 year prior to
             screening.

          -  History or clinical evidence of alcoholism or drug abuse within the 3-year period
             prior to screening.

          -  Excessive caffeine consumption, defined as ≥ 800 mg per day at screening.

          -  Nicotine intake (e.g., smoking, nicotine patch, nicotine chewing gum or electronic
             cigarettes) within 3 months prior to screening and inability to refrain from nicotine
             intake from screening until End-Of-Study (EOS).

          -  Previous treatment with any prescribed medications (including vaccines) or
             over-the-counter (OTC) medications (including herbal medicines such as St John's Wort,
             homeopathic preparations, vitamins, and minerals) within 3 weeks prior to first study
             treatment administration.

          -  Loss of 250 mL or more of blood within 3 months prior to screening.

          -  Positive results from the hepatitis serology, except for vaccinated subjects or
             subjects with past but resolved hepatitis, at screening.

          -  Positive results from the HIV serology at screening.

          -  Any circumstances or conditions, which, in the opinion of the investigator, may affect
             full participation in the study or compliance with the protocol.

          -  Legal incapacity or limited legal capacity at screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shirin Bruderer, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Actelion</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CRS Clinical Research Services Mannheim</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mannheim</city>
        <zip>68167</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 27, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>macitentan</keyword>
  <keyword>rosuvastatin</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rosuvastatin Calcium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Macitentan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

