<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03356067</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IClinicalEM2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03356067</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endoscopic Pyloromyotomy for Refractory Gastroparesis</brief_title>
  <acronym>GREG</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Sham and Cross-Over-Controlled Trial of Per-oral Endoscopic Pyloromyotomy (G-POEM) in Patients With Refractory Gastroparesis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institute for Clinical and Experimental Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>King's College Hospital NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Klinikum Augsburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cliniques universitaires Saint-Luc- Université Catholique de Louvain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Amsterdam</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Trnava</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Comenius University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pavol Jozef Safarik University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Cluj Napoca</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Charles University, Czech Republic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institute for Clinical and Experimental Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Gastroparesis is a disorder triggered by numerous causes and it is defined by symptoms and
      with an objective evidence of delayed gastric emptying in the absence of obstruction.

      Effective treatment for gastroparesis is challenging especially in patients with severe
      symptoms. In refractory gastroparesis, endoscopic or surgical treatments may therefore be
      considered. Endoscopic treatments include intrapyloric injection of botulinum toxin and
      transpyloric insertion of a metallic stent. Surgical options involve implantation of a
      gastric &quot;pacemaker&quot; (gastric stimulation), pyloroplasty and subtotal gastrectomy.

      Recently, a new endoscopic technique, gastric endoscopic per oral pyloromyotomy (G-POEM) has
      been introduced with promising preliminary results.

      The aim of this prospective, sham-controlled, cross-over study (cross-over for patients
      randomized to the sham arm) is to compare short and long-term efficacy and safety of G-POEM
      in patients with refractory gastroparesis. Symptoms and objective parameters of gastric
      emptying will be the main outcome criteria. The reason of using a sham protocol is to control
      for the potential confounders (therapeutic effects of touch and belief, which are components
      of the placebo effect).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Gastroparesis is a disorder triggered by numerous causes and it is defined by symptoms and
      with an objective evidence of delayed gastric emptying in the absence of obstruction (albeit
      pyloric spasms may play a role in a subset of patients). Gastroparesis may be a consequence
      of medication, surgery or diabetes but in approximately one third of patients, the cause
      remains unknown and the patients are diagnosed with idiopathic gastroparesis. Effective
      treatment for gastroparesis is challenging especially in patients with severe symptoms. The
      efficacy of prokinetics is dubious since they have not proven real clinical efficacy in
      placebo controlled trials. In refractory gastroparesis, endoscopic or surgical treatments may
      therefore be considered. Endoscopic treatments include intrapyloric injection of botulinum
      toxin and transpyloric insertion of a metallic stent. Surgical options involve implantation
      of a gastric &quot;pacemaker&quot; (gastric stimulation), pyloroplasty and subtotal gastrectomy. The
      partial effectiveness of botulinum toxin injection, stents and pyloroplasty suggests that
      disruption of the pyloric muscle may lead to a decreased intrapyloric tone and consequently
      to a symptomatic improvement in some patients with refractory gastroparesis.

      Recently, a new endoscopic technique, gastric endoscopic per oral pyloromyotomy (G-POEM) has
      been introduced with promising preliminary results. Uncontrolled studies with so far limited
      number of patients have demonstrated a significant symptomatic improvement in approximately
      70% of patients and improved or normalized of gastric emptying in more than a half of
      patients after G-POEM. A prospective uncontrolled study suggested that patients with
      idiopathic or post-surgical gastroparesis experiences higher success rate after G-POEM
      (70-80%) compared to patients with diabetic gastroparesis (50%).

      G-POEM is, in principle, adaptation of POEM (per-oral endoscopic myotomy) in the stomach.
      POEM is now considered a standard treatment for esophageal achalasia and it has been shown to
      be safe and effective. In contrast to achalasia, pathophysiology of pyloric function in
      patients with gastroparesis is less understood and the explanation of how and why G-POEM
      should work is some-how hypothetical. For example, presumed pylorospasm has not been
      demonstrated as the predictive factor for treatment success of G-POEM yet. Refractory
      gastroparesis is often accompanied by psychological or even psychiatric disturbances and
      hence a placebo&quot; effect of G-POEM cannot be ruled out. Therefore, the real clinical efficacy
      of G-POEM can only be demonstrated in a clinical randomized sham-controlled trial.

      To assess the severity of gastroparesis-related symptoms, the Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom
      Index (GCSI) has been developed for this item. The GCSI is part of a larger questionnaire
      PAGI-SYM (Patient Assessment of Upper Gastrointestinal Symptom severity index) established
      for assessment of patient-reported symptoms in gastroparesis (dyspepsia and gastroesophageal
      reflux). PAGI-SYM as well as GCSI subscale scores varied significantly by global disease
      severity, with higher (worse) scores observed in those subjects who rated their gastroparesis
      as moderate to severe.

      The aim of this prospective, sham-controlled, cross-over study (cross-over for patients
      randomized to the sham arm) is to compare short and long-term efficacy and safety of G-POEM
      in patients with refractory gastroparesis. Symptoms and objective parameters of gastric
      emptying will be the main outcome criteria. The reason of using a sham protocol is to control
      for the potential confounders (therapeutic effects of touch and belief, which are components
      of the placebo effect).

      Investigators plan to randomize 86 patients (43 in the active arm, ratio 1:1 active vs.
      sham). Sample size is calculated based on expected therapeutic success of G-POEM in 50% of
      patients vs. 20% in the sham group; significance level 0,05; study power 0,8; beta error 0,2;
      adjustment for 15% expected drop out.

      Patients will be randomised in blocks of 6, stratified according to the etiologies:
      (idiopathic, diabetic, and post-surgical; patients after esophagectomy with gastric
      pull-through will not be included). Control visits will be scheduled at 3, 6, 12, 24, and 36
      months. The primary outcome will be the proportion of patients with treatment success in the
      active group vs. sham group at 6 months after the procedure. Several secondary outcomes will
      also be assessed, including procedure-related parameters and safety parameters and change in
      Gastric Emptying Study (GET) after G-POEM vs. sham. After 6 months, patients randomized to
      the sham group will be offered G-POEM procedure and further followed up (cross-over part of
      the study) providing that they did not have a therapeutic effect of the sham procedure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized sham-procedure controlled trial with crossover after 6 months after procedure</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Main outcome is the proportion of patients with treatment success after the procedure.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment success is defined as a decrease of a total Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index (GCSI) symptom score at least 50% from the baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with treatment success in the active arm after 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment success is defined as a decrease of a total Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index (GCSI) symptom score at least 50% from the baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with treatment success in the active arm after 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment success is defined as a decrease of a total Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index (GCSI) symptom score at least 50% from the baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with treatment success in the active arm after 24 months</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment success is defined as a decrease of a total Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index (GCSI) symptom score at least 50% from the baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with treatment success in the active arm after 36 months</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment success is defined as a decrease of a total Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index (GCSI) symptom score at least 50% from the baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with treatment success in the sham group at 3M</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment success is defined as a decrease of a total Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index (GCSI) symptom score at least 50% from the baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index (GCSI) before and after G-POEM at 3, 6, 12, 24 and 36M and before vs. after sham procedure at 3M and 6M;</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the change of the scores between the active and sham groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in The Patient Assessment of Gastrointestinal Disorders Symptom Severity Index (PAGI-SYM) before and after G-POEM at 3, 6, 12, 24 and 36M and before vs. after sham procedure at 3M and 6M;</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the change of the scores between the active and sham groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of crossed-over patients with treatment success after 6 moths</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment success is defined as a decrease of a total GSCI symptom score at least 50% from the baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Gastroparesis Cardinal Symptom Index (GCSI) crossed-over patients after the G-POEM procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the change of the scores pre and post-procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in The Patient Assessment of Gastrointestinal Disorders Symptom Severity Index (PAGI-SYM) in crossed-over patients after the G-POEM procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the change of the scores pre and post-procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subgroup post-hoc analyses of the treatment success and change in symptomatic scores according to etiology of gastroparesis.</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment success is defined as a decrease of a total GSCI symptom score at least 50%, change in GCSI and PAGY-SYM scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in gastric emptying (scintigraphy) study and/or gastric emptying breath test before and after both G-POEM and sham procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the mean change of these parameters between active and sham groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedure details</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>length of the procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedural adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>perioperative adverse events (complications)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Long term adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence rate of adverse events in treatment and sham groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">86</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastroparesis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Esophago-gastro-duodenoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard endoscopic examination of the upper GI tract with flexible endoscope.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gastric endoscopic peroral pyloromyotomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental per-oral endoscopic myotomy of the pyloric sphincter</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gastric endoscopic peroral pyloromyotomy</intervention_name>
    <description>G-POEM is, in principle, adaptation of POEM (per-oral endoscopic myotomy) in the stomach. The procedure consists of:
Mucosal incision at the greater curvature 3-5 cm from the pylorus
Submucosal tunnelling
Finding pyloric sphincter
Myotomy (2-3 cm) of the pyloric muscle
Incision closure (endoclips or suture device)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gastric endoscopic peroral pyloromyotomy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>G-POEM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Esophago-gastro-duodenoscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard endoscopic examination of the upper GI tract with flexible endoscope</description>
    <arm_group_label>Esophago-gastro-duodenoscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Refractory (&gt; 6 months) and severe (based on a validated total GSCI = Gastroparesis
             Cardinal Symptom Index) gastroparesis, with confirmed gastric emptying based on a
             gastric emptying study: standardized protocol of scintigraphy in all patients
             (performed less than 4 months prior to enrolment), or confirmed by a validated gastric
             emptying breath test [27]. The total GSCI score must be &gt;2.3 [28].

          -  Abnormal gastric emptying is defined as retention of Tc-99 m &gt;60% at 2 h and/or ≥10%
             of residual activity at 4 h on a standardized sulphur colloid solid-phase gastric
             emptying study.

          -  Radiolabelled liquids emptying study will be reserved as alternative technique for
             patients with poor tolerance of solids during scintigraphy. Abnormal gastric emptying
             will represent &gt;50% retention of radiolabelled content (e.g. In-111) at 1 hour.

          -  Abnormal gastric empyting breath test based on a solid normal range determination for
             the test used (e.g. T1/2 &gt; 109 min)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age less than 18 years

          -  No previous attempt with at least one prokinetic drug

          -  No previous attempt to withdraw anticholinergic agents and glucagon like peptide -1
             (GLP-1) and amylin analogues* in patients treated with these substances

          -  Active treatment with opioids or a history of treatment with opioids within 12 months
             before enrolment.

          -  Previous gastric surgery BI or II, esophagectomy, gastric pull-through

          -  Previous pyloromyotomy or pyloroplasty

          -  Known eosinophilic gastroenteritis

          -  Organic pyloric (or intestinal) obstruction (fibrotic stricture, etc.)

          -  Severe coagulopathy

          -  Esophageal or gastric varices and /or portal hypertensive gastropathy

          -  Advanced liver cirrhosis (Child B or Child C)

          -  Active peptic ulcer disease

          -  Pregnancy or puerperium

          -  Malignant or pre-malignant gastric diseases (dysplasia, gastric cancer, GIST)

          -  Any other condition, which in the opinion of the investigator would interfere with
             study requirements

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus

          -  Diagnosis of rumination syndrome or &quot;eating&quot; disorder (mental anorexia, bulimia
             nervosa) **

          -  Severe constipation without using laxatives

          -  Inability to obtain informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Rösch, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Center Hamburg- Eppendorf | UKE Department for Interdisciplinary Endoscopy, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jan Martinek, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Hepatogastroenterology, Institute for Clinical and Experimental Medicine, Prague, Czech Republic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jan Martinek, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>00420723708839</phone>
    <email>jan.martinek@volny.cz</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Irwing Waxman</last_name>
      <email>iwaxman@uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Hepatogastroenterology at Cliniques universitaires St-Luc, Brussels, Belgium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pierre H Deprez</last_name>
      <email>pdeprez@uclouvain.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Hubert Piessevaux</last_name>
      <email>hubert.piessevaux@uclouvain.be</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pierre H Deprez</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hubert Piessevaux</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Translational Research in GastroIntestinal Disorders, Leuven, Belgium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jan Tack</last_name>
      <email>jan.tack@kuleuven.be</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raf Bishop</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tim Vanuytsel</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jan Tack</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute for Clinical and Experimental Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prague 4</city>
        <state>Prague</state>
        <zip>14021</zip>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jan Martinek, MD. PhD.</last_name>
      <phone>+420723708839</phone>
      <email>jan.martinek@volny.cz</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jan Martinek</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital in Hradec Kralove</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hradec Králové</city>
        <zip>50005</zip>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ilja Tacheci</last_name>
      <email>tacheci@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stanislav Rejchrt</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcela Kopacová</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Department of Surgical Gastroenterology L, Denmark</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus</city>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rastislav Kunda</last_name>
      <email>rasti.kunda@aarhus.rm.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rastislav Kunda</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>III. Medizinische Klinik, Medical Center/Klinikum Augsburg, Germany</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augsburg</city>
        <zip>86156</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Helmut Messman</last_name>
      <email>helmut.messmann@klinikum-augsburg.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helmut Messmann</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center Hamburg- Eppendorf | UKE Department for Interdisciplinary Endoscopy, Germany</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg- Eppendorf</city>
        <zip>20246</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas Thomas Rösch, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>t.roesch@uke.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Rösch</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Fockens</last_name>
      <email>p.fockens@amc.uva.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Arjan Bredenoord</last_name>
      <email>a.j.bredenoord@amc.uva.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Fockens</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arjan Bredenoord</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regional Institute of Gastroenterology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cluj-Napoca</city>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marcel Tantau</last_name>
      <email>matantau@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jesenius Faculty of Medicine in Martin, Clinic of Gastroenterological Internal Medicine, Slovak Republic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Martin</city>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michal Demeter</last_name>
      <email>michaldemeter@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Martin Duricek</last_name>
      <email>martin.duricek@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michal Demeter</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rudolf Hyrdel</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martin Duricek</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Banovcin</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Internal Medicine, University Hospital Trnava, Slovak Republic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Trnava</city>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rastislav Hustak</last_name>
      <email>rhustak@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jan Usak</last_name>
      <email>jan.usak@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jan Maartinek</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rastislav Hustak</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jan Usak</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Surgical Gastroenterology, Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>17176</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Koshi Kumaga</last_name>
      <email>koshi.kumagai@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jon A Tsai</last_name>
      <email>jon.tsai@ki.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Koshi Kumaga</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jon Tsai</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>King's Institute of Therapeutic Endoscopy, London, UK</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE5 9RS</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amyn Haji</last_name>
      <email>amynhaji@nhs.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amyn Haji</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Czechia</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
    <country>Slovakia</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 22, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Institute for Clinical and Experimental Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Doc. (Ass. prof.) Jan Martinek, MD, PhD, AGAF</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Ass. prof.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroparesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

