<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03357705</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SO-GHI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03357705</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness in Limiting the Need to Elevate the Maxillary Sinus</brief_title>
  <acronym>SO-GHI</acronym>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Different Alveolar Preservation Procedures in the Upper Molar Zone in Limiting the Need to Elevate the Maxillary Sinus to Allow the Placement of Dental Implants: a Prospective Cohort Multicentre Clinical Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>International Piezosurgery Academy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>International Piezosurgery Academy</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the present study is to evaluate the effectiveness of different alveolar
      preservation procedures performed at the time of extraction of the first or second upper
      molar in avoiding a maxillary sinus elevation or at least limiting the size, to allow the
      insertion of dental implants. The residual bone height will be radiographically evaluated on
      the sinus sinus floor at the time of extraction and after 6 months by comparing the cases
      where alveolar preservation is performed using a nanocrystalline synthetic hydroxyapatite
      graft (group A) with cases where the procedure of alveolar preservation is performed using
      bovine collagen sponge (group B).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bone resorption and contraction of bone volumes are physiologically occurring after the
      extraction of any dental element. This reabsorption of the alveolar process results in a
      reduction in the size of the alveolar crest both in width and in height. Numerous studies
      have attempted to quantify the size and timing of contraction of bone volumes after a dental
      flotation. The data reported in the literature show an average horizontal reduction of about
      2.5 mm, which appears more marked by the vestibular side than the palatal one. The vertical
      contraction of the crest is estimated at 25-30%, with bone loss of 1-2 mm and a soft
      contraction of soft tissues of about 2 mm. In the area of the first and second upper molars,
      however, the total contraction of the alveoli is greater because the residual crest at the
      insertion of the implant would have undergone a double reduction, namely from the coronal
      side with the mechanisms just indicated, but also from the apex , for maxillary sinus
      pneumonia due to the absence of dental element6. For this reason, insertion of an implant in
      this area may be difficult due to an inadequate height of the remaining bone, which
      necessitates a bone regeneration procedure, ie a maxillary sinus elevation. This procedure
      allows you to regain the abdominal apex lost and the insertion of adequate lengths. In the
      presence of satisfactory residual bone height, maxillary sinus breast can be performed
      crestally, while in more markedly atrophic cases, especially in the presence of anatomically
      wide breasts, a side-by-side approach is preferable.

      Various grafting materials have been used to perform alveolar retention with the aim of
      limiting the contraction of bone volumes and improving bone formation: autologous bone,
      homologous bone and bone substitutes of heterologous origin or alloplastic.

      The use of autologous bone in alveolar preservation was soon abandoned for bone marrow
      morbidity, especially when deciding to use a donor site other than the extraction area. The
      homologous bone, although showing excellent results, is still to date problematic use in
      Italy. The heterologous grafts have been widely used for alveolar preservation; however,
      especially if bovine bone is used, significant percentages of graft (up to 25%) are
      histologically observable at 9 months from graft.

      For these reasons, in this study it was decided to use as a graft in Group A a synthetic
      material (nanocrystalline synthetic hydroxyapatite) and in group B a collagen of bovine
      origin.

      Bovine collagen, while having reduced dimensional stability over time, has the advantage of
      contributing to stabilizing the clot, an essential basis for bone healing, and is completely
      replaced by newly formed tissue in a short time. Synthetic hydroxyapatite, used as a
      biomaterial, has shown ability to stimulate osteoconduction and is slowly but completely
      replaced over time by newly formed bone, thus providing a great capacity for maintaining
      volumes.

      Moreover, nanostructured porous hydroxyapatite appear to favor adhesion of bone matrix
      proteins and promote differentiation of osteogenetic cells. Although the nanocrystalline
      hydroxyapatite in a silica gel matrix has already been successfully tested as a clotting
      material in the maxillary sinus, the behavior of pure sintered nano-hydroxyapatite granules
      has not yet been evaluated in terms of osteoconductive potential and dimensional stability in
      time at post-mining sites.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 31, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>radiographic distance between crestal bone and implant platform</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>necessity of sinus floor regeneration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Alveolar Bone Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>synthetic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>alveolar ridge preservation with synthetic bone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>collagen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>alveolar ridge preservation with bovine collagen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>alveolar ridge preservation with synthetic bone</intervention_name>
    <description>after tooth extraction</description>
    <arm_group_label>synthetic</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ghimas</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>alveolar ridge preservation with bovine collagen</intervention_name>
    <description>after tooth extraction</description>
    <arm_group_label>collagen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Septodont</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. indication for extraction of the first or second upper molar, based on a thorough
             diagnosis and treatment plan;

          2. &quot;three-rooted&quot; anatomy of the first or second upper molar to be extracted so that it
             can have an inter-radicular septum that allows a precise measurement of the height of
             the bone ridge from the septum itself and from the walls of the 3 alveoli to the floor
             of the maxillary sinus;

          3. Extraction of intercalate molar or last arch element;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Anatomy of the molar with unique root or fused roots

          2. contextual extraction of the molar and one or more contiguous elements

          3. apical lesions with a diameter of&gt; 3 mm or cystic lesions with respect to the element
             to be extracted

          4. root fracture which has produced resorption or bone fenestration

        1) acute myocardial infarction in the last six months; 2) uncontrolled clotting disorders;
        3) uncontrolled diabetes (HBA1c&gt; 7.5%); 4) radiotherapy in the head / neck district for the
        last 24 months; 5) immunocompromise (eg HIV infection or chemotherapy over the last 3
        years); 6) treatment in progress or with bisphosphonates via e.v .; 7) autoimmune diseases
        in chronic therapy with methotrexate or other immunosuppressive drugs; 8) allergy to bovine
        collagen; 9) psychological or psychiatric problems; 10) abuse of alcohol or drug use; 11)
        uncontrolled periodontal disease;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claudio Stacchi, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Piezosurgery Academy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Claudio Stacchi, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>0403992020</phone>
    <phone_ext>+39</phone_ext>
    <email>claudio@stacchi.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Federico Berton, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>0403992254</phone>
    <phone_ext>+39</phone_ext>
    <email>fberton@units.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Piezosurgery Academy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parma</city>
        <zip>43100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claudio Stacchi, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>0403992020</phone>
      <phone_ext>+39</phone_ext>
      <email>claudio@stacchi.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Federico Berton, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>0403992254</phone>
      <phone_ext>+39</phone_ext>
      <email>fberton@units.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Teresa Lombardi, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sergio Spinato, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rosario Sentineri, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fabio Bernardello, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Claudio Stacchi, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carlsson GE, Bergman B, Hedegård B. Changes in contour of the maxillary alveolar process under immediate dentures. A longitudinal clinical and x-ray cephalometric study covering 5 years. Acta Odontol Scand. 1967 Jun;25(1):45-75.</citation>
    <PMID>5233859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharan A, Madjar D. Maxillary sinus pneumatization following extractions: a radiographic study. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2008 Jan-Feb;23(1):48-56.</citation>
    <PMID>18416412</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 24, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 30, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>International Piezosurgery Academy</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mr. Claudio Stacchi, DDS, MSc</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>President of the International Piezosurgery Academy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>alveolar ridge preservation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alveolar Bone Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

