<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03359525</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4744</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03359525</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study Comparing Topical Versus Intravenous Tranexamic Acid in Anterior Total Hip Arthroplasty</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Randomized Study Comparing Topical Versus Intravenous Tranexamic Acid in Anterior Total Hip Arthroplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Albany Medical College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Albany Medical College</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Brief Summary Title: Prospective Randomized Trial Comparing Topical Versus Intravenous
      Tranexamic Acid (TXA) in Anterior (Total hip arthroplasty) Several strategies have been used
      to reduce transfusion requirements during total hip arthroplasty (THA). Recently,
      anti-fibrinolytic agent TXA, has been used extensively in THAs to minimize intra-operative
      blood losses. However, few studies have compared the efficacy of topical versus intravenous
      use in direct anterior THA. Therefore, the investigators will attempt to evaluate differences
      in the post-operative outcomes of topical versus intravenous TXA in Direct anterior approach
      to THA. The investigators propose to conduct a prospective randomized study in which patients
      who have exhausted non-operative treatment for hip osteoarthritis and are opting for THA will
      be randomized into 3 groups in a 1:1:1 ratio based on a computer generated algorithm
      following inclusion and exclusion criteria as described below. Patients will be distributed
      in to 3 groups as follows: Group A: Intravenous TXA at a dose of 1 gram administered 30 min
      prior to skin incision and 1 gram 3 hours after the procedure. (Total dose: 2 grams) Group B:
      Topical TXA at a dose of 1 gram injected in to the peri-articular tissues prior to closure
      and 1 gram injected into the joint through the drain following wound closure. (Total dose:2
      grams) Group C: Combined Intravenous 1 gram given intravenous 30 min prior to skin incision
      and topical TXA (1 gram) injected into the peri-articular tissues prior to closure. (Total
      dose: 2 grams). The number of subjects needed to achieve 90% power was calculated based on a
      one-way fixed effects analysis of variance with 3 levels. Primary endpoint used was drainage
      measured in milliliters in the post-operative (POD) #1 following surgery. Criterion for
      significance (alpha) was set at 0.05 and the ANOVA statistics was non-directional (two
      tailed). Preliminary data indicated that drainage volume averages 250 ml with a standard
      deviation of 160 ml in our operating room. Difference (maximum to minimum of the three
      levels) of 150 ml was judged to be the minimally clinically relevant difference in drainage
      volume (effect size =0.38). A 20% loss to follow up was also assumed. The study will need 38
      cases per cell for a total of 114 cases to achieve 90% power of detecting a difference this
      large. Data metrics will be tabulated into excel spreadsheets. Data analysis will be
      performed using statistical software. Quantitative data will be analyzed using
      non-directional analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey's test for multiple comparisons.
      Non-normality or heteroscedasticity of data will either be corrected by transformation or a
      non-parametric (Kruskal Wallis) test will be used. Categorical data will be analyzed using
      chi-square tests (or Fisher's exact test if any cells expected value is 5 or less). A p-value
      &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Detailed Description Prospective Randomized Study Comparing Topical versus Intravenous
      Tranexamic Acid in Anterior Total Hip Arthroplasty A. Study Background and Purpose Hip and
      knee arthroplasty is one of the most successful procedures for relieving pain and correction
      of deformity in patients with degenerative arthritis of the hip and knee with approximately 1
      million procedures performed every year in the United States. However, these joint
      replacements are associated with substantial amounts of blood loss varying between 500 and
      1,500 milliliters often necessitating allogeneic blood transfusions in the post-operative
      period. This potentially leads to delays in discharge, physical recovery, and increased
      complications. In addition, it can escalate the cost of total joint arthroplasties in
      healthcare organizations. Several strategies have been employed in the past with varying
      efficacies to reduce transfusion requirements including preoperative autologous donation,
      erythropoietin use, intra-operative hypotensive anesthesia, fibrin spray, cell salvage, and
      post-operative auto-transfusions drains. Over the past decade the anti-fibrinolytic agent
      tranexamic acid, a synthetic analog of the amino acid lysine, has been used extensively in
      lower extremity arthroplasties to minimize intra-operative blood losses. Tranexamic acid
      prevents the conversion of plasminogen to plasmin on the surface of fibrin, thereby
      inhibiting fibrinolysis and reducing blood loss. Despite its almost universal use and
      documented safety, there is significant controversy regarding the optimal route of
      administration with several studies documenting equivalent efficacy of intravenous and
      topical administration, with both routes of administration currently considered standard of
      care in both hip and knee arthroplasties. Anecdotally, the senior author has found that
      topical use of tranexamic acid has led to greater post-operative drainage and reduction in
      hematocrit compared to intravenous use. This may be secondary to the absence of tamponade
      effect with anterior total hip arthroplasty. However, few studies have compared the efficacy
      of topical versus intravenous use of this medication in direct anterior total hip
      arthroplasty. Therefore, in this prospective randomized study, the investigators will attempt
      to evaluate if there exists any significant difference in the post-operative outcomes of
      topical versus intravenous tranexamic acid following anterior total hip arthroplasty.

      B. Study Design This will be a prospective randomized study in which subjects who have
      exhausted non-operative treatment for hip osteoarthritis and are opting for total hip
      arthroplasty will be randomized into 3 groups in a 1:1:1 ratio based on a computer generated
      algorithm following inclusion and exclusion criteria as described below. The patients will be
      recruited into the study by the principal investigator from his practice cohort. They will be
      consented to enroll in to the study by any one of the co-investigators. They will either be
      recruited in the office at Bone and Joint Center, 1367 Washington Avenue, Albany New York or
      at Albany Medical Center, 43 New Scotland Avenue on the day of surgery. Patients will be
      further stratified according to BMI (body mass index) as this may be a confounding variable
      affecting blood loss. The patients will be distributed in to 3 groups as follows: Group A:
      Intravenous Tranexamic acid at a dose of 1 gram administered 30 min prior to skin incision
      and 1 gram 3 hours after the procedure. (Total dose administered is 2 grams); Group B:
      Topical Tranexamic acid at a dose of 1 gram injected in to the peri-articular tissues prior
      to closure and 1 gram injected into the joint through the drain following wound closure.
      (Total dose administered is 2 grams); Group C: Combined Intravenous 1 gram given intravenous
      30 min prior to skin incision and topical tranexamic acid (1 gram) injected in to the
      peri-articular tissues prior to closure. (Total dose administered is 2 grams). Women who are
      premenopausal will have a pregnancy test prior to total hip arthroplasty as per institutional
      protocol. This will be covered by the patient's health insurance. Subjects will be assigned a
      unique identification number. The principal investigators will maintain a list identifying
      all subjects by their subject identification number and initials. Subjects will be screened
      at the time of scheduling surgery in the outpatient clinic. Study procedures and information
      regarding the nature of the study will be reviewed with potential subjects, and written
      informed consent will be obtained prior to any study-related procedures. Alternatively,
      patients may be contacted by phone regarding the study. In this case, the study information
      will be reviewed with the subject over the phone and subjects will be asked to electronically
      sign a consent form sent via e-mail. Patients will be given a flyer when they are booked for
      surgery which will briefly outline our study and inform them that they may be contact about
      the study via telephone. The phone consent will be performed by one of the primary or
      co-investigators listed on this study. Adobe E-sign software will be used to send subjects a
      consent form via e-mail after the phone conversation. The patient will be given an
      opportunity to review the consent document and then the investigator will place a second call
      to the subject to review any questions or concerns. The subject and the investigator will the
      electronically sign the consent in succession. The Adobe E-signature software provides a date
      and time stamp. After the consent is signed by both parties the subject will be provided a
      copy of the signed consent by email. A copy of the consent will be maintained in a secure
      network drive provided by Albany Medical Center which will be accessible by the investigators
      listed on the study. A printed copy of the signed consent will be placed into the patients
      chart on the date of surgery. A second printed copy will be placed in a locked file cabinet
      in the preoperative unit at Albany Medical Center. All patients will have the right to
      voluntarily withdraw from the study. Any intra-operative or post-operative adverse events
      prior to discharge from the hospital will be recorded.

      Other screening procedures are as follows:

      i. Review inclusion and exclusion criteria. ii. Collect demographic information including
      age, sex, weight, height, BMI, American Society of Anesthesiology status, co-morbidities, and
      medication use.

      iii. Record medical history. iv. Collect baseline data with regards to pre-operative
      hematocrit, creatinine levels, and coagulation profile.

      All patients will have combined spinal with 0.75% bupivacaine heavy with lumbar and sacral
      plexus blocks. The total hip arthroplasties will be performed through a direct anterior
      approach. A closed suction drain will be placed intra-operatively and daily outputs measured
      will be recorded. The drain will be clamped in all patients for 1 hour in the immediate
      post-operative period after wound closure. For group B, the drain will be clamped after 1
      gram tranexamic acid is injected through the drain following completion of wound closure.
      Blood transfusion postoperatively will be dictated by the institutional policy of
      post-operative hemoglobin concentration of &lt;7 g/dl or hematocrit of &lt;21 or when patients
      developed any anemia-related organ dysfunction such as alteration of mental status,
      respiratory distress, or palpitations. The total blood loss will be calculated using a
      modification of the Gross formula where, if a reinfusion or an allogeneic transfusion was
      performed, the total blood loss will be equal to the loss calculated from the change in the
      hematocrit plus the volume transfused 20-22.

      Prophylaxis against venous thromboembolism will be administered according to standard
      practice at our center which includes anti-embolic stockings, intermittent pneumatic
      compression, and early physical therapy on the day after surgery, aspirin 325 milligrams
      twice daily started on first post-operative day and continued at discharge. Analgesic
      irrigation with 7.5 ml of 1% Ropivacaine, 0.25 ml of Epinephrine 1mg/1ml, 1 ml of Morphine
      10mg/ml, 1 ml of Ketorolac 30mg/ml, 1 ml of methylprednisolone acetate 40mg/ml, and 60 ml of
      normal saline will be administered for wound infiltration in the peri-capsular tissues prior
      to closure unless the patient possesses allergies to any of the aforementioned medications.
      Post-operatively, all patients (Groups, A, B, and C) will receive standard post-operative
      analgesic medications. All patients will be discharged with pregabalin 75 mg twice daily
      (BID), celecoxib 200 mg BID, Oxycodone/acetaminophen 5/325 mg to take 1-2 tabs every four
      hours as needed for pain control, and aspirin 325 mg BID for thromboprophylaxis unless they
      possess allergies to the aforementioned medications.

      Duration of the study The proposed data collection period of this study is two years.
      Patients will not be brought back for follow-up beyond their normal post-operative visit
      schedule. They will be seen earlier if any complications arise. During their visits metrics
      that will be specifically assessed include wound infections rates and incidences of deep vein
      thrombosis/ pulmonary thromboembolism (DVT/PE). Emergency department visits and readmissions,
      if any, will be recorded.

      Withdrawal

      Any of the subjects may withdraw from the study at any time without prejudice. However, every
      attempt should be made to encourage subjects to complete the study. If a subject discontinues
      from the study, the reason given must be fully evaluated and recorded appropriately in source
      documentation and the electronic health record. If the subject is withdrawn because of an
      adverse event (AE), that AE must be indicated as the reason for withdrawal. The investigator
      can discontinue a subject at any time if medically necessary. The primary investigator may
      replace subjects that are withdrawn. In addition, subjects meeting the following criteria
      must be withdrawn from the study:

        -  Occurrence of any adverse event (AE), post-operative bleeding complications requiring
           return to operating room or a vascular intervention radiology procedure, or laboratory
           abnormality which, in the opinion of the primary investigator, warrants the subject's
           permanent withdrawal from the study;

        -  Subject noncompliance, defined as refusal or inability to adhere to the study schedule;

        -  At the request of the subject, primary investigator, or regulatory authority

        -  Subject is lost to follow-up.

      C. Subject Population The subjects will be male and female patients of the principal
      orthopedic surgeon's practice who are eligible for unilateral anterior total hip
      arthroplasty. They must meet the above stated inclusion criteria and be willing to
      participate in the study and receive any of the three routes of tranexamic acid. They will be
      preoperatively evaluated for medical clearance by either their primary care physician and/or
      cardiologist as they otherwise would regardless of study inclusion.

      D. Study Location The study will be conducted at Albany Medical Center, 43 New Scotland
      Avenue, Albany New York, Zip 12208, (Phone: 518-262-4000) and Bone and Joint Center, 1367
      Washington Avenue, Albany New York, 12206 (Phone 518-489-2666).

      E. Data analysis All data metrics including demographic variables and primary and secondary
      endpoints will be tabulated in to an excel spreadsheet (Microsoft Inc., Redmond, WA). Data
      analysis will be performed using software GraphPad Prism (GraphPad Software Inc., CA).
      Quantitative data will be analyzed using non-directional analysis of variance (ANOVA) with
      Tukey's test for multiple comparisons. Non-normality or heteroscedasticity of data will
      either be corrected by transformation or a non-parametric (Kruskal Wallis) test will be used.
      Data will be presented as mean and standard deviation if normal or median and interquartile
      range if not. Categorical data will be analyzed using chi-square tests (or Fisher's exact
      test if any cells expected value is 5 or less). A p-value &lt;0.05 will be considered
      statistically significant. Risks of total hip arthroplasty, equally applicable to all
      participants in the study, include intra-operative fracture, post-operative infection,
      deep-vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, post-operative hip pain, and need for future
      surgery. Complications associated with the use of tranexamic acid include unforeseen allergic
      complications.

      G. Benefits The primary advantage, which study subjects may derive from being a part of this
      study include considerable improvements in blood loss in the immediate peri-operative period.
      The benefit expected for study subjects enrolled in this study may include a reduction in
      length of stay, fewer blood transfusions, and earlier achievement of rehabilitative outcomes.

      H. Confidentiality All primary data, or copies thereof (e.g., laboratory records, data
      sheets, correspondence, photographs, and computer records), which are a result of the
      original observations and activities of the study and are necessary for the reconstruction
      and evaluation of any study report, will be retained by the Principal Investigator. Data
      sources will be Albany Medical Center Sorian electronic health record and from Electronic
      health records (EHR) at Bone and Joint Center. The results from screening and data collected
      during the study will be recorded in the electronic health records and/or source documents,
      as appropriate, for each subject. To maintain confidentiality, the subjects will be
      identified by numbers and/or initials on the electronic health records. Beginning on the day
      of surgery, all patients included in the study will be given a number associated with a
      randomly assigned opaque envelope. The only association between patients and their assigned
      numbers will be stored in the principal investigator's locked file cabinet in the locked
      office. However, as an inpatient, all data will be stored under the patient's name in the
      medical record in standard fashion. After discharge, data will be copied onto a file by one
      of the co-investigators and stored under the patient's confidential number. From this point
      on, all data identifying information will be de-identified from the patient.

      I. Options Since intraoperative tranexamic acid use has been shown to be standard of care,
      option of not using tranexamic acid increases the risks of bleeding and post-operative blood
      transfusions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative drain output</measure>
    <time_frame>Drain output will be measured in milliliters on Post-operative Day 1 following total hip arthroplasty . This will be a one time measurement for every participant enrolled in the study.</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured from the drain output recorded over 24 hours on Post-operative day 1. This is a one time measurement for every participant enrolled in to the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in post operative hemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operative day 1 and day 2 hemoglobin change compared to pre-operative hemoglobin.</time_frame>
    <description>calculated from change in pre-op and post operative hemoglobin measured in g/dl. There will be 2 recordings for every participant enrolled in the study for the entire study period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Allogeneic blood transfusion rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured in the number of participants had transfusion during first week following total hip arthroplasty</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in the number of participants who received a blood transfusion during the hospital stay following total hip arthroplasty</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>Number of readmissions and emergency department visits measured in number of patients who were readmitted or visited the emergency department during first 90 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of times participants were admitted after the surgery within 90 days after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured in number of days patient stayed in the hospital following total hip arthroplasty. This will be one measurement for each participant in the study within 1 week after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days the patient spent in the hospital after total hip arthroplasty</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DVT</measure>
    <time_frame>Incidence of deep vein thrombosis measured in number of patients having this complication during first 90 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of DVT among participants enrolled in the study occurring with 90 days of surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Wound infection rates measured in number of cases occuring within first 90 days after total hip arthroplasty.</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of superficial and deep wound infection among participants enrolled in the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency department visits</measure>
    <time_frame>Number of times participants visited the emergency department after discharge from the hospital within 90 days after total hip arthroplasty</time_frame>
    <description>Number of times participants visited the emergency department after discharge from the hospital within 90 days after total hip arthroplasty</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary Thromboembolism</measure>
    <time_frame>Incidence of Pulmonary thromboembolism measured in number of patients having this complication during first 90 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of Pulmonary thromboembolism among participants enrolled in the study occurring with 90 days of surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of units of blood transfused</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured in the number of units of blood transfusion the participants received during the first week following total hip arthroplasty.</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in the number of units of blood transfusion each participant received a blood transfusion during their hospital stay following total hip arthroplasty.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in post operative hematocrit compared to pre-operative hematocrit</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operative day 1 and day 2 hematocrit change compared to pre-operative hematocrit.</time_frame>
    <description>calculated from change in pre-op and post op hematocrit measured in percentage. There will be 2 recordings for every participant enrolled in the study for the entire study period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">114</enrollment>
  <condition>Tranexamic Acid Adverse Reaction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group A: Intravenous Tranexamic acid at a dose of 1 gram administered 30 min prior to skin incision and 1 gram 3 hours after the procedure. (Total dose administered is 2 grams)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group B: Topical Tranexamic acid at a dose of 1 gram injected in to the periarticular tissues prior to closure and 1 gram injected into the joint through the drain following wound closure. (Total dose administered is 2 grams)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group C: Combined Intravenous 1 gram given intravenous 30 min prior to skin incision and topical tranexamic acid (1 gram) injected in to the periarticular tissues prior to closure. (Total dose administered is 2 grams)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tranexamic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>intravenous versus Intraarticular versus intravenous</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        To be eligible to participate in the study, subjects must meet the following criteria:

          1. Males or females age &gt; 18 years and &lt;80 years

          2. Informed consent

          3. Diagnosis of primary osteoarthritis or osteonecrosis

          4. Previous history of contralateral hip or knee arthroplasty will not be excluded from
             the study Exclusion criteria

        Subjects who meet any of the following criteria will NOT be eligible to participate in the
        study:

          1. Unable to comply with study requirements i.e unable to complete first follow-up visit
             at 4 weeks or if they are unable to follow-up.

          2. Has an active joint infection\

          3. Immuno-suppression, e.g., human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection, s/p organ
             transplantation, receipt of steroids for &gt; 10 days at &gt; 10 mg of prednisone equivalent
             daily within the 90 days prior to enrollment

          4. Chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) or hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection

          5. Body mass index &gt; 45

          6. Life expectancy &lt; 6 months

          7. Renal insufficiency (serum creatinine &gt;2.5 mg/dl)

          8. Pre-operative Hemoglobin &lt;8 gm/dl

          9. Congenital and acquired coagulopathy

         10. Patients on pre-operative therapeutic anticoagulation

         11. Patients who need post-operative therapeutic anticoagulation

         12. Pregnancy and nursing mothers or women who are expected to nurse their babies within
             one month of surgery

         13. History of thromboembolism, stroke, transient ischemic attack, traumatic brain injury,
             subdural, or subarachnoid hemorrhage

         14. History of reported allergy to tranexamic acid

         15. Uncontrolled Hypertension

         16. Non-steroidal antiinflammatory use within 3 weeks of surgery other than Celebrex.

         17. Patients who continue the use of aspirin and have not stopped for more than 7 days
             prior to surgery.

         18. Patients who need to be on any anticoagulation other than aspirin 325 mg BID will be
             excluded from the study.

         19. Prisoners will be excluded from the study.

         20. Patients with history of acquired defective color vision

         21. Plan for staged bilateral total hip procedures within 14 days

         22. Family history of thromboembolism

         23. Patient unable to receive spinal anesthesia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ravneet S Bhullar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Albany Medcial Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Samik Banerjee, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>908-376-8990</phone>
    <email>banerjs1@mail.amc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albany Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albany</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>12208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Samik Banerjee, MBBS</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ravneet Bhullar, MD</last_name>
      <email>bhullar@amc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kurtz S, Ong K, Lau E, Mowat F, Halpern M. Projections of primary and revision hip and knee arthroplasty in the United States from 2005 to 2030. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2007 Apr;89(4):780-5.</citation>
    <PMID>17403800</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carling MS, Jeppsson A, Eriksson BI, Brisby H. Transfusions and blood loss in total hip and knee arthroplasty: a prospective observational study. J Orthop Surg Res. 2015 Mar 28;10:48. doi: 10.1186/s13018-015-0188-6.</citation>
    <PMID>25889413</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kasparek MF, Faschingbauer M, Waldstein W, Boettner CS, Boettner F. Topical Tranexamic Acid is Equivalent to Targeted Preoperative Autologous Blood Donation in Total Hip Arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2017 Apr;32(4):1176-1179. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2016.10.026. Epub 2016 Oct 31.</citation>
    <PMID>27913130</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Shang J, Wang H, Zheng B, Rui M, Wang Y. Combined intravenous and topical tranexamic acid versus intravenous use alone in primary total knee and hip arthroplasty: A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Int J Surg. 2016 Dec;36(Pt A):324-329. doi: 10.1016/j.ijsu.2016.11.033. Epub 2016 Nov 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27856355</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moskal JT, Capps SG. Meta-analysis of Intravenous Tranexamic Acid in Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty. Orthopedics. 2016 Sep 1;39(5):e883-92. doi: 10.3928/01477447-20160526-02. Epub 2016 Jun 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27248332</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Anand A, Melvin JS. Tranexamic Acid in Hip and Knee Arthroplasty. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2016 Jun;24(6):e59. doi: 10.5435/JAAOS-D-15-00708.</citation>
    <PMID>27135795</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wei Z, Liu M. The effectiveness and safety of tranexamic acid in total hip or knee arthroplasty: a meta-analysis of 2720 cases. Transfus Med. 2015 Jun;25(3):151-62. doi: 10.1111/tme.12212. Epub 2015 May 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26033447</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wang C, Xu GJ, Han Z, Ma JX, Ma XL, Jiang X, Wang Y. Topical application of tranexamic acid in primary total hip arthroplasty: a systemic review and meta-analysis. Int J Surg. 2015 Mar;15:134-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ijsu.2014.12.023. Epub 2015 Jan 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25576011</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wu YG, Zeng Y, Yang TM, Si HB, Cao F, Shen B. The Efficacy and Safety of Combination of Intravenous and Topical Tranexamic Acid in Revision Hip Arthroplasty: A Randomized, Controlled Trial. J Arthroplasty. 2016 Nov;31(11):2548-2553. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2016.03.059. Epub 2016 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>27179770</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Poeran J, Rasul R, Suzuki S, Danninger T, Mazumdar M, Opperer M, Boettner F, Memtsoudis SG. Tranexamic acid use and postoperative outcomes in patients undergoing total hip or knee arthroplasty in the United States: retrospective analysis of effectiveness and safety. BMJ. 2014 Aug 12;349:g4829. doi: 10.1136/bmj.g4829.</citation>
    <PMID>25116268</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Madsen RV, Nielsen CS, Kallemose T, Husted H, Troelsen A. Low Risk of Thromboembolic Events After Routine Administration of Tranexamic Acid in Hip and Knee Arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2017 Apr;32(4):1298-1303. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2016.10.015. Epub 2016 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>27843042</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hanna SA, Prasad A, Lee J, Achan P. Topical Versus Intravenous Administration of Tranexamic Acid in Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials. Orthop Rev (Pavia). 2016 Sep 19;8(3):6792. eCollection 2016 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>27761223</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chen Y, Chen Z, Cui S, Li Z, Yuan Z. Topical versus systemic tranexamic acid after total knee and hip arthroplasty: A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Medicine (Baltimore). 2016 Oct;95(41):e4656. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27741100</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hallstrom B, Singal B, Cowen ME, Roberts KC, Hughes RE. The Michigan Experience with Safety and Effectiveness of Tranexamic Acid Use in Hip and Knee Arthroplasty. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2016 Oct 5;98(19):1646-1655.</citation>
    <PMID>27707851</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Li J, Zhang Z, Chen J. Comparison of efficacy and safety of topical versus intravenous tranexamic acid in total hip arthroplasty: A meta-analysis. Medicine (Baltimore). 2016 Sep;95(36):e4689. doi: 10.1097/MD.0000000000004689.</citation>
    <PMID>27603364</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Babis GC. Controversy in Tranexamic Acid Administration Route Continues: Commentary on an article by Zeng Yi, MD, et al.: &quot;Tranexamic Acid Administration in Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty: A Randomized Controlled Trial of Intravenous Combined with Topical Versus Single-Dose Intravenous Administration&quot;. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2016 Jun 15;98(12):e51. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.16.00128.</citation>
    <PMID>27307369</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yi Z, Bin S, Jing Y, Zongke Z, Pengde K, Fuxing P. Tranexamic Acid Administration in Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty: A Randomized Controlled Trial of Intravenous Combined with Topical Versus Single-Dose Intravenous Administration. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2016 Jun 15;98(12):983-91. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.15.00638.</citation>
    <PMID>27307358</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kang JS, Moon KH, Kim BS, Yang SJ. Topical administration of tranexamic acid in hip arthroplasty. Int Orthop. 2017 Feb;41(2):259-263. doi: 10.1007/s00264-016-3195-2. Epub 2016 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>27087627</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>North WT, Mehran N, Davis JJ, Silverton CD, Weir RM, Laker MW. Topical vs Intravenous Tranexamic Acid in Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty: A Double-Blind, Randomized Controlled Trial. J Arthroplasty. 2016 Apr;31(4):928-9. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2015.12.001. Epub 2015 Dec 17.</citation>
    <PMID>26783121</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>North WT, Mehran N, Davis JJ, Silverton CD, Weir RM, Laker MW. Topical vs Intravenous Tranexamic Acid in Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty: A Double-Blind, Randomized Controlled Trial. J Arthroplasty. 2016 May;31(5):1022-6. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2015.11.003. Epub 2015 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26703193</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gross JB. Estimating allowable blood loss: corrected for dilution. Anesthesiology. 1983 Mar;58(3):277-80.</citation>
    <PMID>6829965</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nadler SB, Hidalgo JH, Bloch T. Prediction of blood volume in normal human adults. Surgery. 1962 Feb;51(2):224-32.</citation>
    <PMID>21936146</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Liu X, Zhang X, Chen Y, Wang Q, Jiang Y, Zeng B. Hidden blood loss after total hip arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2011 Oct;26(7):1100-5.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2010.11.013. Epub 2011 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21256705</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 15, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 27, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Albany Medical College</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Samik Banerjee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Division of Orthopaedic Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

