<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03352921</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EMU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03352921</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy Of Clinical Pilates Exercises İn Desk-Based Workers With Sagital Cervical Disorientation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy Of Clinical Pilates Exercises İn Desk-Based Workers With Sagital Cervical Disorientation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eastern Mediterranean University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eastern Mediterranean University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to compare the effects of clinical pilates exercises and home
      exercise program on postural disorders, pain intensity, normal range of motion, muscle
      strength, endurance, muscle shortness, joint position sense and functional status in desk
      workers with sagittal cervical disorientation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postural Disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>eigth weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The evaluation of cervical and upper thoracic posture will be done through the lateral photography. A camera placed on the tripod will be placed 1,5 m away from the patient while standing in a standing position, and the lens of the camera corresponds to the shoulder of the person. Before the patients will be asked to be on their neutral position, they will be asked to move their heads forth and back for the three times and leave their two arms loose next to the body. Angular calculations will be done by attaching reflective markers to their anatomical points of T4 spinosus process, C7 spinosus process, tragus and eye canthus before the photography. Computer program (Markus Bader-MB Software Solutions, triangular screen ruler) will be used for the angular calculations (craniovertebral angle, head tilt angle, cervico-thoracic angle).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cervical Joint Position Sense</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>In order to determine cervical joint position sense, the individual's head will be brought to the target position by the investigator and held for 2 seconds at this position. The individual will be ask to save this position into their minds as it will be remembered later on. Again initial position(0°) will be turned here 10 seconds waiting will be and then in the same position (target position) he or she will be asked to move forward slowly and wait for 2 seconds in the same location. The angular difference between result value and target value will be recorded by reading from the baseline inclinometer. 30 seconds break will be given between measurements (flexion, extension, lateral flexion and rotation). The target position determined for the evaluation of joint position sense of neck flexion and extension is determined as 30°, for left-right lateral flexion is 20° and 30° for left-right rotation. All the tests will be done both eyes open and closed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Normal Motion of Cervical Joint</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The cervical normal joint movement will be evaluated by baseline bubble inclinometer. The validity and reliability of the device has been proven and; the active cervical normal joint movements (flexion, extension, left-right lateral flexion, left-right rotation) will be measured.. During sitting, in order to prevent regional movement, the body will be stabilized to the chair with the help of stabilization belt. For each movement, 3 measurements will be done and the best value will be used for the data analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Hand Held Dynamometer (HHD) will be used for isometric muscle strength measurement of neck muscles. Cervical flexor, extensor, left and right lateral flexors' isometric muscle strength will be evaluated by the dynamometer.Stabilizer Pressure Biofeedback device will be used for muscle strength measurement of M.Longus Kolli, M.Longus Capitis, M. Rectus Capitis Lateralis and M. Rectus Capitis Anterior which are defined as deep cervical flexor muscles.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>muscle endurance</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>With the aim of measuring the endurance of neck flexor muscles, the individuals will be asked to lie in the supine position as hands on the abdomen and knees in 90 degrees flexion. 0.5 kg of weight will be placed to the forehead of the patient with the help of a band put above the ears. First the patients will be asked to make cervical retraction and then make a cervical flexion in 10 degrees and the flexion degree will be determined with the help of goniometer.For the evaluation of neck extensor muscle endurance, the individuals will be asked to come up to the chest line and hang their head from the bed while the arms are lying on the side of the body beside the body. There will be weights placed above the ears; 2 kg for women and 4 kg for men.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Sagital Cervical Disorientation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>clinical pilates exercises</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental group will receive clinical pilates exercise training in group form for 3 weeks a week for 8 weeks. The training will be done 40-50 minutes per one day. The exercise session will be started with a 10 minute warming program, 30 minutes with the core stabilization training and the clinical pilates exercises with the postural alignment exercises will be applied and the exercise session will be ended with the 10 minutes cooling period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home exercises program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>For 8 weeks the member in comparison group will be ask to do the exercise program 3 days a week at home. This group will receive a program of stretching, strengthening, and posture exercises. All the exercises in the program will be illustrated on a descriptive form with images. In terms of the follow-up during 8-week duration, the individuals will be called frequently and in the interview by the end of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>clinical pilates exercises</intervention_name>
    <description>servikal, deep flexor muscles, posture exercsises</description>
    <arm_group_label>clinical pilates exercises</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>exercise program</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>home exercises program</intervention_name>
    <description>stretching, strengthening, and posture exercises to reduce functional disability, to relieve the pain and to provide postural straightening.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home exercises program</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>classical exercises</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Neck pain at least for three months,

          -  Anterior head translation of sagittal segmental alignment disorders,

          -  Craniovertebral angle as &lt;50 degree,

          -  Desk-work minimum for 3 years,

          -  Working with the computer daily at least for 5 hours,

          -  Less severe physical activity level according to the International Physical Activity
             Questionnaire.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Taken any physiotherapy program for the last 6 months due to neck or back pain
             complain,

          -  Pain severe 3 cm or less according to the Visual Analog Scale (VAS),

          -  Structural scoliosis,

          -  Broken neck history

          -  Rheumatic disorder that affects the neck,

          -  Acute torticollis,

          -  Vertebral column surgical history,

          -  Spinal cord compression due to tumor or other reasons,

          -  Neurological deficit,

          -  Temporomandibular joint problem,

          -  Taking any kind of pain killers except for basic analgesics.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>CEMALİYE HÜRER</last_name>
    <phone>05338759874</phone>
    <email>cemohurer@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>ENDER ANGIN</last_name>
    <phone>+003926303067</phone>
    <email>ender.angin@emu.edu.tr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eastern Mediterranean University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Famagusta</city>
        <zip>99450</zip>
        <country>Cyprus</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cemaliye Hürer, pt</last_name>
      <phone>05338759874</phone>
      <email>cemohurer@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Cyprus</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 22, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 24, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Eastern Mediterranean University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cemaliye Hürer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PHYSİOTHERAPİST</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>clinical pilates</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Sagital Cervical Disorientation</keyword>
  <keyword>Disorientation</keyword>
  <keyword>Forward Head Posture</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Confusion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

