<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03351725</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0709323371</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03351725</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Peripheral Venous Catheter Colonization Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>IPICCS</acronym>
  <official_title>Incidence of Peripheral Intravenous Cannula Colonization in a Swedish County Hospital</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Linkoeping University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Linkoeping University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Peripheral intravenous cannulas (PIVCs) are utilized in large scale in modern health care.
      Known complications due to a PIVC are phlebitis, thrombosis, bleeding, nerve damage and
      infection. PIVC-related infection causes morbidity, mortality and increased healthcare costs.
      PIVC-related infections can and should be prevented.

      Indwell time is a known risk factor for PIVC-related infection. Another factor potentially
      influencing the risk of developing PIVC-related infection is what type of PIVC that is being
      used. Roughly there are two types of PIVCs. One with an open injection valve and another with
      a closed injection valve. The former being far more used in our hospital and the latter being
      suggested as lowering the risk of PIVC-related infection compared to the open one.

      The investigators aim with this study is to evaluate the incidence of PIVC-colonization in
      300 patients at our 500-bed secondary level hospital in Sweden, as a first step in trying to
      understand what healthcare-providers can improve regarding prevention of PIVC-related
      infections.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Peripheral intravenous cannulas (PIVCs) are utilized in large scale in modern health care.
      Known complications due to a PIVC are phlebitis, thrombosis, bleeding, nerve damage and
      infection. PIVC-related infection causes morbidity, mortality and increased healthcare costs.
      In an Australian study the investigators found the presence of a PIVC the most frequent cause
      (36%) of healthcare-associated Staphylococcus aureus bacteraemia during 2012. PIVC-related
      infections can and should be prevented.

      Indwell time is a known risk factor for PIVC-related infection. Another factor potentially
      influencing the risk of developing PIVC-related infection is what type of PIVC that is being
      used. Roughly there are two types of PIVCs. One with an open injection valve and another with
      a closed injection valve. The former being far more used in Ryhov County Hospital, Sweden,
      and the latter being suggested as lowering the risk of PIVC-related infection compared to the
      open one.

      In a systematic review from 2006 Maki et al report a point incidence of blood stream
      infections of 0,5 per 1000 catheter-days in PIVCs. In 2014 Hammarskjöld reported an incidence
      of 0,6 per 1000 catheter-days regarding central venous catheters (CVC). Maki et al concludes
      &quot;…, infection control programs must strive to consistently apply essential control measures
      and preventive technologies with all types of intravascular devices.&quot; The investigators find
      there is a gap between the large scale utilization of PIVCs and the knowledge about
      PIVC-related infections and recommendations on how to prevent them. Hammarskjöld et al has
      done research on infections related to CVCs, subcutaneous venous ports and on arterial
      cannulas but not PIVCs.

      The aim with this study is to evaluate the incidence of PIVC-colonization at Ryhov County
      Hospital, a 500-bed secondary level hospital in Sweden, as a first step in trying to
      understand what can be done to improve work regarding prevention of PIVC-related infections.

      Materials and methods

      Setting The hospital is a 500-bed general county hospital including most medical, oncological
      and surgical specialties except neurosurgery and cardiac surgery. No solid organ or stem cell
      transplantations are performed.

      Patients Patients admitted to surgical, medical or infectious wards were regularly included
      by a specifically trained nurse from June 2016 until December 2017.

      Inclusion criteria: Patients ≥ 18 years of age with a PIVC in situ for 48 hours or more
      informed verbally and in written and invited to take part in the study. Exclusion criteria:
      Patients &lt; 18 years of age.

      Microbiological methods Intraluminal hub culturing from the two injection sites of the PIVC
      performed with sterile cotton-tipped applicators moistened with sterile sodium chloride 0,9
      %. Swabs transported in Amies medium with charcoal. Identification performed by standard
      methods at our local microbiology laboratory (www.srga.org.accessed _ http://
      www.srga.org.accessed/ _ January 1, 2007).

      Statistics Descriptive. How many positive cultures and which type of microbes were found.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive culture</measure>
    <time_frame>2-7 days</time_frame>
    <description>Swab from peripheral venous catheter (PVC) in situ on patient having had the PVC for 48 hours or more.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Catheters, Indwelling</condition>
  <condition>Catheter-Related Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peripheral venous catheter indwell time more than 48 hours</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>peripheral venous catheter (PVC)</intervention_name>
    <description>No intervention is made only in situ swab from the PVC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peripheral venous catheter indwell time more than 48 hours</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Setting The hospital is a 500-bed general county hospital including most medical,
        oncological and surgical specialties except neurosurgery and cardiac surgery. No solid
        organ or stem cell transplantations are performed. Patients Patients admitted to surgical,
        medical or infectious wards were regularly included by a specifically trained nurse from
        June 2016 until December 2017.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older hospitalized in Ryhov County Hosptial, Sweden, with perhiperal
             venous catheter in situ for 48 hours or more.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Under 18 years of age.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Boel Andersson Gäre, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Linkoeping University, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sören Berg, Associate Professor</last_name>
    <phone>+46702322963</phone>
    <email>soren.berg@regionostergotland.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David Juhlin, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+4636329301</phone>
    <phone_ext>+46709323371</phone_ext>
    <email>johan.david.juhlin@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ryhov County Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jönköping</city>
        <state>Småland</state>
        <zip>55305</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Juhlin, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+46709323371</phone>
      <email>johan.david.juhlin@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Knut Taxbro, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+46706753457</phone>
      <email>knut.taxbro@rjl.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rhodes D, Cheng AC, McLellan S, Guerra P, Karanfilovska D, Aitchison S, Watson K, Bass P, Worth LJ. Reducing Staphylococcus aureus bloodstream infections associated with peripheral intravenous cannulae: successful implementation of a care bundle at a large Australian health service. J Hosp Infect. 2016 Sep;94(1):86-91. doi: 10.1016/j.jhin.2016.05.020. Epub 2016 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>27346623</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>González López JL, Arribi Vilela A, Fernández del Palacio E, Olivares Corral J, Benedicto Martí C, Herrera Portal P. Indwell times, complications and costs of open vs closed safety peripheral intravenous catheters: a randomized study. J Hosp Infect. 2014 Feb;86(2):117-26. doi: 10.1016/j.jhin.2013.10.008. Epub 2013 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24373830</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Maki DG, Kluger DM, Crnich CJ. The risk of bloodstream infection in adults with different intravascular devices: a systematic review of 200 published prospective studies. Mayo Clin Proc. 2006 Sep;81(9):1159-71. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16970212</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hammarskjöld F, Berg S, Hanberger H, Taxbro K, Malmvall BE. Sustained low incidence of central venous catheter-related infections over six years in a Swedish hospital with an active central venous catheter team. Am J Infect Control. 2014 Feb;42(2):122-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ajic.2013.09.023.</citation>
    <PMID>24485369</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mermel LA. Short-term Peripheral Venous Catheter-Related Bloodstream Infections: A Systematic Review. Clin Infect Dis. 2017 Oct 30;65(10):1757-1762. doi: 10.1093/cid/cix562.</citation>
    <PMID>29020252</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 15, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 24, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Linkoeping University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Boel Andersson Gäre</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>peripheral venous catheter</keyword>
  <keyword>catheter colonization</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Catheter-Related Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No individual data, but the the data regarding positive Cultures and what type of microbia found will be official</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

