<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03355391</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BarretosCH-20172</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03355391</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characterization of Brazilian Colorectal Cancer Screening Population</brief_title>
  <official_title>Implementation of a Data System to Better Characterize Brazilian Colorectal Cancer Screening Population</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Barretos Cancer Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Barretos Cancer Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the third most common type of cancer among men and the second
      among women in Brazil. Despite the high incidence and significance of CRC in Brazil, very
      little is known about its prevalence among the asymptomatic population. Recently, a CRC
      screening program was implemented at the Cancer Hospital of Barretos. Characterization of the
      clinical findings detected in the screening population and the prevalence of basal CRC might
      contribute to better organization of the program and define the best strategy for a future
      national screening program. We hypothesize that recruitment and the early outcomes of our
      screening program based on the fecal immunochemical test (FIT) will differ from the outcomes
      corresponding to other populations due to sociodemographic differences. Aims: i. To implement
      a data collection and storage system for follow-up of the screening program participants and
      to measure early outcomes (adenoma, advanced adenoma and cancer) and associate them with
      sociodemographic risk factors; ii. to quantify the risk of CRC in the Brazilian population
      and to develop algorithms for risk stratification of CRC screening; and iii. to compare the
      risk stratification to other countries with low, medium and high incomes. Methods:
      Individuals aged 50 to 65 years will be included in the HCB screening program from November
      2017 to December 2018. The following data will be collected from all participants:
      sociodemographic and ethnic (skin color) characteristics; risk factors for CRC, such as
      smoking and drinking; comorbidities, including diabetes mellitus and arterial hypertension;
      and FIT, colonoscopy and histopathology examination results. Data collection will be
      performed using the REDCap data collection/database system. The risk score will be formulated
      using the Chi-square test (or Fisher's exact test) and simple logistic regression, and the
      regression coefficients will be calculated. Then, the model identified for the training
      sample will be replicated with a validation sample. The resulting score will be used to
      calculate the sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value, negative predictive value,
      accuracy, area under the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve and Kolmogorov D
      statistic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Variables and data collection Upon entry into the program, the following data will be
      collected from all participants: sociodemographic and ethnic (skin color) characteristics;
      risk factors for CRC, such as smoking and drinking; comorbidities, including diabetes
      mellitus and arterial hypertension; and the FIT, colonoscopy and histopathology examination
      results.

      Data collection will be performed using the REDCap electronic data capture tools hosted at
      Barretos Cancer Hospital (Paul et al., 2009). For this purpose, clinical forms were developed
      containing questions relative to the data to be analyzed in the present project.

      Colonoscopy procedure Colonoscopies will be performed according to the routine procedures of
      the Department of Prevention Endoscopy, HCB. Bowel preparation will begin on the eve of the
      test and will consist of a residue-free liquid diet and oral intake of 10 mg of bisacodyl (5
      mg/tablet, Boehringer Ingelheim do Brasil Química e Farmacêutica Ltda, São Paulo, Brazil) at
      2:00 and 6:00 pm. On the test day, preparation will begin 5 hours before the procedure and
      will consist of the oral intake of 500 ml of 20% mannitol.

      Prior to the colonoscopy, the patients will be sedated with fentanyl (0.05 mg/ml - Cristália
      Produtos Químicos Farmacêuticos Ltda, São Paulo, Brazil), midazolam (5 mg/5 ml - Produtos
      Roche Químicos e Farmacêuticos S.A., Rio de Janeiro, Brazil) and propofol (10 mg/ml -
      Cristália Produtos Químicos Farmacêuticos Ltda, São Paulo, Brazil) via the intravenous route.
      Then, a flexible endoscope will be introduced up to the cecum and terminal ileum.

      Oxygen will be supplied at a flow rate of 2 l/min throughout the procedure. The heart rate
      and oxygen saturation will be monitored. All tests will be performed using high-definition
      colonoscopes (Olympus 180), and CO2 insufflation will be performed by senior endoscopists
      with extensive experience in diagnostic colonoscopy.

      The following data will be recorded throughout the procedure: colonoscope introduction and
      withdrawal times; quality of bowel preparation according to the Boston scale; and location
      and characteristics of the detected lesions. Accurate reports of the study outcomes (adenoma,
      advanced adenoma and carcinoma), including the number, size and precise location, will have
      paramount importance. The detected lesions will be classified following the Paris
      classification (Paris Classification, 2002) as follows: type 0-I, polypoid (0-Is: sessile;
      0-Isp: sub-pedunculated; and 0-Ip: pedunculated) and type 0-II, non-polypoid (0-IIa: slightly
      elevated surface; 0-IIb: flat; 0-IIc: slightly depressed; and 0-III: excavated).

      Statistical analysis All statistical analyses will be performed using the SPSS software for
      Windows, version 21.0. In all cases, the significance level will be set to 0.05.

      The sample will be described in terms of the mean, standard deviation, minimum, maximum and
      quartiles for quantitative variables and through frequency tables in the case of qualitative
      variables.

      The risk score will be formulated as follows:

      The sample will be composed of individuals diagnosed or not with cancer. Individuals with
      adenoma or advanced adenoma and individuals without cancer will be excluded from the
      analysis. Cases with a negative FIT will be considered No Cancer. Cases with a positive FIT
      will be subjected to colonoscopy, the results of which will allow the classification of each
      participant as Cancer or No Cancer. The sample will be randomly divided into two groups. The
      first group will comprise 75% of the data and be named the training sample. The second group
      will comprise the remaining 25% of the data and be named the validation sample.

      The training sample will be used to develop the risk score. First, the relationship of all of
      the participants' characteristics with the outcomes (Cancer/No Cancer) will be investigated
      using the Chi-square test (or Fisher's exact test) and simple logistic regression. All
      characteristics with a p-value less than 0.2 in the previous assessment and other
      characteristics that the investigators judge relevant will be included in a multiple logistic
      regression model; then, the regression coefficients will be calculated.

      Next, the model identified for the training sample will be replicated with the validation
      sample; the resulting score will be used to calculate the sensitivity, specificity, positive
      predictive value, negative predictive value, accuracy, area under the receiver operating
      characteristic (ROC) curve and Kolmogorov D statistic.

      If the model is considered discriminant, nomograms will be plotted, and risk groups will be
      defined based on the risk score.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>colorectal cancer rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>number of participants with colorectal cancer diagnosed by colonoscopy after a positive fecal occult blood test (FIT)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Adenoma Colon</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Screening participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals aged 50 to 65 years who were included in the screening program of Cancer Hospital of Barretos</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The target population was invited to participate in the screening program of the Department
        of Prevention, HCB. Recruitment will be performed among individuals attending HCB for the
        prevention of tumors other than CRC, the population of Barretos, who may who may learn
        about the program through the media or friends spontaneously visiting HCB, and participants
        of the neighborhood mobile unit and &quot;door-to-door&quot; screening program in Barretos
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals aged 50 to 65 years who were included in the HCB screening program from
             November 2017 to December 2018.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of signs and symptoms of CRC (rectal bleeding, recent change of the bowel
             pattern, abdominal mass or anemia).

          -  Family history of CRC.

          -  Personal history of adenoma or CRC
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Denise Guimaraes, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Barretos Cancer Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Denise Guimaraes, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>551733216600</phone>
    <phone_ext>7267</phone_ext>
    <email>guimaraes.dp@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 22, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>SCREENING</keyword>
  <keyword>RISK FACTOR</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

