<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03351972</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STH20061</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03351972</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Differences in Preparation for Small Bowel Capsule Endoscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Bowel Preparation (Either as a Single or Divided Dose) Produce Better Cleansing and Diagnostic Yield Than no Preparation at All in Small Bowel Capsule Endoscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hotel Dieu Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The introduction of video capsule endoscopy in 2000 has provided a convenient and minimally
      invasive imaging method for the whole small bowel. Capsule Endoscopy is used to investigate a
      number of conditions such as obscure gastrointestinal bleeding, iron deficiency anaemia,
      inflammatory bowel disease, celiac disease, small bowel tumors, and hereditary polyposis
      syndromes. However, Capsule Endoscopy capsules are not able to suction fluid or wash the
      intestine, thus making it susceptible to decreased visualization quality and diagnostic yield
      due to dark intestinal contents or air bubbles. In order to determine the best method for
      bowel preparation before Capsule Endoscopy, this study seeks to determine in patients
      undergoing small intestine Capsule Endoscopy if split dose Polyethylene Glycol or single
      morning dose of Polyethylene Glycol have a benefit in Visualisation quality when compared to
      clear fluids only. A co-primary outcome will also be the diagnostic yield, as measured by the
      aggregate of all the active preparation groups compared to than clear fluids only group.
      Secondary outcome measures will include tolerance of preparations, cleanliness as assessed by
      a validated 4 point scale, distal small bowel visualization (the last 1/4 of small bowel
      examination by time) and small bowel transit time (measured as time from first duodenal image
      to first cecal image). Adult outpatients referred for small bowel video capsule endoscopy
      will be considered for the study and this will run in the clinical environment as per
      routine. Patients will have been referred for capsule endoscopy as per normal clinical
      practice so not additional procedure will take place. Patients will be randomly assigned to
      in a one to one fashion to one of three groups in order to explore whether bowel preparation
      (either as a single or divided dose) produce better cleansing and diagnostic yield than no
      preparation at all in small bowel capsule endoscopy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In order to determine the best method for bowel preparation before Capsule Endoscopy, this
      study seeks to determine in patients undergoing small intestine Capsule Endoscopy if split
      dose Polyethylene Glycol or single morning dose of Polyethylene Glycol have a benefit in
      Visualisation quality when compared to clear fluids only. A co-primary outcome will also be
      the diagnostic yield, as measured by the aggregate of all the active preparation groups
      compared to than clear fluids only group. Secondary outcome measures will include tolerance
      of preparations, cleanliness as assessed by a validated 4 point scale, distal small bowel
      visualization (the last 1/4 of small bowel examination by time) and small bowel transit time
      (measured as time from first duodenal image to first cecal image).

      Group Assignment:

      The groups will have some common instructions: all groups will be instructed to stop iron
      supplements five days prior to the exam. On the day prior to the exam, patients will be
      instructed to have a light breakfast and lunch, followed by only clear fluids. Over the day,
      patients will be encouraged to have at least two litres of clear fluids. On the day of the
      exam, 80 mg of oral simethicone will be given 10 minutes prior to the exam. The capsule will
      be ingested at 9:00am, after which fluids may be consumed 2 hours later, and solid food 4
      hours later. Patients will be randomly assigned to in a one to one fashion to one of three
      groups using a central online randomization program. The groups for this project include:

      A. Control: no additional instructions beyond those above will be given. B. Single dose
      Polyethylene Glycol: Patients will take 2 litre of Polyethylene Glycol at 6am the day of the
      exam.

      C. Split dose Polyethylene Glycol: Patients will take 1 litre of Polyethylene Glycol at 7pm
      the evening prior to the exam and 1 litre at 6am the day of the exam.

      Recruitment of patients will be performed from outpatient gastroenterology clinics at
      Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust. After a request for Capsule Endoscopy from a
      referring physician, the patient will be contacted by telephone by one of the Capsule
      endoscopy nurse specialists (who are also involved in the study) as per normal practice. The
      study will be discussed, the procedure explained and a convenient date for the procedure will
      be agreed with the patient. The patient will be invited to meet with one of the research
      staff at a mutually agreed time in order to go through the study once more and provide
      written consent should they agree to participate. Should they wish to participate but would
      prefer to complete a postal consent form, this will be arranged. The procedure will be
      completed according to normal practice. Patients will be advised that they can withdraw from
      the study at any point and choose a preferred option for bowel preparation
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 23, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician assessed Visual Quality of small bowel</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Visual quality of the small bowel during capsule endoscopy as assessed by a clinician</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>clinician assessed Diagnostic yield during capsule endoscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Ability to produce a diagnosis following capsule endoscopy as assessed by a clinician</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">230</enrollment>
  <condition>Capsule Endoscopy</condition>
  <condition>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Celiac Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bowel Prep routine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomised to this arm will receive their bowel prep (Klean Prep) with the routine guidance of taking the contents the day before their capsule endoscopy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bowel Prep Split</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomised to this arm will receive their bowel prep (Klean Prep) with the guidance stating to take the first dose the day before the capsule endoscopy and the second dose the morning of the capsule endoscopy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No bowel prep</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomised to this arm will be advised to drink clear liquids only ahead of their capsule endoscopy procedure</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Klean Prep</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomised to use polyethylene glycol will follow either routine guidance of taking the bowel prep the night before their capsule endoscopy or receive guidance that they should split their dose between the night before and the morning of the procedure</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bowel Prep routine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bowel Prep Split</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Polyethylene Glycol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clear liquids only</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants randomised to clear liquids only will receive guidance to only drink clear liquids before their procedure</description>
    <arm_group_label>No bowel prep</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult outpatients (18 years or older)

          -  routinely referred for small bowel video capsule endoscopy (CE)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  dysphagia

          -  severe gastroparesis requiring endoscopic placement of capsule

          -  small bowel obstruction

          -  pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark McAlindon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark McAlindon, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0114 2711899</phone>
    <email>Mark.McAlindon@sth.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Luke Barron, Mr</last_name>
    <phone>0114 2711899</phone>
    <email>Luke.Barron@sth.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hotel Dieu Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston,</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laurence Hookey, MD</last_name>
      <email>hookeyl@hdh.kari.net</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Hallamshire Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sheffield</city>
        <state>South Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>S10 2JF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luke Barron, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>0114 2711899</phone>
      <email>luke.barron@sth.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark McAlindon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laurence Hookey, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 21, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 24, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Celiac Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The study has been set-up and designed to ensure no IPD is shared</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

