<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03351010</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM98765432</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03351010</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mindfulness for Pain Management in Patients With Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Thai Buddhism-based Mindfulness for Pain Management in Thai Outpatients With Cancer: A Preliminary Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministry of Health, Thailand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Using pharmacologic agents are often effective to treat patients with cancer pain, but there
      are associated with serious side-effects and risks of dependence and addiction. The Thai
      Buddhism-based Mindfulness (TBbM) intervention created by a widely respected Buddhist monk
      focuses on testing a meditation technique to manage pain. If effective, millions of patients
      who suffer with cancer pain will benefit from use of a safe, culturally appropriate,
      non-pharmacologic approach to pain management.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cancer is leading cause of death in Thailand. One hundred and twenty-eight men and 83 women
      per 100,000 had a common consequence both of malignancy and its treatment. Pain is
      experienced by 62% of Thai patients with cancer. Cancer pain is a major health problem
      because it causes both physical and psychological suffering for millions of individuals.
      Although pharmacological/analgesic treatment is effective, adverse side effects are common.
      Internationally, mindfulness is being used as an effective non-pharmacological treatment for
      psychological problems including distress, anxiety, stress, depression, and to improve
      quality of life in patients with cancer. However, the effect of mindfulness on pain as the
      primary outcome has not been sufficiently investigated. A few randomized controlled trials
      provide evidence that mindfulness interventions influence pain intensity in patients with
      cancer pain, but culturally targeted interventions have not been tested. Therefore, the
      purpose of this research is to test the effect of the Thai Buddhism-based Mindfulness (TBbM)
      program for pain management in Thai outpatients. Using a randomized controlled trial design,
      the investigators will test theTBbM intervention to improve pain in Thai outpatients (N=160)
      with cancer who are receiving cancer care at Sawanpracharak Hospital, Thailand. The control
      group (n = 80) will receive usual care and participate in a one-hour video educational
      program about cancer pain. The intervention group (n = 80) will receive usual care,
      participate in a one-hour video educational program about cancer pain, and receive an 8-week
      TBbM intervention. Investigators will accomplish the overall objective by pursuing the
      following three specific aims: 1) to compare the effect of the TBbM intervention to that of
      usual care on worst pain severity (primary outcome) as measured by the Brief Pain Inventory
      Thai Version (BPI-T); 2) to compare the effect of the TBbM intervention to that of usual care
      on secondary outcomes (i.e., pain interference, average pain, anxiety and depression,
      mindfulness, locus of control, and QoL) as measured by the BPI-T, the Hospital Anxiety and
      Depression Scale Thai Version (HADS-T), the Mindfulness Assessment Scale Thai Version
      (MAS-T), the Beliefs in Pain Control Questionnaire Thai Version (BPCQ-T) and the Functional
      Assessment of Cancer Therapy-General-Thai Version (FACT-G-T); and 3) to explore the mediating
      effects of TBbM-induced changes in cognitive (locus of control) and psychological factors
      (anxiety and depression) on worst pain severity. The investigators posit that the TBbM
      intervention will be more effective than usual care in reducing pain (primary outcome) and
      improving pain interference, anxiety, depression, mindfulness, locus of control, and QoL
      (secondary outcomes). T-tests, analysis of covariance (ANOVA), and path analysis approaches
      will be used to evaluate TBbM outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 10, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Using a randomized controlled trial design, the investigators will test theTBbM intervention to improve pain in Thai outpatients (N=160) with cancer who are receiving cancer care at Sawanpracharak Hospital, Thailand. The control group (n = 80) will receive usual care and participate in a one-hour video educational program about cancer pain. The intervention group (n = 80) will receive usual care, participate in a one-hour video educational program about cancer pain, and receive an 8-week TBbM intervention.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Eligible patients will 1) have any cancer type or stage, 2) be 18-60 years of age, 3) have a worst pain score &gt; 4 in the past 7 days, 4) be able to read and write the Thai language, 5) have a Karnofsky Performance status &gt; 70%, and be willing to travel to the temple. Exclusion criteria will be any diagnosed psychiatric illness that would prevent the patient from giving informed consent or from participating fully in the study. Patients with comorbidities (e.g., arthritis, bone metastasis, deformity, certain neurologic conditions such as biracial plexus nerve compression) that would impair the ability to perform the hand and arm movements also are ineligible.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Change Over Time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 weeks and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Worst pain scores are measured by Brief Pain Inventory. The Brief Pain Inventory-Short Form asks about pain in general, pain location, pain intensity (worst, least, average, and present), and is scored on a numerical rating scale of 0 (no pain) to 10 (pain as bad as one can imagine.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Pain interference and average pain scores are measured by the Brief Pain Inventory</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety and depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety and depression scores are measured by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mindfulness</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Mindfulness scores are measured by the Mindfulness Assessment Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Locus of control</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Personal control scores are measured by the Beliefs in Pain Control Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life scores are measured by the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-General-Thai Version</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer, Metastatic</condition>
  <condition>Pain, Chronic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receiving education program and mindfulness training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receiving education program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness training program</intervention_name>
    <description>The mindfulness training program is a self-awareness mindfulness training program by performing the 15-position hand movement series</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cancer pain educational program</intervention_name>
    <description>A cancer pain education program by using Videos and personalized face-to-face techniques</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mindfulness</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Eligible patients will:

          -  have any cancer type or stage,

          -  be 18-60 years of age,

          -  have a worst pain score &gt; 4 in the past 7 days,

          -  be able to read and write the Thai language,

          -  have a Karnofsky Performance status &gt; 70%, and

          -  be willing to travel to the temple.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be diagnosed psychiatric illness

          -  Patients will have the comorbidities (e.g., arthritis, bone metastasis, deformity,
             certain neurological conditions such as Brachial plexus nerve compression)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ellen Smith, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>734-936-1267</phone>
    <email>ellenls@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Srisuda Ngamkham, PhD</last_name>
    <email>srisudan@umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sawanpracharak Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mueang</city>
        <state>Nakhonsawan</state>
        <zip>60000</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Srisuda Ngamkham, PhD.</last_name>
      <phone>+66-56-213741</phone>
      <email>nsrisuda05@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ellen Smith, PhD.</last_name>
      <phone>734-936-1267</phone>
      <email>ellenls@umich.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fish JA, Ettridge K, Sharplin GR, Hancock B, Knott VE. Mindfulness-based cancer stress management: impact of a mindfulness-based programme on psychological distress and quality of life. Eur J Cancer Care (Engl). 2014 May;23(3):413-21. doi: 10.1111/ecc.12136. Epub 2013 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24118428</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 16, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mindfulness, Cancer, Pain Management</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The individual data of the participants that we will collect are cancer data, treatment data, and a time period of mindfulness practice</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

