<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03350269</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Kidney Donor Lost Wages Study</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03350269</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Lost Wage Reimbursement to Kidney Donors on Living Donation Rates</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Effect of Lost Wage Reimbursement to Potential Kidney Donors On Living Donation Rates</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Arbor Research Collaborative for Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Laura and John Arnold Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American Society of Transplant Surgeons</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Arbor Research Collaborative for Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is designed as a randomized controlled trial. The investigators hypothesize that
      kidney transplant recipient candidates whose donors are offered reimbursement of lost wages
      (treatment arm) will have a higher probability of receiving a living donor kidney transplant
      than those randomized to no offer of lost wage reimbursement (control arm). The study expects
      to demonstrate incremental living donor kidney transplants by assisting individuals who wish
      to be living organ donors but would be otherwise unable to do so due to the obligatory
      forfeit of income during the evaluation, donation surgery, and post-operative recuperation
      periods.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Following confirmation of eligibility and written informed consent to participate in the
      study, kidney recipient candidates will be randomized at the time of their evaluation
      appointment to the treatment arm (donor eligible for reimbursement of lost wages) or the
      control arm (donor not eligible for reimbursement of lost wages).

      Consented, randomized recipients will be followed for up to one year from the baseline visit,
      with no required in-person visits beyond baseline. Data will be collected at baseline, six
      months after baseline, and one year after baseline. Demographic data (e.g. age, sex, race,
      ethnicity) will be collected on all recipients during screening and eligibility assessment.
      At baseline only, we will collect recipient household size, household income, and limited
      clinical data (on dialysis or not; date of dialysis initiation (if on dialysis); on deceased
      donor waiting list or not; date of wait-listing if on waiting list). At six months after
      baseline (and at one year after baseline, if applicable), we will collect recipient outcome
      data (date of receipt of living donor or deceased donor kidney transplant, if applicable;
      date of death, if applicable).

      Demographic data (e.g. age, sex, race, ethnicity), household size, and household income will
      be collected on all potential donors that come forward for participating recipients, ideally
      as soon as they are known to the participating transplant center, and no later than six
      months after baseline and one year after baseline, if applicable). Administrative and
      financial data will be required only from the subset of donors meeting all of the following
      criteria:

        -  Donors whose recipients are randomized to the treatment arm; AND

        -  Donors who will incur lost wages and wish to receive lost wage reimbursement

      A randomized controlled trial is the gold standard for program evaluation, since it allows
      for a statistical comparison of otherwise similar patients, and determination of a causal
      relationship between the intervention and the measured outcome. By comparing the outcomes of
      the control and treatment arms, we can determine whether the availability of reimbursement of
      lost wages for living donors increases the likelihood that the potential recipient will
      receive a living donor kidney within a year of their initial evaluation visit to a
      participating transplant center. We will also conduct secondary analyses of the timing of
      transplants and the demographics of the living donors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized controlled trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of offering wage reimbursement on rate of living donor kidney transplant</measure>
    <time_frame>One year from time zero</time_frame>
    <description>Number of kidney transplant recipient candidates in intervention vs. control group who receive a living door transplant within one year of their first visit to the participating transplant center for evaluation as a potential kidney transplant recipient (time zero)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in time to outcome events (living donor transplant, deceased donor transplant, removal from transplant waiting list, death) between control group and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>Time zero to one year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of offering donor wage reimbursement on demographic characteristics of living kidney donor pool</measure>
    <time_frame>Time zero to one year</time_frame>
    <description>Compare demographic characteristics of donors in the control and intervention arms 's living kidney donor pool with national living kidney donor characteristics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2750</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Failure</condition>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Renal Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Kidney transplant recipient candidates who are informed that their living donor candidates can receive reimbursement for lost wages incurred during the evaluation, donation surgery and recuperation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Kidney transplant recipient candidates who receive standard of care (donors are not offered wage reimbursement)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Information provision</intervention_name>
    <description>Kidney transplant recipients are informed that their donors may be eligible for lost wage reimbursement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥18 at enrollment

          -  Meet participating transplant center standards to initiate an evaluation to receive a
             kidney transplant

          -  Kidney-only or kidney intended to be followed by other organ (e.g. deceased donor
             pancreas)

          -  First-time recipient candidate

          -  Capable of providing informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kimberly A. Gifford, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>American Society of Transplant Surgeons</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Judd Kessler, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wharton School, University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert M. Merion, MD, FACS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Arbor Research Collaborative for Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amit K. Mathur, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Akinlolu O. Ojo, MD, PhD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arizona Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Peg Hill-Callahan, BS, LSW</last_name>
    <phone>734-369-9674</phone>
    <email>peg.hill-callahan@arborresearch.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Melissa Sexton, BBA, CCRP</last_name>
    <phone>734-369-9635</phone>
    <email>Melissa.Sexton@ArborResearch.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Colin Jenks</last_name>
      <phone>720-848-0833</phone>
      <email>COLIN.JENKS@UCDENVER.EDU</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Trevor Nydam, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michigan Medicine - University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Darlene McLean, RN, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>734-615-3822</phone>
      <email>darkons@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John C Magee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Eischen</last_name>
      <phone>612-626-2498</phone>
      <email>bengt008@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ty Dunn, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary Shaw, RN, BBA</last_name>
      <phone>215-614-0528</phone>
      <email>mary.shaw@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paige M Porrett, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Agerskov H, Ludvigsen MS, Bistrup C, Pedersen BD. From donation to everyday life: Living kidney donors' experiences three months after donation. J Ren Care. 2016 Mar;42(1):43-52. doi: 10.1111/jorc.12137. Epub 2015 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26463844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larson DB, Jacobs C, Berglund D, Wiseman J, Garvey C, Gillingham K, Ibrahim HN, Matas AJ. Return to normal activities and work after living donor laparoscopic nephrectomy. Clin Transplant. 2017 Jan;31(1). doi: 10.1111/ctr.12862. Epub 2016 Dec 22.</citation>
    <PMID>27740731</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clarke KS, Klarenbach S, Vlaicu S, Yang RC, Garg AX; Donor Nephrectomy Outcomes Research (DONOR) Network. The direct and indirect economic costs incurred by living kidney donors-a systematic review. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2006 Jul;21(7):1952-60. Epub 2006 Mar 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16554329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waterman AD, Covelli T, Caisley L, Zerega W, Schnitzler M, Adams D, Hong BA. Potential living kidney donors' health education use and comfort with donation. Prog Transplant. 2004 Sep;14(3):233-40.</citation>
    <PMID>15495783</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warren PH, Gifford KA, Hong BA, Merion RM, Ojo AO. Development of the National Living Donor Assistance Center: reducing financial disincentives to living organ donation. Prog Transplant. 2014 Mar;24(1):76-81. doi: 10.7182/pit2014593.</citation>
    <PMID>24598569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodrigue JR, Schold JD, Morrissey P, Whiting J, Vella J, Kayler LK, Katz D, Jones J, Kaplan B, Fleishman A, Pavlakis M, Mandelbrot DA; KDOC Study Group. Direct and Indirect Costs Following Living Kidney Donation: Findings From the KDOC Study. Am J Transplant. 2016 Mar;16(3):869-76. doi: 10.1111/ajt.13591. Epub 2016 Feb 4.</citation>
    <PMID>26845630</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodrigue JR, Schold JD, Morrissey P, Whiting J, Vella J, Kayler LK, Katz D, Jones J, Kaplan B, Fleishman A, Pavlakis M, Mandelbrot DA; KDOC Study Group. Predonation Direct and Indirect Costs Incurred by Adults Who Donated a Kidney: Findings From the KDOC Study. Am J Transplant. 2015 Sep;15(9):2387-93. doi: 10.1111/ajt.13286. Epub 2015 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25943721</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodrigue JR, Schold JD, Mandelbrot DA. The decline in living kidney donation in the United States: random variation or cause for concern? Transplantation. 2013 Nov 15;96(9):767-73. doi: 10.1097/TP.0b013e318298fa61.</citation>
    <PMID>23759882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Manyalich M, Ricart A, Martínez I, Balleste C, Paredes D, Vilardell J, Avsec D, Dias L, Fehrman-Eckholm I, Hiesse C, Kyriakides G, Line PD, Maxwell A, Nanni Costa A, Paez G, Turcu R, Walaszewski J. EULID project: European living donation and public health. Transplant Proc. 2009 Jul-Aug;41(6):2021-4. doi: 10.1016/j.transproceed.2009.05.021.</citation>
    <PMID>19715823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pruett TL, Tibell A, Alabdulkareem A, Bhandari M, Cronin DC, Dew MA, Dib-Kuri A, Gutmann T, Matas A, McMurdo L, Rahmel A, Rizvi SA, Wright L, Delmonico FL. The ethics statement of the Vancouver Forum on the live lung, liver, pancreas, and intestine donor. Transplantation. 2006 May 27;81(10):1386-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16732173</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collier R. Ontario and Manitoba to reimburse expenses for living organ donors. CMAJ. 2008 Jun 3;178(12):1535. doi: 10.1503/cmaj.080704.</citation>
    <PMID>18519896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Concejero AM, Chen CL. Ethical perspectives on living donor organ transplantation in Asia. Liver Transpl. 2009 Dec;15(12):1658-61. doi: 10.1002/lt.21930.</citation>
    <PMID>19938130</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hippen B, Matas A. Incentives for organ donation in the United States: feasible alternative or forthcoming apocalypse? Curr Opin Organ Transplant. 2009 Apr;14(2):140-6. doi: 10.1097/MOT.0b013e3283295e0d. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19307965</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howell E, Corder L, Dobson A. Out-of-pocket health expenses for Medicaid and other poor and near-poor persons in 1980. Natl Med Care Util Expend Surv B. 1985 Aug;(4):1-52.</citation>
    <PMID>10313450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jotkowitz A. Notes on the new Israeli organ donation law-2008. Transplant Proc. 2008 Dec;40(10):3297-8. doi: 10.1016/j.transproceed.2008.08.128.</citation>
    <PMID>19100375</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Price D. Living kidney donation in Europe: legal and ethical perspectives--the EUROTOLD Project. Transpl Int. 1994;7 Suppl 1:S665-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11271334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rithalia A, McDaid C, Suekarran S, Norman G, Myers L, Sowden A. A systematic review of presumed consent systems for deceased organ donation. Health Technol Assess. 2009 May;13(26):iii, ix-xi, 1-95. doi: 10.3310/hta13260. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19422754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rizvi AH, Naqvi AS, Zafar NM, Ahmed E. Regulated compensated donation in Pakistan and Iran. Curr Opin Organ Transplant. 2009 Apr;14(2):124-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19469028</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodrigue JR, Crist K, Roberts JP, Freeman RB Jr, Merion RM, Reed AI. Stimulus for organ donation: a survey of the American Society of Transplant Surgeons membership. Am J Transplant. 2009 Sep;9(9):2172-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-6143.2009.02741.x. Epub 2009 Jul 16.</citation>
    <PMID>19624568</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vlaicu S, Klarenbach S, Yang RC, Dempster T, Garg AX. Current Canadian initiatives to reimburse live organ donors for their non-medical expenses. Can J Public Health. 2007 Nov-Dec;98(6):481-3.</citation>
    <PMID>19039887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sells R. Incentives for organ donation: some ethical issues. Ann Transplant. 2004;9(1):23-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15478883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schulz-Baldes A, Delmonico FL. Improving institutional fairness to live kidney donors: donor needs must be addressed by safeguarding donation risks and compensating donation costs. Transpl Int. 2007 Nov;20(11):940-6. Epub 2007 Aug 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17711405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolters HH, Heidenreich S, Senninger N. Living donor kidney transplantation: chance for the recipient--financial risk for the donor? Transplant Proc. 2003 Sep;35(6):2091-2.</citation>
    <PMID>14529850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Living kidney donation</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Lost Wage Reimbursement</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Deindentified aggregate data will be shared with other researchers via the Open Science Framework website (https://openscienceframework.org). The website is hosted by the Center for Open Science.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

