<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00995670</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CARA-023-09S</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00995670</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ischemia/Reperfusion Injury of Human Endothelium: Role of Glucose and Statins</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ischemia/Reperfusion Injury of Human Endothelium: Role of Glucose and Statins</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Anesthetic preconditioning (APC, a brief exposure to an anesthetic gas) has become an area of
      intense research interest because of its ability to protect tissue and organs from injury
      resulting from a cessation of blood flow and then a re-establishment of flow. The blood
      vessel lining plays a key role in this injury. This research will examine, in human
      volunteers, several important modifiers of APC in human blood vessels: high blood sugar,
      vitamin C, and statin drugs. Thus, the proposed studies will advance the investigators'
      understanding of mechanisms of this injury in humans and explore important modifiers of APC
      protection from injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Injury to vital organs and tissue can occur when blood flow is stopped and then
      re-established. This happens in a variety of clinical situations and contributes to poor
      outcomes. A newer concept of protection from this injury by an anesthetic drug might occur
      because of the effect of the volatile anesthetics on the tissue that lines blood vessels.
      Thus, a brief exposure to a volatile anesthetic before a cessation of blood flow, called
      anesthetic preconditioning (APC), can substantially reduce the resulting injury to the lining
      of the blood vessels. In animal models, high levels of blood sugar block this protection,
      while cholesterol lowering drugs (statins) restore the protection and may independently
      protect blood vessel lining from injury. The interactions of high blood sugar and statin
      drugs on the blood vessel reaction to APC and a subsequent 20-min cessation of blood flow to
      the forearm will be studied in humans. In addition, the involvement of reactive oxygen
      species (ROS) in the harmful effects of high blood sugar and the beneficial effects of
      statins will be explored. The following four hypotheses will be studied: 1) high blood sugar
      blocks the anesthetic protection of blood vessels from injury in a dose and time dependent
      manner; 2) reactive oxygen species are involved in the inhibition of APC by high blood sugar;
      3) statins modulate injury in a dose related manner; and 4) statins reduce high blood sugar
      inhibition of APC.

      A standard model to evaluate forearm blood vessel function will be used. Thin
      rubber-band-like strain gauges will be strapped around each forearm and the change in their
      stretch during a variety of interventions on the experimental arm (the other arm will not
      receive any interventions and will be the control arm) will be measured. These interventions
      will allow the investigator to determine whether the hypotheses listed above are true. During
      all studies, there will be a 20-min arrest of the forearm circulation. Additional effects of
      injury, APC, high blood sugar, and statins will be determined by evaluating blood vessel
      inflammatory responses from &quot;markers&quot; in blood samples taken before and after I/R injury.
      Several studies will involve varying the forearm blood glucose concentration for brief (30
      min) to longer (2 hours) periods prior to APC and injury. The ROS scavenger vitamin C will be
      used to evaluate the role of ROS in adverse effects of high blood sugar. There are several
      other studies that will continue to seek the mechanism of action of this effect via the use
      of other drug interactions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Forearm Blood Flow</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Glucose Control, 15-min post ischemia</time_frame>
    <description>endothelial (forearm blood flow) responses to acetylcholine stimulation at baseline, and under conditions of high glucose before and after ischemia/reperfusion injury, and same with the addition of an intervention: sevoflurane (Arm 1), vitamin C (Arm 2), and high statin (Arm 3).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Hyperglycemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sevoflurane and Glucose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endothelial function will be measured via forearm blood flow (FBF). Subjects may get I/R injury (ischemia) without glucose or sevoflurane (placebo); I/R with glucose only (glucose trial); I/R with sevoflurane only (sevo trial); I/R with glucose and sevoflurane (combo trial). Baseline FBF was taken in every trial before any intervention, and FBF was taken during intervention and post I/R.
Glucose: 5% dextrose will be infused at 12 ml/hr to a target of 200 mg/dl blood concentration in the experimental forearm for 1 hr to prevent the anesthetic preconditioning (sevoflurane) protection against subsequent I/R injury.
Sevoflurane: 1 minimum alveolar concentration (MAC) for 20 min (after 1 hr glucose and before I/R) 26 volunteers were studied 67 times in this arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin C and Glucose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To determine if vitamin C can restore the impairment of the endothelium (FBF) caused by the glucose (dextrose infusion). All subjects received glucose and I/R injury (ischemia), either with or without vitamin C. Control baseline FBF was taken in every trial before any intervention, and FBF was taken during intervention and post I/R.
Placebo data were the placebo studies from the Sevoflurane and Glucose arm, when appropriate; new subjects (not enrolled in Sevoflurane and Glucose arm) underwent a separate placebo trial.
Glucose: 5% dextrose will be infused at 12ml/hr to a target of 200 mg/dl blood concentration in the experimental forearm for 60 min.
Vitamin C: 1 gm iv bolus injection 5 min before I/R injury 16 volunteers were studied 25 times in this arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Statins and Glucose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers ingested a 40 mg simvastatin (statin) pill for the two evenings prior to study day and the morning of the study to determine the effect of simvastatin on modulating the I/R injury during hyperglycemia (high glucose). Volunteers were studied with statin alone and with statin and glucose.
Placebo data were the placebo studies from the Sevoflurane and Glucose arm, when appropriate; new subjects (not enrolled in Sevoflurane and Glucose arm) underwent a separate placebo trial.
Glucose: 5% dextrose will be infused at 12ml/hr to a target of 200 mg/dl blood concentration in the experimental forearm for 60 min.
Statin: 40 mg of simvastatin 17 volunteers were studied 31 times in this arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5% dextrose</intervention_name>
    <description>Glucose is infused to prevent the anesthetic preconditioning (sevoflurane) protection against subsequent ischemia/reperfusion injury.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sevoflurane and Glucose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin C and Glucose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Statins and Glucose</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Glucose</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin C</intervention_name>
    <description>Vitamin C is intended to restore the impairment of the endothelium caused by the dextrose infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin C and Glucose</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vit C</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Simvastatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Simvastatin will be ingested to determine the efficacy of a statin to modulate the forearm response to glucose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Statins and Glucose</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Statin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sevoflurane</intervention_name>
    <description>Sevoflurane will be given to attenuate or prevent the I/R injury during glucose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sevoflurane and Glucose</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sevo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Young, healthy volunteers, 18-35 yr of age;

          -  Females will be studied at the same phase of their estrous cycle in each protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Beta-blocker therapy or any medication that might interfere with vascular responses;

          -  Pregnant or lactating women;

          -  Substance abusers;

          -  Smokers;

          -  Anyone with cardiovascular, renal, or other systemic disease including hypertension
             and/or diabetes;

          -  Also excluded are volunteers with family history of malignant hyperthermia, or
             significant gastro-esophageal reflux.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas J Ebert, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Zablocki VA Medical Center, Milwaukee</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zablocki VA Medical Center, Milwaukee</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53295-1000</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 13, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 14, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 15, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>January 22, 2015</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2015</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">March 17, 2015</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 17, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hyperglycemia</keyword>
  <keyword>statin</keyword>
  <keyword>blood vessels</keyword>
  <keyword>ischemic preconditioning</keyword>
  <keyword>Anesthesia, inhalational</keyword>
  <keyword>endothelium</keyword>
  <keyword>5% dextrose</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperglycemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Reperfusion Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ascorbic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Simvastatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA Reductase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sevoflurane</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Volunteers were sought from our research subject database.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>None. This was not a clinical intervention study but basic science research in young healthy humans. Primary exclusion criteria included anyone on beta-blockers or other med that would affect vascular responses; pregnant or lactating women; substance abusers; smokers; and cardiovascular, renal or systemic disease including hypertension &amp; diabetes.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Sevoflurane and Glucose</title>
          <description>Endothelial function will be measured via forearm blood flow (FBF). Subjects may get I/R injury (ischemia) without glucose or sevoflurane (placebo trial); I/R with glucose only (glucose trial); I/R with sevoflurane only (sevoflurane trial); I/R with glucose and sevoflurane (combined trial). Control baseline FBF was taken in every trial before any intervention, and FBF was taken during intervention and post I/R.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Vitamin C and Glucose</title>
          <description>To determine if vitamin C can restore the impairment of the endothelium (FBF) caused by the glucose (dextrose infusion). All subjects received glucose and I/R injury (ischemia), either with or without vitamin C. Control baseline FBF was taken in every trial before any intervention, and FBF was taken during intervention and post I/R.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P3">
          <title>Statin and Glucose</title>
          <description>Volunteers ingested a 40 mg simvastatin (statin) pill for the two evenings prior to study day and the morning of the study to determine the effect of simvastatin on modulating the I/R injury during hyperglycemia (high glucose). Volunteers were studied with statin alone and with statin and glucose.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="26"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="16"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="17"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="25">These 26 subjects underwent a total of 58 studies to determine the effect of dose of glucose on I/R.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="16">These 16 subjects underwent a total of 25 studies on the effect of Vitamin C.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="14">These 17 volunteers underwent 33 studies on the effect of statins, glucose, and glucose &amp; statins.</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Failed arterial cannulation</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <population>All volunteers served as their own controls (placebo) and participated in one or more interventions, after each of which the study was repeated.</population>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Sevoflurane and Glucose</title>
          <description>Endothelial function will be measured via forearm blood flow (FBF). Subjects may get I/R injury (ischemia) without glucose or sevoflurane (placebo trial); I/R with glucose only (glucose trial); I/R with sevoflurane only (sevoflurane trial); I/R with glucose and sevoflurane (combined trial). Control baseline FBF was taken in every trial before any intervention, and FBF was taken during intervention and post I/R.
Glucose: 5% dextrose will be infused at 12ml/hr to a target of 200 mg/dl blood concentration in the experimental forearm for 60 min to prevent the anesthetic preconditioning (sevoflurane) protection against subsequent I/R injury.
Sevoflurane: 1 minimum alveolar concentration (MAC) for 20 min (after hour of glucose and before I/R) 26 volunteers were studied 67 times in this arm.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Vitamin C and Glucose</title>
          <description>To determine if vitamin C can restore the impairment of the endothelium (FBF) caused by the glucose (dextrose infusion). All subjects received glucose and I/R injury (ischemia), either with or without vitamin C. Control baseline FBF was taken in every trial before any intervention, and FBF was taken during intervention and post I/R.
Placebo data were the placebo studies from the Sevoflurane and Glucose arm, when appropriate; new subjects (not enrolled in Sevoflurane and Glucose arm) underwent a separate placebo trial.
Glucose: 5% dextrose will be infused at 12ml/hr to a target of 200 mg/dl blood concentration in the experimental forearm for 60 min.
Vitamin C: 1 gm iv bolus injection 5 min before I/R injury 16 volunteers were studied 25 times in this arm.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Statin and Glucose</title>
          <description>Volunteers ingested a 40 mg simvastatin (statin) pill for the two evenings prior to study day and the morning of the study to determine the effect of simvastatin on modulating the I/R injury during hyperglycemia (high glucose). Volunteers were studied with statin alone and with statin and glucose.
Placebo data were the placebo studies from the Sevoflurane and Glucose arm, when appropriate; new subjects (not enrolled in Sevoflurane and Glucose arm) underwent a separate placebo trial.
Glucose: 5% dextrose will be infused at 12ml/hr to a target of 200 mg/dl blood concentration in the experimental forearm for 60 min.
Statin: 40 mg of simvastatin 17 volunteers were studied 31 times in this arm.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B4">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="26"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="16"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="17"/>
            <count group_id="B4" value="59"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age, Customized</title>
          <description>Age range of participants was 18 to 35 years of age.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>18-35 years old</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="26"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="16"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="59"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="33"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="26"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="26"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="16"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="59"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Forearm Blood Flow</title>
        <description>endothelial (forearm blood flow) responses to acetylcholine stimulation at baseline, and under conditions of high glucose before and after ischemia/reperfusion injury, and same with the addition of an intervention: sevoflurane (Arm 1), vitamin C (Arm 2), and high statin (Arm 3).</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, Glucose Control, 15-min post ischemia</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Sevoflurane and Glucose</title>
            <description>To determine the effectiveness of anesthetic preconditioning (APC) via sevoflurane to attenuate the I/R injury during the normal glucose state and during hyperglycemia.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Vitamin C and Glucose</title>
            <description>To determine if vitamin C can restore the impairment of the endothelium caused by the dextrose infusion.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Statin and Glucose</title>
            <description>To determine the effect of simvastatin on modulating the I/R injury during the normal glucose state and during hyperglycemia.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Forearm Blood Flow</title>
          <description>endothelial (forearm blood flow) responses to acetylcholine stimulation at baseline, and under conditions of high glucose before and after ischemia/reperfusion injury, and same with the addition of an intervention: sevoflurane (Arm 1), vitamin C (Arm 2), and high statin (Arm 3).</description>
          <units>ml/100 ml tissue/min</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Error</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="26"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="16"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="17"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Baseline</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6.48" spread="0.86"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="9.2" spread="2.92"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="7.32" spread="1.06"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Control, Glucose</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8.26" spread="1.00"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="9.2" spread="2.92"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="9.91" spread="1.43"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Post Ischemia, Glucose</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="7.10" spread="0.65"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="7.6" spread="2.42"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="7.00" spread="1.01"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Intervention Baseline</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8.47" spread="0.82"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="8.84" spread="1.39"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="8.17" spread="1.06"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Control, after intervention</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="7.90" spread="0.84"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="9.3" spread="1.73"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="9.28" spread="1.34"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Post Ischemia, intervention</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8.45" spread="1.18"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="9.91" spread="1.63"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="6.26" spread="0.82"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Sevoflurane &amp; Glucose</title>
          <description>To determine the effectiveness of anesthetic preconditioning (APC) via sevoflurane to attenuate the I/R injury during the normal glucose state and during hyperglycemia.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Vitamin C &amp; Glucose</title>
          <description>To determine if vitamin C can restore the impairment of the endothelium caused by the dextrose infusion.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E3">
          <title>Statins &amp; Glucose</title>
          <description>To determine the effect of simvastatin on modulating the I/R injury during the normal glucose state and during hyperglycemia.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="16"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Some substudies were not completed because we had difficulty creating ischemia/reperfusion (I/R) injury or a consistent FBF response, which was critical to the purpose of the study to investigate the role of glucose and statins in I/R injury.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Thomas J. Ebert, MD, PhD</name_or_title>
      <organization>Zablocki VA Medical Center</organization>
      <phone>414-384-2000 ext 42429</phone>
      <email>thomas.ebert@va.gov</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

