<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00991146</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CACZ885D2308</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00991146</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety Study of Canakinumab Administered for 6 Months (24 Weeks) in Japanese Patients With Cryopyrin-associated Periodic Syndromes Followed by an Extension Phase</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Efficacy and Safety Study of Canakinumab (Anti-interleukin-1β Monoclonal Antibody) Administered for 6 Months (24 Weeks) in Japanese Patients With the Following Cryopyrin-associated Periodic Syndromes: Familial Cold Autoinflammatory Syndrome, Muckle-Wells Syndrome, or Neonatal Onset Multisystem Inflammatory Disease, Followed by an Extension Phase to Provide Canakinumab to Study Patients Until it is Approved and Marketed in Japan</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To date there are no approved effective therapies for the treatment of cryopyrin-associated
      periodic syndromes (CAPS) including Familial Cold Autoinflammatory Syndrome (FCAS),
      Muckle-Wells Syndrome (MWS), or Neonatal Onset Multisystem Inflammatory Disease (NOMID) in
      Japan.

      The study will assess the efficacy and safety of canakinumab in Japanese patients with
      cryopyrin-associated periodic syndromes (CAPS). In previous and currently ongoing CAPS
      studies (CACZ885A2102, CACZ885D2201, CACZ885D2304, CACZ885D2306), it has been observed that
      treatment with canakinumab in patients with CAPS contributed to ensure absence of relapse, to
      improve signs and symptoms and to prevent secondary disease complications. However, no
      Japanese patients have been included in those studies. This study will allow access for
      Japanese patients to a new potentially efficacious treatment for CAPS patients with a
      convenient dosing regimen.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants without a relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of complete responder patients</measure>
    <time_frame>29 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical improvement (or resolution) with regards to: central nervous system (CNS) involvement, eye disease, hearing impairment, skin disease, joint disease, fever, and kidney function</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients experiencing a relapse during the entire study</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>How much canakinumab is contained in the patients' blood (pharmacokinetics) and what are the effect of canakinumab on the patients' body (pharmacodynamic)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of antibody against canakinumab</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">19</enrollment>
  <condition>Cryopyrin-associated Periodic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Familial Cold Autoinflammatory Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Muckle-Wells Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Neonatal Onset Multisystem Inflammatory Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>canakinumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>canakinumab</intervention_name>
    <description>canakinumab</description>
    <arm_group_label>canakinumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. At study entry, patients should have a clinical diagnosis of FCAS, MWS or NOMID and
             require medication. At the time of screening, patients can be either untreated or
             treated with other medication.

          2. Presence, or history of at least 2 of the following symptoms:

               -  For NOMID patients:

                    -  Typical NOMID urticarial rash

                    -  Signs of central nervous system (CNS) involvement such as increased
                       intracranial pressure and/or papilledema and/or cerebral spinal fluid
                       pleiocytosis and/or stroke and/or seizures, and/or sensorineural hearing
                       loss

                    -  Typical arthropatic changes on X-rays: epiphysal and/or patellar overgrowth
                       With start of NOMID symptoms before or at 6 months of age

               -  For MWS patients:

                    -  periodic fever

                    -  headache/migraine

                    -  arthralgia

                    -  urticarial skin rash

                    -  conjunctivitis

                    -  myalgia

                    -  sensorineural hearing impairment

               -  For FCAS patients:

                    -  urticarial skin rash

                    -  fever/chills

                    -  conjunctivitis

                    -  joint pain

          3. Patients requiring oral steroids, NSAIDs and/or disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs
             (DMARDs) can be enrolled if they are on a stable dose (oral steroids: &lt; 20 mg/day or &lt;
             or = 0.4 mg/kg prednisone or prednisone equivalent, whichever applies) for at least 4
             weeks prior to the screening visit.

          4. Able to communicate with the investigator and comply with the requirements of the
             study (for children the parent can assist when necessary).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women.

          2. All women capable of becoming pregnant unless they are postmenopausal or are using one
             or more methods of contraception.

          3. Participation in any other study within 30 days

          4. Infection with HIV, Hepatitis B or C.

          5. Live vaccinations within 3 months prior to the start of the trial, during the trial,
             and up to 3 months following the last dose.

          6. History of drug or alcohol abuse within the 12 months prior to dosing.

          7. Donation or loss of 400 mL or more of blood within 8 weeks prior to dosing for adults.

          8. History of significant medical conditions, which in the doctor's opinion would exclude
             the patient from participating in this trial.

          9. History of renal transplantation.

         10. Presence of any additional rheumatic diseases or significant systemic diseases. For
             example, major chronic infectious/ inflammatory/ immunologic disease (such as
             inflammatory bowel disease, psoriatic arthritis, spondyloarthropathy, systemic lupus
             erythematosus in addition to the autoinflammatory disease).

         11. Presence of any of the following laboratory abnormalities: ALT or AST greater than 2
             times the upper limit of normal (ULN), platelet count less than 100x109/L.

         12. History of recurrent and/or evidence of clinically significant active bacterial,
             fungal, or viral infections.

         13. History of contact with patients with suspected tuberculosis symptoms; or history or
             complication of tuberculosis infection.

         14. Use of the following therapies:

               -  Etanercept in the 4 weeks prior to the baseline visit (Day 1) and thereafter

               -  Adalimumab in the 8 weeks prior to the baseline visit (Day 1) and thereafter

               -  Infliximab in the 12 weeks prior to the baseline visit (Day 1) and thereafter

               -  Rituximab in the 26 weeks prior to the baseline visit (Day 1) and thereafter

               -  Tocilizumab in the 3 weeks prior to the baseline visit (Day 1) and thereafter

               -  Any other investigational biologics in the 8 weeks prior to the baseline visit
                  (Day 1) and thereafter (with the exception of anakinra therapy-see below)

               -  Anakinra therapy after the baseline visit (Day 1). Last anakinra injection should
                  occur not less than 6 hours prior to the canakinumab injection at Day 1

               -  Leflunomide in the 4 weeks prior to the baseline visit (Day 1) and thereafter.
                  After the completion of leflunomide treatment a cholestiramine in dose 8 g 3
                  times per day for 14 days is recommended.

               -  Thalidomide in the 4 weeks prior to the baseline visit (Day 1) and thereafter

               -  Cyclosporine in the 4 weeks prior to the baseline visit (Day 1) and thereafter

               -  i.v. immunoglobulin (i.v. Ig) in the 8 weeks prior to the baseline visit (Day 1)
                  and thereafter

               -  6-Mercaptopurine, azathioprine, cyclophosphamide, or chlorambucil in the 12 weeks
                  prior to the baseline visit (Day 1) and thereafter

               -  Dapsone, mycophenolate mofetil in the 3 weeks prior to the baseline visit (Day 1)
                  and thereafter

               -  &gt; or = 20 mg/day or &gt;0.4 mg/kg, whichever applies, of prednisone or prednisone
                  equivalent in the 4 week prior to the baseline visit (Day 1) and thereafter

               -  Methyl prednisone pulse therapy in the 4 weeks prior to baseline visit and
                  thereafter

         15. History of allergic reaction to similar drugs. No additional exclusions may be applied
             by the doctor, in order to ensure that the study population will be representative of
             all eligible patients.

        Other protocol-defined inclusion/exclusion criteria may apply
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka-city</city>
        <state>Fukuoka</state>
        <zip>812-8582</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yokohama-city</city>
        <state>Kanagawa</state>
        <zip>236-0004</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kyoto-city</city>
        <state>Kyoto</state>
        <zip>606-8507</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.novctrd.com/CtrdWeb/displaypdf.nov?trialresultid=7923</url>
    <description>Results for CACZ885D2308 from the Novartis Clinical Trials website</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Imagawa T, Nishikomori R, Takada H, Takeshita S, Patel N, Kim D, Lheritier K, Heike T, Hara T, Yokota S. Safety and efficacy of canakinumab in Japanese patients with phenotypes of cryopyrin-associated periodic syndrome as established in the first open-label, phase-3 pivotal study (24-week results). Clin Exp Rheumatol. 2013 Mar-Apr;31(2):302-9. Epub 2013 Feb 1.</citation>
    <PMID>23380020</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 6, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 6, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 7, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CAPS</keyword>
  <keyword>FCAS</keyword>
  <keyword>MWS</keyword>
  <keyword>NOMID</keyword>
  <keyword>cryopyrin-associated periodic syndromes</keyword>
  <keyword>Familial Cold Autoinflammatory Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Muckle-Wells Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Neonatal Onset Multisystem Inflammatory Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>canakinumab</keyword>
  <keyword>ACZ885</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>systemic autoinflammatory disease</keyword>
  <keyword>NALP-3</keyword>
  <keyword>human monoclonal anti-human interleukin-1beta (IL-1beta)antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>autosomal dominant</keyword>
  <keyword>familial autoinflammatory syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cellulitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eosinophilia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cryopyrin-Associated Periodic Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

