<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00995228</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TASMC-09-IM-0501-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00995228</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fluid Management in the Post-Anesthetic Care Unit (PACU) at Sourasky Medical Center</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Practice of Fluid Management in the Post-anesthetic Care Unit (PACU) in Patients Undergoing Elective Surgery: an Observational Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Peri-operative fluid therapy is a controversial area with few randomized trials to guide
      practice. Fluid management has a significant influence on outcome following surgery. Yet
      practically, fluid prescription practice during this period is sub-optimal, resulting in
      avoidable iatrogenic complications.

      Several studies have assessed the effect of a 'liberal' vs. a 'restrictive' perioperative
      fluid regimen on post-operative outcome. However, most of these studies have focused
      primarily on intra-operative fluid management, whereas postoperative strategies have been
      less well defined, even though the immediate postoperative period is of critical importance
      to the patient's recovery. Moreover, whereas intra-operative fluid administration is
      monitored by the anesthesiologist, postoperatively it is less supervised and may result in
      excess or lack of intravenous (IV) fluids. Therefore, fluid management audit at the
      post-anesthesia care unit (PACU) is of paramount importance for patient healthcare. The
      objective of this study is to follow and report the current practice of fluid administration
      in the PACU of Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center, for an extended period of time as a first
      step towards establishing evidence-based guidelines for postoperative fluid management.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background

      Perioperative intravenous (IV) fluid management has been a historically controversial issue
      in anesthesiology. Accumulating evidence suggest that regulated perioperative fluid
      management has beneficial effects on postoperative outcomes. A restricted perioperative IV
      fluid regimen aiming at unchanged body weight resulted in reduced complications after
      elective colorectal resection (1). In another study, patients receiving a reduced
      intraoperative fluid volume demonstrated less postoperative complications, lower morbidity
      rates and shorter hospital stay after intraabdominal surgery (2). Conversely, whereas
      restricted postoperative IV salt and water intake shortened gastrointestinal (GI) function
      and hospitalization after colonic resection in one study (3), it had no effect on the same
      outcomes in another randomized clinical trial (4).

      Despite the reported benefits of restrictive fluid therapy, this strategy may be associated
      with adverse outcomes. Inadequate fluid administration can lead to a reduced effective
      circulating volume resulting in inefficient tissue perfusion (5-7). On the other hand,
      overhydration, resulting from perioperative fluid excess, has shown association with
      deleterious effects on cardiac and pulmonary function (8-12), and on recovery of GI motility
      (2,3,13), tissue oxygenation (14), wound healing and coagulation (15-16). Erroneous fluid
      administration is generally associated with increased morbidity and postoperative
      complications (17-21). Altogether, these observations call for a standardized and regulated
      fluid therapy throughout the perioperative period taking into account patients' premorbid
      diseases and type of surgery.

      Previous studies have focused primarily on intra-operative fluid management. Postoperative
      strategies have been less well defined, even though the immediate postoperative period is of
      critical importance to the patient's recovery. Moreover, whereas intra-operative fluid
      administration is monitored by the anesthesiologist, postoperatively it is less supervised
      and may result in excess or lack of IV fluids.

      The aim of this study is thus to follow and present the current practice of fluid
      administration in the PACU of Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center, for an extended period of
      time as a first step towards establishing evidence-based guidelines for postoperative fluid
      management.

      Methods

      We will collect data regarding intra- and postoperative fluid administration from the charts
      of &gt;18 years old ASA I-III patients undergoing elective general or orthopedic surgery.
      Patients with renal/cardiac failure will be analyzed separately, since their pathology
      dictates extra caution with fluid therapy. Patients demographics, type of surgery, and the
      type and volume of fluids given during the operation and PACU stay, will be documented as
      well as the occurrence of morbidity in PACU, without any interventions. Data collection will
      be anonymous and will last six months. The setting will be the PACU of the Tal Aviv Sourasky
      Medical center.

      Suggested benefits

      The purpose of this data report is to provide an overview on the current practice of fluid
      management in Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center's PACU. We believe that this is a preliminary
      necessary step towards establishing guidelines for postoperative fluid management.

      Study Objective

      To describe the contemporary practice of postoperative fluid management in the PACU of the
      Sourasky Medical Center.

      References

        1. Brandstrup B, Tonnesen H, Pott F et al (2003). Effects of intravenous fluid restriction
           on postoperative complications: comparison of two perioperative fluid regimens: a
           randomized assessor-blinded multicenter trial. Ann Surg 238:641-8.

        2. Nisanevich V, Felsenstein I, Matot I, et al (2005). Effect of intraoperative fluid
           management on outcome after intraabdominal surgery.Anesthesiology.103:25-32.

        3. Lobo DN, Bostock KA, Allison SP, et al (2002). Effect of salt and water balance on
           recovery of gastrointestinal function after elective colonic resection: a randomised
           controlled trial. Lancet 359:1812-8.

        4. MacKay G, Fearon K, O'Dwyer PJ et al (2006). Randomized clinical trial of the effect of
           postoperative intravenous fluid restriction on recovery after elective colorectal
           surgery. Br J Surg 93:1469-74.

        5. Arkilic CF, Taguchi A, Sharma N, et al (2003). Supplemental perioperative fluid
           administration increases tissue oxygen pressure. Surgery 133:49-55.

        6. Bennett-Guerrero E, Welsby I, Dunn TJ, et al (1999). The use of a postoperative
           morbidity survey to evaluate patients with prolonged hospitalization after routine,
           moderate-risk, elective surgery. Anesth Analg 89:514-9.

        7. Mythen MG, Webb AR (1995). Perioperative plasma volume expansion reduces the incidence
           of gut mucosal hypoperfusion during cardiac surgery. Arch Surg 130:423-9.

        8. Arieff AI (1999). Fatal postoperative pulmonary edema: pathogenesis and literature
           review. Chest 115: 1371-77.

        9. Turnage WS, Lunn JJ (1993). Postpneumonectomy pulmonary edema. A retrospective analysis
           of associated variables. Chest. 103:1646-50.

       10. Mathru M, Blakeman BP (1993). Don't drown the &quot;down lung&quot;. Chest 103:1644-5.

       11. Jordan S, Mitchell JA, Quinlan GJ, Goldstraw P, Evans TW. The pathogenesis of lung
           injury following pulmonary resection. Eur Respir J 2000; 15: 790-9

       12. Patel RL, Townsend ER, Fountain SW (1992). Elective pneumonectomy: factors associated
           with morbidity and operative mortality. Ann Thorac Surg 54: 84-8

       13. Prien T, Backhaus N, Pelster F, Pircher W, Bunte H, Lawin P (1990). Effect of
           intraoperative fluid administration and colloid osmotic pressure on the formation of
           intestinal edema during gastrointestinal surgery. J Clin Anesth 2: 317-23

       14. Heughan C, Ninikoski J, Hunt TK (1972). Effect of excessive infusion of saline solution
           on tissue oxygen transport. Surg Gynecol Obstet 135: 257-60

       15. Janvrin SB, Davies G, Greenhalgh RM (1980). Postoperative deep vein thrombosis caused by
           intravenous fluids during surgery. Br J Surg. 67:690-3

       16. Hartmann M, Jönsson K, Zederfeldt B (1992). Effect of tissue perfusion and oxygenation
           on accumulation of collagen in healing wounds. Randomized study in patients after major
           abdominal operations. Eur J Surg 158:521-6.

       17. Mutoh T, Lamm WJ, Embree LJ, Hildebrandt J, Albert RK (1992). Volume infusion produces
           abdominal distension, lung compression, and chest wall stiffening in pigs. J Appl
           Physiol 72: 575-82

       18. Ratner LE, Smith GW (1993). Intraoperative fluid management. Surg Clin North Am 73:
           229-41

       19. Moore FD, Shires G (1967). Moderation. Ann Surg 166:300-1.

       20. Alsous F, Khamiees M, Manthous CA, et al (2000). Negative fluid balance predicts
           survival in patients with septic shock: a retrospective pilot study. Chest 117: 1749-54.

       21. Callum KG, Gray AJG, Hoile RW, et al (1999) Extremes of age: the 1999 report of the
           national confidential enquiry into perioperative deaths. London: National Confidential
           Enquiry into Perioperative Deaths.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Edema</condition>
  <condition>Acute Lung Injury</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Renal Failure</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients from both sexes &gt;18 y/o, undergoing elective general or orthopedic surgery
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women &gt; 18 years old

          -  ASA I-III

          -  Undergoing elective general or orthopedic surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Emergency procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Idit Matot, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Anesthesia and intensive care, Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yifat Klein, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Anesthesia and intensive care, Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tel Aviv Sourasky medical center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Aviv</city>
        <zip>64239</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 14, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 14, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 15, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 14, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 14, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 15, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Prof Idit Matot, director Anesthesiology and intensive care unit</name_title>
    <organization>Tel Aviv sourasky medical center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>overhydration</keyword>
  <keyword>fluid restriction</keyword>
  <keyword>post-anesthesia care unit</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Injury</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Lung Injury</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Edema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

