<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00991133</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLO08808</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00991133</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Safety and Tolerability Study of Clofarabine, Etoposide, Cyclophosphamide, PEG-asparaginase, and Vincristine in Pediatric Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-Label, Multi-Center Safety and Tolerability Pilot Combination Study of Clofarabine, Etoposide, Cyclophosphamide, PEG-asparaginase, and Vincristine in Pediatric Patients With Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL) in First Relapse</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Genzyme, a Sanofi Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label study of Clofarabine, Etoposide, Cyclophosphamide, PEG-asparaginase,
      and Vincristine to assess this 5-drug treatment's safety and tolerability in pediatric
      patients with first relapse Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The trial is a Phase 1, open-label study to assess the safety and tolerability of
      incorporating clofarabine into an intensive chemotherapy regimen of etoposide,
      cyclophosphamide, PEG-asparaginase, and vincristine. Patients enrolled in this study will
      receive a maximum of 2 cycles of the 5-drug regimen, then will be treated according to
      investigator discretion. After the study treatment period, all patients will be followed for
      a minimum of 4 months beyond the final study visit. This study will include a maximum of 12
      evaluable patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of DLTs (Dose Limiting Toxicities) experienced with 1 cycle of this 5-drug regimen in this patient population (in all patients who receive any doses of study drugs)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 cycle</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall toxicity profile documented by incidence of AEs, SAEs, and/or DLTs</measure>
    <time_frame>1 cycle</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy as documented by complete remission (CR), time and duration of remission, event-free survival (EFS), 4-month EFS, disease-free survival (DFS), and overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 cycles</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoblastic Leukemia, Acute, Childhood</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clofarabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients received a maximum of 2 cycles of the intravenous (IV) 5-drug regimen (clofarabine, etoposide,cyclophosphamide, PEG-asparaginase, and vincristine) plus intrathecal methotrexate, and then entered follow-up. Patients who achieved complete remission (CR) or complete remission with incomplete platelet recovery (CRp) after 1 cycle of study drugs were eligible to receive a second cycle of study drugs upon recovery of peripheral blood counts, and patients who did not have leukemic progression were eligible to receive a second treatment cycle at the investigator's discretion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clofarabine incorporated into a 5-drug regimen</intervention_name>
    <description>Clofarabine (IV) 40mg/m2 into an intensive chemotherapy regimen of etoposide, cyclophosphamide, PEG-asparaginas, and vincristine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clofarabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Clolar</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>PEGaspar-aginase</other_name>
    <other_name>Oncovin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be in first relapse with &gt;25% blasts in the bone marrow with a duration of first
             remission of ≥6 months and no longer in the intensive phase(s) of initial ALL therapy
             (e.g., patients who are in the maintenance or continuation phases of therapy [or
             beyond] and who have completed the induction or intensification phases).

          -  Have received no more than 2 prior induction regimens prior to the date of first
             relapse. Patients who are in first relapse but have failed a re-induction attempt
             (i.e., 1 cycle of re-induction therapy) are not eligible for inclusion in this study.

          -  Be ≥1 and ≤30 years old and have a body weight of &gt;10 kg at study entry. (Note: no
             more than 3 patients aged &gt;21 ≤30 are to be enrolled.)

          -  Be able to receive all study drugs with no known contra-indications.

          -  Be able to provide adequate venous access.

          -  Have a Karnofsky Performance Status (KPS) of ≥50 for patients &gt;10 years of age or a
             Lansky Performance Status (LPS) of ≥50 for patients ≤10 years of age.

          -  Patients (≥18 years of age) or the parent or legal guardian(s) (for patients &lt;18 years
             of age) must provide signed, written informed consent according to local institutional
             review board (IRB) and institutional requirements. For patients &lt;18 years of age,
             signed assent should be obtained according to local IRB and institutional
             requirements.

          -  Be able to comply with study procedures and follow-up examinations.

          -  Have adequate liver, renal, pancreatic, and cardiac function considered acceptable by
             laboratory values and cardiac assessments

          -  Have no active central nervous system (CNS) leukemia, as evidenced by negative
             cytology on lumbar puncture and absence of clinical central neurologic symptoms.
             Diagnostic lumbar puncture should be performed only after all other eligibility
             assessments have been completed and reviewed, except for bone marrow aspirate and/or
             biopsy. Patients with CNS1 or CNS2 leukemia may be enrolled in the study.

          -  Have recovered to baseline from all toxicities from prior chemotherapy regimens prior
             to enrollment in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have received previous treatment with clofarabine.

          -  Have a history of clinical allergy (Grade 3 or 4) to PEG-asparaginase.

          -  Have a history of severe pancreatitis (Grade 3 or 4) attributed to asparaginase
             therapy.

          -  Have Burkitt's leukemia.

          -  Have overt testicular relapse.

          -  Adequate time has not elapsed since patient's last therapy. Patients who relapse while
             receiving standard ALL maintenance chemotherapy will not be required to have a washout
             period before entry onto this study. Note that patients may receive intrathecal (IT)
             ara-C, methotrexate, or hydrocortisone immediately prior to the administration of
             study drugs. Patients may also receive hydroxyurea up to 24 hours prior to the start
             of study therapy. Patients who relapse when they are not receiving standard ALL
             maintenance therapy must have fully recovered from the acute toxic effects of all
             prior therapy (excluding hematologic toxicity), immunotherapy or radiotherapy.

          -  Have an uncontrolled systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or other infection. For
             patients with a history of fever within the preceding 3 days at the time of
             enrollment, documentation of negative blood cultures for at least 48 hours is
             required.

          -  Are pregnant or lactating.

          -  Male and female patients who are fertile must agree to use an effective means of birth
             control (i.e., latex condom, diaphragm, cervical cap, etc.) while on study therapy,
             and for a minimum of 1 month following final study visit.

          -  Have psychiatric disorders that would interfere with consent, study participation, or
             follow-up.

          -  Have any other severe concurrent disease, or have a history of serious organ
             dysfunction or disease involving the heart, kidney, liver, or pancreas.

          -  Have received any stem cell transplantation or high-dose chemotherapy with stem cell
             rescue regimen.

          -  Have a history of cirrhosis or known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)/acquired
             immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS).

          -  Have a history of at least 1 positive test for hepatitis B or hepatitis C infection.

          -  Have Down syndrome.

          -  Are currently participating in another concurrent investigational treatment protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Monitor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Genzyme, a Sanofi Company</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60614</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seattle Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 6, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 7, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 29, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 29, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 30, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Clofarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pegaspargase</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vincristine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Asparaginase</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

