<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03075553</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC1681</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2017-00307</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MC1681</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015083</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03075553</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nivolumab in Treating Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Peripheral T-cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 2 Single-Arm, Open-Label Study of Nivolumab in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Peripheral T-Cell Lymphoma (PTCL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well nivolumab works in treating patients with peripheral
      T-cell lymphoma that has come back after a period of improvement or that does not respond to
      treatment. Monoclonal antibodies, such as nivolumab, may block cancer growth in different
      ways by targeting certain cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the clinical benefit of nivolumab in T-cell lymphomas, as measured by objective
      response rate (ORR) within 12 cycles according to the Lugano Classification Response Criteria
      (2014).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess safety and tolerability of the regimen in this patient population. II. To assess
      progression-free survival (PFS). III. To assess duration of response (DOR). IV. To assess
      overall survival (OS).

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate T-cell/cytokine profile in the peripheral blood - peripheral blood specimens
      will be used to assess T-cell activation and cytokine up regulation as measures of treatment
      effect.

      II. To evaluate intratumoral biomarkers- intratumoral cell populations and distribution,
      genetic variability, mutational burden and T-cell activation will be evaluated to identify
      potential biomarkers that correlate with response to therapy.

      III. To assess the potential association between PD-L1/PD-1/PD-L2 expression on tumor and
      T-cells and/or PD-L1 soluble levels in plasma with clinical efficacy of PD-1 blockade.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive nivolumab intravenously (IV) over 60 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats
      every 14 days for up to 8 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity. Patients achieving stable disease, complete response, or partial response receive
      nivolumab IV over 60 minutes on day 1 of course 9. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to
      24 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 35 days, 100-120 days,
      230-250 days, and 330-390 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 17, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of complete or partial responses assessed according to the revised Lugano Classification Response criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of successes will be estimated by the number of successes divided by the total number of evaluable patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of complete or partial responses assessed according to the revised Lugano Classification Response criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Confidence intervals for the true success proportion will be calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Complete Response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>The distribution of duration of complete response will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum grade for each type of adverse event will be recorded for each patient, and frequency tables will be reviewed to determine patterns. Additionally, the relationship of the adverse event(s) to the study treatment will be taken into consideration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>The relationship of the adverse event(s) to the study treatment will be taken into consideration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>The time from registration to death due to any cause, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The distribution of survival time will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>The time from registration to relapse or death due to any cause, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The distribution of progression-free survival will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier. In addition, the progression-free survival rate will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>The time from registration to relapse or death due to any cause, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The progression-free survival rate will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated using complete metabolic response divided by the total number of evaluable patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated using partial metabolic response divided by the total number of evaluable patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker activity (intratumoral cell populations, genetic variability, serum cytokines, T-cell activation)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized and used to help characterize the types of patients accrued to this trial. Nonparametric quantitative comparisons by group will be made as appropriate (Fisher's exact or Wilcoxon rank sum)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker activity (intratumoral cell populations, genetic variability, serum cytokines, T-cell activation)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized and used to help characterize the types of patients accrued to this trial. Kaplan-Meier methods and log-rank statistics will be used to compare between groups for time-to-event measures.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cytokine upregulation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized and used to help characterize the types of patients accrued to this trial. Nonparametric quantitative comparisons by group will be made as appropriate (Fisher's exact or Wilcoxon rank sum)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cytokine upregulation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized and used to help characterize the types of patients accrued to this trial. Kaplan-Meier methods and log-rank statistics will be used to compare between groups for time-to-event measures.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PD-L1/PD-1/PD-L2 expression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized and used to help characterize the types of patients accrued to this trial. Nonparametric quantitative comparisons by group will be made as appropriate (Fisher's exact or Wilcoxon rank sum).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PD-L1/PD-1/PD-L2 expression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized and used to help characterize the types of patients accrued to this trial. Kaplan-Meier methods and log-rank statistics will be used to compare between groups for time-to-event measures.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>T-cell activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized and used to help characterize the types of patients accrued to this trial. Nonparametric quantitative comparisons by group will be made as appropriate (Fisher's exact or Wilcoxon rank sum)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>T-cell activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 390 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized and used to help characterize the types of patients accrued to this trial. Kaplan-Meier methods and log-rank statistics will be used to compare between groups for time-to-event measures.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">39</enrollment>
  <condition>Blastic Plasmacytoid Dendritic Cell Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Hepatosplenic T-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>HTLV-1 Infection</condition>
  <condition>NK-Cell Lymphoma, Unclassifiable</condition>
  <condition>Primary Systemic Anaplastic Large Cell Lymphoma, ALK-Negative</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult T-Cell Leukemia/Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Anaplastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Angioimmunoblastic T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Enteropathy-Associated T-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mycosis Fungoides</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Adult T-Cell Leukemia/Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Anaplastic Large Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Angioimmunoblastic T-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Enteropathy-Associated T-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Mycosis Fungoides</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Nasal Type Extranodal NK/T-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Peripheral T-Cell Lymphoma, Not Otherwise Specified</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nivolumab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive nivolumab IV over 60 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 14 days for up to 8 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving stable disease, complete response, or partial response receive nivolumab IV over 60 minutes on day 1 of course 9. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 24 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nivolumab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (nivolumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BMS-936558</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-1106</other_name>
    <other_name>NIVO</other_name>
    <other_name>ONO-4538</other_name>
    <other_name>Opdivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Relapsed or refractory T-cell lymphoma (TCL) biopsy-proven =&lt; 6 months prior to
             registration, including the following subtypes:

               -  Peripheral T-cell lymphoma, not otherwise specified

               -  Anaplastic large cell lymphoma, anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) negative,
                  primary systemic type

               -  Angioimmunoblastic T-cell lymphoma

               -  Extranodal natural killer (NK)/T-cell lymphoma, nasal type

               -  Adult T-cell lymphoma/leukemia (human T-lymphotropic virus 1 [HTLV1]+)

               -  Blastic NK-cell lymphoma

               -  Enteropathy-associated T-cell lymphoma

               -  Hepatosplenic gamma delta T-cell lymphoma

               -  Transformed mycosis fungoides

               -  T/NK-cell lymphoma, unclassifiable

          -  Measurable disease: subjects must have at least one lesion that is &gt; 15mm (1.5 cm) in
             the longest diameter on cross-sectional imaging and measureable in two perpendicular
             dimensions per computed tomography (spiral CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)

          -  After failure of allogeneic stem cell transplant (ASCT) or after failure of frontline
             therapy in subjects who declined or are not ASCT candidates

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) 0, 1 or 2

          -  White blood cell (WBC) &gt;= 3000/mm^3

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1500/mm^3

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 100,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 9.0 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) unless elevation due to Gilbert's
             Syndrome

          -  Aspartate transaminase (AST) =&lt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Calculated creatinine clearance must be &gt;= 45 ml/min using the Cockcroft-Gault formula

          -  Negative serum or urine pregnancy test done =&lt; 7 days prior to registration, for
             persons of childbearing potential only Note: Persons of child-bearing potential
             (POCBP) must use appropriate method(s) of contraception; POCBP should use an adequate
             method to avoid pregnancy for 23 weeks (30 days plus the time required for nivolumab
             to undergo five half-lives) after the last dose of investigational drug; men who are
             sexually active with POCBP must use any contraceptive method with a failure rate of
             less than 1% per year; men receiving nivolumab and who are sexually active with POCBP
             will be instructed to adhere to contraception for a period of 31 weeks after the last
             dose of investigational product; persons who are not of childbearing potential (ie,
             who are postmenopausal or surgically sterile) as well as azoospermic men do not
             require contraception; should a person become pregnant or suspect being pregnant while
             participating in this study, the person should inform the treating physician
             immediately

          -  Provide written informed consent

          -  Willing to return to enrolling institution for follow-up during the Active Monitoring
             phase of the study

          -  Willing to provide tissue and blood samples for correlative research purposes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  All primary cutaneous T-cell lymphomas

          -  Any of the following:

               -  Pregnant women

               -  Nursing women

               -  Men or women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to employ adequate
                  contraception

          -  Co-morbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the judgment
             of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into this study or
             interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety and toxicity of the
             prescribed regimens

          -  Active, known or suspected autoimmune disease Note: subjects are permitted to enroll
             if they have vitiligo, type I diabetes mellitus, residual hypothyroidism due to
             autoimmune condition only requiring hormone replacement, psoriasis not requiring
             systemic treatment

          -  Use of systemic treatment with either corticosteroids (&gt;10 mg daily prednisone
             equivalents) or other immunosuppressive medications &lt; 14 days of registration Note:
             inhaled or topical steroids are permitted; &gt; 10 mg daily prednisone equivalents are
             permitted only in adrenal insufficiency in the absence of active autoimmune disease

          -  Prohibited treatments and or therapies

               -  Autologous stem cell transplant (ASCT) =&lt; 12 weeks prior to first dose of the
                  study drug

               -  Prior treatments (window prior to registration):

                    -  Chemotherapy =&lt; 2 weeks

                    -  Nitrosureas =&lt; 6 weeks

                    -  Therapeutic anticancer antibodies =&lt; 4 weeks

                    -  Radio- or toxin immunoconjugates =&lt; 10 weeks

                    -  Radiation therapy =&lt; 3 weeks

                    -  Or major surgery =&lt; 2 weeks

               -  Prior treatment with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, anti-PD-L2, anti-CTLA-4 antibody,
                  or any other antibody or drug specifically targeting T-cell costimulation or
                  immune checkpoint pathways

                    -  Prior allogeneic stem cell transplant (SCT)

                    -  Chest radiation =&lt; 24 weeks prior to registration

          -  Immunocompromised patients, patients with known history of testing positive for human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or known acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) and
             currently receiving antiretroviral therapy, active hepatitis B virus surface antigen
             (HBV sAg+), active hepatitis C (if Ab+ then PCR+) indicating acute or chronic
             infection

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Receiving any other investigational agent which would be considered as a treatment for
             the primary neoplasm

          -  Other active malignancy =&lt; 3 years prior to registration EXCEPTIONS: non-melanotic
             skin cancer or carcinoma-in-situ of the cervix NOTE: if there is a history of prior
             malignancy, they must not be receiving other specific treatment for their cancer

          -  Active central nervous system (CNS) involvement or leptomeningeal involvement

          -  History of pancreatitis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Ansell</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>855-776-0015</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen M. Ansell</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 1, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycosis Fungoides</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia-Lymphoma, Adult T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large-Cell, Anaplastic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell, Peripheral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoblastic Lymphadenopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Extranodal NK-T-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intestinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enteropathy-Associated T-Cell Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HTLV-I Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

