<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03075423</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EUDRACT: 2016-000706-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03075423</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized Phase-II Study of Nivolumab Plus Ipilimumab vs. Standard of Care in Untreated and Advanced Non-clear Cell RCC</brief_title>
  <acronym>SUNIFORECAST</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Randomized, Open-Label Study of Nivolumab Combined With Ipilimumab Versus Standard of Care in Subjects With Previously Untreated and Advanced (Unresectable or Metastatic) Non-clear Cell Renal Cell Carcinoma (nccRCC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nicola Goekbuget</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Goethe University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      SUNNIFORECAST (Sunitinib vs. Nivolumab + Ipilimumab as First line treatment Of REnal cell
      CAncer of non-clear cell SubTypes) is a Phase II, randomized, open-label investigator
      initiated trial (IIT) of Nivolumab (BMS-936558) combined with Ipilimumab vs standard of care
      in subjects with previously untreated and advanced (unresectable or metastatic) non-clear
      cell renal cell carcinoma (nccRCC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SUNNIFORECAST (Sunitinib vs. Nivolumab + Ipilimumab as First line treatment Of REnal cell
      CAncer of non-clear cell SubTypes) is a Phase II, randomized, open-label investigator
      initiated trial (IIT) of Nivolumab (BMS-936558) combined with Ipilimumab vs standard of care
      in subjects with previously untreated and advanced (unresectable or metastatic) non-clear
      cell renal cell carcinoma (nccRCC). In the Phase I setting, Nivolumab combined with
      Ipilimumab has demonstrated substantially greater clinical activity, as measured by objective
      response rate (ORR), than either agent alone in metastatic RCC (mRCC). Given the durability
      of responses associated with immunotherapies, Nivolumab combined with Ipilimumab is
      hypothesized to lead to greater clinical benefit, as measured by overall survival (OS) rate
      at 12 months as primary endpoint and OS at 6 months and 18 months, progression-free survival
      (PFS), overall survival (OS) and overall response rate (ORR) as secondary endpoints compared
      to standard of care in this patient population. This study will allow for direct comparison
      of OS rate at 12 months between both arms.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival rate at 12 months (OS12) (landmark)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The overall survival rate at 12 months will be compared in both arms. OS is calculated from date of randomization to death.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OS rate at 6 and 18 months in overall population and histological and prognostic subgroups</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>The overall survival rate at 6 and 18 months will be compared in both arms. OS is calculated from date of randomization to death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The overall survival will be compared in both arms by Kaplan-Meyer plots. OS is calculated from date of randomization to death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>PFs will be compared in both arms. PFS is calculated from date of randomization to progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>ORR will be compared in both both arms. ORR will be assessed by regular tumor imaging as CT or magnetic resonance tomography (MRT).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse event (SAEs) will be recorded in both arms and the frequency will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL) as assessed by patient outcome measurement (FKSI-DRS) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life will be assessed during therapy using the FKSI-DRS questionnaire and evaluated over time and in comparison of both arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">306</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab plus nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ipilimumab 1mg/kg plus nivolumab 3mg/kg, both, will be administered i.v. every 3 weeks for 4 times as an induction therapy followed by a maintenance therapy with a flat dose of 240 mg nivolumab biweekly until progression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sunitinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sunitinib will be administered at a starting dose of 50 mg/die p.o. for 4 weeks on and 2 weeks off per cycle until progression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab plus nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Ipilimumab every 3 weeks for 4 times Nivolumab every 3 weeks for 4 times followed by maintenance therapy with nivolumab every 2nd week</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ipilimumab plus nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Yervoy plus Opdivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sunitinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Sunitinib is administered orally 50 mg tablets for 4 weeks on and 2 weeks off</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sunitinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sutent</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed Written Informed Consent a) Subjects must have signed and dated an approved
             written informed consent form according to the Institutional Review Board (IRB) and in
             accordance with regulatory and institutional guidelines. This must be obtained before
             the performance of any protocol related procedures that are not part of normal subject
             care.

             b) Subjects must be willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment
             schedule, laboratory testing, and other requirements of the study.

          2. Target Population a) Histological confirmation of non-clear cell renal cell carcinoma
             (nccRCC) with at least 50% non-clear cell component according to actual World Health
             Organization (WHO) classification.

             b) Advanced (not amenable to curative surgery or radiation therapy) or metastatic
             (AJCC Stage IV) nccRCC c) Performance status: Karnofsky (KPS) &gt; 70% (See Appendix 2,
             14.2) d) Measurable disease as per RECIST v 1.1 (See Appendix 3, 14.3) documented by
             an English radiology report e) Tumor tissue (FFPE archival or recent acquisition) must
             be available and sent to the central pathological reviewer (see Table 6) in order to
             confirm the diagnosis. (Note: Fine Needle Aspiration (FNA) and bone metastases samples
             are not acceptable for submission).

             f) Patients with all risk categories will be eligible for the study. Patients will be
             stratified for papillary or non-papillary non-clear cell histology and IMDC risk score
             Patients will be categorized according to favorable versus intermediate versus poor
             risk status at registration according to the International Metastatic RCC Database
             Consortium (IMDC) criteria: i. KPS equal to 70% ii. &lt; 1 year from diagnosis to
             randomization iii. Hemoglobin &lt; than the lower limit of normal (LLN) iv. Corrected
             calcium concentration greater than the upper limit of normal (ULN) v. Absolute
             neutrophil count greater than the ULN vi. Platelet count greater than the ULN If none
             of the above factors are present, subjects are only eligible for the favorable-risk
             cohort, if 1-2 factors are present subjects are categorized as intermediate risk and &gt;
             3 factors as poor risk.

          3. Age and Reproductive Status

             a) Males and Females, &gt; 18 years of age b) WOCBP must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test (minimum sensitivity 25 IU/L or equivalent units of HCG) within 24
             hours prior to the start of study drug.

             c) Women must not be breastfeeding d) WOCBP must agree to follow instructions for
             method(s) of contraception for a period of 30 days (duration of ovulatory cycle) plus
             the time required for the investigational drug to undergo five half-lives. The
             terminal half-lives of Nivolumab and Ipilimumab are up to 25 days and 18 days,
             respectively. The terminal half-life of the active metabolite of Sunitinib is up to
             110 hours.

             i. WOCBP randomized to receive Nivolumab + Ipilimumab should use an adequate method to
             avoid pregnancy for 23 weeks (30 days plus the time required for Nivolumab to undergo
             five half-lives) after the last dose of investigational drug.

             ii. WOCBP randomized to receive Sunitinib should use an adequate method to avoid
             pregnancy for 8 weeks (30 days plus the time required for the active metabolite of
             Sunitinib to undergo five half-lives) e) Males who are sexually active with WOCBP must
             agree to follow instructions for method(s) of contraception for a period of 90 days
             (duration of sperm turnover) plus the time required for the investigational drug to
             undergo five half-lives. The terminal half lives of Nivolumab and Ipilimumab are up to
             25 days and 18 days, respectively. The terminal half-life of the active metabolite of
             Sunitinib is up to 110 hours.

             i. Males randomized to receive Nivolumab combined with Ipilimumab who are sexually
             active with WOCBP must continue contraception for 31 weeks (90 days plus the time
             required for Nivolumab to undergo five half-lives) after the last dose of
             investigational drug.

             ii. Males randomized to receive Sunitinib who are sexually active and women of
             childbearing potential (WOCBP) must continue contraception for 16 weeks (90 days plus
             the time required for the active metabolite of Sunitinib to undergo five half-lives)
             after the last dose of investigational drug.

             f) Azoospermic males and WOCBP who are continuously not heterosexually active are
             exempt from contraceptive requirements. However they must still undergo pregnancy
             testing as described in this section.

             Investigators shall counsel WOCBP and male subjects who are sexually active with WOCBP
             on the importance of pregnancy prevention and the implications of an unexpected
             pregnancy Investigators shall advise WOCBP and male subjects who are sexually active
             with WOCBP on the use of highly effective methods of contraception. Highly effective
             methods of contraception have a failure rate of &lt; 1% when used consistently and
             correctly.

             At a minimum, subjects must agree to the use of two methods of contraception, with one
             method being highly effective and the other method being either highly effective or
             uncertain effective as listed below:

             HIGHLY EFFECTIVE METHODS OF CONTRACEPTION

             • Male condoms with spermicide

             • Hormonal methods of contraception including combined oral contraceptive pills,
             vaginal ring, injectables, implants and intrauterine devices (IUDs) by WOCBP subject
             or male subject's WOCBP partner

             • Female partners of male subjects participating in the study may use hormone based
             contraceptives as one of the acceptable methods of contraception since they will not
             be receiving study drug

             • Nonhormonal IUDs

               -  Tubal ligation

               -  Vasectomy

               -  Complete Abstinence*

                    -  Complete abstinence is defined as complete avoidance of heterosexual
                       intercourse and is an acceptable form of contraception for all study drugs.
                       Subjects who choose complete abstinence are not required to use a second
                       method of contraception, but female subjects must continue to have pregnancy
                       tests. Acceptable alternate methods of highly effective contraception must
                       be discussed in the event that the subject chooses to forego complete
                       abstinence.

             UNCERTAIN METHODS OF CONTRACEPTION • Diaphragm with spermicide • Cervical cap with
             spermicide

             • Vaginal sponge

             • Male Condom without spermicide

               -  Progestin only pills by WOCBP subject or male subject's WOCBP partner

               -  Female Condom*. * A male and female condom must not be used together

             Exclusion Criteria:

        1. Target Disease Exceptions

          1. Any active brain metastases requiring systemic corticosteroids. Baseline imaging of
             the brain by MRI is required in patients with clinical signs of potential central
             nerve system (CNS) involvement within 28 days prior to randomization.

          2. Tumors with a clear-cell component of &gt; 50%

             Medical History and Concurrent Diseases

          3. Prior systemic treatment with vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) or VEGF
             receptor targeted therapy (including, but not limited to, Sunitinib, pazopanib,
             axitinib, tivozanib, and bevacizumab) or prior treatment with an mammilian target of
             rapamycin (mTOR) inhibitor or cytokines.

          4. Prior treatment with an immune checkpoint inhibitor as anti-programmed cell death
             (PD)PD-1, anti-PD-L1, anti-PD-L2, anti cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated Protein 4
             (CTLA 4) antibody, or any other antibody or drug specifically targeting T-cell
             co-stimulation or checkpoint pathways.

          5. Any active or recent history of a known or suspected autoimmune disease or recent
             history of a syndrome that required systemic corticosteroids (&gt; 10 mg daily prednisone
             equivalent) or immunosuppressive medications except for syndromes which would not be
             expected to recur in the absence of an external trigger. Subjects with vitiligo or
             type I diabetes mellitus or residual hypothyroidism due to autoimmune thyroiditis only
             requiring hormone replacement are permitted to enroll.

          6. Any condition requiring systemic treatment with corticosteroids (&gt; 10 mg daily
             prednisone equivalents) or other immunosuppressive medications within 14 days prior to
             first dose of study drug. Inhaled steroids and adrenal replacement steroid doses &gt; 10
             mg daily prednisone equivalents are permitted in the absence of active autoimmune
             disease.

          7. Uncontrolled adrenal insufficiency.

          8. Ongoing symptomatic cardiac dysrhythmias, uncontrolled atrial fibrillation, or
             prolongation of the Fridericia corrected QT (QTcF) interval defined as &gt; 450 msec for
             males and &gt; 470 msec for females, where QTcF = QT / 3√RR

          9. Poorly controlled hypertension (defined as systolic blood pressure (SBP) of &gt; 150 mmHg
             or diastolic blood pressure (DBP) of &gt; 90 mmHg), despite antihypertensive therapy.

         10. History of any of the following cardiovascular conditions within 12 months of
             enrollment: cardiac angioplasty or stenting, myocardial infarction, unstable angina,
             coronary artery by-pass graft surgery, symptomatic peripheral vascular disease, class
             III or IV congestive heart failure, as defined by the New York Heart Association.

         11. History of cerebrovascular accident including transient ischemic attack within the
             past 12 months.

         12. History of deep vein thrombosis (DVT) unless adequately treated with low molecular
             weight heparin

         13. History of pulmonary embolism within the past 6 months unless stable, asymptomatic,
             and treated with low molecular weight heparin for at least 6 weeks.

         14. History of abdominal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation, or intra-abdominal abscess
             within the past 6 months.

         15. Serious, non-healing wound or ulcer.

         16. Evidence of active bleeding or bleeding susceptibility; or medically significant
             hemorrhage within prior 30 days.

         17. Any requirement for anti-coagulation, except for low molecular weight heparin.

         18. Prior malignancy active within the previous 3 years except for locally curable cancers
             that have been apparently cured, such as basal or squamous cell skin cancer,
             superficial bladder cancer, or carcinoma in situ of the prostate, cervix, or breast.

         19. Known history of testing positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or known
             acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS).

         20. Any positive test for hepatitis B or hepatitis C virus indicating acute or chronic
             infection.

         21. Known medical condition (eg, a condition associated with diarrhea or acute
             diverticulitis) that, in the investigator's opinion, would increase the risk
             associated with study participation or study drug administration or interfere with the
             interpretation of safety results.

         22. Major surgery (eg, nephrectomy) &lt; 28 days prior to the first dose of study drug.

         23. Anti-cancer therapy &lt; 28 days prior to the first dose of study drug or palliative,
             focal radiation therapy &lt; 14 days prior to the first dose of study drug.

         24. Receiving concomitant CYP3A4 inducers or strong CYP3A4 inhibitors (See Appendix 4,
             14.4).

         25. Impairment of gastrointestinal function or gastrointestinal disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of Sunitinib (eg, malabsorptive disorder,
             ulcerative disease, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or small bowel
             resection).

         26. Hypersensitivity to sunitinib or any of the excipients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lothar Bergmann, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Goethe University (Hospital) Frankfurt</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lothar Bergmann, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 69 63015121</phone>
    <email>L.Bergmann@em.uni-frankfurt.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nicola Goekbuget, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 69 63016365</phone>
    <email>goekbuget@em.uni-frankfurt.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Hochschule Hannover</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hannover</city>
        <state>Niedersachsen</state>
        <zip>30625</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Erlangen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Erlangen</city>
        <zip>91054</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stefan Krause, Prof.</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Essen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Goethe University Frankfurt</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt am Main</city>
        <zip>D-60590</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lothar Prof. Dr. med. Bergmann, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+40 69 63015121</phone>
      <email>l.bergmann@em.uni-frankfurt.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nicola Goekbuget, MD</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uiversitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uniklinikum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jena</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinkum Gießen und Marburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum Rechts der Isar der TU München</name>
      <address>
        <city>München</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Muenster</name>
      <address>
        <city>Münster</city>
        <zip>48149</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinik Tübingen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tübingen</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Universitätsklinik Ulm</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulm</city>
        <zip>89070</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Motzer RJ, Escudier B, McDermott DF, George S, Hammers HJ, Srinivas S, Tykodi SS, Sosman JA, Procopio G, Plimack ER, Castellano D, Choueiri TK, Gurney H, Donskov F, Bono P, Wagstaff J, Gauler TC, Ueda T, Tomita Y, Schutz FA, Kollmannsberger C, Larkin J, Ravaud A, Simon JS, Xu LA, Waxman IM, Sharma P; CheckMate 025 Investigators. Nivolumab versus Everolimus in Advanced Renal-Cell Carcinoma. N Engl J Med. 2015 Nov 5;373(19):1803-13. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1510665. Epub 2015 Sep 25.</citation>
    <PMID>26406148</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armstrong AJ, Halabi S, Eisen T, Broderick S, Stadler WM, Jones RJ, Garcia JA, Vaishampayan UN, Picus J, Hawkins RE, Hainsworth JD, Kollmannsberger CK, Logan TF, Puzanov I, Pickering LM, Ryan CW, Protheroe A, Lusk CM, Oberg S, George DJ. Everolimus versus sunitinib for patients with metastatic non-clear cell renal cell carcinoma (ASPEN): a multicentre, open-label, randomised phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol. 2016 Mar;17(3):378-88. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(15)00515-X. Epub 2016 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>26794930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vera-Badillo FE, Templeton AJ, Duran I, Ocana A, de Gouveia P, Aneja P, Knox JJ, Tannock IF, Escudier B, Amir E. Systemic therapy for non-clear cell renal cell carcinomas: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Eur Urol. 2015 Apr;67(4):740-9. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2014.05.010. Epub 2014 Jun 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24882670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 6, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Goethe University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nicola Goekbuget</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr.med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sunitinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

