<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03073551</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REB 10-188</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03073551</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of Activity Promoting Video Games on Glycemic Control in Gestational Diabetes Mellitus</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of Activity Promoting Video Games on Glycemic Control in Gestational Diabetes Mellitus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) affects up to 3-5% of all pregnancies. When diagnosed
      with GDM, women undergo nutritional counseling, blood sugars monitoring and are encouraged to
      exercise regularly. Women who do not meet therapeutic targets may need to add insulin
      injections. Activity promoting video games are an attractive possibility for improvement of
      exercise compliance. The objective of this study is to determine whether providing women
      recently diagnosed with GDM with a Nintendo Wii™ activity promoting gaming platform will
      increase activity levels, improve glycemic control of sugar levels and decrease the need for
      supplementary insulin treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      As part of the standard of care, all pregnant women are screened with a 50 gram glucose
      challenge test between 24-28 weeks gestation. Women are diagnosed with GDM when they have two
      abnormal values on the 75 gram oral glucose tolerance test. Once a diagnosis of GDM has been
      made women are referred to the diabetes in pregnancy clinic within 1-2 weeks. All women
      initially undergo a group session with a clinical nutritionist and a registered nurse
      specializing in diabetic care. During this session women receive basic information regarding
      gestational diabetes, instruction regarding dietary management of GDM and standard
      recommendations regarding physical activity. Women also routinely receive a glucometer for
      self monitoring of glucose levels and are instructed regarding its use. One week after this
      group session an intake session with an endocrinologist and Maternal-Fetal Medicine
      specialist occurs and glycemic control is reviewed. Follow up visits are scheduled every 1-4
      weeks depending on adequacy of glycemic control. Decisions regarding adequacy of dietary
      management and need for insulin therapy are made by the endocrinologist at each subsequent
      visit.

      For the purpose of our study, patients will be approached after this group teaching session.
      Eligible patients who have consented to participate in the study will undergo randomization
      into two groups:

        1. Control - routine GDM care as mentioned above.

        2. Intervention - This group will undergo all aspects of routine GDM care but will also
           receive a Nintendo Wii gaming console + Wii Fit activity platform. The games provided
           include &quot;Wii sport&quot; and Wii Fit Plus&quot;. Each participant will receive a 30-60 minute
           guided information session to ensure that she is able to install the console at home and
           to set up her personal login information. At this session an overview of the available
           Wii activities will be presented. Each participant will receive a telephone number to
           call in case technical difficulties are encountered at home. At 36 weeks of gestation,
           the Wii hardware and programs will be returned to the investigators. Participants will
           be instructed to note the following warning signs for termination of the exercise
           session; vaginal bleeding, dyspnea before exertion, dizziness, headache, chest pain,
           muscle weakness, calf pain or swelling, preterm labor, decreased fetal movement, and
           amniotic fluid leakage.

      As mentioned, all participants in the study will be encouraged to be physically active. In
      order to independently calculate and compare the overall level of physical activity in both
      groups all participating women will receive a pedometer (StepsCount Digi-Walker SW700) and
      will be instructed to wear it daily during waking hours.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 27, 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 1, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 1, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The control group will receive diabetes treatment and education as per standard of care.
The intervention group will receive diabetes treatment and education as per standard of care, and will also be given a Wii game console to bring home.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from study intake date until 36 weeks gestation</time_frame>
    <description>Mean fasting and post-prandial glucose levels</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from study intake date until 36 weeks gestation</time_frame>
    <description>Need for insulin therapy to control insulin levels</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity level</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from study intake date until 36 weeks gestation</time_frame>
    <description>Level of daily physical activity performed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal weight gain</measure>
    <time_frame>Weight gained during pregnancy, measured from start of pregnancy (1 week gestation) to end of pregnancy (up to 40 weeks gestation).</time_frame>
    <description>Measured as the amount of weight gained from time of conception to time of delivery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Gestational Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will receive diabetic care and education as per the standard of care. They will also be given a pedometer and will be instructed to record their number of steps at the end of each day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wii Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will receive diabetic care and education as per the standard of care. They will also be given a Wii console and game to take home. Participants will be instructed on how to set up and use the Wii. These participants will also be given a pedometer and will be instructed to record their number of steps at the end of each day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Wii Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the Wii group will be given a Wii console and video game to take home. The console includes a Wii balance board and remote controller. The Wii Fit game allows participants to choose different types of exercise such as yoga, aerobics, balance training, and more. Participant movements are shown on screen as they move with the balance board and remote control.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Wii Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women diagnosed with gestational diabetes and a singleton pregnancy at 24-36 weeks of
             gestation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Multiple gestation

          -  Pre-gestational diabetes

          -  Unable to provide informed consent

          -  Any contraindication to performing physical activity in pregnancy (e.g. increased risk
             of preterm delivery)

          -  Has and regularly uses a Nintendo Wii console

          -  Presence of co-morbidities including: Hypertension (systolic pressure &gt; 160 mmHg
             and/or diastolic pressure &gt; 100 mmHg), alcohol abuse (i.e. 2 glasses alcohol or more
             per day); drug abuse, use of the medication that affects insulin secretion or insulin
             sensitivity (antiviral, corticosteroids, antihypertensive drugs, all concomitant
             medication will be discussed); serious pulmonary (COPD, exercise induced asthma),
             cardiac, hepatic or renal (serum creatinine &gt; 150 μmol/l) impairment; malignant
             disease; serious mental or physical impairment (limiting the ability to understand or
             implement the study protocol).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Participants must be pregnant women</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Howard Berger, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 3, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes, Gestational</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

