<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03075033</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Shikani2017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03075033</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SOS Versus Awake Fiberoptic Intubation</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Shikani Optical Stylet As An Alternative To Awake Fiberoptic Intubation In Patients At Risk Of Secondary Cervical Spine Injury - A Randomized Controlled Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Faculty of Medicine, University of Alexandria</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Faculty of Medicine, University of Alexandria</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Conventional intubation of the trachea and consequent prone positioning of
      anaesthetized patients with cervical spine instability may result in secondary neurological
      injury. Historically, the flexible fiber-optics used to be the chief choice for patients
      presenting with cervical spine instability surgery either with normal, predicted difficult
      airway, or even unanticipated difficult airway. Recently, the rigid optical stylets have
      shown promise in assisting difficult intubations.

      Purpose: The aim of the present study was to compare the efficacy of Shikani optical stylet
      (SOS) with the flexible fiberscope for awake intubation in patients with cervical spine
      instability.

      Methods: Sixty adult patients with a neurosurgical diagnosis of cervical instability or at
      risk of secondary cervical injury, who were planned for awake intubation and self-positioning
      prone, were registered in this study and were randomly categorized into two equal groups
      (thirty patients each), a fiberoptic group and a SOS group, then assessment of coughing and
      gagging during and after intubation, time to intubation, number of attempts for successful
      intubation, haemodynamic parameters, careful examination of the oropharynx to determine any
      lip or mucosal trauma, and eventually the motor function by the ability to move arms and legs
      were assessed after tracheal intubation and after positioning prone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim of the work:

      The aim of this study was to compare the efficacy of shikani optical stylet with the flexible
      fiberoptic bronchoscope for awake intubation in patients with cervical spine instability.

      Patients and Methods:

      This prospective, randomized study was approved by the local ethical committee of Alexandria
      main university hospital. Written informed consent was obtained from all the participants.
      Sixty patients aged 18-65 year with American Society of Anaesthesiologists physical status
      I-III with a neurosurgical diagnosis of cervical instability or at risk of secondary cervical
      injury, who were scheduled for awake intubation and self-positioning prone for elective
      neurological intervention, were enrolled in this study. Patients with increased risk of
      pulmonary aspiration, requirement for rapid sequence induction or associated head injury
      precluding adequate clinical neurological examination were excluded from the study. All
      patients received rigid neck collar. Data collected from each patient included demographic
      data, level of cervical spine pathology and the neurological status.

      An assistant who wasn't concerned within this study got numbered opaque pre-sealed envelopes
      containing the randomised group allocations after every patient was joined into the study.
      Patients were randomly assigned into either a fiberoptic group (30) or a Shikani group (30)
      utilizing a sealed-envelope technique.

      Anaesthetists concerned within the study had expertise with both devices and were assured in
      consuming the devices in a difficult airway situation.

      Routin pre-anaesthetic assessments were performed, in addition to a standard airway
      assessment, recording the presence of any oro-pharyngeal injury before surgery. Non-invasive
      monitoring was used before intubation comprising pulse oximetry, blood pressure and
      electrocardiography. Before starting topical anaesthesia, all patients were given atropine
      0.4 mg as an anti sialagogue agent, midazolam 2 mg and increments of fentanyl 25mic
      intravenously till the patient is calm and sedated but controlling his airway.

      Topical anaesthesia of the oral cavity was performed with lidocaine 10% spray. Anesthesia of
      the larynx just above the vocal cords, vocal cords and the upper trachea was encountered with
      superior laryngeal nerves block using 4 ml of 2% lidocaine (2 ml on each side), at the
      lateral ends of the thyrohyoid membrane just beneath the greater cornu of the hyoid bone and
      recurrent laryngeal nerve block (Trans-tracheal injection) using a 20-gauge plastic catheter,
      4ml of 2% lidocaine through the cricothyroid membrane at the end of inspiration.

      Tracheal intubation was then executed with either the flexible fiberoptic bronchoscope or the
      Shikani optical stylet, according to the randomised allocation. The shikani optical stylet
      was bent to the same bend as a Mackintosh laryngoscope blade, lubricated and the endotracheal
      tube was mounted on it. The tube was settled to the stylet by the 'adjustable tube stop' so
      that the tip of the stylet did not project beyond the end of the tube. The anaesthetist hold
      and elevated the mandible using the left hand, the patient was asked to protrude his tongue
      if applicable and the stylet was introduced into the right side of the mouth and advanced
      until the tip was in hypopharynx. Then, under direct vision the tip was inserted between the
      vocal cords.The 'tube stop' was released and the tube was unmounted into the trachea; the
      stylet was removed. Once tracheal intubation was accomplished, confirmation of the position
      of endotracheal tube by capnography and chest auscultation. The patients were then asked to
      move to the prone position on the bolsters, in the cases planned for posterior approach of
      the cervical spine. The anaesthesia provider guarded the head and tube during the move and
      neurological examination was repeated. Once the position is settled, the presence of end
      tidal carbon dioxide was confirmed and general anaesthesia was set up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This prospective, randomized study was approved by the local ethical committee of Alexandria main university hospital. Written informed consent was obtained from all the participants. Sixty patients aged 18-65 year with American Society of Anaesthesiologists physical status I-III with a neurosurgical diagnosis of cervical instability or at risk of secondary cervical injury, who were scheduled for awake intubation and self-positioning prone for elective neurological intervention, were enrolled in this study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Coughing and gagging</measure>
    <time_frame>during and after intubation</time_frame>
    <description>using a scale of 1 to 4: (1= none; 2 &lt; 3 times (slight coughing and gagging comparable to &quot;clearing ones throat&quot;); 3 &gt; 2 times (mild coughing or gagging lasting less than a minute); 4 = persistent coughing or gagging]</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>the interval from the start of intubation to the completion of intubation</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the time in minutes from the start of intubation to the completion of intubation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of attempts for successful intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>During intubation</time_frame>
    <description>How many trials were taken till achieve the intubation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The changes in the haemodynamic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-induction, pre-intubation and at 3 and 5 min after intubation</time_frame>
    <description>the haemodynamic parameters including: heart rate, systolic and diastolic blood pressures during the intubation process with readings taken pre-induction, pre-intubation and at 3 and 5 min after intubation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Spine Instability</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SOS gruop</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Use of The Shikani Optical Stylet In Patients At Risk Of Secondary Cervical Spine Injury</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Awake Fiberoptic Intubation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Use of Awake Fiberoptic Intubation In Patients At Risk Of Secondary Cervical Spine Injury</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Shikani optical stylet</intervention_name>
    <description>Tracheal intubation is performed using Shikani optical stylet. The shikani optical stylet was bent to the same bend as a Mackintosh laryngoscope blade, lubricated and the endotracheal tube was mounted on it. The tube was settled to the stylet by the 'adjustable tube stop' so that the tip of the stylet did not project beyond the end of the tube. After intubation the 'tube stop' was released and the tube was unmounted into the trachea; the stylet was removed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SOS gruop</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Flexible fiberoptic bronchoscope for</intervention_name>
    <description>AwakeRracheal intubation using flexible fiberoptic bronchoscope in patients with cervical spine instability</description>
    <arm_group_label>Awake Fiberoptic Intubation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Society of Anaesthesiologists physical status I-III with a neurosurgical
             diagnosis of cervical instability or at risk of secondary cervical injury, who were
             scheduled for awake intubation and self-positioning prone for elective neurological
             intervention

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with increased risk of pulmonary aspiration, requirement for rapid sequence
             induction or associated head injury precluding adequate clinical neurological
             examination were excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 3, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, University of Alexandria</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rabab Sber Saleh Mahrous</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Shikani optical stylet, rigid optical stylets, awake, fiber-optic intubation, and cervical spine injury.</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

