<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03074422</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-01843</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03074422</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness and Reliability of Hypnosis in Stereotaxy</brief_title>
  <acronym>ERST</acronym>
  <official_title>Effectiveness and Reliability of Hypnosis in Stereotaxy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Geneva</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Geneva</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In certain neurosurgical procedures, the use of a stereotaxic frame is required. It is then
      possible to set a precise target (depending of the type of the surgery) to be reached by the
      surgeon. The fixation of the stereotactic frame on the awake patient's head is done under
      local anesthesia by screwing the frame directly into the skull. This procedure is reported as
      &quot;painful&quot; to &quot;extremely painful&quot; by patients. The objective of this study is to determine
      whether the hypnosis is effective in decreasing the pain perceived by the patient during the
      disposal of the stereotactic frame.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The role of hypnosis (no sedative drug administered) and hypnosedative procedures (hypnosis
      with the adjunct of a sedative drug) during surgical procedures has been largely discussed
      during the past 10 years, and those techniques are now widely practiced in the surgical
      field, for example during thyroidectomies. In neurosurgery specifically, the successful use
      of hypnosedation during awake neurosurgical procedures has been recently reported, with a
      positive feedback from the patients, together with good results regarding extent of
      resection, in the case of brain lesions located in eloquent areas.

      Since 1990, many research groups identified the existence of hypnosis-related phenomena and
      their influence on the pain signal perception. These authors show that there is a modulation
      of the anterior cingulate area activity together with modified interconnectivity with other
      critical regions involved in nociception. In this context, the potential of hypnosis in pain
      modulation and, more extensively, patient management in surgical anesthetics was established.

      In various neurosurgical procedures, the use of a stereotactic frame is required; by using
      coordinates (x, y and z), which are computed and reported on the frame before the
      intervention, it is possible to set a precise target (dependent on the type of surgery) to be
      reached by the surgeon. For instance, during a Deep Brain Stimulation (DBS) performed in a
      patient suffering from Parkinson's disease (PD), the electrodes are introduced into the
      brain, deep down to the sub-thalamic nuclei (STN), which are situated in a very little area
      located in the upper brainstem. The mounting of the stereotactic frame on the patient's head
      is performed under local anesthesia (LA), as the patient is awake during the mounting
      procedure and later on during the surgical intervention. This mounting is done by screwing
      the device directly into the patient's skull, through the skin. This moment is reported as
      &quot;painful&quot; to &quot;extremely painful&quot; by patients, and most of them confess to keep a very
      unpleasant memory of the event, even several years after the procedure and despite the fact
      that the surgery had a positive effect on their functional outcome.

      As exposed above, there is still room for improvement in the management of pain and comfort
      of patients undergoing functional procedures in neurosurgery, especially during the placement
      of the stereotactic frame. To our opinion, hypnosis could represent a serious therapy against
      pain and anxiety generated by the frame fixation, especially those whom facial expressions
      and feelings might be altered by their pathology (i.e. Parkinson's disease). In fact, this
      technique has already been abundantly reported as an important adjuvant to the management of
      pain and comfort during surgeries such as thyroidectomies) and resection of brain tumors.

      The main objective of this study is to determine whether hypnosis is effective in decreasing
      the pain perceived by the patient during the placement of the stereotactic frame on the
      patient's head.

      The secondary aims of this study are: 1) to measure the stress perceived during the procedure
      by submitting the patient to validated scores and 2) to evaluate the incidence of
      Post-traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD), according to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of
      Mental Disorders IV (DSM-IV) criteria.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients will be randomly attributed to either the &quot;hypnosis&quot; group or the control group, by a randomization process. The investigators plan to allocate patients in two groups; in the first group, patients will undergo hypnosis during the fixation of the stereotactic frame. In the second group (control group), the frame disposal will be performed following the actual standard of care, with a LA performed during the procedure.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>No masking</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on pain</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To determine whether the hypnosis is effective in decreasing the pain perceived by the patient during the placement of the stereotactic frame on the patient's head.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on the stress perceived during the procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To measure the stress perceived during the procedure by submitting the patient to validated scores .</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on the incidence of post-traumatic stress disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the incidence of Post-traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD), according to the DSM-IV criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <condition>Tremor, Essential</condition>
  <condition>Dystonia, Primary</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypsnosis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During the fixation of the stereotactic frame, a single hypnosis session is performed by a certified senior anesthesiologist. Blood pressure, heart rate and respiratory rate are continuously monitored by the mean of a regular scope. Pain perceived during and after the procedure is quantifies by the mean of the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) questionnaire. An open, standardized question will be asked to participants concerning feelings and thoughts about the frame fixation. Answers will be audio recorded. A standardized perceived distress questionnaire (PDI-13) will be performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Local anesthesia after clear and complete information of the procedure given the day prior to the surgery. In order to determine the pain perceived during the procedure, a VAS questionnaire will be used, directly after the frame disposal. The rest of the procédure is similar to the hypnosis group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hypnosis</intervention_name>
    <description>Hypnosis session performed by a board certified senior anesthesiologist during the frame fixation on the patient's head.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hypsnosis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients undergoing a stereotactic procedure as listed previously

          -  Patients ≥ 18 y.o.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients &lt; 18 y.o.

          -  Patients unable to take decisions by their own

          -  Patients undergoing deep brain stimulation for obsessive-compulsive disease treatment

          -  Patients refusing to participate to the study

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Invasive monitoring of epilepsy

          -  Psychiatric comorbidity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marco Corniola</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Geneva</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marco Corniola</last_name>
    <phone>0795533770</phone>
    <phone_ext>0041</phone_ext>
    <email>marco.corniola@hcuge.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sabina Catalano-Chiuvé</last_name>
    <phone>022372837</phone>
    <phone_ext>0041</phone_ext>
    <email>sabina.catalano@hcuge.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Geneva University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Geneva</city>
        <zip>1211 Genève 14</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marco Corniola</last_name>
      <phone>795533770</phone>
      <phone_ext>0041</phone_ext>
      <email>marco.corniola@hcuge.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sabina Catalano</last_name>
      <phone>0223728317</phone>
      <phone_ext>0041</phone_ext>
      <email>sabina.catalano@hcuge.ch</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang DD, Lau D, Rolston JD, Englot DJ, Sneed PK, McDermott MW. Pain experience using conventional versus angled anterior posts during stereotactic head frame placement for radiosurgery. J Clin Neurosci. 2014 Sep;21(9):1538-42. doi: 10.1016/j.jocn.2014.02.009. Epub 2014 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24814855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rahman M, Murad GJ, Mocco J. Early history of the stereotactic apparatus in neurosurgery. Neurosurg Focus. 2009 Sep;27(3):E12. doi: 10.3171/2009.7.FOCUS09118.</citation>
    <PMID>19722814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murata J, Sawamura Y, Kitagawa M, Saito H, Kikuchi S, Tashiro K. [Minimally invasive stereotactic functional surgery using an intravenous anesthetic propofol and applying Image Fusion and AtlasPlan]. No To Shinkei. 2001 May;53(5):457-62. Japanese.</citation>
    <PMID>11424357</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Venkatraghavan L, Manninen P, Mak P, Lukitto K, Hodaie M, Lozano A. Anesthesia for functional neurosurgery: review of complications. J Neurosurg Anesthesiol. 2006 Jan;18(1):64-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16369142</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stokes MA, Soriano SG, Tarbell NJ, Loeffler JS, Alexander E 3rd, Black PM, Rockoff MA. Anesthesia for stereotactic radiosurgery in children. J Neurosurg Anesthesiol. 1995 Apr;7(2):100-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7772962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benabid AL, Chabardes S, Mitrofanis J, Pollak P. Deep brain stimulation of the subthalamic nucleus for the treatment of Parkinson's disease. Lancet Neurol. 2009 Jan;8(1):67-81. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(08)70291-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19081516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benabid AL, Chabardès S, Seigneuret E, Fraix V, Krack P, Pollak P, Xia R, Wallace B, Sauter F. Surgical therapy for Parkinson's disease. J Neural Transm Suppl. 2006;(70):383-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17017557</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chevrier E, Fraix V, Krack P, Chabardes S, Benabid AL, Pollak P. Is there a role for physiotherapy during deep brain stimulation surgery in patients with Parkinson's disease? Eur J Neurol. 2006 May;13(5):496-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16722975</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fraix V, Pollak P, Chabardes S, Ardouin C, Koudsie A, Benazzouz A, Krack P, Batir A, Le Bas JF, Benabid AL. [Deep brain stimulation]. Rev Neurol (Paris). 2004 May;160(5 Pt 1):511-21. Review. French.</citation>
    <PMID>15269668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benabid AL, Pollak P, Hommel M, Gaio JM, de Rougemont J, Perret J. [Treatment of Parkinson tremor by chronic stimulation of the ventral intermediate nucleus of the thalamus]. Rev Neurol (Paris). 1989;145(4):320-3. French.</citation>
    <PMID>2660224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cojan Y, Waber L, Schwartz S, Rossier L, Forster A, Vuilleumier P. The brain under self-control: modulation of inhibitory and monitoring cortical networks during hypnotic paralysis. Neuron. 2009 Jun 25;62(6):862-75. doi: 10.1016/j.neuron.2009.05.021.</citation>
    <PMID>19555654</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zemmoura I, Fournier E, El-Hage W, Jolly V, Destrieux C, Velut S. Hypnosis for Awake Surgery of Low-grade Gliomas: Description of the Method and Psychological Assessment. Neurosurgery. 2016 Jan;78(1):53-61. doi: 10.1227/NEU.0000000000000993.</citation>
    <PMID>26313220</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tykocki T, Kornakiewicz A, Mandat T, Nauman P. Pain perception in patients with Parkinson's disease. J Clin Neurosci. 2013 May;20(5):663-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jocn.2012.05.043. Epub 2013 Feb 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23485408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watson R, Leslie K. Nerve blocks versus subcutaneous infiltration for stereotactic frame placement. Anesth Analg. 2001 Feb;92(2):424-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11159245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bellinghausen L, Collange J, Botella M, Emery JL, Albert E. [Factorial validation of the French scale for perceived stress in the workplace]. Sante Publique. 2009 Jul-Aug;21(4):365-73. French.</citation>
    <PMID>20101815</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jehel L, Brunet A, Paterniti S, Guelfi JD. [Validation of the Peritraumatic Distress Inventory's French translation]. Can J Psychiatry. 2005 Jan;50(1):67-71. French.</citation>
    <PMID>15754668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 3, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital, Geneva</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marco Vincenzo Corniola</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief Medical Officer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Functional neurosurgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain management</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypnosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Stereotaxy</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Essential tremor</keyword>
  <keyword>Dystonia</keyword>
  <keyword>Invasive monitoring of epilepsy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tremor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Essential Tremor</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

