<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03077386</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REB17-0360</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03077386</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enhancing Community Health Through Patient Navigation, Advocacy and Social Support</brief_title>
  <acronym>ENCOMPASS</acronym>
  <official_title>Enhancing Community Health Through Patient Navigation, Advocacy and Social Support</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Calgary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alberta Innovates Health Solutions</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Diabetes Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Calgary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In Canada, the prevalence of chronic disease is increasing and patients presenting with
      multiple conditions (i.e., multimorbidity) are becoming the norm in primary care. Complex
      treatment regimens such as administration of medications (including insulin), clinical
      monitoring and screening for complications, adherence to dietary and lifestyle changes, and
      decisions about when to seek medical care are challenging. To help people with complex health
      conditions optimize their care and outcomes, community health worker programs have begun to
      be used across the United States and Canada. Existing community health worker programs share
      a common goal of helping patients to overcome modifiable barriers to care to achieve optimal
      outcomes.

      While community health workers may work within a primary health care team, the primary role
      of the community health worker is not clinically oriented, and may be fulfilled by
      laypersons. Depending on the targeted barriers, specific tasks may include one or more of:
      disease education, health system education, assistance with insurance coverage, aid in care
      coordination, and referral to community resources, among others. Herein, the investigators
      aim to evaluate the effectiveness of a community health worker intervention on improving
      acute care utilization among patients with complex chronic disease seen in primary care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic diseases are long--term conditions that progress in severity over time and are
      generally not curable. Results from the Canadian Community Health Survey (CCHS) indicate that
      approximately 21% of adults over 20 years had at least one major chronic disease. Among
      these, approximately 10% had diabetes, 6% had cardiovascular disease, 4% had heart failure,
      and 10% had asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disorder, reported by the Canadian
      Chronic Disease Surveillance System. In 2012-13, over 735,000 Albertans had at least one
      major chronic disease, and publicly funded health services for these patients cost the
      Alberta government approximately $4.5 billion dollars in that year.

      In Canada, the prevalence of chronic disease is increasing and patients presenting with
      multiple conditions (i.e., multimorbidity) are becoming the norm in primary care.
      Multimorbidity is associated with poor quality of life, decline in functional status, and a
      high burden on the healthcare system. Safe, efficacious and cost--effective interventions for
      chronic diseases are available, however these treatments are under-utilized. Individuals with
      chronic diseases may have difficulty achieving care goals due to a combination of patient,
      provider and system level barriers. Complex treatment regimens such as administration of
      medications (including insulin), clinical monitoring and screening for complications,
      adherence to dietary and lifestyle changes, and decisions about when to seek medical care are
      challenging. The ability to comply with these recommendations is dependent on a number of
      factors, including health and financial status, access to care and care experience, and
      personal circumstance.

      To help people with complex health conditions optimize their care and outcomes, community
      health worker programs have begun to be used across the United States and Canada. Existing
      community health worker programs share a common goal of helping patients to overcome
      modifiable barriers to care to achieve optimal outcomes, and are a possible solution to
      overcoming barriers to accessing health care in patients with complex chronic disease.

      While community health workers may work within a primary health care team, the primary role
      of the community health worker is not clinically oriented, and may be fulfilled by
      laypersons. Depending on the targeted barriers, specific tasks may include one or more of:
      disease education, health system education, assistance with insurance coverage, aid in care
      coordination, and referral to community resources, among others. Herein, the investigators
      propose a trial to evaluate the effectiveness of a community health worker intervention on
      improving acute care utilization among patients with complex chronic disease seen in primary
      care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The investigators will test the effectiveness of the ENCOMPASS program using a parallel, two-arm, pragmatic, cluster-randomized trial in 8 clusters made up of 10 primary care clinics, with a target population size of 800 patients with chronic disease. A CHW will be assigned to each cluster at a ratio of approximately one CHW per five physicians. Consistent with other programs [33], and because the program aims to improve patient activation [34], individual patients will receive the CHW intervention for up to six months unless patient circumstance requires flexibility. Once implemented, the ENCOMPASS program will remain available to clinic patients until the end of the funding period (March 2020). Control patients will continue to receive usual care until their clinic becomes eligible for the program.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute care utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>All emergency department visits and hospital admissions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D-5L (Euroqol 5 dimension- 5 level instrument) administration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-specific intermediate health outcomes (hypertension)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure based on primary data collection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-specific intermediate health outcomes (diabetes)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Hemoglobin A1c based on laboratory data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-specific intermediate health outcomes (chronic kidney disease)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated Glomular Filtration Rate based on laboratory data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-specific intermediate health outcomes (ischemic heart disease)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description># exacerbation based on administrative data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-specific intermediate health outcomes (coronary heart failure)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description># exacerbation based on administrative data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-specific intermediate health outcomes- Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, asthma</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description># exacerbation based on administrative data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient activation measure (PAM) administration via survey questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient experience with chronic illness care</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient assessment of chronic illness care (PACIC) administration via survey questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary care attachment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Usual provider of care index (UPC) based on physician claims data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician experience</measure>
    <time_frame>6- and 12-months post-implementation</time_frame>
    <description>Open-ended questions via semi-structured interview</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmaceutical information network (PIN) administrative data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>All-cause mortality based on administrative data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Weight based on primary data collection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social support</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Social support based on Medical Outcomes Study Social Support Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Kidney Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Ischemic Heart Disease</condition>
  <condition>Congestive Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Community Health Worker Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients enrolled in the intervention will be matched to a Community Health Worker (CHW) from their primary care practice. Based on an initial needs assessment, patients receiving the intervention will have support from a CHW with any of the following: scheduling appointments, language interpretation, obtaining financial and social resources, filling out forms, health system navigation, transportation facilitation, barrier identification, patient advocacy, understanding of treatment plans and communication with health care providers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients not enrolled in the intervention will continue to receive care as usual until their clinic receives the intervention (determined by lottery).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community Health Worker Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be matched to a CHW from their primary care practice. The CHW will conduct a needs assessment to determine the intensity of intervention and frequency of meetings needed. A CHW may perform any of the following: providing information directly to a patient's health care provider, translating to the patient's language, advocating for the patient, connecting the patient with resources (i.e., social, financial, insurance), helping patients set health--related goals, liaising with a patient's employer to make sure the patient's health needs are met, facilitating health care referrals and appointments, monitoring appointments, and facilitating transportation to appointments. These activities may require the CHW to be physically present at the patient's appointments or have direct contact with the patient's health care provider. Goal setting and social support will be provided in- person or over the telephone using motivational interviewing (MI) principles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Community Health Worker Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        ≥ 18 years of age with two or more of the following, as identified in the clinic EMR:

        (i) Poorly controlled hypertension (most recent systolic blood pressure &gt; 160 mmHg); (ii)
        Poorly controlled diabetes (A1C &gt; 9% on at least one occasion within the past year); (iii)
        Stage 3b or greater chronic kidney disease (estimated glomerular filtration rate &lt; 45
        mL/min/1.73m2 in past year); (iv) Established ischemic heart disease (at least one instance
        of a physician billing diagnosis with a relevant International Classification of Diseases,
        9th Edition [ICD-9] code recorded in EMR); (v) Congestive heart failure (at least one
        instance of a physician billing diagnosis with a relevant ICD-9 code recorded in EMR); (vi)
        Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease OR Asthma with at least two visits in the past year
        (at least 2 instances of a physician billing diagnosis with a relevant ICD-9 code).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        i) patient unable to provide informed consent; ii) patient residing in a long-term care
        facility; iii) physician discretion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kerry A McBrien, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Calgary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gabriel Fabreau, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Calgary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ana Mladenovic, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>780-394-8823</phone>
    <email>ana.mladenovic@ucalgary.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mosaic Primary Care Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachel AC Clare, MSW</last_name>
      <phone>403-464-3145</phone>
      <email>rachel.clare@mosaicpcn.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Amanda Brockmann, MHA</last_name>
      <phone>403-700-4286</phone>
      <email>amanda.brockmann@mosaicpcn.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Public Health Agency of Canada. Chronic Disease and Injury Framework Quick Stats, 2016 Edition. Retreived from http://www.phac-aspc.gc.ca/publicat/hpcdp-pspmc/36-8/assets/pdf/ar-04-eng.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saher, MN (2014). Report of the Auditor General of Alberta: Health- Chronic Disease Management. Edmonton, AB: Office of the Auditor General of Alberta.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fortin M, Bravo G, Hudon C, Vanasse A, Lapointe L. Prevalence of multimorbidity among adults seen in family practice. Ann Fam Med. 2005 May-Jun;3(3):223-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15928225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bayliss EA, Bayliss MS, Ware JE Jr, Steiner JF. Predicting declines in physical function in persons with multiple chronic medical conditions: what we can learn from the medical problem list. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2004 Sep 7;2:47.</citation>
    <PMID>15353000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Condelius A, Edberg AK, Jakobsson U, Hallberg IR. Hospital admissions among people 65+ related to multimorbidity, municipal and outpatient care. Arch Gerontol Geriatr. 2008 Jan-Feb;46(1):41-55. Epub 2007 Apr 2.</citation>
    <PMID>17403548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fortin M, Lapointe L, Hudon C, Vanasse A, Ntetu AL, Maltais D. Multimorbidity and quality of life in primary care: a systematic review. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2004 Sep 20;2:51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15380021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Manns BJ, Tonelli M, Zhang J, Campbell DJ, Sargious P, Ayyalasomayajula B, Clement F, Johnson JA, Laupacis A, Lewanczuk R, McBrien K, Hemmelgarn BR. Enrolment in primary care networks: impact on outcomes and processes of care for patients with diabetes. CMAJ. 2012 Feb 7;184(2):E144-52. doi: 10.1503/cmaj.110755. Epub 2011 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22143232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAlister FA, Majumdar SR, Eurich DT, Johnson JA. The effect of specialist care within the first year on subsequent outcomes in 24,232 adults with new-onset diabetes mellitus: population-based cohort study. Qual Saf Health Care. 2007 Feb;16(1):6-11.</citation>
    <PMID>17301194</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah BR, Hux JE, Austin PC. Diabetes is not treated as a coronary artery disease risk equivalent. Diabetes Care. 2007 Feb;30(2):381-3.</citation>
    <PMID>17259516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sirois C, Moisan J, Poirier P, Grégoire JP. Suboptimal use of cardioprotective drugs in newly treated elderly individuals with type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2007 Jul;30(7):1880-2. Epub 2007 Mar 23.</citation>
    <PMID>17384345</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Supina AL, Guirguis LM, Majumdar SR, Lewanczuk RZ, Lee TK, Toth EL, Johnson JA. Treatment gaps for hypertension management in rural Canadian patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Clin Ther. 2004 Apr;26(4):598-606.</citation>
    <PMID>15189757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tonelli M, Bohm C, Pandeya S, Gill J, Levin A, Kiberd BA. Cardiac risk factors and the use of cardioprotective medications in patients with chronic renal insufficiency. Am J Kidney Dis. 2001 Mar;37(3):484-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11228171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tonelli M, Gill J, Pandeya S, Bohm C, Levin A, Kiberd BA. Barriers to blood pressure control and angiotensin enzyme inhibitor use in Canadian patients with chronic renal insufficiency. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2002 Aug;17(8):1426-33.</citation>
    <PMID>12147790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toth EL, Majumdar SR, Guirguis LM, Lewanczuk RZ, Lee TK, Johnson JA. Compliance with clinical practice guidelines for type 2 diabetes in rural patients: treatment gaps and opportunities for improvement. Pharmacotherapy. 2003 May;23(5):659-65.</citation>
    <PMID>12741441</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ronksley PE, Sanmartin C, Campbell DJ, Weaver RG, Allan GM, McBrien KA, Tonelli M, Manns BJ, Hennessy D, Hemmelgarn BR. Perceived barriers to primary care among western Canadians with chronic conditions. Health Rep. 2014 Apr;25(4):3-10.</citation>
    <PMID>24744042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freeman HP. The history, principles, and future of patient navigation: commentary. Semin Oncol Nurs. 2013 May;29(2):72-5. doi: 10.1016/j.soncn.2013.02.002.</citation>
    <PMID>23651676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walkinshaw E. Patient navigators becoming the norm in Canada. CMAJ. 2011 Oct 18;183(15):E1109-10. doi: 10.1503/cmaj.109-3974. Epub 2011 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21930738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parker VA, Lemak CH. Navigating patient navigation: crossing health services research and clinical boundaries. Adv Health Care Manag. 2011;11:149-83. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22908669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pedersen A, Hack TF. Pilots of oncology health care: a concept analysis of the patient navigator role. Oncol Nurs Forum. 2010 Jan;37(1):55-60. doi: 10.1188/10.ONF.55-60.</citation>
    <PMID>20044339</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wells KJ, Battaglia TA, Dudley DJ, Garcia R, Greene A, Calhoun E, Mandelblatt JS, Paskett ED, Raich PC; Patient Navigation Research Program. Patient navigation: state of the art or is it science? Cancer. 2008 Oct 15;113(8):1999-2010. doi: 10.1002/cncr.23815. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18780320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fischer SM, Sauaia A, Kutner JS. Patient navigation: a culturally competent strategy to address disparities in palliative care. J Palliat Med. 2007 Oct;10(5):1023-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17985954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shlay JC, Barber B, Mickiewicz T, Maravi M, Drisko J, Estacio R, Gutierrez G, Urbina C. Reducing cardiovascular disease risk using patient navigators, Denver, Colorado, 2007-2009. Prev Chronic Dis. 2011 Nov;8(6):A143. Epub 2011 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22005636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goff SL, Pekow PS, White KO, Lagu T, Mazor KM, Lindenauer PK. IDEAS for a healthy baby--reducing disparities in use of publicly reported quality data: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial. Trials. 2013 Aug 7;14:244. doi: 10.1186/1745-6215-14-244.</citation>
    <PMID>23919671</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott LB, Gravely S, Sexton TR, Brzostek S, Brown DL. Examining the effect of a patient navigation intervention on outpatient cardiac rehabilitation awareness and enrollment. J Cardiopulm Rehabil Prev. 2013 Sep-Oct;33(5):281-91. doi: 10.1097/HCR.0b013e3182972dd6.</citation>
    <PMID>23823904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 1, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>patient navigator</keyword>
  <keyword>community health worker</keyword>
  <keyword>multi-morbidity</keyword>
  <keyword>primary care</keyword>
  <keyword>social determinants of health</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

