<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03071588</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14/LO/0880</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03071588</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of a New Protocol for Indirect Pulp Capping Procedures</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of a New Protocol for Indirect Pulp Capping Procedures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>King's College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>King's College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the study is to assess clinically, radiographically and microbiologically a new
      protocol for indirect pulp capping procedures compared to the conventional protocol in
      painful teeth. It was postulated that there is no difference between both protocols in terms
      clinical, radiographical and microbial outcome measure after one year of follow up in painful
      teeth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Indirect pulp capping is a common dental procedure carried out on painful teeth with deep
      cavities resulting from dental decay in an attempt to prolong the life of the tooth / pulp
      while relieving pain, This study aims primarily to assess the response of the pulp of the
      tooth to two different clinical procedures used in the treatment of deep caries. One group of
      patients will be treated with a standard clinical procedure which involve mechanical rotary
      burs with no magnification for caries removal, the other group will be treated with a more
      conservative clinical procedure using CarisolvTM gel with the aid of an operating microscope
      for caries removal. The study also involves taking of samples from the tooth decay for
      microbiological / biochemical analysis and evaluation to determine the species richness in
      the bacterial community associated with this condition. The study also compare the
      radiographical findings of 3D cone beam computed tomography (CBCT) scans with that of normal
      Xrays in detecting the presence of early bone changes associated with the roots of these
      teeth.

      The study carried out at King's College London/ Dental Institute at Guy's Hospital and form
      part of the routine dental treatment done at the emergency dental clinics with the exception
      of the CBCT scans. Volunteers given written information about the process and given time to
      consider participation. Once any questions have been answered, fully informed written consent
      obtained if they are interested in taking part. At least one deep cavity causing toothache
      requiring indirect pulp capping detected and diagnosed through conventional clinical and Xray
      dental assessment. The procedure involves removal of the decay using one of the proposed
      clinical techniques and the placement of a pulp capping material according to manufacturer's
      instructions and the definitive filling will be placed, follow up will at 12 months.
      Radiographic assessment including cone beam computed tomography (CBCT) will be done at
      baseline and 12 months. It is hoped that data analysed from this study will provide a
      definitive clinical and radiographic evidence base for the outcome of the indirect pulp
      capping operative treatment procedure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two groups of patients, each group received the investigated intervention at baseline and being followed up in parallel for one year.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cold pulp test (signalling the nerve of the pulp of the tooth by cold application)</measure>
    <time_frame>One year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Binary variable outcome measure whether the nerve is positively or negatively responsive to the cold test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">86</enrollment>
  <condition>Reversible Pulpitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>the conventional protocol in indirect pulp capping include the use of mechanical rotary burs for caries removal in teeth with reversible pulpitis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conservative</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>the conservative protocol of indirect pulp capping include the use of Carisolv gel for caries removal in teeth with reversible pulpitis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mechanical rotary burs</intervention_name>
    <description>A rotary drill made of steel or diamond impregnated materials attached to a steel shank, available in varying degree of sharpness, lengths and sizes used conventionally in preparation of teeth to receive a dental restoration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carisolv gel</intervention_name>
    <description>A chemical gel made of a combination of amino acids and sodium hypochlorite used with hand instruments to soften and remove the decay to prepare the tooth to receive a dental restoration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conservative</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Clinical diagnosis of reversible pulpitis with positive response to cold pulp test.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Clinical diagnosis of irreversible pulpitis, Pregnant women, mobile teeth and teeth with
        tenderness to percussion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francesco Mannocci</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>King's College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 1, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pulpitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

