<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03073421</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-124</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03073421</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Positive Pregnancy Program</brief_title>
  <acronym>P3</acronym>
  <official_title>A Qualitative Evaluation of the &quot;Positive Pregnancy Program&quot;, an Inter-professional Multidisciplinary Program for the Care of HIV-positive Pregnant Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Positive Pregnancy Program is an innovative, unique, interprofessional model of care for
      HIV-positive pregnant women. This program has been in place at St. Michael's Hospital for
      five years. This study is important because it will allow for a critical evaluation of the
      Program, and to identify strengths and weaknesses. This will in turn provide the opportunity
      to improve delivery of care for HIV positive women.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the P3 program is to provide supportive and comprehensive care from a variety of
      perspectives, including medical, social, and psychological. The premises on which the program
      are built include: a commitment to the respect, confidentiality, dignity and medical care of
      clients; health promotion; normalizing the care of HIV-positive pregnant women; knowledge
      translation; and the intentions to build a model of care that is transferable to other
      clinicians and to other conditions.

      During antenatal visits, pregnant women are seen by a multidisciplinary team of professionals
      including an Obstetrician, Midwife, Prenatal Nurse and Social Worker. Different rooms are
      used for routine antenatal care maneuvers and for consultation and counseling. The Midwife
      attends the births of the women in the program, and does home post partum care visits. Care
      is provided that is patient- and family-centered. Partners are invited to attend as many
      visits as the couple wishes. Because of this team approach, significantly more time is spent
      with each woman than would occur at a routine prenatal visit.

      The patient population at the St. Michael's clinic is largely made up of immigrant women.
      Many of these women are refugees, and have fled conflict zones or wars to come to Canada.
      More than 50% have lived in Canada for less than five years. Many of these women are
      marginalized, and may not access care elsewhere. They have many issues beyond HIV, and some
      of the social determinants of health that we observe during their time in the program include
      issues surrounding housing, finance, immigration, legal issues, social support, co-morbid
      conditions and substance use.

      Since the launch of the program, there has been a rapid increase in the number of women
      attending each year. The program has also attracted significant attention, both from within
      the medical and health care communities and beyond.

      This study seeks to determine if women cared for in the Positive Pregnancy Program will have
      a high degree of satisfaction with this model of care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 29, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 1, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 1, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Degree of satisfaction with P3 program during antenatal period</measure>
    <time_frame>36 weeks gestation</time_frame>
    <description>A qualitative 2 hour interview will be conducted with HIV positive pregnant women taking part in the P3 program. The first interview will be timed to occur late in the third trimester, at approximately 36 weeks gestation. This interview will allow an evaluation of women's experiences during antenatal care. The second interview will occur in the post partum period, and will be timed to coincide with the post partum visit at six weeks after birth. This interview will allow an evaluation of women's experiences in the hospital, during labour and delivery, and on the post partum floor.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-partum degree of satisfaction with P3 program</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks post-partum</time_frame>
    <description>The second interview will occur in the post partum period, and will be timed to coincide with the post partum visit at six weeks after birth. This interview will allow an evaluation of women's experiences in the hospital, during labour and delivery, and on the post partum floor.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Positive Pregnant Women</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV positive pregnant women</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>HIV positive pregnant women who took part in the P3 program will take part in a 2-hour qualitative interview.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Qualitative interview</intervention_name>
    <description>This interview will be 2 hours in length and will be conducted with a Peer Research Assistant (PRA). The PRAs will be women living with HIV.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HIV positive pregnant women</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV positive pregnant women who took part in P3 program

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV negative

          -  did not take part in P3 program
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Pregnant women</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Yudin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Seropositivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

