<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03074136</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>36/8</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03074136</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Application of Photodynamic Therapy and Diode Laser for Endodontic Therapy of Young Permanent Teeth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Application Success of Photodynamic Therapy and Diode Laser During Endodontic Therapy of Young Permanent Teeth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Association of Paediatric and Preventive Dentists of Serbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Association of Paediatric and Preventive Dentists of Serbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The pulp necrosis of permanent immature teeth implies the interruption of the root formation
      and apical closure. Diode lasers have been used in many areas of dentistry, with tendency of
      good results in canal and dentine disinfection. The bactericidal effect of high-power lasers
      is based on dose dependent heat generation. Its antimicrobial effectiveness against diverse
      microorganisms has already been demonstrated. Photodynamic therapy (PDT) is a two-step
      therapeutic approach starting with the application of a photosensitizing agent and followed
      by irradiation with light energy that is spectrally matched to activate the drug. The balance
      between disinfection and the creation of an intracanal microenvironment conducive for the
      proliferation of stem cells requires further investigation. Aims of study are to compare the
      time required to obtain the clinical healing and the disappearance of clinical symptoms, and
      absence of periapical radiolucency, by using PDT and diode laser, with standard disinfection
      alone; to assess specificity of microbial load in permanent immature teeth, and root canal
      disinfection ability of PDT and diode laser, in compare with standard disinfection alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background and Significance The pulp necrosis of permanent immature teeth implies the
      interruption of the root formation and apical closure. It is then necessary to implement a
      therapy to induce a calcified barrier at the apical end of the root. The endodontic
      management of permanent immature teeth is fraught with challenges. Although treatment
      modalities for vital pulp therapy in these teeth provide long-term favorable outcome, the
      outcomes from the treatment of pulp necrosis and apical periodontitis are significantly less
      predictable. Key role of microorganisms in the causing and development of pulpal and
      periapical diseases have been demonstrated, and their presence in the canal at the time of
      definitive filling has negative effect on success of the therapy. However, the specificity of
      microbial load of immature permanent teeth is not completely investigated, nor the influence
      of the disinfection protocols on treatment success.

      Available procedures rely heavily on root canal chemical disinfection of the root canal
      system, with minimal mechanical instrumentation. Sodium hypochlorite (NaOCl) in different
      concentrations is the most accepted solution for disinfection of root canal in endodontic.
      Despite common usage, impossibility of NaOCl to completely disinfect root canal has been
      noticed. Traditionally, irrigants and medicaments have been chosen for their maximum
      antimicrobial effect without consideration for their effects on stem cells and the dentinal
      microenvironment. The balance between disinfection and the creation of an intracanal
      microenvironment conducive for the proliferation of stem cells requires further
      investigation. This requires the interpretation of preclinical studies, and this level of
      evidence should be increased by randomized controlled clinical studies.

      Diode lasers have been used in many areas of dentistry, with tendency of good results in
      canal and dentine disinfection. The bactericidal effect of high-power lasers is based on dose
      dependent heat generation. Its antimicrobial effectiveness against diverse microorganisms has
      already been demonstrated.

      Photodynamic therapy (PDT) is a two-step therapeutic approach starting with the application
      of a photosensitizing agent and followed by irradiation with light energy that is spectrally
      matched to activate the drug. Because its high antibacterial potential, usage of photodynamic
      therapy as advance to standard protocol in root canal disinfection have been suggested.
      Studies showed positive effect of photodynamic therapy in the reduction of microbial load in
      root canal treatment. When a photoactive compound is applied in the root canal system, it is
      taken up by residual bacteria in the main canals, isthmuses, lateral canals and dentinal
      tubules. It is also possible that this compound may escape into the periapical tissues.
      During PDT, light will excite the drug in bacteria within the root canal, but could also
      potentially affect the apical stem cells that have taken up the drug. Therefore, it is
      important to determine the therapeutic window whereby host cells are left intact.

      Several studies showed wide-ranging spectra of desirable effects of low level power laser
      (LLLT) on biological tissue. It has been reported to increase cell functional activity,
      induce cell proliferation, lowers inflammation, releasing of endorphins, thus having
      analgetic effect. Furthermore, it has been shown that irradiation with a LLLT following
      photosensitization with phenothiazine chloride had no negative effect on the growth and
      differentiation of human osteoblastic cells, and did not counteract the biostimulatory effect
      induced by LLLT. There were no statistically significant differences in the growth and
      differentiation behavior between the two study groups. Further investigations of PDT on
      dental stem cells are needed to determine possible biostimulative effect on proliferation and
      differentiation, and thereby contribute to root development of non-vital permanent immature
      teeth. Prolonged treatment of young permanent teeth increases possibility of treatment
      failure. Involvement of a method that could help healing process is desirable.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 10, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 15, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 15, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Double blind</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of teeth without viable bacteria load in root canal after Photodynamic therapy and Diode laser in endodontic therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of teeth without viable bacteria load after treatment in all experimental groups, will be determined. Microbiological samples from the root canals will be collected immediately after the accessing the canal, following endodontic treatment, and after the laser procedure in adequate groups (Photodynamic therapy or Diode laser). Samples from the root canals will be cultivated in conditions suitable for growth of anaerobes and facultative anaerobes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of teeth with periapical healing 6 months after treatment, assessed by periapical index (PAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of teeth with periapical healing 6 months after treatment, will be determined by PAI score index, in all experimental groups. Teeth will be categorized in five groups depending of PAI score: (1) normal periapical structure; (2) small changes in bone structure; (3) changes in bone structure with some mineral loss; (4) periodontitis with well-defined radiolucent area; and (5) severe periodontitis with exacerbating features.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Teeth, Endodontically-Treated</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Photodinamic therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chemomechanical preparation will be completed by hand instruments, with minimal instrumentation, and usage of sodium hypochlorite with minimal bactericidal concentration (0.5%, pH 12), on room temperature (21 degree Celsius). After that, HELBO treatment (Helbo Photodynamic System, Bredent, Senden, Germany) will be applied.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diode laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chemomechanical preparation will be completed by hand instruments, with minimal instrumentation, and usage of sodium hypochlorite with minimal bactericidal concentration (0.5%, pH 12), on room temperature (21 degree Celsius). After that high power diode laser therapy will be applied by using Epic diode laser (Biolase® Technology, Inc., San Clemente, CA, USA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>0.5% Sodium hypochlorite</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chemomechanical preparation will be completed by hand instruments, with minimal instrumentation, and usage of sodium hypochlorite with minimal bactericidal concentration (0.5%, pH 12), on room temperature (21 degree Celsius).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Photodinamic therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Dentin sealant (HELBO® Endo Seal, Bredent, Senden, Germany) will be applied over the crown area and light cured. The root canals will be filled with the phenothiazine chloride (HELBO® Endo Blue, Bredent, Senden, Germany), agitated with a size 15K-file and left in the canal for 2 min. After this time, the root canals will be rinsed with distilled water to remove the excess of the photosensitizer, dried with paper points. The disposable 450 µm fiberoptic tip (3D HELBO® Endo Probe, Bredent, Senden, Germany) will be placed in the apical portion of the root canal at the point where resistance to the fiber will be felt, and root canal will be irradiated with HELBO® TheraLite Laser (λ = 660 nm, power = 100 mW) for 60 s (total energy, 6 J) in a continuous wave mode.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Photodinamic therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PDT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diode laser</intervention_name>
    <description>High-power diode laser therapy will be applied by using Epic diode laser (Biolase® Technology, Inc., San Clemente, CA, USA) with settings determined in laboratory researches (λ = 940 nm, maximal power 10W).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diode laser</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>High-power diode laser</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0.5% Sodium hypochlorite</intervention_name>
    <description>Chemomechanical preparation will be completed by hand instruments, with minimal instrumentation, and usage of sodium hypochlorite with minimal bactericidal concentration (0.5%, pH 12), on room temperature (21 degrees Celsius).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Photodinamic therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Diode laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>0.5% Sodium hypochlorite</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>0.5% NaOCl</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          -  a non-vital permanent immature single rooted tooth

          -  primary endodontic infection

          -  6 - 18 years old

          -  written informed consent obtained from each parent and child

        Exclusion criteria

          -  uncontrolled diabetes mellitus,

          -  immunosuppression,

          -  severe asthma

          -  usage of antibiotics, anti-inflammatory, corticosteroid, or immunosuppressive therapy
             during the last 6 months

          -  need for antibiotics at current endodontic therapy

          -  need for antibiotics in prophylaxis of systematic disease before endodontic therapy

          -  periodontal diseases

          -  impossible adequate isolation of the tooth
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Dental Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belgrade</city>
        <country>Serbia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Serbia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diogenes AR, Ruparel NB, Teixeira FB, Hargreaves KM. Translational science in disinfection for regenerative endodontics. J Endod. 2014 Apr;40(4 Suppl):S52-7. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2014.01.015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24698694</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siqueira JF Jr, Rôças IN. Clinical implications and microbiology of bacterial persistence after treatment procedures. J Endod. 2008 Nov;34(11):1291-1301.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2008.07.028. Epub 2008 Sep 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18928835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shabahang S, Pouresmail M, Torabinejad M. In vitro antimicrobial efficacy of MTAD and sodium hypochlorite. J Endod. 2003 Jul;29(7):450-2.</citation>
    <PMID>12877261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waltimo T, Trope M, Haapasalo M, Ørstavik D. Clinical efficacy of treatment procedures in endodontic infection control and one year follow-up of periapical healing. J Endod. 2005 Dec;31(12):863-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16306819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pearson GJ, Schuckert KH. The role of lasers in dentistry: present and future. Dent Update. 2003 Mar;30(2):70-4, 76.</citation>
    <PMID>12705027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gutknecht N, Franzen R, Schippers M, Lampert F. Bactericidal effect of a 980-nm diode laser in the root canal wall dentin of bovine teeth. J Clin Laser Med Surg. 2004 Feb;22(1):9-13.</citation>
    <PMID>15117481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Soukos NS, Chen PS, Morris JT, Ruggiero K, Abernethy AD, Som S, Foschi F, Doucette S, Bammann LL, Fontana CR, Doukas AG, Stashenko PP. Photodynamic therapy for endodontic disinfection. J Endod. 2006 Oct;32(10):979-84. Epub 2006 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>16982278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chrepa V, Kotsakis GA, Pagonis TC, Hargreaves KM. The effect of photodynamic therapy in root canal disinfection: a systematic review. J Endod. 2014 Jul;40(7):891-8. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2014.03.005. Epub 2014 May 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24935531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu Y, Young MJ, Battaglino RA, Morse LR, Fontana CR, Pagonis TC, Kent R, Soukos NS. Endodontic antimicrobial photodynamic therapy: safety assessment in mammalian cell cultures. J Endod. 2009 Nov;35(11):1567-72. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2009.08.002. Epub 2009 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>19840649</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toomarian L, Fekrazad R, Tadayon N, Ramezani J, Tunér J. Stimulatory effect of low-level laser therapy on root development of rat molars: a preliminary study. Lasers Med Sci. 2012 May;27(3):537-42. doi: 10.1007/s10103-011-0935-9. Epub 2011 May 26.</citation>
    <PMID>21614480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martens LC. Laser physics and a review of laser applications in dentistry for children. Eur Arch Paediatr Dent. 2011 Apr;12(2):61-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21473835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein E, Koehn J, Sutter W, Schmidl C, Lezaic V, Wendtlandt G, Watzinger F, Turhani D. Phenothiazine chloride and soft laser light have a biostimulatory effect on human osteoblastic cells. Photomed Laser Surg. 2009 Feb;27(1):71-7. doi: 10.1089/pho.2008.2265.</citation>
    <PMID>19196108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jurič IB, Plečko V, Pandurić DG, Anić I. The antimicrobial effectiveness of photodynamic therapy used as an addition to the conventional endodontic re-treatment: a clinical study. Photodiagnosis Photodyn Ther. 2014 Dec;11(4):549-55. doi: 10.1016/j.pdpdt.2014.10.004. Epub 2014 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>25461966</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 3, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Association of Paediatric and Preventive Dentists of Serbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dejan Markovic</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>photodynamic therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>diode laser</keyword>
  <keyword>immature permanent teeth</keyword>
  <keyword>endodontic therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tooth, Nonvital</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sodium Hypochlorite</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eusol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

