<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01941264</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>6800110</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ISRCTN37259296</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01941264</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community-based Screening and Treatment of Malaria in Pregnancy: a Cluster-randomized Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>COSMIC</acronym>
  <official_title>Community-based Scheduled Screening and Treatment of Malaria in Pregnancy for Improved Maternal and Infant Health: a Cluster-randomized Trial in The Gambia, Burkina Faso and Benin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Royal Tropical Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical Research Council Unit, The Gambia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre Muraz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>World Health Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Union</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Royal Tropical Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Malaria is a common disease in Africa and a major health problem. Pregnant women are also at
      risk of malaria. Malaria in pregnancy is life threatening to both the mother and the baby she
      is carrying. It can result in the destruction of the mother's blood and in babies with a
      lower birth weight than normal, making them less healthy in their first years of life. These
      risks are even higher in women having their first pregnancy.

      When a woman is pregnant she should go to the Antenatal clinic (ANC) for care. Usually the
      ANC health staff gives the woman intermittent preventable treatment (IPTp-SP) against
      malaria. This drug helps protect the woman against getting malaria. Each pregnant woman
      should receive at least 2 doses of this drug during their pregnancy; thus, they should go the
      ANC at least 2 times during their pregnancy. However, many women still do not go often to the
      ANC for health care during their pregnancy.

      This study would like to see whether community health workers (CHW) can work with pregnant
      women to encourage them to attend ANC more often. Also, the CHW will test a pregnant woman
      every month for malaria with a rapid test. If a woman has malaria, the CHW will treat her in
      her home instead of the woman having to go a health clinic for treatment. The woman will be
      treated with a different drug than the drug that is given at the ANC visits. Our hypothesis
      is that this will improve the care and management of malaria during pregnancy and this will
      improve the health of women and their newborns. To see whether this strategy improved the
      health of women and their newborns, we will take a small piece of the placenta at delivery to
      test for malaria and we will weigh the baby. We will test this strategy in multiple
      communities. We will compare this to pregnant women in communities where this strategy was
      not followed, thus where pregnant women received standard care.

      Participants will be pregnant women. There are no direct benefits for participating in the
      study, except the outcome of our research question that is possible health benefits in the
      intervention group. The drugs involved are tested safe in pregnant women from second
      trimester on.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Community health workers (CHWs) that will be working in intervention villages will be trained
      on community-based case management of malaria by monthly testing of pregnant women using a
      rapid diagnostic test (RDT). They will also be taught the benefit of pregnant women visiting
      the antenatal clinics (ANC) and that women should receive intermittent preventive treatment
      with sulphadoxine-pyrimethamine (SP) at the ANC according to WHO guidelines.

      The CHWs will try to identify all pregnant women in their villages and encourage them to
      visit the ANC as early as possible in their pregnancy. The CHW will check after one week if
      the ANC was visited. For women who do not attend the ANC, the CHW will further encourage and
      discuss reasons for non-attendance. Subsequently the CHW will visit the woman's house every
      month to test for malaria with a RDT.The CHW will give a full course of AL to any woman with
      a positive RDT. The CHW will also collect a blood slide and a blood spot on filter paper for
      later analysis in the laboratory. The CHWs will return to women who were treated for malaria
      to check uptake and compliance by using a short questionnaire and checking the empty
      packaging of the treatment at the end of the course.

      In control communities, CHW will not be trained to do RDTs and give AL to pregnant women. The
      only data collection will occur during ANC visits.

      All women are asked to deliver in collaborating health centres. Peripheral blood will be
      tested for hemoglobin, malaria infection and resistance against SP. A placenta biopsy will be
      collected and all babies will be weighed and examined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Placental malaria</measure>
    <time_frame>After delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Placental malaria will be diagnosed by microscopy of placental biopsies and polymerase chain reaction (PCR) on placental blood.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Birth weight</measure>
    <time_frame>After delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Babies of mothers included in the study will be weighed after delivery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>antenatal care clinic attendance</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout inclusion (+/- 6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>A field worker will identify all eligible pregnant women and will follow-up on ANC attendance through lists at the antenatal care clinic</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Resistance to sulphadoxine-pyrimethamine (SP)</measure>
    <time_frame>At delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Samples infected with P.falciparum will be checked for resistance profile for sulphadoxine-pyrimethamine</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Peripheral malaria infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout inclusion (+/- 6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Each collected filter paper en microscopy slide (both in antenatal care clinics and from community health worker visits) will be checked for the presence of malaria parasites.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>hemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>At delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Peripheral blood sample will be tested for hemoglobin</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4265</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria, Antepartum</condition>
  <condition>Maternal Malaria During Pregnancy - Baby Not Yet Delivered</condition>
  <condition>Small for Gestational Age (Disorder)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>community based screening and treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CHWs will identify pregnant women in the village and encourage to go to the antenatal care clinic, furthermore, once a month the community health worker will screen the pregnant women for malaria with a rapid diagnostic test and treat with artemether-lumefantrine in case of a positive test result.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>All pregnant women will be identified in the study area and asked for participation to the study. No intervention will take place.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>community based screening and treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Already described in intervention arm description.</description>
    <arm_group_label>community based screening and treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rapid diagnostic test</other_name>
    <other_name>Coartem</other_name>
    <other_name>Artemether-lumefantrine</other_name>
    <other_name>malaria village worker</other_name>
    <other_name>village health worker</other_name>
    <other_name>community case management</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Residence in the study area and intention to stay in the area for the duration of the
             pregnancy and for delivery.

          -  Aged at least 16 years (pregnant adolescents younger than 16 years will be considered
             only if they are accompanied by a responsible adult (in the Gambia) or married
             (considered an adult by marriage in Burkina Faso and Benin.)

          -  Willing to provide biological samples as and when required during the study period
             (blood and placental biopsy)

          -  Informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A history of sensitivity to sulphonamides.

          -  Already participating in another research study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Henk Schallig, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Royal Tropical Institute (KIT)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre de Recherches Entomologiques de Cotonou (CREC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cotonou</city>
        <country>Benin</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Research Unit of Nanoro URCN/CMA, Centre Muraz (CM)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanoro</city>
        <country>Burkina Faso</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Research Council (MRC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fajara</city>
        <country>Gambia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Benin</country>
    <country>Burkina Faso</country>
    <country>Gambia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cosmicmalaria.eu</url>
    <description>webpage of the study</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott S, Mens PF, Tinto H, Nahum A, Ruizendaal E, Pagnoni F, Grietens KP, Kendall L, Bojang K, Schallig H, D'Alessandro U. Community-based scheduled screening and treatment of malaria in pregnancy for improved maternal and infant health in The Gambia, Burkina Faso and Benin: study protocol for a randomized controlled trial. Trials. 2014 Aug 28;15:340. doi: 10.1186/1745-6215-15-340.</citation>
    <PMID>25169073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 10, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 13, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 3, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 3, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 4, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>malaria</keyword>
  <keyword>placenta</keyword>
  <keyword>pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>plasmodium falciparum</keyword>
  <keyword>screening and treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>rapid diagnostic test</keyword>
  <keyword>coartem</keyword>
  <keyword>artemether-lumefantrine</keyword>
  <keyword>community health worker</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lumefantrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemether</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemether-lumefantrine combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemisinins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

