<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01945905</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FES02013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01945905</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cost-effectiveness of Two Forms of DOTS in a Demonstration Area of the DOTS Strategy in Colombia</brief_title>
  <acronym>DOTS</acronym>
  <official_title>Cost-effectiveness of Two Forms of Delivery of Directly Observed Treatment in a Demonstration Area of the DOTS Strategy in Colombia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundación FES</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto Colombiano para el Desarrollo de la Ciencia y la Tecnología (COLCIENCIAS)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto Nacional de Salud Publica, Mexico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundación FES</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      -  Tuberculosis ( TB ) remains a major global public health problems and actions to ensure
           the diagnosis and complete treatment of all cases is the priority for the control of
           this disease. Despite the availability of effective anti-tuberculosis medications, there
           are still high levels of nonadherence to treatment. The nonadherence increases the
           morbidity and mortality of patients, decreases the cure rate, increases the community
           transmission and the increase of chronically ill patients enables the emergence of multi
           - drug resistant and increases treatment costs.

        -  Despite the knowledge about different forms of cost-effective delivery of DOT (directly
           observed treatment), recognition of the need to establish the DOT strategy related to
           the context from local studies, in Colombia and in Cali we hadn't had made studies
           similar than this one that establish the cost and results of the current DOT delivery
           strategy and to identify other ways to improve adherence and cure rate for the TB
           patients at reasonable cost for both: health services and families

        -  Therefore, this research aims to compare the cost -effectiveness of current DOT delivery
           method with an alternative extra- institutional delivery of anti -TB treatment in urban
           areas of Cali. A cost-effectiveness study was conducted from the institutional and
           familiar perspective with prospective information collection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We compared two strategies for anti- TB treatment delivery: one institutional in which
      patients went to health institutions to receive treatment and other extra- institutional in
      which the medication was delivered in the place of choice for treating patients.

      Measuring the effectiveness ( compliance and cure ) was made from a controlled clinical trial
      , randomized , partially blinded . The measurement of family and institutional costs , direct
      and indirect , will be based on the activities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance with treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the treatment, an expected average of six months</time_frame>
    <description>Total of patients who completed de treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cured patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the treatment, an expected average of six months</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of patients who completed the treatment and had the last or the two last smear negative and had negative cultures at the end of the treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">264</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Extramural</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Extramural medication delivery and supervision</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intramural</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intramural medication delivery and supervision</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intramural</intervention_name>
    <description>Under this alternative, the patients will receive treatment with direct observation from health team. Treatment will be provided for free</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intramural</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extramural</intervention_name>
    <description>In this form the medication will be given by a health worker in the place chosen by patients. This option will be delivered to patients with newly diagnosed pulmonary TB without hospitalization criteria</description>
    <arm_group_label>Extramural</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female (non-pregnant)

          -  15 years of age and older

          -  Living in urban area (Cali)

          -  New diagnosed patients (TB)

          -  In conditions to give survey information

          -  Patients without hemoptysis and special conditions like: hepatic disease, renal
             failure, diabetes, hypertension, HIV/AIDS and negative test for pulmonary tuberculosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not written informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandra L Giron, Msc Epi</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fundación FES</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julio C Mateus, Msc Epi</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fundación FES</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Secretaria de Salud Publica Municipal de Cali</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cali</city>
        <state>Valle</state>
        <zip>76001000</zip>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Colombia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moulding T, Mateus-Solarte JC, Carvajal-Barona R. Factors predictive of adherence to tuberculosis treatment, Valle del Cauca, Colombia. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2009 Mar;13(3):416-7; author reply 417-8.</citation>
    <PMID>19275807</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pablos-Méndez A, Knirsch CA, Barr RG, Lerner BH, Frieden TR. Nonadherence in tuberculosis treatment: predictors and consequences in New York City. Am J Med. 1997 Feb;102(2):164-70.</citation>
    <PMID>9217566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burman WJ, Cohn DL, Rietmeijer CA, Judson FN, Sbarbaro JA, Reves RR. Noncompliance with directly observed therapy for tuberculosis. Epidemiology and effect on the outcome of treatment. Chest. 1997 May;111(5):1168-73.</citation>
    <PMID>9149565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Boyle SJ, Power JJ, Ibrahim MY, Watson JP. Factors affecting patient compliance with anti-tuberculosis chemotherapy using the directly observed treatment, short-course strategy (DOTS). Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2002 Apr;6(4):307-12.</citation>
    <PMID>11936739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jaiswal A, Singh V, Ogden JA, Porter JD, Sharma PP, Sarin R, Arora VK, Jain RC. Adherence to tuberculosis treatment: lessons from the urban setting of Delhi, India. Trop Med Int Health. 2003 Jul;8(7):625-33.</citation>
    <PMID>12828545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clarke M, Dick J, Bogg L. Cost-effectiveness analysis of an alternative tuberculosis management strategy for permanent farm dwellers in South Africa amidst health service contraction. Scand J Public Health. 2006;34(1):83-91.</citation>
    <PMID>16449048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Islam MA, Wakai S, Ishikawa N, Chowdhury AM, Vaughan JP. Cost-effectiveness of community health workers in tuberculosis control in Bangladesh. Bull World Health Organ. 2002;80(6):445-50.</citation>
    <PMID>12132000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sinanovic E, Floyd K, Dudley L, Azevedo V, Grant R, Maher D. Cost and cost-effectiveness of community-based care for tuberculosis in Cape Town, South Africa. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2003 Sep;7(9 Suppl 1):S56-62.</citation>
    <PMID>12971655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lwilla F, Schellenberg D, Masanja H, Acosta C, Galindo C, Aponte J, Egwaga S, Njako B, Ascaso C, Tanner M, Alonso P. Evaluation of efficacy of community-based vs. institutional-based direct observed short-course treatment for the control of tuberculosis in Kilombero district, Tanzania. Trop Med Int Health. 2003 Mar;8(3):204-10.</citation>
    <PMID>12631309</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khan MA, Walley JD, Witter SN, Imran A, Safdar N. Costs and cost-effectiveness of different DOT strategies for the treatment of tuberculosis in Pakistan. Directly Observed Treatment. Health Policy Plan. 2002 Jun;17(2):178-86.</citation>
    <PMID>12000778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Okello D, Floyd K, Adatu F, Odeke R, Gargioni G. Cost and cost-effectiveness of community-based care for tuberculosis patients in rural Uganda. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2003 Sep;7(9 Suppl 1):S72-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12971657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wandwalo E, Robberstad B, Morkve O. Cost and cost-effectiveness of community based and health facility based directly observed treatment of tuberculosis in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania. Cost Eff Resour Alloc. 2005 Jul 14;3:6.</citation>
    <PMID>16018806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elamin EI, Ibrahim MI, Sulaiman SA, Muttalif AR. Cost of illness of tuberculosis in Penang, Malaysia. Pharm World Sci. 2008 Jun;30(3):281-6. doi: 10.1007/s11096-007-9185-0. Epub 2008 Jan 18.</citation>
    <PMID>18204974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 9, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 16, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 19, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 10, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 10, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Fundación FES</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sandra Lorena Girón Vargas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Msc Epidemiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Adherence, medication</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient compliance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

