<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01947322</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P070505</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01947322</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Haploidentical NK-cell Infusion in Acute Myeloid Leukemia</brief_title>
  <acronym>NK</acronym>
  <official_title>Haploidentical NK-cell Infusion in Bad Prognosis AML Patients: Evaluation of Feasibility and Antitumoral Effect</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Leukemia cells can be killed by natural killer (NK) from HLA-I mismatched donor. The proposed
      study plans to realize an adoptive anti-leukaemic immunotherapy by infusion of HLA-I
      mismatched NK cells to treat poor prognosis acute myeloid leukemia patients. NK cells will be
      selected from HLA mismatch familial donor peripheral mononuclear cells by purification
      protocol. Before NK-infusion, patients received immunosuppressive chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      NK cell-mediated cytotoxity is regulated by signals provided by surface inhibitory and
      activating receptors. Target cells will be killed in the absence of interaction between NK
      inhibitory receptors and their ligands (HLA class I molecules) on the target cells. The
      proposed phase I/II study plans to realize an adoptive anti-leukaemic immunotherapy by
      infusion of haploidentical HLA-I mismatched NK cells to treat poor prognosis AML patients.
      Familial donors of NK cells will be selected according to their HLA typing in order to choose
      a donor with NK cells expressing at least one inhibitory receptor that can not recognize any
      HLA class I molecule on recipient cells. NK cells will be selected from donor peripheral
      mononuclear cells by a two step purification protocol (CD3 negative with subsequent CD56
      positive selections). NK cells will be then activated ex vivo overnight in the presence of
      IL-2 before infusion. In vivo IL-2 injections will be performed for 14 days. Before
      NK-infusion, patients will be conditioned by a cytoreductive and immunosuppressive
      chemotherapy. An extensive biological study of NK cells will be performed in the recipient
      post-infusion, including chimerism analyses, phenotypic and functional tests in order to
      evaluate NK-cell expansion post-infusion and their capacity to mediate an antitumoral effect.
      Since donor NK cells have been selected for their potential graft versus host (GvH) and graft
      versus leukemia (GvL) reactivity, such approach might induce prolonged cytopenia due to a
      direct toxicity of NK cells against normal hematopoietic progenitors. The main goals of this
      study will be thus to evaluate (1) the hematological feasibility of allogeneic NK-cell
      infusion, (2) the expansion of the infused population, (3) an antitumoral effect mediated by
      this adoptive immunotherapy. This is an essential step before further development of such
      anti-tumoral immunotherapeutic approach, in leukemic patients but also in solid tumors that
      could be sensitive to an &quot;NK-effect&quot; (melanoma, kidney cancer).

      This project includes 4 clinical departments and several laboratories of cellular therapy and
      immunology that have got an expertise in the field of Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML), cellular
      therapy and NK-cell.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>duration of neutropenia inferior to 500 neutrophils /mm3</measure>
    <time_frame>from the day of NK infusion (day 0) up to 35 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Allogenic NK cells infusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allogenic NK cells infusion</intervention_name>
    <description>HLA Haploidentical selected NK cell infusion (one injection of 1x107/kg CD3-CD56+ cells) after chemotherapy associating fludarabine, cytosine arabinoside and cyclophosphamide.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allogenic NK cells infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>cellular therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. Recipient selection

               1. Patient eligibility

                    -  Poor prognosis de novo AML including :

                         1. Primary refractory disease (absence of complete remission (CR) after at
                            least 2 different induction regimens)

                         2. Relapsed disease that did not reach CR after at least 1 salvage therapy

                         3. First untreated early relapse (less than one year of remission
                            duration) in the absence of allogeneic HSCT project.

                    -  Age between 18 and 65

                    -  No liver and renal dysfunctions contraindicating the administration of
                       Fludarabine, Cyclophosphamide or Cytarabine.

                    -  Written informed consent

               2. Patient exclusion criteria

                    -  Secondary AML.

                    -  Previous autologous or allogeneic transplantation. Since the main objective
                       of the study concerns the hematological toxicity, we decided to exclude
                       patients with secondary AML or who had been previously transplanted because
                       of their expected higher hematological toxicity.

                    -  Patient with allogeneic transplant project

                    -  HIV positive serology

          2. Donor eligibility

               -  HLA haploidentical brother, sister, child (older than 18 years), father, sister,
                  cousin, uncle, aunt.

               -  Donor with KIR ligand mismatch in the GvL direction

               -  Absence of contraindication for leukapheresis.

               -  Negative HIV1-2, HTLV-1-2, HBV, and HCV serology. Negative viral genomic
                  screening for HTLV1-2 and HCV

               -  Written informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nathalie Dhedin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>APHP</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'Hématologie Clinique du Pr. Leblond- Hôpital Pitié salpêtrière</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75013</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'Hématologie adultes du Pr. Hermine - Hôpital Necker Enfants Malades</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75015</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'Hématologie oncologie du Pr. Mohty -Hôpital Saint Antoine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75571</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service d'Hématologie Clinique du Pr. Cordonnier-Hôpital Henri Mondor</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>94010</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 26, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 20, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Natural killer cell</keyword>
  <keyword>Haploidentical</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute myeloid leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

