<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01940003</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>U1111-1147-1141</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01940003</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of an Aquatic Physical Exercise Program on Glycaemic Control and Perinatal Outcomes of Gestational Diabetes: Study Protocol for a Randomized Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of an Aquatic Physical Exercise Program on Glycemic Control and Perinatal Outcomes of Gestational Diabetes - a Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Professor Fernando Figueira Integral Medicine Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação de Amparo à Ciência e Tecnologia do Estado de Pernambuco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Professor Fernando Figueira Integral Medicine Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to verify the efficacy of an aquatic physical exercise program
      on GDM control and adverse maternal and fetal outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) is increasing worldwide and has been associated with
      adverse perinatal outcomes and high risk for chronic disease both for the mother and for the
      child. Physical exercise is feasible to diabetic pregnant women and contributes to a better
      glycemic control and to decrease adverse perinatal outcomes. However there are no randomized
      controlled trials (RCT) assessing the effects of aquatic physical exercise on GDM control and
      adverse maternal and fetal outcomes.

      A RCT will be conducted at Institute of Medicine Professor Fernando Figueira (IMIP), Brazil.
      IMIP is a reference hospital in the Northeast Brazil for mother and child care and performed
      about 6,000 deliveries per year. The recruitment of patients will focus on GDM women
      diagnosed at IMIP that referred to this center for treatment. Obstetrical staff will identify
      pregnant women recently diagnosed with GDM. These patients will be approached by a member of
      the study team and ask permission to be forwarded after an explanation of the study goals.
      GDM women will be considered eligible for enrollment if they fulfill all the inclusion
      criteria and none of the exclusion criteria. Interested patients will be invited to sign a
      written informed consent.

      Sample size was calculated with the aim of reducing glucose levels by 20% in intervention
      group. A power of 80% and a level of significance of 5% was accepted and the calculated
      sample size in each arm was 30 patients. Assuming a drop out of 20%, 72 pregnant women will
      be included in the study. 36 gestational diabetics will develop an aquatic physical exercise
      program in a thermal pool, three times per week during two months, and 36 gestational
      diabetics will receive usual care from IMIP.

      To ensure that similar guidelines for GDM clinical treatment are maintained for the two
      groups, IMIP obstetrical staff will undertake the ongoing GDM management of all trial
      participants for the period of the study. Participants are usually clinically evaluated at
      minimum every two weeks depending on GDM control, according to the IMIP guidelines for GDM. A
      capillary glucose test is performed in each clinical visit. It will be analyzed the mean
      capillary glucose profile after intervention (minimum of five determinations per woman).
      Insulin or oral hypoglycemic required will be compared among the two groups.

      All pregnant women will wear a pedometer (Yamax Digi Walker SW-200, Tokyo, Japan) during the
      whole study. Pedometer readings will provide a measure of physical activity to compare both
      groups. All diabetics pregnant women will be recorded of their clinical history and undertake
      a cardiologic evaluation.

      Randomization will be done according to a computed-generated allocation (www.randomized.com).
      Pregnant women will be assigned, in a 1:1 ratio, to exercise intervention or usual care.
      Blinding of the study to the randomization arm is not possible due to the nature of
      intervention.

      Primary endpoint will be glucose levels control (glicemy test) and use of insulin (use or not
      insulin), secondary endpoints will be the following maternal and fetal outcomes: weight gain
      during pregnancy, blood pressure, preeclampsia diagnosis, intra-uterus growth restriction,
      preterm birth, Cesarean section, macrosomia and maternal or neonatal intensive care
      admission. The information will be acquired through the medical records of patients.

      Maternal and fetal characteristics of the study sample will be presented by group,
      intervention and control in terms of mean and SD. For group comparisons of glucose levels and
      perinatal variables, continuous and nominal data will be analyzed by t test for unpaired data
      and χ2 tests, respectively. Data will be analyzed using the intention-to-treat principle.
      Statistical analysis will be performed with the STATA version 3.1 and the level of
      significance will set to &lt;0.05.

      Even in cases where there is the appearance of some criterion for discontinuation during the
      intervention (Aquatic physical exercise), the patient will be considered part of the group
      which was initially included in the randomization (intent to treat) and is not excluded from
      the study. In order to evaluate the criteria for discontinuation of study will be established
      a Committee on External Monitoring (CME).

      The physical proprieties of water provide aquatic exercises as ideal for pregnant women. An
      aquatic physical exercise program developed with GDM women in a thermal pool and under a
      physiotherapist supervision must ensure compliance. It is expected that this study provide
      evidences to the real role of aquatic physical exercise on GDM control.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycemic control</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Blood glucose test: maternal glucose levels on third trimester of pregnancy and use of insulin
Use of insulin: need to use or not of insulin to control gestational diabetes mellitus. Variable nominal dichotomous yes / no.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-uterus growth restriction (fetal ultrasound parameters)</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Intra-uterus growth restriction diagnosis will based on the following findings:
birthweight percentile &lt; 10 for gestational age, morphological ultrasound with Doppler (assessment of umbilical blood flow).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prematurity</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Preterm birth (before 37th gestational week).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Newborns with macrosomia</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Cesarean section Birth injury Macrosomia (birth weight &gt; 4,000g). Nominal variable, dichotomous yes or no.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight gain in pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Weight measured at the end of pregnancy minus pre-pregnancy weight informed by pregnant woman (cm)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal or neonatal intensive care admission</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal variable, dichotomous yes or no.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic and diastolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in mmHg every medical consultation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preeclampsia diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>blood hypertension (levels of systolic blood pressure ≥ 140 mmHg and / or diastolic blood pressure ≥ 90 mmHglevels of systolic blood pressure ≥ 140 mmHg and / or diastolic blood pressure ≥ 90 mmHg) associated with proteinuria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cesarean section</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Nominal variable, dichotomous yes or no.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Birth injury</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Be will considered any kind of injury of the newborn occurred during delivery. Nominal variable, dichotomous yes or no.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes, Gestational</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care of service Institute of Medicine Professor Fernando Figueira(IMIP) prenatal</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aquatic exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pool-based exercise classes will be completed in groups of 4 to 6 participants under the instruction of a physiotherapist. The exercise program will be conducted three times per week and each session lasting 45 minute. This will be conducted since GDM diagnosis (26-28th gestational week) to the end of the third trimester (38-39th gestational week). Thus, an average of 30 training sessions will be planned for each pregnant woman.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aquatic exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>The aquatic exercise program will be under the professional guidance of a physiotherapist, with water at a temperature of around 26 to 28°C. The exercise sessions will be executed following the steps: 1) Heating (stretching and flexibility, static method, during 5'); 2) Aerobic exercise (running, displacements and combined movements of arms and legs, with 1minute interval, to 1minute activity and of during 20') 3) Spot exercises (strength / endurance of the upper and lower limbs and abdomen, using the resistance of water for 15') 4) Relaxation (slow walks for 5'). During the sessions of exercises the pregnant women will have heart rate monitored by the frequency meter (Polar Electro OY) to control the intensity of the exercises that will focus on the range of moderate intensity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aquatic exercise</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Water aerobics</other_name>
    <other_name>Hydrotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  GDM diagnosis will be based on International Association of the Diabetes in Pregnancy
             Study Group (IADPSG), Hyperglycemia and Adverse Pregnancy Outcomes (HAPO) study (2 h
             75 g oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT): a fasting glucose ≥ 92 mg/dl or a one hour
             result of ≥ 80 mg/dl, or a two hour result of ≥ 153 mg/dl;

          -  Aging 18 to 35 years;

          -  Physically inactive (&lt; 150` per week based on International Physical Activity
             Questionnaire.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Kidney disease or collagenosis;

          -  Previous history of gestational diabetes;

          -  Diabetes type 1 or type 2;

          -  Hypertensive disorders related to pregnancy;

          -  Hemodynamic instability;

          -  Obstetric labor;

          -  Vaginal bleeding;

          -  Cognitive disorder, auditory, visual or motor severely limiting, attested by a medical
             specialist;

          -  Skin disorders who have a contraindication to the use of a swimming pool;

          -  Urinary tract infection;

          -  Be inserted in the program of regular exercise;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>José Roberto da Silva Junior, Master</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Medicine Professor Fernando Figueira</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>João Guilherme Bezerra Alves, doctorate</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Medicine Professor Fernando Figueira</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paulo Sergio Gomes Nogueira Borges, Master</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Medicine Professor Fernando Figueira</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karine Ferreira Agra, Master</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Medicine Professor Fernando Figueira</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Isabelle Eunice de Albuquerque Pontes, Master</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Medicine Professor Fernando Figueira</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>José Roberto da Silva Junior, Master</last_name>
    <phone>55-81-9815-4243</phone>
    <email>roberto.junior@imip.org.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>João Guilherme Bezerra Alves, Doctorate</last_name>
    <phone>99746351</phone>
    <email>joaoguilherme@imip.org.br</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto de Medicina Integral Prof. Fernando Figueira</name>
      <address>
        <city>Recife</city>
        <state>Pernambuco</state>
        <zip>50070-550</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>José Roberto da Silva Junior, Master</last_name>
      <phone>55-81-9815-4243</phone>
      <email>roberto.junior@imip.org.br</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karine Ferreira Agra, Master</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>José Roberto da Silva Junior, Master</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.imip.org.br</url>
    <description>Click here for more information about this Instiuto de Medicina Integral Prof. Fernando Figueira during the study: Effects of an aquatic physical exercise program on glycemic control and perinatal outcomes of gestational diabetes</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 7, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 11, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 10, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Professor Fernando Figueira Integral Medicine Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>José Roberto da Silva Junior</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Physiotherapist. Master in Maternal Health by Institute Medicine Professor Fernando Figueira. Professor of kinesiology at the College IBGM.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes, Gestational</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy Outcome</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>glycemic control</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes, Gestational</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

