<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01949363</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-0025</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN272200800026C</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01949363</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Pharmacokinetics of Extended Duration High-dose Cefixime for the Decreased Susceptibility of Neisseria Gonorrhoeae: A Phase I Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Pharmacokinetics of Extended Duration High-Dose Cefixime for the Decreased Susceptibility of Neisseria Gonorrhoeae: A Phase I Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a Phase I, open label, non-randomized, dose-frequency escalation
      pharmacokinetics study among 24 healthy male and female subjects, aged 18 to 45 years to
      determine the pharmacokinetics and safety of high-, multi-dose cefixime for the treatment of
      reduced susceptibility gonorrhea. Stage 1(Cohorts A and B) will examine the pharmacokinetics
      of single 400mg and 800mg dose of cefixime. Stage 2(Cohorts C and D) subjects will take 800mg
      of cefixime every 12 hours for 2 doses. If that dosing regimen is well tolerated, the
      dose-frequency will escalate to 800mg every 8 hours for 3 doses, and serum levels of cefixime
      will be measured. Study duration is approximately 47 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a Phase I, open label, non-randomized, dose-frequency escalation
      pharmacokinetics study among 24 healthy male and female subjects, aged 18 to 45 years to
      determine the pharmacokinetics and safety of high multi-dose cefixime for the treatment of
      reduced susceptibility gonorrhea. The study will occur in two stages as described below.
      Stage 1: Confirm/establish the pharmacokinetics (PK) of 400mg and 800mg doses of cefixime
      tablet. Stage 2: Define dosing frequency necessary to achieve total serum cefixime levels
      that exceed 2.0 mcg/mL for over 20 hours. Stage 1 (Cohorts A and B): Six subjects will be
      admitted to the Johns Hopkins Bayview Clinic Trials Unit to assess each dosing regimen, for a
      total of 12 subjects. At time=0, subjects will undergo baseline serum cefixime levels,
      followed by ingestion of cefixime. Serum collections will occur at times 0, 1, 2, 4, 8, 12,
      16, 20, and 24 hours. Cohort B will have the same serum collection time points as Cohort A.
      Cohorts A &amp; B will be run nearly simultaneously as logistically feasible. Stage 2 (Cohorts C
      and D): After determining the PK parameters of single dose 800mg, the PK simulation model
      will be repeated, adjusting the model as needed based on findings from study Stage 1.
      Assuming there are no major discrepancies between Figure 2 (above) and the new PK
      simulations, the following regimens will be tested, beginning with Cohort C. Six subjects per
      dosing regimen, Cohorts C and D, will be admitted to the Johns Hopkins Bayview Medical
      Center, for a total of 12 subjects. The 800mg q12 hour x 2 regimen (Cohort C) will be tested
      first. For Cohort C, serum cefixime levels will be drawn at 12, 16, and 26 hours. If the q12
      regimen is deemed safe and tolerable after review by the SMC, Cohort D will commence with the
      800mg q8 hour x 3 regimen. Total serum cefixime levels will be drawn for Cohort D at 8, 16,
      20 and 26 hours (see Section 7.2). All Stages, All Cohorts: All samples collected for PK
      analysis will be shipped to the University of Toledo, Dr. Jeffrey Blumer's HPLC lab for
      processing. Specimens will be analyzed by high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) for
      total cefixime concentration levels. Targeted clinical evaluations will be used to monitor
      for subject reported side effects. Subjects will be asked about specific symptoms they may
      have experienced, including abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, flatulence, headache,
      and rash, or any other symptoms. Additionally, subjects will be asked to maintain a Subject
      Diary (Appendix E) from Study Day 0 through Day 7 to record information about any symptoms
      experienced or medications taken. Study duration is approximately 47 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic curves of cefixime levels versus time: total time that cefixime levels exceed 4x the MIC of 0.5 mcg/mL(serum level of 2.0 mcg/mL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0-1, 2 and Day 7</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic curves of cefixime levels versus time: time to peak drug level, half-life, and elimination rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0-1, 2 and Day 7</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharyngeal fluid concentrations of cefixime for Cohorts C - D: Cmax and ratio of fluid to serum concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0-1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total serum concentrations of cefixime at multiple time points for both individuals and cohorts in total</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 2 and Day 7</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability assessed by laboratory monitoring, targeted clinical evaluations,: serum chemistries, liver functions tests (LFTs), hematology panel, coagulation panel, and urinalysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening to Day 7</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess subject reported adverse events, unsolicited symptoms and discomforts</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 30</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic curves of cefixime levels versus time: peak cefixime level.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0-1, 2 and Day 7</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic curves of cefixime levels versus time: total area under the curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0-1, 2 and Day 7</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Gonorrhoea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stage 2 (Cohorts C and D)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort C will first be given 1200mg cefixime orally once; Cohort D will be given 800mg cefixime orally three times (every 8 hours); 6 subjects in each cohort</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stage 1 (Cohorts A and B)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort A will be given 400mg of cefixime orally once; Cohort B will be given 800mg of cefixime given orally once; 6 subjects in each cohort</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cefixime</intervention_name>
    <description>Cefixime is an FDA approved oral semi-synthetic cephalosporin antibiotic. The standard dose (400mg), high dose (800mg and 1200mg), and multiple 800mg and 1200mg doses given over a 24-hour period using a dose-frequency escalation method. Cohort A receives 400 mg orally once, Cohort B receives 800 mg orally once; Cohort C receives 1200 mg orally once; Cohort D receives 800 mg orally 3 times (every 8 hrs)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stage 1 (Cohorts A and B)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Stage 2 (Cohorts C and D)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male or female subjects between 18 and 45 years, inclusive

          -  Ability to understand the consent process and procedures

          -  Informed consent obtained and signed

          -  Body mass index (BMI) &lt; 35 kg/m^2

          -  Subjects agree to be available for all study visits

          -  Negative Breathalyzer

          -  Agreement by female subjects with reproductive potential to use an adequate method of
             contraception during the study and for 30 days after study drug administration. Female
             subjects must agree to the use of TWO reliable methods of contraception while
             receiving study drug and for 30 days after study drug administration if sexually
             active, which can include: condoms, spermicidal gel, diaphragm, hormonal or
             non-hormonal intrauterine device, surgical sterilization, oral contraceptive pill
             (OCP), and depot progesterone injections.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who take any prescription medication on a regular basis (except oral
             contraceptives, OCPs), including but not limited to, anti-psychotics,
             anti-depressants, anti-epileptics, cardiac medications, anti-hypertensives etc.

          -  Medical condition that precludes participation, including the following:

          -  Hypertension with confirmed systolic blood pressure &gt;140 mmHg or confirmed diastolic
             blood pressure &gt;90 mmHg, measured after 10 - 15 minutes of rest

          -  Morbid obesity (BMI&gt;/=35)

          -  Current diagnosis of pulmonary disease

          -  History of or current diagnosis of diabetes

          -  Autoimmune disorder, such as lupus, Wegener's, rheumatoid arthritis

          -  History of malignancy except low-grade skin cancer, (i.e., basal cell carcinoma
             thought to be cured)

          -  Known diagnosis of prolonged QT interval

          -  History of alcohol abuse

          -  History of seizure disorder

          -  History of renal disease

          -  Chronic renal, hepatic, or pulmonary disease or other condition that could interfere
             with the absorption of the study drug or predispose to adverse gastrointestinal events
             (e.g., surgical resection of significant proportions of the stomach or bowel, gastric
             bypass, gastric banding, irritable bowel syndrome, inflammatory bowel disease)

          -  Positive serology results for HIV, HBsAg, or HCV antibodies

          -  Subjects who have taken any prescription drugs in the previous 14 days or within 5
             half-lives before dosing

          -  Ingestion of over the counter medications or herbal supplements within 7 days of
             dosing

          -  Positive urine toxicology for marijuana, cocaine, amphetamines, opiates, PCP,
             barbiturates or benzodiazepines

          -  History of allergic reaction or intolerance to cephalosporins

          -  History of allergic reaction to penicillin (all stages)

          -  Subjects with an allergy to macrolides may not participate in Stage 3

          -  Subjects with QTc &gt;450ms (Fridericia's correction) on screening ECG may not
             participate in Stage 3.

          -  Positive pregnancy test; pregnant or nursing women

          -  Screening laboratory tests outside of the acceptable limits presented in Appendix C

          -  Any specific condition that, in the judgment of the Investigator, precludes
             participation because it could affect subject safety
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Bayview Medical Center - Infectious Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224-2735</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 19, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 27, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gonococcal Infections, Cefixime, Neisseria gonorrhoeae, Azithromycin, antibiotic, cephalosporin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease Susceptibility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gonorrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cephalosporins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cefixime</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

