<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01945671</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HYMC 0070-13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01945671</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Influence of Obesity on Oocyte, Cumulus and Granulosa Functioning</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Influence of Obesity on Oocyte Functioning and Fertilization, Cumulus and Granulosa Functioning and Metabolic Factors.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hillel Yaffe Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hillel Yaffe Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obese women have a higher prevalence of infertility than their lean counterparts. Obesity is
      a risk factor for anovulation , including in response to gonadotropin treatment .Further,
      even in women who are cycling regularly, obesity is associated with increased
      time-to-pregnancy and decreased chance of natural pregnancy.

      During obesity or periods of overnutrition, lipid accumulates in nonadipose tissues, notably
      skeletal muscle, liver, heart, and pancreas due to cellular uptake of exogenous fatty acids,
      triglycerides, and cholesterol as well as de novo lipogenesis in response to elevated
      glucose. The accumulation of intracellular lipid leads to high levels of free fatty acids
      that are subject to oxidative damage and the formation of cytotoxic and highly reactive lipid
      peroxides, which ultimately are detrimental to intracellular organelles, particularly the
      endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and mitochondria. Exposure of the ER to high levels of free fatty
      acids and lipid peroxides causes structural alterations that perturb ER function and lead to
      accumulation of unfolded proteins and calcium release. Failure of the UPR to reestablish ER
      homeostasis can lead to apoptosis .When mitochondria are exposed to high levels of free fatty
      acids, these can become oxidized by mitochondrial reactive oxygen species, forming lipid
      peroxides that damage essential proteins and uncouple mitochondrial function. This results in
      mitochondrial damage, which can cause further accumulation of lipids that cannot be
      catabolized, disrupted cellular homeostasis, and ultimately apoptosis .

      The cellular mechanisms by which obesity causes decreased conception rates are not known.
      Based on extensive evidence of obesity-induced lipotoxicity in other cells, it was
      hypothesized that obesity results in the activation of lipotoxicity pathways in the ovary. It
      was shown that lipid accumulation, ER stress, mitochondrial dysfunction, and apoptosis occur
      in ovarian cells and the oocyte in response to a high-fat diet.

      The aim of our study was to evaluate the influence of high BMI on oocytes, granulose cells
      and metabolites in the follicular fluid.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All women undergone IVF-ICSI cycles will be recruited in the study. They will be divided into
      3 subgroups according to their BMI: 18.5-24.9 -normal; 25-29.9 - overweight ; ≥30 - obese.

      i. A blood sample will be collected on the day of OPU and several markers will be checked-
      triglycerides, free fatty acid, cholesterol (HDl, LDL), insulin, glucose, lactate, IGF-1,
      Leptin E2, Progessterone, IL-1, Il-6 and TNF-α.

      ii. After isolation of the oocytes from the follicular fluids - a blood free fluid from the
      leading follicle will be collected in a container for further evaluation of metabolic markers
      including triglycerides, free fatty acid, cholesterol (HDl, LDL), insulin, glucose, lactate,
      IGF-1, Leptin E2, Progessterone, IL-1, Il-6 and TNF-α , ROS.

      iii. Cumulus cells will be collected after denudation of oocytes for ICSI and will be
      analyzed for apoptosis marker - Caspase 3 staining , Tunnel iv. Oocytes diameter - all
      denudated oocytes will be captured in the inverted microscope and the diameter will be
      measured.

      v. GV oocytes, M1 and M2 that fail to fertilize will be analyzed for triglycerides, FFA and
      cholesterol concentration.

      vi. GDF-9, BMP-15, BMP-6, TNF-α, SMAD family will be analyzed by western blott as marker for
      oocytes quality.

      vii. Number of oocytes, mature (M2) oocytes, fertilization rate, cleavage rate, number
      embryos transferred, implantation rate, and pregnancy rate will be followed as well.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pregnancy rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>lipid profile in different BMI</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>BMI</condition>
  <condition>Lipid Profile</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      1. triglycerides, free fatty acid, cholesterol (HDl, LDL), insulin, glucose, lactate, IGF-1,
      Leptin E2, Progessterone, IL-1, Il-6 and TNF-2. α.blood free fluid from the leading follicle
      will be collected in a container for further evaluation of metabolic markers including
      triglycerides, free fatty acid, cholesterol (HDl, LDL), insulin, glucose, lactate, IGF-1,
      Leptin E2, Progessterone, IL-1, Il-6 and TNF-α , ROS.

      3. Cumulus cells 4. Oocytes diameter 5. GV oocytes, M1 and M2 that fail to fertilize 6.
      GDF-9, BMP-15, BMP-6, TNF-α, SMAD family will be analyzed by western blott as marker for
      oocytes quality.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients undergo IVF treatments
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>42 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 15, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 18, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 17, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 17, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 18, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

