<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01943994</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00016166</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01943994</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Psilocybin-facilitated Smoking Cessation Treatment: A Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Psilocybin-facilitated Smoking Cessation Treatment: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beckley Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Heffter Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      One of the most promising lines of investigation for the therapeutic use of hallucinogens in
      the 1960s and 1970s was in the treatment of drug dependence. We propose to examine psilocybin
      administration combined with a structured smoking cessation treatment program in nicotine
      dependent individuals in order to provide preliminary data on the efficacy of this combined
      treatment for smoking cessation. Prior work in our laboratory has shown that under carefully
      prepared and supportive conditions, psilocybin administration can facilitate highly salient
      experiences with enduring personal meaning and spiritual significance (Griffiths et al.,
      2006, 2008). It is plausible that embedding such highly meaningful experiences into a drug
      dependence cessation attempt may provide an enduring motivation for remaining abstinent.
      Cigarette smoking is a good model system for studying drug dependence because users are less
      likely to be challenged by the many social and economic impairments that often accompany
      dependence on other drugs such as cocaine, heroin, or alcohol. More specifically, we propose
      to conduct a randomized controlled comparative efficacy study in which either psilocybin or
      transdermal nicotine patch are administered under highly supportive conditions to individuals
      who are nicotine-dependent cigarette smokers, who have had multiple unsuccessful quit
      attempts, and who continue to desire to quit smoking. Other than nicotine dependence,
      participants will be healthy. Fifteen participants have already completed a preliminary
      open-label pilot-study with no control condition. Eighty additional participants will be
      enrolled and randomized to either psilocybin (n=40), or nicotine patch (n=40) treatment.
      Participants will receive a 13-week course of cognitive behavioral therapy for smoking
      cessation, with Target Quit Date set for week 5. After several preparation meetings with
      study monitors, participants will have either a single day-long psilocybin session using a
      high dose (30 mg/70 kg), or a standard 8 to 10-week course of nicotine patch treatment.
      Participant smoking status will be assessed repeatedly for 8 weeks after the Target Quit
      Date, including biological verification of smoking status through breath and urine samples.
      Smoking status will also be assessed at three follow up sessions approximately 3, 6, and 12
      months after the Target Quit Date. Additionally, 50 of these participants (25 per treatment
      condition) will undergo MRI scanning before and after Target Quit Date to assess the
      brain-based mechanisms associated with these treatments. Individuals assigned to the nicotine
      patch study treatment condition will be eligible to undergo an optional high dose psilocybin
      session after completing the 6-month follow-up meeting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary cotinine</measure>
    <time_frame>At study intake, then at 3, 6, and 12 month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>Urinary cotinine is a biological method used to verify smoking or non-smoking status of participants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Breath CO</measure>
    <time_frame>For 13 weeks during active treatment, then at 3, 6, and 12 month follow up.</time_frame>
    <description>Breath Carbon Monoxide (CO) level is a biological method used to verify smoking or non-smoking status of participants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MRI scanning</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks (pre), 5 weeks (post), and 3 month follow up (for individuals still abstinent at this time point)</time_frame>
    <description>50 participants will undergo MRI scanning in week 2 before their Target Quit Date, and in week 5 the day after their Target Quit Date. Participants who are biologically verified as smoking abstinent at 3-month follow-up will also complete an additional MRI scan at that time. For all MRI scanning sessions participants will be asked to refrain from smoking for 24 hours prior to the scan.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Nicotine Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Psilocybin-assisted treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a 13-week cognitive behavioral intervention for smoking cessation, with a high dose of psilocybin (30mg / 70kg) to be administered on the Target Quit Date in week 5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nicotine Replacement Therapy (NRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive a 13-week cognitive behavioral intervention for smoking cessation, with a standard 8 to 10-week regimen of NRT to be administered beginning on the Target Quit Date in week 5. NRT for this study will be a transdermal nicotine patch administered according to recommended label usage (For individuals who smoke more than 10 cigarettes per day: 21mg daily weeks 1-6, 14mg daily weeks 7-8, 7mg daily weeks 9-10. For individuals who smoke 10 or less cigarettes per day: 14mg daily for weeks 1-6, 7mg daily for weeks 7-8).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psilocybin-assisted treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be administered 30 mg/70 kg psilocybin. Preliminary evidence from our ongoing psilocybin dose-effects study suggests that this dose is associated with mystical-type experiences.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Psilocybin-assisted treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>O-phosphoryl-4-hydroxy-N,N-dimethyltryptamine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nicotine Replacement Therapy (NRT)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Nicotine Replacement Therapy (NRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Transdermal Nicotine Patch</other_name>
    <other_name>Nicoderm CQ</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  21 to 65 years old.

          -  Have given written informed consent.

          -  Have a high school level of education.

          -  Be a daily smoker with multiple unsuccessful previous quit attempts, and report a
             continued desire to quit smoking.

          -  Agree to abstain from smoking and alcohol for 24-hours, and caffeine for 12-hours
             prior to MRI scanning (for MRI participants only).

          -  Agree to abstain from smoking for the psilocybin session from 1 hour before psilocybin
             administration until at least 30 hours afterwards.

          -  Agree to consume approximately the same amount of caffeine-containing beverage (e.g.,
             coffee, tea) that he/she consumes on a usual morning, before arriving at the research
             unit on the morning of drug session day. If the volunteer does not routinely consume
             caffeinated beverages, he or she must agree not to do so on session day.

          -  Agree to refrain from using any psychoactive drugs, including alcoholic beverages,
             within 24 hours of psilocybin administration. Exceptions include caffeine and
             nicotine.

          -  Be healthy as determined by screening for medical problems via a personal interview, a
             medical questionnaire, a physical examination, an electrocardiogram (ECG), and routine
             medical blood and urinalysis laboratory tests.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are pregnant (positive pregnancy test) or nursing, or are not practicing an
             effective means of birth control

          -  Cardiovascular conditions: uncontrolled hypertension, angina, a clinically significant
             ECG abnormality (e.g., atrial fibrilation), TIA in the last 6 months stroke,
             peripheral or pulmonary vascular disease

          -  Epilepsy with history of seizures

          -  Insulin-dependent diabetes; if taking oral hypoglycemic agent, then no history of
             hypoglycemia

          -  Currently taking psychoactive prescription medication on a regular basis

          -  Currently taking on a regular (e.g., daily) basis any medications having a primary
             centrally-acting pharmacological effect on serotonin neurons or medications that are
             MAO inhibitors. For individuals who have intermittent or PRN use of such medications,
             psilocybin sessions will not be conducted until at least 5 half-lives of the agent
             have elapsed after the last dose.

          -  Have HIV or Syphilis.

          -  Have any current neurological illnesses including, but not limited to, seizure
             disorders, frequent migraines or on prophylaxis, multiple sclerosis, movement
             disorders, history of significant head trauma, or CNS tumor.

          -  Morbidly obese, or severely underweight as determined by medical examination.

          -  Not suitable to undergo an MRI session due to certain implanted devices (cardiac
             pacemaker or neurostimulator, some artificial joints, metal pins, surgical clips or
             other implanted metal parts), body morphology, or claustrophobia (for MRI participants
             only).

          -  Current or past history of meeting DSM-IV criteria for Schizophrenia, Psychotic
             Disorder (unless substance-induced or due to a medical condition), or Bipolar I or II
             Disorder.

          -  Current or past history within the last 5 years of meeting DSM-IV criteria for alcohol
             or drug dependence (excluding caffeine and nicotine) or severe major depression.

          -  Have a first or second degree relative with schizophrenia, psychotic disorder (unless
             substance induced or due to a medical condition), or bipolar I or II disorder.

          -  Currently meets DSM-IV criteria for Dissociative Disorder, Anorexia Nervosa, Bulimia
             Nervosa, Major Depression, or Post-traumatic Stress Disorder.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew W Johnson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Albert P Garcia-Romeu, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>4105501972</phone>
    <email>AGarci33@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Behavioral Pharmacology Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Albert P Garcia-Romeu, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>410-550-1972</phone>
      <email>AGarci33@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew W Johnson, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roland R. Griffiths, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.QuitSmokingBaltimore.org</url>
    <description>study recruitment website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 12, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 17, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Psilocybin</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking cessation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nicotine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>N,N-Dimethyltryptamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psilocybin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

