<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01943279</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DUNNS-AFPFY112-RFUMA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01943279</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Telephone Follow-up With In-person Follow-up After Medical Abortion</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comparison of Remote Follow-up After Medical Abortion Using Telephone and Serum Pregnancy Testing With Standard In-person Follow-up</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Women's College Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Women's College Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Medical abortions in Canada are provided using a standard regimen of methotrexate
      and misoprostol. After these medications are administered, patients are most commonly checked
      for termination of the pregnancy with an ultrasound and physical examination at an in-clinic
      follow-up appointment. These follow-up appointments can be inconvenient, costly, and take
      away from patient privacy. Furthermore, it has been suggested that these follow-up
      appointments may not be necessary for patients.

      Objective: To determine whether remote follow-up, using telephone and blood testing is a
      feasible, safe, and effective method of follow‐up after medical abortion, compared to
      standard care that requires an in-clinic visit and ultrasound.

      This study offers women the option of remote follow-up by telephone combined with serum
      Beta-human chorionic gonadotropin (β-hCG) testing or standard in-clinic follow up. We will
      determine women's preferences for follow up, and compare adherence to the follow-up schedule,
      number of clinical contacts, and outcomes of the abortion. This study will be performed at
      two clinics in Toronto, the Bay Centre for Birth Control (BCBC) and the Choice in Health
      Clinic (CIHC).

      Primary Hypothesis: Follow-up will be more successful with RFU, compared to SFU.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The protocol is altered for women who have an ultrasound that shows only a gestational sac
      (no yolk sac or fetal pole). Women in both follow-up groups will have β-hCG testing on the
      day of methotrexate injection and again in 8 days. If the level does not fall by 50% or they
      have concerning symptoms, they are asked to return to clinic for evaluation. If the β-hCG
      level falls by 50% or more, they will continue to be followed as per the protocol in their
      chosen group, but will be followed until their β-hCG becomes negative.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of successful follow-up in women choosing RFU compared with those choosing SFU after medical abortion with M&amp;M</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the designated time of 15 days post methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Successful follow-up will be defined as completion of telephone follow-up contact and serum β-hCG testing (for the RFU cohort) or attendance for the in-clinic follow-up visit within the designated time of 15 days post methotrexate injection ±3 days (for the SFU cohort).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of women who choose RFU</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of women choosing RFU who complete follow-up without a clinic visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Within the designated time of 15 days post methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of women in RFU and SFU groups who made no unscheduled visits related to medical abortion</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days of methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency department visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days of methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determined through subject history</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hemorrhage - defined as bleeding resulting in transfusion, intravenous fluids or a drop in hemoglobin of 20 g</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days of methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determined from patient history with retrieval of emergency department/hospital records or documented drop of 20 g.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>D&amp;C with the cause characterized as 1) for bleeding, at clinician's recommendation, 2) for continuing pregnancy, 3) at patient's request (usually because of delayed expulsion of the pregnancy in a medically stable patient)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 35 days of methotrexate injection</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Infection requiring antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days of methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determined from the clinic record or subject history</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of SFU and RFU</measure>
    <time_frame>At 28 days after methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using an Acceptability Questionnaire administered at discharge from ongoing care. This questionnaire is adapted from a previous study of acceptability of mifepristone and misoprostol abortions by Winikoff et al. It contains four close-ended and three open-ended questions designed to capture the patient's perspective on their medical abortion experience, whether they would choose the same method of follow-up in future, and their opinions on the best and worst features of their chosen follow-up method.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subject-initiated telephone contacts during clinic hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days of methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Abstracted from the medical record</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subject-initiated telephone contacts to on-call physician</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days of methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Abstracted from the medical record</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of clinic-initiated telephone contacts outside of the scheduled follow-up contact for the RFU group</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days of methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Abstracted from the medical record</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of letters sent</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days of methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Abstracted from the medical record</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Selected method of contraception</measure>
    <time_frame>At 28 days after methotrexate injection ±3 days</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Reason for choice of follow-up method</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">139</enrollment>
  <condition>Medical; Abortion, Fetus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Follow-up (SFU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women selecting SFU at either site (BCBC or CIHC) will schedule their in-person follow-up appointment before leaving the BCBC clinic on Study Day 1, when they receive their medication. In-person follow-up appointment will be scheduled for Study Day 15 (± 3 days)where, as per usual care, includes a history and a Post-abortion Checklist, transvaginal ultrasound, and a bimanual exam to confirm successful pregnancy expulsion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Remote Follow-up (RFU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>On Study Day 1 in both sites, women selecting RFU will receive 3 laboratory requisition forms for serum β-hCG testing and will be instructed to have testing done at a laboratory site of her choice on Study Day 10-12. The follow-up telephone appointment will be scheduled to take place on Study Day 15 (±3 days). For the follow-up telephone appointment, the research nurse/nurse practitioner will calculate the percentage fall in the β-hCG value. She will contact the subject by phone at the specified time, take a history of the timing of misoprostol use, resulting symptoms and complete the symptom Post-abortion Check-list. The research nurse/nurse practitioner, in consultation with the clinic physician if necessary, will confirm the information, determine whether other follow-up is required.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Remote Follow-up (RFU)</intervention_name>
    <description>Women in the RFU group will be asked to return to the clinic for assessment if they have any complications.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Remote Follow-up (RFU)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>telephone follow-up</other_name>
    <other_name>serum hCG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Follow-up (SFU)</intervention_name>
    <description>Study Day 15 (± 3 days)requires an in-person post-abortion checkup: transvaginal ultrasound, and a bimanual exam to confirm successful pregnancy expulsion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Follow-up (SFU)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>In-clinic visit</other_name>
    <other_name>Ultrasound</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Requests a medical abortion and fulfills standard eligibility criteria for M&amp;M
             abortion:

               -  Clear decision to have an abortion

               -  Valid Ontario Health card

               -  Willing to abstain for vaginal intercourse and alcohol for 14 days

               -  Ability to insert misoprostol vaginal tablets

               -  Emergency Contact number

               -  Stop folic acid vitamins on initial contact

               -  Good general health

               -  Single intrauterine gestation less than or equal to 49 days as determined by
                  transvaginal ultrasound

               -  Telephone access

               -  Access to emergency medical care within 30 minutes of home

               -  Agrees to undergo a surgical abortion in case of failure of the medical abortion
                  method

          2. Ability to understand the protocol and consent

          3. Willingness to comply with either the SFU or RFU follow-up schedule

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Factors that exclude women from eligibility for M&amp;M abortion:

               -  Coagulopathy or hemoglobin less than 100, White Blood Cell count &lt; 4.0 platelet
                  &lt;140,000

               -  Allergy to methotrexate or misoprostol

               -  Presence of an intrauterine device

               -  Acute or chronic renal or hepatic disease

               -  Acute inflammatory bowel disease

               -  Uncontrolled seizure disorder

               -  Sickle cell anemia

               -  Breastfeeding

               -  Chronic oral corticosteroid therapy

               -  Any condition that in the opinion of the clinician investigator would compromise
                  the safety of medical abortion for this patient

          2. Requires the support of an interpreter
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sheila Dunn, MD MSc CCFP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Women's College Hospital, University of Toronto</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women's College Hospital-Bay Center for Birth Control</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G1N8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Choice in Health Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M6P 1A9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perriera LK, Reeves MF, Chen BA, Hohmann HL, Hayes J, Creinin MD. Feasibility of telephone follow-up after medical abortion. Contraception. 2010 Feb;81(2):143-9. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2009.08.008. Epub 2009 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>20103453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark W, Panton T, Hann L, Gold M. Medication abortion employing routine sequential measurements of serum hCG and sonography only when indicated. Contraception. 2007 Feb;75(2):131-5. Epub 2006 Dec 22.</citation>
    <PMID>17241843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark W, Bracken H, Tanenhaus J, Schweikert S, Lichtenberg ES, Winikoff B. Alternatives to a routine follow-up visit for early medical abortion. Obstet Gynecol. 2010 Feb;115(2 Pt 1):264-72. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e3181c996f3.</citation>
    <PMID>20093898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaneshiro B, Edelman A, Sneeringer RK, Ponce de Leon RG. Expanding medical abortion: can medical abortion be effectively provided without the routine use of ultrasound? Contraception. 2011 Mar;83(3):194-201. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2010.07.023. Epub 2010 Sep 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21310279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fiala C, Safar P, Bygdeman M, Gemzell-Danielsson K. Verifying the effectiveness of medical abortion; ultrasound versus hCG testing. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol. 2003 Aug 15;109(2):190-5.</citation>
    <PMID>12860340</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Creinin MD, Vittinghoff E, Keder L, Darney PD, Tiller G. Methotrexate and misoprostol for early abortion: a multicenter trial. I. Safety and efficacy. Contraception. 1996 Jun;53(6):321-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8773418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>von Hertzen H, Honkanen H, Piaggio G, Bartfai G, Erdenetungalag R, Gemzell-Danielsson K, Gopalan S, Horga M, Jerve F, Mittal S, Ngoc NT, Peregoudov A, Prasad RN, Pretnar-Darovec A, Shah RS, Song S, Tang OS, Wu SC; WHO Research Group on Post-Ovulatory Methods for Fertility Regulation. WHO multinational study of three misoprostol regimens after mifepristone for early medical abortion. I: Efficacy. BJOG. 2003 Sep;110(9):808-18.</citation>
    <PMID>14511962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schaff EA, Fielding SL, Westhoff C. Randomized trial of oral versus vaginal misoprostol at one day after mifepristone for early medical abortion. Contraception. 2001 Aug;64(2):81-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11704083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rossi B, Creinin MD, Meyn LA. Ability of the clinician and patient to predict the outcome of mifepristone and misoprostol medical abortion. Contraception. 2004 Oct;70(4):313-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15451336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 11, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 16, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 8, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 8, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Women's College Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sheila Dunn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, MSc, CCFP(EM), FCFP</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>medical abortion</keyword>
  <keyword>telephone follow-up</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>serum hCG</keyword>
  <keyword>methotrexate</keyword>
  <keyword>misoprostol</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

