<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01949675</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SHC02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1127-7355</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01949675</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Two Doses of Oral Cholera Vaccine (Shanchol™) in Subjects Aged 1 Year and Older in the Philippines</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Immunogenicity of Two Doses of Oral Cholera Vaccine (Shanchol™) in Subjects Aged 1 Year and Older in the Philippines</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sanofi Pasteur, a Sanofi Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the study is to generate safety and immunogenicity data with Oral Cholera Vaccine
      (Shanchol™) in The Philippines

      Objectives:

        -  To describe the safety after each dose of Shanchol vaccine.

        -  To describe the immunogenicity after each dose of Shanchol vaccine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Healthy toddlers, children, adolescents and adults, aged 1 year and older will receive two
      doses of vaccine 14 days apart, and will be assessed baseline immunogenicity
      (pre-vaccination), and 14 days after each vaccine dose. Safety data will be collected for 14
      days after the first dose and 30 days after the second dose.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants reporting unsolicited systemic adverse events; solicited systemic reactions including serious adverse events following administration Oral Cholera Vaccine (Shanchol™)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 up to Day 44 post oral vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited systemic reaction: Vomiting, Diarrhea, Fever (temperature), Abdominal pain, Itching, Rash, Weakness, Cough, Vertigo, and Dryness of Mouth</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Summary of titers of serum vibriocidal antibodies Before and 14 days after each Oral Cholera Vaccine (Shanchol™)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 (before) and Day 14 post oral vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Serum vibriocidal antibody (against V. cholerae O1 Inaba serogroup, V. cholerae O1 Ogawa serogroup, and V. cholerae O139 serogroup) will be assessed using the microtiter technique.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with 4-fold or greater rises in titers 14 days after each Oral Cholera Vaccine (Shanchol™) relative to baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 (before) and Day 14 post oral vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Serum vibriocidal antibody (against V. cholerae O1 Inaba serogroup, V. cholerae O1 Ogawa serogroup, and V. cholerae O139 serogroup) will be assessed using the microtiter technique.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">336</enrollment>
  <condition>Cholera</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants aged 1 through 4 years at enrollment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants aged 5 through 14 years at enrollment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants aged 15 years and above at enrollment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Shanchol™: Oral Cholera Vaccine Killed Bivalent (O1 and O139) Whole Cell</intervention_name>
    <description>1.5 mL, Oral administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Shanchol™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Shanchol™: Oral Cholera Vaccine Killed Bivalent (O1 and O139) Whole Cell</intervention_name>
    <description>1.5 mL, Oral administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Shanchol™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Shanchol™: Oral Cholera Vaccine Killed Bivalent (O1 and O139) Whole Cell</intervention_name>
    <description>1.5 mL, Oral administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Shanchol™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 1 year and older on the day of inclusion

          -  Subjects aged 1 through 17 years: informed consent form has been signed and dated by
             the subject's parent (and subject, if applicable by local Institution Ethics Committee
             (IEC) / Institution Review Board (IRB) or country regulations), or another legally
             acceptable representative (and independent witness, if required by local regulations),
             and the assent form has been signed and dated by the subject (if applicable by the
             local IEC / IRB or country regulations)

          -  Subjects aged 18 years and older: informed consent form has been signed and dated by
             the subject (and an independent witness, if required by local regulations).

          -  Subject and subject's parent / legally acceptable representative (if applicable) are
             able to attend all scheduled visits and to comply with all trial procedures

          -  Subjects aged less than 2 years only: Born at full term of pregnancy (≥ 37 weeks)
             and/or with a birth weight ≥ 2.5 kg.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is pregnant, or lactating, or of childbearing potential (to be considered of
             non-childbearing potential, a female must be pre-menarche or post-menopausal for at
             least 1 year, surgically sterile, or using an effective method of contraception or
             abstinence from at least 4 weeks prior to the first vaccination and until at least 4
             weeks after the last vaccination)

          -  Participation at the time of study enrollment or planned participation during the
             present trial period in another clinical trial investigating a vaccine, drug, medical
             device, or medical procedure

          -  Receipt of any vaccine in the 4 weeks preceding the first trial vaccination or planned
             receipt of any vaccine in the 4 weeks following any trial vaccination except for
             influenza vaccination, which may be received at least 2 weeks before or after any
             study vaccination

          -  Previous vaccination against cholera (in the previous 5 years) with either the trial
             vaccine or another vaccine

          -  Receipt of immune globulins, blood or blood-derived products in the past 3 months

          -  Known or suspected congenital or acquired immunodeficiency; or receipt of
             immunosuppressive therapy, such as anti-cancer chemotherapy or radiation therapy,
             within the preceding 6 months; or long-term systemic corticosteroid therapy
             (prednisone or equivalent for more than 2 consecutive weeks within the past 3 months)

          -  History of cholera infection, confirmed either clinically, serologically, or
             microbiologically

          -  At high risk for cholera infection during the trial (i.e., cholera outbreak situation
             or close contact to cholera case)

          -  Known systemic hypersensitivity to any of the vaccine components, or history of a
             life-threatening reaction to the vaccine used in the trial or to a vaccine containing
             any of the same substances

          -  Deprived of freedom by an administrative or court order, or in an emergency setting,
             or hospitalized involuntarily

          -  Current alcohol abuse or drug addiction

          -  Chronic illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, is at a stage where it might
             interfere with trial conduct or completion

          -  Intake of oral antibiotics within one week prior to enrollment

          -  Moderate or severe acute illness/infection (according to investigator judgment) on the
             day of vaccination or febrile illness (temperature ≥ 38.0°C). A prospective subject
             should not be included in the study until the condition has resolved or the febrile
             event has subsided

          -  Identified as an Investigator or employee of the Investigator or study center with
             direct involvement in the proposed study, or identified as an immediate family member
             (i.e., parent, spouse, natural, or adopted child) of the Investigator or employee with
             direct involvement in the proposed study

          -  Diarrhea (3 [or more] loose/watery stools within a 24-hours period) within 6 weeks
             prior to enrollment. A prospective subject should not be included in the study until
             the condition has resolved.

          -  Intake of anti-diarrhea medicine within one week prior to enrollment

          -  Abdominal pain or cramps, loss of appetite, nausea, or vomiting within 24 hours prior
             to enrollment. A prospective subject should not be included in the study until the
             condition has resolved.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sanofi Pasteur SA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Manila</city>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Muntinlupa City</city>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Philippines</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Capeding MRZ, Gonzales MLAM, Dhingra MS, D'Cor NA, Midde VJ, Patnaik BN, Thollot Y, Desauziers E. Safety and immunogenicity of the killed bivalent (O1 and O139) whole-cell cholera vaccine in the Philippines. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2017 Oct 3;13(10):2232-2239. doi: 10.1080/21645515.2017.1342908.</citation>
    <PMID>28910563</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 20, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cholera</keyword>
  <keyword>Shanchol™</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholera Vaccine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cholera</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

