<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01947465</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CS_2013_01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01947465</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunogenicity and Safety of Vaccinations in Immunocompromised Persons</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Cohort Study in 6 Swiss Rheumatology Centres and 4 Travel Clinics on the Immunogenicity and Safety of Tetanus and Hepatitis A Vaccine in Patients With Rheumatoid Arthritis, Axial Spondyloarthritis and Vasculitis and Healthy Controls</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Basel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swiss Tropical &amp; Public Health Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Bern</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Geneva</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cantonal Hospital of St. Gallen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cantonal Hospital of Aarau, Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Zurich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Backgound and relevance of the project:

      Patients with autoimmune inflammatory rheumatic diseases (AIIRD) are at increased risk of
      contracting infections. The increased risk can be attributed to the immunological disorder
      itself, as well as to the immunosuppressive treatment. Vaccination against many infections is
      recommended in this patient group. However, the immunogenicity of vaccines may be reduced and
      may also be influenced by the administered treatment. Potential reactivation of the
      underlying disease triggered by vaccination is another important concern.

      From the patients' and public health perspectives, an important task of physicians is giving
      advice on vaccines. Completing this task is often difficult, because data on the
      immunogenicity and safety of vaccines in these patient groups are scarce, especially with
      regard to treatment with new immunosuppressive medications, such as biological agents. Lastly
      and importantly, due to new therapeutic options, health among AIIRD patients has considerably
      improved and an increasing number of patients undertake overseas travel activities requiring
      additional vaccinations. In this context, reliable advice with regard to vaccinations is
      almost impossible, because for most travel vaccinations the immunogenicity and safety profile
      is unknown.

      Research addressing the immunogenicity and safety of vaccines in different autoimmune
      inflammatory diseases treated with different immunosuppressive medications is urgently needed
      to allow giving evidence based vaccine advice.

      In this observational study the immunogenicity and safety of tetanus booster and hepatitis A
      vaccinations will be assessed in AIIRD patients. The immune response will be evaluated as a
      function of the underlying disease and the possible influence of commonly used
      immunosuppressive drugs on the immune response will be studied.

      Rationale for studying tetanus booster and hepatitis A vaccine Tetanus vaccination is one of
      the most frequently recommended vaccinations, and the effect of a booster vaccination can be
      addressed. Hepatitis A vaccine is the most widely used travel vaccine. Despite their
      importance, only very limited data are available for tetanus and hepatitis A vaccine in this
      patient group. By focusing on these vaccines the study will lead the way to the evaluation of
      further vaccines.

      The purpose of this study is to determine whether tetanus and hepatitis A vaccinations are as
      immunogenic and safe in AIIRD patients as in healthy controls.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be placed in 6 rheumatology clinics in Switzerland and in 4 travel medicine
      clinics. Consecutive subjects with rheumatoid arthritis, spondylarthritis (ankylosing
      spondylitis), vasculitis (ANCA associated vasculitis and Behçet's disease) and healthy
      controls will be recruited.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity of hepatitis A and tetanus vaccination in patients with rheumatoid arthritis, axial spondyloarthritis and vasculitis and in healthy controls</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in geometric mean antibody titre and seroprotection at 4 weeks and at 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of the geometric mean antibody titre and percentage of seroprotected individuals after tetanus and hepatitis A vaccination between each disease group and healthy controls</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of tetanus and hepatitis A vaccines in patients with rheumatoid arthritis, axial spondyloarthritis and vasculitis and in healthy controls</measure>
    <time_frame>Activation of rheumatic disease will be assessed for 1 week after vaccine administration and at 4 and 12 weeks compared to baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with any worsening or reactivation of the rheumatic disease after vaccine administration
Number of participants with adverse vaccine reactions (local and systemic reactions) in patients with rheumatoid arthritis, axial spondyloarthritis and vasculitis and in healthy controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">645</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</condition>
  <condition>Spondylarthritis</condition>
  <condition>Vasculitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>If a vaccination is indicated according to the recommendations by the Swiss Federal Office of Public Health: 319 healthy controls will be enrolled and will receive hepatitis A and/or tetanus vaccination</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with rheumatoid arthritis</arm_group_label>
    <description>If a vaccination is indicated according to the recommendations by the Swiss Federal Office of Public Health: 142 patients with rheumatoid arthritis will be enrolled and will receive hepatitis A and/or tetanus vaccination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with axial spondylarthritis</arm_group_label>
    <description>If a vaccination is indicated according to the recommendations by the Swiss Federal Office of Public Health: 142 patients with axial spondylarthritis will be enrolled and will receive hepatitis A and/or tetanus vaccination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with vasculitis</arm_group_label>
    <description>If a vaccination is indicated according to the recommendations by the Swiss Federal Office of Public Health: 142 patients with vasculitis will be enrolled and will receive hepatitis A and/or tetanus vaccination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hepatitis A vaccine and tetanus vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Hepatitis A and/or tetanus vaccination will be given to participants in all group on day 0. All monovalent active hepatitis A vaccinations and all vaccines containing tetanus toxoid available in Switzerland may be used in the study</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with rheumatoid arthritis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with axial spondylarthritis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with vasculitis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Havrix 1440</other_name>
    <other_name>Epaxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Td-Pur</other_name>
    <other_name>Boostrix</other_name>
    <other_name>BoostrixPolio</other_name>
    <other_name>Revaxis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Sera from participants will be kept in a biobank for further measurements of antibody
      responses after vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The cohort will be selected from patients with rheumatic diseases under treatment at 6
        rheumatology outpatient clinics in Switzerland (University of Basel, University of Bern,
        University of Geneva, University of Zurich, Cantonal Hospital Aarau, Cantonal Hospital St.
        Gallen)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Indication for hepatitis A and/or tetanus vaccination according to Swiss Federal
             Office of Public Health recommendations

          -  Male and female rheumatic patients with rheumatoid arthritis or axial
             spondyloarthritis (ankylosing spondylitis, axial psoriatic arthritis, axial
             undifferentiated spondyloarthritis, enteropahtic arthritis) or peripheral psoriatic
             arthritis or vasculitis (Behçet's disease or ANCA-associated vasculitis) or male and
             female healthy participants ≥ 18 years

          -  Signed Informed Consent after being informed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known hypersensitivity to a vaccine ingredient

          -  Estimated patient survival below 1 year

          -  Active malignant or active infectious disease

          -  Drug/alcohol abuse

          -  Insufficient understanding of local language
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christoph Hatz, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Zurich, Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Prevention Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cantonal Hospital Aarau, Division of Rheumatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarau</city>
        <state>Aargau</state>
        <zip>5001</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of Basel, Rheumatology Division</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <state>Basel Town</state>
        <zip>4031</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Swiss Tropical and Public Health Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <state>Basel Town</state>
        <zip>4051</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Bern, Inselspital, Division of Infectious Diseases and Travel Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Bern, Inselspital, Division of Rheumatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Geneva, University Hospitals, Division of Rheumatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Geneva</city>
        <zip>1211</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Geneva, University Hospitals, Service de Médecine Tropicale et Humanitaire</name>
      <address>
        <city>Geneva</city>
        <zip>1211</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cantonal Hospital St. Gallen, Division of Rheumatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Gallen</city>
        <zip>9007</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Zurich, Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Prevention Institute, Divison of Infectious Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zürich</city>
        <zip>8001</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Zurich, University Hopsital, Divison of Rheumatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zürich</city>
        <zip>8091</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://wwwnc.cdc.gov/travel/yellowbook/2014/chapter-8-advising-travelers-with-specific-needs/immunocompromised-travelers</url>
    <description>Vaccination recommendations in immunocompromised travelers by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.health.belgium.be/internet2Prd/groups/public/@public/@shc/documents/ie2divers/19080078_en.pdf</url>
    <description>Vaccination recommendations in immunocompromised persons, Belgium</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.phac-aspc.gc.ca/publicat/cig-gci/p03-07-eng.php</url>
    <description>Canadian vaccination recommendations in immunocompromised persons</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Assen S, Elkayam O, Agmon-Levin N, Cervera R, Doran MF, Dougados M, Emery P, Geborek P, Ioannidis JP, Jayne DR, Kallenberg CG, Müller-Ladner U, Shoenfeld Y, Stojanovich L, Valesini G, Wulffraat NM, Bijl M. Vaccination in adult patients with auto-immune inflammatory rheumatic diseases: a systematic literature review for the European League Against Rheumatism evidence-based recommendations for vaccination in adult patients with auto-immune inflammatory rheumatic diseases. Autoimmun Rev. 2011 Apr;10(6):341-52. doi: 10.1016/j.autrev.2010.12.003. Epub 2010 Dec 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21182987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bijl M, Kallenberg CG, van Assen S. Vaccination of the immune-compromised patients with focus on patients with autoimmune-inflammatory diseases. Neth J Med. 2011 Jan;69(1):5-13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21325695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doran MF, Crowson CS, Pond GR, O'Fallon WM, Gabriel SE. Frequency of infection in patients with rheumatoid arthritis compared with controls: a population-based study. Arthritis Rheum. 2002 Sep;46(9):2287-93.</citation>
    <PMID>12355475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernatsky S, Hudson M, Suissa S. Anti-rheumatic drug use and risk of serious infections in rheumatoid arthritis. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2007 Jul;46(7):1157-60. Epub 2007 May 3.</citation>
    <PMID>17478469</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kotton CN. Vaccination and immunization against travel-related diseases in immunocompromised hosts. Expert Rev Vaccines. 2008 Jul;7(5):663-72. doi: 10.1586/14760584.7.5.663. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18564020</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rahier JF, Moutschen M, Van Gompel A, Van Ranst M, Louis E, Segaert S, Masson P, De Keyser F. Vaccinations in patients with immune-mediated inflammatory diseases. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2010 Oct;49(10):1815-27. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/keq183. Epub 2010 Jun 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20591834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steffen R, Kane MA, Shapiro CN, Billo N, Schoellhorn KJ, van Damme P. Epidemiology and prevention of hepatitis A in travelers. JAMA. 1994 Sep 21;272(11):885-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8078167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Agarwal N, Ollington K, Kaneshiro M, Frenck R, Melmed GY. Are immunosuppressive medications associated with decreased responses to routine immunizations? A systematic review. Vaccine. 2012 Feb 14;30(8):1413-24. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2011.11.109. Epub 2011 Dec 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22197580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 20, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 25, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vasculitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spondylarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

