<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01008956</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>113924</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01008956</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Immune Response of One-Dose of Candidate H1N1 Influenza Vaccine GSK2340274A in Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunogenicity and Safety Study of GSK Biologicals' Pandemic Influenza (H1N1) Candidate Vaccine GSK2340274A in Adults 18 to 64 Years of Age</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to characterize the safety and immunogenicity of a' pandemic influenza
      (H1N1) candidate vaccine GSK2340274A in adults 18 to 64 years of age.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study was cancelled before enrolment for reasons not related to vaccine safety or efficacy.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral immune response in terms of Hemagglutination Inhibition (HI) antibodies (Vaccine virus-homologous responses)</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 21 after vaccination</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral immune response in terms of HI antibodies against A/California/7/2009 (H1N1)v-like antigen and any drifted strains</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 0, 21 and 182 after vaccination</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral immune response in terms of neutralizing antibodies against A/California/7/2009 (H1N1)v-like antigen and any drifted strains</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 0, 21 and 182 after vaccination</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of solicited local and general symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>During a 7-day (Day 0-6) follow-up period after vaccination.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of unsolicited adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>During a 21-day (Day 0-20) follow-up period after vaccination and from Days 0 to 84.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of medically attended and/or serious adverse events, and of potentially immune-mediated diseases.</measure>
    <time_frame>From the beginning up to the end of the study (Day 182)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects enrolled in this group will be stratified by age (18 to 40 years and 41 to 64 years)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK Biologicals' investigational H1N1 Influenza Vaccine - GSK2340274A</intervention_name>
    <description>Intramuscular injection, one dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Indian male or female adults 18 to 64 years of age at time of the first vaccination,
             inclusive.

          -  Written informed consent obtained from the subject

          -  Good general health as assessed by medical history and physical examination.

          -  Access to a consistent means of telephone contact, which may be either in the home or
             at the workplace, land line or mobile, but NOT a pay phone or other multiple-user
             device (i.e., a common-use phone serving multiple rooms or apartments)

          -  Subjects who the investigator believes can and will comply with the requirements of
             the protocol.

          -  Female subjects of non-childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study.

          -  Non-childbearing potential is defined as pre-menarche, current tubal ligation,
             hysterectomy, ovariectomy or post-menopause.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study, if the
             subject:

          -  has practiced adequate contraception for 30 days prior to vaccination, and

          -  has a negative pregnancy test on the day of vaccination, and

          -  has agreed to continue adequate contraception during the entire treatment period and
             for 2 months after completion of the vaccination series.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical history of physician-confirmed infection with an A/California/7/2009
             (H1N1)v-like virus.

          -  Previous vaccination at any time with an A/California/7/2009 (H1N1)v-like virus
             vaccine.

          -  Presence or evidence of substance abuse or of neurological or psychiatric diagnoses
             which, although stable, are deemed by the investigator to render the potential subject
             unable/unlikely to provide accurate safety reports.

          -  Presence of a temperature &gt;= 38.0ºC (&gt;=100.4ºF) by any route or method, or acute
             symptoms greater than &quot;mild&quot; severity on the scheduled date of first vaccination.
             NOTE: The subject may be vaccinated at a later date, provided symptoms have resolved,
             vaccination occurs within the window specified by the protocol, and all other
             eligibility criteria continue to be satisfied.

          -  Presence of significant acute or chronic, uncontrolled medical or psychiatric illness
             (&quot;uncontrolled&quot; is defined as requiring institution of new medical or surgical
             treatment or a significant alteration in the dose of an ongoing medication for
             uncontrolled symptoms, illness manifestations or drug toxicity within 3 months
             preceding the receipt of study vaccine).

          -  Diagnosed with cancer, or treatment for cancer within 3 years.

          -  Persons with a history of cancer who are disease-free without treatment for 3 years or
             more are eligible.

          -  Persons with a history of histologically-confirmed basal cell carcinoma of the skin
             successfully treated with local excision only are accepted and may enrol, but other
             histologic types of skin cancer are exclusionary.

          -  Women who are disease-free 3 years or more after treatment for breast cancer and
             receiving long-term prophylactic tamoxifen are excepted and may enrol.

          -  Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive or immunodeficient condition based on
             medical history and physical examination (no laboratory testing required).

          -  Chronic administration (defined as more than 14 days in total) of immunosuppressants
             or other immune modifying drugs within 6 months of study enrolment or planned
             administration during the study period. For corticosteroids, this will mean a dose
             equivalent to 10 mg/day of prednisone or equivalent when administered for &gt; 2 weeks.
             Topical, intra-articular or inhaled and topical steroids are allowed.

          -  Receipt of any immunoglobulins and/or any blood products within 3 months of study
             enrolment or planned administration of any of these products during the study period.

          -  Any significant disorder of coagulation or treatment with warfarin derivatives or
             heparin. Persons receiving individual doses of low molecular weight heparin outside of
             24 hours prior to vaccination are eligible. Persons receiving prophylactic
             antiplatelet medications, e.g., low-dose aspirin, and without a clinically-apparent
             bleeding tendency, are eligible.

          -  An acute evolving neurological disorder or history of Guillain-Barré syndrome within 6
             weeks of receipt of seasonal influenza vaccine.

          -  With the exception of seasonal influenza vaccination, administration of any vaccines
             within 30 days before vaccination. Seasonal influenza vaccine may be administered up
             to 14 days prior to study vaccination.

          -  Planned administration of any vaccine not foreseen by the study protocol from
             vaccination up to blood sampling at Day 21 including seasonal influenza vaccine or a
             monovalent pandemic H1N1 vaccine other than the study vaccine.

          -  Use of any investigational or non-registered product (drug or vaccine) other than the
             study vaccine(s) within 30 days preceding the receipt of study vaccine, or planned use
             during the study period.

          -  Any known or suspected allergy to any constituent of influenza vaccines or component
             used in the manufacturing process of the study vaccine; a history of anaphylactic-type
             reaction to consumption of eggs; or a history of severe adverse reaction to a previous
             influenza vaccine.

          -  Known pregnancy or a positive urine beta-human chorionic gonadotropin (ß-hCG) test
             result prior to the time of vaccination.

          -  Lactating or nursing female.

          -  Any conditions which, in the opinion of the investigator, prevents the subjects from
             participating in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 5, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 5, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 6, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Influenza</keyword>
  <keyword>H1N1</keyword>
  <keyword>Pandemic</keyword>
  <keyword>GSK Bio's influenza vaccine GSK2340274A</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

