<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01000077</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00007586</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01000077</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Establishment of Cell Culture Systems From Discarded Operating Room Tissue</brief_title>
  <official_title>Establishment of Cell Culture Systems From Discarded Operating Room Tissue</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to establish viable cell culture system techniques for a variety
      of healthy and diseased tissues for use in future in vitro and in vivo research studies in
      tissue engineering.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Healthy and diseased tissue will be harvested from tissue routinely discarded in the NCBH
      operating rooms, or from delivery rooms at Forsyth Medical Center during routine operative or
      childbirth procedures. Samples will be identified by source and disease state only. Disease
      state may be of several types including inflammation, malignancy, fibrosis, atherosclerosis,
      hyperplasia etc. These tissue samples will be promptly transported under sterile conditions
      to the Institute of Regenerative Medicine. The tissues will be broken down into individual
      cells by mechanical or enzymatic methods, diluted with growth media and inoculated onto
      sterile tissue culture flasks. The flasks will be placed into a 4% CO2 incubator for culture.
      The cultures will be cultivated for primary and progenitor cells and eventual RNA extraction
      and expression profiling. These cell lines may be then used for future in vitro and in vivo
      research studies yet to be determined. An Institutional Review Board (IRB) must approve any
      future research study using these tissue samples.

      Source of Specimens:

      Healthy and diseased tissue from a variety of sources (examples include bladder, foreskin,
      heart valves, blood vessels, prostate, kidney, uterus, ovary, salivary gland tissue, lacrimal
      gland tissue, muscle tissue, epithelial tissue, nerve tissue and vascular tissue from
      patients undergoing surgery) will be harvested from tissue routinely discarded in the NCBH
      operating rooms during routine operative procedures. In addition, normal term placentas will
      be obtained following vaginal deliveries at Forsyth Medical Center. No patient identifying
      information will be retained. No attempt will be made to match established cell lines derived
      from the tissue samples with the source patient. Eligibility for the protocol is restricted
      to an indication for surgical excision of the tissue in question.

      Confidentiality Considerations:

      No patient identifiers will be collected. It will not be possible to identify or link any
      tissue to the individual patient source in any way once it has been delivered to the
      Institute. The only information identifying the specimen will be tissue source, age and sex
      of patient, and disease state (if any). Informed consent will be obtained.

      Sample Size:

      Approximately 1000 people will take part in this study, all of them at Wake Forest University
      Health Sciences or Forsyth Medical Center.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Discarded Operating Room Tissue</arm_group_label>
    <description>The purpose of this research study is to use the discarded (tissue that would normally be thrown out) tissue from your surgery in order to obtain cells that can be grown in a laboratory to study how to use cells like these to fix sick and diseased organs. We will test if these cells can be used to build new and healthy tissues. This technique is called tissue engineering. In this study we will be comparing cells obtained from different individuals.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Discarded Placenta</arm_group_label>
    <description>During a standard surgery or delivery of a baby unneeded tissue is usually discarded. We would like to explore the opportunity to grow the cells of these discarded tissues in the laboratory. The cells will be placed in special dishes and supplemented with a mixture of salts and nutrients that were designed to allow the cells to survive outside the body and grow. This procedure is called tissue culture of cells. We will attempt to isolate a population of cells from the tissue culture and study them in the laboratory.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Healthy and diseased tissue will be harvested from tissue routinely discarded in the NCBH
      operating rooms, or from delivery rooms at Forsyth Medical Center during routine operative or
      childbirth procedures
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        There is no specific study population for the this study. The patients from whom discarded
        tissue will be harvested will be any patients within the set age criteria in the operating
        room that have viable tissue excised for discard. In other words, when any investigators
        from the study have discard tissue as a result of a surgical procedure, this tissue will be
        a possible specimen for use in the protocol. Only discard tissue will be used, however, so
        if the tissue isn't used in the study, it would simply be thrown away.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Eligibility Criteria:

          -  The subjects would include anyone undergoing a surgical procedure by one the of the
             surgeon co-investigators, during which discard tissue may be harvested.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steve J Hodges, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steve J Hodges, MD</last_name>
    <phone>3367160287</phone>
    <email>shodges@wakehealth.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachel Shertzer-Skinner</last_name>
      <phone>336-716-4131</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steve Hodges, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 21, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 21, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 22, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Regenerative Medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Tissue Collection</keyword>
  <keyword>Cell Culture Systems</keyword>
  <keyword>Routine Surgery</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

