<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01000714</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>protocol No. 1 ver. 1 9-Jan-09</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01000714</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Determination of the Efficacy and Safety of Psirelax in the Relief of the Disease in Psoriasis</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Etwal Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Etwal Ltd.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Psoriasis is a chronic disorder characterized by erythematous scaly patches which affect the
      scalp, trunk, extensor surfaces of the limbs and the genital area. The common form of
      psoriasis is referred to as psoriasis vulgaris. There are several variants of psoriasis such
      as guttate psoriasis, inverse psoriasis, pustular psoriasis and erythrodermic psoriasis.

      Psoriasis is highly prevalent in the general population, mainly as a result of its chronicity
      and the absence of a cure. The estimates of psoriasis prevalence are within the range of 0.5%
      to 4%.

      The diagnosis of psoriasis is made on a clinical base, usually by physical examination,
      performed by a dermatologist. Although skin biopsy may be useful in some cases, there is no
      laboratory test which may serve as a reference standard to the clinical diagnosis of
      psoriasis.

      Psoriasis in its mild cases per se is not associated with excess mortality, however, the
      disease may affect quality of life of affected patients to a substantial degree. Psoriasis
      may be readily apparent to others because of scales and redness of the skin. The skin may
      itch and scales may shed from the patients to the environment or directly on other people.
      Feelings of stigmatization and major changes in life-style caused by psoriasis have been
      documented in numerous studies. The burden of the disease may be exaggerated due to expensive
      therapy and complicated therapeutic regimes Patients with mild to moderate psoriasis are
      usually treated with topical treatments. Photo-therapy or systemic treatments are reserved to
      patients with moderate to severe disease.

      Topical corticosteroids may lead to rapid improvement in psoriasis, however rapid relapse
      following discontinuation is the common practice leading to chronic use.

      Calcipotriene ointment may also be used and requires 8 to 12 weeks of use for maximal effect
      and often causes local irritation, particularly when used on the face. The use is limited to
      100 gr/week due to hypercalcemia that might follow systemic absorption.

      Vitamin A derivative tazarotene may be also be used for plaque psoriasis. Although it can
      produce longer remissions than topical steroids, local irritation, cost, and teratogenicity
      limit its use.

      Coal tar products may be used as steroid-sparing agents, especially useful for enhancing the
      efficacy of natural sunlight and phototherapy. Application can be cumbersome because of
      irritation, unpleasant smell, brown color that can stain clothing, and propensity to cause
      folliculitis.

      All of the above treatments are particularly problematic for the face and genital psoriasis
      due to the potential side effects and mainly possible severe irritation reducing patients
      compliance.

      Psirelax is a novel topical medication directed for the treatment of patients with psoriasis.
      The formulation of Psirelax includes the following substances: 5%-15% quince seeds jelly,
      10%-40% natural base cream (e.g. Ferntree Cottage Pure Base Cream), 55%-75% mixture of
      natural anti-oxidants (e.g. Vitamin E, wheat germ oil, Safflower oil), natural skin softening
      agents (e.g. sweet almond oil, sesame oil), natural absorption aids (e.g. jojoba oil,
      vegetable squalene), natural tissue regenerating and protecting agents (e.g. grape seed oil,
      sunflower oil), natural preservatives (e.g. paraben, tea trea essential oil, thyme essential
      oil, grapefruit seed extract, Vitamin E) and natural thickening agents (e.g. bee wax,
      aloevera, medicinal Vaseline, coconut oil, guar gum, palm oil, borax)

      In a preliminary observation, a patient with severe psoriasis applied Psirelax three times
      each day during four days. The patient reported complete disappearance of the psoriatic
      plaques and pruritus was reduced by 70%. It was suggested to conduct an open study to assess
      the effect of Psirelax in patients with psoriasis vulgaris.

      The aim of this study is to examine the safety and efficacy of Psirelax in the treatment of
      psoriasis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Mild to Moderate Psoriasis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psirelax</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Men and women between 18 and 75 years old, inclusive.

          2. Clinical diagnosis of psoriasis.

          3. In otherwise good general health and free of any disease or physical condition which
             might impair evaluation of plaque psoriasis.

          4. Able to understand and willing to comply with all study requirements, particularly the
             regimen for administration of study drug.

          5. Able to understand and willing to sign the Informed Consent Form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Women who are pregnant, lactating, planning to become pregnant, or women of
             child-bearing potential who have not successfully been using the same medically
             acceptable contraceptive methods over the previous 3 months, e.g., oral contraceptive
             agents, intrauterine device (IUD), and barrier method plus spermicide.

          2. Use of topical anti psoriatic therapy (including topical retinoids, corticosteroids,
             or vitamin D analogs) on the areas to be treated within one week prior to the
             beginning of the study.

          3. Received systemic biologic therapy to treat psoriasis (e.g., alefacept, etanercept,
             infliximab, efalizumab, adalimumab) within 12 weeks prior to the beginning of the
             study.

          4. Received systemic psoriasis therapy (e.g., methotrexate, cyclosporine, systemic
             corticosteroids, retinoids such as acitretin) within 4 weeks prior to the beginning of
             the study.

          5. Received phototherapy (including laser), photo chemotherapy for the study areas within
             4 weeks prior to the beginning of the study.

          6. Recent history (within past 12 months) of alcohol or substance abuse. Alcohol abuse
             will be defined as &gt;14 drinks per week (1 drink = 12 oz beer, 4 oz wine, or 1.5 oz
             distilled spirits).

          7. History of noncompliance to medical regimens or unwilling to comply with the study
             protocol.

          8. Participation in an investigational drug study within 30 days prior to the beginning
             of the study.

          9. Serious or unstable medical or psychological conditions that in the opinion of the
             Investigator would compromise the subject's safety or successful participation in the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clalit Health care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel-Aviv</city>
        <zip>63564</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 22, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 23, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 22, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 22, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 23, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>August 23, 2010</submitted>
    <returned>August 24, 2010</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

