<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00334126</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR010501</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00334126</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Effectiveness and Safety of Paliperidone ER (Extended-release) Compared With Quetiapine in Patients With Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Parallel Group Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Paliperidone ER Compared to Quetiapine in Subjects With an Acute Exacerbation of Schizophrenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Janssen, LP</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy (effectiveness of drug) and safety of
      the antipsychotic paliperidone ER compared to another antipsychotic, quetiapine, and to
      placebo in patients who are acutely ill with symptoms of schizophrenia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized (patients are assigned different treatments based on chance), double
      blind (neither the patient nor the physician knows whether drug or placebo is being taken, or
      at what dosage), placebo controlled, parallel group study to compare the efficacy and safety
      of paliperidone ER with quetiapine in the treatment of patients who have schizophrenia and
      are acutely ill. The duration of the study is 42 days. During the first phase (Day 0 - Day
      14) patients receive increasing doses of the treatment to which they are assigned (starting
      with 3mg and increasing to 9 mg or 12 mg of paliperidone ER; starting with 50 mg and
      increasing to 600 mg or 800 mg of quetiapine; or the same number of capsules of placebo).
      During the second phase (Day 15 - Day 42), patients continue to take the dose of medication
      they received on day 14, but may also receive other medications if the investigator
      determines they are needed to treat ongoing symptoms. The hypothesis of the study is that
      paliperidone ER is better than quetiapine in the short term for treating acutely ill patients
      with schizophrenia. Primary outcome is change on the total score of the PANSS (Positive and
      Negative Syndrome scale for Schizophrenia) in the first phase of the study (Day 0 - Day 14).
      Secondary outcomes include time to response, time to readiness for discharge, and additional
      medication use in the second phase of the study (Day 15- Day 42) for patients receiving
      paliperidone ER compared to quetiapine. Safety of paliperidone ER compared with quetiapine
      throughout the study (Day 0 - Day 42) will be based on reported adverse events, results of
      laboratory tests (hematology, biochemistry, and urinalysis), vital signs (blood pressure,
      pulse, and weight), electrocardiogram, and movement disorder scales (Abnormal Involuntary
      Movement Scale, Barnes Akathisia Scale, and Simpson-Angus Rating Scale). Patients may
      participate in a pharmacogenomic (DNA) analysis, if they choose to do so. Patients receive
      study drug by mouth for a total of 42 days. Study medications will be increased to maximum
      tolerated doses of Paliperidone ER 9mg or 12mg/day and Quetiapine 600mg or 800mg at day 8.
      From day 15 through day 42 (end of study) all patients will be eligible for additional
      psychotropic medications at investigators' discretion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2007</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in total PANSS ( Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale) from baseline to endpoint at Day 14</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to response (based on reduction in PANSS plus Clinical Global Impression - Change) and readiness for discharge, utilization of health care resources and polypharmacy use in patients receiving paliperidone ER or quetiapine</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">399</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>paliperidone ER tablets, quetiapine tablets, placebo - all over encapsulated</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnostic and Statistical Manual - Fourth Edition (DSM-IV) diagnosis of schizophrenia
             (paranoid, disorganized or undifferentiated type)

          -  score of &gt;=4 on at least two of a subset of selected PANSS items and a total score on
             these five items of &gt;=17

          -  score of &gt;=5 on the CGI-S (clinical global impression - severity)

          -  body weight of at least 60kg and willing to be hospitalized for 9 days initially

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A primary active mental illness diagnosis other than schizophrenia

          -  subjects whose psychotic symptoms can be explained by substance intake or medical
             illness

          -  pregnancy, breast-feeding, or planning to become pregnant

          -  a history of treatment resistance (defined by failure to respond to 2 adequate trials
             of different antipsychotic medications or clozapine given at adequate dose for
             sufficient time)

          -  unstable or significant medical illness that would increase risk of taking study
             medication or would confuse the interpretation of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L. C. Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_JNJ_6051&amp;studyid=715&amp;filename=CR010501_CSR.pdf</url>
    <description>A randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled, parallel group study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of paliperidone ER compared to quetiapine in subjects with an acute exacerbation schizophrenia</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 18, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Antipsychotic</keyword>
  <keyword>paliperidone</keyword>
  <keyword>quetiapine</keyword>
  <keyword>Seroquel</keyword>
  <keyword>placebo</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Quetiapine Fumarate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paliperidone Palmitate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

