<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00332670</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SOW 014-91-049</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ZonMw SOW nr 014-91-049</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ZonMw AGIKO nr 940-37-033</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00332670</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Light Therapy for Elderly Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>High Cortisol Levels as a Risk Factor for Depression in the Elderly and the Effect of Bright Light Treatment on Mood, Sleep-Wake Pattern and Self-Sufficiency</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GGZ Buitenamstel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Netherlands Institute for Brain Research, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GGZ Buitenamstel</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the following two hypotheses:

        1. Treatment with bright light improves their sleep, mood, concentration and
           self-sufficiency of elderly depressed subjects. This clinical improvement is accompanied
           by decreases in cortisol/DHEA ratio and increases in melatonin concentration in urine
           and saliva.

        2. The eventual beneficial effect of bright light treatment can be predicted by the
           presence of sleep-wake rhythm disturbances as found using muscle activity registration,
           and by cortisol/DHEA and melatonin concentrations in saliva and urine over the day and
           the night.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Depression frequently occurs in the elderly. In normal aging, and in depression,
      the functioning of the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) is impaired, as evidenced by an
      increased prevalence of day-night rhythm perturbations, e.g. sleeping disorders. Also, the
      normal inhibition of SCN neurons on corticotrophin-releasing hormone (CRH) producing cells is
      decreased, which could be responsible for the hyperactive hypothalamus-pituitary
      adrenocortical axis (HPA-axis). This raises the question whether elderly patients with
      depression have more impaired SCN activity and whether HPA-activity is enhanced. Using bright
      light therapy (BLT) the SCN can be stimulated. And, the beneficial effects of BLT on seasonal
      depressive disorders are well accepted. Nevertheless, the effects of BLT in aged depressed
      patients have never been studied, as yet.

      Aims: The aim of this study is to test the hypothesis that BLT improves sleep, mood,
      concentration and self-efficacy of older people with depression and this improvement is
      accompanied by a normalization of HPA-indices.

      Methods: Randomised double blind placebo controlled trial in 120 subjects of 60 years and
      older with a diagnosis of major depressive disorder (DSM-IV/SCID-I). Subjects are recruited
      through referrals of psychiatric outpatient clinics and from case-finding from databases of
      general practitioners and old-people homes in the Amsterdam region. After inclusion subjects
      are randomly allocated to bright blue light vs. dim red light groups using two Philips Bright
      Light Energy boxes type HF 3304 per subject from which the light bulbs have been covered with
      bright blue or dim red light permitting filters. Criteria for stratification are the use of
      SSRIs. Prior to treatment a 1-week run-in period without treatment will be used as a baseline
      condition. At three time points several endocrinological, psychophysiological,
      psychometrically, neuropsychological, and neuroimaging measures are performed: just before
      start of light therapy (T0), after completion of the three week light therapy period (T1),
      and three weeks thereafter (T2).

      Relevance: This study is designed to show whether light therapy can reduce depressive
      symptoms of elderly patients with a major depressive disorder. If this is the case, then
      additional lightning may easily be installed in the homes of patients to serve as a
      maintenance treatment. Also, if our data support the role of a dysfunctional biological clock
      in depressed elderly subjects, such a finding may guide the further development of drugs that
      inhibit the HPA axis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    End of research time, time-resources
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HADRS-17)</measure>
    <time_frame>at T0, T1 and T2</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Actimetry</measure>
    <time_frame>continuous measurement during complete 7 week study period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>24-hour urinary cortisol measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>at T0, T1 and T2 (saliva melatonin evening curve (bedtime minus 4 hours, minus 3 hours, minus 2 hours, minus 1 hour).</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>saliva cortisol daytime curve</measure>
    <time_frame>T0, T1 and t2 (get-up time plus 30 minutes, plus 60 minutes, plus 90 minutes, plus 120 minutes,bedtime minus 4 hours, minus 3 hours, minus 2 hours, minus 1 hour)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Rhythm Metric</measure>
    <time_frame>complete 7-week study period.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Groningen Activity Restriction Scale (GARS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at T0, T1 and T2</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Algemene Competentieverwachtingen Schaal (ALCOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at T0, T1 and T2</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Support List interactions, discrepancies and negative (SSL-i, SSL-d, SSL-n)</measure>
    <time_frame>at T0, T1 and T2</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MOS-short form General Health Survey (SF-20)</measure>
    <time_frame>T0, T1 and T2</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Inventory (PSQI)</measure>
    <time_frame>at T0, T1 and T2</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological test battery</measure>
    <time_frame>at T0, T1 and T2</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>fMRI (encoding task, recognition task, N-Back)</measure>
    <time_frame>at T0 and T1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>structural MRI scanning (brain and volumetry of adrenals)</measure>
    <time_frame>at T0 and T1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MADRS</measure>
    <time_frame>at T0, T1 and t2</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse effects inventarisation</measure>
    <time_frame>3-5 times during treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">89</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>10.000lux bright blue light 1hour every morning 1 hour after wake-up time during three weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>50lux dim red light 1 hour every morning 1 hr after wake-up time during 3 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>10.000lux blue 1 hour every day during three weeks</intervention_name>
    <description>10.000lux during 60 minutes, starting 1 hour after wake-up, during 3 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bright light</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>50lux dim red 1 hour every day during three weeks</intervention_name>
    <description>50 lux red light, 60 minutes every morning, starting 1 hour after wake-up, during three weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dim red light</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Understanding and speaking Dutch language

          -  60 years of age or older

          -  Presence of a Major Depressive Disorder according to DSM-IV (SCID-based)

          -  When under treatment of an ophthalmologist, his / her approval for participation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Progressive eye diseases, glaucoma or cataract for which an operation is scheduled in
             near future, aphakia, retinopathies like maculopathy, retinitis pigmentosa or ablatio
             retina.

          -  Physical problems or disorders which require specific medical treatment like Lupus,
             untreated diabetes, malignancies, organic brain disorders, chronic infections, thyroid
             disorders not adequately treated, thyroid associated ophthalmopathies, M. Parkinson.

          -  Presence of any concurrent substance abuse problem

          -  Presence of other actual axis-I disorders like bipolar disorder, dementias, delirium,
             all psychotic disorders, Posttraumatic stress disorder.

          -  Use of tricyclic antidepressants, MAOIs.

          -  Use of corticosteroids.

          -  Use of tetracyclic antibiotics.

          -  Treatment with antidepressants shorter than 2 months

          -  Use of oral contraceptives.

          -  Treatment with light therapy in the past.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Witte JG Hoogendijk, prof. dr.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Neurogenomics and Cognitive Research, Free University, Amsterdam, the Netherlands; Department of Psychiatry VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands; GGZ Buitenamstel, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eus van Someren, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Netherlands Institute for Brain Research, Amsterdam, The Netherlands; VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marjan MA Nielen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Neurogenomics and Cognitive Research, Free University, Amsterdam, the Netherlands; Department of Psychiatry VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands; GGZ Buitenamstel, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ritsaert Lieverse, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Neurogenomics and Cognitive Research, Free University, Amsterdam, the Netherlands; Department of Psychiatry VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands; GGZ Buitenamstel, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GGZ Buitenamstel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <state>Noord-Holland</state>
        <zip>1081HL</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoogendijk WJ, van Someren EJ, Mirmiran M, Hofman MA, Lucassen PJ, Zhou JN, Swaab DF. Circadian rhythm-related behavioral disturbances and structural hypothalamic changes in Alzheimer's disease. Int Psychogeriatr. 1996;8 Suppl 3:245-52; discussion 269-72.</citation>
    <PMID>9154571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beekman AT, Penninx BW, Deeg DJ, Ormel J, Braam AW, van Tilburg W. Depression and physical health in later life: results from the Longitudinal Aging Study Amsterdam (LASA). J Affect Disord. 1997 Dec;46(3):219-31.</citation>
    <PMID>9547118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deuschle M, Gotthardt U, Schweiger U, Weber B, Körner A, Schmider J, Standhardt H, Lammers CH, Heuser I. With aging in humans the activity of the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal system increases and its diurnal amplitude flattens. Life Sci. 1997;61(22):2239-46.</citation>
    <PMID>9393943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kripke DF, Tuunainen A, Endo T. Benefits of light treatment for depression. Am J Psychiatry. 2006 Jan;163(1):162-3; author reply 163.</citation>
    <PMID>16390913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kripke DF. Light treatment for nonseasonal depression: speed, efficacy, and combined treatment. J Affect Disord. 1998 May;49(2):109-17.</citation>
    <PMID>9609674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Golden RN, Gaynes BN, Ekstrom RD, Hamer RM, Jacobsen FM, Suppes T, Wisner KL, Nemeroff CB. The efficacy of light therapy in the treatment of mood disorders: a review and meta-analysis of the evidence. Am J Psychiatry. 2005 Apr;162(4):656-62.</citation>
    <PMID>15800134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wirz-Justice A, Terman M, Oren DA, Goodwin FK, Kripke DF, Whybrow PC, Wisner KL, Wu JC, Lam RW, Berger M, Danilenko KV, Kasper S, Smeraldi E, Takahashi K, Thompson C, van den Hoofdakker RH. Brightening depression. Science. 2004 Jan 23;303(5657):467-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14739440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wirz-Justice A, Benedetti F, Berger M, Lam RW, Martiny K, Terman M, Wu JC. Chronotherapeutics (light and wake therapy) in affective disorders. Psychol Med. 2005 Jul;35(7):939-44.</citation>
    <PMID>16045060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martiny K, Lunde M, Undén M, Dam H, Bech P. Adjunctive bright light in non-seasonal major depression: results from clinician-rated depression scales. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 2005 Aug;112(2):117-25.</citation>
    <PMID>15992393</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martiny K, Lunde M, Undén M, Dam H, Bech P. Adjunctive bright light in non-seasonal major depression: results from patient-reported symptom and well-being scales. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 2005 Jun;111(6):453-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15877712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gordijn MC, Beersma DG, Korte HJ, Van den Hoofdakker RH. Testing the hypothesis of a circadian phase disturbance underlying depressive mood in nonseasonal depression. J Biol Rhythms. 1998 Apr;13(2):132-47.</citation>
    <PMID>9554575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhou JN, Riemersma RF, Unmehopa UA, Hoogendijk WJ, van Heerikhuize JJ, Hofman MA, Swaab DF. Alterations in arginine vasopressin neurons in the suprachiasmatic nucleus in depression. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2001 Jul;58(7):655-62.</citation>
    <PMID>11448372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 31, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 31, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 2, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 12, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 12, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 15, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>R. Lieverse</name_title>
    <organization>GGZBuitenamstel</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>(Non-seasonal) Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>bright light therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>randomized controlled trial</keyword>
  <keyword>suprachiasmatic nucleus</keyword>
  <keyword>HPA-axis</keyword>
  <keyword>DHEA</keyword>
  <keyword>melatonin</keyword>
  <keyword>actigraphy</keyword>
  <keyword>elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>self-efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>social support</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

