<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00334698</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>06/02 Nacon ITEM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00334698</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Assess the Effect of a Combination of Cetirizine With Pseudoephedrine Versus Cetirizine Alone on Symptoms in Patients With Allergic Rhinitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double Blind, Placebo-controlled, Four Way Cross-over Study to Assess the Effect of a Combination of Cetirizine With Pseudoephedrine Versus Cetirizine Alone on Symptoms Scores and Rhinomanometry in Patients With Allergic Rhinitis Following Pollen Exposure in the Fraunhofer Environmental Challenge Chamber (ECC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fraunhofer-Institute of Toxicology and Experimental Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fraunhofer-Institute of Toxicology and Experimental Medicine</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to assess the efficacy on nasal congestion and other allergic
      symptoms and the onset of action of an oral combination of cetirizine and pseudoephedrine in
      comparison to the single substances under controlled pollen exposure in an Environmental
      Challenge Chamber (ECC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of nasal obstruction symptom score</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Seasonal Allergic Rhinitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cetirizine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pseudoephedrine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cetirizine with Pseudoephedrine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female subjects, aged 18-55 years.

          -  Women will be considered for inclusion if they are:

               -  Not pregnant, as confirmed by pregnancy test (see flow chart) and not nursing.

               -  Of non-child bearing potential (i.e. physiologically incapable of becoming
                  pregnant, including any female who is pre-menarchial or post-menopausal, with
                  documented proof of hysterectomy or tubal ligation, or meet clinical criteria for
                  menopause and has been amenorrhoeic for more than 1 year prior to the screening
                  visit).

               -  Of childbearing potential and using a highly effective method of contraception
                  during the entire study (vasectomized partner, abstinence - the lifestyle of the
                  female should be such that there is complete abstinence from intercourse from two
                  weeks prior to the first dose of study medication and to continue until at least
                  72 hours after treatment -, implants, injectables, combined oral contraceptives,
                  some IUDs)

          -  FEV1 &gt; 80% of predicted at screening.

          -  Absence of any structural nasal abnormalities or nasal polyps on examination, absence
             of a history of frequent nose bleeding or recent nasal surgery.

          -  Absence of conditions or factors, which would make the subject unlikely to be able to
             stay in the Fraunhofer ECC for 6 hours.

          -  Non smokers or smokers with a history of less than 10 pack years.

          -  Able and willing to give written informed consent to take part in the study.

          -  Available to complete all study measurements.

          -  History of allergic rhinitis to grass pollen and a positive skin prick test for
             Dactylis glomerata pollen at or within 12 months prior to the screening visit.

          -  Subject must exhibit a moderate response upon 4000 Dactylis glomerata pollen grains/m3
             during 2 hours in the ECC on visit 2.

          -  Subjects with mild stable asthma that is controlled with occasional use of as-needed
             short-acting beta-agonists and associated with normal lung function may be included.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of a respiratory tract infection and/or exacerbation of asthma within 4 weeks
             before the screening and during the study.

          -  Any history of life-threatening asthma, defined as an asthma episode that required
             intubation and/or was associated with hypercapnia, respiratory arrest or hypoxic
             seizures.

          -  Administration of oral, injectable or dermal corticosteroids within 8 weeks or
             intranasal and/or inhaled corticosteroids within 4 weeks of the screening visit.

          -  Unable to abstain from other medications including non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
             drugs (NSAIDS), anti-depressant drugs, anti-histamines and anti-asthma, anti-rhinitis
             or hay fever medication (other than short acting inhaled beta-agonists) for 1 week
             prior to screening and throughout the course of the study.

          -  Paracetamol up to 1g per day is permitted for the treatment of minor ailments, e.g.
             headache.

          -  Past or present disease, which as judged by the investigator, may affect the outcome
             of this study. These diseases include, but are not limited to, cardiovascular disease,
             malignancy, hepatic disease, renal disease, hematological disease, neurological
             disease, endocrine disease or pulmonary disease (including but not confined to chronic
             bronchitis, emphysema, tuberculosis, bronchiectasis or cystic fibrosis).

          -  Known hypersensitivity, allergic reactions or intolerance to cetirizine,
             pseudoephedrine or any of the other ingredients.

          -  Subject receiving monoamine oxidase inhibitors or has received these agents in the
             last two weeks before dosing.

          -  Subject is undergoing allergen desensitisation therapy.

          -  There is a risk of non-compliance with study procedures.

          -  Participation in another clinical trial 30 days prior to enrolment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prof. Norbert Krug, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fraunhofer Institute of Toxikology and Experimental Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fraunhofer-Institute of Toxicology and Experimental Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hannover</city>
        <zip>30623</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 7, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 7, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic, Seasonal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pseudoephedrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ephedrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cetirizine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

