<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00333411</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1206.5</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00333411</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Double-blind, Randomised, Placebo-controlled Trial Investigating BIRT 2584 XX in Patients With Moderate/Severe Psoriasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 12 Week Double-blind, Randomised, Placebo-controlled, Modified Dose-escalation Trial to Investigate Safety, Efficacy, and Pharmacokinetics of BIRT 2584XX Tablets at Doses of 100, 300 and 500 mg Administered Once Daily in Patients With Moderate to Severe Psoriasis With a 12 Week Treatment Extension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boehringer Ingelheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boehringer Ingelheim</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this clinical study is to determine the effectiveness, pharmacokinetics and
      safety of several doses of BIRT 2584 XX (100mg, 300mg and 500mg) taken once daily in the
      treatment of moderate to severe plaque-type psoriasis. This new medicine will be compared to
      a so-called placebo medicine over 12 weeks with a 12 weeks treatment extension possible.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study is a phase 2a/b international multicentre clinical trial. The general aim
      of this study is to investigate the safety and efficacy (clinical proof of concept) of three
      different doses (100 mg, 300 mg, or 500 mg) of BIRT 2584 XX tablets administered orally once
      daily compared to placebo tablets for the treatment of patients with moderate to severe
      plaque-type psoriasis patients who are candidates for systemic treatment or phototherapy.
      This study may also provide dose-finding information for future pivotal studies.

      The response to treatment will be measured for all patients in the study after 12 weeks of
      treatment using the PASI as the primary endpoint, and also the sPGA. Both instruments
      evaluate the clinical severity of plaque-type psoriatic lesions. Training on PASI and sPGA
      assessment will be provided in order to decrease inter-observer variability. The sPGA is thus
      to be validated for future phase 3 trials.

      After 12 weeks of treatment, only those patients with a response equivalent or better than
      PASI50 and with a satisfactory safety experience will enter a 12 week extension of the
      treatment period. The total time of exposure to study drug in this subgroup of patients will
      be 24 weeks. All other study patients will terminate treatment with study drug after 12
      weeks.

      In addition, the durability of remission/response, and the occurrence of any relapse or
      rebound during the treatment with study drug and after the end of treatment will be assessed
      in an 8 weeks follow-up period. The follow-up period is applicable to all study participants
      who have taken at least one dose of study drug. It initiates after the last dose of study
      medication has been taken, irrespective of the duration of the patients actual treatment
      period.

      The trial will use a modified dose-escalation scheme. The randomisation to the 500 mg
      treatment arm will initiate only after a Data Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB) decision on the
      safety of the other treatment arms. An IVRS will be used for randomisation in this trial.

      Ninety (90) patients are required per dose group. With four groups and an overall 1:1:1:1
      randomisation scheme, a total of 360 eligible patients are planned to be randomised to
      treatment.

      Study Hypothesis:

      Psoriasis is a chronic inflammatory disease that leads to skin sores. These skin sores are
      dependent on the rate of growth of the skin which is driven by an underlying corresponding
      degree of local inflammation. The skin inflammation is caused by different cell types that
      move from the blood vessels into the skin. This cell movement is a result of interaction of
      different proteins. One of these proteins is called LFA-1 (Lymphocyte Function Associated
      Antigen 1). LFA-1 is then a promising target for psoriasis therapy. BIRT 2584 XX will block
      the passage of these inflammatory cells from the blood to the skin by blocking LFA-1, and
      thus indirectly block the inflammatory process. BIRT 2584 XX can also block the activation of
      local inflammatory cells, which altogether may reduce the signs and symptoms of psoriasis.

      A dose-dependent effect of BIRT 2584 XX was observed on a set of markers in the blood that
      are believed to correlate with the severity of the inflammatory process leading to psoriasis.

      Comparison(s):

      In this clinical study, BIRT 2584 XX in a dose of 100 mg, 300 mg or 500 mg, or placebo will
      be given once daily. Patients will receive the same treatment throughout the study.

      Patients will have a 1 in 4 chance (25%) of being allocated to placebo treatment. The placebo
      is identical in appearance compared to any one of the three dose groups with BIRT 2584 XX,
      but does not contain any active ingredient. The purpose of a comparison with placebo is to
      ensure a more reliable assessment of the therapeutic effect and of the side effects of BIRT
      2584 XX.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2006</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Achievement of &gt; 75% reduction from baseline in Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI) score (PASI75 ) at 12 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other PASI assessments, NPF Psoriasis Score Static Psoriasis Global Assessment (sPGA), Discontinuations of therapy due to lack of efficacy, Relapse and rebound, Dermatology Life Quality Index, Pain Visual Analog Scale for psoriatic arthritis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BIRT 2584 XX high dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BIRT 2584 XX medium dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BIRT 2584 XX low dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BIRT 2584 XX</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>BIRT 2584 XX high dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BIRT 2584 XX medium dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BIRT 2584 XX low dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion_Criteria:

          1. Age 18 to 75, males or females

          2. Patients with stable moderate to severe plaque-type psoriasis involving ?10% body
             surface area, with minimum disease severity PASI ?10 and with static PGA of at least
             moderate (score of at least 3) at screening visit

          3. Psoriasis disease duration of at least 6 months prior to screening

          4. Patients must be candidates for systemic psoriasis treatment or phototherapy

          5. Patient must give informed consent and sign an approved consent form prior to any
             study procedures, including wash out of prohibited medications (Patients participating
             in the PK sub-study will sign an additional consent form. Refusal to participate in
             the sub-study will not exclude from participation in the main trial)

        Exclusion_Criteria:

          1. Patients with primary guttatae, erythrodermic, or pustular psoriasis

          2. Patients who have previously discontinued efalizumab treatment due to lack of efficacy

          3. Patients using treatments that could interfere with the primary endpoint of the study
             (cf. protocol section 4.2.2.1)

          4. Patients on treatment with warfarin, paracetamol (acetaminophen), some NSAIDs, some
             antidepressants, medications known to induce or inhibit CYP3A4, or any other
             concomitant medication where potential drug-drug interactions with BIRT 2584 XX could
             either result in decreased efficacy or an unacceptable benefit-risk assessment, and
             where replacement of that concomitant medication with a safe equivalent drug is not
             possible (cf. protocol section 4.2.2.2 and the Investigator Site File).

          5. Patients with active liver disease or history of any significant liver disease.

          6. Any clinically significant illness or unstable disease which according to investigator
             judgement may either put the patient at risk because of participation in the study or
             may influence the results of the study or the patients ability to participate.

          7. Patient with serum creatinine and/or white blood cell count &gt;1.5 x ULN at screening.

             (Repeat laboratory is allowed once between screening and randomisation prior to
             excluding the patient)

          8. Patients with ALT, AST and/or total bilirubin &gt; 1.5xULN at screening (Repeat
             laboratory is allowed once between screening and randomisation prior to excluding the
             patient)

          9. Abnormal values of other laboratory parameters at screening that would define a
             clinically significant disease as described in # 6 above (Repeat laboratory is allowed
             once between screening and randomisation prior to excluding the patient)

         10. Positive testing at screening, or history of HIV or hepatitis B or hepatitis C, or any
             serious infection (requiring hospitalisation or parenteral antibiotic therapy) in the
             past 3 months prior to screening

         11. History of malignancy in the past 5 years or suspicion of active malignant disease
             except treated cutaneous squamous cell or basal cell carcinoma

         12. Patients with the following findings at the screening visit that could interfere with
             cardiac repolarisation:

               -  marked baseline prolongation of QT/QTc interval as measured on ECG (e.g. QTc
                  interval &gt;450ms);

               -  history of additional risk factors for Torsade de pointe (e.g. heart failure, -
                  hypokalemia, family history of long QT syndrome);

               -  use of concomitant medications that prolong the QT/QTc interval

         13. History of drug or alcohol abuse within the past two years

         14. Pre-menopausal (last menstruation &amp;#8804; 1 year prior to screening) sexually active
             woman who:

               -  is pregnant or nursing

               -  is of child bearing potential and not practicing acceptable methods of birth
                  control, or does not plan to continue practising an acceptable method throughout
                  the study (acceptable methods of birth control include surgical sterilisation,
                  intrauterine devices, double barrier, male partner sterilisation, but not
                  hormonal contraceptives**) [A negative serum pregnancy test at screening (Visit
                  1) and a negative urine test prior to randomisation (Visit 2) are required]

         15. Patient not willing to avoid excess sun exposure during the trial duration

         16. Patients who have taken an investigational drug, within the last 4 weeks or 5 half
             lives (which ever is greater) prior to randomisation [Patients who have been treated
             with any investigational antibody or fusion protein within the past 12 weeks before
             randomisation are excluded]

         17. Known allergy to BIRT 2584 XX or to the excipients used for tablet formulation

         18. Body mass index &gt; 34 kg/m2 at screening
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Boehringer Ingelheim Study Coordinator</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>BI France S.A.S.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dermatologie Kliniek</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antwerpen</city>
        <zip>2018</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Erasme</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>1070</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UZ Antwerpen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edegem</city>
        <zip>2650</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2S 3B3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 4E8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eastern Canada Cutaneous Research Associates Ltd.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3H 1Z4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 3H7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Markham</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L3P 7N8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waterloo</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N2J 1C4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Innovaderm Research Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2K 4L5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dr. Wayne Carey</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3G 1C6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3H 1V4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sainte-Foy</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>G1V 4X7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Marselisborg Centret</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus C</city>
        <zip>DK-8000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Amtssygehuset i Gentofte</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hellerup</city>
        <zip>DK-2900</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Odense Universitetshospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Odense C</city>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Päijät-Hämeen keskussairaala</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lahti</city>
        <zip>FI-15850</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Saint Jacques</name>
      <address>
        <city>Besançon cedex</city>
        <zip>25030</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Dupuytren</name>
      <address>
        <city>Limoges cedex 1</city>
        <zip>87042</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital de L'Archet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <zip>06202</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Saint Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris cedex 10</city>
        <zip>75475</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Nord</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Priest en Jarez cedex</city>
        <zip>42277</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU - Hôpital Nord</name>
      <address>
        <city>St Priest en Jarez cedex</city>
        <zip>42277</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charite, Campus Virchow-Klinikum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Josef-Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bochum</city>
        <zip>44791</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum an der TU Dresden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dresden</city>
        <zip>01307</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Erlangen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Erlangen</city>
        <zip>91052</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitäts-Hautklinik</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freiburg</city>
        <zip>79104</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Schleswig-Holstein</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kiel</city>
        <zip>24105</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Otto-von-Guericke-Universität Magdeburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Magdeburg</city>
        <zip>39120</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mahlow</city>
        <zip>15831</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <zip>55101</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Münster</name>
      <address>
        <city>Münster</city>
        <zip>48149</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Ulm</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulm</city>
        <zip>89081</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Academic Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1105 AZ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Centre Nijmegen St. Radboud West</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <zip>6525 GL</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boehringer Ingelheim Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08025</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Servicio de Dermatología</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Servicio de Dermatología</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28041</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karolinska Universitetssjukhuset Solna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>171 76</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aberdeen Royal Infirmary, Department of Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aberdeen</city>
        <zip>AB25 2ZN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiff University, Dermatology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cardiff</city>
        <zip>CF14 4XN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Western Infirmary, Department of Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Glasgow</city>
        <zip>G11 6NT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Free Hospital, Dermatology Department,</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW3 2QG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Skin Therapy Research Unit, St John's Inst of Dermatolology</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE1 7EH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>George Eliot Hospital, Dermatology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nuneaton,</city>
        <zip>CV10 7DJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hope Hospital, The Dermatology Centre,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salford</city>
        <zip>M6 8HD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal South Hants Hospital, Dept of Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Southampton</city>
        <zip>SO14 0YG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>Finland</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 5, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>April 30, 2014</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2014</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Estimate">June 19, 2014</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 13, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 13, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 19, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

