<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02534584</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1.0</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02534584</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Care Bundle in Acute Kidney Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Compliance With a Care Bundle on Acute Kidney Injury Outcomes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Derby Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Derby Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a service evaluation to assess the impact of compliance of Acute Kidney Injury
      care bundle (AKI-CB) on clinical and renal outcomes. The AKI care bundle is coupled with an
      interruptive electronic alert, which is triggered by the first attempt to order blood tests
      or medications on patients who have been identified as having AKI by the electronic
      recognition from serum creatinine results. The interruptive alert will warn the clinician
      about AKI and request them to complete the AKI care bundle. Once the AKI care bundle is
      completed, the clinician is able to request blood tests or medication. The clinician will be
      able to override the alert only after stating the reason. Education with respect to
      importance of AKI and the AKI-CB is provided every four months when junior doctors rotated
      through different specialities and also at clinical governance days. The investigators will
      compare AKI episodes, which have the AKI-CB completed early (defined as within 24 hours of
      availability of the blood results) with those who either had the AKI-CB completed late
      (defined as after 24 hours of availability of the blood results) or not completed at all. The
      AKI patients who either had the AKI-CB completed late or not completed will be considered as
      not having the AKI-CB completed for this analysis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This single centre study will be conducted at the Royal Derby Hospital, a 1139-bed tertiary
      care centre. Data will be collected from February 2013 to December 2013 on all adult patients
      over the age of 18 years. An electronic recognition system for AKI has been in use since 2010
      that allows prospective data collection for all cases of AKI. The electronic recognition
      system was modified in December 2012, to incorporate the Kidney Diseases Improving Global
      Outcomes (KDIGO) definitions for AKI. In an effort to improve the clinical outcomes, intranet
      guidelines were introduced along with the electronic recognition and alerting system. In
      December 2012, a one-page paper version of the AKI CB was devised, which was subsequently
      incorporated into the hospital electronic patient record on 1st February 2013. During this
      period, education on the AKI CB was given to all staff in acute areas of the hospital and a
      poster explaining the AKI CB was displayed in all clinical areas. The hospital already has
      electronic ordering of investigations and prescribing of medications in place. The CB
      consists of simple standardized investigations and interventions, reminding clinicians of the
      importance of thorough Assessment, Urinalysis, establishing a Diagnosis, planning
      Investigations and Treatment and at the same time issuing guidance about Seeking advice from
      nephrologist while caring for patients with AKI (AUDITS). All the steps in the CB are
      objective and the clinicians are requested to click yes or no for each step of the CB. On 1st
      August 2013, the AKI CB was coupled with an interruptive electronic alert, which was
      triggered by the first attempt to order blood tests or medications on patients who had been
      identified as having AKI. The interruptive alert would warn the clinician about AKI and
      request them to complete the AKI CB. Once the AKI CB was completed, the clinician was able to
      request blood tests or medication. The clinician would be able to override the alert only
      after stating the reason. The location of patients was categorized into the following
      divisions - Medical Assessment Unit, Medical wards, Surgical &amp; Orthopedic wards, Haematology
      and Oncology wards, Intensive Care and Surgical Step Down (high dependency unit) and Other
      wards.

      A weekly report is automatically generated which captures patient location in the hospital,
      age, date of admission, date of discharge, finished consultant episode and survival status at
      the reporting date.

      For this study, the investigators will analyze all AKI episodes, which had the AKI CB
      completed early (defined as within 24 hours of availability of the blood results) with those
      who either had AKI CB completed late (defined as after 24 hours of availability of the blood
      results) or not completed at all. The AKI episodes who either had AKI CB completed late or
      not completed will be considered as not having AKI CB completed for this analysis. Community
      acquired AKI will be defined as AKI within 24 hours of admission. Survival status of all
      patients will be obtained in February 2015.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>This is the average follow up</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days</time_frame>
    <description>This is average length of stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of AKI as measured by AKI stages</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients whose AKI increases in severity, from AKI stage 1 to stage 2 and from stage 2 to stage 3</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">944</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Kidney Injury</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All adults patients with acute kidney injury
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All episodes of acute kidney injury in adults patients

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age less than 17 years

          -  Patients without acute kidney injury
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>17 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nitin V Kolhe, MD, DM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Derby Teaching Hospital NHS Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Derby Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Derby</city>
        <state>Derbyshire</state>
        <zip>DE22 3NE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 25, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 27, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 25, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 25, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 27, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Derby Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Nitin Kolhe</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Consultant Nephrologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acute kidney injury</keyword>
  <keyword>outcome</keyword>
  <keyword>mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>care-bundle</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Kidney Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

