<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02535728</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL53243.100.15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02535728</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anesthesia Geriatric Evaluation and Quality of Life After Cardiac Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>AGE</acronym>
  <official_title>Anesthesia Geriatric Evaluation and the Prediction of Quality of Life in Elderly Cardiac Surgery Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Antonius Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Antonius Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A prospective observational cohort study to assess the predictive value of preoperative
      frailty on postoperative quality of life in cardiac surgery patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction:

      The current population is ageing in a rapid pace. Currently elderly represent 17.8% of the
      Dutch population. Most recent estimates show this will increase to 25.6% 20 years' time. This
      rise in elderly will also reflect on the population of patients being referred for cardiac
      surgery. Especially elderly patients are at risk for postoperative complications, mortality
      or functional decline. In frail elderly this effect might be more pronounced. Frailty is an
      umbrella term that encompasses patient related factors such as weight loss, muscle wasting,
      inactivity, comorbidities and polypharmacy. Current scoring systems that are used to predict
      postoperative mortality and complications following cardiac surgery perform poorly in the
      elderly population and do not take into account frailty. Moreover they are designed to
      predict mortality and complications and are not validated to predict patient reported outcome
      measures such as quality of life or functional status. The aim of the AGE study is assess the
      value of frailty factors in predicting an improvement in quality of life one year after
      cardiac surgery.

      Methods:

      The AGE study is a prospective observational cohort study. All patients aged 70 years or
      older, scheduled for cardiac surgery, mentally competent and have signed informed consent are
      eligible for the study. During routine preoperative screening patients will be screened for
      frailty using different questionnaires and physical tests. The battery of tests exist of
      Short Form 36 (SF36), Multi Nutritional Assessment (MNA), Mini Mental State Examination
      (MMSE) and Nagi's scale for disability, Three physical tests: five meter walking speed, timed
      get up and go test and hand grip strength. A non-invasive measurement of Advanced Glycation
      Endproducts (AGEs) and a medication review. A blood sample will be taken to determine vitamin
      status, iron deficiency, pre-operative inflammatory parameters, CMV status, pneumococcal
      carriage and cardiac biomarkers. After surgery electronic patients charts will be studied to
      score postoperative complications or mortality. Three months and one year after cardiac
      surgery patients will receive SF-36 and World Health Organization Disability Assessment
      Schedule (WHODAS) 2.0 questionnaires to determine quality of life and functional status.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Assessed by Short Form-36 (SF-36)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by Short Form-36 (SF-36)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Assessed by Short Form-36 (SF-36)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by Short Form-36 (SF-36)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychosocial or physical functioning Assessed by World Health Organisation Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by World Health Organisation Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0 (WHODAS 2.0)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative complications are scored according to Dutch national guidelines on reporting complications in cardiac surgery and include rethoracotomy, reoperation, bleeding, arrythmia, stroke, myocardial infarction, deep sternal wound infection, pneumonia, urinary tract infection, sepsis, respiratory insufficiency, prolonged respiratory support and renal failure (AKI).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days and 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay in hospital and ICU</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-Surgery. The expected length of stay in the ICU is 1 to 5 days and in hospital 5 to 10 days.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative delirium</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Delirium according to intensive care delirium screening (ICDSC) or delirium observation screening (DOS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">577</enrollment>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples are taken directly after induction of anesthaesia.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients planned for elective cardiac surgery and aged 70 years or older.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 70 years or older

          -  Mentally competent

          -  Planned cardiac surgery (coronary, valvular, rhythm, aortic or combination of those)

          -  Signed informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>70 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter G Noordzij, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Antonius Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Antonius hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nieuwegein</city>
        <state>Utrecht</state>
        <zip>3435 CM</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fruitman DS, MacDougall CE, Ross DB. Cardiac surgery in octogenarians: can elderly patients benefit? Quality of life after cardiac surgery. Ann Thorac Surg. 1999 Dec;68(6):2129-35.</citation>
    <PMID>10616989</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chaturvedi RK, Blaise M, Verdon J, Iqbal S, Ergina P, Cecere R, deVarennes B, Lachapelle K. Cardiac surgery in octogenarians: long-term survival, functional status, living arrangements, and leisure activities. Ann Thorac Surg. 2010 Mar;89(3):805-10. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2009.12.002.</citation>
    <PMID>20172133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ettema RG, Peelen LM, Kalkman CJ, Nierich AP, Moons KG, Schuurmans MJ. Predicting prolonged intensive care unit stays in older cardiac surgery patients: a validation study. Intensive Care Med. 2011 Sep;37(9):1480-7. doi: 10.1007/s00134-011-2314-1. Epub 2011 Jul 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21805158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Afilalo J, Mottillo S, Eisenberg MJ, Alexander KP, Noiseux N, Perrault LP, Morin JF, Langlois Y, Ohayon SM, Monette J, Boivin JF, Shahian DM, Bergman H. Addition of frailty and disability to cardiac surgery risk scores identifies elderly patients at high risk of mortality or major morbidity. Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes. 2012 Mar 1;5(2):222-8. doi: 10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.111.963157. Epub 2012 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22396586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 24, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 26, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Antonius Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>dr. P. Noordzij</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>dr. P. Noordzij, MD PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Frail Elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac Surgical Procedure</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk Assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of Life</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

