<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02530814</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201401073</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02530814</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Organochlorine Pesticide Exposure in Residents Near Lake Apopka</brief_title>
  <official_title>Organochlorine Pesticide Exposure in Residents Near Lake Apopka</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the Lake Apopka, Florida area for over 50 years starting in the 1940s, organochlorine
      pesticides (OCPs) including 4,4'-dichlorodiphenyltrichloroethane (DDT), dieldrin, chlordane,
      toxaphene and more recently methoxychlor were sprayed on farmlands in order to control pests
      and to improve crop harvests. For most of those years, the farmworkers were exposed to the
      pesticides as part of their work. Because of their lipophilic (fat soluble) nature, these
      organochlorine pesticides (OCPs) are readily taken up into the body and not readily
      eliminated. Therefore, they can be detected in exposed individuals for many years after the
      exposure. There is some evidence that certain OCPs can cause or exacerbate medical problems
      in sensitive individuals. For example, exposure to some OCPs has been associated with
      development of Parkinsonism. Exposure to other OCPs has been associated with development of
      lupus erythematosus, an auto-immune disease. Other adverse effects of exposure to OCPs are
      endocrine disruption because some OCPs mimic estrogens and others mimic androgens, or may
      have mixed interactions with steroid receptors.

      In this research study the investigators aim is to test the blood from former farmworkers
      during the 1940s through the late 1970s who reside in the Lake Apopka area for OCPs and for
      the auto-antibodies. In addition, questionnaires will provide insight on their health status
      and health concerns.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this research study, a onetime blood test will be collected from former farmworkers during
      the 1940s through the late 1970s who reside in the Lake Apopka area for OCPs and for the
      auto-antibodies. In addition, questionnaires will provide insight on their health status and
      health concerns.

      The investigators will collect existing data from the National Health and Nutrition
      Examination Survey (NHANES) which has monitored the pesticide exposure (with the exception of
      toxaphene) of people older than 8 years, so there is information on the range of
      concentrations of these chemicals in the blood of Americans. This data will be use as the
      control group for comparison with the values found for OCP concentrations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood levels of organochlorine pesticides will be compared between the groups</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Blood collected will be analyzed for DDT, dieldrin, chlordane, methoxychlor and the metabolites of DDT and methoxychlor. The data will be compared between the groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of auto-antibodies will be recorded</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Blood collected will be analyzed for measurement of auto-antibodies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Pesticide Exposure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lake Apopka Farmworkers</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will have a onetime blood collection and questionnaires regarding health status and health concerns.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Existing Data Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>The investigators will collect existing data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) for the range of concentrations of these chemicals in the blood of Americans.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Collection</intervention_name>
    <description>Onetime blood collection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lake Apopka Farmworkers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples will be collected for analysis of organochlorine pesticides and
      auto-antibodies.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants for this study will be recruited from the Florida Farmworker Association of
        Florida, Lake Apopka, FL.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Persons who worked on farms near lake Apopka, Florida up to 1998.

          -  Preference will be given to those who worked on the farms for over 10 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Persons who did not work on farms near Lake Apopka, Florida up to 1998.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Margaret O. James, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beard J; Australian Rural Health Research Collaboration. DDT and human health. Sci Total Environ. 2006 Feb 15;355(1-3):78-89. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15894351</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eskenazi B, Chevrier J, Rosas LG, Anderson HA, Bornman MS, Bouwman H, Chen A, Cohn BA, de Jager C, Henshel DS, Leipzig F, Leipzig JS, Lorenz EC, Snedeker SM, Stapleton D. The Pine River statement: human health consequences of DDT use. Environ Health Perspect. 2009 Sep;117(9):1359-67. doi: 10.1289/ehp.11748. Epub 2009 May 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19750098</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu X, Dailey AB, Talbott EO, Ilacqua VA, Kearney G, Asal NR. Associations of serum concentrations of organochlorine pesticides with breast cancer and prostate cancer in U.S. adults. Environ Health Perspect. 2010 Jan;118(1):60-6. doi: 10.1289/ehp.0900919.</citation>
    <PMID>20056587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chhillar N, Singh NK, Banerjee BD, Bala K, Mustafa M, Sharma D, Chhillar M. Organochlorine pesticide levels and risk of Parkinson's disease in north Indian population. ISRN Neurol. 2013 Jul 8;2013:371034. doi: 10.1155/2013/371034. Print 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>23936670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang F, Roberts SM, Butfiloski EJ, Morel L, Sobel ES. Acceleration of autoimmunity by organochlorine pesticides: a comparison of splenic B-cell effects of chlordecone and estradiol in (NZBxNZW)F1 mice. Toxicol Sci. 2007 Sep;99(1):141-52. Epub 2007 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>17578864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 18, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 19, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 17, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>organochlorine compounds</keyword>
  <keyword>pesticides</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

