<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02534194</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02534194</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gestational Age Assessment Tool</brief_title>
  <acronym>GestATion</acronym>
  <official_title>Gestational Age Assessment Tool for Newborn Babies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Nottingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Nottingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the UK and worldwide many babies are born without carers knowing their gestation as the
      mothers will not have had good antenatal care. It is possible to estimate gestation but this
      requires a detailed clinical exam. The investigators wish to improve this by using software
      analysis to pick out features of the baby (face and foot) to try and estimate the gestation
      of the baby once it is born. The investigators will also look explore if the software can
      distinguish the normal face or a baby in discomfort.

      Good estimation of gestation can result in more targeted management of the baby. The
      investigators will capture the images of newborn babies, from a variety of gestations, and
      use this dataset to teach the software to estimate gestational age and level of discomfort.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Clinical techniques for the calculation of gestation include fetal ultrasound and clinical
      assessment tools, such as the Ballard Score, following birth. These techniques are rarely
      available (ultrasound which is expensive and requires trained users) or require significant
      training (Ballard) which makes them unsuitable for large scale assessment in many low-middle
      income (LMI) countries. In the UK, the gestational age of babies of mothers with no antenatal
      care requires a detailed clinical examination which can lack accuracy. Clinical assessment of
      postnatal gestational age utilises anatomical characteristics of the face, ear and foot
      during newborn development. There is an element of subjectiveness which reduces the precision
      of such an assessment which is only reduced with significant training and experience. Simpler
      techniques of postnatal gestational age assessment such as anthropometric measures are time
      consuming and lack the accuracy required. Emerging evidence suggests that gestational age can
      be calculated postnatally by measuring the newborn foot length and comparing to population
      appropriate charts. However, when used on their own, the specificity and sensitivity are
      still below acceptable limits to allow universal adoption.

      New software-based analytical techniques now make it possible to perform fully automatic
      recognition of facial actions and dimensions. The investigators have developed techniques
      that allow live video facial feature identification and measurement using advanced analytical
      techniques of muscle actions. These techniques have been used for facial expression analysis
      as well as automated facial feature localization. The investigators propose that the same
      analysis could be used to create a unique gestational age assessment tool using a simple
      brief video clip of the newborns' face and foot.

      Accurate assessment of gestational age, especially in LMI countries, could ensure high risk
      newborns receive appropriate low cost interventions to reduce morbidity and mortality. In the
      UK this could allow better estimation of babies born to mothers with no antenatal care where
      the gestational age is unclear. We propose a smartphone based, ethnic appropriate, combined
      face and foot video analysis tool to accurately determine gestational age of the newborn.
      Such a system could adapted to incorporate pain assessment tools to help inform treatment
      options and study new therapies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 11, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Software analysis tool estimates the gestational age of a newborn baby to within 1 week of its actual gestation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantification of pain from facial features during uncomfortable procedures.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison with two pain scores, the neonatal Pain Assessment Tool (PAT, scored 0 (no pain) to 10 (significant pain)) and the Neonatal Infant Pain Scale (NIPS, scored 0 (no pain) to 7 (significant pain)). The software will be calibrated from these pain scores. This approach hasn't previously been performed so the software scoring system will be developed alongside these commonly used measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Immature Newborn</condition>
  <condition>Premature Birth</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Newborn Infant</arm_group_label>
    <description>Newborn babies (within 7 days of birth) born between 23-42 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Image acquisition</intervention_name>
    <description>Images of baby's face (including ear) and feet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Newborn Infant</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Newborn babies within 7 days of birth recruited from Nottingham University Hospitals NHS
        Trust.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Where the baby's gestational age is known (based on antenatal care)

          -  With written informed parental consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No parental consent

          -  Babies undergoing palliative care
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Don Sharkey, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Nottingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nottingham University Hospitals NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nottingham</city>
        <state>Nottinghamshire</state>
        <zip>NG72UH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 27, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gestation</keyword>
  <keyword>Premature</keyword>
  <keyword>Infants</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

