<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02537093</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>741223</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02537093</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>﻿﻿Pilot Study of Asynchronous and Synchronous Telepsychiatry for Skilled Nursing Facilities</brief_title>
  <official_title>﻿﻿A Pilot Study Examining Use of Asynchronous and Synchronous Telepsychiatry Consultation for Skilled Nursing Facility Residents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Davis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Davis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aims: This study aims to assess the acceptability of asynchronous

      telepsychiatry (ATP) and synchronous (STP) in rural Skilled Nursing Facility (SNF)

      population, in a 12-month randomized controlled trial. ATP relies on video recording of a

      psychiatric interview, where the video is later reviewed by a psychiatrist to make a

      psychiatric diagnosis and treatment recommendation to the primary treatment team.

      STP is real-time, face-to-face psychiatric assessment using video conferencing to come

      up with a psychiatric recommendation. People residing in SNFs generally rely on primary

      and consultant physicians to visit them and rarely have outpatient psychiatrist follow-up.

      SNFs offer more services than what is available to primary care office, and include 24-

      hours skilled nursing services, physical therapy, nutritional consultation, occupational

      therapy, social services, wound care, and psychiatric consultation when available. SNF

      residents are unable to live independently due to their multiple medical comorbidities

      and are therefore more medically ill than patients who are typically seen in primary care

      settings. The present study aims to demonstrate feasibility and to collect pilot data in

      SNFs. This study is funded by the UC Davis Behavior Health Center of Excellence grant

      via the California Mental Health Services Act (Prop 63). In a larger, future study, the
      investigators

      intend to demonstrate that ATP will be no different than STP in clinical outcomes but will

      be more accessible and cost effective.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aims: This study aims to assess the acceptability of asynchronous

      telepsychiatry (ATP) and synchronous (STP) in rural Skilled Nursing Facility

      (SNF) population, in a 12-month randomized controlled trial. ATP relies on

      video recording of a psychiatric interview, where the video is later reviewed by

      a psychiatrist to make a psychiatric diagnosis and treatment recommendation

      to the primary treatment team.

      STP is real-time, face-to-face psychiatric assessment using video conferencing

      to come up with a psychiatric recommendation. People residing in SNFs

      generally rely on primary and consultant physicians to visit them and rarely

      have outpatient psychiatrist follow-up. SNFs offer more services than what is

      available to primary care office, and include 24-hours skilled nursing services,

      physical therapy, nutritional consultation, occupational therapy, social services,

      wound care, and psychiatric consultation when available. SNF residents are

      unable to live independently due to their multiple medical comorbidities and are

      therefore more medically ill than patients who are typically seen in primary care

      settings. The present study aims to demonstrate feasibility and to collect pilot

      data in SNFs. This study is funded by the University of California (UC Davis)

      Behavior Health Center of Excellence grant via the California Mental Health

      Services Act (Prop 63). In a larger, future study, we intend to demonstrate that

      ATP will be no different than STP in clinical outcomes but will be more

      accessible and cost effective.

      Aim 1: To assess whether ATP and STP models improve clinical outcomes:

      Hypotheses: Compared to STP, the ATP arm will: H1: show similar clinical

      outcome trajectory, reflected in improvement from baseline, as measured by

      Clinical Global Impression (CGI), Patient Health Questionaire-9 (PHQ-9), Brief

      Interview for Mental Status (BIMS), and overall behavioral symptoms; H2: have

      similar use of health care resources: psychiatric medications, additional interval

      psychiatric visits, number of emergency room visits and hospitalizations

      (medical, psychiatric, and overall); And H3: produce shorter waiting times for

      psychiatric consultation.

      Aim 2: To assess the acceptability of ATP and STP by examining satisfaction

      surveys from SNF residents (who are able to complete the surveys).

      Hypothesis:

      Compared to STP, ATP participants will show: H1: Similar levels of satisfaction

      as measured by: Telemedicine Satisfaction Survey as completed by

      participants.

      Aim 3: To conduct preliminary healthcare economics analysis and feasibility of

      producing estimates of cost-effectiveness of ATP vs. STP in SNFs. Hypotheses:

      ATP, compared to STP, will: H1: be more cost effective as measured by cost

      savings from reduced need for face-to-face psychiatrist time and similar use of

      other medical and psychiatric services.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in CGI will be measured from baseline to study endpoint of 12-month follow-up</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Interview for Mental Status (BIMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in BIMS will be measured from baseline to 12-month</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Mood Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Substance Use Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Synchronous telepsychiatry (STP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control Arm/Synchronous telepsychiatry (STP): After baseline assessment, subjects will be assessed by a psychiatrist using live interactive videoconferencing every 6 months for a 1 year follow up (3 STP assessments: baseline plus 2 assessments). A report with treatment recommendations following American Psychiatric Association guidelines will be sent to the PCP who will be able to have adlib telephone or email consultations with the telepsychiatrist. The telepsychiatrist will have access to all previous clinical information about the patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Asynchronous telepsychiatry (ATP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention Arm (ATP): All ATP assessments at 6 monthly intervals post baseline will be conducted by an ATP trained clinician. This interview will be video recorded.The ATP clinicians will then fill out a standardized medical template that will be reviewed by a psychiatrist who will provide a written assessment and psychiatric treatment plan. He will have access to any previous assessments and the PCP will also have continuing access to this psychiatrist by phone or email between the 3 consultations.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychiatric Consultation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Synchronous telepsychiatry (STP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Asynchronous telepsychiatry (ATP)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged ≥18, with non-emergent psychiatric symptoms: depression, schizophrenia, bipolar
             disorder, Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD), dementia-related behavioral problems,
             management of psychiatric medications, and other mental health problems that the
             Skilled Nursing Facility (SNF) Primary Care Provider (PCP) and team deems necessary to
             obtain psychiatric consultation.

          -  referred by SNF staff and PCP at participating site

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Residents with imminent suicide and/or violence risks that require emergency
             psychiatric referrals or residents who cannot wait until the next ATP/STP evaluation

          -  Residents with other psychiatric emergencies will be referred to the local emergency
             department as is the current practice at both SNFs.

          -  less than 18 years

          -  immediate violent intentions or plans

          -  incarceration

          -  patient whose PCP recommends not participating.

          -  PCP not at participating site
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Norwood Pines Care Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95838</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cottonwood Post-Acute Rehabilitation Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Woodland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95695</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 25, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 28, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 1, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mood Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

