<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02531906</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>I 262314</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2015-01338</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>I 262314</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016056</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02531906</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gabapentin, Methadone Hydrochloride, and Oxycodone Hydrochloride in Improving Quality of Life in Patients With Stage II-IV Head and Neck Cancer During Chemoradiation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analysis of Analgesia Regimens During Concurrent Chemoradiation for Head and Neck Cancer: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized pilot clinical trial studies the side effects of gabapentin and how well it
      works when given together with methadone hydrochloride and oxycodone hydrochloride in
      improving quality of life in patients with stage II-IV head and neck cancer during
      chemoradiation. Gabapentin, methadone hydrochloride, and oxycodone hydrochloride may help
      relieve moderate or severe pain caused by head and neck cancer during and after
      chemoradiation therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Collect preliminary data on the safety and efficacy of two analgesic regimens that can be
      used to design larger studies for comparing such regimens.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Examine effects of the treatment regimens on pain control, oral mucositis, and
      quality-of-life ratings scores during and after chemoradiation therapy (CRT).

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess treatment regimen effect on patient nutrition and hydration status during and
      after CRT (weight loss, vitals, oral [PO] tolerance, etc.).

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 arms.

      ARM I: Patients receive gabapentin PO thrice daily (TID) for up to 7 weeks during
      radiotherapy.

      ARM II: Patients receive gabapentin PO TID, methadone hydrochloride PO twice daily (BID), and
      oxycodone hydrochloride PO every 8 hours (Q8H) as needed (PRN) for up to 7 weeks during
      radiotherapy.

      All patients may continue to receive treatment for pain throughout their course of
      chemoradiation therapy (and up to 24 months following CRT if continuing on a pain regimen).

      After completion of study, patients are followed up at 30 days, and at 3, 6, 9, and 12
      months. Patients requiring prolonged analgesic therapy may be followed up every 6 months for
      24 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 24, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 6, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 6, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain levels via Oral Mucositis Daily Questionnaire (OMDQ), European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire-Core 30, Head and Neck Quality of Life Survey, and physical evaluations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated using a repeated measures model. Tested using a two-sided 0.05 significance level. Post hoc analyses will be done with multiple comparisons adjusted for using the Bonferroni method. Assumptions of normality and equal variance will be examined, and transformations will be used as appropriate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of side effects or drug intolerance</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be graded and recorded. Tested using a two-sided 0.05 significance level. Post hoc analyses will be done with multiple comparisons adjusted for using the Bonferroni method. Assumptions of normality and equal variance will be examined, and transformations will be used as appropriate. The frequency of toxicities will be tabulated by grade by treatment arm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who require higher equivalents of narcotic support added to their analgesia regimen in each arm</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Each patient requiring rescue medication for breakthrough or refractory pain will be counted as a failure for that specific regimen. At the end of the trial, number of failures will be compared between the two treatment arms using Fisher's exact test. Total amount of opioid intake mean will be compared using a t-test between the two arms. Tested using a two-sided 0.05 significance level. Post hoc analyses will be done with multiple comparisons adjusted for using the Bonferroni method. Assumptions of normality and equal variance will be examined, and transformations will be used as appropriate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in oral mucositis rating scores during and after CRT, using the OMDQ</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The total score of the OMDQ questionnaire will be recorded after each follow-up visit. Tested using a two-sided 0.05 significance level. Post hoc analyses will be done with multiple comparisons adjusted for using the Bonferroni method. Assumptions of normality and equal variance will be examined, and transformations will be used as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life rating scores during and after CRT, using the EORTC QLQ-C30 and H&amp;N35</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The total score of the EORTC questionnaires will be recorded after each follow-up visit. Tested using a two-sided 0.05 significance level. Post hoc analyses will be done with multiple comparisons adjusted for using the Bonferroni method. Assumptions of normality and equal variance will be examined, and transformations will be used as appropriate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patient hydration and nutrition using the OMDQ</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Tested using a two-sided 0.05 significance level. Post hoc analyses will be done with multiple comparisons adjusted for using the Bonferroni method. Assumptions of normality and equal variance will be examined, and transformations will be used as appropriate.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Stomatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (gabapentin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive gabapentin PO TID for up to 7 weeks during radiotherapy.
All patients may continue to receive treatment for pain throughout their course of chemoradiation therapy (and up to 24 months following CRT if continuing on a pain regimen).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (gabapentin, methadone, oxycodone)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive gabapentin PO TID, methadone hydrochloride PO BID, and oxycodone hydrochloride PO Q8H PRN for up to 7 weeks during radiotherapy.
All patients may continue to receive treatment for pain throughout their course of chemoradiation therapy (and up to 24 months following CRT if continuing on a pain regimen).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gabapentin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (gabapentin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (gabapentin, methadone, oxycodone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gralise</other_name>
    <other_name>Neurontin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methadone Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (gabapentin, methadone, oxycodone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Adanon</other_name>
    <other_name>Althose</other_name>
    <other_name>Dolophine</other_name>
    <other_name>Methadose</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxycodone Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (gabapentin, methadone, oxycodone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Oxecta</other_name>
    <other_name>OxyContin</other_name>
    <other_name>Roxicodone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality-of-Life Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (gabapentin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (gabapentin, methadone, oxycodone)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Quality of Life Assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (gabapentin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (gabapentin, methadone, oxycodone)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are eligible for chemoradiation therapy of the head and neck

          -  Baseline creatinine (Cr) no greater than 1.5 times the upper limit of normal

          -  Have a clinical stage II-IV head and neck carcinoma

          -  Have a pathologic diagnosis of squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck region

          -  Have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of =&lt; 2

          -  Ability to swallow and retain oral medication or take through a feeding tube

          -  Patients of child-bearing potential must agree to use adequate contraceptive methods
             (e.g., hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry;
             should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or her partner is
             participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately

          -  Patient or legal representative must understand the investigational nature of this
             study and sign an Independent Ethics Committee/Institutional Review Board approved
             written informed consent form prior to receiving any study related procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have previously been treated with surgery or radiation for head and neck
             cancer and/or are being treated for recurrent head and neck cancer

          -  Patients with known brain metastases will be excluded from this clinical trial

          -  Any patients prescribed medications for chronic pain and/or neuropathy will be
             excluded, including patients under treatment of a pain specialist or substance-abuse
             programs

          -  Uncontrolled concurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Pregnant or nursing female patients

          -  Unwilling or unable to follow protocol requirements

          -  Any condition which in the Investigator's opinion deems the patient an unsuitable
             candidate to receive study drug

          -  Received an investigational agent within 30 days prior to enrollment

          -  Patients on medications that prolong QT interval

          -  Patients on dialysis or with transplanted organs

          -  Patients already enrolled on other studies of systemic pain control agents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anurag Singh</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 19, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 25, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oxycodone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methadone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gabapentin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>gamma-Aminobutyric Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

