<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00249743</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4R44AG022270-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00249743</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Evaluation of a Wireless Monitoring Device to Reduce Falls in the Elderly and Others at High Risk of Falling</brief_title>
  <official_title>NIH-NIA SBIR Phase I/II Study: Clinical Evaluation of a Device to Reduce Patient Falls</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NOCwatch International</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NOCwatch International</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Falls are a public health problem of significant social and economic significance. No primary
      intervention devices have been shown to be effective in reducing falls and associated
      injuries. The objective of this study was to determine whether the new wireless FallSaver
      device reduces falls and fall-related injuries in elderly skilled nursing facility (SNF)
      residents. A randomized, prospective, open-label, cross-over study was conducted over a
      six-month period. The FallSaver device reduced the frequency of falls by 50% and fall-related
      injuries by 82% in 43 elderly at-risk SNF residents studied over 4,222 patient-days. The
      device and associated patch enclosure was well tolerated and devoid of serious problems.
      Significant cost savings and fewer reductions in quality of life are possible if fall-related
      injuries can be reduced.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVE. No existing devices have proven effective in preventing falls in at-risk
      individuals. The objective of this study was to determine whether the FallSaver device
      reduces falls and fall-related injuries in elderly skilled nursing facility (SNF) residents.

      DESIGN. This was a randomized, prospective, open-label, cross-over study conducted over a
      six-month period.

      SETTING: The study took place in a 100-bed State Veterans SNF in Washington State.

      PARTICIPANTS. Forty-four subjects with anticipated institutional stays of at least 120 days
      participated in the study. The subjects’ mean age was 82.2 + 7.1 years and all were rated
      high fall risks using the Morse scale.

      INTERVENTION Subjects were randomly assigned to the FallSaver device or no device
      (Observation) for 60 days. Following the end of the 60-day period subjects were crossed over
      to the opposite treatment. The device, enclosed in an adhesive patch, was applied to the
      subject’s thigh.

      MAIN OUTCOME MEASURE The primary outcome measures were falls and fall-related injuries.
      Secondary outcomes were falls resulting from documented attempts to stand or ambulate without
      assistance, skin-tolerance to the patch, and compliance.

      RESULTS. Total patient-days for the FallSaver and Observation phases were 1,923 and 2,299,
      respectively. A total of 37 falls occurred in 18 subjects. Thirteen falls occurred during the
      FallSaver phase and 24 during Observation (p = &lt; 0.05). A total of 7 fall-related injuries
      occurred; one during the FallSaver phase and 6 during Observation (p = &lt; 0.01). Nineteen
      falls resulted from documented attempts to stand or ambulate without assistance, six during
      the FallSaver phase and 13 during Observation (p = &lt; 0.05). The patch was well tolerated and
      no serious adverse effects were observed.

      CONCLUSION. The FallSaver device reduced the frequency of falls by 50% and fall-related
      injuries by 82% in elderly at-risk SNF residents. The device and associated patch enclosure
      was well tolerated and devoid of serious problems. Significant cost savings and fewer
      reductions in quality of life are possible if fall-related injuries can be reduced.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Falls and fall-related injuries.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Falls resulting from documented attempts to stand or ambulate without assistance.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin tolerance to the adhesive.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>50</enrollment>
  <condition>Accidental Falls</condition>
  <condition>Fractures</condition>
  <condition>Injuries</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FallSaver (formerly called NOCwatch)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Residents of a skilled nursing facility. An anticipated institutional stay of at least
             120 days. Individuals with a high risk of falling according to the Morse scale (a
             score of 55+).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals who were allowed to self-ambulate. Individuals with a history of adverse
             reactions to medical adhesives. Individuals with a history or presence of significant
             skin breakdown on the legs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathryn E Kelly, DrPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>NOCwatch International, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dennis Clifton, PharmD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Spokane Veterans Homes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelly KE, Phillips CL, Cain KC, Polissar NL, Kelly PB. Evaluation of a nonintrusive monitor to reduce falls in nursing home patients. J Am Med Dir Assoc. 2002 Nov-Dec;3(6):377-82.</citation>
    <PMID>12807607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 7, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 29, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>fall prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>fall risk management</keyword>
  <keyword>RCT</keyword>
  <keyword>cost</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

