<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00247494</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Myocardh</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00247494</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Mycophenolate Mofetil (MMF) on Surrogate Markers for Cardiovascular Disease in HIV-1 Infected Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Mycophenolate Mofetil (MMF) on Surrogate Markers for Cardiovascular Disease in HIV-1 Infected Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a substudy of the MAN2 -study (Mycophenol mofetil in Antiretroviral Naïve
      patients 2, see elsewhere in the ClinicalTrials.gov database). In the MAN2 study, HIV-1
      infected patients who are not treated with antiretroviral treatment will be randomized to
      treatment with Mycophenol mofetil (MMF)500 mg BID or a control group without treatment (open
      label). Both patients randomized to treatment with MMF and patients randomized to the control
      group will be asked to participate also in this substudy.

      In this substudy we want to show whether monotherapy with Mycophenol mofetil (MMF) in
      patients infected with HIV-1 can reduce acceleration of atherogenesis by attenuating various
      inflammatory pathways normally involved in progression of atherosclerosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  background Immune activation plays an important role in atherogenesis. In HIV-1
           infection, the immune system is chronically hyperactivated. There also seems to be an
           increased incidence of cardiovascular disease in untreated HIV-1 infection. Mycophenol
           mofetil (MMF) will be used to treat this immune activation in untreated HIV-1 infected
           patients in the MAN2-study (see elsewhere in this ClinicalTrials.gov database).

        -  Hypothesis T-cell inhibition with MMF attenuates T-cell number, T-cell activation and
           T-cell - monocyte interaction, thereby minimizing the T-cell-driven inflammatory
           amplification loop.

      In addition, MMF reduces expression of adhesion molecules on endothelial cells and
      leucocytes, thereby attenuating recruitment of circulating leucocytes to the atherosclerotic
      plaque. Combining these effects MMF treatment will improve anti-atherogenic defence
      mechanisms, such as improvement of endothelial function and attenuation of the
      pro-inflammatory state.

      *design This will be a substudy of of the multi-center, double-blind, randomized, trial
      &quot;Mycophenol mofetil in Antiretroviral Naïve patients 2 (MAN2 study)&quot; (called the main study
      hereafter). The aim of the substudy is to evaluate the effects of mycophenolate mofetil on
      ´surrogate markers´ for atherosclerosis in a group of HIV-1 infected patients. All 90
      patients to be included in the main study will be asked to participate in this substudy. A
      separate informed consent is needed.

      Patients participating in this substudy will undergo study procedures for the substudy only
      on day 0 and week 48 of the main study (i.e. before the first dose of MMF and after 48 weeks
      of MMF treatment for the patients randomized to MMF treatment). Extra blood will be drawn to
      measure several biochemical markers associated with atherosclerosis and will be measured.
      Furthermore measurements of the condition of the blood vessels will be performed (using
      ultrasound, amongst others).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2005</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The difference between the two groups (patients treated with MMF and the control group without treatment) in the change (week 0-week 48) in biochemical markers, Flow Mediated Dilation and Intima Media Thickness.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change (week 0-week 48) within patients in biochemical markers, Flow Mediated Dilation and Intima Media Thickness.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infection</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mycophenol mofetil (MMF, Cellcept®) 500 mg BID</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient included in the MAN2-study van enter this substudy (see protocol MAN2
             study)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any condition, illness or use of medication which according to the investigator is not
             compatible with the conduct of the substudy or which could interfere with the
             evaluations required by the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Erik S Stroes, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Internal Medicine, Division of Vascular Medicine, Academic Medical Center, University of Amsterdam</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sander I. van Leuven, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+31 20 5668675</phone>
    <email>s.i.vanleuven@amc.uva.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Joost N Vermeulen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+31 20 5668992</phone>
    <email>j.n.vermeulen@amc.uva.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Internal Medicine, Academic Medical Center, University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <state>NH</state>
        <zip>1105 AZ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sander I van Leuven, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+31 20 5668675</phone>
      <email>s.i.vanleuven@amc.uva.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Joost N Vermeulen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+31 20 5668992</phone>
      <email>j.n.vermeulen@amc.uva.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Erik S Stroes, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sander I van Leuven, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allison AC, Eugui EM. Mycophenolate mofetil and its mechanisms of action. Immunopharmacology. 2000 May;47(2-3):85-118. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10878285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Romero F, Rodríguez-Iturbe B, Pons H, Parra G, Quiroz Y, Rincón J, González L. Mycophenolate mofetil treatment reduces cholesterol-induced atherosclerosis in the rabbit. Atherosclerosis. 2000 Sep;152(1):127-33.</citation>
    <PMID>10996347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greenstein SM, Sun S, Calderon TM, Kim DY, Schreiber TC, Schechner RS, Tellis VA, Berman JW. Mycophenolate mofetil treatment reduces atherosclerosis in the cholesterol-fed rabbit. J Surg Res. 2000 Jun 15;91(2):123-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10839960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 1, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 2, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 22, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>HIV-1</keyword>
  <keyword>atherosclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>immunomodulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

