<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00247845</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P04-0098</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00247845</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Atazanavir Substitution Intervention (EASI) Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Atazanavir Substitution Intervention (EASI) Study: An Observational Phase IV Study to Evaluate the Impact of Atazanavir Substitution on the Quality of Life and Maintenance of Virologic Suppression in HIV-Infected Patients Intolerant to Current Successful HAART</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      With the advent of highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART), it was hypothesized that its
      consistent use could lead to a cure for HIV infection in as little as three years [Perelson,
      1997]. Subsequent research has shown this model to be incorrect [Finzi, 1999]. In addition,
      long term use of HAART has now been associated with significant metabolic abnormalities,
      which could lead to unintended morbidity, possibly worse than what one could expect from the
      progression of untreated HIV-associated immune disease over the same period of time [Carr,
      2000]. Accordingly, current recommendations for antiretroviral therapy have become more
      conservative. It is now suggested that a person with a CD4 count &gt; 350 cells/mm³ may safely
      delay initiation of HAART [Yeni, 2002].However, for those who still require HAART, the risks
      of short-term and long-term toxicities remain, even if full virologic suppression is
      achieved. In this setting, a number of switching strategies have been evaluated (Negredo et
      al, 2002 &amp; Martinez et al, 2003), mostly involving single drug substitutions of a protease
      inhibitor (PI) for a non-nucleoside agent (NNRTI) or abacavir (ABC). In general terms, these
      hae shown that virologic suppression is usually maintained, with improvement in drug-related
      side effects, including metabolic toxicities. A number of patients who are currently taking
      effective HAART are experiencing side effects to one or more of the agents in their regimen
      that is not severe enough to mandate an immediate change in their regimen, but that is having
      a measurable effect on their qualify of life. Over time, these effects may have an impact on
      adherence to therapy and its long-term efficacy. Given the recent availability of ATV
      (+/-RTV), its once daily administration, low pill count and favourable side effect profile,
      it is being used in clinical practice as part of single drug substitution strategies in
      patients exhibiting a maximal response to HAART. There is a clear need to examine this
      practice in a systematic manner to document its occurrence, efficacy and safety.

      We hypothesize that, in patients with maximal virologic suppression on a double class regimen
      (including two NRTIs and an NNRTI or a PI, boosted with RTV or not), and in whom a decision
      has been made to implement a single drug substitution of the NNRTI or PI for ATV (+/-), this
      will lead to an improvement in objectively measured quality of life without any negative
      impact on the virologic efficacy of the regimen.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a single arm observational study to include 100 subjects. After a clinical
      decision is made to implement a single drug substitution to ATV +/- RTV, there will be an
      initial screening visit, at which time the study will be presented to the patient and
      informed consent for participation will be obtained. A number of evaluations (including blood
      tests) will be completed to definitively assess a subject's eligibility to participate in
      this protocol. The patients will continue on their current therapy and will return within the
      next 14 days for an enrollment visit to review the blood test results and definitively
      confirm study eligibility. In particular, we will ascertain the continued presence of the
      side effect/toxicity motivating consideration of a change in therapy. This being down, the
      quality of life questionnaires (MOS-HIV and ASDM) will be administered for the first time.
      Once again, the patient will continue on their current HAART and return within the next 14
      days for a baseline visit at which time the quality of life questionnaires (MOS-HIV and ASDM)
      will be administered once again, the results being averaged with those obtained at the time
      of the enrollment visit, this serving as a more rigorous evaluation of the patient's current
      status. The patient could be withdrawn from the study if the side effect/toxicity motivating
      consideration of a change in therapy is no longer present. At this baseline visit, all
      patients will switch the PI or NNRTI component of their regimen to ATV (+/- RTV). The
      decision to use boosted or unboosted ATV in this protocol will be left to the discretion of
      the treating physician. All patients will be receiving ATV (+/- RTV) with food. The dose of
      the unboosted ATV will be 300 mg (2 capsules, 150mg each) plus RTV (1 capsule, 100 mg). The
      patients will then be seen in follow up at weeks 4, 12, 24, 32, and 48 after the baseline
      visit. They will continue on their new therapy (including ATV +/- RTV) for this entire period
      of observation. Changes in the NRTI backbone will be permitted without constituting a study
      endpoint, while changes in the ATV +/- RTV that may be required for reasons of efficacy or
      toxicity will constitute such an endpoint, leading to a patient's withdrawal from the study.
      At each study visit, the quality of life questionnaires (MOS-HIV and ASDM) will be
      administered. The results will be compared to the mean results obtained at the enrollment and
      baseline visits, with each individual participant serving as his/her own control. Measures of
      adherence to HAART, CD4 cell counts and HIV plasma viral load will also be obtained at each
      study visit, and will constitute secondary study endpoints.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2007</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        18 years of age or older with a confirmed diagnosis of HIV infection
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        18 years of age or older; a confirmed diagnosis of HIV infection; 2 consecutive HIV RNA
        levels &lt;50 copies/mL with the most recent being within the past 3 months; have been on the
        same HAART regimen for the past 3 months; have side effects to their current antiretroviral
        medications that warrant a consideration of a change in therapy. There must be a clinical
        suspicion by the investigator that these side effects are attributable to either the PI or
        the NNRTI component of the regimen; Have agreement between the treating physician and the
        patient that a single drug substitution to ATV +/- RTV will be proposed, independent of
        participation in the study; be able to provide written informed consent and complete the
        quality of life instruments and, in the opinion of the investigator, comply in every other
        way with the requirements of the study protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Exclusion criteria: Have received investigational drug within 30 days prior to the baseline
        visit of the study; if female, be pregnant or breast-feeding; have an acute illness,
        including an acute opportunistic infection; have grade 3-4 laboratory abnormalities on any
        of the following parameters: CBC, ALT, AST, GGT, LDH, bilirubin, amylase, and alkaline
        phosphatase.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Conway, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Downtown Infectious Diseases Clinic,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oak Tree Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pender Community Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vancouver General Hospital Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cool-Aid Society in Victoria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Victoria</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 31, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 31, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 2, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 22, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Atazanavir</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Experienced</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atazanavir Sulfate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

