<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00240695</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR005947</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00240695</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Follow-up Study to Assess Safety and Tolerability of Galantamine Treatment in Individuals With Mild Cognitive Impairment</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label Extension Study to Assess the Long-Term Safety and Tolerability of Galantamine HBr in the Treatment of Mild Cognitive Impairment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this follow-up study is to assess the long-term safety and tolerability of
      galantamine in individuals with mild cognitive impairment who participated in a previous
      study with galantamine
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Dementia is a chronic, progressive brain disease that may involve a number of symptoms,
      including memory loss and changes in personality, behavior, judgment, attention span,
      language and thought. The most common type of dementia is Alzheimer's disease. Over time,
      patients with Alzheimer's disease may lose ability to perform daily tasks related to personal
      care (for example bathing, dressing, eating) and may be unable to handle money or travel to
      familiar places. The term mild cognitive impairment (MCI) is used to describe individuals who
      have memory impairments suggestive of early dementia, but do not yet meet the criteria for
      Alzheimer's disease. Individuals with MCI are more likely to develop Alzheimer's disease than
      normal elderly patients. Individuals with MCI who completed 1 of 2 previous double-blind
      studies with galantamine may participate in this follow-up study if they have not progressed
      to dementia. They will receive open-label galantamine for 12 months and will be evaluated
      after 2, 6 and 12 months of treatment. Safety evaluations (incidence of adverse events, ECGs,
      physical examinations, laboratory tests) will be performed throughout the study.
      Effectiveness will be assessed after 12 months of treatment (by using standardized tests and
      rating scales (Alzheimer's Disease Assessment Scale: cognitive/MCI version [ADAS-Cog/MCI],
      Clinical Dementia Rating [CDR] and CDR-Sum of the Boxes [CDR-SB]). Health status will be
      assessed using the Health Survey portion of the Short-Form 36 (SF-36) and the use of health
      and social care resources will be assessed using a resource-use questionnaire. The enrolled
      individuals may participate in an optional portion of the study in which their genetic
      material is analyzed to see if contains something that would affect the way galantamine is
      used by their bodies. Galantamine 8 or 12 milligrams (mg) by mouth twice daily for 12 months.
      Dose will start at 4 mg twice daily and be gradually increased to final dose; 12 mg twice
      daily dose may be decreased to 8 mg twice daily based upon tolerability
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events; Changes in laboratory tests, ECGs, and physical examinations</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in CDR, ADAS-Cog/MCI version, CDR-SB and SF-36 scores from baseline to end of treatment; resource use; time to conversion to dementia</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">724</enrollment>
  <condition>Cognition Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Nervous System Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Mental Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Brain Diseases</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>galantamine hydrobromide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Completed 24 months of double-blind treatment in 1 of 2 previous studies with
             galantamine without progressing to dementia (CDR&lt; 1)

          -  Able to safely receive open-label galantamine in the opinion of the investigator and
             treatment is in the individual's best interest

          -  Regular (at least 3 days a week) visits from a person able to accompany patient to
             scheduled visits

          -  Enrolled within 7-30 days after the previous galantamine study Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals who converted to dementia (CDR &gt; = 1) during 1 of the previous galantamine
             studies

          -  Prematurely discontinued 1 of the previous galantamine studies or completed 1 of the
             previous studies more than 30 days prior to this study

          -  Current clinically significant cardiovascular disease (including heart surgery,
             unstable angina, congestive heart failure, fibrillation, valve disease or uncontrolled
             high blood pressure)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L. C. Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_JNJ_6051&amp;studyid=688&amp;filename=CR005947_CSR.pdf</url>
    <description>A follow-up study to assess safety and tolerability of galantamine treatment in patients with mild cognitive impairment</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 14, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 14, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 18, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 18, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Memory Loss</keyword>
  <keyword>galantamine</keyword>
  <keyword>Nervous System Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>open-label</keyword>
  <keyword>elderly</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Galantamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

