<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00243906</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01NS039160</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00243906</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interventional Management of Stroke (IMS) II Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Interventional Management of Stroke (IMS) II Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the effects of delivering intra-arterial recombinant
      tissue plasminogen activator (rt-PA) and ultrasound to the site of the blood clot blocking
      blood flow to the brain of stroke patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overall goal of Interventional Management of Stroke (IMS II) study is to refine
      thrombolytic therapy for patients with acute ischemic stroke who can be treated within three
      hours of stroke onset.

      This multi-center, non-randomized pilot study will provide preliminary data about the
      benefits and risks of combined intravenous (IV) and intra-arterial (IA) recombinant tissue
      plasminogen activator (rtPA) and low-intensity ultrasound energy in ischemic stroke patients
      with baseline NIHSSS &gt;/= 10 in whom intravenous treatment can be started within three hours
      of stroke onset. rt-PA is a thrombolytic, clot-dissolving drug.

      The primary objectives for the study are to obtain reliable estimates of the effectiveness
      and safety of a treatment approach combining IV/IA rt-PA and ultrasound for stroke patients;
      and to determine if the estimated effectiveness of combined IV/IA rt-PA at 3 months—as
      compared to the 3 month outcome of placebo-treated patients in the NINDS rt-PA Stroke
      Trial—warrants proceeding to a large, phase III randomized trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary Safety Endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>36 hours after completion of rt-PA infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Development of intracerebral hematoma or hemorrhagic infarction with clinical deterioration likely to result in permanent disability or death, or other severe systemic bleeding complications such as groin hematoma, retroperitoneal hematoma, or gastrointestinal bleeding requiring transfusion of 3 units of blood replacement or major surgical intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary Angiographic Outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after start of IA therapy</time_frame>
    <description>The primary revascularization end point was complete (arterial occlusive lesion III) recanalization of the targeted arterial occlusion at 60 minutes after the start of IA rt-PA and ultrasound therapy,</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary Outcome Measure</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months following treatment</time_frame>
    <description>modified Rankin Score of 0 or 1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">81</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Recombinant tissue plasminogen activator</intervention_name>
    <description>Low-dose IV rt-PA (0.6 mg/kg) followed by delivery of additional IA rt-PA (up to 22 mg).</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low-intensity ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>Delivery of additional IA rt-PA (up to 22 mg) in the setting of low-energy ultrasound via the EKOS microinfusion catheter at the site of IA occlusion in acute ischemic stroke patients with large strokes (NIHSS &gt;/= 10) treated within 3 hours of symptoms onset.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: 18 through 80 years (i.e., candidates must have had their 18th birthday, but not
             had their 81st birthday)

          -  Initiation of intravenous rt-PA within 3 hours of onset of stroke symptoms. Time of
             onset is defined as the last time when the subject was witnessed to be at baseline
             (i.e., subjects who have stroke symptoms upon awakening will be considered to have
             their onset at beginning of sleep)

          -  An NIHSSS &gt;/= 10 at the time that intravenous rt-PA is begun

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of stroke in the past 3 months

          -  Previous intra-cranial hemorrhage, neoplasm, subarachnoid hemorrhage, or arteriovenous
             malformation

          -  Clinical presentation suggests a subarachnoid hemorrhage, even if initial CT scan is
             normal

          -  Hypertension at time of treatment; systolic BP &gt; 185 or diastolic &gt; 110 mm Hg) or
             aggressive measures to lower blood pressure to below these limits are needed.

          -  Presumed septic embolus

          -  Presumed pericarditis, including pericarditis after acute myocardial infarction

          -  Recent (within 30 days) surgery or biopsy of parenchymal organ

          -  Recent (within 30 days) trauma, with internal injuries or ulcerative wounds

          -  Recent (within 90 days) severe head trauma or head trauma with loss of consciousness

          -  Any active or recent (within 30 days) hemorrhage

          -  Known hereditary or acquired hemorrhagic diathesis, coagulation factor deficiency or
             oral anticoagulant therapy with INR &gt; 1.5 or institutionally equivalent prothrombin
             time

          -  Females of childbearing potential who are known to be pregnant and/or lactating or who
             have positive pregnancy tests on admission

          -  Baseline lab values: glucose &lt; 50mg/dl or &gt; 400mg/dl, platelets &lt;100,000, or Hct &lt;25

          -  Subjects that require hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis

          -  Subjects who have received heparin within 48 hours must have a normal partial
             thromboplastin time (PTT) to be eligible

          -  Subjects with an arterial puncture at a non-compressible site or a lumbar puncture in
             the previous 7 days

          -  Subjects with a seizure at onset of stroke

          -  Subjects with a pre-existing neurological or psychiatric disease that would confound
             the neurological or functional evaluations

          -  Other serious, advanced, or terminal illness

          -  Any other condition that the investigator feels would pose a significant hazard to the
             subject if Activase (Alteplase) therapy is initiated

          -  Current participation in another research drug treatment protocol; subject cannot
             start another experimental agent until after 90 days

          -  Informed consent is not or cannot be obtained. For example, obtunded subjects are not
             automatically excluded from the study. However, if the next of kin or legal guardian
             (i.e., the individual legally empowered in the state where the consent is obtained)
             cannot provide consent, randomization and entry into the study could not proceed

        CT Scan Exclusion Criteria:

          -  High density lesion consistent with hemorrhage of any degree

          -  Significant mass effect with midline shift

          -  Large (more than 1/3 of the middle cerebral artery) regions of clear hypodensity on
             the baseline CT scan. Sulcal effacement and/or loss of grey-white differentiation
             alone are not contraindications for treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph P. Broderick, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas A. Tomsick, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cincinnati</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45267</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>IMS II Trial Investigators. The Interventional Management of Stroke (IMS) II Study. Stroke. 2007 Jul;38(7):2127-35. Epub 2007 May 24.</citation>
    <PMID>17525387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 24, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 25, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>July 18, 2012</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2012</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Estimate">July 25, 2012</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 25, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acute ischemic stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>rt-PA</keyword>
  <keyword>thrombolytic</keyword>
  <keyword>recombinant tissue plasminogen activator</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Plasminogen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tissue Plasminogen Activator</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

