<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01590472</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GTS 36076 MARF</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01590472</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Do Your Genes Put You at a Higher Risk of Developing Mesothelioma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Consortium for the Sharing of Germ Line DNA and Tissue From Subjects With Mesothelioma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mesothelioma Applied Research Foundation, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to investigate the possibility that a person's genes
      put a person at a higher risk of developing mesothelioma. The investigators will examine
      genes from DNA (genetic material) isolated from blood. This study will also examine the
      impact of environmental and work exposures and family history of common cancers on the
      development of mesothelioma. The genetic markers in this study will basically identify how a
      person's body processes frequently encountered environmental pollutants and will not tell
      about chromosomes, specific diseases, or other potential health problems.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Mesothelioma is a cancer that develops from serosal surfaces usually in response to prior
      asbestos exposure. A history of asbestos exposure can be elicited in more than 80% of
      mesothelioma victims. However, asbestos exposure alone is not sufficient to cause the
      development of mesothelioma. Nearly 27 million individuals in the US, were exposed to
      asbestos in the work place between 1940 and 1979 but just 3,000 new cases of mesothelioma are
      diagnosed each year. Therefore, the investigators hypothesis is that genetic variation in
      addition to asbestos exposure, and host factors contribute to the development of
      mesothelioma. It is estimated, based on the investigators preliminary studies, that a
      population in excess of 1,000 subjects with mesothelioma is required to perform a valid GWAS.

      Therefore a multicenter approach is necessary to collect data and DNA on sufficient numbers
      with mesothelioma to adequately evaluate genetic risk. It is the aim of this proposal to
      develop a consortium of mesothelioma investigators to share phenotypic data and DNA samples
      and to perform genome wide association scanning (GWAS).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Creation of a consortium of investigators (6 sites) for collection of blood for germline DNA and demographic information from 1000 mesothelioma subjects.</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be seen on one occasion lasting 30-60 min to draw blood and elicit demographic information. It will require up to 2 years to enroll 1000 subjects with mesothelioma from the various sites.</time_frame>
    <description>Demographic variables that will be collected include; date of birth, gender, age at first exposure to asbestos, type of exposure (occupational or bystander), family health history, personal past medical history, smoking history, age at diagnosis, latency, tumor location and cell type.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GWAS will be performed on the DNA from the 1000 subjects with mesothelioma and compared with 1000 age and asbestos exposure matched controls free of past personal history and family history of cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>It will take up to 1 year, after the collection of the 1000 mesothelioma samples, to perform and analyze the GWAS.</time_frame>
    <description>Given the significant risk for cancers other than the index mesothelioma in both subjects and their 1st degree relative (nearly 3 fold for sibs, parents and the mesothelioma subjects themselves and 7 fold for their children), the goal is to identify SNPs involved with mesothelioma and other common cancer susceptibility.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">69</enrollment>
  <condition>Mesothelioma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mesothelioma</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals who have been diagnosed with mesothelioma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      whole blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects will be recruited from the clinics and in patient wards of the academic medical
        centers noted as collaborators.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects able to provide informed consent who suffer from mesothelioma

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to provide informed consent

          -  Absence of mesothelioma in self
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jill Ohar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lee Krug, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie Brahmer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Harvey I Pass, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tobias Peikert, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel H Sterman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bertazzi PA. Descriptive epidemiology of malignant mesothelioma. Med Lav. 2005 Jul-Aug;96(4):287-303. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16457426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paul S, Neragi-Miandoab S, Jaklitsch MT. Preoperative assessment and therapeutic options for patients with malignant pleural mesothelioma. Thorac Surg Clin. 2004 Nov;14(4):505-16, ix. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15559057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu L, Flynn BJ, Ungar S, Pass HI, Linnainmaa K, Mattson K, Gerwin BI. Asbestos induction of extended lifespan in normal human mesothelial cells: interindividual susceptibility and SV40 T antigen. Carcinogenesis. 1999 May;20(5):773-83.</citation>
    <PMID>10334193</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bocchetta M, Di Resta I, Powers A, Fresco R, Tosolini A, Testa JR, Pass HI, Rizzo P, Carbone M. Human mesothelial cells are unusually susceptible to simian virus 40-mediated transformation and asbestos cocarcinogenicity. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2000 Aug 29;97(18):10214-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10954737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kamp DW, Weitzman SA. Asbestosis: clinical spectrum and pathogenic mechanisms. Proc Soc Exp Biol Med. 1997 Jan;214(1):12-26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9012357</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sluis-Cremer GK. Asbestos disease at low exposures after long residence times. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 1991 Dec 31;643:182-93.</citation>
    <PMID>1809131</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neragi-Miandoab S. Multimodality approach in management of malignant pleural mesothelioma. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2006 Jan;29(1):14-9. Epub 2005 Dec 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16343925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berry G, Wagner JC. Effect of age at inoculation of asbestos on occurrence of mesotheliomas in rats. Int J Cancer. 1976 Apr 15;17(4):477-83.</citation>
    <PMID>1279040</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Becklake MR, Toyota B, Stewart M, Hanson R, Hanley J. Lung structure as a risk factor in adverse pulmonary responses to asbestos exposure. A case-referent study in Quebec chrysotile miners and millers. Am Rev Respir Dis. 1983 Sep;128(3):385-8.</citation>
    <PMID>6311060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spirtas R, Heineman EF, Bernstein L, Beebe GW, Keehn RJ, Stark A, Harlow BL, Benichou J. Malignant mesothelioma: attributable risk of asbestos exposure. Occup Environ Med. 1994 Dec;51(12):804-11.</citation>
    <PMID>7849863</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baris YI, Sahin AA, Ozesmi M, Kerse I, Ozen E, Kolacan B, Altinörs M, Göktepeli A. An outbreak of pleural mesothelioma and chronic fibrosing pleurisy in the village of Karain/Urgüp in Anatolia. Thorax. 1978 Apr;33(2):181-92.</citation>
    <PMID>663877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baris I, Simonato L, Artvinli M, Pooley F, Saracci R, Skidmore J, Wagner C. Epidemiological and environmental evidence of the health effects of exposure to erionite fibres: a four-year study in the Cappadocian region of Turkey. Int J Cancer. 1987 Jan 15;39(1):10-7.</citation>
    <PMID>3025107</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amundadottir LT, Sulem P, Gudmundsson J, Helgason A, Baker A, Agnarsson BA, Sigurdsson A, Benediktsdottir KR, Cazier JB, Sainz J, Jakobsdottir M, Kostic J, Magnusdottir DN, Ghosh S, Agnarsson K, Birgisdottir B, Le Roux L, Olafsdottir A, Blondal T, Andresdottir M, Gretarsdottir OS, Bergthorsson JT, Gudbjartsson D, Gylfason A, Thorleifsson G, Manolescu A, Kristjansson K, Geirsson G, Isaksson H, Douglas J, Johansson JE, Bälter K, Wiklund F, Montie JE, Yu X, Suarez BK, Ober C, Cooney KA, Gronberg H, Catalona WJ, Einarsson GV, Barkardottir RB, Gulcher JR, Kong A, Thorsteinsdottir U, Stefansson K. A common variant associated with prostate cancer in European and African populations. Nat Genet. 2006 Jun;38(6):652-8. Epub 2006 May 7.</citation>
    <PMID>16682969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freedman ML, Haiman CA, Patterson N, McDonald GJ, Tandon A, Waliszewska A, Penney K, Steen RG, Ardlie K, John EM, Oakley-Girvan I, Whittemore AS, Cooney KA, Ingles SA, Altshuler D, Henderson BE, Reich D. Admixture mapping identifies 8q24 as a prostate cancer risk locus in African-American men. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2006 Sep 19;103(38):14068-73. Epub 2006 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>16945910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rai AJ, Flores RM, Mathew A, Gonzalez-Espinoza R, Bott M, Ladanyi M, Rusch V, Fleisher M. Soluble mesothelin related peptides (SMRP) and osteopontin as protein biomarkers for malignant mesothelioma: analytical validation of ELISA based assays and characterization at mRNA and protein levels. Clin Chem Lab Med. 2010 Feb;48(2):271-8. doi: 10.1515/CCLM.2010.066.</citation>
    <PMID>20131968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tajima K, Ohashi R, Sekido Y, Hida T, Nara T, Hashimoto M, Iwakami S, Minakata K, Yae T, Takahashi F, Saya H, Takahashi K. Osteopontin-mediated enhanced hyaluronan binding induces multidrug resistance in mesothelioma cells. Oncogene. 2010 Apr 1;29(13):1941-51. doi: 10.1038/onc.2009.478. Epub 2010 Jan 18.</citation>
    <PMID>20101228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ohashi R, Tajima K, Takahashi F, Cui R, Gu T, Shimizu K, Nishio K, Fukuoka K, Nakano T, Takahashi K. Osteopontin modulates malignant pleural mesothelioma cell functions in vitro. Anticancer Res. 2009 Jun;29(6):2205-14.</citation>
    <PMID>19528482</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cerhan JR, Ansell SM, Fredericksen ZS, Kay NE, Liebow M, Call TG, Dogan A, Cunningham JM, Wang AH, Liu-Mares W, Macon WR, Jelinek D, Witzig TE, Habermann TM, Slager SL. Genetic variation in 1253 immune and inflammation genes and risk of non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Blood. 2007 Dec 15;110(13):4455-63. Epub 2007 Sep 7.</citation>
    <PMID>17827388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langsenlehner U, Renner W, Yazdani-Biuki B, Eder T, Wascher TC, Paulweber B, Clar H, Hofmann G, Samonigg H, Krippl P. Integrin alpha-2 and beta-3 gene polymorphisms and breast cancer risk. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2006 May;97(1):67-72.</citation>
    <PMID>16317580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerger A, Hofmann G, Langsenlehner U, Renner W, Weitzer W, Wehrschütz M, Wascher T, Samonigg H, Krippl P. Integrin alpha-2 and beta-3 gene polymorphisms and colorectal cancer risk. Int J Colorectal Dis. 2009 Feb;24(2):159-63. doi: 10.1007/s00384-008-0587-9. Epub 2008 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>18836731</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Donnell CJ, Nabel EG. Cardiovascular genomics, personalized medicine, and the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute: part I: the beginning of an era. Circ Cardiovasc Genet. 2008 Oct;1(1):51-7. doi: 10.1161/CIRCGENETICS.108.813337. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20031542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ohar J, Sterling DA, Bleecker E, Donohue J. Changing patterns in asbestos-induced lung disease. Chest. 2004 Feb;125(2):744-53.</citation>
    <PMID>14769760</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirschhorn JN, Daly MJ. Genome-wide association studies for common diseases and complex traits. Nat Rev Genet. 2005 Feb;6(2):95-108. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15716906</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boezen HM. Genome-wide association studies: what do they teach us about asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease? Proc Am Thorac Soc. 2009 Dec;6(8):701-3. doi: 10.1513/pats.200907-058DP. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20008879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Landi S, Gemignani F, Neri M, Barale R, Bonassi S, Bottari F, Canessa PA, Canzian F, Ceppi M, Filiberti R, Ivaldi GP, Mencoboni M, Scaruffi P, Tonini GP, Mutti L, Puntoni R. Polymorphisms of glutathione-S-transferase M1 and manganese superoxide dismutase are associated with the risk of malignant pleural mesothelioma. Int J Cancer. 2007 Jun 15;120(12):2739-43.</citation>
    <PMID>17290392</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dianzani I, Gibello L, Biava A, Giordano M, Bertolotti M, Betti M, Ferrante D, Guarrera S, Betta GP, Mirabelli D, Matullo G, Magnani C. Polymorphisms in DNA repair genes as risk factors for asbestos-related malignant mesothelioma in a general population study. Mutat Res. 2006 Jul 25;599(1-2):124-34. Epub 2006 Mar 27.</citation>
    <PMID>16564556</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robinson BW, Lake RA. Advances in malignant mesothelioma. N Engl J Med. 2005 Oct 13;353(15):1591-603. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16221782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robinson BW, Musk AW, Lake RA. Malignant mesothelioma. Lancet. 2005 Jul 30-Aug 5;366(9483):397-408. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16054941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wheatley-Price P, Yang B, Patsios D, Patel D, Ma C, Xu W, Leighl N, Feld R, Cho BC, O'Sullivan B, Roberts H, Tsao MS, Tammemagi M, Anraku M, Chen Z, de Perrot M, Liu G. Soluble mesothelin-related Peptide and osteopontin as markers of response in malignant mesothelioma. J Clin Oncol. 2010 Jul 10;28(20):3316-22. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2009.26.9944. Epub 2010 May 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20498407</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ohar JA, Ampleford EJ, Howard SE, Sterling DA. Identification of a mesothelioma phenotype. Respir Med. 2007 Mar;101(3):503-9. Epub 2006 Aug 21. Erratum in: Respir Med. 2008 Dec;102(12):1844.</citation>
    <PMID>16919927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gudmundsson J, Sulem P, Steinthorsdottir V, Bergthorsson JT, Thorleifsson G, Manolescu A, Rafnar T, Gudbjartsson D, Agnarsson BA, Baker A, Sigurdsson A, Benediktsdottir KR, Jakobsdottir M, Blondal T, Stacey SN, Helgason A, Gunnarsdottir S, Olafsdottir A, Kristinsson KT, Birgisdottir B, Ghosh S, Thorlacius S, Magnusdottir D, Stefansdottir G, Kristjansson K, Bagger Y, Wilensky RL, Reilly MP, Morris AD, Kimber CH, Adeyemo A, Chen Y, Zhou J, So WY, Tong PC, Ng MC, Hansen T, Andersen G, Borch-Johnsen K, Jorgensen T, Tres A, Fuertes F, Ruiz-Echarri M, Asin L, Saez B, van Boven E, Klaver S, Swinkels DW, Aben KK, Graif T, Cashy J, Suarez BK, van Vierssen Trip O, Frigge ML, Ober C, Hofker MH, Wijmenga C, Christiansen C, Rader DJ, Palmer CN, Rotimi C, Chan JC, Pedersen O, Sigurdsson G, Benediktsson R, Jonsson E, Einarsson GV, Mayordomo JI, Catalona WJ, Kiemeney LA, Barkardottir RB, Gulcher JR, Thorsteinsdottir U, Kong A, Stefansson K. Two variants on chromosome 17 confer prostate cancer risk, and the one in TCF2 protects against type 2 diabetes. Nat Genet. 2007 Aug;39(8):977-83. Epub 2007 Jul 1.</citation>
    <PMID>17603485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gudmundsson J, Sulem P, Manolescu A, Amundadottir LT, Gudbjartsson D, Helgason A, Rafnar T, Bergthorsson JT, Agnarsson BA, Baker A, Sigurdsson A, Benediktsdottir KR, Jakobsdottir M, Xu J, Blondal T, Kostic J, Sun J, Ghosh S, Stacey SN, Mouy M, Saemundsdottir J, Backman VM, Kristjansson K, Tres A, Partin AW, Albers-Akkers MT, Godino-Ivan Marcos J, Walsh PC, Swinkels DW, Navarrete S, Isaacs SD, Aben KK, Graif T, Cashy J, Ruiz-Echarri M, Wiley KE, Suarez BK, Witjes JA, Frigge M, Ober C, Jonsson E, Einarsson GV, Mayordomo JI, Kiemeney LA, Isaacs WB, Catalona WJ, Barkardottir RB, Gulcher JR, Thorsteinsdottir U, Kong A, Stefansson K. Genome-wide association study identifies a second prostate cancer susceptibility variant at 8q24. Nat Genet. 2007 May;39(5):631-7. Epub 2007 Apr 1.</citation>
    <PMID>17401366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith DD. Women and mesothelioma. Chest. 2002 Dec;122(6):1885-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12475820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asbestos, asbestosis, and cancer: the Helsinki criteria for diagnosis and attribution. Scand J Work Environ Health. 1997 Aug;23(4):311-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9322824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Malignant mesothelioma mortality--United States, 1999-2005. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2009 Apr 24;58(15):393-6.</citation>
    <PMID>19390506</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Genetics of Mesothelioma</keyword>
  <keyword>Mesothelioma Consortium</keyword>
  <keyword>GWAS</keyword>
  <keyword>Asbestos</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mesothelioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

