<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01591759</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCL 2011-P-002028</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01591759</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Trial of Citicoline in Individuals With Mild Traumatic Brain Injury (mTBI)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Trial of Citicoline in Individuals With mTBI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mclean Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mclean Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This investigation will explore the impact of 8 weeks of citicoline treatment on cognitive
      function, clinical state and substance use in 40 individuals with mild traumatic brain injury
      (mTBI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Traumatic brain injury (TBI) remains a major cause of death and disability within the United
      States. Approximately 1.4 million individuals sustain a TBI each year, and currently, more
      than 5.3 million Americans or 3% of the general population live with disabilities associated
      with a TBI, resulting in enormous financial, physical and psychosocial burdens to the
      patients, their families and society. The issue of TBI has never been more salient, as it is
      now labeled the &quot;signature wound&quot; of the current conflict in Iraq and Afghanistan.

      Patients with mTBI often experience a variety of symptoms including headache, dizziness,
      fatigue, irritability, depression, anxiety, insomnia, reduced alcohol tolerance, and problems
      with cognitive function. In acute stages, cognitive deficits may affect multiple domains and
      be severe enough to interfere with everyday activities.

      The proposed investigation will explore the impact of 8 weeks of citicoline treatment on
      cognitive function, clinical state and substance use in 40 individuals with mTBI. The
      investigators hypothesize that individuals with mTBI who receive citicoline will demonstrate
      improvements in cognitive performance relative to their own pre-treatment levels as well as
      to those randomized to placebo. Specifically, the investigators expect the greatest
      improvement on frontal/executive measures following treatment with citicoline. In addition,
      the investigators also hypothesize that 8 weeks of treatment with citicoline will result in a
      reduction of comorbid substance use and improvements in clinical state measures relative to
      both pre-treatment levels and those randomized to receive placebo. Given the relationship
      between cognitive function and clinical state, the investigators expect a primary improvement
      in cognitive function will likely precede the expected improvement of mTBI-related symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Our citicoline supply expired and the exact product has discontinued.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurocognitive Assessment Changes with Citicoline Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at treatment week 4 and week 8</time_frame>
    <description>4-Subtest Wechsler Abbreviated Scale of Intelligence (WASI) at the baseline visit only. Measures to be administered at baseline and both follow-up visits: Hopkins Verbal Learning Test-Revised (HVLT-R), Brief Visuospatial Memory Test-Revised (BVMT-R), Logical Memory (LM) Subtest of the Wechsler Memory Scale-Revised (WMS-R) and Sullivan Multiple Versions, Rey-Osterreith Complex Figure (Rey-O), Stroop Color-Word Test, Trailmaking Test A &amp; B, Controlled Oral Word Association Test (COWAT), Digit Span subtest of the WAIS-R, Digit Symbol Substitution Test (DSST), Wisconsin Card Sort Test (WCST), Go/No Go Test, Time Estimation Task (TET), and Facial Expressions of Emotion-Stimuli and Tests (FEEST).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical State Assessment Changes with Citicoline Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly assessment &amp; biweekly clinical scales for 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS), Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS), Hamilton Anxiety Scales (HAM-A), Positive &amp; Negative Affect Scale (PANAS), Profile of Mood States (POMS), Barratt Impulsiveness Scale (BIS), UPPS Impulsive Behavior Scale (UPPS-P), Impulsiveness-Venturesomeness-Empathy Scale (IVE), State/Trait Inventory (STAI), Beck Depression Inventory (BDI), Beck Hopelessness Scale (BHS), Beck Scale for Suicidal Ideation (BSS), Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI), Frontal Systems Behavior Scale (FrSBe), Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT), Cannabis Use Disorders Identification Test-Revised (CUDIT-R), National Center for PTSD 17-item checklist (PCL), Neurobehavioral Symptom Inventory (NSI), Combat Exposure Scale (CES), &amp; Clinician Administered PTSD Scale (CAPS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional MRI and Diffusion Tensor Imaging Changes with Citicoline Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at treatment week 8</time_frame>
    <description>All functional MR imaging (fMRI) will be performed on the 3 Tesla (3T) scanner retrofitted with a whole body echo-planar coil with a TIM upgrade. The challenge paradigms will be a Masked Affect paradigm, the Multi-Source Interference Task (MSIT), and a Trauma-Related Emotional Counting Stroop. In addition, diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) will be acquired to assess white matter microstructure integrity by measuring fractional anisotropy (FA) and mean diffusivity (MD).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy Changes with Citicoline Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and at treatment week 8</time_frame>
    <description>Proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) will be acquired at 3 Tesla using both single voxel and chemical shift imaging (CSI) techniques in order to assess brain metabolite levels pre and post treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Citicoline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>8-week treatment of 2,000mg/day of citicoline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Citicoline</intervention_name>
    <description>2,000mg/day of citicoline taken as twice daily unit doses of 1,000 mg for the 8-week period of the clinical trial</description>
    <arm_group_label>Citicoline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Citicoline Sodium</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo arm of single-blind study</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is able to provide informed consent

          -  Subject is cooperative

          -  Subject is between 18 and 35 years of age (inclusive)

          -  Subject meets criteria for mTBI

          -  Subject has separate treating physician and is willing to provide consent for treating
             physician to be contacted by research team

          -  Subject is a native English speaker or acquired English prior to age 5

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Serious medical illness, including diabetes, neurodegenerative disorder (i.e. multiple
             sclerosis, lupus, etc)

          -  Neurological disorder or history of serious head trauma resulting in loss of extended
             loss of consciousness or coma

          -  History of ECT treatment

          -  Estimated IQ &lt; 75

          -  Positive urine pregnancy test (screened on all study visits)

        Additional MR Imaging Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of a medical condition known to affect MR BOLD imaging (i.e. metabolism
             disorders, eating disorders, hormonal dysregulation, etc)

          -  Uncorrectable poor vision, as subjects must have normal or corrected-to normal vision
             for viewing of cognitive challenge paradigms during fMRI protocols

          -  Claustrophobia or metal implanted within the body, including body piercings which are
             not removable

          -  Additional MR related contraindications:

               -  Cardiac pacemakers

               -  Metal clips on blood vessels (also called stents)

               -  Artificial heart valve, artificial arms, hands, legs, etc.

               -  Brain stimulator devices

               -  Implanted drug pumps

               -  Ear or eye implants

               -  Known metal fragments in eyes

               -  Exposure to metal filings (sheetmetal workers, welders, and others)

               -  Other metallic surgical hardware in vital area

               -  Certain tattoos with metallic ink

               -  Certain transdermal (skin) patches such as:

               -  NicoDerm (nicotine for tobacco dependence)

               -  Transderm Scop (scopolamine for motion sickness)

               -  Ortho Evra (birth control)

               -  Certain intrauterine devices (IUDs containing metal)

          -  Since some will be military veterans with combat experience and may have been exposed
             to shrapnel, they will be screened with a handheld metal detector to ensure that they
             do not have any metal embedded in their body. Subjects who do not pass the metal
             detector screen and subjects with known shrapnel or other metal embedded or implanted
             in their body will not be eligible to participate in the MRI portion of this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Staci A Gruber, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mclean Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott E Lukas, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mclean Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McLean Hospital Brain Imaging Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belmont</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02478-9106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 29, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 2, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 4, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 22, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 22, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 23, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mclean Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Staci Gruber, Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Cognitive and Clinical Neuroimaging Core/Assistant Professor of Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>citicoline</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive function</keyword>
  <keyword>function magnetic resonance imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>magnetic resonance spectroscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>diffusion tensor imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cytidine Diphosphate Choline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

