<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01590056</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STN_Cog_HMO-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>0064-12-HMO</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01590056</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Emotional and Cognitive Subthalamic Nucleus in Deep Brain Stimulation Treated Parkinson Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mapping and Manipulating the Motor, Emotional and Cognitive Territories of the Subthalamic Area in Deep Brain Stimulation Treated Parkinson Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hadassah Medical Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hadassah Medical Organization</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      About 300 patients with Parkinson's disease (PD) have been successfully treated by deep brain
      stimulation (DBS) during the last 10 years in Hadassah. In most of the patients the site of
      stimulation is the subthalamic nucleus (STN). Recent studies by our group and others have
      demonstrated that the STN is divided into motor and non-motor areas. The investigators have
      recently shown that electrophysiological mapping of the STN during the surgery can
      differentiate motor and non-motor areas of the STN. Existing methods of adjustment of DBS
      parameters aim at amelioration of the motor signs and therefore with inactivation of the STN
      motor territory only. Although the DBS parameter setting is believed to influence the mental
      and cognitive states, there is no data that correlates stimulation parameters with mental and
      cognitive state. In addition, DBS parameter setting is also believed to influence important
      verbal functions which are partially related to motor, mental and cognitive states, but no
      data correlates the verbal function with the DBS stimulation parameters.

      The investigators hypothesize that the cognitive areas of the STN have distinct
      electrophysiological properties similar to our findings with the limbic / mental areas of the
      STN. The investigators further hypothesize that specific stimulation of these cognitive areas
      can influence the cognitive state and thus treatment with cognitive-adjusted DBS can improve
      the cognitive symptoms of PD.

      In this project, the investigators intend to map the motor, emotional and cognitive areas of
      the STN using neuronal (single units) responses to emotional voices and cognitive tasks and
      to identify the emotional and cognitive spectral signature of the STN single unit activity
      using spectral analysis and neuronal responses to emotional voices and cognitive tasks. In
      addition the investigators intend to find the neuronal signature of speech and to find the
      correlation between motor, mental and limbic electrophysiology to speech. The investigators
      also intend to investigate the motor, emotional and cognitive processing of PD patients by
      manipulating the stimulation of the STN. The proposed study will combine neural recording,
      stimulation and psychological and cognitive tests to shed new light on processing in the
      basal ganglia, as well as to provide better treatment for PD patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mapping the motor, emotional and cognitive areas of the STN using neuronal (single units) responses to motor stimuli, emotional voices and cognitive tests during surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PD patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>PD patients that are treated or are candidates for treatment with STN DBS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electrophysiological recording</intervention_name>
    <description>During the surgery for bilateral DBS electrode implantation, electrophysiological recording from the STN will be made while patients are:
listening to nonverbal affect bursts corresponding to emotions
applying a simple go-no-go auditory test</description>
    <arm_group_label>PD patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        PD patients that are treated or are candidates for treatment with STN DBS will be followed
        for 12 months (n=20). These patients will represent a consecutive sample of community based
        PD patients who will be enrolled in a prospective, open label, clinical trial.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically definite PD treated / candidates for treatment with DBS (patients with
             advanced idiopathic PD who are deemed appropriate for DBS surgery).

          -  Patients will be included in the study irrespective of whether a diagnosis of major
             depression (mild to moderate but not severe MDD) is fulfilled at baseline. Patients
             without depression will be monitored in the study for evidence of treatment emergent
             depression. Patients with depression will be monitored for antidepressant effects of
             stimulation change.

          -  Age 40-75 years

          -  Male or female.

          -  Competent and willing to give written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Significant suicidal risk [Hamilton Depression scale item 3 (suicide) &gt;2].

          -  Comorbidity with any Psychotic Disorder, Bipolar Disorder, Post Traumatic Stress
             Disorder (PTSD), Eating Disorder.

          -  Lifetime history of substance or alcohol dependence or of abuse in the preceding 12
             months

          -  Significant cognitive decline, as measured by Addenbrooke's Cognitive Examination
             (ACE) and the Frontal Assessment Battery (FAB).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Renana Eitan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Renana Eitan, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>972-050-4048165</phone>
    <email>renanaeitan@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hadassah Medical Organization, Jerusalem, Israel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem,</city>
        <zip>91120</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hadas Lemberg, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>00 972 2 6777572</phone>
      <email>lhadas@hadassah.org.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Renana Eitan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 2, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 2, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Renana Eitan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head, Neuropsychiatry Clinic</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mapping limbic areas of the STN</keyword>
  <keyword>neuronal responses to stimuli during surgery</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

