<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01596751</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UCSF Protocol No. 12751</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01596751</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase Ib/II Study of PLX 3397 and Eribulin in Patients With Metastatic Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Enhancing Efficacy of Chemotherapy in Triple Negative/Basal-Like Breast Cancer by Targeting Macrophages: A Multicenter Phase Ib/II Study of PLX 3397 and Eribulin in Patients With Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hope Rugo, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Susan G. Komen Breast Cancer Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Plexxikon</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the Phase 1b portion of the study is to determine the best dose of PLX3397
      when given in combination with standard dose eribulin (Halaven™). The purpose of the Phase 2
      portion of the study is to find out what effects, good and/or bad, these drugs have on
      patients and their metastatic breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a nonrandomized, open label phase Ib/II study evaluating the safety and efficacy of
      eribulin in combination with PLX3397, a novel CSF1 inhibitor, in patients with metastatic
      breast cancer. The phase II portion of this trial will be limited to patients with triple
      negative disease.

      The phase I portion of this trial is a dose escalation of PLX3397 to determine the maximum
      tolerated dose (MTD) of PLX3397 when given in combination with standard dose eribulin.
      Patients will be enrolled in cohorts of three, using the dose levels and plan outlined in the
      statistical section, with 6 patients enrolled at the MTD. All patients with accessible tumor
      will be required to have a tumor biopsy at study start before starting therapy.
      Pharmacokinetics of PLX3397 and eribulin, and blood levels of CSF1 will be obtained as
      outlined in section 14. To allow rapid accrual to phase Ib, and an earlier start to the phase
      II trial, patients will be enrolled in phase I with both hormone receptor positive and
      negative disease, and at any line of therapy assuming eligibility criteria are otherwise met.

      Dose limiting toxicity (DLT) will be defined as any treatment-related toxicity meeting the
      criteria below and occurring within the first 21 days of combination therapy. Patients must
      receive at least 14 days of PLX3397 and 2 doses of eribulin during the first cycle in order
      to be considered evaluable for DLT (unless the missed doses are due to a DLT).

      Patients in each cohort will be followed for at least 3 weeks (one full cycle) before opening
      accrual to the next dose level. If one patient in any cohort develops a DLT, an additional 3
      patients will be enrolled at that level. If no additional toxicities occur in the six
      patients, then this particular dose would be used for the phase II trial, and the next higher
      dose would be considered the MTD. A minimum of 12 and maximum of 24 patients will be enrolled
      in the phase I study. The phase II trial will not open until the last patient in the phase I
      study has been followed for at least 3 weeks.

      The phase II portion of this trial will evaluate PFS in patients with TNBC treated with
      PLX3397 and eribulin, using the dose of PLX3397 determined in the phase Ib study in a
      two-step design. Please see the statistical section for details regarding enrollment and
      statistical design. Treatment is preceded by a 5 to 7 day lead-in phase, in which patients
      will take PLX3397 alone daily. Patients with accessible tumor will undergo a core biopsy of
      tumor before the start of PLX3397 treatment, and then a fine needle aspiration or core biopsy
      will be performed on the day of or the day before the start of eribulin (day -1 to day 0).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose of PLX3397 given in combination with with standard dose eribulin in patients with metastatic breast cancer (Phase 1b)</measure>
    <time_frame>Estimated up to 24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with chemotherapy pre-treated triple negative metastatic breast cancer treated with PLX3397 in combination with eribulin who are progression free at 12 weeks (Phase 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluated at week 12 tumor assessment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum concentrations for the combination of PLX3397 and eribulin (Phase 1b)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of treatment (Phase 1b &amp; 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>AE and toxicity assessments (laboratory tests, physical exams &amp; history) on Days 1 and Day 8 of each cycle during treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune response (Phase 1b &amp; 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of drug combination including response rate and duration of response (Phase 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be assessed every 3 weeks and have CT scans every 6 weeks during treatment. Average participation is approximately 24 months.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eribulin in combination with PLX3397</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase Ib:
21 day treatment cycle: PLX3397 100-200 mg gelcaps, po daily &amp; Eribulin 1.4 mg/m2 IV day 1 and 8
Cohort 1: 600 mg/day
Cohort 2: 800 mg/day
Cohort 3: 1000 mg/day
Phase II:
Lead in period of 5-7 d with PLX3397 at MTD po qd (day -7/5 to day 0)
21 day cycles; Day 1:
Add eribulin 1.4 mg/m2 IV day 1 and 8
Continue PLX3397 at MTD po qd</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PLX3397</intervention_name>
    <description>Dosage Form: 100 mg or 200 mg capsules, Dosage: 400 - 1000 mg, oral administration</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eribulin in combination with PLX3397</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eribulin</intervention_name>
    <description>Dosage Form: 1 mg per 2 mL (0.5 mg per mL); Solution (clear, colorless, sterile, packaged in glass vial) Dosage: 1.4 mg/m2, 2-5 min IV, Day 1, 8 q21 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eribulin in combination with PLX3397</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Halaven</other_name>
    <other_name>E7389</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pathologically confirmed diagnosis of breast cancer with documented progressive
             disease.

          -  Patients with stable brain metastases are eligible for this trial.

          -  At least one prior chemotherapy regimen for metastatic breast cancer. Prior treatment
             must be discontinued at least 2 weeks before treatment start.

          -  Concomitant therapy with bisphosphonates is allowed.

          -  Stable dose coumadin anticoagulation is allowed, providing that anticoagulation can be
             safely held to an INR within normal range for the purpose of tumor biopsy. LMWH is the
             preferred method of anticoagulation.

          -  PT/INR and PTT within institutional normal limits within two weeks before initial
             biopsy.

          -  Measurable disease, as defined by RECIST guidelines or evaluable disease. Bone
             metastases must be evaluable.

          -  Disease amenable to core biopsy. Patients with pulmonary metastases as their only site
             of disease may enroll on this trial and will not undergo biopsy.

          -  For Phase I: patients with HER2 overexpressing disease must have been previously
             treated with trastuzumab. Patients with HER2 overexpressing disease are not eligible
             for the Phase II trial.

          -  Age eighteen years or older.

          -  ECOG performance status &lt;/= 2.

          -  Life expectancy of &gt;/= 12 weeks.

          -  Patients with &lt; grade 1 peripheral neuropathy are eligible for this trial.

          -  Adequate bone marrow reserve: ANC &gt;/= 1000, platelets &gt;/= 100,000.

          -  Adequate renal function: serum creatinine &lt;/= 1.5x upper limit of normal OR calculated
             creatinine clearance ≥ 50 ml/min.

          -  Sodium, potassium, and chloride levels within institutional normal limits.

          -  Adequate hepatic function: AST and ALT &lt;/= 2.5 x ULN, and total bilirubin &lt;/= 1.5x
             upper limit of normal. In patients with liver dysfunction due to hepatic metastases,
             AST and ALT are permitted to be &lt;/= 5 times the ULN.

          -  At baseline: EF ≥ 50%, no evidence of QT prolongation, no history of congenital long
             QT syndrome, and no use of drugs known to increase the risk of Torsades de Point -
             patients may be eligible for study if the drug can be changed to another agent with
             less risk (such as changing from citalopram to an alternate antidepressant).

          -  Able to take oral medications and maintain hydration.

          -  Ability to give written informed consent and willingness to comply with the
             requirements of the protocol

          -  Women of child-bearing potential must agree to use an effective method of birth
             control during treatment and for six months after receiving their last dose of study
             drug

        Specific inclusion criteria for Phase II

        • Patients enrolling on the phase II portion of this trial must have ER, PR and HER2
        negative disease defined as less than 10% staining for ER and PR, and HER2 not amplified by
        FISH, 0-1% by IHC, or 2+ by IHC and no evidence of amplification by FISH.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Treatment with another chemotherapy or hormonal therapy within the past 2 weeks.

          -  Treatment with trastuzumab, bevacizumab or other targeted therapies within the past 2
             weeks.

          -  Concurrent treatment with radiotherapy.

          -  Ongoing treatment with any other investigational therapy.

          -  Prior treatment with eribulin

          -  Severe, concurrent illness including congestive heart failure, significant cardiac
             disease and uncontrolled hypertension, that would likely prevent the patient from
             being able to comply with the study protocol.

          -  Inadequate bone marrow, renal, or hepatic function as defined above, or an active
             coagulopathy that precludes tissue biopsy.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women and women of child-bearing potential who are not using an
             effective method of birth control. Women of childbearing potential must undergo a
             serum pregnancy test within seven days of starting the study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hope S. Rugo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt-Ingram Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 11, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hope Rugo, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>breast</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>triple</keyword>
  <keyword>negative</keyword>
  <keyword>PLX</keyword>
  <keyword>Eribulin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

