<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01592214</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-0007</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN272201500007I</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>XF-73</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01592214</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Safety and Local Tolerability of Intranasal Gel Formulations of XF-73</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Two-Part Phase I Study to Establish and Compare the Safety and Local Tolerability of Two Nasal Formulations of XF-73 for Decolonization of Staphylococcus Aureus: A Previously Investigated 0.5 mg/g Viscosified Gel Formulation Versus a Modified Formulation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I, multi-center, clinical study of XF-73 to evaluate the local (nasal) safety
      and tolerability of a modified, thinner lower viscosity formulation of intranasal XF-73 in
      healthy male and female subjects. In addition, the potential for systemic absorption of XF-73
      in the modified, thinner lower viscosity and the previously investigated thicker, higher
      viscosity formulations and their decolonization efficacy in comparison to placebo will be
      evaluated. Both parts of the study will be double-blinded and Part 2 will also be
      placebo-controlled. Primary objective is to establish the safety and tolerability of two
      concentrations of a modified thinner, lower viscosity nasal formulation of XF-73 and to
      compare them to a previously investigated, thicker, higher viscosity formulation
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I, multi-center, clinical study of XF-73 to evaluate the local (nasal) safety
      and tolerability of a modified, thinner, lower viscosity formulation of intranasal XF-73 in
      healthy male and female subjects. In addition, the potential for systemic absorption of XF-73
      in the modified, thinner, lower viscosity and the previously investigated thicker, higher
      viscosity formulations and their decolonization efficacy in comparison to placebo will be
      evaluated. Both parts of the study will be double-blinded, and Part 2 will also be
      placebo-controlled. Study subjects will be healthy volunteers, male or female, aged 18 - 45
      years. The study will be conducted in two distinct parts. In Part 1 of the study 8 healthy
      male and female subjects, aged 18 to 45 years, will be in two groups of four per formulation
      will have a study duration of up to 36 days. All subjects will receive intranasal
      applications of 5,15-bis-[4-(3-Trimethylammonio-propyloxy)-phenyl]-porphyrin dichloride
      (XF-73). In Part 2 only, subjects will also need to be confirmed as persistent nasal SA
      carriers (n = 48). (Persistent SA carriage is defined by 3 separate, SA positive cultures
      from nasal swabs: the first taken at Pre-Screening no more than 12 weeks (84 days).
      Administration will last five days, being three times a day on Day 1, then twice a day
      thereafter. Primary objective is to establish the safety and tolerability of two
      concentrations of a modified thinner, lower viscosity nasal formulation of XF-73 and to
      compare them to a previously investigated, thicker, higher viscosity formulation. Secondary
      objectives are to establish whether there is any potential systemic exposure following
      administration of the two nasal formulations of XF-73 and to evaluate the anti-staphylococcal
      efficacy of two concentrations of a lower and one of a thicker, higher viscosity nasal
      formulation of XF-73.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The local (nasal and nasal passage) and systemic safety and tolerability of XF-73 following nasal administration in healthy male and female subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 8 (Part 1) and Day 1 through Day 14 (Part 2)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In the Part 2 of the study, anti-staphylococcal activity will be investigated, activity will be assessed as the presence or absence of SA and by quantification of the level of colonization</measure>
    <time_frame>Part 2: Enrollment, Day 1 through Day 6 and Day 14.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The efficacy of the modified formulation of XF-73 and of the previous formulation on nasal load of S. aureus after daily treatment with XF-73 for five days as compared to placebo (in Part 2 of the study only).</measure>
    <time_frame>Part 2: Enrollment, Day 1 through Day 6 and Day 14.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The pharmacokinetics (PK) of XF-73 following nasal administration of two concentrations of a modified formulation (in both parts of the study) and a single concentration of a previously investigated formulation (in Part 2 of the study).</measure>
    <time_frame>Part 1: 0 hr, at 15, 30 min, 1, 2, 4, 8, 12 hr after each dose. Part 2 within 15 min before 1st dose, 30, 240, 480 min after 1st dose. Day 3: 30 min after 1st dose; Day 5: within 15 min before 1st dose, 30, 240 min after.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Staphylococcal Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1 #2-XF-73 in 2% Klucel® gel, concentration 2.0 mg/g</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>4 subjects: 2.0 mg/g concentrations of a modified 2% Klucel® gel formulation of XF-73 intranasally to both nares twice in a single day in a volume of 0.3 mL/naris/dose and total daily dose of 2.4 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 #4-Placebo in 4% Klucel® gel, concentration 0 mg/g</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 subjects: a placebo in 4% Klucel® gel intranasally to both nares in a volume of 0.3 mL/naris/dose,3 doses 8 hours apart on Day 1 and 2 doses, 12 hours apart on Days 2 to 5. Total daily volume of 1.8 ml on Day 1 and 1.2 ml on Days 2 to 5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 # 3-XF-73 in 4% Klucel® gel, concentration 0.5 mg/g:</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 subjects: a modified 4% Klucel® gel formulation of XF-73 intranasally to both nares in a concentration of 0.5 mg/g and volume of 0.3 mL/naris/dose in, 3 doses 8 hours apart on Day 1 and 2 doses, 12 hours apart on Days 2 to 5. Total daily volume of 1.8 ml on Day 1 and 1.2 ml on Days 2 to 5; and total daily dose of 0.9 mg on Day 1 and 0.6 mg on Days 2 to 5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 #2- XF-73 in 2% Klucel® gel, concentration 2.0 mg/g</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 subjects; a modified 2% Klucel® gel formulation of XF-73 intranasally to both nares in a concentration of 2.0 mg/g and volume of 0.3 mL/naris/dose,3 doses 8 hours apart on Day 1 and 2 doses, 12 hours apart on Days 2 to 5. Total daily volume of 1.8 ml on Day 1 and 1.2 ml on Days 2 to 5; and total daily dose of 3.6 mg on Day 1 and 2.4 mg on Days 2 to 5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 #1- XF-73 in 2 % Klucel® gel, concentration 0.5 mg/g</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 subjects: a modified 2% Klucel® gel formulation of XF-73 intranasally to both nares in a concentration of 0.5 mg/g and volume of 0.3 mL/naris/dose, 3 doses 8 hours apart on Day 1 and 2 doses, 12 hours apart on Days 2 to 5. Total daily volume of 1.8 ml on Day 1 and 1.2 ml on Days 2 to 5; and total daily dose of 0.9 mg on Day 1 and 0.6 mg on Days 2 to 5.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1 #1-XF-73 in 2% Klucel® gel, concentration 0.5 mg/g:</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>4 subjects: 0.5 mg/g concentration of a modified 2% Klucel® gel formulation of XF-73 intranasally to both nares twice in a single day in a volume of 0.3 mL/naris/dose and total daily dose of 0.6 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo: 4% Klucel® gel formulation, concentration 0, total daily volume 1.8 ml, 3 doses 8 hours apart on Day 1 and 1.2 ml, 2 doses 12 hrs apart on Days 2 to 5.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 #4-Placebo in 4% Klucel® gel, concentration 0 mg/g</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>XF-73 in 2% Klucel gel</intervention_name>
    <description>XF-73 in a modified 2% Klucel® gel formulation: Part 1, #1: concentration 0.5 mg/g, twice a day in volume 0.3 mL/naris/dose, total dose 0.6 mg; Part 1, #2: 2.0 mg/g concentration, twice a day in volume 0.3 mL/naris/dose, total dose 2.4 mg; Part 2, #1: Concentration 0.5 mg/g, 3 doses 8 hours apart on Day 1, total volume 1.8 ml, total dose 0.9 mg, 2 doses 12 hours apart on Days 2-5, total volume 1.2 ml and total dose 0.6 mg ; Part 2, #2: 2.0 mg/g, 3 doses 8 hours apart on Day 1, total volume 1.8 ml, total dose 3.6 mg, 2 doses 12 hours apart on Days 2-5,total volume 1.2 ml and total dose 2.4 mg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1 #1-XF-73 in 2% Klucel® gel, concentration 0.5 mg/g:</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1 #2-XF-73 in 2% Klucel® gel, concentration 2.0 mg/g</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 #1- XF-73 in 2 % Klucel® gel, concentration 0.5 mg/g</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 #2- XF-73 in 2% Klucel® gel, concentration 2.0 mg/g</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>XF-73 in 4% Klucel gel</intervention_name>
    <description>XF-73 in a 4% Klucel® gel formulation: Part 2 #3: concentration of 0.5 mg/g and volume of 0.3 mL/naris/dose in 3 doses 8 hours apart on Day 1 and 2 doses, 12 hours apart on Days 2 to 5. Total daily volume of 1.8 ml on Day 1 and 1.2 ml on Days 2 to 5; and total daily dose of 0.9 mg on Day 1 and 0.6 mg on Days 2 to 5.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2 # 3-XF-73 in 4% Klucel® gel, concentration 0.5 mg/g:</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Normal, healthy male or female subjects aged between 18 and 45 years inclusive.

          2. For Part 2 only: Normal healthy subjects confirmed to be persistent SA carriers (NOTE:
             Persistent SA carriage is defined by 3 separate, SA (Staphylococcus aureus) positive
             cultures from nasal swabs: the first taken at Pre-Screening no more than 12 weeks (84
             days) prior to first dosing, a confirmatory swab taken at Screening at least 7 days
             after Pre-Screening and a final confirmation swab taken on Admission, a day before
             dosing and at least 7 days after screening. Subjects may be dosed with only two
             positive swabs while awaiting the result of the third swab obtained on Admission, but
             dosing will be discontinued in subjects whose Admission swab is found to be negative
             for SA.

          3. Subject must be healthy, in the opinion of the Investigator, as determined by medical
             history (MH), physical examination (PE), normal nasal examination, and vital signs
             (VS).

          4. Subject's 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) must be normal or abnormal not clinically
             significant as reported by the overreading cardiologist.

          5. Subject's clinical laboratory results at Screening must be within the reference range
             or expanded range.Subjects may undergo a repeat screening test of out-of-range
             analytes at the discretion of the investigator to confirm a plausible alternative
             explanation that will be indicated in the source documentation.

          6. Any subject having laboratory values outside of the reference range or expanded range
             at Day -1 but were within the reference or expended range at screening may be enrolled
             on study. Abnormal urine dipstick values for blood/hemoglobin, nitrite, and leukocyte
             esterase will not be exclusionary if a microscopic examination of the urine on the
             same sample or the most recent sample obtained prior to dosing is within the reference
             or expanded range. Laboratory values outside the reference or expanded range will be
             assigned to toxicity grade.

          7. Subjects who are able and willing to provide written informed consent to participate
             in the study.

          8. Subject agrees to comply with all study requirements.

          9. All female subjects of childbearing potential must have a negative serum and urine
             pregnancy test at Screening and Admission respectively.

         10. Subjects who have a body mass index (BMI) &gt;/= 18.5 kg/m^2 and &lt;/= 35 kg/m^2.

         11. Subject agrees not to participate in another clinical trial at any time during the
             study period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Female subjects who are pregnant or who are lactating.

          2. Heterosexually active females of child-bearing potential, defined as being
             physiologically capable of becoming pregnant, unless they agree to use two of the
             following acceptable methods of contraception throughout their participation in the
             study and for at least 12 weeks after the final dose: (a) established use of oral,
             injected or implanted hormonal contraception, (b) intrauterine Device (IUD or Coil),
             (c) a female barrier method (diaphragm or cervical/vault cap) and/or (d) condom plus
             spermicidal cream/gel. Women who are not sexually active (abstinent) but become active
             must use two of the listed contraceptive methods.

          3. Heterosexually active males unless they agree to use two concomitant acceptable
             methods of contraception throughout their participation in the study and for at least
             12 weeks after receiving their final dose of study medication (examples include:
             vasectomy combined with latex condom with spermicide, latex condom with spermicide
             combined with a female partner who practices an acceptable method of contraception as
             indicated above); Men who are not sexually active (abstinent) but become active must
             use two of the listed contraceptive methods. Subjects who currently have or have had
             any acute illness within the past two weeks.

          4. Subjects who currently have or have had within the past two weeks a poorly controlled
             chronic illness(anemia, thrombocytopenia, or coagulation disorders), cancer,
             infection, or any other clinically significant disorder.

          5. Subjects who currently have or have had an autoimmune disease.

          6. Subjects who have had within the past two weeks a symptomatic upper respiratory tract
             infection, nasopharyngitis, influenza or condition involving increase in nasal
             secretion such as seasonal or chronic, allergic rhinitis. Additionally, any subject
             with history of atopy/allergies within the past 30 days will be excluded.

          7. Subjects who have had been diagnosed with a concussion within the past two years.

          8. Subjects with a history of serious psychiatric condition (depression, bipolar
             disorder, schizophrenia, suicidal ideation, or suicide attempts) or receiving two
             concomitant medications for the treatment of a psychiatric disorder or hospitalized
             for the treatment of a serious psychiatric disorder within six months of participation
             in the study.

          9. Subjects with known skin photosensitivity.

         10. Subjects with a personal or family history of porphyria.

         11. Subjects with any open wound, lesion, inflammation, erythema, or infection affecting
             the nostrils, nose, upper lip, and area of skin close to the nose, including herpes
             simplex lesions and discoid lupus.

         12. Subjects with a history of abnormal bleeding, bruising, frequent nosebleeds, or the
             diagnosis of von Willebrand disease.

         13. Subjects with nasal polyps or significant anatomical nasal abnormality. Patients with
             deviated septa will be allowed in the study, provided the principal investigator does
             not deem a deviation to be of significant medical consequence. An ENT(Ear, Nose and
             Throat) specialist will be available for consult as needed.

         14. Subjects with a history of nasal surgery, including cauterization, in the last 6
             months.

         15. Subjects with a history of multiple episodes [&gt;3] of epistaxis within the 12 months
             prior to screening.

         16. Subjects with in situ nasal jewelry or open nasal piercings.

         17. Subjects with a known clinically significant history of atopy or hypersensitivity to
             any drug or latex or to ingredients of the nasal gel (such as benzalkonium chloride or
             other quaternary ammonium disinfectants) or to drugs related to XF-73.

         18. Subjects known to have dermal sensitivity to chlorhexidine gluconate (CHG).

         19. Subjects who have smoked within the month prior to screening.

         20. Subjects who have been treated with or have taken any prescribed or over-the-counter
             medication daily for the last 14 days, with the exception of hormonal contraceptives
             or hormone replacement therapy.

         21. Subjects who have taken or used topical or systemic antibiotics within the month prior
             to screening.

         22. Subjects who have received an immunization within 30 days prior to screening.

         23. Subjects with a history of drug or alcohol abuse in the last 12 months or who have a
             positive urine drug test for substances of abuse (amphetamines, barbiturates,
             benzodiazepines, cannabinoids, cocaine metabolites, opiates, phencyclidine [PCP]) or
             alcohol.

         24. Subjects who are known to have serum hepatitis, or who are carriers of the hepatitis B
             surface antigen(HBsAg) or hepatitis C (HCV) antibody, or who have a positive result to
             the test for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibodies.

         25. Subjects who have participated in a drug or vaccine clinical trial within the last
             month.

         26. Subjects who have been exposed to XF-73 as part of a previous clinical trial.

         27. Presence of any other condition or laboratory result that, in the opinion of the
             investigator would jeopardize the safety or rights of a subject participating in the
             trial or would render the subject unable to comply with the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Anaheim Clinical Trials - Phase I Clinical Pharmacology Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Anaheim</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92801-2417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case Western Reserve University - Case Medical Center - Infectious Disease &amp; HIV Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106-1716</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 7, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 1, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 1, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Staphylococcus aureus, nasal decolonization, XF-73, gel formulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Staphylococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Benzocaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

