<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01596881</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OHSU IRB #00008179-MS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01596881</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Optical Coherence Tomography to Capture Retinal Microvascular Changes Associated With Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>OCT in MS</acronym>
  <official_title>Using OCT to Capture Retinal Microvascular Changes Associated With MS</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oregon Health and Science University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recent studies have shown that people with multiple sclerosis (MS) who also have diseases
      related to vascular health such as high cholesterol, high blood pressure, diabetes,
      cardiovascular disease, and others, may end up more disabled than people with MS who don't
      have those diseases. This has led to a growing interest in the role of vascular diseases in
      MS since they may provide another avenue of MS treatment. Some also think that vascular
      disease may even be a cause of MS. The back of the eye, the retina, is well-suited to
      studying vascular diseases as blood vessels can be seen even on routine examination of the
      eye by eye doctors. These specialists are used to seeing changes in retinal blood vessels due
      to diseases known to affect the eyes such as glaucoma and diabetes. Sophisticated techniques
      for examining the retina allow for not only visualization of blood vessels, but the rate of
      blood flow through the blood vessels as well. These blood flow changes are thought to come
      before changes in what the blood vessels look like, and so may be able to detect problems
      even earlier than routine examination of the retina by eye doctors. Retinal blood flow has
      never been carefully studied in MS. Given that MS affects the retina due to the late effects
      of inflammation of the optic nerve, or optic neuritis, the investigators expect to see
      altered blood flow in the retinal blood vessels of people with MS compared to healthy control
      subjects. If so, the investigators can then use retinal blood flow as a way to measure
      therapies that target vascular diseases in the MS population and determine if those therapies
      can alter the course of disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background data including age, sex, medical history, and neurologic history and status will
      be gathered prior to the study/OCT testing visit. At the single study/testing visit, subjects
      will have their blood pressure and intraocular pressure checked (using numbing drops that
      last 15-20 minutes), undergo vision testing and then have their eyes dilated with standard
      dilating drops. They will then undergo optical coherence tomography testing to determine the
      blood flow of the retinal blood vessels and to take other measurements of the back of the eye
      including thicknesses of the nervous tissue elements of the retina.

      OCT Procedure: The subject will be seated and have their head positioned on a chin rest. They
      will be asked to look at a target (a lighted spot) while a beam of light scans the front part
      of the eye. The light is infrared and will not be visible or cause any sensation. A cotton
      tip swab may be used to help hold the eyelid open temporarily if necessary.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 8, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 8, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with MS who also have reduced blood flow in the retina and/or changes in the blood flow to the retina compared to healthy subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with MS who have different blood flow response than healthy subjects to visually stimulating patterns.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">101</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multiple Sclerosis Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Physician-confirmed diagnosis of multiple sclerosis. Any subtype is acceptable. For example, relapsing-remitting, secondary progressive, primary progressive</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Normal Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>Volunteers with healthy eyes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study will enroll both males and females and include all ethnic and racial groups
        through clinical practices. The study will enroll subjects from 18 to 70 years of age.
        Participants older than 70 years are excluded as cooperation with tests may be difficult.
        For similar reasons, participants who have MS and vision worse than 20/200 are excluded.
        The study also excludes those with any eye disease that would interfere with of assessment
        of MS. Otherwise people with any health status are eligible for enrollment. Two groups of
        participants are recruited: people with healthy, normal eyes and people with any type of
        MS.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (Subjects with MS):

          -  Physician-confirmed diagnosis of MS (any subtype acceptable, e.g. relapsing-
             remitting, secondary progressive, primary progressive)

          -  Age 18-70 years old

          -  Able to comply with study procedures

          -  Corrected visual acuity at least 20/200 in either eye

        Inclusion Criteria (Healthy subjects):

          -  Age 18-70 years old

          -  Able to comply with study procedures

          -  Able to maintain stable fixation for OCT imaging

          -  Corrected visual acuity of at least 20/40 in either eye

        Exclusion Criteria (all participants):

          -  Intravenous or oral steroids in the prior 30 days

          -  Evidence on ophthalmological exam within the last year of other ocular diseases or
             pathology that would confound the assessment of MS and optic nerve head (e.g.
             glaucoma, diabetic or hypertensive retinal disease, amblyopia, etc.)

          -  Previous intraocular surgery except for uncomplicated cataract surgery

          -  Inability to maintain stable fixation for OCT imaging

          -  Refractive error greater than +3 or -7 diopters

          -  MS exacerbation in the prior 60 days.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rebecca Spain, MD, MSPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon Health &amp; Science Universtiy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 11, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Huang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Rebecca Spain, MD, MSPH, Assistant Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood flow</keyword>
  <keyword>Optical Coherence Tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>Imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

