<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01594177</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GBG 70</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2011-004704-38</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01594177</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dual Blockage With Afatinib and Trastuzumab as Neoadjuvant Treatment for Patients With Locally Advanced or Operable Breast Cancer Receiving Taxane-anthracycline Containing Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>DAFNE</acronym>
  <official_title>Dual Blockage With Afatinib and Trastuzumab as Neoadjuvant Treatment for Patients With Locally Advanced or Operable Breast Cancer Receiving Taxane-anthracycline Containing Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>German Breast Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boehringer Ingelheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>German Breast Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Anthracycline/taxane based combination chemotherapy of at least 18 weeks represents the
      standard of care in the neoadjuvant setting. In HER2 positive disease trastuzumab is given
      simultaneously. Neoadjuvant anthracycline-taxane-based chemotherapy given simul-taneously
      with trastuzumab achieves a pCR rate of approx. 40%. Recent data showed that a double
      blockade of the HER2 receptor (e.g. trastuzumab + lapatinib; trastuzumab + pertuzumab) given
      together with a few cycles of chemotherapy can increase the pCR rate by approximately 20%. So
      far, there is uncertainty, if afatinib (BIBW 2992), an irreversible HER family blocker can
      lead to an even more complete blockade of the HER2 pathway when given in combination with
      trastuzumab. The neoadjuvant setting provides the unique opportunity to assess precisely and
      at short term the effect of systemic treatment by assessing the pCR at surgery. It also
      allows treating patients with HER2 positive breast cancer before surgery without standard
      trastuzumab treatment, as, according to current guideline, trastuzumab can also be given
      sequentially after surgery. The aim of the study is to show that chemotherapy + trastuzumab +
      afatinib can achieve significant pCR rates.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary objectives:

      To compare the pathological complete response (pCR = ypT0/is ypN0) rates of neoadjuvant
      treatment of afatinib in combination with weekly paclitaxel + trastuzumab followed by
      epirubicin/ cyclophosphamide/ trastuzumab in patients with HER2-positive primary breast
      cancer.

      Secondary objectives:

      To determine the rates of ypT0 ypN0; ypT0; ypT0/is; ypN0; and regression grades according to
      Sinn.

      To determine the response rates of the breast tumor and axillary nodes by physical
      examination and imaging tests (sonography, mammography, or MRI) after 6 weeks of the 2
      anti-HER2 agents alone and at surgery.

      To determine the breast and axilla conservation rate after treatment. To assess the toxicity
      and compliance. To correlate skin toxicity and diarrhoea with pCR. To examine and compare
      pre-specified molecular markers such as EGFR, HER2, HER3, HER4, TGFß, EGF, AREG, HBEGF, BTC,
      EPIGEN, EREG, NRG1, NRG2, neuroglycan, tomoregulin, NRG4 and NRG3K-RAS, MET, IGF1R, IRS1,
      PTEN, FGFR1, FGFR2, FGFR3, AXL, RET, and PDGFR; EGFR signature, Ki67, p95HER2, and PI3K
      mutation before start of afatinib+trastuzumab, before and after chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathological Complete Response</measure>
    <time_frame>30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the pathological complete response (pCR = ypT0/is ypN0) rates of neoadjuvant treatment of afatinib in combination with weekly paclitaxel + trastuzumab followed by epirubicin/ cyclophosphamide/ trastuzumab in patients with HER2-positive primary breast cancer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathological Complete Response</measure>
    <time_frame>30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the rates of ypT0 ypN0; ypT0; ypT0/is; ypN0; and regression grades according to Sinn.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rate by Physical Examination and Imaging Tests</measure>
    <time_frame>30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the response rates of the breast tumor and axillary nodes by physical examination and imaging tests (sonography, mammography, or MRI) after 6 weeks of the 2 anti-HER2 agents alone and at surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Conservation Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the breast and axilla conservation rate after treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with (Serious) Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of number and grading of (serious) adverse events during the different treatment phases.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Skin Toxicity and Diarrhea as (Serious) Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability and Pathological Complete Response</measure>
    <time_frame>30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of number and grading of skin toxicity and diarrhea as (serious) adverse events in correlation with pCR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Translational Research</measure>
    <time_frame>30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To examine and compare pre-specified molecular markers such as EGFR, HER2, HER3, HER4, TGFß, EGF, AREG, HBEGF, BTC, EPIGEN, EREG, NRG1, NRG2, neuroglycan, tomoregulin, NRG4 and NRG3K-RAS, MET, IGF1R, IRS1, PTEN, FGFR1, FGFR2, FGFR3, AXL, RET, and PDGFR; EGFR signature, Ki67, p95HER2, and PI3K mutation before start of afatinib+trastuzumab, before and after chemotherapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Unilateral HER2 Positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Afatinib-Trastuzumab (6 weeks) followed by Afatinib*-Paclitaxel-Trastuzumab (12 weeks) followed by Epirubicin-Cyclophosphamide-Trastuzumab (12 weeks). *only 11 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Afatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>20 mg daily for 17 weeks (first two weeks every second day).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trastuzumab</intervention_name>
    <description>First cycle: loading dose 8 mg/kg (day 1 q day 22), thereafter maintenance dose for 9 cycles: 6 mg/kg (day 1 q day 22).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HERCEPTIN</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>80 mg/m² i.v. given weekly on day 1 q day 8 for 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epirubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>90 mg/m² i.v. given on day 1 q day 22 for 4 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>600 mg/m² i.v. given on day 1 q day 22 for 4 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent for all study procedures according to local regulatory
             requirements prior to beginning of specific protocol procedures.

          2. Complete baseline documentation must be sent to GBG Forschungs GmbH.

          3. Unilateral primary carcinoma of the breast, confirmed histologically by core biopsy.
             Fine-needle aspiration is not sufficient. Incisional biopsy is not allowed. Tumor
             lesion in the breast with a sonographical size of ≥ 2 cm in maximum diameter. The
             lesion has to be measurable in two dimensions, preferably by sonography. In case of
             inflammatory disease, the extent of inflammation can be used as measurable lesion.

          4. Operable or locally advanced or inflammatory breast cancer (cT2 - cT4a-d). In patients
             with multifocal or multicentric breast cancer, the largest lesion should be measured.

          5. Centrally confirmed positive HER2 status detected on core biopsy. HER2-positive is
             defined as IHC 3+ by a validated test method or FISH/SISH ratio &gt; 2.0. Formalin-fixed,
             paraffin-embedded (FFPE) breast tissue from core biopsy has therefore to be sent to
             the Department of Pathology at the Charité, Berlin, prior to regsitration.

          6. Centrally confirmed hormone receptor status (ER/PgR).

          7. Age ≥ 18 years.

          8. Karnofsky Performance status ≥ 80%.

          9. Normal cardiac function must be confirmed by ECG and cardiac ultrasound (LVEF or
             shortening fraction) within 3 months prior to registration. Results must be above 55%.

         10. Laboratory requirements:

             Hematology

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 2.0 x 109/L and

               -  Platelets ≥ 100 x 109/L and

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 10 g/dL (≥ 6.2 mmol/L) Hepatic function

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5x UNL and

               -  ASAT (SGOT) and ALAT (SGPT) ≤ 1.5x UNL and

               -  Alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5x UNL. Renal function

               -  Creatinine ≤ 175 µmol/L (2 mg/dL) &lt; 1.5x UNL.

         11. Negative pregnancy test (urine or serum) within 14 days prior to registration for all
             women of childbearing potential.

         12. Complete staging work-up within 3 months prior to registration. All patients must have
             bilateral mammography, breast ultrasound (≤ 21 days), breast MRI (optional), chest
             X-ray (PA and lateral), abdominal ultrasound or CT scan or MRI, and bone scan done. In
             case of positive bone scan, bone X-ray is mandatory. Other tests may be performed as
             clinically indicated.

         13. Patients must be available and compliant for treatment and follow-up. Patients
             registered on this trial must be treated at the participating or at a cooperating
             centre.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Bilateral breast cancer.

          2. Prior chemotherapy for any malignancy.

          3. Prior radiation therapy for breast cancer.

          4. Pregnant or lactating patients. Patients of childbearing potential must implement
             adequate non-hormonal contraceptive measures (barrier methods, intrauterine
             contraceptive devices, sterilisation) during study treatment.

          5. Inadequate general condition (not fit for anthracycline-taxane based chemotherapy) as
             per investigator´s assessment.

          6. Previous malignant disease with a disease-free period of less than 5 years (except CIS
             of the cervix and non-melanomatous skin cancer).

          7. Known or pre-existing interstitial lung disease.

          8. Known or suspected congestive heart failure (NYHA &gt; I) or coronary heart disease,
             angina pectoris requiring antianginal medication, previous history of myocardial
             infarction, evidence of transmural infarction on ECG, uncontrolled or poorly
             controlled arterial hypertension (i.e. BP &gt; 160/90 mm Hg under treatment with two
             antihypertensive drugs), rhythm abnormalities requiring permanent treatment,
             clinically significant valvular heart disease.

          9. History of significant neurological or psychiatric disorders including psychotic
             disorders, dementia or seizures that would prohibit the understanding and giving of
             informed consent.

         10. Chronic-inflammatory bowel diseases.

         11. Pre-existing motor or sensory neuropathy of a severity grade ≥ 2 by NCI-CTCAE
             criteria.

         12. No evidence or history of infection (including hepatitis B, C or HIV).

         13. Known hypersensitivity reaction to one of the investigational compounds or
             incorporated substances used in this protocol.

         14. Definite contraindications for the use of corticosteroids except inhalative
             corticoids.

         15. Concurrent treatment with:

               -  chronic corticosteroids unless initiated &gt; 6 months prior to study entry and at
                  low dose (≤ 10 mg methylprednisolone or equivalent).

               -  sex hormones. Prior treatment must be stopped before study entry.

               -  other experimental drugs or any other anti-cancer therapy.

         16. Participation in another clinical trial with any investigational, not marketed drug
             within 30 days prior to study entry.

         17. Male patients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claus A Hanusch, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rotkreuzklinikum München, 80634 München, Rotkreuzplatz 8</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rotkreuzklinikum München</name>
      <address>
        <city>München</city>
        <zip>80634</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 8, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 13, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>DAFNE</keyword>
  <keyword>GBG 70</keyword>
  <keyword>GBG</keyword>
  <keyword>German Breast Group</keyword>
  <keyword>GBG Forschungs GmbH</keyword>
  <keyword>Afatinib</keyword>
  <keyword>neo-adjuvant</keyword>
  <keyword>HER-2 positive breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>BIBW 2992</keyword>
  <keyword>1200.159</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Taxane</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epirubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

