<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02891252</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SJ-495</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02891252</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized Investigation of Thyroid Operation as Day Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Investigation of Thyroid Operation as Day Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Zealand University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Zealand University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      hemithyroidectomy as a outpatient procedure is performed in some countries, it has never been
      done a RCT whether it is feasible
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Many surgical procedures, which previously resulted in days to week's hospital admissions,
      are now done as outpatient procedures. This is the result of better surgical and
      anaesthesiology techniques as well as the economic incentive.

      Examples from another surgical fields are cholecystectomy and further back in oto-rhino-
      laryngology (ORL) also tonsillectomy.

      Hemithyriodectomy as an outpatient procedure is becoming increasingly popular and is already
      applied in some countries. However many European countries is continuing the procedure with
      hospital admission post-operatively (inpatient surgery), due to risk of complications. In
      Denmark hemithyroidectomy is currently done with at least one night hospital admission for
      observation of above mentioned . At the ORL department at Køge hospital it is annually
      performed approximately 200 hemithyroidectomies. It is a common procedure and the number of
      procedures yearly is increasing. Complications to hemithyroidectomy include postoperative
      haemorrhage, damage to the recurrent laryngeal nerve, hypothyroidism and infection and veryn
      rarely hypocalcaemia. With sufficient patient information, the above-mentioned complications
      can be managed in an outpatient setting. Postoperative haemorrhage is the most serious
      complication and thyroid surgery is unique in outpatient setting, considering the risk of
      cervical haemorrhage which secondary can lead to respiratory failure due to tracheal
      compression and laryngeal oedema in a rapid sequence. Incidence of haemorrhage after thyroid
      surgery varies from 0.19 % to 2.8 % of which most bleedings occur within six hours
      postoperatively. There are two different approaches in the event of post- operative
      haemorrhage; acute decompression bedside and acute re-operation.

      Acute decompression is reserved for respiratory failures. Eligibility criteria for who may
      undergo outpatient thyroid surgery have been debated in the literature. No consensus has been
      reached for these criteria. For now, there is consensus that some patients (high risk of
      bleeding) will require inpatient procedure, and in carefully selected groups of patients
      outpatient thyroid surgery is already performed, as the inclusion criteria below. Outpatient
      hemithyroidectomy has shown low number of complications in retrospective studies as well as
      high patient acceptance and economical advantage in recent prospective and retrospective
      studies studies. However, recent national and international studies recommend against
      outpatient procedure, mainly due to the risk of late cervical haemorrhage. It is therefore
      important to continue to investigate whether hemithyroidectomyis feasible as an outpatient
      procedure, especially considering patient safety and acceptance. This will be done in a
      randomized controlled trial where half of the patients are allocated to outpatient procedure
      and the other half to inpatient procedure. The aim is non-inferiority comparing the two
      above-mentioned procedures. As far as the authors know, no previous RCT has been done or
      published with this purpose.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients that are converted to inpatient and/or re- admitted within 24h are under 20% in the outpatient group</measure>
    <time_frame>24 h</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient acceptance to outpatient procedure from patient satisfactory questionnaire (Appendix 1).</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in postoperative haemorrhage</measure>
    <time_frame>24 h</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in mean level of NRS pain scores at rest based on measurements at 2h and 20h on POD0 and at 8h and 20 h on POD 1.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 h</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in mean level of NRS pain scores during swallowing of saliva based on measurements at 2h and 20h on POD0 and at 8h and 20 h on POD 1.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 h</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in mean levels of NRS nausea at 2h, 20h (POD 0) and at 8h and 20h (POD1)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 h</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in NRS rated quality of sleep and level of tiredness at 8h on POD1</measure>
    <time_frame>24 h</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">86</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemithyroidectomy</condition>
  <condition>Outpatient</condition>
  <condition>Hemmorhage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>outpatient</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>outpatient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>inpatient</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>inpatient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>outpatient procedure</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>outpatient</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The hospitals normal outpatient criteria (ASA II or I), adult person to stay

        with patient on night of surgery) Euthyroid Normal function of vocal cords preoperatively
        Lives within a 30 km radius or within 45 minutes away with ambulance, from the hospital
        Speaks Danish

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Suspected malignancy Previous thyroid or major neck surgery Intrathoracic thyroid gland
        Former treatment with radioactive iodine Anticoagulation treatment except ASA and ADP
        inhibitors
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexander Nygren, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+4522955265</phone>
    <email>alexander.nygren@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Preben Homoe, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+4547329609</phone>
    <email>prho@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Copenhagen University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Køge</city>
        <zip>4200</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexander Nygren, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+4522955265</phone>
      <email>alexander.nygren@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 1, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 7, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 1, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 1, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>v</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

