<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02892721</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RD16/055</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02892721</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Performance and Evaluation for CT Colonography Screening</brief_title>
  <acronym>PERFECTS</acronym>
  <official_title>Performance and Evaluation for CT Colonography Screening</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>London North West Healthcare NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University College London Hospitals</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>London North West Healthcare NHS Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer (CRC) is an important United Kingdom healthcare issue affecting 1 in 20
      individuals, half of whom will die from the disease. Late presentation of CRC has a poor
      prognosis, whereas excellent cure rates (&gt;95%) are seen in those who present early. Accurate
      and early diagnosis of CRC is therefore crucial. In most patients this is achieved via
      colonoscopy, a camera test which is widely available and allows tissue samples to be taken of
      any abnormalities seen during the procedure. However, a non-invasive alternative is Computed
      Tomography Colonography (CTC) which uses X-rays to produce images of the large bowel which
      are then interpreted by Radiologists. CTC has high sensitivity for the diagnosis of CRC
      (comparable to colonoscopy) and the cancer precursor - adenomatous polyps.

      Unlike colonoscopy, however, there is no accreditation process for CTC and there is no
      infrastructure to ensure that all reporting Radiologists are able to do so adequately and, as
      a result, there is a wide range of diagnostic accuracy. There are no universally-accepted
      standards to monitor quality or assess diagnostic performance, partly because we do not know
      what the quality markers are and there is currently no system to quantify them. Overall, this
      contributes to low cancer detection rates, missed cancers and inequity for patients across
      the National Health Service (NHS).

      This study aims to assess the impact of a structured training programme with assessment and
      feedback on NHS radiologist performance. If the impact is positive and results in
      significantly improved performance, then such a scheme could be adopted into an accreditation
      programme for CTC in the English Bowel Cancer Screening Programme (BCSP).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CT Colonography is a test which can can detect early cancer accurately, however, unlike
      colonoscopy (or mammography in breast cancer screening) there is currently no formalised
      program to help ensure Radiologists interpret CTC accurately. Colonoscopists are highly
      regulated, must be accredited and have ongoing quality assurance metrics, based on evidence
      linking these to clinical outcomes. Conversely, for CTC in the United Kingdom, there is no
      accreditation process, little regulatory oversight and no universally-accepted metrics to
      monitor quality or diagnostic performance.

      Radiologists who interpret CTC images are often inexperienced; one-third have interpreted
      &lt;300 cases in total and 20% report &lt;100 cases per annum (the minimum recommendation).
      Futhermore, in clinical practice across the NHS Bowel Cancer Screening Programme (NHS BCSP)
      CTC may have up to a 50% lower cancer and polyp detection rate than colonoscopy. Missed
      abnormalities at CTC are likely to underpin this difference, as centres with highly
      experienced radiologists (&gt;1000 cases) using 3-dimensional interpretation have significantly
      higher detection rates.

      There is a Quality Assurance (QA) framework for the NHS BCSP (with an overseeing QA Committee
      for Radiology) but recommendations are largely based on opinion rather than evidence and any
      radiologist can report CTC, without accreditation; a fact which our patient representatives
      find extremely disappointing.

      Prior to wide-scale implementation of a possible accreditation programme and to justify both
      financial and human resource, Public Health England and the British Society of
      Gastrointestinal and Abdominal Radiologists have mandated that such a program is
      scientifically proven to improve Radiologist performance. Consequently, this project will
      investigate training and assessment methods to improve diagnostic accuracy and elucidate the
      factors associated with higher Radiologist sensitivity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in sensitivity between arms</measure>
    <time_frame>One month after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in sensitivity between intervention and control groups for detection of colorectal cancer / polyps on CT colonography at the 1 month post-intervention test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in sensitivity between intervention and controls for colorectal cancer/ polyps at the 12 month post-training test set (i.e. to test longer-term durability of one-off training supplemented by individualized feedback).</measure>
    <time_frame>Twelve months after intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in specificity between intervention and controls at 1 month.</measure>
    <time_frame>One month after intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in specificity between intervention and controls at 12 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>Twelve months after intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in sensitivity between intervention and controls at 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months after intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in specificity between intervention and controls at 6 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months after intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in raw score between the control and intervention arms on the knowledge questions as compared to true answers.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month after intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between interpretation time and diagnostic performance of radiologists on all test sets.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after intervention and after final test set.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characteristics of radiologists performing well versus those that do not.</measure>
    <time_frame>After the final test set at 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">106</enrollment>
  <condition>Colonic Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will not receive the one-day training course or access to the online educational module. Test sets will be administered in the same manner as for the intervention group, but the control group will not receive any feedback on performance during the 12 month assessment phase. Feedback on test performance will only be provided after the 12 month period has ended.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Training with feedback</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>See intervention description</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Training with feedback</intervention_name>
    <description>One-day workshop of face to face training, comprising a mixture of theory and real-world CTC cases. Radiologists will complete four interpretation assessments lasting 2 to 3 hours: one set of 10 CTC cases immediately prior to training and a further test set of 10 immediately after, with tests repeated at 6 and 12 months (using different CTC cases for each set). Radiologists will be asked to identify colorectal cancer and polyps on the scans and complete an online answer form, including questions regarding diagnostic confidence, site of abnormality and management.
The intervention group will receive online, confidential, individualised feedback after each test, which will include a case by case breakdown of their performance with explanatory answers and learning points.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training with feedback</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  National Health Service (NHS) Consultant Radiologists in the UK who currently
             routinely report CT colonography scans as part of the NHS Bowel Cancer Screening
             Programme.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Radiologists who are not consultants and are not part of Bowel Cancer Screening
             Programme at the start of the study.

        This study is limited to NHS staff and does not involve any patients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pickhardt PJ, Hassan C, Halligan S, Marmo R. Colorectal cancer: CT colonography and colonoscopy for detection--systematic review and meta-analysis. Radiology. 2011 May;259(2):393-405. doi: 10.1148/radiol.11101887. Epub 2011 Mar 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21415247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pickhardt PJ, Choi JR, Hwang I, Butler JA, Puckett ML, Hildebrandt HA, Wong RK, Nugent PA, Mysliwiec PA, Schindler WR. Computed tomographic virtual colonoscopy to screen for colorectal neoplasia in asymptomatic adults. N Engl J Med. 2003 Dec 4;349(23):2191-200. Epub 2003 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>14657426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson CD, Chen MH, Toledano AY, Heiken JP, Dachman A, Kuo MD, Menias CO, Siewert B, Cheema JI, Obregon RG, Fidler JL, Zimmerman P, Horton KM, Coakley K, Iyer RB, Hara AK, Halvorsen RA Jr, Casola G, Yee J, Herman BA, Burgart LJ, Limburg PJ. Accuracy of CT colonography for detection of large adenomas and cancers. N Engl J Med. 2008 Sep 18;359(12):1207-17. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0800996. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2008 Dec 25;359(26):2853.</citation>
    <PMID>18799557</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atkin W, Dadswell E, Wooldrage K, Kralj-Hans I, von Wagner C, Edwards R, Yao G, Kay C, Burling D, Faiz O, Teare J, Lilford RJ, Morton D, Wardle J, Halligan S; SIGGAR investigators. Computed tomographic colonography versus colonoscopy for investigation of patients with symptoms suggestive of colorectal cancer (SIGGAR): a multicentre randomised trial. Lancet. 2013 Apr 6;381(9873):1194-202. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)62186-2. Epub 2013 Feb 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23414650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stoop EM, de Haan MC, de Wijkerslooth TR, Bossuyt PM, van Ballegooijen M, Nio CY, van de Vijver MJ, Biermann K, Thomeer M, van Leerdam ME, Fockens P, Stoker J, Kuipers EJ, Dekker E. Participation and yield of colonoscopy versus non-cathartic CT colonography in population-based screening for colorectal cancer: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol. 2012 Jan;13(1):55-64. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(11)70283-2. Epub 2011 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22088831</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plumb AA, Halligan S, Taylor SA, Burling D, Nickerson C, Patnick J. CT colonography in the English Bowel Cancer Screening Programme: national survey of current practice. Clin Radiol. 2013 May;68(5):479-87. doi: 10.1016/j.crad.2012.10.018. Epub 2012 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23245277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plumb AA, Halligan S, Nickerson C, Bassett P, Goddard AF, Taylor SA, Patnick J, Burling D. Use of CT colonography in the English Bowel Cancer Screening Programme. Gut. 2014 Jun;63(6):964-73. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2013-304697. Epub 2013 Aug 16.</citation>
    <PMID>23955527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCoubrie P. Metrics in medical education. Ulster Med J. 2010 May;79(2):52-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21116419</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Halligan S, Altman DG, Mallett S, Taylor SA, Burling D, Roddie M, Honeyfield L, McQuillan J, Amin H, Dehmeshki J. Computed tomographic colonography: assessment of radiologist performance with and without computer-aided detection. Gastroenterology. 2006 Dec;131(6):1690-9. Epub 2006 Oct 1.</citation>
    <PMID>17087934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 2, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 8, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 2, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 2, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CT Colonography</keyword>
  <keyword>Virtual colonoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Colon cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Training</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Anonymised participant data will be included in the research analysis.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

