<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02899936</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201607068</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02899936</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Death to Onchocerciasis and Lymphatic Filariasis (DOLF) Triple Drug Therapy for Lymphatic Filariasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Community Based Safety Study of 2-drug (Diethylcarbamazine and Albendazole) Versus 3-drug (Ivermectin, Diethylcarbamazine and Albendazole) Therapy for Lymphatic Filariasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Case Western Reserve University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Indian Council of Medical Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The DOLF Triple Drug Therapy for Lymphatic Filariasis study will determine the frequency,
      type and severity of adverse events following triple-drug therapy (IVM+DEC+ALB, IDA) compared
      to the standard two-drug treatment (DEC+ALB, DA) in infected and uninfected individuals in a
      community in 5 different countries. The objective is to acquire safety, efficacy, and
      acceptability data to assess the safety and acceptability of the IDA drug combination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In 2000, the World Health Organization (WHO) launched the Global Programme to Eliminate
      Lymphatic Filariasis (GPELF) to eliminate lymphatic filariasis as a public health problem by
      2020. To interrupt transmission, WHO recommends therapy using combinations of two medicines
      delivered to entire at-risk populations through a strategy known as mass drug administration.
      Ivermectin (IVM) and albendazole (ALB) are administered in areas where onchocerciasis is
      co-endemic; diethylcarbamazine (DEC) and albendazole (ALB) are administered in areas where
      onchocerciasis is not co-endemic.

      Results of a pilot study in Papua New Guinea suggest that triple drug therapy (ivermectin,
      diethylcarbamazine and albendazole) is superior to the currently recommended two-drug regimen
      (DEC+ALB, DA). A single dose of the triple therapy (IVM+DEC+ALB, IDA) rapidly achieved
      complete clearance of Wuchereria bancrofti microfilariae from the blood of 12 individuals for
      at least one year post-treatment. All six individuals tested at 24 months were still
      amicrofilaremic, suggesting that the triple therapy might permanently sterilizes adult
      filarial worms. Many people treated in these studies experienced transient systemic adverse
      events commonly associated with diethylcarbamazine or ivermectin treatment of filariasis.
      Adverse events were more frequent after the triple therapy than after the usual combination
      of two drugs. However, no serious adverse events were observed. The dramatic reduction and
      sustained decrease of microfilaria along with the safety profile seen in the Papua New Guinea
      studies suggest that the triple drug therapy may be a useful tool to achieve the goal of
      eliminating lymphatic filariasis as a public health problem by 2020.

      Although the study cited above has clearly demonstrated the superiority of the triple therapy
      for clearing W. bancrofti microfilaria from the blood, more safety and efficacy data are
      needed before triple therapy can be rolled out on a large scale as a mass drug administration
      regimen in lymphatic filariasis endemic countries. WHO recommends a best practice called
      &quot;cohort event monitoring&quot; for demonstrating safety of new drug regimens for public health
      program use. Establishing safety through such methodology requires pre and post treatment
      assessment from at least 10,000 people treated with the triple therapy across multiple
      settings.

      It is therefore proposed to conduct a cohort event monitoring study to acquire safety data.
      Efficacy and acceptability components will also be included in the study. Similar studies
      will be conducted simultaneously in Haiti, India, Indonesia, Papua New Guinea and Sri Lanka
      to reach the 10,000 people necessary to assess the safety of this new drug combination.

      This will be an open label, two-armed study. The two arms are (1) mass drug administration
      (MDA) with the currently used combination of two-drug regimen (DA) and (2) MDA with triple
      drug therapy (IDA).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by modified CTCAE v4.0 scale</measure>
    <time_frame>within 7 days of drug administration</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the frequency, type and severity of adverse events following triple-drug therapy Ivermectin, Diethylcarbamazine and Albendazole (IVM+DEC+ALB, IDA) compared to the standard two-drug treatment Diethylcarbamazine and Albendazole (DEC+ALB, DA) in infected and uninfected individuals in a community as assessed by modified CTCAE v4.0 scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with clearance of microfilaremia (MF) as measured with microfilaremia night blood smear testing (finger prick - 60ul)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-treatment), within 7 days of drug administration and follow up at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the efficacy of IDA vs. DA administered in communities for clearance of MF and filarial antigenemia (Ag) in cohort and effectiveness (prevalence) in community settings. A minimum of 21 (70%) of MF-positive participants in each arm will be retested at 12 months post-treatment for antigenemia and microfilaremia. This sample size is adequate to demonstrate superiority of the IDA regimen (assumptions: 90% reduction in MF prevalence after IDA and 60% reduction after DA, 80% power for detecting an effect size of 30%). The primary endpoint for efficacy will be complete clearance of MF 12 months post Mass Drug Administration (MDA). Clearance of filarial antigenemia at 12 months will be a secondary endpoint for the efficacy analysis. Testing of microfilaria is by analyzing 60 microliter (ul) measured volume thick blood smear by finger prick method and results are either positive or negative for MF presence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants Filarial Test Strip (FTS) and/or MF positive as tested with FTS and night blood smears with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by modified CTCAE v4.0 scale</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (pre-treatment), within 7 days of drug administration and follow up at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the presence and intensity of filarial infection on the frequency and severity of adverse events. One year post MDA, all participants who were positive for either microfilaremia or filarial antigenemia during the baseline visit will be tested for filarial antigen using the FTS to assess their response to treatment and to compare the efficacy of the two treatment regimens. Participants with positive FTS will also be tested for nocturnal microfilaremia by blood smear (finger prick - 60ul)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Community acceptance will be measured using on a survey using likert scale questions based on perception of efficacy, intent to participate and relevance of the treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>6-8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Community acceptance will be measured using a survey to community members receiving both the 2-drug and 3-drug treatments during the safety trial. To complement this survey, a series of focus group discussions in the community as well as key informant interviews are proposed with community leaders, health personnel and drug distributors in the same communities to assess perceptions about the 3-drug versus the 2-drug regimen. The community acceptability study will be carried out within one month of the completion of the safety trial. The acceptability score will use a set of likert scale questions based on perception of efficacy, intent to participate and relevance of the treatment. Some of the questions have been inspired by Reimer's Treatment Acceptability Rating form-Revised and general principles of social validity but mostly the questions are not from one particular survey instrument.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of STH (hookworm, ascaris, trichuris and strongyloides) as measured by Kato-katz or PCR at baseline and 12 months after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Stool collected at baseline (pre-treatment), 4 weeks (individual response), and 12 months (community prevalence).</time_frame>
    <description>Some sites will include stool sample collections to compare the efficacy of 2 and 3-drug regimens on STH. Stool samples will be analysed using Kato-katz method, as well as PCR.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23789</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphatic Filariasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2 drug dose - DA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug treatment with two-drug regimen diethylcarbamazine and albendazole (DA)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3 drug dose - IDA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Triple-drug regimen Ivermectin, diethylcarbamazine and albendazole (IDA)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>3 drug dose - IDA</intervention_name>
    <description>Lymphatic Filariasis Mass Drug Administration (MDA) with triple drug therapy of ivermectin, diethylcarbamazine, and albendazole (IDA)</description>
    <arm_group_label>3 drug dose - IDA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IDA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>2 drug dose - DA</intervention_name>
    <description>Lymphatic Filariasis Mass Drug Administration (MDA) with the currently used standard of care combination drug therapy of diethylcarbamazine, and albendazole (DA)</description>
    <arm_group_label>2 drug dose - DA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        In India:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 5 years, male or female for IDA arm and age &gt; 2 years for DA arm.

          2. Able to provide informed consent to participate in the trial (forms to be attached)

          3. No evidence of severe or systemic co-morbidities except for features of filarial
             disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt; 5 years (ivermectin is contraindicated in children below 5 years of age) for IDA
             arm and age &lt; 2 years for DA arm

          2. Pregnant women (DEC, ivermectin and albendazole are contraindicated in pregnancy)

          3. Severe chronic illness (for example, chronic renal failure, inability to care for
             oneself with activities of daily living)

          4. History of previous allergy to MDA drugs

        For rest of countries:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 5 years, for IDA and DA arms (males and females).

          2. Able to provide informed consent or give parental consent for minors to participate in
             the trial

          3. No evidence of severe or systemic co-morbidities except for features of filarial
             disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt; 5 years (ivermectin is not approved for use in children less than 5 years of
             age)

          2. Unable to provide informed consent or give parental consent for minors to participate
             in the trial

          3. Pregnant women (DEC, ivermectin and albendazole are not known to be safe for use
             during pregnancy)

          4. Severe chronic illness (chronic renal insufficiency, severe chronic liver disease, or
             any illness that is severe enough to interfere with activities of daily living)

          5. History of previous allergy to MDA drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary Weil, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher King, MD PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Case Western Reserve University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ministere de la Sante Publique et de la Population</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port-au-Prince</city>
        <country>Haiti</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vector Control Research Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Puducherry</city>
        <zip>605006</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitas Indonesia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jakarta</city>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Papua New Guinea Institute for Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madang</city>
        <country>Papua New Guinea</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Haiti</country>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>Indonesia</country>
    <country>Papua New Guinea</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://nvbdcp.gov.in/filariasis-new.html</url>
    <description>National Vector Borne Disease Control Programme (2015)</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization (1997). Elimination of lymphatic filariasis as a public health problem - resolution of the executive board of the WHO.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomsen EK, Sanuku N, Baea M, Satofan S, Maki E, Lombore B, Schmidt MS, Siba PM, Weil GJ, Kazura JW, Fleckenstein LL, King CL. Efficacy, Safety, and Pharmacokinetics of Coadministered Diethylcarbamazine, Albendazole, and Ivermectin for Treatment of Bancroftian Filariasis. Clin Infect Dis. 2016 Feb 1;62(3):334-341. doi: 10.1093/cid/civ882. Epub 2015 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>26486704</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gyapong JO, Kumaraswami V, Biswas G, Ottesen EA. Treatment strategies underpinning the global programme to eliminate lymphatic filariasis. Expert Opin Pharmacother. 2005 Feb;6(2):179-200. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15757416</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>489 Global programme to eliminate lymphatic filariasis: progress report, 2014. Wkly Epidemiol Rec. 2015 Sep 18;90(38):489-504. English, French.</citation>
    <PMID>26387149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oscar R, Lemoine JF, Direny AN, Desir L, Beau de Rochars VE, Poirier MJ, Varghese A, Obidegwu I, Lammie PJ, Streit TG, Milord MD. Haiti National Program for the elimination of lymphatic filariasis--a model of success in the face of adversity. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2014 Jul 17;8(7):e2915. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0002915. eCollection 2014 Jul.</citation>
    <PMID>25032697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Rochars MB, Kanjilal S, Direny AN, Radday J, Lafontant JG, Mathieu E, Rheingans RD, Haddix AC, Streit TG, Beach MJ, Addiss DG, Lammie PJ. The Leogane, Haiti demonstration project: decreased microfilaremia and program costs after three years of mass drug administration. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2005 Nov;73(5):888-94.</citation>
    <PMID>16282299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horton J. Albendazole: a review of anthelmintic efficacy and safety in humans. Parasitology. 2000;121 Suppl:S113-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11386684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goa KL, McTavish D, Clissold SP. Ivermectin. A review of its antifilarial activity, pharmacokinetic properties and clinical efficacy in onchocerciasis. Drugs. 1991 Oct;42(4):640-58. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1723366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edwards G. Ivermectin: does P-glycoprotein play a role in neurotoxicity? Filaria J. 2003 Oct 24;2 Suppl 1:S8.</citation>
    <PMID>14975065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ottesen EA, Campbell WC. Ivermectin in human medicine. J Antimicrob Chemother. 1994 Aug;34(2):195-203. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7814280</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Awadzi K, Edwards G, Duke BO, Opoku NO, Attah SK, Addy ET, Ardrey AE, Quartey BT. The co-administration of ivermectin and albendazole--safety, pharmacokinetics and efficacy against Onchocerca volvulus. Ann Trop Med Parasitol. 2003 Mar;97(2):165-78.</citation>
    <PMID>12803872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ottesen EA. Efficacy of diethylcarbamazine in eradicating infection with lymphatic-dwelling filariae in humans. Rev Infect Dis. 1985 May-Jun;7(3):341-56.</citation>
    <PMID>3895352</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Norões J, Dreyer G, Santos A, Mendes VG, Medeiros Z, Addiss D. Assessment of the efficacy of diethylcarbamazine on adult Wuchereria bancrofti in vivo. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 1997 Jan-Feb;91(1):78-81.</citation>
    <PMID>9093637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gary Weil, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine/ Microbiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mass drug administration</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety Data</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Filariasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Elephantiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Elephantiasis, Filarial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Albendazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diethylcarbamazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ivermectin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Datasets used for published results will be shared publically through a journal or other open source data repository so that the broader scientific community can access it. Only de-identified data will be shared publicly.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

