<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02891200</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR-1507-31247</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02891200</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of a Peer Support Program Amongst COPD Patients and Their Caregivers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparing Effectiveness of Self-management and Peer Support Communication Programs Amongst Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) Patients and Their Family Caregivers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is to compare the effectiveness of two health communication and dissemination
      strategies that are designed to engage patients and family caregivers in successfully
      managing COPD in 'real-world' settings. Both strategies aim to advance patient understanding
      of COPD, its treatment options, and self-care tasks; support them in coping with the disease;
      and enable them to adopt a variety of positive behaviors, including adherence to treatment
      plans, smoking cessation, joining pulmonary rehabilitation programs, and assuming an active,
      healthy lifestyle. One strategy relies on the healthcare professional (HCP) as the primary
      communicator about COPD self-management (HCP arm), whereas the other uses a dual approach
      that involves both healthcare professionals and peer mentors delivering such communication
      (HCP plus Peer arm). Peer mentors are COPD patients and caregivers who have successfully
      managed COPD and have received foundational training on peer mentoring. Specifically, the
      study aims are to : 1) Conduct a randomized controlled trial in which the 'HCP' and 'HCP plus
      Peer' strategies are tested in 'real-world' healthcare settings; 2) compare the impact of
      these strategies on patient satisfaction, experience, activation, self- efficacy, self-care
      behavior, health status, quality of life, use of Emergency Department (ED) and hospital
      services, and survival; and, 3) compare the impact of these strategies on caregiver
      satisfaction, experience, self-efficacy, stress, and coping skills.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) is a prevalent global condition that results in
      high mortality, morbidity, symptom burden, and functional limitations that impact the quality
      of life. COPD is the third leading cause of death in the US and a leading cause of
      hospitalizations. COPD patients report unmet needs in regards to information about their
      disease and how to manage and cope with it at an intellectual, emotional, and social level.
      Many COPD patients lack the information and skills that they need to correctly use their
      inhaled medications, manage 'breathlessness episodes', and detect early signs of a COPD
      exacerbation. Pulmonary rehabilitation programs are established to help COPD patients
      increase their exercise capacity and reduce fatigue and dyspnea with daily activity. While
      clinical trials testing these programs have demonstrated significant improvements in
      health-related quality of life and reduced dyspnea and fatigue amongst participants, it
      remains unclear how best to engage and motivate patients to participate in them.

      Self-management support interventions which involve &quot;collaboratively helping patients acquire
      and practice the skills needed to carry out disease-specific medical regimens, change their
      health behavior to adjust their roles for optimal function, improve day-to-day control of
      their disease, and improve their well-being&quot;, have been demonstrated in several trials to
      improve health-related quality of life, and reduce symptom burden, hospitalizations, and ED
      visits amongst COPD patients. However, it is still unclear which self-management support
      strategies employed in 'real world' settings are most effective in engaging, motivating, and
      enabling patients to successfully follow recommended treatments, adopt desired health
      behaviors, and thus achieve the desired improvements in their health outcomes.

      The planned study design is a single- blinded randomized controlled trial to compare the
      effectiveness of two strategies for engaging and supporting COPD patients and their family
      caregivers in self-management of COPD. The two strategies/study arms are: 1) the 'HCP arm'
      where the healthcare professional (HCP) is the primary communicator about COPD
      self-management with the patient participants; and 2) the 'HCP plus Peer arm', where both
      healthcare professionals and peer mentors engage with study participants in conversations
      about COPD self-management using multiple channels including one- to- one and group
      conversations. Participants will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio into the two study arms. The
      trial will be conducted amongst COPD patients coming to the hospital or clinic at two study
      sites within Johns Hopkins Healthcare System. Recruitment from both sites and multiple
      settings allows for a more representative COPD patient population to be enrolled in the
      study, thus increasing the external validity of study findings.

      The research study will answer the research question: Amongst COPD patients and their
      caregivers, would a dual strategy that combines healthcare professional and peer mentor
      delivery of COPD self- management education and support result in greater improvements in
      health status and quality of life, and reductions in acute healthcare services' utilization,
      compared to relying on healthcare professionals alone in these communications? Would such
      dual strategy result in reduced caregiver stress and improved coping and satisfaction? The
      study hypothesis is that the dual strategy of using 'HCP plus peer support' to engage and
      support COPD patients and caregivers will have superior outcomes to the 'HCP only' strategy
      in the following areas : a) Improved health- related quality of life and reduced numbers of
      COPD-related hospital and ED visits; b) improved patient activation, self-efficacy, and
      self-care behaviors; c) improved family caregivers' satisfaction and self- efficacy. These
      improvements will be noted at 3, 6, and 9 months compared to baseline.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 17, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in health-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>enrollment to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in health-related quality of life at 6 months post-intervention (from baseline). This is measured using a validated instrument that will be administered to participant by a trained research team member.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>combined number of COPD-related hospitalizations and ED visits per participant</measure>
    <time_frame>enrollment to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>All hospitalizations and ED visits will be reviewed for cause and those deemed to be COPD-related will be counted from time of participant enrollment into study till 6 months afterwards.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">290</enrollment>
  <condition>COPD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthcare professional (HCP) Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Healthcare professional (HCP) Arm includes a trained respiratory therapist who will provide COPD self-management education and support via an in-person session and written materials .</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HCP plus Peer arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HCP plus Peer arm involves delivering of HCP support as in HCP Arm , along with adding Peer Support Program services. This program is offered to participants by especially trained 'peer mentors' with oversight from a social worker.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peer support program</intervention_name>
    <description>The Peer Support Program offers education and support to participants by especially trained 'peer mentors' with oversight from a social worker.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HCP plus Peer arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HCP support</intervention_name>
    <description>Healthcare professional (HCP) support will be provided by a trained respiratory therapist who will provide COPD self-management education and support via an in-person session and written materials .</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthcare professional (HCP) Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>HCP plus Peer arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 years or older

          -  Has a physician diagnosis of COPD AND is on treatment for it ( defined as receiving
             treatment at hospital or clinic for COPD)

          -  Smoking history of &gt; or = to 10 pk-years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cognitive dysfunction impairing ability to provide informed consent and follow
             instructions

          -  Active substance abuse or unstable psychiatric condition

          -  Terminal illness (i.e. less than 6 months life expectancy) that is non-COPD related

          -  Planning to move from area

          -  Living at a facility, such as Hospice or nursing home

          -  Unable to provide contact information

          -  Does not understand English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hanan Aboumatar, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hanan Aboumatar, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>410-637-7152</phone>
    <email>habouma1@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mohammad Naqibuddin, MBBS, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>410-637-4397</phone>
    <email>mnaqibu2@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Bayview Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hanan Aboumatar, MD, MPH</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Howard County General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21044</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 7, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

