<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02898987</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DAT_001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02898987</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Quality of Care in French HIV Infected Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>Dataids_PEC</acronym>
  <official_title>Dataids Prospective Observational Cohort on Quality of Care of French HIV Infected Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>DatAids</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>DatAids</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of the Dataids cohort is to continue a long-term, prospective collection of
      clinical, laboratory and therapeutic data on a large cohort of HIV infected patients seeking
      care in 15 HIV centers in France in order :

        1. to provide and develop a surveillance system to describe clinical practice and temporal
           changes in the clinical course of HIV and HIV-related co-infections and co-morbidities
           in France.

        2. to assess the factors associated with the clinical, immunological and virological course
           of HIV infection and HIV-related co-infections and co-morbidities

      The specific objectives are as follows

        -  To continue surveillance of HIV infection in France to describe temporal changes

        -  To evaluate the efficacy of ART and factors associated with ART efficacy

        -  To monitor the uptake and outcome of HCV therapy
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Dataids cohort is a prospective observational cohort of 30,000+ patients followed in 15+
      HIV centers scattered throughout France. The Dataids cohort is an ongoing collaboration and
      patients have been enrolled into the study since 2010; the data are collected from the
      clinics as part of routine care. Included patients should be patients who had a scheduled
      visit in the outpatient clinic regardless of CD4 cell count, HIV viral load or ART status.
      For all HIV patients enrolled and under follow up, demographic data, immunological and
      virological data, serological evidence for infection with hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis
      C virus (HCV), or syphilis, laboratory, therapeutic and clinical data are collected annually.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of HIV treated patients with HIV plasma viral load &lt; 50 copies/mL</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment, through study completion, an average of 6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of HIV/HCV coinfected patients who start treatment with direct acting antivirals agents</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment, through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of HIV patients according to their antiretroviral status : naive, on treatment, therapeutic stop</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment, through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of HIV/HCV patients with undetectable HCV viral load after treatment with direct acting antivirals agents</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment, through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of HIV patients with CD4 cells count above 500 /ml</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment, through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of antiretroviral modification due to simplification or failure</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment, through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The observational cohort study concept means that Dataids does not collect Adverse Events, Adverse Reactions, Serious Adverse Reactions or Suspected Unexpected Serious Adverse Reactions as defined by pharmacovigilance requirements for marketing authorization holders. However, Dataids often analyses and reports specific clinical events of interest, occasionally related to drug classes, but more regularly with a focus on differences in treatment and care</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of aids events among patients enrolled in the cohort study</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment, through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of non aids events among patients enrolled in the cohort study</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment, through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30000</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All HIV-infected patients seeking care at 15 centers using NADIS are included in the
        Dataids cohort after receiving oral information and giving written consent. NADIS is an
        electronic medical record (EMR) for HIV-, hepatitis B virus (HBV)- or hepatitis C virus
        (HCV)-infected adults seeking care in French public hospitals.

        The Dataids study recruits HIV-1 positive patients above the age of 18 years. Approximately
        30 % of the patients are women. The study does not intervene with the clinical management
        of the patients followed, but only collects information from patient records.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-1 infected patients regardless of CD4 cell count and antiretroviral therapy status

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients under 18 years of age

          -  Patients without written informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pascal PUGLIESE, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU de Nice</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>André CABIE, MD-PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU de Martinique</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dataids.org</url>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pugliese P, Cuzin L, Cabié A, Poizot-Martin I, Allavena C, Duvivier C, El Guedj M, de la Tribonnière X, Valantin MA, Dellamonica P; Nadis Group. A large French prospective cohort of HIV-infected patients: the Nadis Cohort. HIV Med. 2009 Sep;10(8):504-11. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-1293.2009.00719.x. Epub 2009 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19486189</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 29, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis C</keyword>
  <keyword>Comorbidities</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

