<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02897739</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14/NS/1068</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02897739</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pathogenesis of Acute Stress Induced (Tako-tsubo) Cardiomyopathy: Energy Shut-Down or Intense Inflammation?</brief_title>
  <acronym>TERRIFIC</acronym>
  <official_title>Pathogenesis of Acute Stress Induced (Tako-tsubo) Cardiomyopathy: Energy Shut-Down or Intense Inflammation? The TERRIFIC Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aberdeen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NHS Grampian</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aberdeen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Tako Tsubo Cardiomyopathy (TTC), also known as &quot;Broken Heart Syndrome&quot;, is a disorder of the
      heart that occurs most commonly in women (although it occasionally occurs in men) and is
      usually related to a stressful event. Symptoms are often similar to a heart attack, and
      include chest pain and shortness of breath. Although Tako Tsubo Cardiomyopathy is not a new
      medical condition, it has not been widely recognised until the last decade. Currently the
      investigators don't have an exact understanding of how or why the heart is affected in this
      way, and so the investigators are conducting a study to help understand what causes Tako
      Tsubo Cardiomyopathy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aim to study the reciprocal modulation of fatty acids and glucose
      metabolism in the Tako Tsubo Cardiomyopathy physiology, in both humans and an animal model,
      and to investigate which metabolic pathway is preferentially adopted by acute Tako Tsubo
      Cardiomyopathy myocytes during this severe functional shut down with largely preserved
      variability. The human model will be used to determine the preferential stimulated uptake of
      glucose/fatty acids under optimal metabolic conditions for each (hyperinsulineamic euglycemic
      clamp for 18F-Fludeoxyglucose (18F-FDG) and fasting for
      14Fluorine-18Fluoro-6-Thia-Heptadecanoic Acid (18F-FTHA cardiac Positron Emission
      Tomography)). In the rat model the investigators will examine both the metabolic tracer
      uptake (using micro Positron Emission Tomography-Computed Tomography) as well as the
      downstream modulation of the two metabolic pathways (transcriptional regulators,
      mitochondrial respiration, expression of the uncoupling proteins, levels of Adenosine
      Triphosphate generation and reactive oxygen species production).

      The investigators aim to test the hypothesis that inflammation plays a pivotal role in the
      pathophysiology of this condition by further exploring: 1) In the rat model define time
      course, extent and subtypes of cellular infiltrate, 2) In the rat model of Tako Tsubo
      Cardiomyopathy, demonstrate the presence of inflammatory macrophages using in-vivo Ultrasmall
      Superparamagnetic Iron Oxide-cardiac magnetic resonance imaging and whether this relates to
      numbers and types of macrophages present as determined by immunohistochemical analysis, 3) In
      clinical patients, define the time course of specific peripheral blood monocyte subsets and
      the serum levels of inflammatory cytokines versus matched controls and 4) In clinical
      patients, establish the compartmentalisation of tissue macrophages in the left ventricle its
      time course resolution using Ultrasmall Superparamagnetic Iron Oxide-enhanced cardiac
      magnetic resonance.

      The investigators will assess the psycho-emotional factors involved in Tako Tsubo
      Cardiomyopathy given that in the majority of cases intense emotional trauma is immediately
      preceding onset.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>4 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac Inflammation as measured by Cardiac Magnetic Resonance Imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>Three years</time_frame>
    <description>As measured by cardiac MRI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence of psycho-emotional factors following intense physical or emotional stress as measured by Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Three years</time_frame>
    <description>As measured by psychiatric interview</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence of alterations of the metabolism of myocardium by Cardiac Positron Emission Tomography</measure>
    <time_frame>Three years</time_frame>
    <description>As measured by PET CT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systemic Inflammation as measured by inflammatory markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Three years</time_frame>
    <description>As measured by inflammatory markers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Tako-tsubo Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TTC Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with Tako-tsubo cardiomyopathy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health Volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants who have normal hearts.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic resonance imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Cardiac MRI and short MRI following USPIO infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>TTC Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Health Volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acute Inflammatory Activation study</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood sampling for exploration of type and level of inflammatory response</description>
    <arm_group_label>TTC Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Health Volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PET CT</intervention_name>
    <description>PET study for metabolic pathway study</description>
    <arm_group_label>TTC Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Health Volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychological assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Assessment by a psychologist</description>
    <arm_group_label>TTC Patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Health Volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      EDTA blood samples, EDTA Plasma and Serum to be retained.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who have been diagnosed with Tako-tsubo Cardiomyopathy Healthy volunteers
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients diagnosed with TTC in the past 12 days, able to give consent and who have
             not lost capacity of consent between the time of diagnosis (usually made at coronary
             catheterisation, for which they are consented clinically) and time of being approached
             for inclusion in the study.

          -  Age and gender matched healthy controls willing to participate and able to give
             consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unwillingness to participate

          -  Patients with contraindications to MR scanning

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dana Dawson, MD, MRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Aberdeen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dana Dawson, MD, MRCP</last_name>
    <phone>01224 437969</phone>
    <email>dana.dawson@doctors.org.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Caroline Scally, MD, MRCP</last_name>
    <phone>01224 559573</phone>
    <email>carolinescally@abdn.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiac Research Office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aberdeen</city>
        <state>Aberdeenshire</state>
        <zip>AB25 2ZD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Dawson, MD, MRCP</last_name>
      <phone>01224 437969</phone>
      <email>dana.dawson@doctors.org.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Caroline Scally, MD, MRCP</last_name>
      <phone>01224 559573</phone>
      <email>carolinescally@abdn.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prasad A, Lerman A, Rihal CS. Apical ballooning syndrome (Tako-Tsubo or stress cardiomyopathy): a mimic of acute myocardial infarction. Am Heart J. 2008 Mar;155(3):408-17. doi: 10.1016/j.ahj.2007.11.008. Epub 2008 Jan 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18294473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gianni M, Dentali F, Grandi AM, Sumner G, Hiralal R, Lonn E. Apical ballooning syndrome or takotsubo cardiomyopathy: a systematic review. Eur Heart J. 2006 Jul;27(13):1523-9. Epub 2006 May 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16720686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neil C, Nguyen TH, Kucia A, Crouch B, Sverdlov A, Chirkov Y, Mahadavan G, Selvanayagam J, Dawson D, Beltrame J, Zeitz C, Unger S, Redpath T, Frenneaux M, Horowitz J. Slowly resolving global myocardial inflammation/oedema in Tako-Tsubo cardiomyopathy: evidence from T2-weighted cardiac MRI. Heart. 2012 Sep;98(17):1278-84. doi: 10.1136/heartjnl-2011-301481. Epub 2012 Jul 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22791656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharkey SW, Windenburg DC, Lesser JR, Maron MS, Hauser RG, Lesser JN, Haas TS, Hodges JS, Maron BJ. Natural history and expansive clinical profile of stress (tako-tsubo) cardiomyopathy. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2010 Jan 26;55(4):333-41. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2009.08.057.</citation>
    <PMID>20117439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abraham J, Mudd JO, Kapur NK, Klein K, Champion HC, Wittstein IS. Stress cardiomyopathy after intravenous administration of catecholamines and beta-receptor agonists. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2009 Apr 14;53(15):1320-5. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2009.02.020. Erratum in: J Am Coll Cardiol. 2009 May 12;53(19):1828. Kapur, Navin [corrected to Kapur, Navin K].</citation>
    <PMID>19358948</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nef HM, Möllmann H, Akashi YJ, Hamm CW. Mechanisms of stress (Takotsubo) cardiomyopathy. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2010 Apr;7(4):187-93. doi: 10.1038/nrcardio.2010.16. Epub 2010 Mar 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20195267</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elesber AA, Prasad A, Lennon RJ, Wright RS, Lerman A, Rihal CS. Four-year recurrence rate and prognosis of the apical ballooning syndrome. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2007 Jul 31;50(5):448-52. Epub 2007 Jul 16.</citation>
    <PMID>17662398</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neubauer S, Horn M, Naumann A, Tian R, Hu K, Laser M, Friedrich J, Gaudron P, Schnackerz K, Ingwall JS, et al. Impairment of energy metabolism in intact residual myocardium of rat hearts with chronic myocardial infarction. J Clin Invest. 1995 Mar;95(3):1092-100.</citation>
    <PMID>7883957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dawson DK, Neil CJ, Henning A, Cameron D, Jagpal B, Bruce M, Horowitz J, Frenneaux MP. The Authors Reply. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2016 May;9(5):633. doi: 10.1016/j.jcmg.2015.02.032. Epub 2016 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>26897679</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feola M, Chauvie S, Rosso GL, Biggi A, Ribichini F, Bobbio M. Reversible impairment of coronary flow reserve in takotsubo cardiomyopathy: a myocardial PET study. J Nucl Cardiol. 2008 Nov-Dec;15(6):811-7. doi: 10.1007/BF03007363. Epub 2008 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>18984457</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoshida T, Hibino T, Kako N, Murai S, Oguri M, Kato K, Yajima K, Ohte N, Yokoi K, Kimura G. A pathophysiologic study of tako-tsubo cardiomyopathy with F-18 fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography. Eur Heart J. 2007 Nov;28(21):2598-604. Epub 2007 Oct 7.</citation>
    <PMID>17921529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ibrahim T, Nekolla SG, Langwieser N, Rischpler C, Groha P, Laugwitz KL, Schwaiger M. Simultaneous positron emission tomography/magnetic resonance imaging identifies sustained regional abnormalities in cardiac metabolism and function in stress-induced transient midventricular ballooning syndrome: a variant of Takotsubo cardiomyopathy. Circulation. 2012 Nov 20;126(21):e324-6. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.112.134346.</citation>
    <PMID>23169256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerber BL, Ordoubadi FF, Wijns W, Vanoverschelde JL, Knuuti MJ, Janier M, Melon P, Blanksma PK, Bol A, Bax JJ, Melin JA, Camici PG. Positron emission tomography using(18)F-fluoro-deoxyglucose and euglycaemic hyperinsulinaemic glucose clamp: optimal criteria for the prediction of recovery of post-ischaemic left ventricular dysfunction. Results from the European Community Concerted Action Multicenter study on use of(18)F-fluoro-deoxyglucose Positron Emission Tomography for the Detection of Myocardial Viability. Eur Heart J. 2001 Sep;22(18):1691-701.</citation>
    <PMID>11511119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herrero P, Peterson LR, McGill JB, Matthew S, Lesniak D, Dence C, Gropler RJ. Increased myocardial fatty acid metabolism in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2006 Feb 7;47(3):598-604. Epub 2006 Jan 18.</citation>
    <PMID>16458143</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kurisu S, Inoue I, Kawagoe T, Ishihara M, Shimatani Y, Nishioka K, Umemura T, Nakamura S, Yoshida M, Sato H. Myocardial perfusion and fatty acid metabolism in patients with tako-tsubo-like left ventricular dysfunction. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2003 Mar 5;41(5):743-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12628716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wittstein IS, Thiemann DR, Lima JA, Baughman KL, Schulman SP, Gerstenblith G, Wu KC, Rade JJ, Bivalacqua TJ, Champion HC. Neurohumoral features of myocardial stunning due to sudden emotional stress. N Engl J Med. 2005 Feb 10;352(6):539-48.</citation>
    <PMID>15703419</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paur H, Wright PT, Sikkel MB, Tranter MH, Mansfield C, O'Gara P, Stuckey DJ, Nikolaev VO, Diakonov I, Pannell L, Gong H, Sun H, Peters NS, Petrou M, Zheng Z, Gorelik J, Lyon AR, Harding SE. High levels of circulating epinephrine trigger apical cardiodepression in a β2-adrenergic receptor/Gi-dependent manner: a new model of Takotsubo cardiomyopathy. Circulation. 2012 Aug 7;126(6):697-706. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.112.111591. Epub 2012 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22732314</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shao Y, Redfors B, Scharin Täng M, Möllmann H, Troidl C, Szardien S, Hamm C, Nef H, Borén J, Omerovic E. Novel rat model reveals important roles of β-adrenoreceptors in stress-induced cardiomyopathy. Int J Cardiol. 2013 Oct 3;168(3):1943-50. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2012.12.092. Epub 2013 Jan 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23357048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nef HM, Möllmann H, Kostin S, Troidl C, Voss S, Weber M, Dill T, Rolf A, Brandt R, Hamm CW, Elsässer A. Tako-Tsubo cardiomyopathy: intraindividual structural analysis in the acute phase and after functional recovery. Eur Heart J. 2007 Oct;28(20):2456-64. Epub 2007 Mar 29.</citation>
    <PMID>17395683</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ziegler-Heitbrock L, Ancuta P, Crowe S, Dalod M, Grau V, Hart DN, Leenen PJ, Liu YJ, MacPherson G, Randolph GJ, Scherberich J, Schmitz J, Shortman K, Sozzani S, Strobl H, Zembala M, Austyn JM, Lutz MB. Nomenclature of monocytes and dendritic cells in blood. Blood. 2010 Oct 21;116(16):e74-80. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-02-258558. Epub 2010 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>20628149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gill JM, Saligan L, Woods S, Page G. PTSD is associated with an excess of inflammatory immune activities. Perspect Psychiatr Care. 2009 Oct;45(4):262-77. doi: 10.1111/j.1744-6163.2009.00229.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19780999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alam SR, Shah AS, Richards J, Lang NN, Barnes G, Joshi N, MacGillivray T, McKillop G, Mirsadraee S, Payne J, Fox KA, Henriksen P, Newby DE, Semple SI. Ultrasmall superparamagnetic particles of iron oxide in patients with acute myocardial infarction: early clinical experience. Circ Cardiovasc Imaging. 2012 Sep 1;5(5):559-65. Epub 2012 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22875883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yilmaz A, Dengler MA, van der Kuip H, Yildiz H, Rösch S, Klumpp S, Klingel K, Kandolf R, Helluy X, Hiller KH, Jakob PM, Sechtem U. Imaging of myocardial infarction using ultrasmall superparamagnetic iron oxide nanoparticles: a human study using a multi-parametric cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging approach. Eur Heart J. 2013 Feb;34(6):462-75. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehs366. Epub 2012 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23103659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paternostro G, Camici PG, Lammerstma AA, Marinho N, Baliga RR, Kooner JS, Radda GK, Ferrannini E. Cardiac and skeletal muscle insulin resistance in patients with coronary heart disease. A study with positron emission tomography. J Clin Invest. 1996 Nov 1;98(9):2094-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8903329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen X, Lee G, Maher BS, Fanous AH, Chen J, Zhao Z, Guo A, van den Oord E, Sullivan PF, Shi J, Levinson DF, Gejman PV, Sanders A, Duan J, Owen MJ, Craddock NJ, O'Donovan MC, Blackman J, Lewis D, Kirov GK, Qin W, Schwab S, Wildenauer D, Chowdari K, Nimgaonkar V, Straub RE, Weinberger DR, O'Neill FA, Walsh D, Bronstein M, Darvasi A, Lencz T, Malhotra AK, Rujescu D, Giegling I, Werge T, Hansen T, Ingason A, Nöethen MM, Rietschel M, Cichon S, Djurovic S, Andreassen OA, Cantor RM, Ophoff R, Corvin A, Morris DW, Gill M, Pato CN, Pato MT, Macedo A, Gurling HM, McQuillin A, Pimm J, Hultman C, Lichtenstein P, Sklar P, Purcell SM, Scolnick E, St Clair D, Blackwood DH, Kendler KS; GROUP investigators; International Schizophrenia Consortium. GWA study data mining and independent replication identify cardiomyopathy-associated 5 (CMYA5) as a risk gene for schizophrenia. Mol Psychiatry. 2011 Nov;16(11):1117-29. doi: 10.1038/mp.2010.96. Epub 2010 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>20838396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashbrook DG, Williams RW, Lu L, Hager R. A cross-species genetic analysis identifies candidate genes for mouse anxiety and human bipolar disorder. Front Behav Neurosci. 2015 Jul 1;9:171. doi: 10.3389/fnbeh.2015.00171. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26190982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCalmon SA, Desjardins DM, Ahmad S, Davidoff KS, Snyder CM, Sato K, Ohashi K, Kielbasa OM, Mathew M, Ewen EP, Walsh K, Gavras H, Naya FJ. Modulation of angiotensin II-mediated cardiac remodeling by the MEF2A target gene Xirp2. Circ Res. 2010 Mar 19;106(5):952-60. doi: 10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.109.209007. Epub 2010 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>20093629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pison L, De Vusser P, Mullens W. Apical ballooning in relatives. Heart. 2004 Dec;90(12):e67.</citation>
    <PMID>15547001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumar G, Holmes DR Jr, Prasad A. &quot;Familial&quot; apical ballooning syndrome (Takotsubo cardiomyopathy). Int J Cardiol. 2010 Oct 29;144(3):444-5. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2009.03.078. Epub 2009 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>19375184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharkey SW, Lips DL, Pink VR, Maron BJ. Daughter-mother tako-tsubo cardiomyopathy. Am J Cardiol. 2013 Jul 1;112(1):137-8. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2013.02.063. Epub 2013 Apr 2.</citation>
    <PMID>23561588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caretta G, Robba D, Vizzardi E, Bonadei I, Raddino R, Metra M. Tako-tsubo cardiomyopathy in two sisters: a chance finding or familial predisposition? Clin Res Cardiol. 2015 Jul;104(7):614-6. doi: 10.1007/s00392-015-0837-0. Epub 2015 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25743177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 24, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 7, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 13, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Takotsubo Cardiomyopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

