<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02892448</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20150281</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02892448</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cardiac MRI for Metal on Metal Hip Resurfacing</brief_title>
  <acronym>CardiacMRI</acronym>
  <official_title>Cardiac MRI for Metal on Metal Orthopaedic Prostheses</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There may be a relationship between heart function and the metal ION levels in patients
      having undergone total hip replacement. The idea is to use results from a clinical cardiac
      MRI to assess heart function in a sample of 30 patients whom have undergone either
      metal-on-metal hip replacement (unilateral or bilateral) or a non-metal on metal total hip
      replacement to determine whether having undergone a metal on metal hip procedure may be
      impacting heart function. In addition to the clinically used parameters, the images will also
      be retrospectively assessed using special software to assess amount of fibrosis and early
      changes affecting cardiac muscle contraction which may be indicative of impaired heart
      function. With these values we will compare to known, and previously collected, hip
      replacement and function data to determine whether there is any differences in how the heart
      works in those having had a hip replacement relative to a normal population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There has been some recent concern regarding possible systemic health effects resulting from
      elevated blood cobalt concentrations in patients with cobalt containing hip implants (1). To
      date there are no blood cobalt criteria to help guide physicians when evaluating an
      individual hip implant patient's risk of developing systemic health effects because
      historically there was little or no concern about systemic cobalt toxicity in implant
      patients. Included within this is heart function, for which investigators see a need to use
      this novel software to analyze heart function relative to Hip status and Metal Ion levels.

      Patients with metal on metal hip prosthesis are subject to local and systemic release of
      cobalt and chromium ions which may increase the potential for locally aggressive ion-induced
      local tissue reactions such as pseudotumours, a type of Adverse Reaction to Metal Debris
      (ARMD) (2). Although there have been reports of local toxicity as well as cases of cobaltism
      (as seen during outbreak in Quebec of so called 'cobalt beer drinkers' cardiomyopathy)
      leading to cardiac and ototoxicity, it is unclear if chronic exposure to these ions can lead
      to impaired cardiac function (cardiotoxicity) in a well-functioning prosthesis.

      The majority of the blood cobalt concentrations reported for hip implant patients appear to
      range from approximately 0.2 to 10 µg/L, and based on our review of the available literature,
      should not pose an increased risk for the development of systemic health effects.

      The concern for systemic health effects is for the small number of patients with
      cobalt-containing hip implants with markedly elevated blood cobalt concentrations.

      Extensive evaluations of these 'cobalt beer drinkers' have found that poor nutrition and
      underlying disease states caused by severe alcoholism were likely significant contributing
      factors to heart disease in this particular population. However, there remains a significant
      concern that cardiac function could be affected in the long term. This is especially relevant
      as the majority of these implants are put in patients less than 50 years age.

      Cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (CMR) is the gold standard method to assess cardiac
      function in patients at risk of cardiotoxicity. In addition to assessing cardiac function,
      CMR enables imaging of inflammation, and fibrosis (which may be secondary to the ion
      deposition) in the heart which may provide more specific information about the mechanism of
      injury in these patients.

      The purpose of this study is to look at cardiac function in patients with a metal on metal
      hip prostheses.

      Recruitment: 30 patients in total (10 unilateral and 10 bilateral hip resurfacing patients
      and 10 non-metal on metal total hip replacement patients) will be recruited which should
      provide indication of relationship both between either instances and heart function, as well
      as compared to one another. All patients will be undergoing clinical cardiac MRI. All
      patients will have extra images collected during their MRI and these images will be analyzed
      to determine any relationship between heart function and the possible metal ion levels from
      the hip implant. As part of the scan analysis they will be required to also have a 5mL vial
      of blood collected. Ultrasound values will be retrospectively collected, for analysis of soft
      tissue reaction, from a previous clinically ordered ultrasound of the affected joint.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comprehensive cardiac function</measure>
    <time_frame>Minimum 5 years post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>Ventricular function</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cobalt and chromium ion level measurements in the blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to cardiac MRI</time_frame>
    <description>To see the level of ions in blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Unilateral Hip Resurfacing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who received either right or left total hip resurfacing procedure. This group of patients will undergo a cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (CMR).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bilateral Hip Resurfacing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who received both right and left hip resurfacing procedure on the same day. This group of patients will undergo a cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (CMR).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Metal on Metal Total Hip</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who received either a unilateral (one hip) or bilateral (both hips) non-metal on metal total hip arthroplasty. This group of patients will undergo a cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (CMR).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cardiac magnetic resonance imaging (CMR)</intervention_name>
    <description>Cardiac MRI is used to assess cardiac function in patients at risk of cardiotoxicity. In addition, Cardiac MRI enables imaging of inflammation, and fibrosis in the heart which may provide more specific information about the mechanism of injury in patients with high ion blood levels. Patients in all three groups (Unilateral hip resurfacing, bilateral hip resurfacing, and non-metal on metal total hip arthroplasty) will undergo a Cardiac MRI.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Unilateral Hip Resurfacing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bilateral Hip Resurfacing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Metal on Metal Total Hip</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Undergoing clinical Cardiac MRI

          -  Currently enrolled with either unilateral or bilateral MoM Hip replacement device

          -  Willing to sign Informed Consent Form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient does not meet all 'inclusion' criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul E Beaule, MD, FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Paul E Beaule</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H8L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kim PR, Beaulé PE, Dunbar M, Lee JK, Birkett N, Turner MC, Yenugadhati N, Armstrong V, Krewski D. Cobalt and chromium levels in blood and urine following hip resurfacing arthroplasty with the Conserve Plus implant. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2011 May;93 Suppl 2:107-17. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.J.01721.</citation>
    <PMID>21543699</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moon JC, Messroghli DR, Kellman P, Piechnik SK, Robson MD, Ugander M, Gatehouse PD, Arai AE, Friedrich MG, Neubauer S, Schulz-Menger J, Schelbert EB; Society for Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance Imaging; Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance Working Group of the European Society of Cardiology. Myocardial T1 mapping and extracellular volume quantification: a Society for Cardiovascular Magnetic Resonance (SCMR) and CMR Working Group of the European Society of Cardiology consensus statement. J Cardiovasc Magn Reson. 2013 Oct 14;15:92. doi: 10.1186/1532-429X-15-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24124732</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Messroghli DR, Greiser A, Fröhlich M, Dietz R, Schulz-Menger J. Optimization and validation of a fully-integrated pulse sequence for modified look-locker inversion-recovery (MOLLI) T1 mapping of the heart. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2007 Oct;26(4):1081-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17896383</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Diesbourg LD, Prato FS, Wisenberg G, Drost DJ, Marshall TP, Carroll SE, O'Neill B. Quantification of myocardial blood flow and extracellular volumes using a bolus injection of Gd-DTPA: kinetic modeling in canine ischemic disease. Magn Reson Med. 1992 Feb;23(2):239-53.</citation>
    <PMID>1549039</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 8, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

