<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02893982</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 102014-018</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2017-02248</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02893982</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>High Dose Rate Brachyablation of Primary Liver Lesions</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Therapeutic Dose Escalation Study Using Percutaneous Image-Guided Navigation for High Dose Rate Brachyablation of Primary Liver Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of this study are to demonstrate feasibility of an optimized, image-guided
      pre-planned workflow to deliver at least 25 Gy to the periphery of the target lesion while
      maintaining established dose constraints to normal tissues, and to determine the maximum
      tolerated dose (MTD) while evaluating treatment delivery, safety, and efficacy utilizing a
      pre-planned and optimized image-guided workflow for percutaneous HDR brachytherapy of liver
      lesions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary endpoints of this protocol are to demonstrate feasibility of an optimized,
      image-guided pre-planned workflow to deliver at least 25 Gy to the periphery of the target
      lesion while maintaining established dose constraints to normal tissues, and then to
      determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of navigated percutaneous interstitial HDR
      brachytherapy for liver lesions. Secondary endpoints include assessment of toxicity and
      oncologic outcome (primarily local control at the treated site) and exploratory endpoints
      will be supported by advanced imaging studies at the time of the treatment procedure.

      The 25 Gy starting dose was chosen as it has been shown to be effective at controlling tumor,
      albeit with limited followup. The promising outcomes noted at that dose are predicated on
      actually delivering that dose, hence the feasibility endpoint for meeting the goal dose
      delivery. While the other primary endpoint will be toxicity so as to avoid exceeding the MTD,
      this trial will treat more patients at each level to better characterize both toxicity and
      efficacy within a dose level (the therapeutic window). The investigators will attempt to
      escalate to levels that modeling would predict to have durable local control approaching
      100%.55 Dose escalation levels of 5 Gy were chosen to mirror other studies performed at this
      institution with SBRT
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 9, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>dosimetric coverage of liver lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Verify feasibility of HDR brachytherapy treatment and workflow for liver lesions using catheters placed under image-guided navigational techniques, to provide dosimetric coverage of liver lesions such that:
Minimum CTV peripheral dose ≥ 25 Gy (D100 ≥ 25 Gy)
67% or 700 cc Liver &lt; 5 Gy
Esophagus, stomach, bowel, or duodenum &lt; 15 Gy to 1cc, &lt; 12 Gy to 5cc, &lt; 9 Gy to 10cc, and 85 Gy in BED(2Gy) equivalent including current and prior treatment to 1cc
Spinal cord/cauda equina &lt; 8 Gy to 1 cc, or 75 Gy in 2 Gy fractions BED(2Gy) equivalent including current and prior treatment
Kidney &lt; 11 Gy, 200 cc &lt; 8.4 Gy
4. Spinal cord/cauda equina &lt; 8 Gy to 1 cc, or 75 Gy in 2 Gy fractions BED(2Gy) equivalent including current and prior treatment 5. Kidney &lt; 11 Gy, 200 cc &lt; 8.4 Gy Verify feasibility of HDR brachytherapy treatment and workflow for liver lesions using catheters placed under image-guided navigational techniques</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>maximum tolerated dose</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) for percutaneous image-guided navigated high dose rate brachytherapy for liver lesions.
Initial dose level; as above, minimum CTV peripheral dose ≥ 25 Gy
Dose level 2: minimum CTV peripheral dose ≥ 30 Gy
Dose level 3: minimum CTV peripheral dose ≥ 35 Gy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>severe toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Demonstrate safety of HDR brachytherapy for lesions of the liver, defined as an acceptable level of severe toxicity (both acute and late effects) in the setting of HDR brachytherapy treatment. Severe toxicity will be defined as ≥ grade 3 Clavien-Dindo scale surgical complication score within 30 days of treatment or by NCI CTCAE v 4.0 toxicity after 30 days that is at least possibly related to treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>local control</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess patients for duration of local control at the treatment site, as well as other oncologic outcomes including progression-free and overall survival.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>brachytherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>image-guided navigation of catheter placement for high dose rate (HDR) brachytherapy treatment of patients with primary liver lesions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>brachytherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>image-guided navigation of catheter placement for high dose rate (HDR) brachytherapy treatment of patients with primary liver lesions</description>
    <arm_group_label>brachytherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologic or radiographic proof of a primary liver malignancy
             suitable for radiation therapy.

          -  Lesion size ≥ 3cm in maximum dimension.

          -  Predicted survival of &gt;6 months.

          -  KPS ≥ 60 (See Appendix B).

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry, for
             the duration of study participation, and for 90 days following completion of therapy.
             Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this
             study, she should inform her treating physician immediately.

          -  A female of child-bearing potential is any woman (regardless of sexual orientation,
             having undergone a tubal ligation, or remaining celibate by choice) who meets the
             following criteria:

               -  Has not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy; or

               -  Has not been naturally postmenopausal for at least 12 consecutive months (i.e.,
                  has had menses at any time in the preceding 12 consecutive months).

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent.

          -  Formal evaluation by the Liver Tumor Program at UTSW: All patients should be fairly
             and prudently informed of their treatment options. To this end, all patients must be
             evaluated by the Liver Tumor Program at conference before brachytherapy treatment for
             discussion and consideration of other options for treatment of liver cancer including
             surgical resection.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a history of prior irradiation or other treatment to the liver or
             abdomen who after treatment on this protocol would have a cumulative dose to the liver
             or other normal tissues greater than the protocol defined constraints.

          -  Need or plans for concomitant antineoplastic therapy (including surgery, cryotherapy,
             radiofrequency ablation, chemo-embolization, conventionally fractionated radiotherapy,
             stereotactic body radiation therapy, and hepatic artery chemotherapy) for the protocol
             treated lesions except at progression. Adjuvant systemic therapy before and after the
             protocol therapy per section 4.4.1, and surgery or other ablative therapy is allowed
             for lesions appearing after enrollment to this protocol as per section 4.4.2 and 4.4.3
             is allowed. At least 4 weeks must have passed since the last directed intervention to
             the protocol-treated lesion.

          -  Germ cell or hematologic malignancies.

          -  History of Crohn's Disease or Ulcerative Colitis.

          -  Active peptic ulcer disease for lesions within 5cm of the stomach.

          -  Underlying hepatic cirrhosis with Child-Pugh class B9 or C

          -  A major psychiatric illness which would limit understanding of the proposed protocol
             treatment and consent process.

          -  Men and women of reproductive potential may not participate unless they agree to use
             an effective contraceptive method.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women.

          -  Patients with parahepatic extension of disease with direct non-liver visceral
             involvement.

          -  Abnormal laboratory chemistries

               -  Albumin &lt; 2.5

               -  Alkaline Phosphatase &gt; 5 X upper limits of normal (ULN)

               -  LT/AST &gt; 5 X ULN

               -  Total bilirubin &gt; 5

          -  Abnormal complete blood count refractory to treatment. Any of the following:

               -  Platelet count &lt; 75,000/ml

               -  Hb level &lt; 8 gm/dl

               -  ANC &lt; 500/ml

          -  Abnormal coagulation profile: INR &gt; 2 and/or PTT &gt; 80

               -  Patients who are on anticoagulation medication that may not be safely held for
                  the procedure (≥ 5 days for antiplatelet agents and warfarin; ≥ 24 hours for
                  low-molecular weight heparin formulations) will be excluded.

          -  Contraindications to general anesthesia

          -  Subjects receiving any other investigational agents.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Folkert, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Folkert, MD</last_name>
    <phone>214-645-2112</phone>
    <email>MichaelR.Folkert@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarmistha Sen</last_name>
    <phone>214-645-1477</phone>
    <email>sarmistha.sen@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Folkert, MD</last_name>
      <phone>214-645-2112</phone>
      <email>MichaelR.Folkert@UTSouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sarmistha Sen</last_name>
      <phone>2146451477</phone>
      <email>sarmistha.sen@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 9, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

