<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02891811</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AGMT_MM-2</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-000475-24</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02891811</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma Comparing KTd vs. KRd Induction Therapy and Investigating a K-mono Maintenance Strategy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase II, 2-armed Study in Transplant Ineligible (TI) Patients With Newly Diagnosed Multiple Myeloma (NDMM) Comparing Carfilzomib + Thalidomide + Dexamethasone (KTd) Versus Carfilzomib + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone (KRd) Induction Therapy With Respect to Response Rates and Investigating a Carfilzomib (K) Monotherapy Maintenance Strategy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Arbeitsgemeinschaft medikamentoese Tumortherapie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Arbeitsgemeinschaft medikamentoese Tumortherapie</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, 2-arm phase II, multi-center study to evaluate the overall response
      rate in newly diagnosed, transplant ineligible patients receiving 9 cycles induction therapy
      with either KTd or KRd followed by randomization to either carfilzomib maintenance treatment
      for 12 months or to observation only. Maintenance is given for 12 cycles or progression of
      disease, whatever occurs first.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Multiple myeloma, a clonal neoplastic proliferation of plasma cells, is the second most
      common hematologic malignancy and accounts for approximately 72,000 annual deaths worldwide.
      There are an estimated 11,000 deaths per year in the US and more than 19,000 deaths per year
      in Europe.

      This study examines the efficacy of carfilzomib (K) in combination with thalidomide, an old,
      well established first line immunomodulatory imide drugs (IMiD) in newly diagnosed multiple
      myeloma versus K in combination with lenalidomide in 1st line. This trial will also evaluate
      the adherence to and the safety of a thalidomide containing triplet by using a non-neurotoxic
      proteasome inhibitor. Moreover, weekly dosing of carfilzomib addresses the need for a more
      convenient dosing schedule. Finally, yet importantly, this trial will assess the efficacy of
      a less cost intensive triplet and a strategy to keep lenalidomide as backup for later lines..
      The second part of the study - after completing 9 cycles induction therapy with KTd or KRd -
      patients of both arms will be pooled and again randomized 1:1 stratified by induction therapy
      into two arms (K-monotherapy versus observation-only).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 10, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>36 weeks after start of induction treatment (9 cycles, each cycle is 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Overall response rate (ORR) will be assessed according to International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) criteria to determine the ORR in patients NDMM after receiving 9 cycles induction therapy with either carfilzomib in combination with thalidomide and dexamethasone or carfilzomib in combination with lenalidomide and dexamethasone</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of a carfilzomib monotherapy maintenance</measure>
    <time_frame>after 12 months of maintenance therapy or observation only</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility of maintenance therapy with carfilzomib will be investigated in comparison with observation only strategy by observing treatment and visit compliance (listing withdrawals, treatment/visit delays and drug modifications).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety (adverse events) of a carfilzomib monotherapy maintenance</measure>
    <time_frame>after 12 months of maintenance therapy or observation only</time_frame>
    <description>Safety will be assessed by the type, incidence, severity (CTCAE v 4.0), and relatedness of adverse events (AEs) to treatment and by the descriptive analysis of laboratory parameters related to safety. Adverse events will be summarized by presenting the number and percentage (as appropriate) of patients having any adverse event by body system, type of adverse event, and maximum severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (efficacy) of a carfilzomib monotherapy maintenance</measure>
    <time_frame>after 12 months of maintenance therapy or observation only</time_frame>
    <description>After 12 months maintenance treatment or observation overall response rate (ORR, ratio of the number of patients with CR to partial response (PR) divided by the number of all patients evaluable for response) will be analyzed descriptively and compared using a chi^2 test without continuity correction. A one-sided 97.5% confidence interval for the difference in ORR will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response</measure>
    <time_frame>after 21 months (9 months induction therapy and 12 months maintenance)</time_frame>
    <description>The updated IMWG response criteria will be applied for response evaluation in all patients; this also includes minimal residual disease (MRD) evaluation; thus, response rates will be assessed qualitatively and quantitatively; MRD testing will be performed in all patients achieving complete remission (CR) and in patients which are in a CR at the end of maintenance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 21 months (9 months induction therapy and 12 months maintenance)</time_frame>
    <description>To determine Overall Survival (OS) in patients with NDMM ineligible for transplantation receiving either KTd versus KRd induction therapy and sub-sequent being randomised either to maintenance arm with carfilzomib or to control only for a maximum period of 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 9 months induction therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Response rates will be assessed qualitatively and quantitatively (PR, VGPR, CR, sCR, MRD according to IMWG Rajkumar 2011)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability (adverse events) of induction and maintenance treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>after 21 months (9 months induction therapy and 12 months maintenance)</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability of KTd and KRd followed by randomization to carfilzomib maintenance for a maximum period of 12 months or observation only will be assessed by the type, incidence, severity (CTCAE v 4.0), and relatedness of AEs to treatment and by the descriptive analysis of laboratory parameters related to safety. Adverse events will be summarized by presenting the number and percentage (as appropriate) of patients having any adverse event by body system, type of adverse event, and maximum severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in quality of life (QoL)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 21 months (9 months induction therapy and 12 months maintenance)</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in quality of life will be analyzed by using the cancer patient-specific questionnaire EORTC-QLQ-C30. Measures will be calculated and analyzed descriptively, and compared between treatment groups using a Mann-Whitney U-test for unpaired observations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in quality of life (QoL) using multiple myeloma specific questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>after 21 months (9 months induction therapy and 12 months maintenance)</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in quality of life will be analyzed by using the multiple myeloma-specific questionnaire &quot;EORTC-QLQ-MY20&quot;. Measures will be calculated and analyzed descriptively, and compared between treatment groups using a Mann-Whitney U-test for unpaired observations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of general health status</measure>
    <time_frame>after 21 months (9 months induction therapy and 12 months maintenance)</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in general health status will be analyzed by using the questionnaires &quot;EQ-5D-5L&quot;. QoL measures will be calculated and analyzed descriptively, and compared between treatment groups using a Mann-Whitney U-test for unpaired observations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">146</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Induction Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Carfilzomib + Thalidomide + Dexamethasone (KTd) for 9 cycles (day 1-28) Followed by second randomisation: maintenance arm with carfilzomib monotherapy versus &quot;observation only&quot; arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Induction Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Carfilzomib + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone (KRd) for 9 cycles (day 1-28) Followed by second randomisation: maintenance arm with carfilzomib monotherapy versus &quot;observation only&quot; arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carfilzomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction treatment: Cycle 1 day 1+2: 20 mg/m2; days 8,9, 15 and 16: 27 mg/m2; Cycle 2: 27 mg/m2 on days 1,2,8,9,15 and 16; Cycle 3-9: 56 mg/m2 on days 1, 8 and 15; IV duration: 30-60 minutes; Maintenance treatment with carfilzomib (last tolerated dose on day 1 and 15 (± 7 days) of each cycle)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Induction Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Induction Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kyprolis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>100mg orally on days 1-28 in patients &lt;75 years of age at Cycle 1; 50mg p.o. on days 1-28 in patients ≥ 75 years of age at Cycle 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>Induction Arm A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>25mg p.o. on days 1-21 of each cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Induction Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>40mg p.o. on days 1, 8, 15,22 (± 1 day ) in patients &lt;75 years of age at Cycle 1; 20mg p.o. on days 1, 8, 15, 22 (± 1 day) in patients ≥ 75 years of age at Cycle 1, given 4 hours-30 min prior to carfilzomib</description>
    <arm_group_label>Induction Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Induction Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Able to provide written informed consent in accordance with federal, local, and
             institutional guidelines

          -  newly diagnosed, symptomatic multiple myeloma

          -  Transplant-ineligibility: age &gt; 65 years or patients not eligible due to comorbidities
             determined by investigator or patients not willing to undergo autologous stem-cell
             transplantation (ASCT) on personal preference

          -  Measurable disease, as defined by one or more of the following (assessed within 21
             days prior to randomization):

               -  Serum M-protein ≥ 0.5 g/dL, or

               -  Urine M-protein ≥ 200 mg/24 hours, or

               -  In subjects without detectable serum or urine M-protein, serum-free light chain
                  (SFLC) &gt; 100 mg/L (involved light chain) and an abnormal κ/λ ratio

          -  No prior treatment for multiple myeloma

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status (ECOG PS) of 0-1

          -  Patients at cardiac risk (NYHA &gt;II or pre-existing coronary heart disease or any other
             relevant cardiac complication) should be scheduled for a baseline echocardiography
             (ECHO) and can only be included if the left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) is
             ≥40%

          -  Adequate organ and bone marrow function within the 21 days prior to randomization
             defined by:

               -  Bilirubin &lt; 2 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), Aspartate aminotransferase
                  (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt; 3 times the ULN

               -  growth factor support for max 3 days allowed to achieve an absolute neutrophil
                  count (ANC) ≥ 1000/mm3 (screening ANC should be of required)

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 7.0 g/dL; use of erythropoietic stimulating factors and red blood
                  cell (RBC) transfusion per institutional guidelines is allowed, however the most
                  recent RBC transfusion may not have been done within 7 days prior to obtaining
                  screening hemoglobin.

               -  Platelet count ≥ 30,000/mm3

          -  Calculated or measured creatinine clearance (CrCl) of ≥ 30 mL/min. Calculation should
             be based on the Cockcroft and Gault formula: [(140 - Age) ∙ Mass (kg) / (72 ∙
             Creatinine mg/dL)]; multiply result by 0.85 if female

          -  Females of childbearing potential (FCBP) must have a confirmed negative serum
             pregnancy test within the 21 days prior to randomization (performed at a central
             laboratory).

          -  Females of childbearing potential and male subjects who are sexually active with FCBP
             must agree to use effective concomitant method(s) of contraception during the study
             and for 30 days (women) and 90 days (men) following the last study drug treatment
             administration.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  ECOG ≥2

          -  Frail patients

          -  Waldenström macroglobulinemia

          -  POEMS syndrome (polyneuropathy, organomegaly, endocrinopathy, monoclonal protein, and
             skin changes)

          -  Plasma cell leukemia (&gt; 2.0 × 109/L circulating plasma cells by standard differential)

          -  Myelodysplastic syndrome

          -  Smoldering myeloma and monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance (MGUS)

          -  Second malignancy within the past 5 years except:

               -  Adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer

               -  Carcinoma in situ of the cervix

               -  Prostate cancer ≤ Gleason score 6 with stable prostate-specific antigen (PSA over
                  12 months

               -  Ductal breast carcinoma in situ with full surgical resection (i.e., negative
                  margins)

               -  Treated medullary or papillary thyroid cancer

               -  Similar condition with an expectation of &gt; 95% five-year disease-free survival

          -  History of or current amyloidosis

          -  Immunotherapy within the 21 days prior to randomization

          -  Glucocorticoid therapy within the 14 days prior to randomization that exceeds
             accumulative dose of 160 mg dexamethasone or 1000 mg prednisone

          -  Extended field radio therapy (more than 3 fields) within the 21 days prior to
             randomization

          -  Known history of allergy to Captisol (a cyclodextrin derivative used to solubilize
             carfilzomib) or any other component of formulation

          -  Contraindication to dexamethasone, thalidomide or lenalidomide or any of the required
             concomitant drugs or supportive treatments, including hypersensitivity to antiviral
             drugs

          -  Active congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association [NYHA] Class III or IV),
             symptomatic ischemia, conduction abnormalities uncontrolled by conventional
             intervention, acute diffuse infiltrative pulmonary disease, pericardial disease, or
             myocardial infarction within 4 months prior to enrollment

          -  Active infection within the 14 days prior to randomization requiring systemic
             antibiotics and/or antiviral therapy

          -  Pleural effusions requiring thoracentesis within the 14 days prior to randomization

          -  Ascites requiring paracentesis within the 14 days prior to randomization

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension or uncontrolled diabetes despite medication

          -  Significant neuropathy (Grade 2 with pain or Grade 3 or higher) within the 14 days
             prior to randomization

          -  Known cirrhosis

          -  Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositivity, hepatitis C infection, or
             hepatitis B infection: subjects with past hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection or
             resolved HBV infection defined as having a negative HBsAg test and a positive antibody
             to hepatitis B core antigen (HBc) antibody test are eligible; subjects positive for
             hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody are eligible only if polymerase chain reaction (PCR)
             is negative for HCV RNA.

          -  Participation in another interventional study within the 28 days prior to
             randomization

          -  Major surgery (except kyphoplasty) within the 28 days prior to randomization

          -  Female subjects who are pregnant or lactating

          -  Any other clinically significant medical disease or social condition that, in the
             investigator's opinion, may interfere with protocol adherence or a subject's ability
             to give informed consent, be compliant with study procedures, or provide accurate
             information.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Heinz Ludwig, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Wilhelminenspital Vienna</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard Greil, MD</last_name>
    <phone>004357255</phone>
    <phone_ext>25801</phone_ext>
    <email>r.greil@salk.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Daniela Wolkersdorfer, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0043 662 640</phone>
    <phone_ext>44 12</phone_ext>
    <email>d.wolkersdorfer@agmt.at</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Universitaet Graz, Univ.-Klinik f. Innere Medizin, Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Graz</city>
        <zip>A-8036</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Siegfried Sormann, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043 316 385</phone>
      <phone_ext>81814</phone_ext>
      <email>siegfried.sormann@klinikum-graz.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pia-Carina Gallaun, BSc</last_name>
      <email>Pia-Carina.Gallaun@klinikum-graz.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Siegfried Sormann, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Med. Universität Innsbruck, Univ.-Klinik f. Innere Medizin V, Hämatologie u. Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Innsbruck</city>
        <zip>6020</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eberhard Gunsilius, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 512 504</phone>
      <phone_ext>80669</phone_ext>
      <email>Eberhard.Gunsilius@i-med.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eberhard Gunsilius, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bezirkskrankenhaus Kufstein, Innere Medizin, Interne II u. onkologische Tagesklinik</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kufstein</city>
        <zip>6330</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>August Zabernigg, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 5372 6966</phone>
      <phone_ext>3000</phone_ext>
      <email>august.zabernigg@bkh-kufstein.at</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>August Zabernigg, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>LKH Hochsteiermark, Standort Leoben</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leoben</city>
        <zip>A-8700</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christoph Tinchon, MD, DL</last_name>
      <phone>0043 3842 401</phone>
      <phone_ext>3402</phone_ext>
      <email>christoph.tinchon@lkh-leoben.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Manuela Maderdonner, BSc, MSc</last_name>
      <email>Manuela.Maderdonner@kages.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christoph Tinchon, MD, DL</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ordensklinikum Linz - Barmherzige Schwestern Linz, Interne I</name>
      <address>
        <city>Linz</city>
        <zip>A-4010</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andreas Petzer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043 732 7677</phone>
      <phone_ext>4555</phone_ext>
      <email>andreas.petzer@ordensklinikum.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Martina Lang</last_name>
      <email>studien.linz@ordensklinikum.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andreas Petzer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ordensklinikum Linz - Elisabethinen, I. Interne Abt. Haemato-Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Linz</city>
        <zip>A-4020</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sigrid Machherndl-Spandl, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043 732 7676</phone>
      <phone_ext>4428</phone_ext>
      <email>sigrid.machherndl-spandl@ordensklinikum.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Silvia Löschenberger</last_name>
      <email>silvia.loeschenberger@ordensklinikum.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sigrid Machherndl-Spandl, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kepler Univ.-Klinikum Linz, Klinik f. Interne 3</name>
      <address>
        <city>Linz</city>
        <zip>A-4021</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Fridrik, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043 5 7680 82</phone>
      <phone_ext>6195</phone_ext>
      <email>michael.fridrik@kepleruniklinikum.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Bettina Pfleger</last_name>
      <email>bettina.pfleger@kepleruniklinikum.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Fridrik, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ.Klinikum Krems, Klin. Abt. f. Innere Medizin 2</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mitterweng</city>
        <zip>3500</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Klaus Podar, MD, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+43 2732 9004</phone>
      <phone_ext>4456</phone_ext>
      <email>klaus.podar@krems.lknoe.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elisabeth Zwickl-Traxler, Mag.</last_name>
      <phone>4161</phone>
      <phone_ext>4161</phone_ext>
      <email>studienzentrale@krems.lknoe.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Klaus Podar, MD, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Landeskrankenhaus Rankweil, Interne E (Hämatologie u. Onkologie)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rankweil</city>
        <zip>6830</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alois Lang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 5522 303</phone>
      <phone_ext>2301</phone_ext>
      <email>alois.lang@lkhf.at</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alois Lang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PMU Salzburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salzburg</city>
        <zip>5020</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Greil, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 57255</phone>
      <phone_ext>25801</phone_ext>
      <email>r.greil@salk.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michaela Schachner</last_name>
      <email>m.schachner@salk.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Richard Greil, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Landeskrankenhaus Steyr, Innere Medizin II Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Steyr</city>
        <zip>A-4400</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Johannes Andel, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043 5 055466</phone>
      <phone_ext>24200</phone_ext>
      <email>johannes.andel@gespag.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Regina Neuhauser</last_name>
      <email>regina.neuhauser@gespag.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Johannes Andel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Univ. Wien, Univ.Klinik f. Innere Medizin I, Onkologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hermine Agis, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 1 40400</phone>
      <phone_ext>44570</phone_ext>
      <email>hermine.agis@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ursula Schäff, Mag.</last_name>
      <phone>+43 1 40400</phone>
      <phone_ext>44325</phone_ext>
      <email>ursula.schaeff@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hermine Agis, Priv.Doz.Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sozialmedizinisches Zentrum Ost - Donauspital, 2. Medizinische Abteilung</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1220</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Reinhard Ruckser, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 1 288 02</phone>
      <phone_ext>3202</phone_ext>
      <email>reinhard.ruckser@wienkav.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Elvira Kitzweger</last_name>
      <phone>+43 1 288 02</phone>
      <phone_ext>743261</phone_ext>
      <email>elvira.kitzweger@wienkav.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Reinhard Ruckser, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Univ. Wien, Univ.Klinik f. Innere Medizin I, Hämatologie u. Hämostaseologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>A-1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria-Theresa Krauth, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043 40400</phone>
      <phone_ext>44010</phone_ext>
      <email>maria.krauth@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Renate Schoder</last_name>
      <email>renate.schoder@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria-Theresa Krauth, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wilhelminenspital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>A-1160</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Niklas Zojer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043149150</phone>
      <phone_ext>2151</phone_ext>
      <email>niklas.zojer@wienkav.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Heidrun Forstner</last_name>
      <email>heidrun.forstner@extern.wienkav.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Niklas Zojer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Krankenhaus Zams, Innere Medizin, Internistische Onkologie u. Hämatologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zams</city>
        <zip>6511</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ewald Wöll, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+43 5442 600</phone>
      <phone_ext>7413</phone_ext>
      <email>ewald.woell@krankenhaus-zams.at</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Carmen Ruepp</last_name>
      <email>carmen.ruepp@krankenhaus-zams.at</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ewald Wöll, Univ.Doz.Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.agmt.at</url>
    <description>Sponsor</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 8, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>newly diagnosed multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>carfilzomib</keyword>
  <keyword>thalidomide</keyword>
  <keyword>lenalidomide</keyword>
  <keyword>dexamethasone</keyword>
  <keyword>transplant ineligible</keyword>
  <keyword>induction therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>maintenance</keyword>
  <keyword>Study Group of Medical Tumour Therapy (AGMT)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

