<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02890303</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MYN-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02890303</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective Multi-Center Study of Anterior Lens Capsulotomy Using the Mynosys Zepto System</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Multi-Center Study of Anterior Lens Capsulotomy Using the Mynosys Zepto System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mynosys Cellular Devices, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mynosys Cellular Devices, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate outcome in subjects who have elected to have Zepto capsulotomies
      during cataract surgery with phacoemulsification.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate outcome in subjects who have elected to have Zepto capsulotomies
      during cataract surgery with phacoemulsification to evaluate safety and effectiveness. The
      primary effectiveness endpoint is a complete capsulotomy in at least 95 percent of the cases.
      The primary safety endpoint is posterior capsular rupture and virtuous loss in 4 percent or
      less of the subjects. Other parameters to be captured during the study include anterior
      capsule tears, corneal touch, capsulotomy diameter, contraption of the Zepto capsulotomy,
      size of the corneal incision pre and post Zepto, interocular lens contraption and evaluation
      of zonular stability and the incidence and severity of adverse events. The criteria for
      patient success will be accessed based on the successful completion of a 360 degree
      capsulotomy without tissue bridges and no posterior capsule rupture and vitreous loss. The
      criteria for study success will be accessed based on a greater than or equal to 95 percent of
      the cases having a complete 360 degree capsulotomy without tissue bridges and less than 4
      percent of subjects with posterior capsule rupture and vitreous loss.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 12, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 14, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 15, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Capsulotomy</measure>
    <time_frame>During surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A successful complete Zepto capsulotomy is defined in this protocol to be one that results in a complete 360 degree capsulotomy without any residual tissue bridges visible to the surgeon. If there are such tissue bridges, the surgeon completes the capsulotomy manually.
The primary effectiveness endpoint was defined as :Complete capsulotomy (target ≥ 95% of cases).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Cataract</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Zepto Capsulotomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study will evaluate outcome in subjects who have elected to have Zepto capsulotomies during cataract surgery. Effectiveness Rate - An effectiveness rate of 95% complete capsulotomies provides reasonable assurance that the Zepto system is effective. Primary Safety Endpoint - Posterior Capsular Rupture &amp; Vitreous Loss (4% or less)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zepto System</intervention_name>
    <description>Anterior Capsulotomy using the Zepto System.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zepto Capsulotomy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zepto</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects must be age 22 or older,

          2. Subjects consenting to undergoing phacoemulsification and IOL implant surgery for the
             treatment of symptomatic age related lens cataract, and then electing to undergo
             ZeptoTM capsulotomy,

          3. Subjects must be willing and able to return for scheduled treatment and follow-up
             examinations for 3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Disease or pathology in the treatment eye that will compromise visual performance or
             refractive outcome (e.g. previous refractive surgery),

          2. Zonular abnormality,

          3. Posterior polar cataract,

          4. Fellow eye with acuity less than 20/200,

          5. Any prior ocular surgery of the study eye,

          6. Pupillary dilation during the pre-operative exam of less than 7 mm in diameter,

          7. Proliferative diabetic retinopathy,

          8. Disorders of the ocular muscles, such as nystagmus or strabismus,

          9. Chronic uveitis,

         10. Abnormal corneal endothelium,

         11. Subjects on medications with, in the opinion of the surgeon, significant ocular side
             effects,

         12. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women,

         13. Implanted ocular device or drug in the study eye,

         14. Any other condition, which in the judgment of the investigator would prevent the
             subject from completing the study (e.g. documented diagnosis or treatment for symptoms
             associated with dementia, mental illness),

         15. Current participation in another drug or device clinical study, or participation in
             such a clinical study within the six months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Christie, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Scott &amp; Christie and Associates P C</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel H Chang, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Empire Eye and Laser Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David F Chang, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peninsula Eye Surgery Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric D Donnenfeld, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lasik Garden City</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philip C Hoopes, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hoopes Vision</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Vukich, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Davis Duehr Dean Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Farrell C Tyson II, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cape Coral Eye Ctr Pa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vance Thompson, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vance Thompson Vision</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang DF, Mamalis N, Werner L. Precision Pulse Capsulotomy: Preclinical Safety and Performance of a New Capsulotomy Technology. Ophthalmology. 2016 Feb;123(2):255-64. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2015.10.008. Epub 2015 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26578447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carifi G, Miller MH, Pitsas C, Zygoura V, Deshmukh RR, Kopsachilis N, Maurino V. Complications and outcomes of phacoemulsification cataract surgery complicated by anterior capsule tear. Am J Ophthalmol. 2015 Mar;159(3):463-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ajo.2014.11.027. Epub 2014 Nov 26.</citation>
    <PMID>25461300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Agrawal V, Upadhyay J; Indian Cataract Risk Stratification Study group. Validation of scoring system for preoperative stratification of intra-operative risks of complications during cataract surgery: Indian multi-centric study. Indian J Ophthalmol. 2009 May-Jun;57(3):213-5. doi: 10.4103/0301-4738.49396.</citation>
    <PMID>19384016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ang GS, Whyte IF. Effect and outcomes of posterior capsule rupture in a district general hospital setting. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2006 Apr;32(4):623-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16698484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan FM, Mathur R, Ku JJ, Chen C, Chan SP, Yong VS, Au Eong KG. Short-term outcomes in eyes with posterior capsule rupture during cataract surgery. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2003 Mar;29(3):537-41.</citation>
    <PMID>12663021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Desai P, Minassian DC, Reidy A. National cataract surgery survey 1997-8: a report of the results of the clinical outcomes. Br J Ophthalmol. 1999 Dec;83(12):1336-40.</citation>
    <PMID>10574810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greenberg PB, Tseng VL, Wu WC, Liu J, Jiang L, Chen CK, Scott IU, Friedmann PD. Prevalence and predictors of ocular complications associated with cataract surgery in United States veterans. Ophthalmology. 2011 Mar;118(3):507-14. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2010.07.023. Epub 2010 Oct 29.</citation>
    <PMID>21035868</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hyams M, Mathalone N, Herskovitz M, Hod Y, Israeli D, Geyer O. Intraoperative complications of phacoemulsification in eyes with and without pseudoexfoliation. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2005 May;31(5):1002-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15975469</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ionides A, Minassian D, Tuft S. Visual outcome following posterior capsule rupture during cataract surgery. Br J Ophthalmol. 2001 Feb;85(2):222-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11159491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lundström M, Barry P, Leite E, Seward H, Stenevi U. 1998 European Cataract Outcome Study: report from the European Cataract Outcome Study Group. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2001 Aug;27(8):1176-84.</citation>
    <PMID>11524187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martin KR, Burton RL. The phacoemulsification learning curve: per-operative complications in the first 3000 cases of an experienced surgeon. Eye (Lond). 2000 Apr;14 ( Pt 2):190-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10845015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zaidi FH, Corbett MC, Burton BJ, Bloom PA. Raising the benchmark for the 21st century--the 1000 cataract operations audit and survey: outcomes, consultant-supervised training and sourcing NHS choice. Br J Ophthalmol. 2007 Jun;91(6):731-6. Epub 2006 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>17050577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simanovskii DM, Mackanos MA, Irani AR, O'Connell-Rodwell CE, Contag CH, Schwettman HA, Palanker DV. Cellular tolerance to pulsed hyperthermia. Phys Rev E Stat Nonlin Soft Matter Phys. 2006 Jul;74(1 Pt 1):011915. Epub 2006 Jul 24.</citation>
    <PMID>16907135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson VM, Berdahl JP, Solano JM, Chang DF. Comparison of Manual, Femtosecond Laser, and Precision Pulse Capsulotomy Edge Tear Strength in Paired Human Cadaver Eyes. Ophthalmology. 2016 Feb;123(2):265-74. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2015.10.019. Epub 2015 Dec 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26707416</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Auffarth GU, Reddy KP, Ritter R, Holzer MP, Rabsilber TM. Comparison of the maximum applicable stretch force after femtosecond laser-assisted and manual anterior capsulotomy. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2013 Jan;39(1):105-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jcrs.2012.08.065.</citation>
    <PMID>23245363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagy Z, Takacs A, Filkorn T, Sarayba M. Initial clinical evaluation of an intraocular femtosecond laser in cataract surgery. J Refract Surg. 2009 Dec;25(12):1053-60. doi: 10.3928/1081597X-20091117-04.</citation>
    <PMID>20000286</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trivedi RH, Wilson ME Jr, Bartholomew LR. Extensibility and scanning electron microscopy evaluation of 5 pediatric anterior capsulotomy techniques in a porcine model. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2006 Jul;32(7):1206-13.</citation>
    <PMID>16857511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Androudi S, Brazitikos PD, Papadopoulos NT, Dereklis D, Symeon L, Stangos N. Posterior capsule rupture and vitreous loss during phacoemulsification with or without the use of an anterior chamber maintainer. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2004 Feb;30(2):449-52.</citation>
    <PMID>15030840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mearza AA, Ramanathan S, Bidgood P, Horgan S. Visual outcome in cataract surgery complicated by vitreous loss in a district general hospital. Int Ophthalmol. 2009 Jun;29(3):157-60. doi: 10.1007/s10792-008-9214-6. Epub 2008 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>18401555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tan JH, Karwatowski WS. Phacoemulsification cataract surgery and unplanned anterior vitrectomy--is it bad news? Eye (Lond). 2002 Mar;16(2):117-20.</citation>
    <PMID>11988808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang JS, Chen IN, Chan WM, Ng JC, Chan VK, Law AK. Initial evaluation of a femtosecond laser system in cataract surgery. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2014 Jan;40(1):29-36. doi: 10.1016/j.jcrs.2013.08.045. Epub 2013 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>24269139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagy ZZ, Takacs AI, Filkorn T, Kránitz K, Gyenes A, Juhász É, Sándor GL, Kovacs I, Juhász T, Slade S. Complications of femtosecond laser-assisted cataract surgery. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2014 Jan;40(1):20-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jcrs.2013.08.046.</citation>
    <PMID>24355719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roberts TV, Lawless M, Bali SJ, Hodge C, Sutton G. Surgical outcomes and safety of femtosecond laser cataract surgery: a prospective study of 1500 consecutive cases. Ophthalmology. 2013 Feb;120(2):227-33. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2012.10.026. Epub 2012 Dec 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23218822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 31, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 7, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>September 5, 2017</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2018</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>This study enrolled patients at 8 clinical study sites, with symptomatic age-related lens cataract desiring lens extraction and IOL implantation. The last patient was enrolled in the study in December 2016.</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Zepto Capsulotomy</title>
          <description>This study will evaluate outcome in subjects who have elected to have Zepto capsulotomies during cataract surgery. Effectiveness Rate – An effectiveness rate of 95% complete capsulotomies provides reasonable assurance that the Zepto system is effective. Primary Safety Endpoint - Posterior Capsular Rupture &amp; Vitreous Loss (4% or less)
Zepto System: Anterior Capsulotomy using the Zepto System.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="100"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="100"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Zepto Capsulotomy</title>
          <description>This study will evaluate outcome in subjects who have elected to have Zepto capsulotomies during cataract surgery. Effectiveness Rate – An effectiveness rate of 95% complete capsulotomies provides reasonable assurance that the Zepto system is effective. Primary Safety Endpoint - Posterior Capsular Rupture &amp; Vitreous Loss (4% or less)
Zepto System: Anterior Capsulotomy using the Zepto System.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="100"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age, Customized</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="69.4" lower_limit="46" upper_limit="89"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="58"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="42"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>American Indian or Alaska Native</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Asian</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Black or African American</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>White</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="92"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>More than one race</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="100"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Intraocular Pressure</title>
          <units>mm Hg</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="16" lower_limit="7" upper_limit="35"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Manifest Refraction</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="96"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Uncorrected distance visual acuity (UCVA)</title>
          <units>ft</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="138" lower_limit="25" upper_limit="800"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Best spectacle corrected distance visual acuity (BSCVA)</title>
          <units>ft</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="40" lower_limit="20" upper_limit="400"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Slit Lamp</title>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>% of Normal treatment lids</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="97"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% presenting with 1 + Meibomian gland dysfunction</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% of Normal cornea</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="97"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% 1 + punctuate epithelial keratitis/ keratopathy</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% with Waite Beecham Lines - mild</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% with faint stromal scarring</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Fundus Examination</title>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>% with normal findings</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="87"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% presented with posterior vitreous detachment</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% with mild macular drusen</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% with peripheral drusen</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% with mild epiretinal membrane</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% with choroidal nevus</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% with post vitreous degeneration</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>% with a tilted disc</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Dilated Pupil Size</title>
          <units>mm</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8" lower_limit="6" upper_limit="9.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Complete Capsulotomy</title>
        <description>A successful complete Zepto capsulotomy is defined in this protocol to be one that results in a complete 360 degree capsulotomy without any residual tissue bridges visible to the surgeon. If there are such tissue bridges, the surgeon completes the capsulotomy manually.
The primary effectiveness endpoint was defined as :Complete capsulotomy (target ≥ 95% of cases).</description>
        <time_frame>During surgery</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Zepto Capsulotomy</title>
            <description>This study will evaluate outcome in subjects who have elected to have Zepto capsulotomies during cataract surgery. Effectiveness Rate – An effectiveness rate of 95% complete capsulotomies provides reasonable assurance that the Zepto system is effective. Primary Safety Endpoint - Posterior Capsular Rupture &amp; Vitreous Loss (4% or less)
Zepto System: Anterior Capsulotomy using the Zepto System.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Complete Capsulotomy</title>
          <description>A successful complete Zepto capsulotomy is defined in this protocol to be one that results in a complete 360 degree capsulotomy without any residual tissue bridges visible to the surgeon. If there are such tissue bridges, the surgeon completes the capsulotomy manually.
The primary effectiveness endpoint was defined as :Complete capsulotomy (target ≥ 95% of cases).</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="100"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="98"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>Adverse event data will be collected from Day 0 (once the Informed Consent Form has been signed) until 1 month post surgery. Data points include Day 0, Day 1, 1 week and 1 month post-op.</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Zepto Capsulotomy</title>
          <description>This study will evaluate outcome in subjects who have elected to have Zepto capsulotomies during cataract surgery. Effectiveness Rate – An effectiveness rate of 95% complete capsulotomies provides reasonable assurance that the Zepto system is effective. Primary Safety Endpoint - Posterior Capsular Rupture &amp; Vitreous Loss (4% or less)
Zepto System: Anterior Capsulotomy using the Zepto System.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="100"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="100"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="100"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Eye disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Epithelial Erosion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="100"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Macular Edema</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="100"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Anterior Capsule Tear</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="100"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Posterior Tear without Vitreous Loss</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="100"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Elevated IOP</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="100"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Ache in Treatment Eye</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="100"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Headache</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="100"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There IS an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Daniel Marinsik</name_or_title>
      <organization>Mynosys Cellular Devices, Inc.</organization>
      <phone>(510) 857-6296</phone>
      <email>dmarinsik@mynosys.com</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

