<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02151526</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HGB-205</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-000695-42</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02151526</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Evaluating the Efficacy and Safety of LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product in Beta-Thalassemia Major and Sickle Cell Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2 Open Label Study Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of Gene Therapy of the Beta-Hemoglobinopathies (Sickle Cell Disease and Beta-Thalassemia Major) by Transplantation of Autologous CD34+ Stem Cells Transduced Ex Vivo With a Lentiviral Beta-A-T87Q Globin Vector (LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>bluebird bio</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>bluebird bio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1/2, open label, safety, and efficacy study of the administration of
      LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product to subjects with either beta-thalassemia major or severe
      sickle cell disease (SCD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Success and kinetics of hematopoietic stem cell (HSC) engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of transplant related mortality through 100 days post treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection of vector derived replication-competent lentivirus (RCL) in any subject</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterization of events of insertional mutagenesis leading to clonal dominance or leukemia</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitoring of laboratory parameters and frequency and severity of clinical AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>AEs assessed by the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE), version 4.03.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantify gene transfer efficiency and expression by evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Therapeutic globin expression, as measured by assessing the ratio of beta A-T87Q-globin to alpha-globin in whole blood, as well as the amount of beta A-T87Q-globin as a fraction of all beta-chains in whole blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantify gene transfer efficiency and expression by evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Average vector copy number (VCN) in cell populations from peripheral blood and bone marrow containing the integrated LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>For all subjects, red blood cell (RBC) transfusion requirements (measured in milliliters [mL] per kilogram [kg]) per month and per year post transplant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>1-24 months post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>For sickle cell disease (SCD) subjects only, vaso-occlusive crisis (VOC) and acute chest syndrome (ACS) events in each subject compared with the 2 year pre-treatment period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">7</enrollment>
  <condition>Beta-Thalassemia Major</condition>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product (autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells transduced with LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector encoding the human beta-A-T87Q-globin gene)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product</intervention_name>
    <description>autologous CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) transduced with the LentiGlobin BB305 lentiviral vector encoding the human beta-A-T87Q globin gene
Subjects with beta-thalassemia major will undergo HSC procurement by bone marrow harvest or apheresis after mobilization with filgrastim, a granulocyte-colony stimulating factor (G-CSF), alone or in combination with plerixafor, as decided by the clinical transplant team.
Stem cell mobilization by is contraindicated in sickle cell disease (SCD), as it could induce a sickle cell crisis; thus, procurement of HSCs for subjects with severe SCD will be conducted by bone marrow harvest.</description>
    <arm_group_label>LentiGlobin BB305 Drug Product</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Be between 5 and 35 years of age, inclusive.

          2. Have severe sickle cell disease (SCD) or transfusion dependent beta-thalassemia major,
             regardless of the genotype with the diagnosis confirmed by Hb studies. Transfusion
             dependence is defined as requiring at least 100 mL/kg/year of packed red blood cells
             (pRBCs).

          3. Be eligible for allogeneic HSC transplant based on institutional medical guidelines,
             but without a matched related donor.

          4. Have been treated and followed for at least the past 2 years in a specialized center
             that maintained detailed medical records, including transfusion history.

             Subjects with severe SCD also must:

          5. Have failed to achieve adequate clinical benefit following hydroxyurea treatment with
             sufficient dosage, for at least 4 months unless this treatment was not indicated or
             not well tolerated.

          6. Have 1 or more of the following poor prognostic risk factors:

               -  Recurrent vaso occlusive crises (at least 2 episodes in the preceding year or in
                  the year prior to start of a regular transfusion program).

               -  Presence of any significant cerebral abnormality on magnetic resonance imaging
                  (MRI) (such as stenosis or occlusions).

               -  Stroke without any severe cognitive disability.

               -  Osteonecrosis of 2 or more joints.

               -  Anti-erythrocyte alloimmunization (&gt;2 antibodies).

               -  Presence of sickle cell cardiomyopathy documented by Doppler echocardiography.

               -  Acute chest syndrome (at least 2 episodes) defined by an acute event with
                  pneumonia-like symptoms (e.g., cough, fever [&gt;38.5°C], acute dyspnea,
                  expectoration, chest pain, findings upon lung auscultation, tachypnea, or
                  wheezing) and the presence of a new pulmonary infiltrate. Subjects with a chronic
                  oxygen saturation &lt;90% (excluding periods of SCD crisis) or carbon monoxide
                  diffusing capacity (DLco) less than 60% in the absence of an infection should not
                  be included in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Availability of a willing 10 /10 matched HLA identical sibling hematopoietic cell
             donor, unless recommendation for enrollment is provided by the Comité de Surveillance
             following a review of the case.

          2. Clinically significant, active bacterial, viral, fungal, or parasitic infection.

          3. Contraindication to anesthesia for bone marrow harvesting.

          4. Any prior or current malignancy, myeloproliferative or immunodeficiency disorder.

          5. A white blood cell (WBC) count &lt;3×10^9/L and/or platelet count &lt;120×10^9/L.

          6. History of major organ damage including:

               -  Liver disease, with transaminase levels &gt;3× upper limit of normal.

               -  This observation will not be exclusionary if a liver biopsy shows no evidence of
                  extensive bridging fibrosis, cirrhosis, or acute hepatitis.

               -  Histopathological evidence of extensive bridging fibrosis, cirrhosis, or acute
                  hepatitis on liver biopsy.

               -  Heart disease, with a left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;25%.

               -  Kidney disease with a calculated creatinine clearance &lt;30% normal value.

               -  Severe iron overload, which in the opinion of the physician is grounds for
                  exclusion.

               -  A cardiac T2* &lt;10 ms by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).

               -  Evidence of clinically significant pulmonary hypertension requiring medical
                  intervention.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-Antoine Ribeil, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>bluebird bio, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 30, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalassemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>beta-Thalassemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

