<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02152748</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KLI 394</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02152748</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Disease Progression and Treatment-induced Alterations in Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analysis of Disease Progression and Treatment-Induced Alterations in Glioblastoma - an Integrative Morphological and Molecular Approach</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Summary of scientific evidence and rationale of this project:

      Integrative molecular-genetic approaches have provided important insights in the biology of
      glioblastoma. It has meanwhile become clear, that glioblastoma is not a single tumor entity
      but comprises different molecular subtypes, which are associated with a distinct
      genetic/epigenetic signature and prognosis. Multimodal treatment approaches combining radio-
      and chemotherapy as well as the recent introduction of novel antiangiogenic agents have
      resulted in increasing survival times and improved quality-of-life of glioblastoma patients.
      Yet, despite these intense treatment efforts the therapeutic efficacy in glioblastoma
      patients is limited, leading in virtually all cases to tumor recurrence and death of the
      patients.

      As only a limited fraction of glioblastoma patients undergo second neurosurgery at tumor
      recurrence (&lt; 10%), post-therapeutic samples are rare and no systematic, large-scale studies
      exist, which address post-therapeutic morphological and molecular alterations in glioblastoma
      tumor tissue. Yet, these data would help to improve the understanding of mechanisms involved
      in therapy-resistance and tumor progression, to develop new therapeutic approaches and could
      pave the way for personalized treatment strategies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives of the project:

      The aim of this study is to analyze systematically morphological and molecular changes
      associated with glioblastoma progression and therapy-resistance in matched pre- and
      post-therapeutic glioblastoma samples.

      The following primary aims will be addressed:

        1. Morphological characterisation of changes in a large series of matched glioblastoma
           tissues pertaining to i. Vascularization and hypoxia-mediated factors ii. Tumor necrosis
           and chemoradiation-induced necrosis iii. Inflammatory response iv. Tumor cellularity and
           proliferation v. Tumor cell phenotype after treatment e.g. glial-mesenchymal transition

        2. Molecular analyses

           i. Transcriptomic, DNA methylation and genomic profiling will be performed to detect
           changes in gene expression, methylation and copy number aberrations in post-therapeutic
           as compared to pre-therapeutic tumor tissue. ii. The relationship between the
           transcriptomic, DNA methylation and genomic profiles will be analyzed.

        3. Exploratory analysis of associations between morphological and molecular changes in a
           screening set of 30 glioblastoma cases (with available fresh frozen tissues at first and
           second surgery) and subsequent validation of relevant findings in a larger glioblastoma
           cohort (150 cases with matched formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded tissues) by appropriate
           methods including immunohistochemistry, fluorescence-in-situ-hybridization, and
           sequencing.

        4. Special attention will be paid to gender-specific patterns of therapy-related changes
           and tumor progression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Morphology- based analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Histopathological workup and evaluation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Molecular analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of genomic alterations at DNA-, RNA- and methylation level</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Glioblastoma</arm_group_label>
    <description>The aim of this study is to analyze systematically morphological and molecular changes associated with glioblastoma progression and therapy-resistance in matched pre- and post-therapeutic glioblastoma samples.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>analyze systematically morphological and molecular changes associated with glioblastoma progression and therapy-resistance</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Glioblastoma</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Tissue
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All newly diagnosed GB patients will be identified in the Austrian population since 2007 -
        after the current firstline therapy has become standard, in order to warrant a homogenously
        treated patient cohort. GB patients with multiple resections will be identified.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adelheid Wöhrer, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University Vienna</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of Vienna, Institute of Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 2, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adelheid Wöhrer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr.med.univ et scient.med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>morphological and molecular changes</keyword>
  <keyword>progression</keyword>
  <keyword>therapy-resistance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease Progression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

