<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02155491</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TRI08889</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02155491</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Global Anticoagulant Registry in the FIELD- Venous Thromboembolic Events</brief_title>
  <acronym>GARFIELD-VTE</acronym>
  <official_title>Global Anticoagulant Registry in the Field Observing Treatment and Outcomes in Patients With Treated Acute Venous Thromboembolic Events in the Real World</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thrombosis Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bayer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thrombosis Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The protocol is a large registry to describe acute, sub-acute and extended duration of
      anticoagulation management, clinical and economic duration of anticoagulation management,
      clinical and economic outcomes in patients with treated acute VTE (DVT and PE) in the
      real-world setting.

      Main objectives are to clarify the:

        -  treatment related details for acute VTE (either conventional anticoagulation therapy,
           treatment with a direct oral anti-coagulant or other modalities of treatment)

        -  Rate of early and late symptomatic VTE recurrence

        -  Rate and nature of complications of VTE including post thrombotic syndrome and chronic
           thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension

        -  Rate of bleeding complications

        -  Rate of all-cause mortality at six months
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Other objectives are to clarify the additional outcomes of:

        -  Stroke (Measured by number of incidences)

        -  Transient Ischemic Attack (TIA) (Measured by number on incidences)

        -  ST Elevated Myocardial Infarction (STEMI) (Measured by number of incidences)

        -  Non-ST Elevated Myocardial Infraction (NSTEMI) (Measured by number of incidences)

        -  Unstable Angina (Measured by number of incidences)

        -  Quality of life and patient reported outcomes and costs associated with the management
           of VTE.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>3 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of recurrent symptomatic VTE (DVT and fatal or non-fatal PE)</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding events</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency, location, severity (classified as major or non-major)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by number of occurrences.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post Thrombotic Syndrome</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by number of occurrences and severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by number of occurrences and severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>IVC filter placement</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by number of occurrences.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Other urgent interventions for VTE</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by number of occurrences.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anticoagulation therapy persistence</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Estimation of Anticoagulation therapy will be compared to actual total time Anticoagulation therapy was used by patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause of mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Causes of death: PE, stroke, cardiac, cancer-related, other...</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>International Normalized Ratio (INR) Values in Patients treated with Vitamin K Antagonists</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be assessed by frequency of INR monitoring, and number of INR readings taken before patient achieved optimum range.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ischemic stroke, hemorrhagic stroke</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trans Ischemic Attack (TIA)</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by number of occurrences.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial Infarction</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by number of occurrences of both ST-Elevated Myocardial Infarction and Non-ST Elevated Myocardial Infarction (STEMI/NSTEMI).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unstable angina</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by number of occurrences.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life and patient treatment satisfaction over a three year period</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by Questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10000</enrollment>
  <condition>Venous Thromboembolism</condition>
  <condition>Deep Vein Thrombosis</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Embolism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prospective cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>In order to observe temporal trends in management of VTE a first cohort of 5000 consecutive unselected patients treated for acute VTE will be recruited. This cohort will take approximately 9 months to recruit. Potential patients must be assessed for eligibility within 30 days of their acute VTE diagnosis. They will be followed prospectively for 36 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prospective cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>In order to observe temporal trends in management of VTE a second cohort of 5000 consecutive unselected patients treated for acute VTE will be recruited. Recruitment into the second cohort will commence when recruitment is completed in the first cohort. This cohort will take approximately 9 months to recruit. Potential patients must be assessed for eligibility within 30 days of their acute VTE diagnosis. They will be followed prospectively for 36 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Sites will be selected at random from a representative list reflecting treatment patterns
        in each country. Consecutive male and female VTE patients at the randomly selected sited
        will be included in the registry if they meet the eligibility criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Age 18 years and over

          -  Treated first time or recurrent DVT (lower or upper extremity), PE alone or
             overlapping DVT and PE confirmed by appropriate diagnostic methods (patients must be
             assessed for eligibility within 30 days of diagnosis)

          -  Patients included with recurrent VTE must have completed treatment for the previous
             VTE episode

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients for whom long-term follow-up is not envisaged within the enrolling hospital
             or the associated primary care physician

          -  Patients participating in an interventional study that dictates treatments, visit
             frequency, or diagnostic procedures

          -  Patients with only superficial vein thrombosis (SVT)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ajay K Kakkar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Thrombosis Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Glorya Kayani</last_name>
    <email>gkayani@tri-london.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ravi Shukla</last_name>
    <email>rshukla@tri-london.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dr Terence Hart</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muscle Shoals</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35662</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrea Davis, RN</last_name>
      <phone>256-386-1105</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alice Arnold</last_name>
      <phone>2567102923</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heit JA. The epidemiology of venous thromboembolism in the community. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol. 2008 Mar;28(3):370-2. doi: 10.1161/ATVBAHA.108.162545. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18296591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen AT, Agnelli G, Anderson FA, Arcelus JI, Bergqvist D, Brecht JG, Greer IA, Heit JA, Hutchinson JL, Kakkar AK, Mottier D, Oger E, Samama MM, Spannagl M; VTE Impact Assessment Group in Europe (VITAE). Venous thromboembolism (VTE) in Europe. The number of VTE events and associated morbidity and mortality. Thromb Haemost. 2007 Oct;98(4):756-64.</citation>
    <PMID>17938798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eurostat, Eurostat statistics on health and safety 2001.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silverstein MD, Heit JA, Mohr DN, Petterson TM, O'Fallon WM, Melton LJ 3rd. Trends in the incidence of deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism: a 25-year population-based study. Arch Intern Med. 1998 Mar 23;158(6):585-93.</citation>
    <PMID>9521222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prandoni P, Noventa F, Ghirarduzzi A, Pengo V, Bernardi E, Pesavento R, Iotti M, Tormene D, Simioni P, Pagnan A. The risk of recurrent venous thromboembolism after discontinuing anticoagulation in patients with acute proximal deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism. A prospective cohort study in 1,626 patients. Haematologica. 2007 Feb;92(2):199-205.</citation>
    <PMID>17296569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kahn SR, Ginsberg JS. Relationship between deep venous thrombosis and the postthrombotic syndrome. Arch Intern Med. 2004 Jan 12;164(1):17-26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14718318</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prandoni P, Kahn SR. Post-thrombotic syndrome: prevalence, prognostication and need for progress. Br J Haematol. 2009 May;145(3):286-95. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2141.2009.07601.x. Epub 2009 Feb 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19222476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leizorovicz A. Long-term consequences of deep vein thrombosis. Haemostasis. 1998;28 Suppl 3:1-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10069756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prandoni P, Lensing AW, Prins MR. Long-term outcomes after deep venous thrombosis of the lower extremities. Vasc Med. 1998;3(1):57-60. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9666534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruppert A, Steinle T, Lees M. Economic burden of venous thromboembolism: a systematic review. J Med Econ. 2011;14(1):65-74. doi: 10.3111/13696998.2010.546465. Epub 2011 Jan 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21222564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacDougall DA, Feliu AL, Boccuzzi SJ, Lin J. Economic burden of deep-vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, and post-thrombotic syndrome. Am J Health Syst Pharm. 2006 Oct 15;63(20 Suppl 6):S5-15.</citation>
    <PMID>17032933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pengo V, Lensing AW, Prins MH, Marchiori A, Davidson BL, Tiozzo F, Albanese P, Biasiolo A, Pegoraro C, Iliceto S, Prandoni P; Thromboembolic Pulmonary Hypertension Study Group. Incidence of chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension after pulmonary embolism. N Engl J Med. 2004 May 27;350(22):2257-64.</citation>
    <PMID>15163775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hyers TM, Agnelli G, Hull RD, Morris TA, Samama M, Tapson V, Weg JG. Antithrombotic therapy for venous thromboembolic disease. Chest. 2001 Jan;119(1 Suppl):176S-193S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11157648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McRae SJ, Ginsberg JS. Initial treatment of venous thromboembolism. Circulation. 2004 Aug 31;110(9 Suppl 1):I3-9. Review. Erratum in: Circulation. 2005 Jan 25;111(3):378. Circulation. 2004 Dec 14;110(24 Suppl 1):IV33.</citation>
    <PMID>15339875</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kearon C, Akl EA, Comerota AJ, Prandoni P, Bounameaux H, Goldhaber SZ, Nelson ME, Wells PS, Gould MK, Dentali F, Crowther M, Kahn SR. Antithrombotic therapy for VTE disease: Antithrombotic Therapy and Prevention of Thrombosis, 9th ed: American College of Chest Physicians Evidence-Based Clinical Practice Guidelines. Chest. 2012 Feb;141(2 Suppl):e419S-e496S. doi: 10.1378/chest.11-2301. Erratum in: Chest. 2012 Dec;142(6):1698-1704.</citation>
    <PMID>22315268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adcock, D.M., Recurrence of thromboembolism: determining risk. Clinical Haemostasis Review. 2005. 19:1.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spyropoulos AC, Lin J. Direct medical costs of venous thromboembolism and subsequent hospital readmission rates: an administrative claims analysis from 30 managed care organizations. J Manag Care Pharm. 2007 Jul-Aug;13(6):475-86.</citation>
    <PMID>17672809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>KDIGO, Summary of recommendation statements. Kidney Int, 2013. 3 (Suppl):5.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 4, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 10, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 10, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 11, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>venous, thromboembolism, embolism, DVT, Pulmonary Embolism, thrombosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thromboembolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anticoagulants</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

