<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02159404</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ProtOmicsSeasons01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>KLI 425-B23</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02159404</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nasal Mucus Proteome and Immunotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Seasonal Differences in Nasal Mucus Proteome and Impact of Immunotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Graz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Graz</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nasal mucus as first line defense barrier of the nasal mucosa contains a variety of proteins
      that act as functional units. We recently showed that the nasal mucus proteome between
      allergic rhinitis patients and healthy controls is significantly altered.

      The aim of the present project is to show changes in nasal mucus proteome between allergic
      rhinitis patients and healthy controls over the pollen and non pollen season and to further
      determine whether and if so how the proteome changes under immunotherapy. Patients and
      healthy controls will be enrolled at two time points namely during the pollen season and out
      of the pollen season. Statistical differences will be determined within the groups and
      between the groups as well as impact of immunotherapy on patients undergoing therapy.

      Mucus will be collected with a special suction device equipped with a mucus trap. Then,
      proteomic analysis will be performed by LC MS/MS mass spectrometry. Database search will
      identify distinct proteins and their function, origin etc. will be annotated. Protein groups
      will be analyzed through pathway enrichment and cluster analysis. Furthermore, mechanisms of
      immunotherapy in responders and success or failure of therapy could be determined. These
      could lead to the identification of potential biomarkers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nasal mucus as first line defense barrier of the nasal mucosa contains a variety of proteins
      that act as functional units. We recently showed that the nasal mucus proteome between
      allergic rhinitis patients and healthy controls is significantly altered. On protein level,
      immune response in allergic rhinitis is enhanced and barrier function is reduced as reflected
      by increased epithelial permeability. Moreover, there is an unfavorable imbalance in innate
      anti-proteases. Proteases in pollen grain could therefore not be adequately deactivated in
      the mucus further damaging the epithelium which leads to submucosal penetration of allergens
      and facilitated presentation to antigen presenting cells.

      The aim of the present project is to show changes in nasal mucus proteome between allergic
      rhinitis patients and healthy controls over the pollen and non pollen season and to further
      determine whether and if so how the proteome changes under immunotherapy. For the first aim
      patients and healthy controls will be enrolled at two time points namely during the pollen
      season and out of the pollen season. Statistical differences will be determined within the
      groups and between the groups. The protein changes over the time course reflect how allergics
      but also healthy controls react to allergen challenge. The results should give insight on
      possible biomarkers that could be used for diagnostics and therapy. Protein substitution or
      inhibition may be a future therapy to reinforce the barrier function of nasal mucus and treat
      allergic rhinitis symptoms. The effect of immunotherapy as sole causal therapy will be
      determined and therapy responders will be compared to non-responders. We hypothesize that
      responders will show proteome changes similar to healthy conditions. This further concretizes
      distinct proteins as biomarkers that could be used as therapeutic agents. Moreover proteome
      changes could be used to predict and monitor therapeutic success or failure and patients may
      be stratified to be subjected to other therapeutic strategies than immunotherapy saving time
      and money.

      Mucus will be collected with a special suction device equipped with a mucus trap. Then,
      proteomic analysis will be performed by LC MS/MS mass spectrometry. Database search will
      identify distinct proteins and their function, origin etc. will be annotated. Protein groups
      will be analyzed through pathway enrichment and cluster analysis. By this means complex
      proteomic data can be visualized for a better understanding of global changes in protein
      networks and functions.

      Investigating the nasal mucus proteome in diseased and healthy state leads to a better
      understanding of its barrier function and reaction to allergens. Distinct proteins and/or
      proteins groups could be used as biomarkers for novel diagnostic and therapeutic approaches.
      Furthermore, mechanisms of immunotherapy in responders and success or failure of therapy
      could be determined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of protein spectra obtained by mass spectrometry</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Areas under the curve of protein spectra will be determined</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">88</enrollment>
  <condition>Allergic Rhinoconjunctivitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Allergic Rhinoconjunctivitis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with diagnosed Allergic Rhinoconjunctivitis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Immunotherapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Allergic Rhinoconjunctivitis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with Allergic Rhinoconjunctivitis Healthy controls
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  pollen allergy verified by skin-prick test, blood tests for specific IgE (RAST) and
             allergic rhinitis symptoms, eligible for immunotherapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  chronic infectious diseases, bad overall health condition, pregnancy, long-term intake
             of nasal and/or systemic steroids or antihistamines, acute and/or chronic
             rhinosinusitis and parallel participation in other studies
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Peter V Tomazic, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+4331638581347</phone>
    <phone_ext>+4331638583448</phone_ext>
    <email>peter.tomazic@medunigraz.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ENT University Hospital Graz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Graz</city>
        <state>Styria</state>
        <zip>8036</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ruth Birner-Grünberger, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Doris Lang-Loidolt, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tomazic PV, Birner-Gruenberger R, Leitner A, Obrist B, Spoerk S, Lang-Loidolt D. Nasal mucus proteomic changes reflect altered immune responses and epithelial permeability in patients with allergic rhinitis. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2014 Mar;133(3):741-50. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2013.09.040. Epub 2013 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>24290289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 5, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Graz</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tomazic Peter Valentin, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Conjunctivitis, Allergic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

