<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02150122</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ODIN/1213</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02150122</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dietary Requirement for Vitamin D in Adolescents Aged 14-18 Years</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Dose-response, Double-blind Randomised Placebo-controlled Trial to Estimate the Dietary Requirement for Vitamin D in Caucasian Male and Female Adolescents Aged 14-18 Years (The ODIN Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Surrey</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Surrey</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It is known that low vitamin D status is a very common problem in the UK. It is also known
      that a lack of vitamin D availability has potentially serious health implications, especially
      with respect to bone and muscle function. Much research has recently taken place to establish
      the vitamin D requirements of key population groups (i.e. pregnant women, the elderly, ethnic
      minorities). However few data are available describing the vitamin D requirements for male
      and female adolescents. The period of adolescence is a key stage of growth and development -
      poor nutrition during this time can have detrimental health consequences for a lifetime.

      No intervention studies have comprehensively investigated the vitamin D requirements of
      adolescents. The proposed ODIN Study will enable a better understanding of how adolescents
      respond to vitamin D supplementation and the most effective daily amount that will raise and
      maintain vitamin D status in adolescents during the winter-time. In addition, investigations
      into the mechanisms of action with respect to any differences observed across the doses of
      vitamin D and between the genders of the participants will also provide key information.
      Mechanisms of action will focus on genetic differences as well as differences in vitamin D
      metabolising enzymes.

      The results obtained from this significant study will not only inform the European Food
      Standards Agency (EFSA) with respect to their imminent deliberations regarding vitamin D
      recommendations. The ODIN Study will also inform the UK Department of Health's Scientific
      Advisory Committee on Nutrition (SACN), the wider scientific community and be a critical
      resource for key stakeholders (i.e. food industry, government health agencies) to collaborate
      in determining future public health strategies, thus potentially positively impacting on the
      health of the population for years to come.

      The investigators propose that the daily supplementation of 10µg/day (400 IU) and 20µg/day
      (800 IU) of vitamin D3 for five months will meet the vitamin D requirements of males and
      females aged 14-18 year and will be sufficient to maintain winter-time 25OHD levels above a
      range of thresholds between 30 and 50nmol/l.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 5 months of supplementation</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the vitamin D intakes needed to maintain serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25OHD) concentrations above the deficiency and insufficiency cut off thresholds (30nmol/l and 50nmol/l respectively) in male and female adolescents during the winter time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of genetic polymorphisms for vitamin D</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 5 months of supplementation</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the mechanisms (genetic/enzymatic) underlying the differences observed in the preceding objective via genotyping the participants for polymorphisms related to vitamin D metabolism. Secondary analyses will include evaluation of variations in the response to supplementation by single SNP variations and by the genetic vitamin D risk score. To determine, through transcriptomic (global mRNA) analysis of leukocyte samples, genome-wide differences in gene expression, in the adolescents in response to the vitamin D3 supplementation.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Family links in vitamin D levels and bone health</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the bone mineral density and vitamin D levels (in addition to the assessment of related blood markers and lifestyle factors) of the mothers of the adolescent participants, in order to establish possible familial links in the factors that affect vitamin D status and bone health.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D Concentrations (25OHD)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>10 micrograms (400 IU) vitamin D3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be given a daily supplement containing 10 micrograms (400 IU) vitamin D3 to take for 5 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>20 micrograms (800 IU) vitamin D3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be given a daily supplement containing 20 micrograms (800 IU) vitamin D3 to take for 5 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be given a placebo, similar in appearance to the vitamin D3 tablets, to take for 5 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin D3</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>10 micrograms (400 IU) vitamin D3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>20 micrograms (800 IU) vitamin D3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female

          -  Aged between 14 and 18 years

          -  Caucasian ethnicity

          -  In good health

          -  Written informed consent from the adolescent (and parent if required)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently receiving treatment for medical conditions likely to affect vitamin D
             metabolism

          -  Hypercalcaemia (&gt;2.5mmol/l)

          -  Regular use of sun-beds

          -  Having a sun holiday one month prior to commencing the trial or plans for a sun
             holiday within the study period.

          -  Use of vitamin supplements containing vitamin D - if the prospective participant
             agrees to stop vitamin D supplementation to join the study, a wash-out period of 8
             weeks prior to commencing the trial would be acceptable.

          -  Excessive consumption of alcohol (&gt;14 units per week for females, &gt;21 units per week
             for males)

          -  Smoking &gt;10 cigarettes per day

          -  Those following a weight-reducing diet or under dietary restriction (except
             vegetarianism)

          -  Known intolerance/allergy to the constituent ingredients of the daily supplement

          -  Clinically significant haematological abnormalities other than mild anaemia
             (Hb&lt;12.0g/dl)

          -  Active malignancy

          -  Pregnant or planning a pregnancy during the study period.

          -  Breast-feeding mothers
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan Lanham-New, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Surrey</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Surrey</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guildford</city>
        <state>Surrey</state>
        <zip>GU2 7XH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 29, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 1, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 1, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 2, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vitamin D</keyword>
  <keyword>Serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25OHD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescents</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholecalciferol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

