<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02150278</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PREVENCON</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02150278</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of an Intervention to Reduce Driving Under the Influence of Alcohol Among Drivers</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREVENCON</acronym>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of an Intervention to Reduce Driving Under the Influence of Alcohol Among Drivers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jordi Gol i Gurina Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Societat Catalana de Medicina Familiar i Comunitària (CAMFIC)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Associació Catalana d'Infermeria (ACI)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Associació Catalana d'Infermeria Familiar i Comunitària (AIFIC)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jordi Gol i Gurina Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: The main objective of this pilot study is to assess the feasibility and
      effectiveness of a brief intervention to reduce drinking-driving behavior.

      Methods:

      Design: Pilot multicentre before/after intervention study without control group.
      Participants: We aim to recruit, from 01/01/2013 to 01/05/2013, 212 drivers aged 18 to 65 who
      declared to have consumed alcohol previous to driving, at least once in the past 30 days.
      Intervention: Brief behavioral intervention to reduce alcohol consumption before driving.
      Outcomes: Frequency of driving under the influence of alcohol in the past 30 days, regular
      alcohol consumption (Audit-C test), level of self-efficacy and stage of change according to
      the Prochaska and DiClemente's Transtheoretical Model of Change, sociodemographic variables,
      driver's profile, chronic pathologies, long -term medications, level of self risk perception.
      Information will be checked against medical record. Information on a) frequency of driving
      under the influence of alcohol in the past 30 days, b) regular alcohol and c) level of
      self-efficacy and stet of change according Prochaska State will be gathered at one month and
      12 month post intervention. Descriptive bivariate analysis to assess the distribution of risk
      elements associated to drinking-driving behavior.

      Potential impact expected: This pilot project will determine the feasibility of making a
      brief advice intervention in drivers under the influence of alcohol in primary care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Driving under the influence of alcohol is one of the main risk factors for road
      traffic collisions since it alters driving ability and impairs human performance.
      Consequently, is very important to identify those drivers who drive under the influence of
      alcohol; furthermore, interventions are necessary to diminish drinking-driving behavior.

      Objectives: The main objective of this pilot study is to assess the feasibility and
      effectiveness of a brief intervention to reduce drinking-driving behavior.

      Secondary objectives include:

        1. To assess the effect of the intervention on stage of change and level of self-efficacy,
           at month 1 and 12 post-intervention.

        2. To assess the feasibility of this intervention by professionals and patients.

        3. To assess the effectiveness of decreasing the regular alcohol consumption at month 12
           post-intervention.

      Methods:

      Design: Pilot multicentre before/after intervention study without control group.

      Participants: We aim to recruit 212 participants. We included by random consecutive sampling
      drivers (with a valid driver's license) aged 18 to 65 with an open medical history in any of
      the 20 Primary Health Care participating centers and who declared to have consumed alcohol
      previous to driving, at least once in the past 30 days. Recruitment took place from xxx 2013
      to xxx 213.

      Intervention: Brief behavioral intervention to reduce alcohol consumption before driving.

      Measurements:

      At baseline, the following information will be gathered using a structured questionnaire in
      the face to face interview between the patient and the health professional:

        1. Frequency of driving under the influence of alcohol in the past 30 days. gathered as a)
           the number of times that the patient drinks any amount of alcohol previous to driving
           and b) the amount alcohol consumed previous to driving

        2. Regular alcohol consumption (Audit-C test) in units of standard drinks weekly consumed
           (UBE).

        3. Level of self-efficacy and stage of change according to the Prochaska and DiClemente's
           Transtheoretical Model of Change.

        4. Sociodemographic variables: age, sex, social class, educational level, marital status.

        5. Driver profile: Type of driver's license, driving experience, , weekly driving time,
           safety behaviours, collisions (with and without injury) suffered in the past year.

        6. Chronic pathologies and chronic consumption of medications associated to road traffic
           injuries

        7. Level of self risk perception. When possible, all the information will be checked with
           that specified in the electronical medical record of the patient.

      In order to assess the feasibility of the intervention we will undertake a survey among
      health professionals.

      Information on a) frequency of driving under the influence of alcohol in the past 30 days, b)
      regular alcohol and c) level of self-efficacy and stet of change according Prochaska State
      will be gathered at one month and 12 month post intervention.

      Analysis: A descriptive analysis of population will be performed. The distribution of risk
      elements associated to drinking-driving behavior will be described through bivariate
      analyses.

      Potential impact expected:

      This pilot project will determine the feasibility of making a brief advice intervention in
      drinking-driving behavior drivers attended in primary care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Enrolling by invitation</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of driving under the influence of alcohol in the past 30 days</measure>
    <time_frame>up to month 12 post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>We will gather a) the number of times that the patient drinks any amount of alcohol previous to driving and b) the amount alcohol consumed previous to driving</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stage of change</measure>
    <time_frame>Information will be gathered at baseline, at month 1 post-intervention, and at month 12 post-intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>: Stage of change according to the Prochaska and DiClemente's Transtheoretical Model of Change, also called The Transtheoretical Model (TTM) wich assumes that individuals change habitual behaviors through a cyclical process. It includes the following stages: precontemplation, contemplation, preparation and action, among others</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Regular alcohol consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Information will be gathered at baseline, at month 1 post-intervention, and at month 12 post-intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Regular alcohol consumption according to the Audit-C test in units of standard drinks weekly consumed (UBE). Information will be checked against patient's medical record.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Consumption</condition>
  <condition>Traffic Accident</condition>
  <condition>Risk Perception of Driving After Alcohol Consumption</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brief intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The brief intervention consist of one face to face minimal advice to reduce drinking-driving behavior and it was personalized according to the state of change of the patient (based on the Prochaska and DiClemente model). An additional informative pamphlet is offered to the participant. The intervention was done by the general practitioner or nurse that regularly attends the patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brief intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The brief intervention consist of one face to face minimal advice to reduce drinking-driving behavior and it was personalized according to the state of change of the patient (based on the Prochaska and DiClemente model). An additional informative pamphlet is offered to the participant. The intervention was done by the general practitioner or nurse that regularly attends the patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Brief intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  drivers with driving license of any vehicle with current validity

          -  People aged 18 to 65 years

          -  People attended Primary Health Care reported having consumed any alcohol at least one
             time before driving the 30 days prior

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  People advise against that approach: severe psychiatric illnesses and terminals

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of alcohol dependence

          -  Difficulty communication language

          -  Unstable demographic status: People residing outside the study area, traffic situation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos Martín_Cantera, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>IDIAP Jordi Gol</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carlos Martin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 29, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 28, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 28, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 29, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Driving</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol consumption</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk perception</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

