<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02041858</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00079765</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02041858</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Altered Alarm Settings on Patient Adverse Events and Alarm Signal Frequency</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Altered Alarm Settings on Patient Adverse Events and Alarm Signal Frequency: A Randomized Controlled Trial Feasibility Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Alarm fatigue, a lack of response to an alarm due to desensitization, is a national problem.
      The problem of alarm desensitization is multifaceted and is related to a high false alarm
      rate, poor positive predictive value, lack of alarm standardization and the large number of
      medical devices with built in alarms in use today. Cardiac monitor alarms are intended to
      notify the healthcare practitioner that a clinical crisis is imminent. However, hundreds of
      physiologic monitor alarms occur on monitored units each day. As a result, practitioners are
      highly vulnerable to alarm fatigue which has resulted in serious harm to patients and death
      due to staff inattention from alarm signal desensitization. Research indicates that 80-99.4%
      of monitor alarms are false or clinically insignificant. Alarm hazards is the number one
      medical device technology hazard of 2012 and has been listed by ECRI (Emergency Care Research
      Institute) among the top 3 medical device hazards for the past three years (ECRI, 2011).
      Delivering actionable alarm information to care providers is challenging given the
      significant number of false alarms.

      Ideally, alarms should activate for events in greatest need of clinical attention without
      increasing the risk of adverse patient outcomes. This is not the case with current monitoring
      technology which is designed for high sensitivity and low specificity. Practitioners must use
      clinical intuition for determining how conservatively alarms should be set to be most useful.
      There is no research evidence to support how best to set alarms without affecting patient
      outcomes.

      Quality improvement studies performed at The Johns Hopkins Hospital have demonstrated that
      the frequency of alarm signals can be reduced by more than 50% through an altered set of
      alarm parameters. This reduction in alarm signals has lead to an increase awareness of alarms
      that do occur as well as create a quieter, healing environment for patients. Although this
      change was not associated with a &quot;noticeable&quot; increase in adverse patient events, this
      important outcome was not rigorously studied.

      The specific aims of this pilot study is to determine if decreasing the number of alarms by
      using an altered set of alarm parameters has an effect on patient outcomes in an intensive
      care unit.

      This project may have a significant impact on patient safety. A decrease in noise at the
      bedside may result in less distraction to caregivers and may have a positive effect on
      patient recovery. It is expected that the altered set of monitor default parameters will
      result in a decrease in audible alarms without increasing clinically significant adverse
      patient events.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically significant adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>A variety of clinically significant events were assessed while subjects were on the protocol</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alarm Signals</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>The number of alarm signals were assessed while the subject was on the protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alarm-triggered interventions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>The number and type of alarm-triggered interventions were assessed while the patient was on the protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Physiologic Monitoring</condition>
  <condition>Alarms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control arm with organizational-based alarm parameter settings</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Altered Alarm Settings</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Altered set of alarm parameter settings.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Altered Alarm Settings</intervention_name>
    <description>An altered set of alarm parameter settings</description>
    <arm_group_label>Altered Alarm Settings</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: All patients who are in the Coronary Care Unit and able to provide
        consent during the collection time period will be considered for inclusion. This unit
        consists of adult patients with a primary cardiac etiology for their illness. The vast
        majority of these patients are either there for coronary artery disease or congestive heart
        failure.

        Exclusion Criteria: Patients who are unable to provide consent to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julius C Pham, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cvach M. Monitor alarm fatigue: an integrative review. Biomed Instrum Technol. 2012 Jul-Aug;46(4):268-77. doi: 10.2345/0899-8205-46.4.268. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22839984</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lawless ST. Crying wolf: false alarms in a pediatric intensive care unit. Crit Care Med. 1994 Jun;22(6):981-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8205831</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsien CL, Fackler JC. Poor prognosis for existing monitors in the intensive care unit. Crit Care Med. 1997 Apr;25(4):614-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9142025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chambrin MC, Ravaux P, Calvelo-Aros D, Jaborska A, Chopin C, Boniface B. Multicentric study of monitoring alarms in the adult intensive care unit (ICU): a descriptive analysis. Intensive Care Med. 1999 Dec;25(12):1360-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10660842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atzema C, Schull MJ, Borgundvaag B, Slaughter GR, Lee CK. ALARMED: adverse events in low-risk patients with chest pain receiving continuous electrocardiographic monitoring in the emergency department. A pilot study. Am J Emerg Med. 2006 Jan;24(1):62-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16338512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siebig S, Kuhls S, Imhoff M, Langgartner J, Reng M, Schölmerich J, Gather U, Wrede CE. Collection of annotated data in a clinical validation study for alarm algorithms in intensive care--a methodologic framework. J Crit Care. 2010 Mar;25(1):128-35. doi: 10.1016/j.jcrc.2008.09.001. Epub 2009 Jan 17.</citation>
    <PMID>19327311</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 17, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 17, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 22, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Julius Cuong Pham</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alarms</keyword>
  <keyword>Physiologic Monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Critical Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Alarm fatigue</keyword>
  <keyword>Adverse Events</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

