<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02043184</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01CA162401-01A1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01CA162401</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02043184</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Adherence to Oral Cancer Agents and Self Care of Symptoms Using an IVR</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Adherence to Oral Cancer Agents and Self Care of Symptoms Using an IVR</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Michigan State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Michigan State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Improving Adherence to Oral Cancer Agents and Self Care of Symptoms Using an IVR The goals of
      this study are to improve adherence to oral chemotherapeutic medications and self-management
      of symptoms among cancer patients. More than 40 oral agents currently are on the market with
      projections that in three years 30% of the cancer treatment agents will be delivered in oral
      form. As a result, patients must assume responsibility for taking medications and
      self-management of associated side effects.

      This longitudinal randomized trial tests and compares 'two strategies' for improving patient
      adherence to their oral cancer medication prescriptions to standard care. Both strategies
      incorporate symptom management support using an interactive voice response system (IVR) for
      symptom assessment and a printed evidence-based Medication Management and Symptom Management
      Toolkit (Toolkit) with helpful strategies and information for symptom management.

      We will collaborate with NCI Comprehensive Cancer Centers to recruit patients into this
      study. Recruiters will identify patients as they are prescribed oral cancer medications,
      present the study to the patient, and ask them to consent to be part of the study.

      Study Aims Following are the Aims of the study.

        1. Cancer patients assigned to the intervention will have greater adherence to their
           prescribed regimen: a) at week 4 (immediate effect), and b) at weeks 8 and 12 (sustained
           effect).

        2. When compared with patients receiving weekly assessments only, patients receiving weekly
           assessments plus daily adherence reminders and printed symptom management strategies for
           4 weeks will report: lower symptom severity during weeks 2-4 that will be sustained at
           weeks 5-8, and at 12 weeks.

      Two exploratory aims are assessed:

        1. To test how patient characteristics (age, sex, depression), dose variation, symptom
           severity, and concurrent infusion therapy moderate the impact of the novel intervention
           on adherence at 4, 8, and 12 weeks.

        2. To test the impact of the novel intervention on dose alterations, emergency department
           visits and hospital admissions over the 12 weeks in order to support the translation of
           this system into oncology practices.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design and Methods A unique feature of this study is that assessments, reminders, and symptom
      management strategies will be delivered by an Interactive Voice Response system (IVR). This
      system has been tested in a previous trial and in a pilot study of medication adherence; it
      received high satisfaction ratings from patients.

      All patients will complete intake (baseline), 4 week, 8 week, and 12 week interviews for
      symptom severity, depression, beliefs about oral agents, self-efficacy, and pill count.
      Following the intake interview a computerized procedure will randomize patients to one of two
      groups: experimental and control. Patients in both arms will receive 12 weekly assessments of
      adherence to their oral cancer medications and symptom severity delivered by the IVR.

      In addition, patients in the experimental group will receive daily reminder calls for 4 weeks
      delivered by the IVR. At the end of week 4 patients will be offered the option to reduce
      calls to every other day, or continue with daily reminders for weeks 5-8. Reminder calls will
      be tailored to the cycle of each medication. Daily reminder calls include a question to
      determine if medication changes have occurred. If this occurs, reminder calls are stopped
      and/or adjusted to the revised prescription. Patients in the experimental group will be
      mailed a Toolkit. Patients who report symptoms above designated thresholds during a weekly
      assessment call will be referred to the Toolkit to assist with self-management.

      The control group will not receive IVR reminder calls during the first 8 weeks. Control group
      patients, who report difficulty taking their cancer medications as prescribed, will be
      randomized following the 8 week interview to either receive 4 weeks of daily IVR reminder
      calls during weeks 9-12, or to continue in the control group. Patients randomized to receive
      daily IVR reminder calls will receive a Toolkit following randomization (and if during their
      weekly assessment calls they report symptoms above designated thresholds they will be
      referred to the Toolkit to assist with self-management). Patients randomized to continue in
      the control group will receive a Toolkit upon completion of the 12 week interview.

      Medical records will be audited for oral cancer medication changes during the study period as
      well as adverse toxic events noted, and scripts written.

      Implications &amp; Impact This research will identify and explore the factors (symptom severity,
      medication complexity, patient characteristics) affecting adherence to oral cancer
      medications and how symptom management might improve levels of adherence. This will allow
      patients to engage in their care and potentially transform the safety and quality of cancer
      care for patients on oral cancer medications.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication Adherence using pill count and self report</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication Self-Efficacy using Horne Measure</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>this assesses the ability to believe that they can adhere</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom Burden is determining the overall number of symptoms on the given symptom tool</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Given Symptom assessment tool is used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom Interference is the interference with daily activities</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This is an adaptation of the Cleeland Interference scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression using the full Clinical Screening for depression measure</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>we are using the CESD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Function using the Physical Function Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>We use the PROMIS physical function measure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Utilization is the use of Emergency room and Hospital admissions</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This captures the use during the 8 weeks and is Emergency room use and hospital admissions including length of stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">322</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostatic Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Breast Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care 12 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard care. Standard supportive care and Toolkit given at 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care 8 wks, Daily IVR 4 wks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Interactive Voice Response (IVR) Reminders Daily delivery for the last 4 weeks of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Daily IVR 8 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Interactive Voice Response (IVR) Reminders daily for the first 8 weeks of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Daily IVR 4 wk, Every other day IVR 4 wk</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Interactive Voice Response (IVR) Reminders daily for the first 4 weeks of the study and every other day for weeks 4-8.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interactive Voice Response (IVR) Reminders</intervention_name>
    <description>Reminders tailored to the oral cancer medication(s) the patients are receiving delivered by interactive voice response system with referral to a self-management guide when symptoms exceed thresholds.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care 12 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care 8 wks, Daily IVR 4 wks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Daily IVR 8 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Daily IVR 4 wk, Every other day IVR 4 wk</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  21 years of age or older

          -  Newly prescribed one of the designated oral cancer medications for treatment of cancer

          -  ECOG score of 0,1,or 2 OR Karnofsky score of 50 or higher

          -  Patient of one of the participating National Cancer Institute comprehensive cancer
             centers

          -  Able to speak, read and understand English

          -  Able and willing to receive phone calls

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Difficulty hearing on the telephone

          -  Limited or no access to a touch tone phone

          -  Cognitive deficits

          -  Hospice care at enrollment

          -  Those prescribed a hormonal therapy for cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Barbara Given, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Michigan State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles Given, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Michigan State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06520</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MSU Breslin Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lansing</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48910</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sparrow Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lansing</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 20, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 21, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 23, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Michigan State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Barbara Given</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>University Distinguished Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Medication Adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Administration, Oral</keyword>
  <keyword>Symptom Assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurobehavioral Manifestations</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral Symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Utilization</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mouth Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data will not be made available.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

