<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02046317</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSC-MS-11-0035</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02046317</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultrasound Guided Femoral Nerve Block on Isolated Femur Fracture Using Echo Friendly Needles</brief_title>
  <acronym>TUFFEN</acronym>
  <official_title>Trial of Ultrasound Guided Femoral Nerve Block on Isolated Femur Fracture Using Echo Friendly Needles</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For bone fracture injuries, particularly femur fractures, the femoral nerve block (FNB) can
      provide a fast and effective means to control pain. However, this method is not always
      employed due to the fact that positioning the needle and therefore the block can be time
      consuming and challenging, and if not precisely placed, the nerve block results in poor pain
      control. Traditional methods for nerve blockade include the blind technique and use of a
      peripheral nerve stimulator (PNS). Unfortunately, neither of these methods provide a reliable
      guide for needle placement and can lead to intraneural placement and/or failed attempts.

      Hypothesis: When ultrasound technology is implemented in this procedure it may improve the
      success rate when compared to other techniques by providing real-time visual guidance. This
      may result in a faster and prolonged pain relief reducing the amount of analgesics needed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To date, the published information regarding ultrasound guided femoral blocks using echo
      friendly needle is very limited. More so, there is even less information regarding ultrasound
      guided nerve blocks using echogenic versus standard of care needles.

      This study hopes to add to the general knowledge of pain management in the ED setting and
      provide a unique perspective on ultrasound guided techniques using echogenic needles to
      enhance accuracy and success rate of nerve blocks in ED patients. Results from this study
      will be compared to the results of other similar studies to see if these findings are
      comparative to relevant factors.

      The study design will have two comparative arms; in both arms we use the same local
      anesthetic which is Bupivacaine 0.25% with epinephrine; in all cases a total of 15 ml will be
      injected around the femoral nerve. Once identified with ultrasound 5 ml will be injected at
      lateral, medial and posterior aspect of the nerve. The experimental arm, will receive a FNB
      using an echogenic needle; and the control group will receive a FNB using standard of care
      needles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    No further enrolled patients, Primary researcher left the institution
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient pain level</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after initial femoral block</time_frame>
    <description>Pain level will be measured on a numeric scale of 0-10 with 0 being no pain and 10 being the worst pain ever. This study aims to determine if there is any difference in the success rate of femoral nerve block based on pain control between those performed with an echogenic needle and those performed with a standard needle.
The success of the nerve block is measured by pain control. Pain control is assessed based on a visual analog scale of pain 0-10. We are comparing nerve block success rates based on pain control</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Echogenic needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental arm will receive femoral nerve block using echogenic needles</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will receive femoral nerve block using standard of care needles</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Femoral Nerve Block</intervention_name>
    <description>Femoral Nerve Block for isolated femur fractures</description>
    <arm_group_label>Echogenic needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care needle</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years and older

          -  Patients who present to the ED with isolated femur fracture (no other injuries)

          -  Patients who are cognitively alert and are able to verbalize their pain using a visual
             analog scale (VAS)

          -  Patients who are mentally competent to consent for the study

          -  Patients who can communicate in English or Spanish

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Gestation

          -  Prisoners

          -  Patients who cannot communicate in English or in Spanish

          -  Patients who have other significant injuries besides a femur fracture

          -  Patients who are cognitively impaired and/or unable to verbalize their pain using a
             visual analog scale (VAS)

          -  Patients with allergies to local anesthetics

          -  Patients with severe liver disease

          -  Patients with existing peripheral neuropathies in the affected limb

          -  Patients with history of complications from previous femoral blocks

          -  Patients with contraindications for needle insertion at inguinal area

               -  Local signs of infection

               -  Patient on anticoagulants and/or with history of coagulation disorders
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos J Roldan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lyndon Baines Johnson General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77026</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Hermann Hospital Texas Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Beaudoin FL, Nagdev A, Merchant RC, Becker BM. Ultrasound-guided femoral nerve blocks in elderly patients with hip fractures. Am J Emerg Med. 2010 Jan;28(1):76-81. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2008.09.015.</citation>
    <PMID>20006206</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bijur P, Bérard A, Nestor J, Calderon Y, Davitt M, Gallagher EJ. No racial or ethnic disparity in treatment of long-bone fractures. Am J Emerg Med. 2008 Mar;26(3):270-4. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2007.05.010.</citation>
    <PMID>18358935</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brull R, Perlas A, Chan VW. Ultrasound-guided peripheral nerve blockade. Curr Pain Headache Rep. 2007 Feb;11(1):25-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17214918</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Deam RK, Kluger R, Barrington MJ, McCutcheon CA. Investigation of a new echogenic needle for use with ultrasound peripheral nerve blocks. Anaesth Intensive Care. 2007 Aug;35(4):582-6.</citation>
    <PMID>18020079</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fletcher AK, Rigby AS, Heyes FL. Three-in-one femoral nerve block as analgesia for fractured neck of femur in the emergency department: a randomized, controlled trial. Ann Emerg Med. 2003 Feb;41(2):227-33.</citation>
    <PMID>12548273</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Haddad FS, Williams RL. Femoral nerve block in extracapsular femoral neck fractures. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1995 Nov;77(6):922-3.</citation>
    <PMID>7593107</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Iamaroon A, Raksakietisak M, Halilamien P, Hongsawad J, Boonsararuxsapong K. Femoral nerve block versus fentanyl: Analgesia for positioning patients with fractured femur. Local Reg Anesth. 2010;3:21-6. Epub 2010 Mar 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22915864</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee JS, Hobden E, Stiell IG, Wells GA. Clinically important change in the visual analog scale after adequate pain control. Acad Emerg Med. 2003 Oct;10(10):1128-30.</citation>
    <PMID>14525749</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Marhofer P, Chan VW. Ultrasound-guided regional anesthesia: current concepts and future trends. Anesth Analg. 2007 May;104(5):1265-9, tables of contents. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17456684</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Marhofer P, Schrögendorfer K, Wallner T, Koinig H, Mayer N, Kapral S. Ultrasonographic guidance reduces the amount of local anesthetic for 3-in-1 blocks. Reg Anesth Pain Med. 1998 Nov-Dec;23(6):584-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9840855</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Marhofer P, Schrögendorfer K, Koinig H, Kapral S, Weinstabl C, Mayer N. Ultrasonographic guidance improves sensory block and onset time of three-in-one blocks. Anesth Analg. 1997 Oct;85(4):854-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9322469</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moher D, Dulberg CS, Wells GA. Statistical power, sample size, and their reporting in randomized controlled trials. JAMA. 1994 Jul 13;272(2):122-4.</citation>
    <PMID>8015121</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mutty CE, Jensen EJ, Manka MA Jr, Anders MJ, Bone LB. Femoral nerve block for diaphyseal and distal femoral fractures in the emergency department. Surgical technique. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2008 Oct;90 Suppl 2 Pt 2:218-26. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.H.00314.</citation>
    <PMID>18829935</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Saygi B, Ozkan K, Eceviz E, Tetik C, Sen C. Skin traction and placebo effect in the preoperative pain control of patients with collum and intertrochanteric femur fractures. Bull NYU Hosp Jt Dis. 2010;68(1):15-7.</citation>
    <PMID>20345356</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Terrell KM, Hui SL, Castelluccio P, Kroenke K, McGrath RB, Miller DK. Analgesic prescribing for patients who are discharged from an emergency department. Pain Med. 2010 Jul;11(7):1072-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1526-4637.2010.00884.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20642733</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tondare AS, Nadkarni AV. Femoral nerve block for fractured shaft of femur. Can Anaesth Soc J. 1982 May;29(3):270-1.</citation>
    <PMID>7074406</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 27, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carlos Roldan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor - Emergency Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Femoral Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

