<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02045251</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IM.AS1.33</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02045251</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Open-Label Trial Of Reduced- Dose Pylera, Amoxicillin, and Esomeprazole in the Treatment Of Helicobacter Pylori Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>AN OPEN-LABEL TRIAL OF REDUCED- DOSE PYLERA (BISMUTH, METRONIDAZOLE, TETRACYCLINE), AMOXICILLIN, AND ESOMEPRAZOLE IN THE TREATMENT OF HELICOBACTER PYLORI INFECTION</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>American University of Beirut Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>American University of Beirut Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Over the years, it has become clear that the first-line triple therapy is losing efficacy
      worldwide. A capsule containing 3 agents (Pylera®) containing 125mg metronidazole, 140mg
      bismuth subcitrate potassium, and 125mg tetracycline was made available.

      The efficacy of the Pylera capsule was studied in a randomized control trial, in which a
      quadruple Pylera therapy (Pylera capsule and a PPI) was evaluated against the standard triple
      regimen. In the study, 3 three-in-one capsules were taken four times daily (after meals and
      at bedtime).

      Given the above, we aim at assessing the effectiveness of fewer pills per day of the Pylera
      capsule (3 Pylera capsules supplemented with the addition of amoxicillin and esomeprazole
      twice daily; sum of 10 pills/day for 10 days) in the eradication of H. pylori.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ABSTRACT

      Infection with H. pylori has been linked with chronic active gastritis, peptic ulcer disease,
      adenocarcinoma and Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma of the stomach. Eradication of this organism has
      been recommended for patients with peptic ulcer disease, low-grade gastric mucosa-associated
      lymphoid tissue lymphoma, atrophic gastritis, unexplained iron deficiency anemia, chronic
      idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura, as well as first-degree relatives of gastric cancer
      patients. Guidelines still recommend using triple therapy regimen of PPI, clarithromycin and
      amoxicillin/metronidazole twice daily for 7 to 14 days. Over the years, it has become clear
      that the first-line triple therapy is losing efficacy worldwide with per protocol (PP) and
      intent-to-treat (ITT) eradication rates of less than 80%. In light of the low eradication
      rates of this regimen, quadruple regimens (bismuth and non bismuth based) or alternative
      fluoroquinolones-based regimens evolved in an attempt to increase the eradication of H.
      pylori. Most of the new quadruple regimens are clarithromycin-based. Quadruple therapies
      improved eradication rates to 85-90% but the increasing resistance of H. pylori to
      clarithromycin rendered the above-mentioned regimens suboptimal. Many attempts to increase
      the number of antibiotics in treatment regimens were faced with intolerability by patients of
      the large number of pills and increasing side effects (metallic taste, nausea, etc.).
      Considering the above, a capsule containing 3 agents (Pylera®) containing 125mg
      metronidazole, 140mg bismuth subcitrate potassium, and 125mg tetracycline was made available.
      The importance of such capsule lies in the 3 in 1 packaging and in the avoidance of
      clarithromycin use and hence the low risk of resistance. The efficacy of the Pylera capsule
      was studied in a randomized control trial, in which a quadruple Pylera therapy (Pylera
      capsule and a PPI) was evaluated against the standard triple regimen. In the study, 3
      three-in-one capsules were taken four times daily (after meals and at bedtime). An omeprazole
      capsule was taken with the three single three-in-one capsules after morning and evening
      meals. Quadruple therapy (Pylera-based) provided superior eradication rates when compared to
      the standard triple therapy (as high as 80% eradication rate versus 55% on ITT) with similar
      safety and tolerability [1]. In the aforementioned study, patients on quadruple therapy were
      taking the sum of 14 pills per day. This big number of pills per day is too high and may
      threaten compliance and adherence in real life situations outside of controlled clinical
      trials. This is evidenced by the difference in the PP and ITT eradication rates (93% and 80%
      respectively) that can be attributed to the load of pill load.

      The sensitivity of H. pylori to tetracycline and amoxicillin is very high and resistance is
      approximately zero [2]. Our local data in Lebanon show essentially no resistance to
      tetracycline or amoxicillin and a modest rate of metronidazole resistance, similar to Western
      countries (Fig 1). The use of these antibiotics to treat H. pylori infection is promising. In
      addition, we have recently shown in 2 separate randomized controlled trials that the reduced
      or half-dose of antibiotics (including 500 mg bid of amoxicillin and 250 mg bid of
      metronidazole) can achieve the same eradication of H. pylori at reduced cost and reduced side
      effects.

      Fig 1. In vitro Susceptibility of H. Pylori in Lebanon. Sharara AI, et al. Int J Antimicrob
      Agents 2000; 19:155-8.

      Our studies have shown a declining rate of H. pylori eradication with conventional triple
      therapy over time (Fig2).

      Fig 2. 10-day Legacy Triple Therapy in Lebanon. Soweid A, et al. ACG 2005 [abstract]; Mansour
      N, et al, Sharara AI. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol 2011

      Given the above, we aim at assessing the effectiveness of fewer pills per day of the Pylera
      capsule (3 Pylera capsules supplemented with the addition of amoxicillin and esomeprazole
      twice daily; sum of 10 pills/day for 10 days) in the eradication of H. pylori. The total dose
      of drugs is shown in Figure 3.

      One hundred patients from the outpatient department and the endoscopy unit at AUBMC will be
      enrolled in this open-label single arm trial. Patients with positive CLO tests or urea breath
      tests, or histological documentation of H. pylori infection, will be enrolled in the study.
      The patients will be followed up by phone calls on day 10 for side effects and for pill
      count. Patients will be assessed for the presence of these side effects at the end of the
      treatment (Day 10). A urea breath test will be done for all patients after ≥ 4 weeks of
      therapy completion and a minimum of 2 weeks of PPI therapy to evaluate eradication rates

      Eradication rate will be assessed periodically (every 10 patients) to confirm efficacy with
      stop points as follows:

      Patients 1-10: &lt;60% eradication Patients 1-20: &lt;65% eradication Patients 1-30: &lt;70%
      eradication Patients 1-40: &lt;75%eradication Patients 1-50: &lt;80% eradication

      Fig 3. Doses of drugs of the proposed Pylera regimen compared to the previously studied
      full-dose and half-dose quadruple (non-bismuth based) regimens.

      Study Description:

      A- Objective:

      The objective of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of the 4 tablets (2 capsules
      containing metronidazole, bismuth, and tetracycline) plus amoxicillin and esomeprazole) given
      twice a day for 10 days in the eradication of H. pylori. The primary end point is H. pylori
      eradication rate on ITT and PP analysis. Secondary endpoints include: (1) tolerability, (2)
      adverse events of the drug regimen, (3) and cost.

      B- Patient population:

      One hundred patients from the outpatient department and the endoscopy unit at AUBMC will be
      enrolled in this open-label trial.

        -  Inclusion criteria Patients with either positive CLO tests, urea breath tests, or
           histopathologic documention of H. pylori infection, and agreeing to the study by signing
           the informed consent.

        -  Exclusion criteria

             -  Age under 18 or older than 80 years

             -  Allergies to any of the drugs used

             -  Recent antibiotic therapy (within 2 weeks of enrollement)

             -  Severe ulcers or bleeding

             -  Gastric perforation or obstruction

             -  Previous gastrectomy

             -  Gastric cancer

             -  Pregnancy or lactation

             -  Prior eradication therapy for H. pylori

             -  Severe concomitant disease or condition making the treatment unlikely to be
                effective i.e. alcoholism, drug addiction, and history of poor compliance.

      C- Design and methods:

      After documentation of the H. pylori infection, the primary physician will introduce the
      patient to the research fellow who will give to the patients a clear explanation of the
      purpose of the study, risks, and benefits. Those who agree to participate and sign the
      informed consent will be enrolled in our study. All patients will take the treatment for ten
      days. The patients will be assessed for side effects on days 5 and 10 of the treatment
      regimen. The eradication rate will be assessed periodically (every 10 patients for the first
      50 patients) for efficacy and the study will be stopped if the target rates are not met. The
      Pylera tablets will be provided free to patients. However, the amoxicillin and esomeprazole
      are not provided freely.

      Patients will be taking:

        -  3 Pylera capsules b.i.d (per capsule: 125mg metronidazole, 125mg tetracycline, 140mg
           bismuth; i.e. 250mg metronidazole, 250 tetracycline, and 280mg bismuth b.i.d)

        -  Amoxicillin (Amoxil®) 500 g b.i.d.

        -  PPI (Esomeprazole 20mg b.i.d)

      Compliance and potential side effects will be evaluated by phone calls (day 10) during and
      shortly after the treatment period. After a minimum of 4 weeks of therapy completion,
      patients will be asked to present for a urea breath test free of charge in order to evaluate
      the eradication rate of H. pylori. All patients should be off any PPI for at least two weeks
      before testing.

      D- Statistical Interpretation:

      Efficacy of eradication of each group will be evaluated directly from the quotient of the
      patients with negative urea breath test over the total number of patients enrolled in that
      group. Success of therapy will be evaluated according to intent-to treat and per-protocol
      analyses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Unavailability of clarithromycin 250 mg in the market
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Helicobacter pylori eradication</measure>
    <time_frame>Eradication</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of eradication of H. pylori using the proposed regimen</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 10 (at the end of treatment)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of side effects of the new regimen</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Treatment of H. Pylori Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will have 100 patients receiving the proposed Pylera based regimen for 10 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pylera based reduced regimen</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with H. pylori infection will be treated with a 10 day course of reduced Pylera based regimen.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients with either positive CLO tests, urea breath tests, or histopathologic documention
        of H. pylori infection, and agreeing to the study by signing the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age under 18 or older than 80 years

          -  Allergies to any of the drugs used

          -  Recent antibiotic therapy (within 2 weeks of enrollement)

          -  Severe ulcers or bleeding

          -  Gastric perforation or obstruction

          -  Previous gastrectomy

          -  Gastric cancer

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  Prior eradication therapy for H. pylori

          -  Severe concomitant disease or condition making the treatment unlikely to be effective
             i.e. alcoholism, drug addiction, and history of poor compliance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>American University of Beirut Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beirut</city>
        <zip>00961</zip>
        <country>Lebanon</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Lebanon</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 22, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 24, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 14, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 14, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Helicobacter pylori</keyword>
  <keyword>H. pylori</keyword>
  <keyword>Pylera</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Helicobacter Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amoxicillin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esomeprazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

