<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02671058</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CINC-2015-BA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02671058</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetics and Bioavailability of Hydrocortisone Acetate Suppositories</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Open Label, Crossover Study Pharmacokinetics and Bioavailability of Hydrocortisone Acetate Administered as a Suppository With the Sephure® Rectal Suppository Applicator Compared With Cortenema in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cristcot LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Parexel</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cristcot LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will be an open label, single dose, randomized, 2 way (2 period) crossover study
      in healthy adult subjects at a single study center.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be an open label, single dose, randomized, 2 way (2 period) crossover study
      in healthy adult subjects at a single study center. Screening evaluations will occur from Day
      28 to Day 2 and subjects will be confined to the clinical research unit (CRU) from Day 1 to
      Day 2 for each treatment period. The treatment periods will be separated by at least a 7 day
      washout period. Subjects meeting the study enrollment criteria will be randomly assigned to 1
      of 2 sequences (AB or BA) on Day 1 of Treatment Period 1 and will receive either the
      reference product (A) or the treatment product (B) once during the study
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 24, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 24, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>primary PK endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>at time 0,1, 2 and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum plasma concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>primary PK endpoints</measure>
    <time_frame>at time 0,1, 2 and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the concentration-time curve</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cortenema</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hydrocortisone retention enema (Cortenema) administered rectally as a single dose; each dose unit delivers 100 mg of hydrocortisone per 60 mL.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hydrocortisone acetate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hydrocortisone acetate suppository 90 mg administered rectally as a single dose with the Sephure Rectal Suppository Applicator</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cortenema</intervention_name>
    <description>Hydrocortisone Administered as a Liquid Enema</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cortenema</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydrocortisone Acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>Hydrocortisone Acetate Administered as a Suppository with the Sephure® Rectal Suppository Applicator</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hydrocortisone acetate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy male and female subjects between 18 to 45 years of age, inclusive, at the time
             of Screening.

          2. Female subjects must be:

             Of non childbearing potential (surgically sterile [hysterectomy, oophorectomy or
             bilateral tubal ligation] or post-menopausal &gt;1 year with follicle stimulating hormone
             [FSH] &gt; 40 U/L), or Non pregnant, non lactating females of childbearing potential who
             are able and willing to undertake adequate measures to prevent a pregnancy including
             the use of any medically acceptable forms of birth control by the subject or partner
             (hormonal birth control, abstinence, diaphragm with spermicide, condom with
             spermicide, intrauterine device, vasectomy or surgical sterilization) from Screening
             until the End of Study.

          3. Male subjects must be able and willing to undertake adequate measures to prevent a
             pregnancy throughout the study including the use of any medically acceptable forms of
             birth control by the subject or partner (hormonal birth control, abstinence, diaphragm
             with spermicide, condom with spermicide, intrauterine device, vasectomy, surgical
             sterilization or post menopausal partner) from Screening until the End of Study.

          4. Body mass index (BMI) of ≥ 18.0 and ≤ 30.0 kg/m2 at the time of Screening.

          5. Subject is willing and able to provide informed consent.

          6. Subject is willing and able to be confined to the CRU and adhere to the study and
             lifestyle restrictions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of clinically significant illness or surgery as determined by the Principal
             Investigator or designee, within 5 years prior to the first IMP administration.

          2. History or evidence of any clinically significant pathology including neurological,
             cardiovascular, endocrine, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, renal, hepatic, hematological,
             immunological, psychiatric or metabolic disorder(s) as determined by the Principal
             Investigator or designee.

          3. Any significant rectal pathology that, in the opinion of the Principal Investigator or
             designee, would be a contraindication (or warning) with a hydrocortisone acetate
             suppository or hydrocortisone retention enema including rectal obstruction, abscess,
             perforation, active fungal infection(s) and/or bacterial infection(s).

          4. Subject has had anal sex, cosmetic anal bleaching or perianal waxing within 30 days
             prior to the first IMP administration.

          5. History of constipation, diarrhea or frequent bowel movements per day within 30 days
             prior to the first IMP administration.

          6. Any clinically significant abnormality (including clinically significant laboratory
             test result[s]) found at Screening or febrile illness or infection within 7 days prior
             to Screening through Admission (Day 1 of Treatment Period 1) to the CRU.

          7. Positive test for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis C virus antibody
             (anti HCV), or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody at Screening.

          8. Clinically significant electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormality at Screening, as determined
             by the Principal Investigator or designee.

          9. Positive pregnancy test (females only) at Screening or Admission (Day 1 of Treatment
             Periods 1 or 2) to the CRU.

         10. Subject has history of alcohol abuse or of significant regular alcohol use within 1
             year prior to Screening, defined as exceeding 14 units of alcohol per week, where, 1
             unit = 12 ounces of beer, 5 ounces of wine or 1.5 ounces of hard liquor.

         11. Positive serum alcohol test at Screening or Admission (Day 1 of Treatment Periods 1 or
             2) to the CRU.

         12. History of regular tobacco use or use of nicotine containing products to control
             tobacco use within the past 6 months prior to Screening.

         13. Positive urine drug test (including amphetamines, barbiturates, benzodiazepines,
             cannabinoids, cocaine, opiates and phencyclidine) at Screening or Admission (Day 1 of
             Treatment Periods 1 or 2) to the CRU.

         14. Use of over the counter (OTC) medications (including oral natural health products,
             vitamin and herbal supplements) within 7 days prior to the first IMP administration
             until the End of Study or use of prescription medication within 14 days prior to the
             first IMP administration until the End of Study. By exception, acetaminophen &lt;1000 mg
             per day, hormonal contraception and hormonal replacement therapy are permitted.

         15. Known allergy or history of hypersensitivity to hydrocortisone or any of the inert
             components of either of the formulations being tested.

         16. Participation in another clinical study within 60 days prior to the first IMP
             administration. Participation is considered the last dose of IMP from another study.

         17. Donation or loss of blood (&gt; 100 mL) of either whole blood or plasma within 60 days
             prior to the first IMP administration.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marck C Ensign</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Executive VP Product Development</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 26, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 26, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bioavailability</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone 17-butyrate 21-propionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cortisol succinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

