<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02670889</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CNMC 7230, U54-HD061221</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02670889</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Urease Inhibitor Drug Treatment for Urea Cycle Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Manipulating the Gut Microbiome in Urea Cycle Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nicholas Ah Mew</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Data Management and Coordinating Center (DMCC)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if acetohydroxamic acid (AHA) can prevent
      hydrolysis of urea by inhibiting the bacterial urease of gut flora of both healthy control
      adults as well as adults with urea cycle disorders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood and urine measurements of isotopic [13C]-urea concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood: 0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240 minutes on Day 1 and Day 4; Urine: 0, 240 minutes on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>At time zero of the study, participants will be given an intravenous bolus infusion of [13C]-urea. The concentration of [13C]-urea in the body will be measured/traced throughout the duration of the study (4 hours) by collecting blood and urine samples at specified time points. Blood [13C]-urea will be measured at time points 0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, and 240 minutes. Urine [13C]-urea will be measured at time points 0 and 240 minutes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood measurements of isotopic [13-CO2] concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240 minutes on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>At time zero of the study, participants will receive an intravenous bolus infusion of [13C]-urea. The amount of metabolized [13C]-urea in the body will be measured throughout the duration of the study by collecting blood samples and analyzing them for [13CO2] concentration. Blood [13-CO2] will be measured at time points 0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, and 240 minutes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood and urine samples measuring urea concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood: 0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240 minutes on Day 1 and Day 4; Urine: 0, 240 minutes on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>The drug under study, Lithostat, is a bacterial urease inhibitor. Throughout the study, the investigators will measure the concentration of urea in blood and urine samples to get baseline urea measurements for the participant (no study drug) and to see how drug administration affects the levels of blood urea concentration (study drug). Blood urea measurement will occur at time points 0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, and 240 minutes. Urine urea measurement will occur at time points 0 and 240 minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood samples measuring ammonia concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240 minutes on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will have ammonia levels measured at various time points throughout the study. Ammonia is produced when urea is hydrolyzed by bacterial urease. The investigators predict that the administration of Lithostat, a gut bacterial urease inhibitor, will have an effect on the concentration of blood ammonia by using this study intervention. Blood ammonia will be measured at time points 0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, and 240 minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood plasma samples measuring glutamine concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, 240 minutes on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>The new indication proposed for the drug Lithostat, is for use in patients with urea cycle disorders. Elevated blood ammonia levels in patients with urea cycle disorders usually also corresponds to elevated blood glutamine levels as well. The investigators will collect blood samples to measure glutamine concentration at specified time points. Blood glutamine will be measured at time points 0, 30, 60, 90, 120, 180, and 240 minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values for Blood Hemoglobin That Are Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 240 min on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at baseline and at 240 minutes on days 1 and 4 of the study to measure safety labs. Safety labs will include measurement of blood hemoglobin. This will help determine if the principal investigator should take any action to remove the participant from the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values for White Blood Count That Are Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 240 min on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at baseline and at 240 minutes on days 1 and 4 of the study to measure safety labs. Safety labs will include measurement of white blood count. This will help determine if the principal investigator should take any action to remove the participant from the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values for Blood Platelet Count That Are Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 240 min on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at baseline and at 240 minutes on days 1 and 4 of the study to measure safety labs. Safety labs will include measurement of blood platelet count. This will help determine if the principal investigator should take any action to remove the participant from the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values for Blood AST level That Are Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 240 min on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at baseline and at 240 minutes on days 1 and 4 of the study to measure safety labs. Safety labs will include measurement of blood AST levels. This will help determine if the principal investigator should take any action to remove the participant from the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values for Blood ALT level That Are Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 240 min on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at baseline and at 240 minutes on days 1 and 4 of the study to measure safety labs. Safety labs will include measurement of blood ALT levels. This will help determine if the principal investigator should take any action to remove the participant from the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values for Blood Bilirubin level That Are Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 240 min on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at baseline and at 240 minutes on days 1 and 4 of the study to measure safety labs. Safety labs will include measurement of blood bilirubin levels. This will help determine if the principal investigator should take any action to remove the participant from the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values for Urine Creatinine level That Are Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 240 min on Day 1 and Day 4</time_frame>
    <description>Urine samples will be collected at baseline and at 240 minutes on days 1 and 4 of the study to measure safety labs. Safety labs will include measurement of urine creatinine levels. This will help determine if the principal investigator should take any action to remove the participant from the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Ornithine Transcarbamylase Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Argininosuccinate Synthetase Deficiency (Citrullinemia)</condition>
  <condition>Argininosuccinic Acid Lyase Deficiency (Argininosuccinic Aciduria)</condition>
  <condition>Carbamyl-Phosphate Synthase I Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment with AHA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study day using acetohydroxamic acid (with experimental drug) Safety labs will be collected prior to administering acetohydroxamic acid (AHA, experimental drug) to participants. The investigators will give the participant one dose of the AHA (dose: 60 mg/kg). 1 hour after taking the AHA, the participant will receive a single dose of Isotopic Intravenous [13C]-Urea through a different IV which will be inserted into the opposite arm and removed after the administration of the isotope. Over the next 4 hours, the investigators will collect blood samples to measure safety labs and various biomarkers. Urine samples will also be collected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Baseline Measurements without AHA (Study Drug)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study day without the use of acetohydroxamic acid (no experimental drug) Procedures are identical except for the administration of AHA, which will not occur.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acetohydroxamic Acid</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment with AHA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lithostat</other_name>
    <other_name>AHA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Isotopic Intravenous [13C]-Urea</intervention_name>
    <description>Used to trace 13CO2 and 13C-urea in the blood.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment with AHA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Baseline Measurements without AHA (Study Drug)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        For Healthy Adult Volunteers:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Compliant with receiving medications orally and intravenously

          -  Compliant with providing blood and urine samples

        For Urea Cycle Disorder Adults:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Compliant with receiving medications orally and intravenously

          -  Compliant with providing blood and urine samples

          -  Established diagnosis of CPSD, OTCD, ASSD or ASLD as follows:

               -  Diagnosis of CPS I deficiency, defined as decreased (less than 20 % of control)
                  CPS I enzyme activity in liver or an identified pathogenic mutation

               -  Diagnosis of OTC deficiency, defined as the identification of a pathogenic
                  mutation, linkage analysis in an affected family, less than 20% of control of OTC
                  activity in the liver, or elevated urinary orotate (greater than 20 uM/mM) in a
                  random sample or following allopurinol loading with absence of argininosuccinic
                  acid

               -  Diagnosis of AS deficiency (Citrullinemia), defined as a greater than or equal to
                  10-fold elevation of citrulline in plasma, decreased AS enzyme activity in
                  cultured skin fibroblasts or other appropriate tissue, or identification of a
                  pathogenic mutation in the AS gene

               -  Diagnosis of AL deficiency (Argininosuccinic Aciduria, ASA), defined as the
                  presence of argininosuccinic acid in the blood or urine, decreased AL enzyme
                  activity in cultured skin fibroblasts or other appropriate tissue, or
                  identification of a pathogenic mutation in the AL gene

        Exclusion Criteria (both arms):

          -  Current or prior Helicobacter pylori infection

          -  Chronic gastrointestinal illness (e.g., inflammatory bowel disease)

          -  Chronic renal failure

          -  Taking probiotic medications within a week of study start date

          -  Currently pregnant or lactating. Documentation of a negative pregnancy test within a
             week prior to testing is required, unless pre-menarchal or menopausal, experiencing
             menses that week, or other circumstances which preclude pregnancy (e.g. hysterectomy).

          -  Presence of acute infection at the time of inclusion

          -  Participation in any other clinical interventional trial or received experimental
             medication within the last 30 days

          -  Any clinical or laboratory abnormality or medical condition that, at the discretion of
             the investigator, may put the subject at an additional risk by participating in this
             study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas Ah Mew, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Children's National Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas Ah Mew, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's National Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marshall L Summar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's National Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nicholas Ah Mew, MD</last_name>
    <phone>202-476-5863</phone>
    <email>NAhMew@childrensnational.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lillian Assatourian, BS</last_name>
    <phone>202-476-6137</phone>
    <email>lassatouri@childrensnational.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 14, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 23, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 23, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 25, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nicholas Ah Mew</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Urea Cycle Disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urea Cycle Disorders, Inborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ornithine Carbamoyltransferase Deficiency Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Citrullinemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Argininosuccinic Aciduria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acetohydroxamic acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

