<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02676713</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GAMHospital</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2014BAI10B08</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02676713</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Traditional Chinese Medicine Sequential Treatment for Endometriosis Associated Infertility</brief_title>
  <official_title>Activating Blood, Dredging Liver and Nourishing Kidney Sequential Treatment for Endometriosis Associated Infertility - a Randomized Double-blind Placebo Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guang'anmen Hospital of China Academy of Chinese Medical Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Peking Union Medical College Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beijing Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital, Guangzhou University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital of Anhui University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Guang'anmen Hospital of China Academy of Chinese Medical Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Endometriosis is a common, chronic disease. 30% to 50% of women with endometriosis are
      infertile. There is moderate quality evidence that laparoscopic surgery to treat mild and
      moderate endometriosis increases live birth or ongoing pregnancy rates. There was no evidence
      of benefit for post-surgical hormonal suppression of endometriosis compared to surgery alone
      for the outcomes of pregnancy rates. Past studies have confirmed that Chinese herbal medicine
      can inhibit post-surgical endometriosis recurrence, increase pregnancy rate.This study
      evaluates the efficacy and safety of Traditional Chinese Medicine Sequential Treatment of
      endometriosis-associated infertility. The study objective is to confirm that clinical
      pregnancy rate of patients with endometriosis-associated infertility post-conservative
      surgery accepting Chinese medicine activating blood, dredging liver and nourishing kidney
      sequential treatment is higher than expectant treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicenter, prospective
      clinical study, conducted in China (six research centers).

      204 cases of patients with endometriosis-associated infertility confined with Syndrome of qi
      stagnation blood stasis pattern in TCM after conservative surgery will be recruited. Patients
      will be randomly divided into two groups: experimental group (TCM Sequential Treatment) and
      control group (placebo). All the patients are treated for six menstrual cycles, taking
      pre-ovulation decoction before ovulation and post-ovulation decoction after ovulation.
      Pre-ovulation decoction of experimental group is HuoXueXiaoYi decoction, and post-ovulation
      decoction is BuShenZhuYun decoction. The drug of control group is placebo.

      Each menstrual cycle, patient is monitored of antral follicle count (AFC), ovulation,
      endometrial thickness, and endometrial blood flow by ultrasonography, and need fill TCM
      syndrome rating scale, pictorial blood loss assessment chart (PBAC), and the visual analogue
      scale(VAS).The 1st, 3rd, 6th menstrual cycle after surgery, the level of serum female hormone
      (FSH, LH, E2) are detected in menstrual period of 2 to 5 days, and female hormone (E2, P) in
      the middle of the corpus luteum 6-9 days.

      Patient must be security check (blood routine, urine routine, liver and kidney function,
      electrocardiogram) before and after drug treatment. Such as patients find pregnancy during
      medication, adopt the security check in finding pregnancy 7 days.

      Patients after amenorrhea need to be confirmed pregnancy by serum β-HCG detection. According
      to the level of serum HCG, E2 and P and clinical symptoms, corresponding tocolytic treatment
      will be given. At 6～8 weeks of pregnancy, patient need to be confirmed the clinical pregnancy
      by ultrasonography. If confirmed the clinical pregnancy (at least having one heart throb in
      intrauterine gestational sac), patient need to be confirmed ongoing pregnancy by
      ultrasonography at the 12～14 weeks of pregnancy.

      In the process of the entire study, adverse events will be closely observed, and the
      frequency and severity of adverse events will be recorded.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>December 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pregnancy rate</measure>
    <time_frame>six menstrual cycles（each cycle is 28±7 days）</time_frame>
    <description>Pregnancy rate is defined as the proportion of participants finding pregnancy after amenorrhea and confirming serumβ-HCG positive.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical pregnancy rate (with intrauterine pregnancy sac)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 6～8 weeks of pregnancy</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the proportion of participants confirmed there are at least one gestational sac in uterine cavity (No matter whether there is a heart throb) by ultrasonography.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical pregnancy rate (with a heart throb)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 6～8 weeks of pregnancy</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the proportion of participants confirmed at least having one heart throb in intrauterine gestational sac by ultrasonography.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Continued pregnancy rate</measure>
    <time_frame>at the 12～14 weeks of pregnancy</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the proportion of participants confirmed at least one live fetuses by ultrasonography.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Treatment-emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>six menstrual cycles（each cycle is 28±7 days）</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment-emergent Adverse Events were assessed by CTCAE v4.0.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">204</enrollment>
  <condition>Endometriosis</condition>
  <condition>Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TCM Sequential Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After conservative surgery, patients start to take pre-ovulation decoction for 14 days. Each menstrual period 2～5 days, patients start to take pre-ovulation decoction. If ultrasonography found ovulation, change to take post-ovulation decoction. If having taken 14 days, ultrasonography found LUFS or no follicle develop maturity, change to take post-ovulation decoction. Taking post-ovulation decoction for 14 days, or continue to next time menstruation. Taking medication for six menstrual cycles.
Pre-ovulation decoction is HuoXueXiaoYi decoction, and post-ovulation decoction is BuShenZhuYun decoction. 2 bags each time, 2 times a day, fused with hot water, 1 hour after dinner.
All drugs are tcm formula granules, manufactured by Jiangyin Tianjiang Pharmaceutical Co. ltd</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After conservative surgery, patients start to take pre-ovulation decoction(placebo) for 14 days. Each menstrual period 2～5 days, patients start to take pre-ovulation decoction. If ultrasonography found ovulation, change to take post-ovulation decoction. If having taken 14 days, ultrasonography found luteinized unruptured follicle syndrome (LUFS) or no follicle develop maturity, change to take post-ovulation decoction. Taking post-ovulation decoction(placebo) for 14 days, or continue to next time menstruation. Taking medication for six menstrual cycles. 2 bags each time, 2 times a day, fused with hot water, 1 hour after dinner.
Pre-ovulation decoction and post-ovulation decoction is placebo, manufactured by Jiangyin Tianjiang Pharmaceutical Co. ltd</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pre-ovulation Decoction</intervention_name>
    <description>HuoXueXiaoYi Decoction(Bupleurum 10g, Cyperus 10g, Salvia miltiorrhiza 20g, Red peony 10g,etc)has activating blood and absorbing clots effect, can inhibit the growth of ectopic endometrium, promote follicular growth, maturity, improve ovulation and the receptivity of endometrium.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TCM Sequential Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HuoXueXiaoYi Decoction</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>post-ovulation Decoction</intervention_name>
    <description>BuShenZhuYun Decoction(Bupleurum 10g,Poria 15g, Atractylodes 15g,Ligustrum 15g,etc) has dredging liver and nourishing kidney effect, can improve the function of corpus luteum.
All are made into granules.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TCM Sequential Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BuShenZhuYun Decoction</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pre-ovulation Decoction(placebo)</intervention_name>
    <description>Composition of maltodextrin, lactose, edible pigment, taste masking agent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>post-ovulation Decoction(placebo)</intervention_name>
    <description>Composition of maltodextrin, lactose, edible pigment, taste masking agent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Clinical diagnosis of endometriosis, infertility, with Syndrome of qi stagnation blood
             stasis pattern in TCM ;

          2. The first time undergoing Laparoscopic or laparoscopy combined surgery , in lined with
             endometriosis-related infertility, tubal patency or obstruction lightly;

          3. EFI score greater than 4 points;

          4. Early follicular phase FSH≤10mIU / L;

          5. 28 days of the menstrual cycle ± 7 days;

          6. Female patients between 20-35 years old;

          7. No previous history of severe drug allergies;

          8. Past Three-month no taking hormone drugs such as danazol, Gestrinone, GnRHa;

          9. No severe primary brain vascular diseases, liver, kidney and hematopoietic systems
             diseases, no history of mental illness, no drugs, alcohol, tobacco, caffeine dependent
             history;

         10. Have signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Associated with uterine fibroids, the diameter greater than 4cm, adenomyosis, pelvic
             tuberculosis, endometrial tuberculosis, intrauterine adhesions, polycystic ovary
             syndrome, hyperprolactinemia, thyroid dysfunction patients.

          2. Serious history of drug allergy.

          3. Male factor infertility.

          4. The couple separated persons.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ruihua Zhao, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Guang'anmen Hospital of China Academy of Chinese Medical Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yi Tang, Master</last_name>
    <phone>+86 13260185007</phone>
    <email>yier1990@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jie Wang, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>8601088001246</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Anhui University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hefei</city>
        <state>Anhui</state>
        <zip>230031</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Weili Li, PHD</last_name>
      <phone>8601052276423</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Obstetrics and Gynecology Hospital,Captial Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100026</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dan Lu, PHD</last_name>
      <phone>8601052276423</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GAMHospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100053</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yi Tang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>13260185007</phone>
      <email>yier1990@126.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Yong Liu</last_name>
      <phone>13488676266</phone>
      <email>liuyong115@126.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510405</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cheng Zeng, PHD</last_name>
      <phone>8602036591369</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Traditional Chinese Medicine Hospital of Guangdong Province</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xiaoyun Wang, PHD</last_name>
      <phone>8602081887233</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijng Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijng</city>
        <zip>100730</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Qingwei Meng, PHD</last_name>
      <phone>8601085138118</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duffy JM, Arambage K, Correa FJ, Olive D, Farquhar C, Garry R, Barlow DH, Jacobson TZ. Laparoscopic surgery for endometriosis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014 Apr 3;(4):CD011031. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD011031.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24696265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yap C, Furness S, Farquhar C. Pre and post operative medical therapy for endometriosis surgery. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2004;(3):CD003678. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15266496</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zhao RH, Hao ZP, Zhang Y, Lian FM, Sun WW, Liu Y, Wang R, Long L, Cheng L, Ding YF, Song DR, Meng QW, Wang AM. Controlling the recurrence of pelvic endometriosis after a conservative operation: comparison between Chinese herbal medicine and western medicine. Chin J Integr Med. 2013 Nov;19(11):820-5. doi: 10.1007/s11655-012-1247-z. Epub 2012 Dec 22.</citation>
    <PMID>23292545</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 8, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 19, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Guang'anmen Hospital of China Academy of Chinese Medical Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhao RuiHua</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief Physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Traditional Chinese Medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Chinese Herbal</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometriosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

