<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02674802</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Affiliated Hospital of NCU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02674802</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reinfection After Eradication of Helicobacter Pylori Infection</brief_title>
  <acronym>RAEHPI</acronym>
  <official_title>Reinfection After Eradication of Helicobacter Pylori Infection in Adult :A National Multicentre Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Helicobacter pylori is closely related with gastritis, peptic ulcer, gastric cancer and
      gastric MALT lymphoma, and it may participate in a variety of parenteral diseases. Infection
      rates of Helicobacter pylori is still high, so effectively eradication is necessary. At
      present, the eradication therapy has achieved very good curative effect. However, relapse
      after eradication is unoptimistic. This study has made an analysis for reinfection after
      eradication of Helicobacter pylori Infection include the retrospective and prospective
      studies, aims to explore the epidemiological data and related risk factors of Hp reinfection
      in China.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the retrospective study,we choose the people received regular eradication therapy,
      successfully eradicated helicobacter pylori more than six months, but 4 to 8 weeks after drug
      withdrawal ,the detection result of helicobacter pylori were negative to ensure that the
      results of the study is the reinfection, not residual. Even more noteworthy is during the
      treatment and detection again, the patients must not received any eradication therapy of Hp.
      What's more , before the detection, they also has not used antibiotics, bismuth agent and the
      traditional Chinese medicine with antibacterial effect in 1 monthor and has not used H2RA and
      PPI in 2 weeks to prevent affecting the accuracy of the results. At the same time, we also
      investigated the patient's general situation, conomic conditions, living conditions, personal
      health and lifestyle to explore related risk factors of Hp reinfection in China. In the
      prospective study, we detected Hp by C-UBT after regular eradication therapy of Hp for 4
      weeks, 8 weeks and 6 months to prospect the reinfection of Hp.It also can make up the defects
      of retrospective study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>December 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Helicobacter Pylori Infection</measure>
    <time_frame>six months</time_frame>
    <description>Retrospective study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Helicobacter Pylori Infection</measure>
    <time_frame>After regular eradication therapy of Hp for 4 weeks, 8 weeks and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Prospective study</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3500</enrollment>
  <condition>Bacterial Infection Due to Helicobacter Pylori (H. Pylori)</condition>
  <condition>Eradication Therapy of Helicobacter Pylori</condition>
  <condition>Detection of Helicobacter Pylori</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Retrospective study</arm_group_label>
    <description>People who has successfully eradicated helicobacter pylori more than six months detected helicobacter pylori by the C-urea breath test in order to evaluate the reinfection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prospective study</arm_group_label>
    <description>People who has infected helicobacter pylori received regular eradication therapy after the 4 weeks, 8 weeks and 6 months detected helicobacter pylori by the C-urea breath test in order to prospect the reinfection .</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        In the retrospective study,people who has infected helicobacter pylori and successfully
        eradicated it more than six months detected helicobacter pylori by the C-urea breath test
        in order to evaluate the reinfection In the prospective study,people who has infected
        helicobacter pylori received regular eradication therapy after the 4 weeks, 8 weeks and 6
        months detected helicobacter pylori by the C-urea breath test in order to prospect the
        reinfection
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        -1、Retrospective study：

          1. Received regular eradication therapy, 4 to 8 weeks after drug withdrawal , detected of
             helicobacter pylori and the results were negative

          2. Eradication program and original disease is unlimited

          3. Without any eradication therapyof Hp during the treatment and detection again

          4. before the detection has not used antibiotics, bismuth agent and the traditional
             Chinese medicine with antibacterial effect in 1 monthor and has not used H2RA and PPI
             in 2 weeks.

        2、Prospective study

          1. Infected with H. pylori that detected by C-UBT

          2. With out alimentary tract hemorrhage,ulceration and complications of eradication

          3. Eradication program and original disease is unlimited

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy or breast-feeding women

          2. With the major disease which would influence the research such as liver disease, heart
             disease, kidney disease, malignant tumor and alcohol poisoning

          3. Participated in other drug research in the past three months

          4. The patient can't express himself correctly such as mental illness and severe neurosis
             and can't cooperation this test
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nonghua Lv, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ying Huang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>15270953973</phone>
    <email>497514037@qq.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yong Xie, MD</last_name>
    <phone>13177893950</phone>
    <email>xieyong_med@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanchang</city>
        <state>Jiangxi</state>
        <zip>330006</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nonghua Lv, MD</last_name>
      <phone>13707086809</phone>
      <email>lunonghua@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kunhe Zhang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>13007202818</phone>
      <email>393467260@qq.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nonghua Lv, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cdyfy.com/</url>
    <description>the First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malfertheiner P, Megraud F, O'Morain CA, Atherton J, Axon AT, Bazzoli F, Gensini GF, Gisbert JP, Graham DY, Rokkas T, El-Omar EM, Kuipers EJ; European Helicobacter Study Group. Management of Helicobacter pylori infection--the Maastricht IV/ Florence Consensus Report. Gut. 2012 May;61(5):646-64. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2012-302084.</citation>
    <PMID>22491499</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silva FM, Navarro-Rodriguez T, Barbuti RC, Mattar R, Hashimoto CL, Eisig JN. Helicobacter pylori reinfection in Brazilian patients with peptic ulcer disease: a 5-year follow-up. Helicobacter. 2010 Feb;15(1):46-52. doi: 10.1111/j.1523-5378.2009.00734.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20302589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benajah DA, Lahbabi M, Alaoui S, El Rhazi K, El Abkari M, Nejjari C, Amarti A, Bennani B, Mahmoud M, Ibrahimi SA. Prevalence of Helicobacter pylori and its recurrence after successful eradication in a developing nation (Morocco). Clin Res Hepatol Gastroenterol. 2013 Nov;37(5):519-26. doi: 10.1016/j.clinre.2013.02.003. Epub 2013 Apr 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23567104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Take S, Mizuno M, Ishiki K, Imada T, Okuno T, Yoshida T, Yokota K, Oguma K, Kita M, Okada H, Yamamoto K. Reinfection rate of Helicobacter pylori after eradication treatment: a long-term prospective study in Japan. J Gastroenterol. 2012 Jun;47(6):641-6. doi: 10.1007/s00535-012-0536-9. Epub 2012 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22350696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Archimandritis A, Balatsos V, Delis V, Manika Z, Skandalis N. &quot;Reappearance&quot; of Helicobacter pylori after eradication: implications on duodenal ulcer recurrence: a prospective 6 year study. J Clin Gastroenterol. 1999 Jun;28(4):345-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10372933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 3, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 3, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lingyu Luo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Physician-in-charge</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Reinfection</keyword>
  <keyword>Eradication therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>C-urea breath test</keyword>
  <keyword>Helicobacter Pylori</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bacterial Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Helicobacter Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

