<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02676765</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HM20006291</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MISP 52707</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02676765</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Desensitization and Cross-Desensitization During Oral Grass or Ragweed Pollen Immunotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Desensitization and Cross-Desensitization During Oral Grass or Ragweed Pollen Immunotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Virginia Commonwealth University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if sublingual allergen immunotherapy tablets work
      by inducing a state of desensitization in mast cells and basophils.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To induce clinical tolerance, a failure to respond to an allergen to which one was previously
      responsive, is an important objective for physicians, one that plays a significant role in
      the primary prevention of allergic reactions in the clinical practice of Allergy &amp;
      Immunology. The tolerance resulting after standard subcutaneous immunotherapy to aeroallergen
      and insect venom allergens is long lasting and allergen-specific, and may involve
      antigen-specific T regulatory cells. In contrast, tolerance resulting from drug
      desensitization protocols is short-lived, and postulated to target mast cells and basophils.
      Research into the cellular and biochemical processes by which desensitization occurs has
      revealed that mast cells desensitized to one antigen in vitro, under certain conditions, lose
      the ability to degranulate to unrelated antigens or to direct FcεRI cross-linking.
      Preliminary data suggests that this cross-desensitization can happen in patients undergoing
      incremental desensitization, depending in part on the percentage of IgE targeted to the
      allergen used for desensitization. This proposal therefore aims to explore desensitization
      and cross-desensitization in human volunteers undergoing standard sublingual (SL)
      immunotherapy to grass or ragweed pollen.

      Subjects will undergo SL immunotherapy with either Timothy or Short Ragweed tablets, taking
      one tablet per day, or will take a placebo tablet. Titration skin testing to Timothy or Short
      Ragweed, to one or preferably two additional allergens to which the subject is sensitive, and
      to codeine as a control for mast cell activation capability through a non-IgE-dependent
      pathway will be performed to determine the PC3 value (see below). Skin testing, including
      histamine and diluent controls, will be performed prior to and at one and four weeks after
      initiation of immunotherapy. At each time point, blood will be obtained to measure total and
      antigen-specific IgE levels, tryptase and cytokine levels, and basophil activation with the
      relevant allergens and C5a as a non-IgE-mediated control for basophil activation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PC3</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 2 weeks and at the end of the study (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the dose of allergen eliciting a wheal 3 mm greater than negative control upon skin prick testing (PC3)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Basophil Activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 2 weeks and at the end of the study (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the dose of allergen eliciting a 50% increase in CD63 and/or CD203c expression relative to negative and positive controls</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cross-desensitization - PC3</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 2 weeks and at the end of the study (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the dose of an unrelated allergen eliciting a wheal 3 mm greater than negative control upon skin prick testing (PC3)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cross-desensitization - Basophil Activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 2 weeks and at the end of the study (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the dose of an unrelated allergen eliciting a 50% increase in CD63 and/or CD203c expression relative to negative and positive controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Allergen-specific IgE</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at enrollment, at 2 weeks, and at the end of the study (2 months)</time_frame>
    <description>The percent of total serum IgE that is specific for the primary allergen will be compared to the degree (if any) of cross-desensitization seen by skin prick or basophil activation testing</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Immunologic Desensitization</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Allergen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be administered either Timothy Grass or Short Ragweed sublingual allergen tablets, depending on their individual allergic sensitization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be administered placebo sublingual tablets</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allergen</intervention_name>
    <description>1 allergen extract tablet, placed under the tongue until dissolved, taken daily; do not swallow for 1 minute after placing tablet; do not eat or drink for 5 minutes after placing tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Allergen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ragwitek</other_name>
    <other_name>Grastek</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>1 placebo tablet, placed under the tongue until dissolved, taken daily; do not swallow for 1 minute after placing tablet; do not eat or drink for 5 minutes after placing tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Verified allergic sensitivity to either Timothy Grass or Short Ragweed pollen (primary
             allergen)

          -  Verified allergic sensitivity to at least one allergen in addition to the primary
             allergen

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Negative skin testing to Timothy Grass or Short Ragweed pollen and at least one other
             environmental allergen

          -  Dermatographism

          -  Severe dermatologic condition that may interfere with skin testing

          -  Pregnancy

          -  H1 receptor antihistamine taken within 7 days of testing

          -  Systemic steroids

          -  Omalizumab taken at any time in the past

          -  Receiving or received allergen immunotherapy

          -  Desensitized to any drug within 6 months

          -  Current uncontrolled or severe asthma

          -  Eosinophilic esophagitis

          -  Significant pulmonary, cardiovascular, renal, hepatobiliary, or neurological diseases,
             or another disease process felt to put a subject at increased risk for adverse events

          -  Hypersensitivity to any of the inactive ingredients in the allergen extract tablets

          -  History of mental illness or drug or alcohol abuse that could interfere with the
             ability to comply with study requirements

          -  Inability or unwillingness to give written informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lawrence B Schwartz, M.D.,Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Virginia Commonwealth University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brant Ward, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>804-828-8681</phone>
    <email>brant.ward@vcuhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Commonwealth University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23298</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao W, Gomez G, Macey M, Kepley CL, Schwartz LB. In vitro desensitization of human skin mast cells. J Clin Immunol. 2012 Feb;32(1):150-60. doi: 10.1007/s10875-011-9605-8. Epub 2011 Oct 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22009002</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maloney J, Bernstein DI, Nelson H, Creticos P, Hébert J, Noonan M, Skoner D, Zhou Y, Kaur A, Nolte H. Efficacy and safety of grass sublingual immunotherapy tablet, MK-7243: a large randomized controlled trial. Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol. 2014 Feb;112(2):146-153.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.anai.2013.11.018. Epub 2013 Dec 21.</citation>
    <PMID>24468255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Creticos PS, Maloney J, Bernstein DI, Casale T, Kaur A, Fisher R, Liu N, Murphy K, Nékám K, Nolte H. Randomized controlled trial of a ragweed allergy immunotherapy tablet in North American and European adults. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2013 May;131(5):1342-9.e6. doi: 10.1016/j.jaci.2013.03.019.</citation>
    <PMID>23622121</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cockcroft DW, Davis BE, Boulet LP, Deschesnes F, Gauvreau GM, O'Byrne PM, Watson RM. The links between allergen skin test sensitivity, airway responsiveness and airway response to allergen. Allergy. 2005 Jan;60(1):56-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15575931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niederberger V, Laffer S, Fröschl R, Kraft D, Rumpold H, Kapiotis S, Valenta R, Spitzauer S. IgE antibodies to recombinant pollen allergens (Phl p 1, Phl p 2, Phl p 5, and Bet v 2) account for a high percentage of grass pollen-specific IgE. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 1998 Feb;101(2 Pt 1):258-64.</citation>
    <PMID>9500760</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 3, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 8, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Allergic rhinitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy, Allergen</keyword>
  <keyword>Sublingual Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

