<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02675790</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>141077</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02675790</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Moderate Dose Hydroxyurea for Secondary Stroke Prevention in Children With Sickle Cell Disease in Sub-Saharan Africa</brief_title>
  <acronym>SPRINT</acronym>
  <official_title>Hydroxyurea for Stroke Prevention in Children With Sickle Cell Disease in Sub-Saharan Africa</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aminu Kano Teaching Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Murtala Muhammed Specialist Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall goal of the proposed study is to determine the effectiveness of hydroxyurea
      therapy for secondary stroke prevention and prevention of other neurological events in
      children with SCA with an acute overt stroke.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sub-Saharan Africans are disproportionately affected with sickle cell disease (SCD). In the
      most populous country in sub-Saharan Africa, Nigeria, over 150,000 children with the most
      severe form of SCD, sickle cell anemia (SCA), are born per year as compared to about 1,100
      births in the United States. In Nigeria, for every birth year cohort of children with SCA
      followed to their 18th birthday with no premature deaths, there are at least 15,000 overt
      strokes. The prevalence of stroke among children with SCA, particularly in low-income
      countries, is associated with an increased rate of morbidity and premature death. If
      untreated, 50% of children who have had their first overt stroke will have a recurrent stroke
      within two years of the event. Regular blood transfusion is standard therapy for secondary
      stroke prevention in this high stroke risk population. However, monthly blood transfusion
      therapy is not a feasible option for children with SCA in sub-Saharan Africa for several
      reasons, including the high cost of monthly transfusion and limited blood supplies.
      Preliminary data from observational studies suggest that hydroxyurea (HU) therapy may be an
      effective alternative strategy for secondary stroke prevention in children with SCA. In
      sub-Saharan Africa, the critical unanswered question is what appropriate HU dose for
      secondary stroke prevention maximizes therapeutic benefit while minimizing toxicity to
      children.

      In preparation for this application, over the last 9 months, we achieved the following
      milestones with the SPIN trial (NCT01801423; NIH/NINDS Grant number 1R21NS080639-01): 1)
      demonstrated the feasibility of HU therapy for primary stroke prevention in Africa, with 92%
      of the eligible participants enrolled; 2) showed favorable data that moderate dose HU therapy
      (20 mg/kg/day) is safe; 3) demonstrated that HU therapy may be effective for primary stroke
      prevention (3 months after starting HU therapy, two-thirds of the children in the SPIN Trial
      (n=25) with baseline elevated transcranial Doppler (TCD) measurements decreased their TCD
      values to normal levels); 4) demonstrated short-term safety of HU therapy, with no deaths or
      increase in hospitalizations when compared to a prospectively followed comparison group
      (n=210) that had 7 deaths and a higher rate of all-cause hospitalizations; 5) revealed very
      good adherence to HU therapy based on the biological correlate, mean corpuscular volume
      (MCV), and the validated Morisky Medication Adherence Scale; and 6) conducted a one-month
      intensive clinical research training at Vanderbilt University, paired with ongoing mentoring
      for more than one year with multi-disciplinary teams from Aminu Kano Teaching Hospital (AKTH)
      and an affiliated satellite clinic, Murtala Muhammad Specialist Hospital (MMSH) both located
      in Kano, Nigeria. Our results to date indicate that no children have developed a stroke while
      on HU therapy, and the rate of adverse events has been lower than in the comparison group
      with a normal TCD measurement at baseline who were followed for the same period of time
      (median of 25 months). In the SPIN trial, both the treatment and the comparison group are
      being followed for 3 years.

      Based on our encouraging early results for primary stroke prevention in the SPIN Trial among
      children with SCA in Kano, Nigeria, we propose a definitive partial phase III trial with the
      same study team, wherein we will test the hypothesis that moderate dose HU therapy (20
      mg/kg/day) results in 80% relative risk reduction when compared to low dose HU therapy (10
      mg/kg/day) for secondary stroke prevention among children 1 - 18 years of age with SCA and
      acute overt stroke.

      The aims for the two center randomized partial double-blind Phase III clinical trial are: 1)
      to assess the efficacy of moderate dose HU therapy for secondary stroke prevention when
      compared to low dose HU therapy among children with SCA; 2) to determine whether moderate HU
      therapy decreases the rate of all-cause hospitalizations when compared to low dose HU
      therapy; and 3) to assess prevalence of strokes and incidence of recurrent strokes among
      individuals with SCD ages 1 - 18 at active study site from January 1, 2014 to June 30, 2017.
      We will randomly allocate up to 120 children who meet the inclusion criteria in a ratio of
      1:1 with follow-up for at least 36 months per participant from a pool of over 10,000 children
      with SCA who attend the two study sites, AKTH and MMSH, both located in Kano, Nigeria.
      Similar methods of operation and procedures from the SPIN Trial with participants from both
      sites will be used to conduct this proposed trial.

      Among the study population of over 10,000 children with SCA in Kano, &lt; 1% receive a TCD
      measurement between the two study sites; therefore, we expect ≥ 100 children will have an
      initial stroke annually, based on an incidence of 1 per 100 patient years.(2) Among those
      with an initial stroke who are untreated, which includes most of the children with strokes at
      the study sites, we expect at least 50% will have a recurrent stroke within two years.(3)
      Rarely do we have an opportunity to conduct a trial that will likely result in a paradigm
      shift of medical care for children who have strokes. Completion of the trial will provide a
      targeted strategy for secondary stroke prevention in regions of the world where regular blood
      transfusion therapy is not routinely available, and children with strokes are left with no
      reasonable alternative for stroke prevention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence of clinically overt stroke, transient ischemic attack or death</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effectiveness of moderate dose HU therapy at 20 mg/kg/day for secondary stroke prevention when compared to low dose HU therapy at 10 mg/kg/day in children with SCA. Within 30 days after the onset of a first stroke, children 1 to 18 years of age with SCA will be randomized to receive moderate dose HU therapy at 20 mg/kg/day (study group) or low dose HU therapy at 10 mg/kg/day (control group) with monthly follow-up for at least 36 months per participant. Parents will be educated on how to recognize signs and symptoms of a stroke. The rate of stroke recurrence will be measured using standardized neurological examinations (Pediatric NIH Stroke Scale).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of all cause hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine whether moderate HU therapy at 20 mg/kg/day decreases the rate of all-cause hospitalizations when compared to low dose HU therapy at 10 mg/kg/day with monthly follow-up for at least 36 months per participant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of stroke and incidence of recurrent strokes</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess prevalence of strokes and incidence of recurrent strokes among individuals with SCD ages 1 - 18 at active study site from January 1, 2014 to June 30, 2017.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Anemia</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hydroxyurea (Moderate Dose)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study intervention will include moderate dose hydroxyurea therapy at 20 mg/kg/day (range 17.5 - 26 mg/kg/day) for 36 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hydroxyurea (Low Dose)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study intervention will include random allocation to low dose hydroxyurea therapy at 10 mg/kg/day (range 7 - 15 mg/kg/day) for 36 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Moderate Dose Hydroxyurea</intervention_name>
    <description>Hydroxyurea therapy at 20 mg/kg/day for primary stroke prevention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hydroxyurea (Moderate Dose)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hydrea</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low Dose Hydroxyurea</intervention_name>
    <description>Hydroxyurea therapy at 10 mg/kg/day (range 7 - 15 mg/kg/day) for primary stroke prevention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hydroxyurea (Low Dose)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hydrea</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children ages 1 to 18 years of age with sickle cell anemia confirmed by hemoglobin
             electrophoresis evaluation or high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC);

          -  Informed consent from a parent or legal guardian and assent of participants;

          -  Children with presence of new stroke up to and including 30 days prior to signing the
             informed consent;

          -  Acceptance of HU therapy for at least three years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children with history of stroke with event occurring more than 30 days prior to
             signing the informed consent;

          -  Confirmed pregnancy or considering family planning - due to possible
             hydroxyurea-induced congenital anomalies or abnormal fetal growth. Adolescents who
             have started their menses must have a pregnancy test done every month prior to getting
             a prescription for HU;

          -  Children who are already on blood transfusion or HU therapy;

          -  Other exclusions: significant cytopenias [absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt;1500/ul,
             platelets &lt;150,000/ul, reticulocytes &lt;80,000/ul, unless Hb is &gt; 9 g/dl], renal
             insufficiency (creatinine &gt; 0.8 mg/dl); other significant organ system dysfunction, or
             other contraindication to HU therapy; and history of seizures or diagnosis of
             epilepsy;

          -  Other significant organ system dysfunction based on the site investigators discretion;

          -  Any other condition, such as malnutrition, or chronic illness, which in the opinion of
             the site's Principal Investigator makes study therapy not advisable or unsafe;

          -  Active infections: bacterial, viral or fungal (tuberculosis, malaria, active
             hepatitis, osteomyelitis);

          -  Active chronic leg ulcers.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael R. DeBaun, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aminu Kano Teaching Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kano</city>
        <country>Nigeria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Murtala Muhammad Specialist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kano</city>
        <country>Nigeria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Nigeria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 5, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael DeBaun</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hydroxyurea</keyword>
  <keyword>sub-Saharan Africa</keyword>
  <keyword>secondary stroke prevention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hydroxyurea</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

