<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02676908</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SJH-01-VV</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02676908</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimum Duration of Compression Stockings After Endovenous Varicose Vein Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised Controlled Trial Comparing Duration of Compression Hosiery After Endovenous Ablation of Varicose Veins</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. James's Hospital, Ireland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. James's Hospital, Ireland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Compression stockings are traditionally worn for a period of time after varicose vein surgery
      to reduce pain and bruising. The investigators provide an ambulatory endovenous ablation
      service. Patients come to the Veins Unit, receive oral sedation, have their veins treated
      with either laser or radiofrequency ablation plus phlebectomies* under local anaesthetic,
      recover for an hour and then go home. *Phlebectomy describes the technique of pulling out
      small varicose veins through small incisions in the overlying skin. The standard practice of
      the Veins Unit is to advise patients to wear class two compression stockings for four weeks
      post-operatively. Many patients would prefer a shorter period of time in stockings.

      The Nice Guidelines for Varicose Veins has posed the question: 'How long should stockings be
      worn for after endovenous ablation?'

      Three trials have addressed this issue:

      Bakker looked at patients who wore stockings for either two or seven days after laser
      ablation only; the group who wore stockings for seven days fared better.

      Elderman looked at patients who either wore no stockings or stockings for two weeks after
      laser ablation only; the group who wore stockings for two weeks had less pain.

      Krasznai looked at patients who wore stockings for either 4 hours or 72 hours after
      radiofrequency ablation only; there was no significant difference in post-op pain among
      groups.

      None of these trials included patients who had phlebectomies at the same time. This study
      aims to answer the question 'How long is it necessary to wear compression stockings for after
      endovenous ablation (either laser or radiofrequency) plus concomitant phlebectomies?' The
      investigators plan to divide 110 patients into two groups- either 'stockings for 2 weeks'
      (trial group) or 'stockings for 4 weeks' (usual treatment group).

      Pre-operatively, all patients will fill out a pain score and two short quality of life
      questionnaires, one specific to varicose veins. Post-operatively at home, all patients will
      be asked to keep a diary of pain and analgesia use. They will also document bruising at seven
      days on charts and on a visual scale. At their four week clinic review, all patients will be
      asked to fill out a pain and bruising score, a bruising chart and the two short quality of
      life questionnaires again.

      The group with the best pain, bruising and quality of life scores post-operatively will help
      guide duration of compression therapy for future patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Nice Guidelines for Varicose Veins, published by the NHS in 2013, questioned the clinical
      benefit of stockings after endovenous ablation, and if there is benefit, how long the
      stockings should be worn for.

      Three randomised controlled trials have addressed these issues:

      Bakker and colleagues randomised 69 patients into two groups- stockings were worn for either
      two or seven days after laser ablation. The group who wore stockings for seven days had
      better pain and quality of life scores.

      Elderman and colleagues randomised 111 patients who had laser ablation into two groups- a
      group who wore no stockings, or a group who wore stockings for two weeks. The group who wore
      stockings for two weeks had less pain and required less analgesia.

      Krasznai and colleagues randomised 101 patients into two groups- stockings were worn for
      either 4 hours or 72 hours after radiofrequency ablation only; there was no significant
      difference in post-op pain among groups.

      None of these trials included patients who had phlebectomies at the same time.

      This study hopes to answer the question 'How long is it necessary to wear compression
      stockings for after endovenous ablation (either laser or radiofrequency) plus concomitant
      phlebectomies?'

      110 consecutive patients will be randomised into 'stockings for 2 weeks' (trial group) or
      'stockings for 4 weeks' (usual treatment group). Randomisation will be facilitated by online
      random number generation (https://www.random.org/). Patients with odd numbers will be
      allocated into the trial group; those randomly assigned even numbers will be allocated into
      the usual treatment group.

      Pre-operatively, all patients will be asked to fill out a visual analog pain score (VAS), the
      Aberdeen Varicose Veins questionnaire and the RAND 36-Item Health Survey. Patients will be
      evaluated in terms of CAEP staging and the Venous Clinical Severity Score (VCSS) by the
      supervising nurse or physician.

      Endovenous laser therapy (EVLT) plus phlebectomies or radiofrequency ablation (RFA) plus
      phlebectomies will be performed in the standard manner.

      The trial group will wear the stockings for 24 hours a day for the first 4 days, and then
      during the day only for the next 10 days. The usual treatment group will wear the stockings
      for 24 hours a day for a week, and then during the day only for the next 3 weeks.

      Post-operatively at home, patients will be asked to keep a diary of pain and analgesia use.
      They will also document bruising at 7 days on a diagram and on a visual analog scale.

      At their 4 week clinic review, again the VCSS will completed and patients will be asked to
      fill out a visual analog pain and bruising score, a bruising diagram, the Aberdeen Varicose
      Veins questionnaire and the RAND 36-Item Health Survey.

      Primary outcome measures are post-operative pain scores on the visual analog scale and
      post-operative bruising scores on the visual analog scale.

      Secondary outcome measures are changes in veins-related quality of life measured on the
      Aberdeen Varicose Veins Questionnaire and changes in overall quality of life based on the
      RAND 36-Item Health Survey.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Scores on the Visual Analog Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at four weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (Veins Related)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in veins related quality of life based on the Aberdeen Varicose Veins Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (General)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in general quality of life based on the RAND 36-Item Health Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Varicose Veins</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4 weeks &amp; EVLT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>After endovenous laser therapy and avulsions, patients will wear compression socks for four weeks (usual care)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4 weeks &amp; RFA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>After radiofrequency ablation therapy and avulsions, patients will wear compression socks for four weeks (usual care)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2 weeks &amp; EVLT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After endovenous laser therapy and avulsions, patients will wear compression socks for two weeks (trial group)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2 weeks &amp; RFA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After radiofrequency ablation therapy and avulsions, patients will wear compression socks for two weeks (trial group)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Compression socks for 2 weeks</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in the intervention group will be asked to wear compression stockings for two weeks post-operatively</description>
    <arm_group_label>2 weeks &amp; EVLT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2 weeks &amp; RFA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary or recurrent varicose veins

          -  Diagnosis on duplex of truncal (GSV and/or SSV and/or AATV) insufficiency

          -  Must be able to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who require long term compression (active ulcers/ deep venous incompetence)

          -  Patients who have already had one leg enrolled in the study

          -  Patients with congenital venous malformations

          -  Patients who require avulsions only

          -  Patients who are unable to complete the questionnaires due to a lack of command over
             the language or who have vision/ hearing disabilities

          -  Patients who are unable to attend the hospital for follow-up
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St James's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dublin</city>
        <zip>8</zip>
        <country>Ireland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Caitriona Canning</last_name>
      <phone>0860840771</phone>
      <email>cnichainin@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Ireland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jvsv.2014.01.003</url>
    <description>Elderman JH, Krasznai AG, Voogd AC, Hulsewé KWE, Sikkink CJJM. Role of compression stockings after endovenous laser therapy for primary varicosis. JVS Venous and Lymphatic Disorders. 2014 2(3): 289-296</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bakker NA, Schieven LW, Bruins RM, van den Berg M, Hissink RJ. Compression stockings after endovenous laser ablation of the great saphenous vein: a prospective randomized controlled trial. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2013 Nov;46(5):588-92. doi: 10.1016/j.ejvs.2013.08.001. Epub 2013 Sep 5.</citation>
    <PMID>24012465</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krasznai AG, Sigterman TA, Troquay S, Houtermans-Auckel JP, Snoeijs M, Rensma HG, Sikkink C, Bouwman LH. A randomised controlled trial comparing compression therapy after radiofrequency ablation for primary great saphenous vein incompetence. Phlebology. 2016 Mar;31(2):118-24. doi: 10.1177/0268355514568658. Epub 2015 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>25616874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 6, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 8, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. James's Hospital, Ireland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Caitriona Canning</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Fellow in Vascular Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>endovenous ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>laser</keyword>
  <keyword>radiofrequency</keyword>
  <keyword>stockings</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Varicose Veins</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

