<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02679638</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>27-15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02679638</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Factors and Perceptions Affecting Treatment Choices of Breast Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Factors and Perceptions Affecting Treatment Choices of Breast Cancer Patients. Multi-center Cross-sectional Study in Israel Among Breast Cancer Survivors, With a Preliminary Qualitative Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Haifa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Haifa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Multi-center Cross-sectional quantitative study with a preliminary qualitative study part
      aiming to identify and analyze demand factors, supply factors and perceptions affecting
      Breast Cancer patients' treatment choices of Breast Cancer patients in 5 key decision points:
      participation role in the decision making process, hospital choice, treatment regimen choice,
      surgical extent and surgeon choice. 25 patients and caregivers will participate in the
      qualitative part and 425 Israeli Breast Cancer patients will participate in the quantitative
      study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Breast Cancer (BC) is the most common cancer in women worldwide. Newly diagnosed BC patients
      are asked to participate in a number of treatment related decisions. No research has
      systematically studied the full decision sequence in a disease such as BC, analyzing demand
      factors, supply factors and patient perceptions.

      Study goal:

      Identify and analyze demand factors, supply factors and perceptions affecting BC patients'
      treatment choices, and model the demand function of BC patients in 5 key decision points:
      participation role in the decision making process, hospital choice, treatment regimen choice,
      surgical extent and surgeon choice.

      Study hypothesis: Patient perceptions will have at least as much impact as demand and supply
      factors.

      Study design:

      Two stage study. A preliminary qualitative study, holding depth interviews with 20 breast
      cancer patients, 2 spouses and 3 staff members is taking place these days. The qualitative
      study findings will be used to develop a survey questionnaire for a cross sectional
      quantitative study, interviewing a quota sample of 425 breast cancer survivors, diagnosed up
      to 5 years prior to joining the study, who have successfully completed all radiation therapy
      and chemotherapy.

      Data analysis:

      Qualitative data will be analyzed according to the Criteria Bases Qualitative Methodology.
      Quantitative data will be analyzed by two-variable statistical analysis and multi-variable
      statistical analysis adjusted to the nature of the dependent and independent variables.

      Possible policy recommendations:

      Forming consulting teams for cancer patients. Improving medical information communication.
      Focusing patients on the key decisions they face. Evaluating patient needs using demand
      factors, supply factors and perceptions to create systemic tools helping them face treatment
      decisions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of active, collaborative and passive patients according to the Control Preferences Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 18 months.</time_frame>
    <description>According to the Control Preferences Scale, a questionnaire developed by Degner and Colleagues (Degner, 1997), patients can take fully active role in the treatment decision process or be mostly active, collaborative, mostly passive or fully passive. The study will look at the factors and perceptions affecting patient's decision role.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Large or small hospital choice</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 18 months.</time_frame>
    <description>The study interviews patients treated at two large Hospitals (Rambam, Sheba), and two small hospitals (Kaplan, Barzilay) looking for the factors and perceptions affecting large or small hospital choice.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who chose an oncological regimen more intense than recommended by clinical guidelines.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 18 months.</time_frame>
    <description>The study will look at the factors and perceptions affecting patient's choice to undergo an oncological treatment more intense than recommended by clinical guidelines.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients choosing radical mastectomy over lumpectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 18 months.</time_frame>
    <description>The study will look at the factors and perceptions affecting patient's choice to undergo a surgical cancer removal procedure more radical than recommended by clinical guidelines.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific surgeon choice</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 18 months.</time_frame>
    <description>The study will look at the factors and perceptions affecting patient's choice a specific surgeon in the Israeli healthcare system.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">450</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kaplan Hospital</arm_group_label>
    <description>Breast cancer survivors recruited at the Kaplan Medical Center</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rambam Hospital</arm_group_label>
    <description>Breast cancer survivors recruited at the Rambam Medical Center</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sheba</arm_group_label>
    <description>Breast cancer survivors recruited at the Sheba Medical Center</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Barzilai</arm_group_label>
    <description>Breast cancer survivors recruited at the Barzilai Medical Center</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Factors and perceptions questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>A detailed questionnaire inquiring about demand factors, supply factors and perceptions affecting patients' treatment choices in 5 key decision points: participation role in the decision making process, hospital choice, treatment regimen choice, surgical extent and surgeon choice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Kaplan Hospital</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rambam Hospital</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sheba</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Barzilai</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Qualitative interview</intervention_name>
    <description>Depth interviews with 20 breast cancer patients, 2 spouses and 3 staff members.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Kaplan Hospital</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rambam Hospital</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Hebrew speaking Jewish women aged 30 - 75 years, diagnosed with breast cancer up to 5 years
        prior to study recruitment, which have successfully completed all chemotherapy and
        radiotherapy treatments and are considered disease free.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Hebrew speaking Jewish women

          -  Aged 30 - 75 years

          -  Diagnosed with breast cancer up to 5 years prior to study recruitment

          -  Successfully completed all chemotherapy and radiotherapy treatments

          -  Considered Cancer free

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any type of residual cancer

          -  Any type of chemotherapy or radiotherapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shuli Brammli-Greenberg, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Head of the Master of Public Health Program at Haifa University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shuli Brammli-Greenberg, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+972508159054</phone>
    <email>Shuli@jdc.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Boaz Hovav, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+972543166653</phone>
    <email>bhovav@campus.haifa.ac.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Adams EK, Houchens R, Wright GE, Robbins J. Predicting hospital choice for rural Medicare beneficiaries: the role of severity of illness. Health Serv Res. 1991 Dec;26(5):583-612.</citation>
    <PMID>1743970</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Beaver K, Luker KA, Owens RG, Leinster SJ, Degner LF, Sloan JA. Treatment decision making in women newly diagnosed with breast cancer. Cancer Nurs. 1996 Feb;19(1):8-19.</citation>
    <PMID>8904382</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Benbassat J, Pilpel D, Tidhar M. Patients' preferences for participation in clinical decision making: a review of published surveys. Behav Med. 1998 Summer;24(2):81-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9695899</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bouche G, Migeot V, Mathoulin-Pélissier S, Salamon R, Ingrand P. Breast cancer surgery: do all patients want to go to high-volume hospitals? Surgery. 2008 Jun;143(6):699-705. doi: 10.1016/j.surg.2008.03.013. Epub 2008 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>18549885</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Celaya MO, Rees JR, Gibson JJ, Riddle BL, Greenberg ER. Travel distance and season of diagnosis affect treatment choices for women with early-stage breast cancer in a predominantly rural population (United States). Cancer Causes Control. 2006 Aug;17(6):851-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16783613</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Duric V, Stockler M. Patients' preferences for adjuvant chemotherapy in early breast cancer: a review of what makes it worthwhile. Lancet Oncol. 2001 Nov;2(11):691-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11902540</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Harris KM. How do patients choose physicians? Evidence from a national survey of enrollees in employment-related health plans. Health Serv Res. 2003 Apr;38(2):711-32.</citation>
    <PMID>12785569</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hawley ST, Griggs JJ, Hamilton AS, Graff JJ, Janz NK, Morrow M, Jagsi R, Salem B, Katz SJ. Decision involvement and receipt of mastectomy among racially and ethnically diverse breast cancer patients. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2009 Oct 7;101(19):1337-47. doi: 10.1093/jnci/djp271. Epub 2009 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>19720966</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jansen SJ, Otten W, Stiggelbout AM. Review of determinants of patients' preferences for adjuvant therapy in cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2004 Aug 1;22(15):3181-90. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15284271</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Katz SJ, Lantz PM, Janz NK, Fagerlin A, Schwartz K, Liu L, Deapen D, Salem B, Lakhani I, Morrow M. Patient involvement in surgery treatment decisions for breast cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Aug 20;23(24):5526-33.</citation>
    <PMID>16110013</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Keating NL, Guadagnoli E, Landrum MB, Borbas C, Weeks JC. Treatment decision making in early-stage breast cancer: should surgeons match patients' desired level of involvement? J Clin Oncol. 2002 Mar 15;20(6):1473-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11896094</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nelson JA, Tchou J, Domchek S, Sonnad SS, Serletti JM, Wu LC. Breast reconstruction in bilateral prophylactic mastectomy patients: factors that influence decision making. J Plast Reconstr Aesthet Surg. 2012 Nov;65(11):1481-9. doi: 10.1016/j.bjps.2012.05.001. Epub 2012 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22640643</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rees CE, Bath PA. The information needs and source preferences of women with breast cancer and their family members: a review of the literature published between 1988 and 1998. J Adv Nurs. 2000 Apr;31(4):833-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10759979</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Simes RJ, Coates AS. Patient preferences for adjuvant chemotherapy of early breast cancer: how much benefit is needed? J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr. 2001;(30):146-52.</citation>
    <PMID>11773309</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tropman SE, Ricketts TC, Paskett E, Hatzell TA, Cooper MR, Aldrich T. Rural breast cancer treatment: evidence from the Reaching Communities for Cancer Care (REACH) project. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 1999 Jul;56(1):59-66.</citation>
    <PMID>10517343</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Degner LF, Sloan JA, Venkatesh P. The Control Preferences Scale. Can J Nurs Res. 1997 Fall;29(3):21-43.</citation>
    <PMID>9505581</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 9, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 10, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 9, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 9, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 10, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment choice</keyword>
  <keyword>factor</keyword>
  <keyword>perception</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

