<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02671292</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MPS-72-3248</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DK104115</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02671292</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preventing Obesity in Military Communities-Adolescents</brief_title>
  <acronym>POMC-A</acronym>
  <official_title>Preventing Obesity in Military Communities-Adolescents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Henry M. Jackson Foundation for the Advancement of Military Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fort Belvoir Community Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Henry M. Jackson Foundation for the Advancement of Military Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine whether reducing loss of control eating (LOC) with Interpersonal
      Psychotherapy-Weight Gain (IPT-WG) will be effective for adolescent military-dependents who
      report such behavior. The investigators will examine whether IPT-WG influences body weight
      gain trajectories and prevents worsening disordered eating, psychosocial problems, and
      metabolic functioning among military dependents at heightened risk for adult obesity and
      disordered eating. This study will provide key efficacy data for a new promising obesity
      prevention program for youth from military families.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The prevalence of overweight among military personnel and their dependents is at a rate
      similar to that of the civilian population. Nearly 30% of adolescent dependents are
      overweight, including approximately 15-17% who are obese, placing them at high risk for
      impairments in metabolic functioning, type 2 diabetes, and adult obesity. Youth who are
      overweight (body mass index, kg/m2, BMI ≥ 85th percentile) are at high risk for excess weight
      gain as they grow. Since effective weight loss and maintenance treatments are rare,
      prevention may be the most important approach to reducing the high prevalence of obesity. To
      date, most pediatric obesity prevention programs have been met with limited success. To
      address those at greatest risk for obesity, more targeted approaches may be required. There
      is a need to reduce prospectively identified risk factors in order to prevent excess weight
      gain in youth at high risk for adult obesity. The most common disordered eating behavior
      among overweight adolescents is loss of control (LOC) eating, during which the feeling of
      being unable to stop eating is experienced. LOC eating predisposes youth to gain excessive
      weight and fat. Thus, LOC eating is likely to be an important contributor to obesity in
      susceptible individuals. Decreasing LOC in adolescents may prevent excess weight gain.
      Investigators at the Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences (USUHS) is in
      partnership with Ft. Belvoir Community Hospital (FBCH) and Walter Reed National Military
      Medical Center (WRNMMC) to test the effectiveness of IPT-WG to slow the trajectory of weight
      gain in overweight adolescent boys and girls who report LOC and prevent worsening disordered
      eating and metabolic functioning. The unique stress burdening the children of military
      personnel while the country is at war suggests that obesity prevention programs targeting
      interpersonal stress and promoting positive social functioning may be especially timely in
      this population. It is hypothesized that IPT-WG will decrease LOC eating and related eating
      behaviors and, in turn, prevent excess weight gain and the development of exacerbated
      disordered eating in adolescent children of military personnel. Secondary to the prevention
      of excess weight gain, youth will experience improvements in metabolic functioning.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in weight from baseline to 3 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Weight will be measured</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of binge eating</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in presence of binge eating from baseline to 1 year post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The Eating Disorder Examination (EDE) will be administered to assess for the presence of binge eating. The EDE identifies three types of eating episodes: objective binge eating (overeating with LOC), subjective binge eating (LOC without objective overeating as assessed by the interviewer, but viewed as excessive by the interviewee), and objective overeating (overeating without LOC), as well as the range of compensatory behaviors described in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-5).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist Circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in waist circumference from baseline to 3 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Waist circumference will be measured using a flexible measuring tape.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in blood pressure from baseline to 3 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure will be measured using an automatic blood pressure cuff.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Triglycerides</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in triglycerides from baseline to 3 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Blood will be drawn to collect a sample for the measurement of triglycerides.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HDL Cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in HDL cholesterol from baseline to 3 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Blood will be drawn to collect a sample for the measurement of HDL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin Function</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in insulin sensitivity from baseline to 3 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Blood will be drawn to collect a sample for the measurement of insulin.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in glucose from baseline to 3 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Blood will be drawn to collect a sample for the measurement of glucose.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoglobin A1c</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in hemoglobin A1c from baseline to 3 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Blood will be drawn to collect a sample for the measurement of hemoglobin A1c.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BMI Percentile</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in BMI percentile from baseline to 3 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Height and weight will be measured and BMI percentile calculated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <condition>Binge Eating</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interpersonal Psychotherapy (IPT-WG)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>IPT-WG targets the difficult social functioning and stressful events that are associated with loss of control eating and that are highly relevant to the adolescent children of military personnel.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health Education (HE)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>HE improves knowledge on various health topics including, alcohol, drug and tobacco use, depression and suicide, nutrition and body image, nonviolent conflict resolution, sun safety, exercise, and domestic violence.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interpersonal Psychotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>IPT-WG involves one initial 1.5-hour individual session, and 12 weekly 90-minute group sessions. The IPT-WG group sessions follow 3 phases (initial, middle, and termination) and use the interpersonal inventory to identify interpersonal problems that might be contributing to or exacerbated by LOC eating. A framework of common problem areas is used to teach interpersonal problem-solving and communication skills and educate youth about risk factors for excessive weight gain and warning signs such as eating in response to negative affect as opposed to hunger, or feeling a sense of LOC while eating.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interpersonal Psychotherapy (IPT-WG)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Education</intervention_name>
    <description>The HE group is based upon the &quot;HEY-Durham&quot; health program designed by researchers at Duke University. This program, designed to be delivered to youth attending community high schools, was adapted to a 12-week program (each session is 90 minutes). Additionally, individuals will attend a pre-group individual meeting with the group leaders to review family health history.The curriculum includes focus on various health topics, including alcohol, drug and tobacco use, depression and suicide, nutrition and body image, nonviolent conflict resolution, sun safety, exercise, and domestic violence. Session content will be largely identical for boys and girls, with the exception of gender-specific videos and articles (e.g., on body image), which will be tailored for each sex.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health Education (HE)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Adolescent Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age between 12 and 17 years (at the start of the study)

          2. BMI at or above the 85th percentile for age and sex

          3. English-speaking

          4. Ability to complete study procedures, including the ability to participate in a group

          5. &gt; 1 episode of LOC eating during the 3 months prior to assessment

          6. Must have a parent(s) enrolled in TRICARE at the time of study initiation

        Parent Inclusion Criteria:

        1.The consenting parent or caregiver must be able to comprehend English.

        Adolescent Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of a chronic major medical illness: renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal,
             endocrinologic (e.g., Cushing syndrome, hyper- or hypothyroidism), hematological
             problems or pulmonary disorders (other than asthma not requiring continuous
             medication).

          2. Presence of a documented, obesity-related medical complication that would require a
             more aggressive weight loss intervention approach: type 2 diabetes, hyperlipidemia,
             hypertension, fasting hyperglycemia, or nonalcoholic steatohepatitis.

          3. Self-reported current pregnancy, current breast-feeding, or recently pregnant girls
             (within 1 year of delivery).

          4. Current, regular use of prescription medications that affect appetite, mood, or body
             weight: currently prescribed SSRI's, neuroleptics, tricyclics, stimulants, or any
             other medication known to affect appetite, mood, or body weight. For girls, oral
             contraceptive use will be permitted, provided the contraceptive has been used for at
             least two months before starting the prevention groups. Medication use for non-serious
             conditions (e.g., acne) will be considered on a case-by-case basis.

          5. Current involvement in psychotherapy or a structured weight loss program.

          6. Weight loss during the past two months for any reason exceeding 3% of body weight.

          7. Current anorexia nervosa or bulimia nervosa as determined by documented medical
             history or if uncovered during K-SADS semi-structured interview. Current binge eating
             disorder (BED) will be permitted, although adolescents will be informed that they have
             an eating disorder and have the option to participate in the study or seek outside
             treatment (and not participate in the study).

          8. Individuals who have major depressive disorder, psychoses, current substance or
             alcohol abuse, conduct disorder, as determined by Kiddie Schedule for Affective
             Disorders and Schizophrenia (K-SADS) semi-structured interview and as defined by
             criteria outlined in the DSM-5, or any other DSM psychiatric disorder that, in the
             opinion of the investigators, would impede competence or compliance or possibly hinder
             completion of the study.

        Parent Exclusion Criteria:

        1. None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marian Tanofsky-Kraff, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Abigail Pine, B.A.</last_name>
    <phone>301-295-1598</phone>
    <email>abigail.pine.ctr@usuhs.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mary Quattlebaum, B.A.</last_name>
    <phone>301-295-0864</phone>
    <email>mary.quattlebaum.ctr@usuhs.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20814</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Abigail Pine, B.A.</last_name>
      <phone>301-295-1598</phone>
      <email>abigail.pine.ctr@usuhs.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mary Quattlebaum, B.A.</last_name>
      <phone>301-295-0864</phone>
      <email>mary.quattlebaum.ctr@usuhs.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fort Belvoir Community Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Belvoir</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22060</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Abigail Pine, B.A.</last_name>
      <phone>301-295-1598</phone>
      <email>abigail.pine.ctr@usuhs.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mary Quattlebaum, B.A.</last_name>
      <phone>301-295-0864</phone>
      <email>mary.quattlebaum.ctr@usuhs.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Klein, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Loss of Control Eating</keyword>
  <keyword>Binge Eating</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Interpersonal Psychotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bulimia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Binge-Eating Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

