<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02676622</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB1100448</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02676622</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Autologous Stem Cell Transplant for Refractory Crohn's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Autologous Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation With Post-Transplant Ultra Low-Dose IL-2 for Refractory Crohn's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nationwide Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nationwide Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Crohn's disease is an 'auto-immune' disorder of the gut. In this condition the body's own
      immune system is fighting its gut and causing inflammation and other symptoms. Patients who
      are refractory (not responding) to the medications usually used to control Crohn's disease
      (medicines like steroids, azathioprine, methotrexate, cyclophosphamide and antibodies like
      Infliximab), may consider being part of this study.

      In this study, the investigators plan to wipe out (ablate) the 'faulty immune system' with
      medicines (immune-ablation) and then give back the patients own stored stem cells (that have
      been collected before) - a procedure called autologous (self) stem cell transplant (ASCT).
      Once the new immune system regrows again from the stem cells, it is hoped that the 'faulty'
      immune cells do not return again and do not fight the gut leading to remission from symptoms
      of Crohn's disease. The aim of this treatment therefore, is to reset or re-program the immune
      system, so that it does not fight the patient's own body.

      Currently, there are very few trials and experience with this procedure in children and young
      adults. There have been a few studies that have shown benefit of ASCT procedure in adult
      patients. In some patients, the benefit lasted for 1-5 years; but 1 in 5 (20%) participants
      were not taking their medications for the Crohn's disease even 5 years after ASCT. Other 80%
      needed medications again, but in most cases with better disease control.

      In order to potentially improve the long term outcomes of ASCT, the investigators are adding
      another medication (in addition to those used in adult studies) called IL-2 (Aldesleukin),
      which will be given as an every-other-day injection under the skin (subcutaneous) at very low
      doses for 6 weeks after the ASCT and can be taken at home. Low dose IL-2 is known to increase
      a type of immune cell called T-regulatory cells (Tregs) that make immune cells less reactive
      to self. Study doctors believe that increased population of Tregs after ASCT may lead to a
      better control of Crohn's disease- higher percentage of cures or disease control for a longer
      period of time compared to the previous adult trials.

      Therefore, the goals of this study are-

        1. To see if ASCT can be used safely and can provide substantial benefit in young adults
           who have refractory Crohn's disease.

        2. To see if addition of IL-2 after the ASCT is safe and effective.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Crohn's Disease (CD) is an immunologically mediated chronic illness that has a relapsing and
      remitting course, most commonly presenting in the 2nd or 3rd decade and causing life long
      impairment of health and quality of life. Mainstay of clinical treatment for severe disease
      is combination of anti-inflammatory agents like 5-aminosalicyaltes and immunosuppressive
      medications like corticosteroids and newer anti-TNF antibodies like Infliximab. None of the
      drugs are, at present, curative and a relevant subset of patients are refractory to many of
      these pharmacologic approaches.

      Immunoablative treatment followed by autologous stem cell rescue (Autologous HSCT) has been
      tried in this refractory group of patients with successful results. Autologous HSCT works in
      this auto-immune setting through the eradication of effector/memory T-cell clones due to a
      direct immuno-ablative effect of drugs used in the preparative regimen; by leading to an
      immune-reset- recovering clones of T- cells from the infused stem cells do not mount an
      auto-immune response and are tolerant to 'self' antigens and, by upregulation of T regulatory
      cells (Treg, CD4+CD25+FOXP3+ or CD8+ FOXP3+) via change in cytokine mileu during transplant.
      Increased population of Tregs restricts the activity of self reactive effector T-cells.

      This pilot study is designed to gain on the success of previously published adult studies of
      autologous HSCT in refractory CD, with the aim to confirm the feasibility, safety and
      efficacy of HSCT and ultra low dose IL-2 when given post-HSCT in pediatric patients and young
      adults. IL-2 in very low doses has been shown to increase the proliferation of Treg
      lymphocytes and decrease inflammatory response. Hence, use of IL-2 post-transplant will
      result in significant and persistent increase in Treg population that may lead to more
      durable remissions after immunoablative therapy.

      This pilot will focus on the 'safety' of this treatment in pediatric population.Since, this
      combination of immuno-ablative therapy followed by ultra low dose IL-2 has not been studied
      in children with CD, therefore transplant related mortality (TRM) and severe toxicity (&gt;
      grade 3 toxicity by NCI criteria) will be monitored for 100 days post-transplant in all the
      patients and stopping rules will be enforced in case of excessive toxicity or TRM (&gt;10%).
      Correlative studies will be performed at specific time points to assess the cytokine and
      inflammatory markers, immune-reconstitution and quantitative Treg cells; while clinical
      assessments will be done for 1 year post-HSCT for disease activity, steroid free remission
      period to evaluate the 'clinical efficacy' of this procedure.

      The major aim of this pilot is to generate the preliminary safety and cytokine profile data
      to confirm the feasibility and benefit of autologous HSCT and IL-2 in children and young
      adults with refractory CD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    PI moved to a different institution.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoint of the study is feasibility and safety of the autologous HSCT and low dose IL-2 post-HSCT, as evaluated by day +100 TRM (transplant related mortality) and incidence of severe toxicity.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after transplant</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary endpoints are evaluations of the effects of HSCT on clinical and laboratory manifestations of Crohn's Disease, i.e. frequency of and types of transplant related complications that were observed.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of Infections: CMV reactivation and disease, adenovirus infection, BK virus reactivation, EBV PTLD and invasive fungal infections will be estimated and documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Crohn's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stem-cell mobilization and Leukapheresis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Stem-cell mobilisation will be achieved using Cyclophosphamide (CY) 4g/m² (2g/m2 on 2 consecutive days) followed 5 days later by filgrastim (G-CSF) 10 mg/kg injection. This will be done daily until the day before the last day of leukapheresis. The PBSCs will be harvested usually between day +9 and +11 of completing CY.
Leukapheresis will be performed to a target cell dose of 3-8 x106 CD34+ cells/kg Approximately 1 month later patients will undergo HSCT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mobilization of stem cells to prepare for Leukapheresis</intervention_name>
    <description>Cyclophosphomide 2 g/m2 x 2 consecutive days.
Filgrastim (G-csf) 10 mcg/kg SC will start 5 days after the last dose of CY and will end the day before the last leukapharesis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stem-cell mobilization and Leukapheresis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cytoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>G-csf</other_name>
    <other_name>Neupogen</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leukapheresis- Collection of stem cells</intervention_name>
    <description>Placement of an Apheresis Catheter on the day of collection of stem cells.
Leukapheresis will be performed on a continuous flow separator machine to target 3-8 x 106 CD34+ cells/kg body weight.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stem-cell mobilization and Leukapheresis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>white blood cells</other_name>
    <other_name>Apheresis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Preparative regimen 4-6 weeks after Leukapheresis</intervention_name>
    <description>Prior to starting medicines, a central venous line will be placed (arm or chest)
Cyclophosphamide iv: 50 mg/kg iv over 2 hours
Mesna iv (uro-protectant): 36 mg/kg iv over 12 hours
r-ATG (Thymoglobulin, Genzyme): 2.5 mg/kg/dose iv over 6 hours on days -3,-2,-1</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stem-cell mobilization and Leukapheresis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cytoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Mesnex</other_name>
    <other_name>Thymoglobulin</other_name>
    <other_name>Genzyme</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stem Cell Transplant</intervention_name>
    <description>Infusion of the(cryopreserved and thawed)peripheral blood stem cells (PBSC)occurs on Day 0.
Day +5: start Filgrastim (G-csf) subcutaneous injections
Hospitalization in isolation room for 4-5 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stem-cell mobilization and Leukapheresis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HSCT</other_name>
    <other_name>Neupogen</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low-dose IL-2 administration</intervention_name>
    <description>IL-2 Subcutaneous injections will start once ANC is &gt; 500/µL and patient is afebrile (start IL-2 will be approximately day +20)for 6 weeks of treatment.
Once patient or parent has learnt the administration and patient is tolerating it well, then the rest of the treatment can be administered at home after discharge with weekly follow up visits.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stem-cell mobilization and Leukapheresis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aldesleukin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 12 and &lt; 30 years

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of Crohn's Disease -Pediatric Crohn's Disease Activity Index
             (PCDAI) &gt;30 or Crohn's Disease Activity Index (CDAI) of &gt;250 any time within 3 months
             prior to enrollment and any one of the following- i)Endoscopic evidence of active
             disease confirmed on histology within 3 months prior to enrollment, or ii) Clear
             evidence of active small bowel Crohn's disease on small bowel imaging within 3 months
             prior to enrollment.

          -  Refractory Crohn's Disease: Moderate to severe disease that has been unresponsive to
             current or prior therapy with mercaptopurine and/or azathioprine (thiopurines),
             methotrexate and anti-TNF therapy. Patients should have relapsing disease (i.e. &gt; 1
             exacerbation/year) or corticosteroid dependence despite current or prior thiopurines,
             methotrexate and anti-TNF maintenance therapy or clear demonstration of intolerance or
             toxicity to these drugs. Patients who fail induction therapy with corticosteroids and
             anti-TNF therapy, and are therefore not eligible to receive maintenance therapy with
             thiopurines or methotrexate will also be candidates for enrollment.

          -  Current active disease and problems not amenable to surgery or patient at risk for
             developing short bowel syndrome.

          -  Negative stool culture, C. difficile, and negative CMV pcr (in stool or colonic
             biopsy). Patients with CMV colitis will receive a trial of anti-viral treatment and
             only responders will be considered eligible for inclusion.

          -  Female patients of childbearing potential must have a documented negative serum
             pregnancy test within 2 weeks prior to starting the mobilization regimen.

          -  Patients with a prior ileostomy or colostomy may enter the study. For this group of
             patients', physician's global assesment will be used to assess clinical activity of
             CD, as Pediatric CDAI and CDAI scoring method may not be representative of disease
             activity.

          -  Patients with abscesses are eligible to enroll once the abscesses or any other
             significant infection has resolved.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy or unwillingness to use adequate contraception during the study- if a woman
             is of childbearing age.

          -  HIV infection. -Organ function criteria-

               1. Renal: creatinine clearance &lt; 50 ml/min/1.73m2 (measured or estimated).

               2. Cardiac: left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;30% by multigated radionuclide
                  angiography (MUGA) or a shortening fraction of &lt; 25% by cardiac echocardiogram.

               3. Pulmonary Function tests: DLCO &lt; 30% or patient on oxygen.

               4. Hepatic: serum bilirubin &gt; 3 mg%; AST and ALT &gt; 3x ULN for the institutional lab.

          -  Uncontrolled Hypertension (using age based criteria) despite at least 2
             anti-hypertensive agents.

        -Active Infection or risk thereof-

          1. Current abscess or significant active infection (see 6.2.9 above)

          2. Perianal infection is not an exclusion criterion, provided there is drainage with or
             without placement of seton.

          3. Abnormal chest x ray (CXR) consistent with active infection or neoplasm.

               -  Severe diarrhea due to short small bowel; pateints believed to have &lt; 700 mm of
                  small bowel and diarrhea attributable to this will be excluded.

               -  Patients with toxic megacolon, active bowel obstruction or intestinal
                  perforation.

               -  Lack of insurance payer approval.

               -  Unable to collect minimum cell dose from Leukapheresis required for transplant.
                  These patients will be excluded from receiving the preparative regimen.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>29 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandeep Soni, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nationwide Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 21, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 8, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Crohn's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Autologous Hematopoietic Stem cell Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Cyclophosphamide</keyword>
  <keyword>IL-2</keyword>
  <keyword>Aldesleukin</keyword>
  <keyword>Proleukin</keyword>
  <keyword>PCDAI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Crohn Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thymoglobulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

