<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02673827</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>618.841/2014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02673827</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Progressive Muscle Relaxation Effect on Sleep Quality, Depression and Stress in People With Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Progressive Muscle Relaxation as a Nursing Intervention on Sleep Quality, Depression and Stress in People With Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federal University of Espirito Santo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal University of Espirito Santo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective: Evaluate the effects of Progressive Muscle Relaxation on sleep quality and on
      stress and depression levels of individuals with multiple sclerosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: Multiple sclerosis is a chronic, autoimmune disease, characterized by
      demyelination and neurodegeneration of the central nervous system. The progressive course of
      this disease may cause individuals to develop extreme dependency and create serious
      difficulties both to the individuals themselves and family members and caregivers, since the
      disease brings a number of physical, emotional, psychological and social symptoms. Therefore,
      it is essential to offer healthcare practices that go beyond the usually fragmenting,
      dehumanized care services that focus on the disease bodily processes.

      Objective: Evaluate the effects of Progressive Muscle Relaxation on sleep quality and on
      stress and depression levels of individuals with multiple sclerosis.

      Methodology: This is randomized clinical test. The sample was made up of 40 individuals with
      multiple sclerosis (20 in control group and 20 in the experimental group) in outpatient
      follow-up. The progressive muscle relaxation technique was employed. In order to collect the
      data, we adopted the interview with form filling technique, using the Pittsburgh Sleep
      Quality Index, Perceived Stress Scale and Beck Depression Inventory. Blood pressure, heart
      rate and respiratory rate of experimental group were measured before and after the
      progressive muscle relaxation intervention. In order to treat statistical data, we used
      Statistical Package for Social Sciences, version 19.0.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress Level</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Instrument: Perceived Stress Scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of depression</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Instrument : Beck Depression Inventory.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>sleep quality</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Instrument: Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Sleep</condition>
  <condition>Stress Psychological</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group: 20 patients with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis only receive traditional treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>experimental group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention group: 20 patients with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis receive five sessions of Progressive Muscle Relaxation under the supervision of a researcher in neurology clinic. Before and after each session of the Progressive Muscle Relaxation.
They will be measured heart rate, respiratory rate and blood pressure. Participants will be guided to realize the Progressive Muscle Relaxation daily for 8 weeks, the time of day you feel more comfortable. the same receive education and training as the technical as well as a audio and a leaflet with the description the stages of the Progressive Muscle Relaxation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Progressive muscle relaxation</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention group: 20 patients with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis receive five sessions of Progressive Muscle Relaxation under the supervision of a researcher in neurology clinic. Before and after each session of the Progressive Muscle Relaxation They will be measured heart rate, respiratory rate and blood pressure. Participants will be guided to realize the Progressive Muscle Relaxation daily for 8 weeks, the time of day you feel more comfortable. the same receive education and training as the technical as well as a audio and a leaflet with the description the stages of the Progressive Muscle Relaxation. Control group: 20 patients with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis only receive traditional treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>experimental group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  To be diagnosed with Multiple Sclerosis for at least 6 months

          -  To be diagnosed with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis

          -  To have Expanded Disability Status Scale score &lt; 5.0

          -  To not have had any attacks during the 3-month period preceding enrollment in the
             study

          -  To have audio at home

          -  To be residing in the Metropolitan region of Vitória-Espirito Santo-Brazil.

          -  To be 18-65 years of age

          -  Treatment with an immunomodulator

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Being hospitalized at the time of data collection or outbreak at the time of data
             collection

          -  Have physical and / or mental changes that prevent the collection of data, such as
             motor or cognitive deficits

          -  Experiencing relapse and/or corticosteroid use within the last month, diagnosed with
             progressive MS (primary or secondary)

          -  Use of psychotropic drugs (antidepressants, benzodiazepines, antipsychotic and
             cannabis, or other stimulants),

          -  Practice of other relaxation techniques (yoga, pilates, meditation, psychotherapy)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 28, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 1, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 1, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal University of Espirito Santo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paolla Gabrielle Nascimento Novais</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

