<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02512757</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Ajinomoto 2015-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02512757</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Case-Control Study to Verify Diagnostic Performance of AminoIndex™ Technology</brief_title>
  <official_title>The AminoIndex™ Study - A Case-Control Study to Verify Diagnostic Performance of AminoIndex™ Technology</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Innovis LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ajinomoto Co., Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Innovis LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, multi-center study to evaluate the diagnostic performance
      characteristics of the AminoIndex™ technology among patients at high risk for developing lung
      cancer as compared with standard lung cancer screening and diagnostic procedures including
      low-dose CT, high-dose CT, biopsy and histopathology.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, multi-center study to evaluate the diagnostic performance
      characteristics of the AminoIndex™ technology among patients at high risk for developing lung
      cancer as compared with standard lung cancer screening and diagnostic procedures including
      low-dose CT, high-dose CT, biopsy and histopathology.

      The study will enroll patients into one of three arms:

        1. patients with lung nodule(s) ≥ 6 mm but ≤ 35 mm that have been biopsied and diagnosed
           with primary lung cancer who have not yet initiated treatment of any kind for their lung
           cancer;

        2. patients with lung nodule(s) ≥ 6 mm but ≤ 35 mm that have been biopsied and determined
           to not be cancerous OR that have demonstrated no nodule growth for &gt; 2 years by repeat
           CT imaging; and

        3. patients at high-risk for lung cancer (per NLST guidelines) with no evidence or history
           of lung cancer (negative LDCT/CT/X-ray).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 13, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 17, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 17, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The diagnostic performance of AminoIndex™ to discriminate lung cancer patients from high-risk subjects.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the diagnostic performance characteristics of the AminoIndex™ technology among patients at high risk for developing lung cancer as compared with standard lung cancer screening and diagnostic procedures including low-dose CT, high-dose CT, biopsy and histopathology.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The capability of AminoIndex™ to distinguish malignant lung cancer from benign lung nodules.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gathering residual patient samples that will be used for discovery research.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with lung nodule(s) ≥ 6 mm but ≤ 35 mm that have been biopsied and diagnosed with primary lung cancer who have not yet initiated treatment of any kind for their lung cancer will contribute a fasting blood sample.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients whose most recent screening imaging is within 60 days who have lung nodule(s) ≥ 6 mm but ≤ 35 mm that have been biopsied and determined to not be cancerous OR that have demonstrated no nodule growth for &gt;2 years by repeat CT imaging will contribute a fasting blood sample.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who have undergone low-dose computed tomography (LDCT) or standard computed tomography (CT) or X-ray testing to screen for lung cancer with no nodules suspicious for lung cancer within 1 year prior to signing informed consent will contribute a fasting blood sample.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Subjects will consent to archiving and future analysis of their blood samples for up to
      twenty (20) years.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study will enroll sufficient subjects to yield a minimum of 60 subjects in Study Group 1,
        30 subjects in Study Group 2 and 60 subjects in Study Group 3 - a total of 150 evaluable
        study subjects who meet all inclusion and exclusion criteria. Eligible subjects will be men
        and women age ≥ 18 years for Group 1 and 2 and 55 - 79 years inclusive for Group 3. Group 3
        study subjects must also meet NLST guidelines of being at high risk for lung cancer:
        greater than or equal to a 30 pack year smoking history (equivalent of 1 pack per day for
        30 or more years) and a current smoker or quit less than 15 years ago.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        All Groups:

          -  Able to read, understand and sign informed consent to participate in study.

          -  Willing and able to provide written informed consent.

          -  Willing and able to meet all study requirements and undergo venipuncture to provide a
             fasting blood sample.

        Group 1:

          -  Men or women age 18 years or older;

          -  Lung nodule size ≥ 6 mm but ≤ 35 mm/ lung, nodule or mass.

          -  Diagnosis of lung cancer based upon histopathology performed on lung nodule, lesion or
             mass tissue obtained from biopsy or surgical excision performed after study-related
             fasting blood sample obtained.

        Group 2:

          -  Men or women age 18 years or older;

          -  Lung nodule size ≥ 6 mm but ≤ 35 mm/ lung nodule, lesion or mass;

          -  Definitive diagnosis of benign (non-cancerous) lung nodule based upon one of the
             following:

               -  Histopathology performed on lung nodule tissue obtained from biopsy or surgical
                  excision performed after study-related fasting blood sample obtained;

               -  No nodule growth for &gt; 2 years by repeat CT imaging, the most recent being
                  performed within the 60 days prior to signing informed consent.

        Group 3:

          -  Men or women age 55-79 years inclusive;

          -  Current smoker or quit &lt; 15 years ago with a &gt; 30 pack-year smoking history
             (equivalent of 1 pack per day for 30 or more years)*.

          -  Have undergone low-dose computed tomography (LDCT) or standard computed tomography
             (CT) or X-ray testing to screen for lung cancer with no nodules suspicious for lung
             cancer within 1 year prior to signing informed consent.

        ' * ' One pack year is calculated as follows: 20 cigarettes = 1 pack. One &quot;pack year&quot; is
        the equivalent of smoking:

          -  20 cigarettes (one pack) per day for one year; or

          -  40 cigarettes (two packs) per day for 6 months; or

          -  60 cigarettes (three packs) per day for 3 months

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Inability to fast for 8 hours prior to the blood sample collection.

          -  Known to be positive for HIV and/or, HBV and/or HCV.

          -  Pregnancy.

          -  Breastfeeding.

          -  Currently undergoing dialysis.

          -  Congenital metabolic disease.

          -  Currently receiving investigational treatments of any type.

          -  History of receiving any drug therapy or surgery for the treatment of lung cancer.

          -  Diagnosis of cancer within past 5 years and/or currently undergoing treatment for any
             cancer.

          -  Any clinical condition, diagnosis, or social circumstance that, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, would be mean participation in the study would be contraindicated.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>79 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gregg S. Britt</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Innovis LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Lung Asthma and Sleep Specialists P.A.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Celebration</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34747</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pulmonary and Critical Care Associates of Baltimore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21237</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt-Ingram Cancer Center (VICC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 27, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 28, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 31, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neoplasms, Lung</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Cancer</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

