<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02517476</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EKNZ 2014-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02517476</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Early Nutritional Therapy on Frailty, Functional Outcomes and Recovery of Undernourished Medical Inpatients Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>EFFORT</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of Early Nutritional Therapy on Frailty, Functional Outcomes and Recovery of Undernourished Medical Inpatients Trial: The EFFORT Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swiss National Science Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Luzerner Kantonsspital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kantonsspital Münsterlingen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clinical Trial Unit, University Hospital Basel, Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aims of the randomized-controlled, multicenter EFFORT trial are to assess the effects of
      early nutritional therapy in regard to effectiveness, safety and costs when applied to the
      heterogenous, polymorbid medical inpatient population. EFFORT will not only answer the
      question about overall benefit or harm, but using a physio-pathological mechanistic approach,
      it also will explore and provide conclusive answers about whether, why, how, and in which
      patient populations nutritional therapy does and does not works.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aims of the randomized-controlled, multicenter EFFORT trial are to test the hypothesis
      that in medical inpatients at risk for undernutrition defined by the nutritional risk score
      (NRS 2002), early tailored nutritional therapy to reach nutritional targets based on
      individualized nutritional counseling is a cost-effective strategy to prevent mortality,
      morbidity and functional decline.

      The primary composite endpoint is combined adverse outcome within 30 days defined as (a)
      all-cause mortality, (b) admission to the intensive care unit from the medical ward, (c)
      major complications, (d) unplanned hospital readmissions and (d) decline in functional
      outcome from admission to day 30 assessed by Barthel`s index (-10%). Secondary endpoints
      include (a) each single component of the primary endpoint (b) short-term nutritional and
      functional outcomes from inclusion to day 10 or hospital discharge; (c) hospital outcomes;
      (d) 30-day and 180-day outcomes (e) Other safety endpoints including adverse gastrointestinal
      effects associated with nutritional therapy assessed daily until hospital discharge.

      The investigators will include unselected adult medical inpatients at risk of undernutrition
      [NRS≥3 points] and an expected hospital stay of ≥5 days who are willing to provide informed
      consent. The investigators will exclude patients in critical care or post-operative state,
      unable to swallow, at long-term need for parenteral/enteral nutrition, in terminal condition,
      pregnant, with acute pancreatitis or acute liver failure, with anorexia nervosa, that were
      earlier included into the trial Patients in the intervention group will receive
      individualized nutritional therapy to reach nutritional targets (caloric, protein,
      micronutrients, other) based on a predefined nutritional strategy. In control patients,
      according to patients` appetite, standard hospital nutrition will be served. Nutritional
      therapy may be started in control patients, if any sort of swallowing disorders develops or
      if patients need to be prepared for operation. All patients will be re-assessed daily during
      the hospital stay for nutritional intake and nutritional therapy may be escalated every 24-48
      hours (food fortification, oral supplements, enteral, parenteral nutrition) if targets are
      not met (at least 75% of targets).

      The targeted sample size is 2000 - 3000 patients. The inclusion of 2000 - 3000 patients will
      provide between 76% and 91% power to detect a reduction in the primary endpoint of 15% (from
      40% to 34%) assuming a lost to follow up rate of 10%.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 16, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>primary composite endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>measured at day 30 by telephone interview</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with adverse events including
All-cause mortality
Admission to the intensive care unit
Unplanned hospital readmission after hospital discharge
Major complications including nosocomial infection or abscess requiring antibiotic treatment, respiratory failure with need for invasive or non-invasive ventilation, major cardiovascular event or pulmonary embolism, acute renal failure (defined by 2x increase of baseline creatinine or new requirement of dialysis), gastro-intestinal hemorrhage or intestinal perforation assessed by medical chart review and telephone interview
decline in functional status of 10% or more from admission to day 30 measured by the Barthel`s index assessed by patient interview on admission and after 30 days</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight change</measure>
    <time_frame>measured at day 30 by telephone interview</time_frame>
    <description>change in weight and BMI from inclusion to day 30 by patient interview and medical chart review</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>lenght of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay with an expected average of 10 days</time_frame>
    <description>days in the hospital within index hospitalisation and within the 30 days of follow up measured by patient interview and medical chart review</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>measured at days 30 and 180 by telephone interview</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement in quality of life measured with the EuroQol Group 5-Dimension Self-Report Questionnaire on admission and during follow up measured by patient interview</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Combined safety endpoints in regard to side effects from nutritional therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>measured at day 30</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with side effects from nutritional therapy including
(a) adverse gastrointestinal effects (diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain) assessed by patient interview (yes/no) b) Complications due to tube feeding or center catheter for parenteral nutrition assessed by medical chart review (c) Refeeding syndrome assessed by chart review (d) Acute pancreatitis defined as 2 out of 3 criteria: abdominal pain, 3-fold increase in lipase or amylase, characteristic imaging findings assessed by chart review (e) Liver or gall bladder dysfunction assessed by chart review (f) Hyperglycemia (defined as glucose levels &gt;12mmol/l or persistent levels &gt;10mmol/l in patients without diabetes or well controlled diabetes) assessed by medical chart review</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>new decubital ulcer</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed on the day of hospital discharge after an expected average of 10 days</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical diagnosis of decubital ulcer with onset after study inclusion measured by patient interview and medical chart review</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Discharge location</measure>
    <time_frame>assessed on the day of hospital discharge after an expected average of 10 days</time_frame>
    <description>proportion discharge home or to a rehab facility measured by patient interview and medical chart review</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2088</enrollment>
  <condition>Malnutrition</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nutritional support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the purpose of this study, we have developed nutritional guidelines by consensus and adapted to current guidelines (e.g., ESPEN, ASPEN). These guidelines specify a reinforced nutritional therapy strategy to cover nutritional requirements, focusing on nutritional targets based on the specific nutritional diagnoses defined by the IDNT. The nutritional guidelines may vary according to important medical diagnoses (i.e. renal failure). They specify not only nutritional targets, but also escalation of the route (i.e. food fortification, oral, enteral, parenteral) if targets cannot be achieved (≤75%) every 5 hours. Nutritional goals are being assessed daily in patients in the intervention group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care (&quot;appetite-guided&quot;) controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In control patients, we will use conventional nutrition according to the ability and desire of the patient to eat, using standard care food provided by the hospital kitchen (&quot;appetite-guided&quot;).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nutritional therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Any nutritional product and route (i.e. food fortification, oral, enteral, parenteral) is possible to reach goals</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nutritional support</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  NRS ≥3 points

          -  expected hospital LOS ≥5 days (as estimated by the treating physician team)

          -  willingness to provide informed consent (see informed consent statement)

        Exclusion criteria

          -  initially admitted to critical care units (except intermediate care)

          -  scheduled for surgery or in an immediate post-operative state

          -  unable to ingest oral nutrition and thus need for enteral or parenteral nutrition

          -  admitted with, or scheduled for, total parenteral nutrition or tube feeding

          -  currently under nutritional therapy (defined by at least one visit with a dietician in
             the last month)

          -  who are hospitalized because of anorexia nervosa

          -  in terminal condition (end of life situation)

          -  hospitalized due to acute pancreatitis

          -  hospitalized due to acute liver failure

          -  earlier inclusion into this trial

          -  cystic fibrosis

          -  patients after gastric bypass operations

          -  stem cell transplantation

          -  any contraindication against nutritional therapy (i.e., enteral and/or parenteral)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philipp Schuetz, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Clinic, Kantonsspital Aarau</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Clinic, Kantonsspital Aarau</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarau</city>
        <state>AG</state>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schuetz P. &quot;Eat your lunch!&quot; - controversies in the nutrition of the acutely, non-critically ill medical inpatient. Swiss Med Wkly. 2015 Apr 23;145:w14132. doi: 10.4414/smw.2015.14132. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25906253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schütz P, Bally M, Stanga Z, Keller U. Loss of appetite in acutely ill medical inpatients: physiological response or therapeutic target? Swiss Med Wkly. 2014 Apr 29;144:w13957. doi: 10.4414/smw.2014.13957. eCollection 2014. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24782139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 30, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Philipp Schuetz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malnutrition</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

