<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02516358</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Gly 1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02516358</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Glycaemic Alterations in ICU</brief_title>
  <official_title>Glycaemic Alterations in ICU: an Observational, Prospective Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To quantify the local prevalence of diabetes mellitus in critically ill patients. To
      understand whether a correlation does exist between premorbid glycaemic control and glycaemic
      status in ICU. A subgroup analysis will be conducted to investigate whether a relationship
      does exist between Neuron Specific Enolase levels and glycaemic disorders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to determine the local prevalence of critical illness-associated
      hyperglycaemia (CIAH) and recognised and unrecognised diabetes, as well as to evaluate how
      premorbid glycaemia impacts the relationship between three glycaemic domains and mortality.

      The investigators will calculate the Time In Range (TIR, 70-180 mg/dl) and evaluate
      distribution of percentage time in range for non-diabetics and diabetics patients, in order
      to understand the association between TIR and survival in both groups of patients (patients
      with diabetes and patients without diabetes).

      In view of the potential adverse effects of hyperglycaemia, hypoglycaemia and glycaemic
      variability on the brain, the investigators will dose Neuron Specific Enolase in critically
      ill patients.

      The aim is to define if a biochemical correlation does exist between critically ill
      dysglycaemia and NSE plasma concentration.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in glycaemic blood levels during ICU stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Glycaemic values expressed as mean glycaemia will be collected at the baseline and every 8 hours for the duration of ICU stay, expected average of 10 days per patient.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Episodes of hypoglicaemia (number)</measure>
    <time_frame>For the duration of ICU stay, expected average of 10 days per patient.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Episodes of hyperglycaemia (number)</measure>
    <time_frame>For the duration of ICU stay, expected average of 10 days per patient.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coefficient of variation of blood glucose levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Time point A:24 hours. Time point B: 48 hours after ICU admission. Time point C: for the duration of ICU stay, an expected average of 10 days per patient.</time_frame>
    <description>Coefficient of Variation, calculated as a percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time in glycaemic Range (TIR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time point A:24 hours. Time point B: 48 hours after ICU admission. Time point C: for the duration of ICU stay, an expected average of 10 days per patient.</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated in hours TIR/ total hours in ICU; calculated as a percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days of mechanical ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of ICU stay, expected average per patient: 10 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days of continuous renal replacement therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of ICU stay, expected average per patient: 10 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuron Specific Enolase (NSE) blood levels and glycaemic disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>NSE collection: Time point A: ICU admission. Time point NSE: 48-72 hours after ICU admission</time_frame>
    <description>To detect a correlation between NSE levels and glycaemic alterations in both diabetic and non diabetic patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Critically ill patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ICU patients

          -  expected ICU length of stay &gt; 48 hours

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  age &lt;18 years

          -  ICU length of stay &lt;48 hours

          -  diabetic ketoacidosis

          -  hyperosmolar nonketonic hyperglycaemia syndrome

          -  pregnancy

          -  hypoglycaemic coma

          -  acute or acute on chronic liver failure, liver transplantation or end-stage liver
             disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Francesca Di Muzio</last_name>
    <phone>0467556315; 00393470333656</phone>
    <email>francescadimuzio@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cely CM, Arora P, Quartin AA, Kett DH, Schein RM. Relationship of baseline glucose homeostasis to hyperglycemia during medical critical illness. Chest. 2004 Sep;126(3):879-87.</citation>
    <PMID>15364770</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalfon P, Le Manach Y, Ichai C, Bréchot N, Cinotti R, Dequin PF, Riu-Poulenc B, Montravers P, Annane D, Dupont H, Sorine M, Riou B; CGAO-REA Study Group. Severe and multiple hypoglycemic episodes are associated with increased risk of death in ICU patients. Crit Care. 2015 Apr 8;19:153. doi: 10.1186/s13054-015-0851-7.</citation>
    <PMID>25888011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Egi M, Bellomo R, Stachowski E, French CJ, Hart GK, Hegarty C, Bailey M. Blood glucose concentration and outcome of critical illness: the impact of diabetes. Crit Care Med. 2008 Aug;36(8):2249-55. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0b013e318181039a.</citation>
    <PMID>18664780</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krinsley JS, Egi M, Kiss A, Devendra AN, Schuetz P, Maurer PM, Schultz MJ, van Hooijdonk RT, Kiyoshi M, Mackenzie IM, Annane D, Stow P, Nasraway SA, Holewinski S, Holzinger U, Preiser JC, Vincent JL, Bellomo R. Diabetic status and the relation of the three domains of glycemic control to mortality in critically ill patients: an international multicenter cohort study. Crit Care. 2013 Mar 1;17(2):R37. doi: 10.1186/cc12547.</citation>
    <PMID>23452622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plummer MP, Bellomo R, Cousins CE, Annink CE, Sundararajan K, Reddi BA, Raj JP, Chapman MJ, Horowitz M, Deane AM. Dysglycaemia in the critically ill and the interaction of chronic and acute glycaemia with mortality. Intensive Care Med. 2014 Jul;40(7):973-80. doi: 10.1007/s00134-014-3287-7. Epub 2014 Apr 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24760120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sulter G, Elting JW, De Keyser J. Increased serum neuron specific enolase concentrations in patients with hyperglycemic cortical ischemic stroke. Neurosci Lett. 1998 Aug 28;253(1):71-3.</citation>
    <PMID>9754808</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krinsley JS, Meyfroidt G, van den Berghe G, Egi M, Bellomo R. The impact of premorbid diabetic status on the relationship between the three domains of glycemic control and mortality in critically ill patients. Curr Opin Clin Nutr Metab Care. 2012 Mar;15(2):151-60. doi: 10.1097/MCO.0b013e32834f0009. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22234163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krinsley JS, Preiser JC. Time in blood glucose range 70 to 140 mg/dl &gt;80% is strongly associated with increased survival in non-diabetic critically ill adults. Crit Care. 2015 Apr 20;19:179. doi: 10.1186/s13054-015-0908-7.</citation>
    <PMID>25927986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kochanek PM, Berger RP, Bayir H, Wagner AK, Jenkins LW, Clark RS. Biomarkers of primary and evolving damage in traumatic and ischemic brain injury: diagnosis, prognosis, probing mechanisms, and therapeutic decision making. Curr Opin Crit Care. 2008 Apr;14(2):135-41. doi: 10.1097/MCC.0b013e3282f57564. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18388674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>NICE-SUGAR Study Investigators, Finfer S, Chittock DR, Su SY, Blair D, Foster D, Dhingra V, Bellomo R, Cook D, Dodek P, Henderson WR, Hébert PC, Heritier S, Heyland DK, McArthur C, McDonald E, Mitchell I, Myburgh JA, Norton R, Potter J, Robinson BG, Ronco JJ. Intensive versus conventional glucose control in critically ill patients. N Engl J Med. 2009 Mar 26;360(13):1283-97. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0810625. Epub 2009 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19318384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dungan KM, Braithwaite SS, Preiser JC. Stress hyperglycaemia. Lancet. 2009 May 23;373(9677):1798-807. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)60553-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19465235</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 3, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 31, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 31, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 1, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Francesca Di Muzio</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

