<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02513563</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-18304</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02513563</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AZD1775 Plus Carboplatin-Paclitaxel in Squamous Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of AZD1775 Plus Carboplatin-Paclitaxel in Squamous Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out what effects (good and bad) AZD1775 used in
      combination with carboplatin and paclitaxel will have on participants and their cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 8, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is measured from date of first study treatment to death, progression of disease, or the last follow-up data, whichever comes first. Progressive Disease (PD): At least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study (this includes the baseline sum if that is the smallest on study). In addition to the relative increase of 20%, the sum must also demonstrate an absolute increase of at least 5 mm. (Note: the appearance of one or more new lesions is also considered progression).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>OS is defined as the duration of time from the date for first treatment (Cycle 1 Day 1) to the date of death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Overall Response (OR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of overall response is measured from the time measurement criteria are met for Complete Response (CR) or Partial Response (PR) (whichever is first recorded) until the first date that recurrent or progressive disease is objectively documented (taking as reference for progressive disease the smallest measurements recorded since the treatment started). CR: Disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes (whether target or non-target) must have reduction in short axis to &lt;10 mm. PR: At least a 30% decrease in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum diameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Stable Disease (SD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Stable disease is measured from the start of the treatment until the criteria for progression are met, taking as reference the smallest measurements recorded since the treatment started, including the baseline measurements. Stable Disease (SD): Neither sufficient shrinkage to qualify for PR nor sufficient increase to qualify for PD, taking as reference the smallest sum diameters while on study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rates (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>DCR: Complete Response (CR), Partial Response (PR), and Stable Disease (SD).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carboplatin/Paclitaxel/AZD1775</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment: Combination of AZD1775 plus carboplatin and paclitaxel. Participants will be treated with this combination of drugs twice daily on days 1 and 2 and once on day 3 for a total of 5 doses during each 21 day cycle of treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be treated with carboplatin (area under the curve 5 (AUC5) will be used to determine the dosage) twice daily, days 1 and 2 and once a day on day 3 (5 doses) during each 21 day cycle of treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carboplatin/Paclitaxel/AZD1775</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Paraplatin®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be treated with paclitaxel 175 mg/m^2 twice daily, days 1 and 2 and once a day on day 3 (5 doses) during each 21 day cycle of treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carboplatin/Paclitaxel/AZD1775</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TAXOL®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AZD1775</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive AZD1775 225 mg twice daily, days 1 and 2 and once a day on day 3 (5 doses) during each 21 day cycle of treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carboplatin/Paclitaxel/AZD1775</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MK1775</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provision of informed consent prior to any study specific procedures

          -  Histologic or cytological diagnosis of Squamous Cell Lung Cancer (SQCLC) with
             advanced/metastatic stage, with no known curative treatment options. Prior
             platinum-containing adjuvant, neoadjuvant, or definitive chemoradiation therapy given
             for locally advanced disease is considered first line therapy only if recurrent (local
             or metastatic) disease developed within 6 months of completing therapy. Potential
             participants with recurrent disease &gt; 6 months will be eligible.

          -  Female or male aged &gt;/= 18 years

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0/1

          -  Prior chemotherapy in the adjuvant setting is allowed

          -  Prior radiotherapy is allowed

          -  Prior Immunotherapy with PD1i, PDL1i, anti-CTLA -4 or vaccines is allowed

          -  Must have normal organ and marrow function

          -  Have archival tissue available or undergo a fresh biopsy where clinically feasible
             after discussion with the sponsor

          -  Women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception prior
             to study entry and for the duration of study participation and women who are breast
             feeding are excluded from the study. Both women and men should be fully informed of
             the lack of reproductive toxicity testing, and women must have a negative pregnancy
             test prior to enrolment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Progressive, symptomatic untreated brain metastases

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding

          -  A serious uncontrolled medical disorder or active infection that in the investigator's
             opinion would impair the participant's ability to receive study treatment

          -  Prior use of platinum or paclitaxel for stage IV Non-small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) or
             concurrent use of other anticancer approved or investigational agents

          -  Known Hepatitis B or C or HIV infection

          -  Second primary malignancy, other than in situ malignancies or adequately treated basal
             cell carcinoma of the skin or other malignancy treated at least 2 years previously
             with no evidence of recurrence

          -  Have had prescription or non-prescription drugs or other products (i.e., grapefruit
             juice) known to be sensitive to CYP3A4 substrates or CYP3A4 substrates with a narrow
             therapeutic index, or to be moderate to strong inhibitors or inducers of CYP3A4, which
             cannot be discontinued 2 weeks before Day 1 of dosing and withheld throughout the
             study until 2 weeks after the last dose of study drug

          -  Co-administration of aprepitant and fosaprepitant during this study is prohibited

          -  AZD1775 is an inhibitor of breast cancer resistance protein (BCRP). The use of statins
             including Atorvastatin which are substrates for BCRP are therefore prohibited and
             patients should be moved on to non-BCRP alternatives.

          -  Herbal preparations are not allowed throughout the study. These herbal medications
             include, but are not limited to: St. John's wort, kava, ephedra (ma huang), gingko
             biloba, dehydroepiandrosterone (DHEA), yohimbe, saw palmetto, and ginseng.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jhanelle Gray, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Germaine Gonzalez-Vazquez</last_name>
      <phone>813-745-6636</phone>
      <email>germaine.gonzalezvazquez@moffitt.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jhanelle Gray, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>813-745-7282</phone>
      <email>jhanelle.gray@moffitt.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jhanelle Gray, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Scott Antonia, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alberto Chiappori, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ben Creelan, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eric Haura, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tawee Tanvetyanon, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles Williams, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Trevor Rose, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.moffitt.org/clinical-trials-research/</url>
    <description>Moffitt Cancer Center Clinical Trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 30, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 30, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 31, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Squamous cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

