<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02516553</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1367.1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-001111-12</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02516553</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BI 894999 First in Human Dose Finding Study in Advanced Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label, Phase Ia/Ib Dose Finding Study With BI 894999 Orally Administered Once a Day in Patients With Advanced Malignancies, With Repeated Administration in Patients With Clinical Benefit</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boehringer Ingelheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boehringer Ingelheim</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the phase Ia (dose escalation) part of this trial is to assess the Maximum
      Tolerated Dose (MTD) of BI 894999 administered at escalating doses in two treatment schedules
      (schedule A of continuous dosing, schedule B with two weeks on treatment followed by one week
      off in 3-week cycles) in patients with solid tumours. In the phase Ib expansion part, the aim
      is to further evaluate the safety profile of BI 894999 at the recommended dose and schedule
      in patients with solid tumours and to assess target modulation and the potential antitumour
      efficacy in patients with selected types of tumours. Once the MTD has been determined for
      both schedules in patients with solid tumours, the MTD will be determined as well in patients
      with diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL), using the recommended schedule for solid
      tumours.The PK profile will be determined from the first cycle in all patients in both
      phases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 8, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 19, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>In phase Ib: Number of patients experiencing DLTs from start of treatment until end of treatment (in all cycles) as assessed approximately every 3 weeks after Cycle 2 (at the end of each new cycle) in order to determine the recommended phase II dose</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>In phase Ia: Number of patients with DLT observed in the first cycle (first 21 days) to meet the objective of assessing MTD of BI 894999 for each schedule in solid tumour patients and in schedule A or B in the DLBCL cohort</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy endpoint in phases Ia and Ib: Objective response (OR), defined as CR or PR with tumour assessment during treatment period for each schedule</measure>
    <time_frame>every 6 weeks, average of 4 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy endpoint in phases Ia and Ib: Disease control defined as CR, partial response (PR) or stable disease (SD) by investigator's assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>every 6 weeks, average of 4 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy endpoint in phase Ib: Progression-free Survival (PFS) or radiological PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 5 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy endpoint in phase Ib: Best overall response with an evaluation of approximately every 2 cycles (6 weeks if no delays) during the entire treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>every 6 weeks, average of 4 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In both phases: Cmax(,ss) after single and multiple dose of BI 894999, as measured during the first cycle (3 weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In both phases: AUC0-24 after single and multiple dose of BI 894999, as measured during the first cycle (3 weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In both phases: AUC tau after single and multiple dose of BI 894999, as measured during the first cycle (3 weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase Ia:Number of patients experiencing DLTs from start of treatment until end of treatment (in all cycles) for each schedule in patients with solid tumours and in schedule A or B in the DLBCL cohort as assessed approximately every 3 weeks after Cycle 2</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In both phases: Cmax after single and multiple dose of BI 894999, as measured during the first cycle (3 weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy endpoint in phase Ib: Prostate Specific Antigen (PSA) response (decline in PSA value ≥50% from baseline) in patients with Metastatic Castration Resistant Prostate Cancer (mCRPC)</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">143</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>once daily continuous oral intake in 3-week cycles</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>arm B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>once daily intermittent oral intake with two weeks on treatment followed by one week off in 3-week cycles</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BI 894999</intervention_name>
    <description>day 1 to day 21 in 3-week cycles</description>
    <arm_group_label>arm A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BI 894999</intervention_name>
    <description>day 1 to day 14 followed by a week off in 3-week cycles in schedule B</description>
    <arm_group_label>arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        For all patients

          1. Age 18 years and older at the time of signature of the informed consent

          2. Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks after the start of the treatment according to the
             investigator's judgement

          3. Male or female patients. Women of childbearing potential* must be ready and able to
             use highly effective methods of birth control per ICH M3(R2) that result in a low
             failure rate of less than 1% per year when used consistently and correctly. A list of
             contraception methods meeting these criteria is provided in the patient information.
             For women of childbearing potential using a contraceptive pill, an additional barrier
             method is necessary due to the potential CYP3A4 inducing effect of BI894999. Male
             patients having a partner of childbearing potential must use condoms and ensure their
             partner is using a highly effective method of birth control as described above, during
             the trial and for at least three months after the end of the trial

             * Any female who has experienced menarche and does not meet the criteria for &quot;women
             not of childbearing potential&quot; as described below.

             Women not of childbearing potential are defined as: women who are postmenopausal (12
             months with no menses without an alternative medical cause) or who are permanently
             sterilized (e.g., tubal occlusion, hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy or bilateral
             salpingectomy).

          4. Written informed consent consistent with ICH-GCP and local legislation For patients
             with solid tumours

        1. Patients with a histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of an advanced
        unresectable and/or metastatic solid tumour, who have failed conventional treatment or for
        whom no therapy of proven efficacy exists, or who are not amenable to standard therapies 2.
        Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance score 0 or 1 at the time of screening 3.
        Recovery of therapy-related toxicities from previous chemotherapy, tyrosine kinase
        inhibitors, hormone therapy, immunotherapy, antibodies, vaccine therapy, or radiotherapy to
        CTCAE &lt; or =grade 1 (with the exception of alopecia, peripheral sensory neuropathy grade 2)
        4. Written informed consent for tumour biopsies in the escalation phase Ia

          1. optional for those patients until extension of the MTD cohort,

          2. or the patients in the extension of MTD cohort at the same time points as described
             below for the expansion phase. For these patients in the extension of the MTD cohort,
             if they have an accessible lesion for biopsy, they will be offered optional consent
             for tumour biopsies

             In addition, all patients included in the expansion phase (part Ib) must:

             5. have been diagnosed with one of the one to four types of tumours selected: SCLC,
             mCRPC, CRC or NMC 6. have a measurable disease (radiated lesions do not qualify as
             target lesions) according to RECIST 1.1 or according to PCWG3 for the mCRPC cohort 7.
             have progressive disease within the last 6 months, according to RECIST 1.1 according
             to PCWG3 for the mCRPC cohort 8. have a tumour lesion accessible for biopsies (pre-
             and at steady state under treatment in Cycle 1, ideally from the same anatomic lesion)
             (except for mCRPC patients having only bone metastases or NMC patients) 9. give
             written informed consent to tumour biopsies, one at screening and one after start of
             treatment, between Day 11 and Day 14 of Cycle 1 (when applicable) In patients with
             DLBCL

               1. Patients with histologically confirmed DLBCL who have failed or who are not
                  amenable to standard therapies but have an indication for therapy as per
                  investigator's judgement

               2. ECOG Performance Status 0, 1 or 2 at the time of screening

               3. Measurable disease (radiated lesions do not qualify as target lesions) according
                  to according to RECIL 2017 on the CT scan part of the FDG/PET-CT scan

               4. Recovery of therapy-related toxicities from previous anti-lymphoma therapy to
                  CTCAE &lt;= grade 1 (with the exception of alopecia, peripheral sensory neuropathy
                  grade 2)

               5. written informed consent for tumour biopsies (optional) Further inclusion
                  criteria apply

             Exclusion criteria:

             For all patients:

               1. Inability to swallow tablets

               2. Second malignancy currently requiring another anti-cancer therapy

               3. Serum creatinine greater than 1.5 mg/dL (&gt;132 µmol/L, SI unit equivalent)

               4. Women who are pregnant, nursing, or who plan to become pregnant while in the
                  trial

               5. Treatment with other investigational drugs or participation in another clinical
                  interventional trial within the past four weeks or within five times the
                  half-life of the previous investigational drug, whichever is shorter, before
                  start of therapy or concomitant with this trial

               6. Patients unable to comply with the protocol

               7. Patients who are actively abusing alcohol or drugs. Since no alcohol or drug
                  testing is required per protocol, it is at the investigator's discretion to
                  determine abuse.

             For patients with solid tumours:

               1. Additional other serious illness , concomitant non-oncological disease (e.g.
                  active infectious disease or known chronic Hepatitis B/Hepatitis C infection and
                  HIV), or ongoing toxicity from prior therapies considered by the investigator to
                  potentially compromise patient's safety in this trial

               2. History or presence of cardiovascular abnormalities deemed clinically relevant by
                  the investigator such as uncontrolled hypertension, congestive heart failure NYHA
                  classification of 3, unstable angina or poorly controlled arrhythmia. Myocardial
                  infarction within 6 months prior to study entry

               3. Clinical evidence of symptomatic progressive brain or leptomeningeal disease
                  during the last 28 days before the start of treatment with BI 894999

               4. Absolute neutrophil count less than 1500/mm3

               5. Platelet count less than 100 000/mm3

               6. Bilirubin greater than 1.5 mg/dL (&gt;26 µmol/L, SI unit equivalent) (except known
                  Gilbert's syndrome, accepted up to 2 mg/dL or up to 34.2 µmol/L in this case)

               7. Aspartate amino transferase (AST) and/or alanine amino transferase (ALT) greater
                  than 2.5 times the upper limit of normal (if related to liver metastases, greater
                  than five times the upper limit of normal)

               8. Systemic anti-cancer therapy within four weeks or five times the half-life of the
                  drug, whichever is shorter or other than palliative radiotherapy within the past
                  four weeks before start of therapy or concomitantly with this trial. This
                  restriction does not apply to Luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone (LHRH)
                  agonists or antagonists, steroids (given at a stable dose in the last four weeks)
                  used for palliative intent, bisphosphonates and denosumab

             For patients with DLBCL:

               1. Patient is eligible for curative salvage high dose therapy followed by stem cell
                  transplant.

               2. Primary central nervous system (CNS) lymphoma or known CNS involvement

               3. Prior allogeneic bone marrow or stem cell transplant

               4. High-dose therapy with stem cell support &lt;3 months prior to visit 1

               5. AST or ALT &gt;2.5 x upper limit of normal (CTCAE grade 2 or higher)

               6. Total bilirubin &gt;1.5 x upper limit of normal (CTCAE grade 2 or higher)

               7. Absolute neutrophil count &lt;1.0 x 10^9/L(without growth factor support)

               8. Platelets &lt;100 x 10^9/L (without transfusions)

               9. Significant concurrent medical disease or condition which according to the
                  investigator's judgement would either compromise patient safety or interfere with
                  the evaluation of the safety of the test drug, e.g. symptomatic congestive heart
                  failure, unstable angina pectoris, myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to
                  study entry, cardiac arrhythmia requiring therapy with the exception of extra
                  systoles or minor conduction abnormalities

              10. Chronic or ongoing infection requiring treatment at the time of enrolment or
                  within the previous two weeks, e.g. active infectious disease or known Hepatitis
                  B/Hepatitis C infection, HIV

              11. Systemic anti-DLBCL therapy within the past two weeks or five times the half-life
                  of the drug, whichever is shorter (palliative radiotherapy and agents used for
                  palliative reasons for example steroids (steroids must have been given at a
                  stable dose in the last four weeks) and bisphosphonates, are allowed) Further
                  exclusion criteria apply
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Boehringer Ingelheim</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Boehringer Ingelheim</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Boehringer Ingelheim Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-243-0127</phone>
    <email>clintriage.rdg@boehringer-ingelheim.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brussels - HOSP Jules Bordet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <zip>1000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brussels - UNIV St-Luc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>1200</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNIV UZ Gent</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UZ Leuven</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 27, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 6, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

