<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02517944</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14DRM_CHOLCOEUR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02517944</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MYOCARDIAL SILENT INFARCTIONS AND FIBROSIS IN FAMILIAL HYPERCHOLESTEROLEMIA (CHOLCOEUR)</brief_title>
  <acronym>CHOLCOEUR</acronym>
  <official_title>MYOCARDIAL SILENT INFARCTIONS AND FIBROSIS IN FAMILIAL HYPERCHOLESTEROLEMIA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institute of Cardiometabolism and Nutrition, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institute of Cardiometabolism and Nutrition, France</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with familial hypercholesterolemia (FH) at high cardiovascular risk may suffer from
      silent micro-infarctions (MI) before clinical coronary heart disease manifestations because
      of the lifetime exposure to elevated serum LDL-cholesterol levels.

      The study aims to demonstrate the higher prevalence of silent myocardial infarction in a
      population of asymptomatic patients with familial hypercholesterolemia at high cardiovascular
      risk in comparison to control patients using Cardiac Magnetic Resonance sequences of delayed
      gadolinium enhancement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To demonstrate the higher prevalence of silent myocardial infarction in a population of
      asymptomatic patients with familial hypercholesterolemia at high cardiovascular risk in
      comparison to control patients, the protocol is the following:

        -  to enroll 75 patients with familial hypercholesterolemia (FH)

        -  to enroll 35 subjects without FH (control group)

        -  for each subject, to collect data from his medical file (blood test results) and to
           perform a cardiac and aortic MRI in order to evaluate the micro-infarction proportion.

      The study will be performed according to GCPs and with respect with french laws.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>4 Weeks</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients presenting with at least one micro infarction at RMI</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 weeks after consent signature</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiac and aortic RMI with gadolinium</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LDL-Cholesterol burden (compared to standard values)</measure>
    <time_frame>The most recent value within the last 5 years.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anatomic and functional indexes of the aorta (maximal and minimal areas of aortic lumen, aortic flow)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 weeks after consent signature</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlations between LDL-Cholesterol burden &amp; presence of micro infarction, between LDL-Cholesterol burden &amp; myocardial fibrosis, and between LDL-Cholesterol burden &amp; aortic stiffness indexes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Familial Hypercholesterolemia - Heterozygous</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Familial hypercholesterolemia patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>clinical data
biological data
cardiac and aortic RMI with gadolinium</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <description>clinical data
biological data
cardiac and aortic RMI with gadolinium</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        110 subjects divided into:

          -  75 patients with heterozygous form at high cardiovascular risk

          -  35 controls patients without dyslipidaemia
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        For patients with heterozygous form of familial hypercholesterolemia:

          -  Aged between 40 and 60 years

          -  With an identified genetic mutation (LDL-R, ApoB, PCSK9)

          -  Asymptomatic,

          -  With no EKG sign of ischemia

          -  No personal history of coronary heart disease.

          -  Treated or untreated by lipid lowering treatment

          -  High cardiovascular risk identified by 1 of the following criteria:

             1. Current smoking (1 cigarette a day) 2 Family history of very premature onset CHD:
             first- or second-degree male relative onset before age 45, first- or second-degree
             female relative onset before age 55 3.Two or more cardiovascular risk factors among
             this list: increasing age (men &gt; 30, women &gt; 40 years of age), LDL-C &gt; 250 mg/dL, male
             sex, family history of premature onset CHD, first-degree male relative onset before
             age 55, first-degree female relative onset before age 65, metabolic syndrome, HDL-C &lt;
             40 mg/dL, hypertension (BP &gt; 140/or &gt; 90 mmHg or drug treatment), Lp (a) ≥ 50 mg/dL,
             tendon xanthoma

        For control subjects:

          -  Aged between 40 and 60 years

          -  With a normal lipid profile (LDL-C &lt; 1.6g/L HDL-C &gt; 0,45g/L and TG &lt; 4g/L) and
             untreated by any lipid lowering therapies

          -  Asymptomatic,

          -  With EKG showing normal sinus rhythm , no sign of ischemia nor Left Bundle Branch
             Block

          -  No personal history of coronary heart disease.

          -  Control subjects will be matched for age/gender/smoking status and blood pressure

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Non-affiliation to a healthcare system

          -  Consent refusal

          -  Contra-indication to MRI or to gadolinium injection.

          -  Claustrophobia, metallic devices, pacemaker, mechanical valve implanted before 1985,
             pregnancy, nursing

          -  Renal failure

          -  Technical contra-indication: patient diameter &gt; 70 cm weight &gt; 250 kg

          -  Personal history of cardiovascular disease and myocardial infarction

          -  Diabetes mellitus

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension

          -  TG &lt; 4 g/L

          -  Previous use of an Amgen product in the past 12 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Rosenbaum, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Study principal investigator</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aurélie RABIER</last_name>
    <email>a.rabier@ican-institute.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unité de prévention des maladies cardiovasculaires- Unité INSERM 939 Pôle Cardiologie/Métabolisme Groupe Hospitalier Pitié-Salpêtrière</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75013</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Rosenbaum, MD</last_name>
      <email>david.rosenbaum@psl.aphp.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Eric Bruckert, Pr</last_name>
      <email>eric.bruckert@psl.aphp.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hovingh GK, Davidson MH, Kastelein JJ, O'Connor AM. Diagnosis and treatment of familial hypercholesterolaemia. Eur Heart J. 2013 Apr;34(13):962-71. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/eht015. Epub 2013 Feb 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23416791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nemati MH, Astaneh B. Optimal management of familial hypercholesterolemia: treatment and management strategies. Vasc Health Risk Manag. 2010 Dec 3;6:1079-88. doi: 10.2147/VHRM.S8283. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21191428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Descamps OS, Gilbeau JP, Leysen X, Van Leuven F, Heller FR. Impact of genetic defects on atherosclerosis in patients suspected of familial hypercholesterolaemia. Eur J Clin Invest. 2001 Nov;31(11):958-65.</citation>
    <PMID>11737238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Austin MA, Hutter CM, Zimmern RL, Humphries SE. Familial hypercholesterolemia and coronary heart disease: a HuGE association review. Am J Epidemiol. 2004 Sep 1;160(5):421-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15321838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Risk of fatal coronary heart disease in familial hypercholesterolaemia. Scientific Steering Committee on behalf of the Simon Broome Register Group. BMJ. 1991 Oct 12;303(6807):893-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1933004</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kroon AA, Ajubi N, van Asten WN, Stalenhoef AF. The prevalence of peripheral vascular disease in familial hypercholesterolaemia. J Intern Med. 1995 Nov;238(5):451-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7595185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kolansky DM, Cuchel M, Clark BJ, Paridon S, McCrindle BW, Wiegers SE, Araujo L, Vohra Y, Defesche JC, Wilson JM, Rader DJ. Longitudinal evaluation and assessment of cardiovascular disease in patients with homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia. Am J Cardiol. 2008 Dec 1;102(11):1438-43. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2008.07.035. Epub 2008 Sep 11.</citation>
    <PMID>19026292</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benn M, Watts GF, Tybjaerg-Hansen A, Nordestgaard BG. Familial hypercholesterolemia in the danish general population: prevalence, coronary artery disease, and cholesterol-lowering medication. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2012 Nov;97(11):3956-64. doi: 10.1210/jc.2012-1563. Epub 2012 Aug 14. Erratum in: J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2014 Dec;99(12):4758-9.</citation>
    <PMID>22893714</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farnier M, Bruckert E. Severe familial hypercholesterolaemia: current and future management. Arch Cardiovasc Dis. 2012 Dec;105(12):656-65. doi: 10.1016/j.acvd.2012.05.011. Epub 2012 Oct 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23199621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vilahur G, Casani L, Juan-Babot O, Guerra JM, Badimon L. Infiltrated cardiac lipids impair myofibroblast-induced healing of the myocardial scar post-myocardial infarction. Atherosclerosis. 2012 Oct;224(2):368-76. doi: 10.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2012.07.003. Epub 2012 Jul 22.</citation>
    <PMID>22882904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaufmann PA, Gnecchi-Ruscone T, Schäfers KP, Lüscher TF, Camici PG. Low density lipoprotein cholesterol and coronary microvascular dysfunction in hypercholesterolemia. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2000 Jul;36(1):103-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10898420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dayanikli F, Grambow D, Muzik O, Mosca L, Rubenfire M, Schwaiger M. Early detection of abnormal coronary flow reserve in asymptomatic men at high risk for coronary artery disease using positron emission tomography. Circulation. 1994 Aug;90(2):808-17.</citation>
    <PMID>8044952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giulia Gagliardi M, Crea F, Polletta B, Bassano C, La Vigna G, Ballerini L, Ragonese P. Coronary microvascular endothelial dysfunction in transplanted children. Eur Heart J. 2001 Feb;22(3):254-60.</citation>
    <PMID>11161937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watts GF, Sullivan DR, Poplawski N, van Bockxmeer F, Hamilton-Craig I, Clifton PM, O'Brien R, Bishop W, George P, Barter PJ, Bates T, Burnett JR, Coakley J, Davidson P, Emery J, Martin A, Farid W, Freeman L, Geelhoed E, Juniper A, Kidd A, Kostner K, Krass I, Livingston M, Maxwell S, O'Leary P, Owaimrin A, Redgrave TG, Reid N, Southwell L, Suthers G, Tonkin A, Towler S, Trent R; Familial Hypercholesterolaemia Australasia Network Consensus Group (Australian Atherosclerosis Society). Familial hypercholesterolaemia: a model of care for Australasia. Atheroscler Suppl. 2011 Oct;12(2):221-63. doi: 10.1016/j.atherosclerosissup.2011.06.001. Epub 2011 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>21917530</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Backer G, Ambrosioni E, Borch-Johnsen K, Brotons C, Cifkova R, Dallongeville J, Ebrahim S, Faergeman O, Graham I, Mancia G, Cats VM, Orth-Gomér K, Perk J, Pyörälä K, Rodicio JL, Sans S, Sansoy V, Sechtem U, Silber S, Thomsen T, Wood D; European Society of Cardiology. American Heart Association. American College of Cardiology. European guidelines on cardiovascular disease prevention in clinical practice. Third Joint Task Force of European and other Societies on Cardiovascular Disease Prevention in Clinical Practice (constituted by representatives of eight societies and by invited experts). Atherosclerosis. 2004 Apr;173(2):381-91.</citation>
    <PMID>15195638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nordestgaard BG, Chapman MJ, Humphries SE, Ginsberg HN, Masana L, Descamps OS, Wiklund O, Hegele RA, Raal FJ, Defesche JC, Wiegman A, Santos RD, Watts GF, Parhofer KG, Hovingh GK, Kovanen PT, Boileau C, Averna M, Borén J, Bruckert E, Catapano AL, Kuivenhoven JA, Pajukanta P, Ray K, Stalenhoef AF, Stroes E, Taskinen MR, Tybjærg-Hansen A; European Atherosclerosis Society Consensus Panel. Familial hypercholesterolaemia is underdiagnosed and undertreated in the general population: guidance for clinicians to prevent coronary heart disease: consensus statement of the European Atherosclerosis Society. Eur Heart J. 2013 Dec;34(45):3478-90a. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/eht273. Epub 2013 Aug 15.</citation>
    <PMID>23956253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kwong RY, Sattar H, Wu H, Vorobiof G, Gandla V, Steel K, Siu S, Brown KA. Incidence and prognostic implication of unrecognized myocardial scar characterized by cardiac magnetic resonance in diabetic patients without clinical evidence of myocardial infarction. Circulation. 2008 Sep 2;118(10):1011-20. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.727826. Epub 2008 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>18725488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mewton N, Liu CY, Croisille P, Bluemke D, Lima JA. Assessment of myocardial fibrosis with cardiovascular magnetic resonance. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Feb 22;57(8):891-903. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2010.11.013. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21329834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Choi DS, Ha JW, Choi B, Yang WI, Choi EY, Rim SJ, Chung N. Extent of late gadolinium enhancement in cardiovascular magnetic resonance and its relation with left ventricular diastolic function in patients with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. Circ J. 2008 Sep;72(9):1449-53.</citation>
    <PMID>18724020</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin Y, Yang SG, Chen H, Zhang HQ, Wang CS. [The predictive value of DE-CMR in patients with severe chronic aortic regurgitation and extremely dilated left ventricular chamber]. Zhonghua Wai Ke Za Zhi. 2012 Dec;50(12):1087-90. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>23336485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuruvilla S, Adenaw N, Katwal AB, Lipinski MJ, Kramer CM, Salerno M. Late gadolinium enhancement on cardiac magnetic resonance predicts adverse cardiovascular outcomes in nonischemic cardiomyopathy: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Circ Cardiovasc Imaging. 2014 Mar;7(2):250-258. doi: 10.1161/CIRCIMAGING.113.001144. Epub 2013 Dec 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24363358</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lipinski MJ, McVey CM, Berger JS, Kramer CM, Salerno M. Prognostic value of stress cardiac magnetic resonance imaging in patients with known or suspected coronary artery disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Aug 27;62(9):826-38. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2013.03.080. Epub 2013 May 30.</citation>
    <PMID>23727209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mascherbauer J, Marzluf BA, Tufaro C, Pfaffenberger S, Graf A, Wexberg P, Panzenböck A, Jakowitsch J, Bangert C, Laimer D, Schreiber C, Karakus G, Hülsmann M, Pacher R, Lang IM, Maurer G, Bonderman D. Cardiac magnetic resonance postcontrast T1 time is associated with outcome in patients with heart failure and preserved ejection fraction. Circ Cardiovasc Imaging. 2013 Nov;6(6):1056-65. doi: 10.1161/CIRCIMAGING.113.000633. Epub 2013 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>24036385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dall'Armellina E, Ferreira VM, Kharbanda RK, Prendergast B, Piechnik SK, Robson MD, Jones M, Francis JM, Choudhury RP, Neubauer S. Diagnostic value of pre-contrast T1 mapping in acute and chronic myocardial infarction. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2013 Jun;6(6):739-42. doi: 10.1016/j.jcmg.2012.11.020.</citation>
    <PMID>23764100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu CY, Liu YC, Wu C, Armstrong A, Volpe GJ, van der Geest RJ, Liu Y, Hundley WG, Gomes AS, Liu S, Nacif M, Bluemke DA, Lima JAC. Evaluation of age-related interstitial myocardial fibrosis with cardiac magnetic resonance contrast-enhanced T1 mapping: MESA (Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis). J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Oct 1;62(14):1280-1287. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2013.05.078. Epub 2013 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>23871886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sacré K, Brihaye B, Hyafil F, Serfaty JM, Escoubet B, Zennaro MC, Lidove O, Laissy JP, Papo T. Asymptomatic myocardial ischemic disease in antiphospholipid syndrome: a controlled cardiac magnetic resonance imaging study. Arthritis Rheum. 2010 Jul;62(7):2093-100. doi: 10.1002/art.27488.</citation>
    <PMID>20506512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheng HM, Ye ZX, Chiou KR, Lin SJ, Charng MJ. Vascular stiffness in familial hypercholesterolaemia is associated with C-reactive protein and cholesterol burden. Eur J Clin Invest. 2007 Mar;37(3):197-206.</citation>
    <PMID>17359487</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt HH, Hill S, Makariou EV, Feuerstein IM, Dugi KA, Hoeg JM. Relation of cholesterol-year score to severity of calcific atherosclerosis and tissue deposition in homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia. Am J Cardiol. 1996 Mar 15;77(8):575-80.</citation>
    <PMID>8610605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 14, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Familial hypercholesterolemia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypercholesterolemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperlipoproteinemia Type II</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

