<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02519491</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20150116-01H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02519491</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Utility of a Smart Phone Application in Assessing Radial Artery Patency - the CAPITAL iRADIAL Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Utility of a Smart Phone Application in Assessing Radial Artery Patency - the CAPITAL iRADIAL Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Accessing the arteries of the heart through the blood vessels of the wrist is becoming
      increasingly popular. By obtaining access via the artery in the arm as opposed to the groin,
      there is less risk of complications and improved patient satisfaction. However, using the
      wrist can cause blockage of the artery after the procedure. If there is too little blood flow
      from a second artery that supplies the hand, this could result in significant injury.
      Therefore, it is important to test these blood vessels in the wrist prior to having this
      procedure. The best way to evaluate these arteries involves the use of ultrasounds but this
      takes a long time and is expensive. Therefore, the artery is usually evaluated with a
      clinical test known as the modified Allen's test, which relies on the doctor watching the
      flushing of the hand during compression of the artery. Currently smart phones with cameras
      are able to assess blood flow by passing light through the skin and watching differences in
      brightness. This may be a better way to assess the arteries in the hand as it is less
      subjective than simply watching the flushing of the hand. This study aims to assess the
      ability of an iPhone application in determining whether there is sufficient blood flow
      through the arteries of the wrist and comparing it to the clinical test commonly used.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Over the past decade, the transradial approach to cardiac catheterization has emerged as the
      preferred method of angiography and intervention. There have been several observational and
      randomized controlled trials which have shown an association between transradial access and
      reduced risk of bleeding and other vascular complications, increased cost-effectiveness,
      improved patient satisfaction, and a mortality benefit in high-risk patient populations.
      However, this technique does carry risks of complications including radial artery occlusion,
      non-occlusive radial artery injury, radial artery spasm, hand ischemia, pseudoaneurysm,
      radial artery perforation, nerve damage, arteriovenous fistulisation, and bleeding. Radial
      artery occlusion is the most commonly noted complication and the clinical impact is unclear.
      In individuals with intact collateral palmar circulation from the ulnar artery, the
      individual is usually asymptomatic and do not require further intervention. However, if an
      individual lacks adequate collateral circulation, that individual is at risk of hand ischemia
      and loss of tissue or function necessitating surgical intervention or, ultimately,
      amputation. Thus, it is common practice to assess competency of the collateral palmar
      circulation prior to transradial cardiac catheterization to mitigate the risks associated
      with this approach.

      The gold standard for assessment of radial artery patency is colour Doppler ultrasound
      imaging of the artery. This gold standard allows for direct, objective assessment of arterial
      patency and competency through direct visualization of blood flow. The use of pre-procedural
      ultrasound remains both labour and resource intensive and hence is not feasible for practical
      use, therefore a physician must rely on clinical assessment of collateral circulation. This
      has been traditionally evaluated through use of the modified Allen's test (MAT), a technique
      performed at the bedside as part of the pre-procedural physical examination. More recently,
      the introduction of plethysmography and pulse oximetry have been utilized to theoretically
      provide a more objective measure of assessing collateral circulation, though these too are
      limited by the available resources. Given the ever increasing prevalence of smart phones,
      this study aims to address the utility and feasibility of an iPhone application in
      determining adequacy of collateral palmar circulation. Should this iPhone application provide
      superior diagnostic accuracy, it could quickly become an alternative method of providing an
      objective measure of collateral palmar circulation rather than relying on the subjective MAT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Diagnostic accuracy of the iRADIAL iPhone application in assessing competency of the collateral blood supply to the hand by comparing the results of the iPhone application to the gold standard (i.e. Doppler ultrasound)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">438</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Modified Allen's Test</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Modified Allen's Test to assess radial and ulnar patency.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iphone assessment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>iPhone assessment of radial and ulnar patency.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Modified Allen Test</intervention_name>
    <description>The Modified Allen's Test (MAT) will be performed in a well-lit room on both of the participant's hands. This technique will involve compression of both the radial and ulnar arteries by the investigator to assess patency of the contralateral artery. The participant will then be asked to clench and open their hand several times. The participant will then be asked to maintain their hand in an open position. The investigator will then release the compression over the ulnar artery and observe for palmar blush. The length of time to achieve maximal palmar blush will be recorded. This technique will then be repeated by maintaining compression over the ulnar artery and releasing of the compression over the radial artery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Modified Allen's Test</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Iphone artery assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>The iRADIAL iPhone app (Heart Rate, Azumio software) will be used to assess radial and ulnar artery patency. Briefly, the iPhone camera will be placed over the participant's thumb and patency assessed before and immediately following isolated contralateral artery compression for a maximum of two minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iphone assessment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All persons who are patients at the University of Ottawa Heart Institute and are
             candidates for coronary angiography.

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Benjamin Hibbert, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y4W7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 6, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 30, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

