<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02510248</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AL-704-701</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02510248</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>First in Human Study of AL-704; Single Dose, Food Effect in Healthy Volunteers; Multiple Doses in Chronic Hepatitis C</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, First-in-human, 3-part Study of Orally Administered JNJ-54257099 to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of Single Ascending Doses (Part 1) and Food-effect (Part 2) in Healthy Subjects, and Multiple Doses in Subjects With Chronic Hepatitis C Infection (Part 3)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alios Biopharma Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Janssen Pharmaceutica</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alios Biopharma Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, first-in-human, 3-part study
      in which the safety, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics of orally administered AL-704 will be
      assessed in healthy adult subjects and in adult subjects with CHC infection.

      Part 1: Healthy adult subjects will receive one of 5 single ascending oral doses (SAD) of
      AL-704 ranging from 100 mg to 1,500 mg (Cohorts 1 to 5). Within each cohort subjects will be
      randomized to receive either AL-704 or placebo (n=8 per cohort; 6 assigned to AL-704 and 2
      assigned to placebo), in a fasted state.

      The planned dose-escalation scheme may be changed based on the emerging PK and safety data.
      Two additional cohorts (Cohorts 6 and 7) may be enrolled for evaluation of additional doses
      at the discretion of the Sponsor and Investigator, based on the emerging pharmacokinetic (PK)
      profile, and the presence of an acceptable safety profile.

      Part 2: To assess the food effect on pharmacokinetics, 8 healthy subjects from one full Part
      1 cohort who received a single dose of AL-704 or placebo in a fasted state, will receive the
      same single dose of AL-704 or placebo in a fed state in Part 2 after a washout period of 7-14
      days (depending on PK results). It is expected that Cohort 3 of Part 1 (600 mg dose) will be
      selected, however this depends on the evaluation of available PK and safety data from Part 1
      of the study.

      Part 3: The following cohorts of 10 adult subjects each, with CHC infection, will be
      evaluated. Subjects with CHC genotype 1 infection (Cohorts 8 to 10) and subjects with CHC
      genotype 3 infection (Cohort 11) will be randomized to receive AL-704 or placebo for 7
      consecutive days (n=10 per cohort, 8 assigned to AL-704 and 2 assigned to placebo) in a fed
      state. The treatment is anticipated to be administered in a once daily dose regimen or a
      twice daily dose regimen. The dose and dose regimen to be administered will be determined by
      the Sponsor depending on the PK and safety outcomes of previous cohorts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 31, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 24, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 24, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Data assessed by Number and frequency of treatment emergent adverse events, physical examination findings</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening to last visit (up to 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>abnormal vital signs, 12 lead ECG and abnormal clinical laboratory results examination findings, vital signs, ECG and clinical lab results</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Single dose PK Profile from Cmax, tmax, t1/2, CL/F and Vz/F, AUC0-inf or AUClast</measure>
    <time_frame>From dosing to Day 8 visit for each SAD/FE cohort</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Multiple dose PK: profile from Cmax, tmax, t1/2, AUClast and AUC0 tau</measure>
    <time_frame>From dosing to final study visit (21 days) for each cohort</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hepatitis C virus levels</measure>
    <time_frame>From screening to final study visit (21 days) for each cohort</time_frame>
    <description>HCV RNA viral load change from baseline to final study visit in subjects with Chronic hepatitis C infection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Hepatitits C</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Drug</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Study drug will be AL-704 once or twice daily for up to 7 days in dosages ranging from 100 mg to 1500 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo to match study drug dosing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AL-704</intervention_name>
    <description>JNJ-54257099 (also known as ALS-022704 or AL-704) is a hepatitis C virus (HCV) nonstructural (NS)5B inhibitor, belonging to the nucleoside / nucleotide inhibitor class, and is being developed as an orally administered anti-HCV therapeutic.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Drug</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>JNJ-54257099</other_name>
    <other_name>ALS-022704</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo to match AL-704</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject must be a man or woman 18 to 60 years of age, inclusive for healthy subjects,
             or 18 to 65 years of age, inclusive for subjects with CHC infection.

          -  Each subject must sign an ICF indicating that he or she understands the purpose of and
             procedures required for the study and are willing to participate in the study before
             starting any screening activities.

          -  Subject must be willing and able to adhere to the prohibitions and restrictions

          -  Subject included in Part 1 and 2 of the study, must be non-smokers for at least 3
             months prior to screening.

          -  Subject included in Part 1 and 2 of the study, must be healthy on the basis of a
             medical evaluation that reveals the absence of any clinically relevant abnormality and
             includes a physical examination, medical history, vital signs, and the results of
             biochemistry, and hematology tests and a urinalysis performed at screening and
             admission. If there are abnormalities, the subject may be included only if the
             Investigator judges the abnormalities or deviations from normal to be not clinically
             significant. This determination must be recorded in the subject's source documents and
             initialed by the Investigator.

          -  Subject with CHC infection included in Part 3 of the study, must be otherwise healthy
             on the basis of a medical evaluation that reveals the absence of any clinically
             relevant abnormality other than those related to CHC infection, and includes a
             physical examination, medical history, vital signs, and the results of blood
             biochemistry, blood coagulation and hematology tests and a urinalysis performed at
             screening and admission. If there are abnormalities, the subject may be included only
             if the Investigator judges the abnormalities or deviations from normal to be not
             clinically significant or to be appropriate and reasonable for the population under
             study. This determination must be recorded in the subject's source documents and
             initialed by the Investigator and the Sponsor.

          -  Subject included in Part 1 and 2 of the study, must have a body mass index (BMI) of
             18.0 to 32.0 kg/m2, extremes included. Subjects with CHC infection included in Part 3
             of the study must have a BMI of 18.0 to 35.0 kg/m2, extremes included, with a minimum
             weight of 50 kg in both populations. No more than 25% of patients in any cohort may be
             enrolled with a BMI ≥30 kg/m2.

          -  Female subject must be of non-childbearing potential.

          -  Female subject, except if postmenopausal, should have a negative serum pregnancy test
             at screening and a negative urine pregnancy test at admission.

          -  Subject must agree to comply with contraceptive measures .

          -  Subject must have a normal 12-lead ECG (based on the mean value of the triplicate
             parameters at admission)

          -  Additional inclusion criteria for CHC-infected subjects in Part 3 of the study:

          -  Documentation of HCV infection for longer than 6 months and determination of genotype
             1 or 3 HCV infection at screening. In case of discrepancy between previously
             documented geno- or subtype and the geno- or subtype determined at screening, the
             eligibility results will be used to determine eligibility.

          -  HCV RNA viral load ≥105 IU/mL using a sensitive quantitative assay

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has a history or current clinically significant medical illness (except for

          -  CHC infection in subjects in Part 3 of the study) that, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, might confound the results of the study or pose an additional risk in
             administering study drug to the subject or that could prevent, limit, or confound the
             protocol-specified assessments. This may include but is not limited to renal
             dysfunction (calculated creatinine clearance below 60 mL/min at screening),
             significant cardiac, vascular, pulmonary, gastrointestinal (such as significant
             diarrhea, gastric stasis, or constipation that in the Investigator's opinion could
             influence drug absorption or bioavailability), endocrine, neurologic, hematologic,
             rheumatologic, psychiatric, neoplastic, or metabolic disturbances.

          -  Subject has a positive human immunodeficiency virus type 1 or 2 (HIV-1 or HIV-2) test
             at screening.

          -  Subject has hepatitis A infection (confirmed by hepatitis A antibody immunoglobulin M
             [IgM]), or hepatitis B virus infection (confirmed by hepatitis B surface antigen
             [HBsAg]) at screening. Subject has current hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection
             (confirmed by HCV

          -  antibody) at screening, only applicable in Part 1 and 2 of the study.

          -  Subject has received an investigational agent (small molecule) or vaccine within 30
             days, or having received a biological product within 3 months or 5 elimination
             half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the planned intake of study drug.

          -  Subject has a past history of heart arrhythmias (extrasystole, tachycardia at rest) or
             of risk factors for Torsade de Pointes syndrome (eg, hypokalemia, family history of
             long QT Syndrome).

          -  Subject has donated or lost more than 1 unit of blood (500 mL) within 60 days or more
             than one unit of plasma within 7 days prior to the first intake of study drug.

          -  Subject has evidence of active infection (other than CHC infection for subjects
             enrolled in Part 3).

          -  Subject has a positive urine drug test at study screening or admission.

          -  Additional exclusion criteria for CHC-infected subjects in Part 3 of the study:

          -  Subject with HCV RNA &lt;105 IU/mL.

          -  Subject has a history of clinical hepatic decompensation, eg, variceal bleeding,
             spontaneous bacterial peritonitis, ascites, hepatic encephalopathy or active jaundice.

          -  Subject has had a liver biopsy within 2 years or Fibroscan evaluation within 6 months
             prior to randomization that demonstrates cirrhosis (Knodell score &gt;3, Metavir score
             &gt;3, Ishak score &gt;4). Fibroscan liver stiffness score &gt;12.5 kPa.

          -  Subject has received prior treatment for CHC.

          -  Subject has ultrasound evidence consistent with or suspicious for hepatocellular
             carcinoma.

          -  Subject has alpha fetoprotein (AFP) &gt;50 ng/mL, unless the absence of a hepatic mass or
             lesion is demonstrated by ultrasound within the screening period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Biotrial</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rennes</city>
        <state>Brittany</state>
        <zip>355042</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arensia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tbilisi</city>
        <country>Georgia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arensia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chisinau</city>
        <country>Moldova, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Georgia</country>
    <country>Moldova, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 2, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 27, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 29, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

