<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00712660</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ITA-04-2008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00712660</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study With Information Technology (IT) - Aided Preventive Program in Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>ITAREPS Trial: A Prospective Randomized Double-blind Controlled Study in IT-aided Mobile Phone-based Relapse Prevention Program in Schizophrenia.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Prague Psychiatric Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Prague Psychiatric Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Information Technology-aided Program of Relapse Prevention in Schizophrenia (ITAREPS) will
      decrease the number of hospitalizations in patients with schizophrenia or schizoaffective
      disorder who are treated in the outpatient psychiatric setting, as evidenced by the reduction
      of the total number of hospitalizations due to relapse of psychosis at the end of the
      12-months follow-up period in the active ITAREPS group compared to the control
      (treatment-as-usual) group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Title of Study:

      ITAREPS Trial: A Prospective Randomized Double-blind Controlled Study in IT-aided Mobile
      Phone-based Relapse Prevention Program in Schizophrenia.

      Estimated Number of Study Centers and Countries:

      30-40 outpatient psychiatrists in the Czech Republic and in the Slovak Republic.

      Research Hypothesis:

      Information Technology-aided Program of Relapse Prevention in Schizophrenia (ITAREPS) will
      decrease the number of hospitalizations in patients with schizophrenia or schizoaffective
      disorder who are treated in the outpatient psychiatric setting, as evidenced by the reduction
      of the total number of hospitalizations due to relapse of psychosis at the end of the
      12-months follow-up period in the active ITAREPS group compared to the control
      (treatment-as-usual) group.

      Study Phase:

      Non Drug Interventional Study

      Study Objective:

      To evaluate effectiveness of the ITAREPS program in reduction of the number of
      hospitalizations due to relapse of psychosis. The ITAREPS program employs mobile phone
      communication between the psychiatrist and the patient. Subjects enrolled in the project
      (patient and his/her family member) are instructed to complete two separate versions of the
      10-item Early Warning Signs Questionnaire (EWSQ) upon a weekly SMS request sent automatically
      by the system. EWSQ detects proportional worsening (or a new onset) of psychotic symptoms
      compared to the last week's score of the completed questionnaire. Individual EWSQ scores are
      sent by the subjects back to the ITAREPS system as a SMS text message. If the EWSQ score
      exceeds given score thresholds, an immediate ALERT requesting a therapeutic intervention is
      announced to the investigator as an e-mail message and a timely pharmacological intervention
      is triggered in accordance with the Early Intervention Algorithm (EIA).

      Study design:

      This is an international, randomized, double-blind, controlled, design-blinded, non drug,
      interventional study. Subjects (patient and family member pairs) will be randomized at a 1:1
      ratio into the interventional or control group. All subjects will complete the EWSQ on a
      weekly basis. In the interventional group, e-mail alert message feedback to the investigator
      will be active and the investigator will react by using the EIA. In the control
      (treatment-as-usual) group, alerts will not be generated and the investigator will detect and
      react on the potential signs of the psychotic relapse only by using the standard clinical
      approach. The ALERTs will be reported to the investigators in approximately 50% of all ALERT
      events but the investigators and subjects will be kept blinded about the real study design -
      parallel or (multiple) cross-over. The type of the study design is specified only in section
      3.1.1. of the protocol. This section will not be available to the investigators and will be
      provided only for the purpose of the regulatory and ethics review.

      Study duration: 12 months

      Number of subjects:

      150 enrolled patient/family member pairs (i.e. 300 subjects) resulting in expected 120
      evaluable patient/family member pairs (i.e. 240 subjects) will be participating in the study.

      Study population:

      Male and female patients between 18 to 60 having ICD-10 diagnosis of schizophrenia or
      schizoaffective disorder and their healthy family members, both eligible for mobile phone
      communicating.

      Statistical Methods:

      The primary effectiveness analysis will be a comparison of the upper bound of 95% confidence
      interval (CI) for the mean number of hospitalizations in patients in the active ITAREPS group
      at month 12 compared to the control (treatment-as-usual) group. Rehospitalization risk will
      be analyzed using Kaplan-Meier survival analysis in both groups. An interim analysis
      evaluating the between group differences in the number of psychiatric hospitalization days
      will be performed after all enrolled patients have completed their Visit 2 (month 6).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The reduction of the number of hospitalizations for psychotic relapses in patients diagnosed with schizophrenia and schizoaffective disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>November 2008-November 2009</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EWSQ 10P and 10FM sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value</measure>
    <time_frame>November 2008-November 2009</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>No. of hospitalization days</measure>
    <time_frame>November 2008-November 2009</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the natural course of the psychotic illness</measure>
    <time_frame>November 2008-November 2009</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between baseline CGI and the No. of hospitalizations at the endpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>November 2008-November 2009</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">146</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the active-ITAREPS group, the e-mail ALERT message feedback to the investigator will be activated. The core study intervention was 20% antipsychotic dose increase within 24 hours in response to a Pharmacological Intervention Requiring Event (PIRE) defined as either: A) the receipt of any INITIAL ALERT (IA) e-mail. A dose increase was obligatory in such cases regardless of the current clinical status of the patient; or B) the receipt of an ALERT EMERGENCY (AE) e-mail after which the investigator confirmed clinical worsening via phone contact with the patient. AE is defined as further worsening in EWSQ scores during 3 week period after announcement of IA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TAU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the treatment-as-usual study arm (control, non-active ITAREPS), the e-mail ALERT message feedback will not be activated. In this group, even in the presence of early warning sings, the investigators will be kept blinded to the EWSQ scores, will receive no ALERT message and thus no early pharmacologic intervention based on the ITAREPS program will be prompted. Treatment in the control group will consist of routine clinical and medication management with the frequency of visits common in the outpatient clinical settings. There will be no intevention based on ITAREPS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>antipsychotic dose increase</intervention_name>
    <description>20% increase in the dose of current antipsychotic medication</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>All antipsychotics approved for clinical use in Czech and Slovak Republic:</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>no intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment as usual</description>
    <arm_group_label>TAU</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Treatment as usual</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Men and women, ages 18 to 60 years, inclusive. Earliest inclusion day is the 18th
             birthday and the latest is the day before the 61st birthday.

          2. A diagnosis of schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder according to ICD-10
             classification.

          3. Increased risk for relapse, defined as having at least 1 psychiatric hospitalization
             for psychosis within the past 3 years and at least 2 psychiatric hospitalizations for
             psychosis in total (i.e. ≥ 2 hospitalizations).

          4. Clinical Global Impression scale - Severity (CGI-S) ≤ 3 at study Visit 1.

          5. All patients must be on stable doses of antipsychotic medication during the study
             entry.

          6. Absence of organic mental disorder, mental disorder due to psychoactive substance use
             or mental retardation.

          7. Presence of a cooperating family member, caregiver or other person who is in frequent
             contact with the patient (at least 4 times a week) and who is willing to participate
             in the trial.

          8. Signed written informed consent. The informed consent process must be documented by
             signing the informed consent form prior to any study-related procedures.

          9. Eligibility for mobile phone communicating.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participation in another relapse prevention program or another interventional clinical
             trial will be prohibited during the entire participation in the study. Subjects
             enrolled in observational (non-interventional) trials are not excluded from this
             study.

          2. Hayward compliance rating scale score &lt; 2 at Visit 1.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Filip Spaniel, M.D., PhD.,</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Prague Psychiatrc Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prague Psychiatric Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prague</city>
        <state>Ustavni</state>
        <zip>181 03</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.itareps.com</url>
    <description>itareps web page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spaniel F, Vohlídka P, Hrdlicka J, Kozený J, Novák T, Motlová L, Cermák J, Bednarík J, Novák D, Höschl C. ITAREPS: information technology aided relapse prevention programme in schizophrenia. Schizophr Res. 2008 Jan;98(1-3):312-7. Epub 2007 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>17920245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 10, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 31, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 31, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 2, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Prague Psychiatric Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Filip Spaniel, M.D., Ph.D</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>relapse</keyword>
  <keyword>schizophrenia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antipsychotic Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

