<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00715169</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MLN1202</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00715169</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Trial of MLN1202 on C-Reactive Protein Levels in Patients With Risk Factors for Cardiovascular Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 2 A, Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Trial Measuring the Effects of MLN1202 on C-Reactive Protein Levels in Patients With Risk Factors for Cardiovascular Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase 2a trial evaluating the
      potential of MLN1202 to reduce circulating levels of C-reactive protein (CRP)in patients with
      risk factors for Atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease (ASCVD). Patients with risk factors
      for ASCVD will be screened for inclusion and exclusion criteria including assessment of
      C-reactive protein. If the patient's CRP is greater than 3.0 mg/L on repeated measurements at
      least 2 weeks apart, the patient will be enrolled, stratified by screening CRP levels (≤5.0
      mg/L and &gt;5.0 mg/L), and randomized to receive 1 dose of either placebo or MLN1202. Safety
      will be assessed by vital signs, physical examination, clinical laboratories at baseline, and
      adverse event (AE) reporting from Day 1 to Day 113 of the trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2005</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the effect of C-C Chemokine Receptor-2 (CCR2) blockade in reducing Creactive protein (CRP) levels in patients with risk factors for atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease (ASCVD) and a baseline elevation of CRP</measure>
    <time_frame>The change from baseline to Day 57 in CRP between patients treated withplacebo compared with MLN1202</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Elevation of Creactive protein (CRP) number of days from baseline until the first 1.0 mg/L decrease in CRP levels and changes from baseline to other study visits.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 1 to Day 113 of the trial.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">108</enrollment>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MLN1202</intervention_name>
    <description>10 mg/kg dose of MLN1202 administered via IV infusion administered approximately 30 minutes to an hour</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo consist of 0.9% saline solution administered as a 10 mg/kg dose via IV infusion administered approximately 30 minutes to an hour</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female age 35 years or older

          -  Willing and able to comply with the protocol for the duration of the study

          -  Willing to use adequate double-barrier contraceptive methods for the duration of the
             study

          -  Presence of 2 or more of the following risk factors for ASCVD:

        Age of 45 years (male) or 55 years (female) or greater History of or current cigarette
        smoking of ≥20 pack years History of hypertension Body mass index (BMI) defined as weight
        (kg) divided by height (in m2) ≥30 History of hypercholesterolemia defined as fasting
        low-density lipoprotein &gt;130 mg/dL History of high-density lipoprotein levels of 40 mg/dL
        or less Diabetes mellitus Family history of a definable ASCVD event (myocardial infarction
        or intervention)in a first-degree relative prior to the age of 55 (male) or 65 (female)

          -  Patients with hypercholesterolemia may be on stable doses of lipid-lowering agents
             with no change in regimen/dose within 60 days prior to randomization

          -  Have high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (from peripheral blood) levels &gt;3.0 mg/L on
             more than 1 test date separated by at least 2 weeks in the last 12 months; the most
             recent hsCRP must be measured during Screening within 14 days of randomization

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of stroke History of acute coronary syndrome (ACS) including unstable angina,
             acute myocardial infarction (both ST segment elevation and non-ST segment elevation)
             or stable angina

          -  Evidence of coronary artery disease as determined by either prior history of
             CAD-related event (stable angina, unstable angina, MI) or evidence on diagnostic
             procedure (exercise stress test, echocardiogram, stress test, radionucleotide stress
             test, others) that in the opinion of the investigator is consistent with CAD

          -  Diagnosis of congestive heart failure or clinical evidence suggesting CHF including
             history of orthopnea, exertional dyspnea, pedal edema, pulmonary rales,
             hepatosplenomegaly, cardiomegaly, and a prediastolic (S3) gallop

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension with a blood pressure &gt;140/90 at Screening

          -  Concurrent chronic inflammatory illness (eg, inflammatory bowel disease, rheumatoid
             arthritis, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, asthma, systemic lupus
             erythematosus) or concurrent chronic infectious illness (eg, human immunodeficiency
             virus, tuberculosis, hepatitis, osteomyelitis)

          -  Concurrent use of anti-inflammatory or disease-modifying agents (eg,
             methotrexate,azathioprine, oral corticosteroids). Past use (&gt;3 months) of these
             anti-inflammatory ordisease modifying agents is acceptable. Aspirin, clopidogrel, and
             nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs are acceptable

          -  History of cancer with the exception of cervical carcinoma-in-situ or basal cell
             carcinoma of the skin within the last 5 years

          -  History of receiving live attenuated vaccine within last 60 days prior to
             randomization

          -  Use of an investigational product in the last 60 days prior to randomization

          -  History of illicit drug use or alcohol abuse in the last year

          -  History of or planned percutaneous coronary intervention, such as angioplasty or
             coronary stent placement, or coronary artery bypass graft or other vascular surgery
             planned within study duration

          -  Chest X-ray within 6 months prior to study entry with clinically significant findings,
             in the opinion of the investigator Screening electrocardiogram obtained once during
             Screening Days -14 to -1 with clinically significant findings, in the opinion of the
             investigator

          -  Renal function reflected by a serum creatinine ≥1.5 times the upper limit of normal

          -  Hepatic function reflected by elevated liver function tests (eg, aspartate
             aminotransferase, alanine aminotransferase or total bilirubin) ≥2 times the ULN

          -  If female, positive results on a serum pregnancy test or breastfeeding

          -  Any other reason in the opinion of the investigator that a subject should not be
             enrolled in this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>July 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 11, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 14, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Clinical Research Monitor</name_title>
    <organization>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

