<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00712270</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>05-009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00712270</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Best Event Schizophrenia Trial--A Randomized Double-Blind Trial of Aripiprazole and Risperidone in Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <acronym>BEST</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Double-blind Trial of Aripiprazole and Risperidone in Schizophrenia: An Evaluation of Neuroimaging, Neuropsychological, and Pharmacogenomic Markers of Differential Treatment Response</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kettering Health Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kettering Health Network</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being conducted to find a way to predict how individual schizophrenic patients
      will respond if they are treated with different types of antipsychotic drugs. This could help
      doctors prescribe the medication that will work best for each individual.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the proposed research project is to identify a practical method of
      predicting differential antipsychotic drug treatment response in patients with schizophrenia.
      In particular, we will examine differential response to two antipsychotic drugs, aripiprazole
      and risperidone, that have contrasting pharmacologic activity at D2-type dopamine receptors,
      i.e., partial agonism vs. antagonism, respectively. A number of candidate predictors will be
      examined, including neuroimaging parameters (regional neuroanatomical and metabolic
      variations, fallypride binding to D2-like receptors), neuropsychological testing, clinical
      features, laboratory measures, and genetic studies.

      Secondary objectives include: (1) extension of our previous efforts to characterize
      abnormalities in cortico-striato-thalamic circuits in unmedicated schizophrenics using PET
      and MR imaging; and, (2) examination of the role of omega-3 fatty acid activity in
      schizophrenics as a predictor of dopaminergic activity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study terminated due to failure to meet sufficient enrollment for valid analysis
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pre and Post Treatment PET and MRI imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 16 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of pretreatment and posttreatment psychiatric rating scales to include PANSS and CGI</measure>
    <time_frame>7 visits over 16 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Screening and Baseline Procedures followed by Referral to Community Care. Baseline Procedures may be repeated at a later time if appropriate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: Aripiprazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Screening and Baseline Procedures followed by 16 weeks of treatment with aripiprazole, followed by repeat of baseline procedures and referral to community care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Risperidone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Screening and Baseline Procedures followed by 16 weeks of treatment with Risperidone,followed by repeat of baseline procedures and referral to community care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aripiprazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Target dose = 15mg by mouth per day for 16 weeks. The dosage will be titrated in accordance with the treating physician's clinical judgment, generally reaching full dosage within one week of initiation. The dosage may be increased as clinically indicated, by the treating physician. Any deviation from these target dosing schedules must be reviewed and approved by the principal investigator, generally prior to the adjustment unless clinical circumstances require more immediate adjustment (in which case the treating physician should consult with the principal investigator as soon as is practically possible).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: Aripiprazole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Abilify</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Risperidone</intervention_name>
    <description>Target Dose = 2mg by mouth per day for 16 weeks. The dosage will be titrated in accordance with the treating physician's clinical judgment, generally reaching full dosage within one week of initiation. The dosage may be increased as clinically indicated, by the treating physician. Any deviation from these target dosing schedules must be reviewed and approved by the principal investigator, generally prior to the adjustment unless clinical circumstances require more immediate adjustment (in which case the treating physician should consult with the principal investigator as soon as is practically possible).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Risperidone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Risperdal</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects will meet DSM-IV diagnostic criteria for schizophreniform disorder,
             schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder or (non-affective) psychotic disorder, NOS.
             Subjects with schizophreniform disorder or psychotic disorder, NOS, will be
             diagnostically reevaluated (recontacted if no longer involved in the study) after a
             minimum of six months of psychotic symptoms in order to determine whether diagnostic
             criteria for schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder have been met.

          2. Subjects will be between 18 and 55 years of age, inclusive.

          3. Subjects will be able to fully participate in the informed consent process, or have a
             legal guardian able to participate in the informed consent process.

          4. Present score on at least one PANSS psychosis items (P1, P2, P3, P5 or P6) &gt;
             4(moderately severe) and CGI Severity score &gt; 4 (moderate).

          5. Female patients of childbearing potential must be using a medically accepted means of
             contraception

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current active substance use disorder diagnosis or a history of cocaine abuse or
             dependence;

          2. Female patients who are either pregnant or nursing;

          3. Known history of mental retardation, seizure disorder, or a clinically significant
             head injury (prolonged loss of consciousness, neurological sequelae, or demonstrated
             structural brain injury);

          4. Non-English speaking (mastery of English insufficient to participate in study
             evaluation procedures);

          5. Serious, unstable medical illness;

          6. Known hypersensitivity to any study medication;

          7. Medical contraindication to any element of the study procedure;

          8. Current symptoms which present serious risk of danger to self or others;

          9. Participation in a clinical trial of an investigational drug within 30 days of study
             entry;

         10. Current severity of psychiatric symptoms contraindicates a delay in initiation of
             antipsychotic medication treatment until functional imaging studies and
             neuropsychological testing have been completed;

         11. Baseline QTc interval of &gt; 450 msec.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Douglas S Lehrer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wallace Kettering Neuroscience Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wallace Kettering Neuroscience Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kettering</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45429</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 7, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 7, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 9, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 26, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Antipsychotic drug treatment response</keyword>
  <keyword>Risperidone</keyword>
  <keyword>Aripiprazole</keyword>
  <keyword>Fallypride</keyword>
  <keyword>Positron emission tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Dopamine D2 Receptors</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Risperidone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aripiprazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

