<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00719979</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34MH078922</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DSIR 83-ATP</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>5P20MH090318-02</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00719979</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of a Technology Assisted Behavioral Intervention in Assisting People With Major Depressive Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Integrated Telemental Health Intervention for Depression in Primary Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will develop and evaluate the effectiveness of a technology-assisted behavioral
      intervention, consisting of Internet-based cognitive behavioral therapy combined with
      telephone and email support, in reducing depressive symptoms and improving treatment
      adherence in primary care patients with major depressive disorder.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Major depressive disorder (MDD) is a common mental disorder, with up to 10.3% of the
      population experiencing the disorder in a given 12-month period. Symptoms of MDD include
      feelings of anxiety, guilt, or hopelessness; irregular sleep and appetite patterns; lethargy;
      excessive irritability and restlessness; inability to concentrate; and lack of enjoyment in
      previously enjoyed activities. Fortunately, MDD is treatable with forms of psychotherapy
      and/or antidepressant medications. Several studies have found that when given a choice, about
      two-thirds of depressed patients prefer psychotherapy treatment over antidepressant
      medication. Although psychotherapy treatments are both effective and desirable, a variety of
      barriers exist to initiating and sustaining psychotherapy. Only about 20% of all patients
      referred for psychotherapy treatments ever follow up. Of those who do initiate psychotherapy,
      nearly half drop out before completing treatment.

      Delivering an intervention through telecommunication technologies, such as the telephone and
      Internet, has the potential to overcome many of the barriers to existing treatments for
      depression. For example, telephone- and Web-based interventions can reduce cost, extend
      specialized treatment over broad geographic areas, and permit considerable flexibility in
      scheduling of treatment components. Technology-assisted Behavioral Intervention(TABI) is a
      specific form of a telecommunication behavioral intervention that incorporates Web-based
      Internet, e-mail, and telephone intervention. Further study is needed to determine the
      effectiveness of TABI in reducing depressive symptoms and attrition rates in people with MDD.
      This pilot study will first develop TABI, which will consist of Internet-based cognitive
      behavioral therapy (I-CBT) accompanied by telephone and e-mail support. The study will then
      compare the effectiveness of TABI with the effectiveness of I-CBT alone and treatment as
      usual (TAU) in reducing depressive symptoms and improving treatment adherence in primary care
      patients with MDD.

      Participation in the treatment phase of this study will last 12 weeks. All participants will
      first undergo initial assessments that will include a telephone interview and a series of
      questionnaires about mood. Eligible participants will then be assigned randomly to receive
      TABI, I-CBT alone, or TAU. Participants assigned to TABI and I-CBT will both undergo 12 weeks
      of a Web-based Internet intervention consisting of modules to help them learn skills to
      manage their moods. Participants assigned to TAU will receive standard treatment from their
      primary care physicians and will be able to choose between TABI and I-CBT treatment options
      after a 6-week wait-list period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and Weeks 6 &amp; 12 (post treatment)</time_frame>
    <description>PhQ-9 and diagnosis (using MINI)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Utilization and Attrition</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline-Week 12</time_frame>
    <description># logins</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction (Satisfaction Index-Mental Health)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and Weeks 6 &amp; 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">102</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iCBT and TeleCoaching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received the technology-assisted behavioral intervention (iCBT + TeleCoaching).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iCBT(MoodManager)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received Internet-based cognitive behavioral therapy only.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual / Wait-list control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received treatment as usual . For wait-list control, participants were not provided any intervention for 6 weeks, after which they were allowed to choose coached or self-directed moodManager.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral intervention (iCBT + TeleCoach)</intervention_name>
    <description>TABI will include 12 weeks of Internet-based cognitive behavioral therapy (iCBT) combined with brief telephone and email support from a coach.</description>
    <arm_group_label>iCBT and TeleCoaching</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>iCBT(MoodManager)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Internet-based cognitive behavioral therapy (I-CBT)</intervention_name>
    <description>I-CBT will include access to an interactive Web-based intervention designed to teach and facilitate the use of cognitive behavioral skills. The intervention will last 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>iCBT(MoodManager)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment as usual / Wait-list control</intervention_name>
    <description>TAU will include standard treatment from participants' primary care physicians. Participants will be able to choose between TABI and I-CBT treatment options after a 6-week wait-list period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual / Wait-list control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-IV diagnosis of MDD as assessed
             using the Mini Mental State Exam (MINI)

          -  Has a telephone, email account, computer, and broadband access to the Internet

          -  Able to navigate the Internet

          -  Able to speak and read English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hearing or voice impairment

          -  Visual impairment that would prevent use of the workbook and completion of assessment
             materials

          -  Meets criteria for dementia

          -  Diagnosed with a psychotic disorder, bipolar disorder, dissociative disorder, current
             substance abuse, or other diagnosis for which participation in a clinical trial of
             psychotherapy may be either inappropriate or dangerous

          -  Currently receiving individual psychotherapy or planning to receive psychotherapy
             during the 12-week treatment phase of the study

          -  Planning to be out of town or unavailable for treatment for 4 weeks or more during the
             scheduled treatment time

          -  Exhibits severe suicidality, including ideation, plan, and intent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David C. Mohr, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 18, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 22, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 18, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 18, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Mohr</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Behavior Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Technology Assisted</keyword>
  <keyword>Internet</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

