<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02558309</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO15070113</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02558309</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optic Nerve Head Quantification While Reducing Elevated Intracranial Pressure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optic Nerve Head Quantification While Reducing Elevated Intracranial Pressure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to examine in-vivo the effect of intraocular (IOP) and intracranial
      pressures (ICP) on the optic nerve head (ONH). The effect of ICP on eye health has been an
      area of concrete research effort in recent years. The ability to acquire non-invasive and
      highly detailed information on both the eye and the brain using technologies such as magnetic
      resonance imaging (MRI) and optical coherence tomography (OCT) have paved the way to assess
      non-invasively the effect of ICP in-vivo. In this study, we will quantify the structural
      changes in the ONH in subjects with elevated ICP while they are treated to reduce the
      elevated pressure. This process will occur in a stepwise fashion over a period of time
      determined by the clinical treatment plans. We will apply controlled pressures to the eye
      during each step of ICP lowering while OCT images are obtained.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      The goal of this study is to examine in-vivo the effect of intraocular (IOP) and intracranial
      pressures (ICP) on the optic nerve head (ONH).

      Specific Aims:

      In this study, the investigators will quantify the structural changes in the ONH in subjects
      with elevated ICP while they are treated to reduce the elevated pressure. This process will
      occur in a stepwise fashion over a period of time determined by the clinical treatment plans.
      The investigators will apply controlled pressures to the eye during each step of ICP lowering
      while OCT images are obtained.

      Background:

      The effect of ICP on eye health has been an area of concrete research effort in recent years.
      The ability to acquire non-invasive and highly detailed information on both the eye and the
      brain using technologies such as magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and optical coherence
      tomography (OCT) have paved the way to assess non-invasively the effect of ICP in-vivo.

      The ONH separates two pressurized compartments: the eyeball and the central nervous system.
      Situations in which ICP is elevated are often associated with papilledema, though the
      magnitude and the rate of change in ONH elevation in response to increased ICP or the
      reduction in ONH elevation in response to ICP treatments are yet to be determined. On the
      opposite side, glaucoma is a leading cause of blindness where elevated IOP is the leading
      risk factor, with clinical evidence suggesting the presence of ICP below the normal level in
      these subjects. The impaired balance between IOP and ICP leads to the deformation of the ONH,
      which triggers strangulation of the retinal ganglion cell axons when trespassing through the
      lamina cribrosa within the ONH on their way from the eye to the brain, leading to gradual
      axonal loss and irreversible visual impairment.

      Significance:

      Little is known about how the interaction of IOP and ICP pressure changes affect the
      macrostructure and microstructure of the optic nerve head structure. This information has a
      significant impact both for neurosurgical conditions with elevated ICP along with ocular
      conditions such as glaucoma and papilledema. The ability to gauge non-invasively changes in
      ICP will have a tremendous impact on neurosurgical management as it eliminates the need of
      longitudinal invasive measurements of ICP. The study will also improve the investigator's
      understanding of the pathophysiologic processes that lead to development of glaucoma as well
      as the response to treatment for subjects with papilledema. A better understanding of these
      processes will ultimately lead to improved detection and management of these conditions and a
      better understanding of ocular bio-mechanics.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    The Primary Investigator is no longer with UPMC. No patients have been enrolled.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Optic Nerve Head</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Week</time_frame>
    <description>The optic nerve head (ONH) structures will be evaluated for tissue deformation. The association between the structural findings in the optic nerve head region and intracranial and intraocular pressures will be evaluated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Intraocular Pressure</condition>
  <condition>Intracranial Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intracranial Pressure Reduction</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects scheduled to undergo gradual, step-wise reduction of Intracranial Pressure (ICP) will be screened.
The Glasgow Coma Scale will be administered to ascertain the cognitive ability of the participant.
A slit lamp examination and indirect ophthalmoscopy will be performed.
Experimental:
The subject's eye will be held open with an eye speculum during the exam.
Another eye exam, which includes a slit lamp examination and indirect ophthalmoscopy, will be performed.
Intraocular Pressure will be measured.
An Optic Coherence Tomography (OCT) will be performed.
At each step along the process of ICP reduction, the eye exam, IOP &amp; OCT will be performed.
Optional:
The Ophthalmology study team will raise the IOP using an Ophthlmodynanometer. It will be raised to 20 mmHg and 40 mmHg while OCT scans are obtained.
OCT scans will be taken at pre-manipulation, 20mmHg, 40mmHg, and post-manipulation at each step of the ICP lowering procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects who are scheduled to undergo gradual, step-wise reduction of Intracranial Pressure
        (ICP) will be screened.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 and older.

          -  Patients with an external ventricular drain (EVD).

          -  Normally appearing eye as determined during the screening clinical examination.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of intraocular surgery or ocular trauma (with the exception of laser
             procedures or uneventful cataract surgery more than 1 year from enrollment date).

          -  Ocular disorders that could affect retinal function such as retinal detachment,
             diabetic retinopathy, Macular degeneration.

          -  Neurological &amp; Non-Glaucomatous causes for Visual Field damage.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gadi Wollstein, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 22, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 22, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 23, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Intracranial Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

