<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02558556</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL47718.068.14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02558556</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>FALCON: a Multicenter Randomized Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Near-infrared Fluorescence Cholangiography Assisted Laparoscopic Cholecystectomy Versus Conventional Laparoscopic Cholecystectomy (FALCON): a Multicenter Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Several clinical feasibility studies have shown the potential benefit of
      near-infrared fluorescence (NIRF) imaging using indocyanine green (ICG) for enhanced and
      earlier biliary anatomy visualization during laparoscopic cholecystectomy with the aim to
      reduce the number of vascular and biliary injuries. Although the incidence of injuries is low
      (0.7%), the impact on patients in terms of morbidity, quality of life and costs are dramatic.
      The Critical View of Safety (CVS) technique is regarded as the safety valve in conventional
      laparoscopic cholecystectomy (CLC). It is hypothesized that standard application of
      near-infrared fluorescence imaging during laparoscopic cholecystectomy can be useful to
      obtain establishment of CVS (at least 5 minutes) earlier and with more certainty regarding
      visualization when compared to conventional laparoscopic imaging alone.

      Study design: A multicenter randomized controlled trial with two study arms. Patients
      scheduled for an elective laparoscopic cholecystectomy will be recruited and randomized at
      the outpatient clinic (n = 308 total). One group will undergo near-infrared fluorescence
      cholangiography assisted laparoscopic cholecystectomy (NIRF-LC) and the other group will
      undergo conventional laparoscopic cholecystectomy (CLC).

      Compared with standard care, patients in the NIRF-LC group have to receive one preoperative
      intravenous injection of ICG. This is the only additional minimally invasive action for the
      patient. Initially, patients participating in this study will not benefit from the
      application of NIRFC during the surgical procedure. The administration of ICG and the
      modified laparoscope itself are not related with any kind of additional risk for the patient.

      Despite the encouraging results from several (pre)clinical feasibility studies, wide clinical
      acceptance of the routine use of ICG fluorescence laparoscopy is still lacking due to the
      absence of reliable and validated clinical data. A randomized clinical study is desirable to
      assess the potential added value of the NIRF imaging technique during laparoscopic
      cholecystectomy. Strong evidence in favor of routine implementation of this new imaging
      technique during laparoscopic cholecystectomy, will probably lead to worldwide routine
      application of the NIRF technique. Therewith long term sustainability of this research
      project is guaranteed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Laparoscopic cholecystectomy (LC) is one of the most commonly performed laparoscopic
      procedures in gastrointestinal surgery. Bile duct injury during this procedure is rare but
      constitutes a serious complication (0.3-0.7%) (Flum 2003, Fletcher 1999, Nuzzo 2005 and Waage
      2005). Misidentification of the extra-hepatic bile duct anatomy during laparoscopic
      cholecystectomy is the main cause of bile duct injury (Way 2006).

      The Critical View of Safety (CVS) technique, which was first described by Strasberg in 1995
      (Strasberg 2003) and recommended by the Dutch Guidelines and Best Practice for laparoscopic
      cholecystectomy (Lange 2006), was introduced to reduce the risk of bile duct injury. To
      establish CVS, two windows need to be created: one window between the cystic artery, cystic
      duct and gallbladder, another window between the cystic artery, gallbladder and liver. The
      CVS technique is especially aimed at mobilizing the gallbladder neck from the liver, in order
      to obtain a circumferential identification of the transition of the cystic duct into the
      gallbladder.

      Intraoperative cholangiography has been advised to reduce the risk of bile duct injury (Flum
      2003, Buddinhg 2011). However, this radiological imaging of the biliary tree is only used
      selectively, as the process takes time, radiation exposure is involved and additional
      equipment and manpower for the procedure are required. Therefore, worldwide consensus about
      implementation of intraoperative cholangiography is still lacking (Ford 2012).

      Near-infrared fluorescence (NIRF) imaging after intravenous injection of indocyanine green
      (ICG) is a promising new technique for easier intraoperative recognition of the biliary
      anatomy. It may help improve the outcome of laparoscopic cholecystectomy (Buddingh 2011,
      Agarwal 2009). ICG is cleared quickly and exclusively by the liver after intravenous
      administration. Neither radiological support nor additional intervention, such as opening the
      biliary tree, is required. The NIRF laparoscopy technique using ICG has been evaluated in
      various animal models (Figueiredo 2010, Figueiredo 2011, Tagaya 2010, Matsui 2010) and in
      open, laparoscopic, and single-incision laparoscopic cholecystectomy (Tagaya 2010, Ishazawa
      2010, Ishazawa 2011 Aoki 2010). Promising results were presented for successful
      intraoperative identification of the common bile duct and the cystic duct, compared to
      conventional laparoscopic imaging. Another clinical study showed that the NIRFC technique
      provides significantly earlier identification of the extra-hepatic bile ducts during the CVS
      dissection phase: up to 10 minutes earlier identification of cystic duct and common bile duct
      could be obtained (Schols 2012). Real-time simultaneous imaging of the hepatic and cystic
      arteries can also be obtained (Ashitate 2011, Mitsuhashi 2008, Schols 2013).

      Despite the encouraging results from these (pre)clinical feasibility studies, wide clinical
      acceptance of the routine use of ICG fluorescence laparoscopy is still lacking due to the
      absence of reliable clinical data. Therefore, a multicenter randomized clinical study is
      desirable to assess the potential added value of the fluorescence imaging technique during
      laparoscopic cholecystectomy in order to perform a more safe procedure leading to a reduction
      in the vascular and bile duct injuries. This study will compare NIRF assisted laparoscopic
      cholecystectomy to conventional laparoscopic cholecystectomy.

      The main objective of this study is to evaluate whether earlier establishment of Critical
      View of Safety can be obtained using the NIRF laparoscopy technique during laparoscopic
      cholecystectomy. This will shorten the operation time, and thereby reduce the cost of the
      procedure.

      Study design: Multicenter randomized controlled trial. 308 patients will be included for
      randomization. All patients (age &gt;18 years) scheduled for an elective laparoscopic
      cholecystectomy and meeting the inclusion criteria will be suitable for inclusion. Patients
      will be included in at least 3 hospitals in The Netherlands: Maastricht University Medical
      Center+; Leiden University Medical Center; Catharina Hospital.

      Treatment of subjects: All operations will be performed by a surgical resident, assisted by a
      surgeon or surgical resident with a track record of at least 50 laparoscopic
      cholecystectomies, or will be performed by a surgeon or surgical resident with that track
      record him/herself. In the CLC group conventional laparoscopic cholecystectomy will be
      performed using conventional laparoscopic imaging systems. In the NIRF-LC group, using
      laparoscopic fluorescence imaging systems near-infrared fluorescence cholangiography
      technique will be conducted to assist during laparoscopic cholecystectomy. To obtain
      fluorescence imaging of the biliary tract a contrast agent has to be administered. Directly
      after induction of anesthesia the fluorescent dye, indocyanine green (ICG), will be
      administered for intraoperative visualization of the extra-hepatic bile ducts with the NIR
      fluorescence laparoscope. Since many years ICG has been approved for commercial and clinical
      diagnostic use by the FDA.

      Randomization: After inclusion in the study (i.e., after written informed consent is
      obtained) patients will be randomized to NIRF-LC or CLC group. Randomization will be
      performed centrally. Computerized treatment allocation will be conducted on the day of
      surgery. There will be no blinding of patients or surgeons.Stratification factor will be
      performed for participating center.The experience level of the surgical team will be
      recorded, but no stratification will take place for this factor, as due to the large volume
      of patients an even distribution of skill level over both randomization arms in expected.
      Experience is defined in performing laparoscopic cholecystectomy as first surgeon.

      Study procedures: The laparoscopic cholecystectomy procedure itself will not be performed
      differently than usual. Next, there will not be any radiation involved for the patient.
      Neither are any psychological or psychiatric investigations involved. Patients are not asked
      to undergo additional testing after the surgical procedure, they are also not requested to
      fulfill any questionnaire.

      The following procedures will be conducted during this study:

        -  Preoperative (NIRF-LC group): Directly after induction of anesthesia 1ml (2,5mg/ml)
           indocyanine green will be administrated via intravenous injection, by the surgeon or
           surgical trainee (under supervision of the surgeon and the anesthesiologist).

        -  Intraoperative (CLC and NIRF-LC group): Intraoperatively the PhD researcher / local
           researcher (to be appointed in each participating center) systematically whether the
           localization of the common bile duct, cystic duct and cystic artery can be identified at
           set time points, by both the conventional camera mode (CLC group) and fluorescence
           camera mode (NIRF-LC group). Also establishment of CVS is registered. For agreement on
           the identification of the aforementioned structures the attending surgeon is consulted.
           A structure is scored as 'identified' if its localization is confirmed with great
           certainty by the experienced surgeon. In case of the common bile duct this does
           explicitly not mean that it was surgically exposed, as this is contradictory to the
           CVS-technique. In accordance with regular care, all laparoscopic surgical procedures
           will be digitally recorded.

        -  Postoperative qualitative video analysis (CLC and NIRF-LC group)

      Performed by expert panel of 3 surgeons:

        -  Is CVS actually established? (and: at what time is CVS established?)

        -  Time until identification of the cystic duct, and time until identification of the
           transition of the cystic duct in the gallbladder during dissection of CVS;

        -  Time until identification of the cystic artery, and time until identification of the
           transition of the cystic artery in the gallbladder during dissection of CVS;
           Postoperative quantitative fluorescence image analysis (NIRF-LC group): For objective
           assessment of the degree of fluorescence illumination in the extra-hepatic bile ducts
           and artery, OsiriX 5.5.1 Imaging Software will be used. The fluorescence images will be
           analyzed by determining target-to-background ratio (TBR). TBR is defined as the mean
           fluorescence intensity (FI) of two point regions of interest (ROIs) in the target (i.e.
           CBD, CD or CA) minus the mean fluorescence intensity of two background (BG) ROIs in the
           liver hilum, divided by the mean fluorescence intensity of the two background ROIs in
           the liver hilum; in formula: TBR = (FI of target - FI of BG) / FI of BG.

      Postoperative registration of secondary endpoints (CLC and NIRF-LC group). The researcher
      will document the following remaining secondary endpoints: Intraoperative bile leakage from
      the gallbladder or cystic duct; Bile duct injury; Postoperative length of hospital stay;
      Complications due to the intravenously injected contrast agent; Conversion to open
      cholecystectomy; Postoperative complications (until 90 days after surgery) After 90 days the
      patient will contacted by telephone to register any complications that occurred after the
      routine visits.

      Cost-effectiveness minimisation of the procedure will be calculated, limited to the
      per-operative period. The observed reduction in time until CVS, calculated in cost per minute
      use of the operating suite, will be weighed against the extra cost of the use of the
      equipment and the fluorescent dye.

      Postoperative analysis of time measurements (CLC and NIRF-LC group) Regarding the primary and
      secondary endpoints, a linear regression analysis will be applied for determination of
      possible significant differences between the time measurements from &quot;first look at liver
      hilum&quot; until &quot;establishment of CVS&quot; / &quot;identification of transition CD in gallbladder&quot; /
      &quot;identification of transition CA in gallbladder&quot;; therewith comparing fluorescence
      laparoscopic imaging with conventional laparoscopic imaging. In case of missing values (which
      can occur with the expert panel analysis, when the panel concludes that actually no CVS was
      obtained or the transition of the mentioned structures in the gallbladder had not been
      properly identified) a Cox regression analysis will be used.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>time to identification of CVS</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>change in time to identification of CVS</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time until identification of the transition of the cystic duct in the gallbladder during dissection of CVS</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>change in time to identification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>visualization of CVS and visualization of the transition of the cystic duct and cystic artery in the gallbladder</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Are these structures actually visualized?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>total surgical time</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>change in duration of surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>intraoperative bile leakage from the gallbladder or cystic duct</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>change in number of intraoperative bile leakage from the gallbladder or cystic duct</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>bile duct injury</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>change in number of bile duct injuries</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>postoperative length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 1-2 days</time_frame>
    <description>change in length of hospital stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>complications due to the injected contrast agent</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>appearance of complications in intervention group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>conversion to open cholecystectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>at time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>change in number of conversions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>change in number of postoperative complications</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cost-minimisation: difference in costs between the treatment in both groups</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>change in costs per patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">308</enrollment>
  <condition>Cholecystolithiasis</condition>
  <condition>Cholecystitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NIRF-LC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group of patients will undergo near-infrared fluorescence cholangiography assisted laparoscopic cholecystectomy by use of a Laparoscopic Fluorescence Imaging System (Karl Storz), in combination with one intravenous injection of contrast agent ICG. The ICG is given directly after induction of anesthesia in a dose of 1 ml of 2,5 mg/ml solution.
Intraoperatively every 2-5 minutes (more often if desired by surgeon) camera is switched to ICG mode for fluorescence cholangiography, until CVS is established.
Registration of time until establishment of CVS, visualization of the individual structures as described as secondary endpoints, and total operation time will be done.
The complete procedure will be recorded on video.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CLC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will undergo conventional laparoscopic cholecystectomy as in standard practice with no other intervention.
Registration of time until establishment of CVS, visualization of the individual structures as described as secondary endpoints, and total operation time will be done.
The complete procedure will be recorded on video.
Postoperatively, as in the NIRF-LC arm, the videos will be analysed to determine whether CVS is actually established, is the transition of the cystic duct into the gallbladder visualized? Is transition of the cystic artery into the gallbladder visualized? Furthermore, cost-minimalisation will be calculated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laparoscopic Fluorescence Imaging System (Karl Storz)</intervention_name>
    <description>The Laparoscopic Fluorescence Imaging System (incl. laparoscope, light source, light cable) will supply the needs for near-infrared fluorescence imaging with ICG. The hypothesis is that this device will help in visualizing the anatomical structures such as the common bile duct, which are hard to visualize in white light due to the surrounding tissues.</description>
    <arm_group_label>NIRF-LC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Indocyanine Green</intervention_name>
    <description>Indocyanine Green will be injected intravenously as a contrast agent for the use of the Laparoscopic Fluorescence Imaging System.</description>
    <arm_group_label>NIRF-LC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ICG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Scheduled for elective laparoscopic cholecystectomy

          -  Normal liver and renal function

          -  No hypersensitivity for iodine or ICG

          -  Able to understand nature of the study procedures

          -  Willing to participate and with written informed consent

          -  Physical Status Classification: ASA I / ASA II

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 18 years

          -  Liver or renal insufficiency

          -  Known iodine or ICG hypersensitivity

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  Not able to understand nature of the study procedure

          -  Physical Status Classification: ASA III and above

          -  iv Heparin injection in the last 24 h; (LMWH not contraindicated)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laurents PS Stassen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Maastricht UMC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacqueline van den Bos, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0031613206302</phone>
    <email>jacqueline.vanden.bos@mumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maastricht University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maastricht</city>
        <state>Limburg</state>
        <zip>6229</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacqueline van den Bos, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0031613206302</phone>
      <email>jacqueline.vanden.bos@mumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flum DR, Dellinger EP, Cheadle A, Chan L, Koepsell T. Intraoperative cholangiography and risk of common bile duct injury during cholecystectomy. JAMA. 2003 Apr 2;289(13):1639-44.</citation>
    <PMID>12672731</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fletcher DR, Hobbs MS, Tan P, Valinsky LJ, Hockey RL, Pikora TJ, Knuiman MW, Sheiner HJ, Edis A. Complications of cholecystectomy: risks of the laparoscopic approach and protective effects of operative cholangiography: a population-based study. Ann Surg. 1999 Apr;229(4):449-57.</citation>
    <PMID>10203075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nuzzo G, Giuliante F, Giovannini I, Ardito F, D'Acapito F, Vellone M, Murazio M, Capelli G. Bile duct injury during laparoscopic cholecystectomy: results of an Italian national survey on 56 591 cholecystectomies. Arch Surg. 2005 Oct;140(10):986-92.</citation>
    <PMID>16230550</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waage A, Nilsson M. Iatrogenic bile duct injury: a population-based study of 152 776 cholecystectomies in the Swedish Inpatient Registry. Arch Surg. 2006 Dec;141(12):1207-13.</citation>
    <PMID>17178963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Way LW, Stewart L, Gantert W, Liu K, Lee CM, Whang K, Hunter JG. Causes and prevention of laparoscopic bile duct injuries: analysis of 252 cases from a human factors and cognitive psychology perspective. Ann Surg. 2003 Apr;237(4):460-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12677139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strasberg SM, Hertl M, Soper NJ. An analysis of the problem of biliary injury during laparoscopic cholecystectomy. J Am Coll Surg. 1995 Jan;180(1):101-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8000648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buddingh KT, Nieuwenhuijs VB, van Buuren L, Hulscher JB, de Jong JS, van Dam GM. Intraoperative assessment of biliary anatomy for prevention of bile duct injury: a review of current and future patient safety interventions. Surg Endosc. 2011 Aug;25(8):2449-61. doi: 10.1007/s00464-011-1639-8. Epub 2011 Apr 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21487883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ford JA, Soop M, Du J, Loveday BP, Rodgers M. Systematic review of intraoperative cholangiography in cholecystectomy. Br J Surg. 2012 Feb;99(2):160-7. doi: 10.1002/bjs.7809. Epub 2011 Dec 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22183717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Agarwal BB. Patient safety in laparoscopic cholecystectomy. Arch Surg. 2009 Oct;144(10):979; author reply 979. doi: 10.1001/archsurg.2009.180.</citation>
    <PMID>19841374</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Figueiredo JL, Siegel C, Nahrendorf M, Weissleder R. Intraoperative near-infrared fluorescent cholangiography (NIRFC) in mouse models of bile duct injury. World J Surg. 2010 Feb;34(2):336-43. doi: 10.1007/s00268-009-0332-8.</citation>
    <PMID>20033407</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Figueiredo JL, Nahrendorf M, Vinegoni C, Weissleder R. Intraoperative near-infrared fluorescent cholangiography (NIRFC) in mouse models of bile duct injury: reply. World J Surg. 2011 Mar;35(3):694-5. doi: 10.1007/s00268-010-0728-5.</citation>
    <PMID>20645091</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tagaya N, Shimoda M, Kato M, Nakagawa A, Abe A, Iwasaki Y, Oishi H, Shirotani N, Kubota K. Intraoperative exploration of biliary anatomy using fluorescence imaging of indocyanine green in experimental and clinical cholecystectomies. J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Sci. 2010 Sep;17(5):595-600. doi: 10.1007/s00534-009-0195-2. Epub 2009 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19806299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Matsui A, Tanaka E, Choi HS, Winer JH, Kianzad V, Gioux S, Laurence RG, Frangioni JV. Real-time intra-operative near-infrared fluorescence identification of the extrahepatic bile ducts using clinically available contrast agents. Surgery. 2010 Jul;148(1):87-95. doi: 10.1016/j.surg.2009.12.004. Epub 2010 Feb 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20117813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ishizawa T, Bandai Y, Ijichi M, Kaneko J, Hasegawa K, Kokudo N. Fluorescent cholangiography illuminating the biliary tree during laparoscopic cholecystectomy. Br J Surg. 2010 Sep;97(9):1369-77. doi: 10.1002/bjs.7125.</citation>
    <PMID>20623766</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ishizawa T, Kaneko J, Inoue Y, Takemura N, Seyama Y, Aoki T, Beck Y, Sugawara Y, Hasegawa K, Harada N, Ijichi M, Kusaka K, Shibasaki M, Bandai Y, Kokudo N. Application of fluorescent cholangiography to single-incision laparoscopic cholecystectomy. Surg Endosc. 2011 Aug;25(8):2631-6. doi: 10.1007/s00464-011-1616-2. Epub 2011 Mar 18.</citation>
    <PMID>21424202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aoki T, Murakami M, Yasuda D, Shimizu Y, Kusano T, Matsuda K, Niiya T, Kato H, Murai N, Otsuka K, Kusano M, Kato T. Intraoperative fluorescent imaging using indocyanine green for liver mapping and cholangiography. J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Sci. 2010 Sep;17(5):590-4. doi: 10.1007/s00534-009-0197-0. Epub 2009 Oct 21.</citation>
    <PMID>19844652</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schols RM, Bouvy ND, Masclee AA, van Dam RM, Dejong CH, Stassen LP. Fluorescence cholangiography during laparoscopic cholecystectomy: a feasibility study on early biliary tract delineation. Surg Endosc. 2013 May;27(5):1530-6. doi: 10.1007/s00464-012-2635-3. Epub 2012 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23076461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitsuhashi N, Kimura F, Shimizu H, Imamaki M, Yoshidome H, Ohtsuka M, Kato A, Yoshitomi H, Nozawa S, Furukawa K, Takeuchi D, Takayashiki T, Suda K, Igarashi T, Miyazaki M. Usefulness of intraoperative fluorescence imaging to evaluate local anatomy in hepatobiliary surgery. J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Surg. 2008;15(5):508-14. doi: 10.1007/s00534-007-1307-5. Epub 2008 Oct 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18836805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashitate Y, Stockdale A, Choi HS, Laurence RG, Frangioni JV. Real-time simultaneous near-infrared fluorescence imaging of bile duct and arterial anatomy. J Surg Res. 2012 Jul;176(1):7-13. doi: 10.1016/j.jss.2011.06.027. Epub 2011 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21816414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schols RM, Bouvy ND, van Dam RM, Masclee AA, Dejong CH, Stassen LP. Combined vascular and biliary fluorescence imaging in laparoscopic cholecystectomy. Surg Endosc. 2013 Dec;27(12):4511-7. doi: 10.1007/s00464-013-3100-7. Epub 2013 Jul 23.</citation>
    <PMID>23877766</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Laparoscopic cholecystectomy (LC)</keyword>
  <keyword>Indocyanine green (ICG)</keyword>
  <keyword>Near-Infrared Fluorescence Imaging (NIRF)</keyword>
  <keyword>Critical View of Safety (CVS)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cholecystitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acalculous Cholecystitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholecystolithiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholelithiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gallstones</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

