<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02559011</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015_09_21</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02559011</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Arrhythmias in Patients Undergoing Transcatheter Aortic Valve Implantation Using a Small Insertable Cardiac Monitoring Device</brief_title>
  <acronym>Reveal</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessment of Arrhythmias in Patients Undergoing Transcatheter Aortic Valve Implantation Using a Small Insertable Cardiac Monitoring Device</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Transcatheter aortic valve implantation (TAVI) has emerged as a valuable minimal-invasive
      treatment option in patients with symptomatic severe aortic valve (AV) stenosis at
      prohibitive or increased risk for conventional open-heart surgery. Recent randomized clinical
      trials reported a large treatment effect of TAVI over medical treatment among inoperable
      patients and similar or superior outcomes compared with surgical aortic valve replacement in
      high to intermediate risk patients. However, atrio-ventricular conduction disturbances and
      arrhythmias (in particular atrial fibrillation) before, during or after TAVI remain a matter
      of concern as they have important consequences.

      The objective of this study is to investigate the incidence, nature and prognostic
      significance of AV-conduction disturbances and arrhythmias among patients with severe,
      symptomatic aortic stenosis undergoing TAVI before, during and after the procedure using a
      small implantable cardiac monitoring system (ICM; Medtronic REVEAL LinQTM).

      One hundred patients will be enrolled in this study. Prior to TAVI (at least 4 weeks), at the
      time of preprocedural hemodynamic and anatomical assessment, the ICM will be inserted under
      the skin of the chest under local anesthesia. The device will be interrogated just prior to
      readmission for TAVI and thereafter at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months of follow-up. The incidence of
      symptomatic as well as silent brady- and tachyarrhythmias will be recorded, and its impact on
      medical and device treatment as well as clinical outcomes analyzed.

      The present study will provide information about the actual incidence and impact of
      symptomatic and silent arrhythmias and AV-conduction disturbances among patients with severe,
      symptomatic aortic stenosis undergoing TAVI. Specifically, the study estimate the burden of
      arrhythmias before TAVI and to accurately determine the incidence of new onset atrial
      fibrillation and complete AV-block within 12 months after the procedure. Identifying patients
      at risk for AV- conduction abnormalities, atrial fibrillation (AF), and non-sustained or
      sustained ventricular arrhythmias may guide future preventive measures, medical treatment and
      improve patients outcomes after TAVI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background

      TAVI has emerged as a valuable minimal-invasive treatment option in patients with symptomatic
      severe aortic valve stenosis at prohibitive or increased risk for conventional open-heart
      surgery. AV conduction disturbances and arrhythmias before, during or after TAVI remain a
      matter of concern as they have consequences.

      Prior to TAVI the ICM will be inserted under the skin of the chest under local anesthesia.
      The device will be interrogated just prior to readmission for TAVI and thereafter at 1, 3, 6,
      and 12 months of follow-up. The incidence of symptomatic as well as silent brady- and
      tachyarrhythmias will be recorded, and its impact on medical and device treatment as well as
      clinical outcomes analyzed.

      All patients with severe, symptomatic aortic stenosis undergoing TAVI at the institution
      irrespective selected bioprosthesis will be included in the study. Final decision on
      eligibility will be made by the local Heart Team.

      Objective

      To investigate the incidence, nature and prognostic significance of AV-conduction
      disturbances and arrhythmias among patients with severe, symptomatic aortic stenosis
      undergoing TAVI before, during and after the procedure using a small implantable cardiac
      monitoring system (ICM; Medtronic REVEAL LinQTM). The primary endpoint of the study is to
      establish the incidence of new onset atrial fibrillation and complete AV-block within 12
      months after TAVI.

      Methods

      One hundred patients with severe, symptomatic aortic stenosis undergoing TAVI will be
      enrolled in this prospective, observational study. Prior to TAVI (at least 4 weeks), at the
      time of preprocedural hemodynamic and anatomical assessment, the ICM will be inserted under
      the skin of the chest under local anesthesia. The device will be interrogated just prior to
      readmission for TAVI and thereafter at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months of follow-up. The incidence of
      symptomatic as well as silent brady- and tachyarrhythmias will be recorded, and its impact on
      medical and device treatment as well as clinical outcomes analyzed.

      The study is observational: the patients will not be assigned to a specific intervention.
      Patients consenting will be monitored using a specific device that has been approved for
      market release. The objective of the study is to use the information obtained with this
      monitoring device to assess the incidence, nature and prognostic significance of
      atrioventricular conduction disturbances and arrhythmias among patients with severe,
      symptomatic aortic stenosis undergoing Transcatheter Aortic Valve Implantation before, during
      and after the procedure. The objective of the study is not to investigate the performance of
      the monitoring device.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with incidence of new onset atrial fibrillation and complete AVB within 12 months after TAVI</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with resolution of atrial Fibrillation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with resolution of Atrium Ventricular Block (AVB) after TAVI with permanent pacemaker (PPM) implantation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with cardiac death due to arrhythmias</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with presyncope and syncope</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with pacemaker Implantation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with cardiovascular mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Aortic Valve Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All study participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who need a TAVI with symptomatic severe aortic valve stenosis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients with severe, symptomatic aortic valve stenosis undergoing TAVI at the
        institution irrespective selected bioprosthesis will be included in the study. Final
        decision on eligibility will be made by the local Heart Team.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe symptomatic aortic valve stenosis undergoing TAVI

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Missing IC

          -  Pacemaker, internal cardioverter-defibrillator or cardiac resynchronization therapy
             (CRT) device at the time of screening

          -  Anatomic or clinical contraindications for TAVI or REVEAL insertion

          -  Patient currently participating in another study evaluating a new transcatheter valve
             prosthesis or a new drug
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephan Windecker, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bern University Hospital, Dep. of Cardiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anja Thoms</last_name>
    <phone>+41 31 632 30 70</phone>
    <email>Anja.Thoms@insel.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bern University Hospital, Dep. of Cardiology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephan Windecker, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <phone>+41 31 632 96 53</phone>
      <email>Stephan.Windecker@insel.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Fabien Praz, Dr. med.</last_name>
      <phone>+41 31 632 21 11</phone>
      <email>Fabien.Praz@insel.ch</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephan Windecker, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirabel M, Iung B, Baron G, Messika-Zeitoun D, Détaint D, Vanoverschelde JL, Butchart EG, Ravaud P, Vahanian A. What are the characteristics of patients with severe, symptomatic, mitral regurgitation who are denied surgery? Eur Heart J. 2007 Jun;28(11):1358-65. Epub 2007 Mar 9.</citation>
    <PMID>17350971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kodali SK, Williams MR, Smith CR, Svensson LG, Webb JG, Makkar RR, Fontana GP, Dewey TM, Thourani VH, Pichard AD, Fischbein M, Szeto WY, Lim S, Greason KL, Teirstein PS, Malaisrie SC, Douglas PS, Hahn RT, Whisenant B, Zajarias A, Wang D, Akin JJ, Anderson WN, Leon MB; PARTNER Trial Investigators. Two-year outcomes after transcatheter or surgical aortic-valve replacement. N Engl J Med. 2012 May 3;366(18):1686-95. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1200384. Epub 2012 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22443479</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedman HS, Zaman Q, Haft JI, Melendez S. Assessment of atrioventricular conduction in aortic valve disease. Br Heart J. 1978 Aug;40(8):911-7.</citation>
    <PMID>687491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris A, Davies M, Redwood D, Leatham A, Siddons H. Aetiology of chronic heart block. A clinico-pathological correlation in 65 cases. Br Heart J. 1969 Mar;31(2):206-18.</citation>
    <PMID>5775291</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Urena M, Hayek S, Cheema AN, Serra V, Amat-Santos IJ, Nombela-Franco L, Ribeiro HB, Allende R, Paradis JM, Dumont E, Thourani VH, Babaliaros V, Francisco Pascual J, Cortés C, Del Blanco BG, Philippon F, Lerakis S, Rodés-Cabau J. Arrhythmia burden in elderly patients with severe aortic stenosis as determined by continuous electrocardiographic recording: toward a better understanding of arrhythmic events after transcatheter aortic valve replacement. Circulation. 2015 Feb 3;131(5):469-77. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.114.011929. Epub 2014 Dec 2.</citation>
    <PMID>25466975</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith R, Grossman W, Johnson L, Segal H, Collins J, Dalen J. Arrhythmias following cardiac valve replacement. Circulation. 1972 May;45(5):1018-23.</citation>
    <PMID>5020795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Matthews IG, Fazal IA, Bates MG, Turley AJ. In patients undergoing aortic valve replacement, what factors predict the requirement for permanent pacemaker implantation? Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg. 2011 Mar;12(3):475-9. doi: 10.1510/icvts.2010.254607. Epub 2010 Dec 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21138915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreno R, Dobarro D, López de Sá E, Prieto M, Morales C, Calvo Orbe L, Moreno-Gomez I, Filgueiras D, Sanchez-Recalde A, Galeote G, Jiménez-Valero S, Lopez-Sendon JL. Cause of complete atrioventricular block after percutaneous aortic valve implantation: insights from a necropsy study. Circulation. 2009 Aug 4;120(5):e29-30. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.109.849281.</citation>
    <PMID>19652115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubín JM, Avanzas P, del Valle R, Renilla A, Ríos E, Calvo D, Lozano I, Anguera I, Díaz-Molina B, Cequier A, Morís de la Tassa C. Atrioventricular conduction disturbance characterization in transcatheter aortic valve implantation with the CoreValve prosthesis. Circ Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Jun;4(3):280-6. doi: 10.1161/CIRCINTERVENTIONS.111.961649. Epub 2011 May 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21540440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adams DH, Popma JJ, Reardon MJ. Transcatheter aortic-valve replacement with a self-expanding prosthesis. N Engl J Med. 2014 Sep 4;371(10):967-8. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc1408396.</citation>
    <PMID>25184874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van der Boon RM, Nuis RJ, Van Mieghem NM, Jordaens L, Rodés-Cabau J, van Domburg RT, Serruys PW, Anderson RH, de Jaegere PP. New conduction abnormalities after TAVI--frequency and causes. Nat Rev Cardiol. 2012 May 1;9(8):454-63. doi: 10.1038/nrcardio.2012.58. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22547171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Houthuizen P, Van Garsse LA, Poels TT, de Jaegere P, van der Boon RM, Swinkels BM, Ten Berg JM, van der Kley F, Schalij MJ, Baan J Jr, Cocchieri R, Brueren GR, van Straten AH, den Heijer P, Bentala M, van Ommen V, Kluin J, Stella PR, Prins MH, Maessen JG, Prinzen FW. Left bundle-branch block induced by transcatheter aortic valve implantation increases risk of death. Circulation. 2012 Aug 7;126(6):720-8. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.112.101055. Epub 2012 Jul 12.</citation>
    <PMID>22791865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Arrhythmias, Cardiac</keyword>
  <keyword>Transcatheter Aortic Valve implantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Aortic Valve Stenosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aortic Valve Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

