<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02555111</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AOM 11077 - P 110150</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-001190-40</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02555111</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Xarelto Versus no Treatment for the Prevention of Recurrent Thrombosis in Patients With Chronic Portal Vein Thrombosis.</brief_title>
  <acronym>RIPORT</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicentric Randomized Study of Xarelto Versus no Treatment for the Prevention of Recurrent Thrombosis in Patients With Chronic Portal Vein Thrombosis.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Open randomized therapeutic study to assess the efficacy of Xarelto 15mg/day in the
      recurrence of thromboembolic event compared to an untreated group in patients with chronic
      portal vein thrombosis without high risk thrombophilia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic portal vein thrombosis (PVT) is a rare disease, affecting young patients,
      characterized by permanent obstruction of the portal vein trunk causing portal hypertension.
      In 60-70% of cases it is related to high risk, moderate or mild prothrombotic risk factors.

      Accordingly, there are 2 types of complications from PVT :(i) gastrointestinal haemorrhage
      related to portal hypertension; and (ii) recurrent thrombosis.

      Recurrent thrombosis its most dreaded complication as it may lead to intestinal infarction
      with a related mortality of 20-60% and a high risk of intestinal insufficiency.

      Gastrointestinal haemorrhage related to portal hypertension occurs in 20% patients/year. It
      is less frequent in patients treated with medical or endoscopic prophylaxis for variceal
      bleeding.

      Retrospective data shows that anticoagulation does not worsen the prognosis, and may
      conversely improve it. Thus, in patients at risk for gastrointestinal bleeding due to portal
      hypertension and a mild or moderate risk of recurrent thrombosis, the benefit-risk ratio of
      anticoagulation therapy is unclear.

      The aim of this open randomised trial is to assess the efficacy of Xarelto 15mg/day, a new
      oral factor Xa inhibitor, in the recurrence of thromboembolic event and the risk of major
      bleeding compared to an untreated group in patients with chronic portal vein thrombosis
      without high risk thrombophilia.

      This is a national, multicentric, interventional study. 17 french centers already agreed to
      participate.

      296 patients will be included on a 3 years period with 2 to 4 years treatment period. All
      data will be collected after informed consent will be obtained.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of thromboembolic event in any territory (arterial or venous, splanchnic or extra splanchnic) or death</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>In patients with chronic portal vein thrombosis without high risk thrombophilia, to assess the efficacy of Xarelto in the recurrence of thromboembolic event compared to absence of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of xarelto</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the efficacy regarding:
- Incidence of Pulmonary embolism, Deep vein thrombosis, Major bleedings and Portal hypertension bleeding, new non bleeding complication of portal hypertension, minor bleeding,</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of xarelto</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the safety regarding:
Toxicity of Xarelto, especially hepatic.
Gastrointestinal clinically relevant non major bleedings related to portal hypertension
Other gastrointestinal clinically relevant non major bleedings
Other adverse events
Survival (12months, 24 months and at the end of the follow up).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of hospitalization during follow up.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of clotting activator marker with and without Xarelto.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of hospitalization during follow up.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">112</enrollment>
  <condition>Deep Vein Thrombosis</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Portal Vein Thrombosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Xarelto</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>15mg/day oral administration during 2 to 4 years (based on the recruitment date).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>untreated</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>the patient won't receive any treatment during his study participation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Xarelto</intervention_name>
    <description>15mg/day oral administration during 2 to 4 years (based on the recruitment date).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Xarelto</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rivaroxaban</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  90 years old &gt;Adults &gt; 18 years old

          -  Patients Either affected by cavernous portal, with a constituted diagnostic on
             radiological criteria, treated or not with anticoagulant Or acute portal thrombosis
             history dating back more than 6 months, documented by angiography or angio-MRI ;
             followed or not by a repermeabilize.

          -  Patient who was used prophylaxis for gastrointestinal bleeding in portal hypertension,
             according to current consensus recommendations for patients with cirrhosis

          -  Barrier contraception or intrauterine device (with or without progestin), for women of
             childbearing age, or progestin alone. Do not use combined hormonal contraception.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of a high risk factor of recurrence of thrombosis veinous after review of the
             medical file by a validation committee composed of an hepatologist and a hematologist
             physician hemostasis specialist.

          -  Disease with relevant coagulopathy and bleeding risk clinically relevant (platelet &lt;
             50 000, or TP &lt;30 % without AVK or Factor V &lt; 30% ou fibrinogen &lt; 0.8)

          -  Cirrhosis clinically relevant or with histological test or Budd Chiari syndrome.

          -  Personnel or first degree familial past history of spontaneous (unprovoked) deep vein
             thrombosis require an anticoagulant treatment

          -  Pregnancy and breast feeding women

          -  Past history of mesenteric infarction

          -  Absolute necessity of anticoagulation whatever the cause

          -  Galactose intolerance, Lapp lactase deficiency, malabsorption of glucose and galactose

          -  HIV positive and treated by antiprotease

          -  Patient with impossible follow up

          -  Severe renal failure (creatinin clearance &lt; 30 ml/min)

          -  Concomitant treatment with ketoconazole, l'itraconazole, le voriconazole or
             posaconazole, or HIV protease inhibitor, potent CYP3A4 and P-gp inhibitors

          -  Simultaneous treatment with rifampicin or other CYP3A4 inductor

          -  Hypersensitivity to Xarelto or one of the excipients

          -  Progressive bleeding, clinically relevant including lesion or disease with significant
             risk of major bleeding.

          -  Concomitant treatment with other anticoagulant (unfractionated heparin (UFH), low
             molecular weight heparin (enoxaparin, dalteparin, etc.), heparin derivatives
             (fondaparinux, etc.), oral anticoagulants (warfarin, dabigatran etexilate, apixaban,
             etc.), unless relay with Xarelto® or &quot;vice-versa&quot;, or when administered at doses f UFH
             necessary to maintain the permeability of a central venous or arterial catheter.

          -  Concomitant treatment of acute coronary syndrome clopidogrel / Plavix®

          -  Liver transplantation

          -  Transjugular intrahepatic portosystemic shunt
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aurélie Dr Plessier</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hôpital Beaujon - APHP</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Beaujon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clichy</city>
        <zip>92110</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>thrombosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rivaroxaban</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

