<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02556346</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MT-3724_CLL_SLL_001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02556346</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetics (PK), Pharmacodynamics (PD), Safety, Tolerability of Multiple Dose Regimens of MT-3724 for the Treatment of Patients With Relapsed Chronic B-cell Lymphocytic Leukemia or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics, Safety and Tolerability of Multiple Dose Regimens of MT-3724 for the Treatment of Patients With Relapsed Chronic B-cell Lymphocytic Leukemia or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Molecular Templates, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Molecular Templates, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase I, multiple ascending dose study will seek to enroll subjects with
      relapsed/refractory Chronic B-cell Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma
      (SLL) with confirmed and measurable disease who have received standard treatment with at
      least one anti-CD20 antibody (e.g.; rituximab, ofatumumab) containing front-line regimen that
      resulted in initial response, followed by relapse/recurrence and who are not eligible for any
      further approved biologic therapy, chemotherapy and/or autologous stem transplantation and/or
      refuse alternative approved therapies and/or are unlikely to achieve clinical benefit from
      any therapy of higher priority by Investigator assessment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is intended to provide investigators and sponsor with the following information
      regarding the investigational new drug MT-3724 in patients with relapsed/refractory Chronic
      B-cell Lymphocytic Leukemia or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma:

      The maximum dose of a single course of MT-3724 given as intravenous (IV) infusions on Days 1,
      3, 5, 8, 10 and 12 at which there are negligible side effects and/or at which maximum serum
      levels and/or at which maximum effect on blood lymphocytes are observed. Four dose levels
      will be investigated.

      The changes in MT-3724 serum levels and blood lymphocytes over time following IV doses at
      different points in the study.

      The changes and kinds of clinical and laboratory effects and side effects that may occur over
      repeated courses of MT-3724 The changes in each subject's immune status and their CLL or SLL
      following one or more cycles of 6 infusions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    The patient population (CLL &amp; SLL) was included in another ongoing study involving NHL
    patients.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability as measured by number of subjects with dose limiting toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of tolerability of MT-3724 measured by number of subjects with dose limiting toxicities (DLTs)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as measured by number of subjects with Adverse Events using CTCAE</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days and then every 6 months for up to 24 months following first dose if subject does not continue into Phase Ib</time_frame>
    <description>Safety measured by number of subjects with Adverse Events using CTCAE Version 4.03</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability as measured by adverse events using CTCAE and clinical laboratory parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>2-3 weeks following last dose and then every 6 months for up to 24 months following first dose</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of tolerability of MT-3724 given for up to 4 additional cycles measured by number, nature and severity of Adverse Events using CTCAE Version 4.03</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK as measured by concentrations of free MT-3724 (Cmax, Cinf)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 5, 8, 12, 23, and 28</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the pharmacokinetic profile of MT-3724</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK as measured by area under the curve of free MT-3724 (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 5, 8, 12, 23, and 28</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the pharmacokinetic profile of MT-3724</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK as measured by time to maximum concentration of free MT-3724 ( tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1, 5, 8, 12, 23, and 28</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the pharmacokinetic profile of MT-3724</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PD as measured by immunogenicity (anti-drug antibodies)</measure>
    <time_frame>During Screening, Days 23-25, Day 1 of cycle 2, and at final end of study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the pharmacodynamic profile of MT-3724</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor Response as measured by PET or CT scan</measure>
    <time_frame>During Screening, Days 43 &amp; 86</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of tumor response using International Working Group Response Criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic B-cell Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Small Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MT-3724 Phase 1 5 mcg/kg/dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MT-3724 5 mcg/kg/dose IV for 6 doses over 12 days (M-W-F X 2 weeks), followed by dose escalations (Phase 1) until recommended phase 2 dose of MT-3724 is determined</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MT-3724 Phase 1 10 mcg/kg/dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MT-3724 10 mcg/kg/dose IV for 6 doses over 12 days (M-W-F X 2 weeks), followed by dose escalations (Phase 1) until recommended phase 2 dose of MT-3724 is determined</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MT-3724 Phase 1 20 mcg/kg/dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MT-3724 20 mcg/kg/dose IV for 6 doses over 12 days (M-W-F X 2 weeks), followed by dose escalations (Phase 1) until recommended phase 2 dose of MT-3724 is determined</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MT-3724 Phase 1 50 mcg/kg/dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MT-3724 50 mcg/kg/dose IV for 6 doses over 12 days (M-W-F X 2 weeks), followed by dose escalations (Phase 1) until recommended phase 2 dose of MT-3724 is determined</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MT-3724 Phase 1b</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MT-3724 IV for 6 doses over 12 days for up to 4 additional cycles to explore safety, tolerability and tumor response to repeat doses of MT-3724 (subject will continue with dose that was tolerated in the Phase 1 portion of the study)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MT-3724</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous dosing M-W-F X 2 weeks; MT-3724 infusion over 2 hours on each dosing day over 4 week initial cycle and then 3 week repeat cycles for up to 5 total cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MT-3724 Phase 1 5 mcg/kg/dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MT-3724</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous dosing M-W-F X 2 weeks; MT-3724 infusion over 2 hours on each dosing day over 4 week initial cycle and then 3 week repeat cycles for up to 5 total cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MT-3724 Phase 1 10 mcg/kg/dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MT-3724</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous dosing M-W-F X 2 weeks; MT-3724 infusion over 2 hours on each dosing day over 4 week initial cycle and then 3 week repeat cycles for up to 5 total cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MT-3724 Phase 1 20 mcg/kg/dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MT-3724</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous dosing M-W-F X 2 weeks; MT-3724 infusion over 2 hours on each dosing day over 4 week initial cycle and then 3 week repeat cycles for up to 5 total cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MT-3724 Phase 1 50 mcg/kg/dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MT-3724</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous dosing M-W-F X 2 weeks; MT-3724 infusion over 2 hours on each dosing day over 4 week initial cycle and then 3 week repeat cycles for up to 5 total cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MT-3724 Phase 1b</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men or women, age 18 years or older

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 3 months

          -  Flow cytometric confirmation of CLL is required at screening. Previous confirmation of
             CLL/SLL including confirmed immunohistological diagnosis with a characteristic
             CD5+/CD20+ B-cell immunophenotype according to WHO criteria

          -  For CLL: a. An absolute peripheral blood monoclonal CD20+/CD5+ B-lymphocyte count &gt;
             5000/μL for the duration of at least 3 months

          -  For SLL: An absolute peripheral blood monoclonal CD20+/CD5+ B-lymphocyte count &lt;
             5000/μL AND Presence of lymphadenopathy and/or splenomegaly, with histopathological
             evaluation of a lymph node biopsy consistent with CLL/SLL.

          -  Staging CLL: Rai Stage III or IV disease, or stage 0-II disease that meets NCIWG
             criteria for active disease requiring therapy; SLL: Intermediate or high risk by Ann
             Arbor Staging with Cotswald Modifications that meets criteria for active disease
             requiring therapy.

          -  Relapsed/ Refractory CLL/SLL that has progressed despite treatment with all approved
             therapies known to provide clinical benefit for their disease and for which the
             potential subject is eligible or the potential subject must have refused any other
             available approved treatment options prior to consideration for enrollment.

          -  Potential subjects must have received at least one anti-CD20 antibody containing
             regimen in the past that resulted in initial measurable response (partial or complete
             remission), followed by relapse/recurrence.

          -  Potential subjects for which high-dose chemotherapy and autologous stem cell
             transplantation (HD-ASCT) is considered a standard curative therapy are eligible for
             this study if the potential subject's disease has relapsed after HD-ASCT, or the
             potential subject is not eligible for HD-ASCT or the potential subject has refused
             HD-ASCT.

          -  Potential subjects who have had HD-ASCT must be at least 26 weeks beyond transplant.

          -  All potential subjects are required to have measurable disease following previous
             therapy for CLL/SLL. Measurable disease, as determined by NCI-WG criteria, following
             standard first-line or salvage therapy; this includes potential subjects with
             progressive disease (PDs), stable disease (SDs), or partial remission (PR) and/or
             Residual disease as determined by measurable disease (i.e., PDs, SDs, or PR) or by MRD
             positivity, determined by flow cytometry of bone marrow and/or peripheral blood (see
             Laboratory Manual) in potential subjects with Complete Response (CR) or CR with
             incomplete bone marrow recovery (CRi) (previously termed &quot;nodular partial remission&quot;
             [(nPR])

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of &lt; 2.

          -  Patients must be at least 28 days past their last course of leukemia or lymphoma
             treatment and have recovered from side effects of such therapy completely or with only
             minor residual symptoms including any significant laboratory. Patients with
             pre-existing severe or life threatening side effects/conditions from prior therapy or
             due to other diseases may not be enrolled

          -  Female patients of childbearing potential must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test within 3 days prior to initiating dosing. Male and female subjects with
             reproductive potential must agree to use acceptable contraceptive methods while on
             study therapy and for 12 week following their last dose of study medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Ongoing use of any approved or investigational anti-neoplastic therapies with the
             exceptions of ongoing hormonal therapy for breast cancer (without evidence of active
             disease) or prostate cancer (stable on hormonal therapy).

          -  History of an absolute anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody (MAb) refractory CLL/SLL, defined
             as a failure to have ever achieved a PR, CR with persistent lymphocytic nodules in the
             marrow (&quot;nPR&quot;), or CR for at least 6 months in response to at least one anti-CD20
             MAb-containing regimen amongst all past CLL/SLL treatments.

          -  Potential subjects cannot have experienced a significant (CTCAE Grade 3 or 4 with or
             without neutropenia) infection within 2 weeks of the first dose of MT-3724.

          -  Patients who cannot comply with protocol requirements including clinic visits for
             intravenous infusions and birth control measures may not be enrolled.

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or are breast feeding.

          -  Patients are not eligible if they are using any other approved or investigational
             anti-neoplastic therapies or any other investigational therapies for any other reason.

          -  Patients may not be receiving systemic corticosteroid therapy at a prednisone dose &gt;
             20 mg/day (or steroid equivalent) within 2 weeks of starting study.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled or severe cardiovascular disease, including myocardial
             infarct or unstable angina within 6 months prior to start of study treatment, New York
             Heart Association (NYHA) Class II or greater congestive heart failure, serious
             arrhythmias requiring medication for treatment, clinically significant pericardial
             disease, or cardiac amyloidosis may not be enrolled.

          -  Patients with a known history of drug abuse or any chronic neurologic, psychiatric,
             endocrine, metabolic, immunologic, hepatic or renal disease (including a history of
             hemolytic uremic syndrome) that in the opinion of the Investigator would adversely
             affect study participation.

          -  Patients with known active Hepatitis C, HIV or a present history of Hepatitis B

          -  Patients must not have received any vaccines for 28 days prior to administration of
             their first dose of MT-3724 and should not receive any vaccine during the study or
             within 28 days after their last dose of MT-3724.

          -  Patients with a suspected allergy or sensitivity to any component of MT-3724 drug
             preparation based upon known allergies to compounds of a similar class who have had an
             anaphylactic or other severe infusion reaction to human immunoglobulin or monoclonal
             antibody administration are not eligible.

          -  Potential subjects who have undergone allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant or
             any solid organ transplant.

          -  Autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplant within 26 weeks prior to study entry;
             any history of allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Valacer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Molecular Templates</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 18, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 22, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 29, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 29, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 2, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CD20</keyword>
  <keyword>immunotoxin</keyword>
  <keyword>CLL</keyword>
  <keyword>SLL</keyword>
  <keyword>leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>lymphocytic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>lymphocytic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>MT-3724</keyword>
  <keyword>relapsed</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>antibodies</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

