<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02555501</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCCF-060264-AM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02555501</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oral Mucositis and Laser Therapy Associated With Photodynamic Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>OMLTPT</acronym>
  <official_title>Laser Therapy Associated With Photodynamic Therapy in the Treatment of Oral Mucositis Induced by Chemotherapy in Young Patients: Randomized Blind Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade Ceuma</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa e Desenvolvimento Científico do Maranhão</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Ceuma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the study was to evaluate the therapeutic action through the diameter of the
      lesion, of low level laser (LLL) associated to photodynamic therapy (PDT) in oral mucositis
      (OM) lesions, in young patients. A randomized clinical trial blinded, split-mouth was
      performed. The study sample consisted of 15 cancer patients (3-16 years old) of Aldenora
      Bello Hospital (São Luís, Maranhão, Brazil). Random allocation by lot of treatments (PDT +
      LLL and LLL) to quadrants of the oral cavity was performed, and the patient was his own
      control. Patients were masked about therapy performed on each side of the arch. The
      evaluation period of both therapeutic regimens was 8 days, and the outcome assessed was the
      lesion size (measured in cm²). Friedman and Wilcoxon tests were applied and the effect
      magnitude calculated. The significance level was 5%. Statistically significant difference was
      observed between the groups for the lesion diameter of the 6th to the 8th day (greater
      regression of lesion size for the PDT + LLL group), which was confirmed by a difference
      magnitude moderated. Based on the findings, it is concluded that PDT + LLL showed greater
      therapeutic effect when compared to LLL in reducing the severity of OM lesions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The blind randomized clinical trial included 18 young patients, between 3 and 16 years old,
      undergoing chemotherapy or chemo/radiological the pediatric ward of Aldenora Bello Hospital
      in São Luís (Maranhão, Brazil). The study was conducted from October/2014 to January/2015. It
      was adopted as inclusion criteria patients between 3 and 18 years old, in the inductive phase
      of chemotherapy, with oral mucositis (OM) and bilateral lesions.

      A mouth split model was conducted, and the patients were their own controls. The entry of the
      patients in the study occurred consecutively. To each patient, the operator/examiner drafted
      an envelope containing treatments to either side, being masked patient about the treatment of
      each side: PDT (photosensitized and low level laser) + low level laser; Low level laser].

      The following parameters were used for the calculation of sample size: 95% confidence level,
      80% statistical power and minimal difference of 0.82 point in the lesions diameter detected
      between paired samples. A &quot;n&quot; sample minimum of 14 was determined for each treatment. In
      order to compensate for possible losses, 18 patients were treated.

      The treatments (PDT and low level laser; Low level laser) were performed in a hospital bed.
      Prior to treatment, the OM lesions were evaluated and a lesion on each side was chosen.
      Lesions should be located at the same site on both sides. The chosen site was the lip mucosa.
      Before the procedure, the patient was instructed as to brushing and not using mouthwashes,
      followed by cleaning of the oral cavity with gauze and distilled water. Two days before the
      laser treatment, the side of the oral cavity chosen for the experimental treatment (PDT and
      low level laser) was pigmented with the photosensitizer (aqueous solution of 0.005% methylene
      blue). A ball of sterile cotton was soaked in the dye solution and placed in the center of
      the lesion. Photosensitizer remained in the place for 5 minutes (pre-irradiation period).
      Then, to activate the dye, the lesion was irradiated with red light (InGaAlP / phosphide and
      Indium, Gallium and potassium) (Flash Laser III, DMC, São Carlos, São Paulo, Brazil), with a
      wavelength of 660 nm, for a period 90 seconds, with a power of 100mW, to 1cm away, according
      to the manufacturer's specifications. The lesion on the opposite side was treated with ball
      of sterile cotton soaked in distilled water and the laser unit placed on the lesion without
      activation of the light. This procedure aimed to mask the patient about the side that
      received the experimental therapy (PDT and low level laser). This masking was possible
      because the experimental solution is insipid, very soluble and thus leaves no residue.

      From the 3rd to the 10th day (total of 8 days) was carried out only laser therapy on both
      sides. Lesions were evaluated until the 8th day. After the 8th day of assessment, the lesions
      were only treated to a complete remission as well as other lesions present in the oral
      cavity. For laser therapy was first used infrared emitter laser unit with active medium
      AsGaAl (Gallium Arsenide and Aluminium), with wavelength of 808nm, for analgesia. Then, the
      investigators used the red emitter, whose active medium was the InGaAlP (phosphide and
      Indium, Gallium and Potassium), with wavelength of 660nm to photobiomodulation. For both
      units emitting laser, the tip of the device was closed against the edges of the lesion,
      perpendicular to the tissue. A irradiation was continuous and the application punctual (10
      seconds). The distance between the points of irradiation was about 1cm. The energy delivered
      was 4J per point of application. The interval between sessions was 24 hours.

      The tip of the laser was disinfected with 70% alcohol solution and wrapped with a plastic
      film. Patients and operators wore glasses for eye protection.

      A questionnaire containing demographic, socioeconomic and type of treatment for cancer was
      applied to parents and children. White blood cell count and platelets (beginning and end of
      the inductive phase of QT) were extracted from medical records.

      The assessed outcome measure was the diameter of the lesion (in cm2). The areas of the
      lesions were measured with a flexible ruler (record made in cm2) by the operator/examiner
      from the start of treatment with exclusive laser therapy (3rd day). This procedure was
      repeated on subsequent days until the 8th day of laser treatment. The measurement of the
      lesions occurred prior to laser therapy applications.

      The Friedman test was used for multiple comparisons within groups (different times of
      treatment). Paired evaluation between each two moments was evaluated using the Wilcoxon test,
      with significance corrected by Bonferroni test (p = 0.0071). The Wilcoxon test was used to
      compare the diameter of the lesion, every day, between the PDT + Low level laser and Low
      level laser groups (dependent samples/split-mouth). It calculated the effect magnitude (d) of
      standardized differences between averages of two groups. The level of significance for
      analysis was 5%.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lesion size</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>Lesion size measured in cm²</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Oral Mucositis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PDT + Low level laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PDT (photosensitizer and low level laser) and low level laser
Photosensitizer: aqueous solution of 0.005% methylene blue; Low level laser: infrared emitter laser unit with active medium AsGaAl (Gallium Arsenide and Aluminium) and red emitter with active medium InGaAlP (phosphide and Indium, Gallium and Potassium)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low level laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low level laser: infrared emitter laser unit with active medium AsGaAl (Gallium Arsenide and Aluminium) and red emitter with active medium InGaAlP (phosphide and Indium, Gallium and Potassium)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PDT + Low level laser</intervention_name>
    <description>Two days before the laser treatment, the side of the oral cavity chosen for the experimental treatment was pigmented with aqueous solution of 0.005% methylene blue. A ball of sterile cotton was soaked in the dye solution and placed in the center of the lesion. Photosensitizer remained in the place for 5 minutes (pre-irradiation period). Then, to activate the dye, the lesion was irradiated with red light (InGaAlP / phosphide and Indium, Gallium and potassium).
From the 3rd to the 10th day was carried out only laser therapy. For laser therapy was first used infrared emitter laser unit with active medium AsGaAl (Gallium Arsenide and Aluminium). Then, we used the red emitter, whose active medium was the InGaAlP (phosphide and Indium, Gallium and Potassium).</description>
    <arm_group_label>PDT + Low level laser</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low level laser</intervention_name>
    <description>Two days before the laser treatment, the lesion of the side of the oral cavity chosen for the control treatment was treated with ball of sterile cotton soaked in distilled water and the laser unit placed on the lesion without activation of the light. From the 3rd to the 10th day was carried out laser therapy. For laser therapy was first used infrared emitter laser unit with active medium AsGaAl (Gallium Arsenide and Aluminium). Then, we used the red emitter, whose active medium was the InGaAlP (phosphide and Indium, Gallium and Potassium).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low level laser</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients between 3 and 18 years old

          -  Patients on chemotherapy inductive phase

          -  Patients with oral mucositis and bilateral lesions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients outside the established age

          -  Patients who are in other phases of chemotherapy

          -  Patients who did not have bilateral lesions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Meire C. Ferreira, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Programa de Mestrado em Odontologia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Aldenora Bello</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Luís</city>
        <state>Maranhão</state>
        <zip>65031-630</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Braga PE, Latorre Md Mdo R, Curado MP. [Childhood cancer: a comparative analysis of incidence, mortality, and survival in Goiania (Brazil) and other countries]. Cad Saude Publica. 2002 Jan-Feb;18(1):33-44. Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>11910422</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Instituto Nacional do Câncer (Brasil). Incidência de Câncer no Brasil: Estimativa 2014/2015. Rio de Janeiro: INCA, 2014.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonan PRF, Lopes MA, Alves FA, Almeida OP. Clinical, biological, histopathological and proposed treatments for oral mucositis induced by radiation therapy: Literature Review. J Oncol 2005; 51:235-42.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sonis ST. Pathobiology of mucositis. Semin Oncol Nurs. 2004 Feb;20(1):11-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15038512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan KK, Oza AM, Siu LL. The statins as anticancer agents. Clin Cancer Res. 2003 Jan;9(1):10-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12538446</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reichart PA, Philipsen HP. Oral Pathology; Trad. John Peter Stein and Maximiano Ferreira Tovo. Porto Alegre: Medical Arts South; 2000.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andrade MC, Ribeiro AP, Dovigo LN, Brunetti IL, Giampaolo ET, Bagnato VS, Pavarina AC. Effect of different pre-irradiation times on curcumin-mediated photodynamic therapy against planktonic cultures and biofilms of Candida spp. Arch Oral Biol. 2013 Feb;58(2):200-10. doi: 10.1016/j.archoralbio.2012.10.011. Epub 2012 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>23153629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee YH, Park HW, Lee JH, Seo HW, Lee SY. The photodynamic therapy on Streptococcus mutans biofilms using erythrosine and dental halogen curing unit. Int J Oral Sci. 2012 Dec;4(4):196-201. doi: 10.1038/ijos.2012.63. Epub 2012 Dec 7.</citation>
    <PMID>23222991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mattiello FD, Coelho AA, Martins OP, Mattiello RD, Ferrão Júnior JP. In vitro effect of photodynamic therapy on aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans and Streptococcus sanguinis. Braz Dent J. 2011;22(5):398-403.</citation>
    <PMID>22011896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miyabe M, Junqueira JC, Costa AC, Jorge AO, Ribeiro MS, Feist IS. Effect of photodynamic therapy on clinical isolates of Staphylococcus spp. Braz Oral Res. 2011 May-Jun;25(3):230-4. Epub 2011 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>21359491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ishiyama K, Nakamura K, Ikai H, Kanno T, Kohno M, Sasaki K, Niwano Y. Bactericidal action of photogenerated singlet oxygen from photosensitizers used in plaque disclosing agents. PLoS One. 2012;7(5):e37871. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0037871. Epub 2012 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>22629466</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corti L, Chiarion-Sileni V, Aversa S, Ponzoni A, D'Arcais R, Pagnutti S, Fiore D, Sotti G. Treatment of chemotherapy-induced oral mucositis with light-emitting diode. Photomed Laser Surg. 2006 Apr;24(2):207-13.</citation>
    <PMID>16706701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sonis ST. Mucosite oral em câncer de cabeça e pescoço: risco, biologia e gestão. Am Soc Clin Oncol Educ Book 2013; 33: 236.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sonis ST, Fazio RC, Fang L. Principles and Practice of Oral Medicine. 2 ed. Rio de Janeiro: Guanabara Koogan; 1996.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown CG, Wingard J. Clinical consequences of oral mucositis. Semin Oncol Nurs. 2004 Feb;20(1):16-21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15038513</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sonis ST. Mucositis as a biological process: a new hypothesis for the development of chemotherapy-induced stomatotoxicity. Oral Oncol. 1998 Jan;34(1):39-43. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9659518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheng KK, Chang AM, Yuen MP. Prevention of oral mucositis in paediatric patients treated with chemotherapy; a randomised crossover trial comparing two protocols of oral care. Eur J Cancer. 2004 May;40(8):1208-16.</citation>
    <PMID>15110885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hejna M, Köstler WJ, Raderer M, Steger GG, Brodowicz T, Scheithauer W, Wiltschke C, Zielinski CC. Decrease of duration and symptoms in chemotherapy-induced oral mucositis by topical GM-CSF: results of a prospective randomised trial. Eur J Cancer. 2001 Nov;37(16):1994-2002.</citation>
    <PMID>11597376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Köstler WJ, Hejna M, Wenzel C, Zielinski CC. Oral mucositis complicating chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy: options for prevention and treatment. CA Cancer J Clin. 2001 Sep-Oct;51(5):290-315.</citation>
    <PMID>11577493</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martens LC. Laser physics and a review of laser applications in dentistry for children. Eur Arch Paediatr Dent. 2011 Apr;12(2):61-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21473835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Costa AC, de Campos Rasteiro VM, Pereira CA, da Silva Hashimoto ES, Beltrame M Jr, Junqueira JC, Jorge AO. Susceptibility of Candida albicans and Candida dubliniensis to erythrosine- and LED-mediated photodynamic therapy. Arch Oral Biol. 2011 Nov;56(11):1299-305. doi: 10.1016/j.archoralbio.2011.05.013. Epub 2011 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21704304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Costa AC, Campos Rasteiro VM, da Silva Hashimoto ES, Araújo CF, Pereira CA, Junqueira JC, Jorge AO. Effect of erythrosine- and LED-mediated photodynamic therapy on buccal candidiasis infection of immunosuppressed mice and Candida albicans adherence to buccal epithelial cells. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol. 2012 Jul;114(1):67-74. doi: 10.1016/j.oooo.2012.02.002. Epub 2012 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>22727094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Albuquerque ILS, Camargo TC. Prevention and Treatment of oral mucositis induced by radiation therapy: Literature Review. J Oncol 2007; 53:195-209.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lino MD, Carvalho FB, Oliveira LR, Magalhães EB, Pinheiro AL, Ramalho LM. Laser phototherapy as a treatment for radiotherapy-induced oral mucositis. Braz Dent J. 2011;22(2):162-5.</citation>
    <PMID>21537592</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Oberoi S, Zamperlini-Netto G, Beyene J, Treister NS, Sung L. Effect of prophylactic low level laser therapy on oral mucositis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS One. 2014 Sep 8;9(9):e107418. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0107418. eCollection 2014. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25198431</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carvalho PA, Jaguar GC, Pellizzon AC, Prado JD, Lopes RN, Alves FA. Evaluation of low-level laser therapy in the prevention and treatment of radiation-induced mucositis: a double-blind randomized study in head and neck cancer patients. Oral Oncol. 2011 Dec;47(12):1176-81. doi: 10.1016/j.oraloncology.2011.08.021. Epub 2011 Sep 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21911312</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Figueiredo AL, Lins L, Cattony AC, Falcão AF. Laser therapy in the control of oral mucositis: a meta-analysis. Rev Assoc Med Bras (1992). 2013 Sep-Oct;59(5):467-74. doi: 10.1016/j.ramb.2013.08.003. Epub 2013 Oct 10. Review. English, Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>24119379</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kharkwal GB, Sharma SK, Huang YY, Dai T, Hamblin MR. Photodynamic therapy for infections: clinical applications. Lasers Surg Med. 2011 Sep;43(7):755-67. doi: 10.1002/lsm.21080. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22057503</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cieplik F, Tabenski L, Buchalla W, Maisch T. Antimicrobial photodynamic therapy for inactivation of biofilms formed by oral key pathogens. Front Microbiol. 2014 Aug 12;5:405. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2014.00405. eCollection 2014. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25161649</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Abramoff MM, Lopes NN, Lopes LA, Dib LL, Guilherme A, Caran EM, Barreto AD, Lee ML, Petrilli AS. Low-level laser therapy in the prevention and treatment of chemotherapy-induced oral mucositis in young patients. Photomed Laser Surg. 2008 Aug;26(4):393-400. doi: 10.1089/pho.2007.2144.</citation>
    <PMID>18754720</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kuhn A, Porto FA, Miraglia P, Brunetto AL. Low-level infrared laser therapy in chemotherapy-induced oral mucositis: a randomized placebo-controlled trial in children. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2009 Jan;31(1):33-7. doi: 10.1097/MPH.0b013e318192cb8e.</citation>
    <PMID>19125084</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bensadoun RJ, Franquin JC, Ciais G, Darcourt V, Schubert MM, Viot M, Dejou J, Tardieu C, Benezery K, Nguyen TD, Laudoyer Y, Dassonville O, Poissonnet G, Vallicioni J, Thyss A, Hamdi M, Chauvel P, Demard F. Low-energy He/Ne laser in the prevention of radiation-induced mucositis. A multicenter phase III randomized study in patients with head and neck cancer. Support Care Cancer. 1999 Jul;7(4):244-52.</citation>
    <PMID>10423050</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sandoval RL, Koga DH, Buloto LS, Suzuki R, Dib LL. Management of chemo- and radiotherapy induced oral mucositis with low-energy laser: initial results of A.C. Camargo Hospital. J Appl Oral Sci. 2003 Dec;11(4):337-41.</citation>
    <PMID>21394411</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ferreira MVL, Sousa GR, Silveira LB, Amorim JCF. Aplicações da PDT - Terapia Fotodinâmica - na Clínica Odontológica. DMC Journal 2010; 6: 40-4.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cauwels RG, Martens LC. Low level laser therapy in oral mucositis: a pilot study. Eur Arch Paediatr Dent. 2011 Apr;12(2):118-23.</citation>
    <PMID>21473845</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cruz LB, Ribeiro AS, Rech A, Rosa LG, Castro CG Jr, Brunetto AL. Influence of low-energy laser in the prevention of oral mucositis in children with cancer receiving chemotherapy. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2007 Apr;48(4):435-40.</citation>
    <PMID>16862549</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Figueiredo ALP, Lins L, Cattony AC, Falcão AFP. Laser terapia no controle da mucosite oral: um estudo de metanálise. Rev Assoc Med Bras. 2013;5 9(5):467-74.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 18, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 18, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 18, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Ceuma</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Meire Coelho Ferreira</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Matheus Coelho Bandeca</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stomatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>clinical trial</keyword>
  <keyword>laser therapy, low-level</keyword>
  <keyword>methylene blue</keyword>
  <keyword>photochemotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mucositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methylene Blue</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Photosensitizing Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

