<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02556710</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AP-003-B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02556710</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AP-003-B Study to Evaluate the Efficacy And Safety Of An Intra-Articular Injection Of Ampion™ In Adults With Pain With Osteoarthritis Of The Knee</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind Study to Evaluated the Efficacy and Safety of an Intra-Articular Injection of AMPION™ in Adults With Pain Due to Osteoarthritis of the Knee</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ampio Pharmaceuticals. Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ampio Pharmaceuticals. Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the efficacy and safety of an intra-articular injection of AMPION™
      in adults with pain due to osteoarthritis of the knee
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind Study To Evaluate The Efficacy And Safety Of
      An Intra-Articular Injection Of AMPION™ In Adults With Pain Due to Osteoarthritis Of The Knee

      The primary trial objective is to evaluate the efficacy of 4 mL of AMPION™ versus 4 mL
      placebo intra-articular (IA) injection in improving knee pain, when administered to subjects
      suffering from OA of the knee.

      The secondary trial objective is evaluation of the safety of an intra-articular injection of
      AMPION™.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>WOMAC osteoarthritis index 3.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The primary trial objective is to evaluate the efficacy of 4 mL Ampion™ versus 4 mL placebo intra-articular (IA) injection in improving knee pain, when administered to subjects suffering from OA of the knee. Efficacy will be evaluated using the 5-Likert scale to assess change in WOMAC A from Baseline to Week 12.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety. Safety data will be evaluated by changes in vital sign measurements and the frequency and severity of AEs. Concomitant medication will be recorded for safety.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary trial objective is evaluation of the safety of an intra-articular injection of Ampion.™ Safety data will be evaluated by changes in vital sign measurements and the frequency and severity of AEs. Concomitant medication will be recorded for safety. Safety will be assess by the Safety Monitoring Committee throughout the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">480</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis of the Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4 mL AMPION™</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>AMPION™, 4 mL, single intra-articular injection. Ampion is the ultrafiltrate of 5% HSA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4 mL Saline Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Saline placebo, 4 mL, single intra-articular injection. Saline used as the comparator is 0.9% Sodium Chloride.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMPION™</intervention_name>
    <description>4 mL Ampion Injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>4 mL AMPION™</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>4 mL Saline Injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>4 mL Saline Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Able to provide written informed consent to participate in the study;

          -  Willing and able to comply with all study requirements and instructions of the site
             study staff;

          -  Male or female, 40 years to 85 years old (inclusive);

          -  Must be ambulatory;

          -  Index knee must be symptomatic for greater than 6 months with a clinical diagnosis of
             OA and supported by radiological evidence (Kellgren Lawrence Grade II to IV) read by a
             central reader;

          -  WOMAC 5-point Likert pain subscale &lt;1.5 in the contralateral knee;

          -  Moderate to moderately-severe OA pain in the index knee (rating of at least 1.5 on the
             WOMAC Index 3.1 5-point Likert Pain Subscale);

          -  Moderate to moderately-severe OA pain in the index knee (even if chronic doses of
             nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID), which have not changed in the 4 weeks
             prior to screening, have been/are being used);

          -  Ability to discontinue NSAID use at Screening visit and/or 72 hours prior to the
             Baseline visit and for the duration of the clinical study (low dose Aspirin is allowed
             during the study);

          -  No analgesia (including acetaminophen [paracetamol]) taken 24 hours prior to an
             efficacy measure;

          -  No known clinically significant liver abnormality (e.g. cirrhosis, transplant, etc.).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  As a result of medical review and screening investigation, the Principal Investigator
             considers the patient unfit for the study

          -  A history of allergic reactions to human albumin (reaction to non-human albumin such
             as egg albumin is not an exclusion criterion)

          -  A history of allergic reactions to excipients in 5% human albumin (N-acetyltryptophan,
             sodium caprylate)

          -  Presence of tense effusions

          -  Inflammatory or crystal arthropathies, acute fractures, history of aseptic necrosis or
             joint replacement in the affected knee, as assessed locally by the Principal
             Investigator

          -  Isolated patella femoral syndrome, also known as chondromalacia

          -  Any other disease or condition interfering with the free use and evaluation of the
             index knee for the duration of the trial (e.g. cancer, congenital defects, spine
             osteoarthritis)

          -  Major injury to the index knee within the 12 months prior to screening

          -  Severe hip osteoarthritis ipsilateral to the index knee

          -  Any pain that could interfere with the assessment of index knee pain (e.g. pain in any
             other part of the lower extremities, pain radiating to the knee)

          -  Any pharmacological or non-pharmacological treatment targeting OA started or changed
             during the 4 weeks prior to randomization or likely to be changed during the duration
             of the study

          -  Pregnancy or planning to become pregnant during the study.

          -  Use of the following medications:

          -  No IA injected pain medications in the study knee during the study

          -  No analgesics containing opioids.

          -  NSAIDs are not permitted during the study; acetaminophen is available as a rescue
             medication during the study from the provided supply.

          -  No topical treatment on osteoarthritis index knee during the study

          -  No significant anticoagulant therapy (e.g. Heparin or Lovenox) during the study
             (treatment such as low dose Aspirin and Plavix are allowed)

          -  No systemic treatments that may interfere with safety or efficacy assessments during
             the study

          -  No immunosuppressants

          -  No use of corticosteroids

          -  No human albumin treatment in the 3 months before randomization or throughout the
             duration of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Bar-Or, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ampio Pharmaceuticals. Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ampio Pharmaceuticals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Englewood</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 18, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 21, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 22, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 27, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 27, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis of the Knee</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

