<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02559739</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>014/15</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>320030_149752</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02559739</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sleep Deficiency and Stroke Outcome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sleep Deficiency and Sleep Fragmentation and Their Impact on the Short- and Long-term Outcome of Ischemic Stroke and Transient Ischemic Attacks - a Two-center Prospective Observational Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Neurocenter of Southern Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swiss Heart Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Deficient sleep duration and sleep disturbances - such as insomnia, sleep disordered
      breathing (SDB) and restless legs syndrome (RLS)- are associated with hypertension and
      cardio-cerebrovascular morbidity and mortality. Several studies suggest that sleep disorders
      are frequent after stroke and detrimental for stroke outcome. However, more prospective
      studies in a large unselected sample of stroke survivors are needed to better investigate the
      short- and long-term consequences of sleep disturbances on mortality and occurrence of new
      cardio-cerebrovascular events. Also their pathophysiological mechanisms and their influence
      on stroke recovery should be better understood.

      Therefore, the aim of this study is to assess the impact of sleep deficiency and sleep
      fragmentation on the frequency of new cerebro- and cardiovascular events and death after
      stroke or transient ischemic attacks, and clinical outcome within one and two years after
      stroke.

      The working hypotheses are that stroke survivors with sleep deficiency and sleep
      fragmentation due to insomnia, sleep-disordered breathing or restless leg syndrome will
      present: (1) higher mortality from all causes and higher frequency of new cardio-/
      cerebrovascular events; and (2) a less favorable clinical outcome. Outcomes will be compared
      between patients with and without sleep deficiency and fragmentation.

      Since current clinical practice in cerebrovascular patients does not sufficiently consider
      sleep disorders in patient's management, this study can help to bring attention to a still
      overlooked medical problem and change the current standard of management of stroke survivors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background

      Experimental and clinical data suggest a detrimental effect of sleep deficiency/sleep
      fragmentation on stroke outcome. In rodents, sleep fragmentation and sleep deprivation
      induced in the acute phase of stroke enhance the extension of the lesion and impair
      functional recovery - inversely, sleep-promoting drugs have a positive effect on functional
      recovery. In humans, a negative effect of sleep deficiency and sleep fragmentation due to
      sleep-disordered breathing (SDB), restless legs syndrome (RLS) and insomnia on stroke outcome
      has also been suggested but only insufficiently tested.

      SDB is found in 50-70% of patients with transient ischemic attacks and acute ischemic stroke.
      Patients with SDB demonstrate a more rapid progression of stroke severity as well as higher
      blood pressure and longer hospitalization in the acute phase of stroke. Over time, they also
      exhibit a higher mortality. Functional outcome is also negatively affected by the presence of
      SDB. Moreover, SDB was shown to represent an independent risk for hypertension and
      cardiovascular morbidity and mortality, and for stroke.

      The frequency of insomnia in patients with stroke in a prospective study achieved 68% in the
      acute phase decreasing to 49% after 18 months. However, systematic large scale observational
      studies on the frequency of insomnia in stroke patients are lacking. Sleep duration after
      stroke has been assessed in few studies only (e.g. in patients with paramedian thalamic
      stroke), in some of them a good correlation with actigraphic measurements was found.
      Moreover, over the last three decades a link was found between sleep deficiency and
      fragmentation and cardiocerebrovascular morbidity and mortality based on epidemiological
      data. In particular, short sleepers (e.g. sleep duration &lt; 6 hours) and poor sleepers
      (reporting a non-restorative sleep) presented a higher risk of cardiovascular events
      including death, coronary heart disease and stroke. Insomnia and sleep duration in the
      general population were also reported to predispose to an increased risk of hypertension,
      cardiovascular events and mortality.

      A high association between RLS and stroke was demonstrated in a few studies. RLS was found in
      12% of 137 patients after stroke and predicted a worse outcome. Few case reports reported
      high numbers of periodic limb movements during sleep (PLMS), which are often associated with
      RLS, in stroke patients. An association of RLS/PLMS with hypertension, cardiovascular
      diseases and stroke was also discussed in recent years. However, the large scale data on the
      impact of RLS for the stroke outcomes are lacking.

      The possible mechanisms linking sleep deficiency, poor sleep and sleep fragmentation with
      cardiovascular disorders (including stroke) are multiple and include an elevated sympathetic
      activation, procoagulatory and inflammatory changes, increased atherosclerosis, and changes
      in cerebral hemodynamics and oxygenation. However, the clinical relevance and the association
      with clinical outcomes needs further investigation.

      Objective

      The aim of this study is to assess the impact of sleep deficiency and sleep fragmentation
      resulting from insomnia, SDB or RLS on the frequency of new cerebro- and cardiovascular
      events after stroke or TIA including death of any cause, and clinical outcome within one and
      two years after stroke.

      Primary objective of the study is the assessment of the frequency of all-cause deaths and new
      cerebro- and cardiovascular events within 24 months after stroke or transient ischemic attack
      in patients with and without sleep deficiency/fragmentation.

      The main secondary objective is an assessment of clinical outcome 12 months after stroke in
      patients with and without sleep deficiency/fragmentation.

      Methods

      Patients with acute ischemic stroke or TIA will be recruited at two Neurology Departments in
      Switzerland (Inselspital Bern &amp; Neurocenter of Southern Switzerland Lugano). Two groups will
      be formed based on the presence or absence of sleep deficiency/fragmentation assessed at one
      month following stroke by questionnaires and telephone interviews. Examinations (at baseline
      &amp; 3, 12 and 24 months follow up after stroke) will include standardized and validated
      questionnaires assessing stroke outcome (independence and activities of daily living) as well
      as insomnia, RLS, risk for sleep apnea, depression and apathy. Additional non-invasive
      physiological assessments will be performed in about every fifth of all recruited patients in
      the acute phase of stroke and after 3 and 12 months. They include ambulatory blood pressure
      measurements and wrist activity assessing 24h physical activity patterns over 3 weeks,
      assessment of arterial stiffness/endothelial function and basic cognitive performance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A composite of death from any cause, stroke, transient ischemic attack, myocardial infarction, unplanned hospitalization (or unplanned prolongation of hospitalization) for heart failure or leading to urgent revascularization within 24 months</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome after stroke, as assessed by modified Rankin scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome after stroke, as assessed by Barthel index</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome after stroke, as assessed by Quality of Life Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A composite of death from any cause, stroke, transient ischemic attack, myocardial infarction, unplanned hospitalization (or unplanned prolongation of hospitalization) for heart failure or leading to urgent revascularization)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 12 months and 2 to 4 years after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of new-onset sleep deficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 12 and 24 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of insomnia</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 12 and 24 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of RLS</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 12 and 24 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk for sleep-disordered breathing</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 12 and 24 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial stiffness (assessed in 1/5 of all patients)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 and 12 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endothelial function (assessed in 1/5 of all patients)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 and 12 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure values (variability and absolute values, assessed in 1/5 of all patients 3 times a day over 3 weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 and 12 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3-week wrist-actigraphy parameters (including inactivity and activity indices) (assessed in 1/5 of all patients)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 and 12 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Basic cognitive performance (Montreal Cognitive Assessment) (assessed in 1/5 of all patients)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 and 12 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Course of SDB frequency measured by an objective respirography (assessed in 1/5 of all patients)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 and 12 months after stroke</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">520</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Insomnia</condition>
  <condition>Restless Legs Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sleep deficiency/fragmentation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with sleep deficiency/fragmentation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No sleep deficiency/fragmentation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients without sleep deficiency/fragmentation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients suffering from ischemic stroke or transient ischemic attack (TIA) will be
        recruited at the Stroke Unit and the ward of the Department of Neurology, Inselspital Bern,
        and the Stroke Unit and ward of the Neurocenter of Southern Switzerland, Lugano, and
        followed-up for (at least) 2 (maximum 4) years. They will be evaluated for pre-existing and
        new-onset sleep disturbances that result in sleep deficiency (&lt; 6h sleep /night and/or
        post-stroke reduction of average sleep time/night ≥ 2h) or sleep fragmentation (insomnia,
        sleep-disordered breathing, restless legs syndrome).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients' informed consent as documented by signature.

          -  Hospitalization either at the Stroke Unit and ward of the Department of Neurology,
             Inselspital Bern or at the Stroke Unit and ward of the Neurocenter of Southern
             Switzerland (Lugano)

          -  Age: 18-85

          -  Transient ischemic attack or ischemic stroke of any localization

          -  Symptom onset until study inclusion ≤ 7 days

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Primary hemorrhagic stroke

          -  Coma/Stupor

          -  Clinical unstable or life threatening condition (severe heart failure,
             oxygen-dependent pulmonary disease or severe pulmonary complications, severe renal or
             liver insufficiency)

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Inability of the participant to give informed consent (e.g. patients under tutelage)
             or to follow the procedures of the study due to psychological or medical conditions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claudio L Bassetti, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chairman and Head, Department of Neurology Inselspital, Bern University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mauro Manconi, Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Head of Sleep and Epilepsy Center, Neurocenter of Southern Switzerland, Lugano</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Claudio L Bassetti, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <phone>+41 (0)31 632 30 66</phone>
    <email>claudio.bassetti@insel.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Frédéric Zubler, Dr. med.</last_name>
    <phone>+41 (0)31 632 30 54</phone>
    <email>frederic.zubler@insel.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Neurology Inselspital, Bern University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <state>Canton Bern</state>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claudio L Bassetti, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <phone>+41 (0)31 632 30 66</phone>
      <email>claudio.bassetti@insel.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Simone Duss, Dr. med.</last_name>
      <phone>+41 (0)31 632 30 54</phone>
      <email>simone.duss@insel.ch</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Horvath, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sebastian Ott, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sleep and Epilepsy Center, Neurocenter of Southern Switzerland, Civic Hospital of Lugano</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lugano</city>
        <zip>6900</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hodor A, Palchykova S, Gao B, Bassetti CL. Baclofen and gamma-hydroxybutyrate differentially altered behavior, EEG activity and sleep in rats. Neuroscience. 2015 Jan 22;284:18-28. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2014.08.061. Epub 2014 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25301745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poryazova R, Huber R, Khatami R, Werth E, Brugger P, Barath K, Baumann CR, Bassetti CL. Topographic sleep EEG changes in the acute and chronic stage of hemispheric stroke. J Sleep Res. 2015 Feb;24(1):54-65. doi: 10.1111/jsr.12208. Epub 2014 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>25159577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cereda CW, Petrini L, Azzola A, Ciccone A, Fischer U, Gallino A, Györik S, Gugger M, Mattis J, Lavie L, Limoni C, Nobili L, Manconi M, Ott S, Pons M, Bassetti CL. Sleep-disordered breathing in acute ischemic stroke and transient ischemic attack: effects on short- and long-term outcome and efficacy of treatment with continuous positive airways pressure--rationale and design of the SAS CARE study. Int J Stroke. 2012 Oct;7(7):597-603. doi: 10.1111/j.1747-4949.2012.00836.x. Epub 2012 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22812731</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siccoli MM, Valko PO, Hermann DM, Bassetti CL. Central periodic breathing during sleep in 74 patients with acute ischemic stroke - neurogenic and cardiogenic factors. J Neurol. 2008 Nov;255(11):1687-92. doi: 10.1007/s00415-008-0981-9. Epub 2008 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>19009334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hermann DM, Siccoli M, Kirov P, Gugger M, Bassetti CL. Central periodic breathing during sleep in acute ischemic stroke. Stroke. 2007 Mar;38(3):1082-4. Epub 2007 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>17255543</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Ischemic Attack, Transient</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Insomnia</keyword>
  <keyword>Restless Legs Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep Deprivation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychomotor Agitation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Restless Legs Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

