<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03200301</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Jubilee MMCRI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03200301</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Intact Umbilical Cord Milking on Neonatal and First Year Neurodevelopmental Outcomes in Very Preterm Infants.</brief_title>
  <acronym>Cord Milking</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of Intact Umbilical Cord Milking Versus Immediate Cord Clamping on Neonatal Outcomes and First Year Neurodevelopmental Outcomes in Very Preterm Infants - A Randomised Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jubilee Mission Medical College and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jubilee Mission Medical College and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesise that intact umbilical cord milking (I-UCM) will reduce neonatal
      morbidity and improve long term neurodevelopmental outcome in very preterm infants. All
      babies born less than 32 weeks gestation, meeting the inclusion criteria will be randomly
      assigned to either I-UCM or immediate cord clamping (ICC) and their short and long term
      outcome measures analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Optimizing placental transfusion at birth promotes a more physiologic transition from
      intrauterine to extrauterine life. There is increasing evidence about the benefits of
      enhanced placental transfusion in improving neonatal outcomes, such as higher hemoglobin
      concentration, improved hemodynamic stability, reduced incidence of intraventricular
      hemorrhage, less need for blood transfusions and better neurodevelopmental outcome in preterm
      infants.

      The investigators propose to evaluate the the safety and effectiveness of I-UCM versus ICC in
      mothers undergoing preterm delivery before 32 weeks, by randomly assigning them to one of two
      groups - study and control. The study group will undergo I-UCM during delivery and the
      control group will have ICC, which is the current standard of care. Both groups will
      subsequently receive routine care for mother and infant. In the study group the infants will
      be placed at or ∼20 cm below the level of the placenta and about 20 cm of the intact
      umbilical cord will be milked towards the umbilicus three times. The technique consists of
      pinching the cord close to the placenta and milking about 20 cm segment of the cord proximal
      to the umbilicus, towards the infant over a 2-second duration. The cord will then be released
      and allowed to refill with blood for a brief 2-second pause between each milking motion.
      After completion of milking three times, the cord will be clamped close to the umbilicus and
      the neonate handed over to the neonatal team. The procedure of cord milking will be completed
      within 20 seconds.

      Prenatal and delivery data will be collected from the mother's charts. Infant data will be
      collected from hospital admission records and from follow up for a period up to 12 months of
      corrected age. The infant data collected will include hemoglobin levels at birth, incidence
      and severity of intraventricular hemorrhage in the first week of life and neonatal morbidity
      (resuscitation measures, peak bilirubin, need for phototherapy and blood transfusion, sepsis,
      necrotizing enterocolitis, retinopathy of prematurity and chronic lung disease) and
      mortality. The neurodevelopmental status of both the study and control group of infants will
      be assessed at 6 months and one year of corrected age. The investigators hypothesize that
      I-UCM provides a greater placental transfusion and better neonatal outcomes when compared to
      ICC. It is a simple procedure which can be practiced universally and of great relevance to
      both developed and developing countries.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Haemoglobin levels at birth</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Haemoglobin levels at birth</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraventricular Haemorrhage</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days of life</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence and severity of Intraventricular Haemorrhage in the first week of life - Cranial Ultrasound done on day 7</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The resuscitation interventions required with and without umbilical cord milking.</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes after delivery</time_frame>
    <description>The resuscitation interventions required that will be assessed are requirement of Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP), oxygen, mask and bag ventilation, endotracheal intubation and ventilation, chest compressions, drugs, and fluid boluses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resuscitation outcomes with and without umbilical cord milking.</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes after delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Short term outcomes of resuscitation will be assessed using the validated Combined Apgar score (consisting of the Expanded and Specified Apgar scoring systems) introduced by Rudiger et al, in depressed neonates with and without UCM.
Ref:Dalili H, Nili F, Sheikh M, Hardani AK, Shariat M, Nayeri F (2015) Comparison of the Four Proposed Apgar Scoring Systems in the Assessment of Birth Asphyxia and Adverse Early Neurologic Outcomes. PLoS ONE 10(3): e0122116</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of hypotension</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours of life</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of hypotension</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Requirement of inotropic support</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours of life</time_frame>
    <description>Number of inotropes required for support</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>symptomatic polycythemia</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours of life</time_frame>
    <description>The number of neonates with symptomatic polycythemia (defined as lethargy, plethora, jitteriness, tachycardia, tachypnea and with venous hematocrit &gt; 65%).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sepsis (culture positive)</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours of life</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of Sepsis (culture positive)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak bilirubin levels</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours of life</time_frame>
    <description>Serum peak bilirubin levels</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Requirement of phototherapy or exchange transfusion</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours of life</time_frame>
    <description>Neonates requiring phototherapy or exchange transfusion will be evaluated according to the NICE guidelines and serum bilirubin levels will be interpreted according to the baby's age in hours. Physicians who assess the neonate and advice phototherapy or exchange transfusion will be blinded to the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Necrotising Enterocolitis (NEC)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days of life</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of Necrotising Enterocolitis as defined by modified Bell's Criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Requirement of Oxygen</measure>
    <time_frame>36 weeks of gestational age</time_frame>
    <description>Requirement of Oxygen at 28 days of life and at 36 weeks gestation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Requirement of red blood cell transfusions</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks of life</time_frame>
    <description>Requirement of red blood cell transfusions before discharge</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days of Hospital Stay after Birth</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks of life</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days of Hospital Stay after Birth</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death prior to discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks of life</time_frame>
    <description>Death prior to discharge</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum iron stores</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months of age</time_frame>
    <description>Serum iron stores (ferritin levels) at 6 weeks and 6 months of age</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Developmental Assessment Scales for Indian Infants (DASII)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year of corrected age</time_frame>
    <description>Developmental Assessment Scales for Indian Infants (DASII) tests carried out at 6 months and 1 year of corrected age. The DASII scale is divided into motor scale and mental scale. The motor scale consists of 67 items and mental scale consists of 163 items. (P Phatak, et al, 1996)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Preterm Infant</condition>
  <condition>Umbilical Cord Milking</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intact Umbilical Cord Milking</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Umbilical Cord Milking involves pinching of the cord close to the placenta and milking about 20 cm segment of the cord proximal to the umbilicus, towards the infant over a 2-second duration. The cord will be then released, allowing for a brief 2-second pause between each milking motion. This will be repeated for a total of 3 times over a duration less than 20 seconds.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early Cord Clamping</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Umbilical cord will be clamped immediately after delivery and baby will be handed over to the neonatal team.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intact Umbilical Cord Milking</intervention_name>
    <description>Immediately after delivery, the infant will be placed at or ∼20 cm below the level of the placenta and about 20 cm of the intact umbilical cord will be milked towards the umbilicus three times. The technique consists of pinching the cord close to the placenta and milking about 20 cm segment of the cord proximal to the umbilicus, towards the infant over a 2-second duration. The cord will then be released and allowed to refill with blood for a brief 2-second pause between each milking motion. After completion of milking three times, the cord will be clamped close to the umbilicus and the neonate handed over to the neonatal team. The procedure of cord milking will be completed within 20 seconds.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intact Umbilical Cord Milking</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Milking of the Umbilical Cord</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All the preterm infants of less than 32 weeks of gestation born of consenting parents
             in the hospital

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Neonates depressed at birth, MCMA, MCDA Twin pregnancy (DCDA twins are included),
             Severe IUGR in antenatal scans (&lt; 10th Centile), Known case of Hydrops fetalis, Known
             major congenital anomaly, Placenta previa and abruptions, bleeding, accreta, nuchal
             cord, anhydramnios, PROM &gt; 2 weeks before 24 weeks and Refusal to Consent by the
             Parents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Minutes</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Manoj Varanattu, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+919388407588</phone>
    <email>manojvaranattu@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Varghese PR, Ph D</last_name>
    <phone>+919349151985</phone>
    <email>drprvarghese@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Wassia H, Shah PS. Efficacy and safety of umbilical cord milking at birth: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA Pediatr. 2015 Jan;169(1):18-25. doi: 10.1001/jamapediatrics.2014.1906. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25365246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boere I, Roest AA, Wallace E, Ten Harkel AD, Haak MC, Morley CJ, Hooper SB, te Pas AB. Umbilical blood flow patterns directly after birth before delayed cord clamping. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2015 Mar;100(2):F121-5. doi: 10.1136/archdischild-2014-307144. Epub 2014 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25389141</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katheria AC, Brown MK, Rich W, Arnell K. Providing a Placental Transfusion in Newborns Who Need Resuscitation. Front Pediatr. 2017 Jan 25;5:1. doi: 10.3389/fped.2017.00001. eCollection 2017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28180126</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katheria AC, Truong G, Cousins L, Oshiro B, Finer NN. Umbilical Cord Milking Versus Delayed Cord Clamping in Preterm Infants. Pediatrics. 2015 Jul;136(1):61-9. doi: 10.1542/peds.2015-0368.</citation>
    <PMID>26122803</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rabe H, Sawyer A, Amess P, Ayers S; Brighton Perinatal Study Group. Neurodevelopmental Outcomes at 2 and 3.5 Years for Very Preterm Babies Enrolled in a Randomized Trial of Milking the Umbilical Cord versus Delayed Cord Clamping. Neonatology. 2016;109(2):113-9. doi: 10.1159/000441891. Epub 2015 Dec 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26650133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ghavam S, Batra D, Mercer J, Kugelman A, Hosono S, Oh W, Rabe H, Kirpalani H. Effects of placental transfusion in extremely low birthweight infants: meta-analysis of long- and short-term outcomes. Transfusion. 2014 Apr;54(4):1192-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24843886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niermeyer S. A physiologic approach to cord clamping: Clinical issues. Matern Health Neonatol Perinatol. 2015 Sep 8;1:21. doi: 10.1186/s40748-015-0022-5. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27057338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nolan JP, Hazinski MF, Aickin R, Bhanji F, Billi JE, Callaway CW, Castren M, de Caen AR, Ferrer JM, Finn JC, Gent LM, Griffin RE, Iverson S, Lang E, Lim SH, Maconochie IK, Montgomery WH, Morley PT, Nadkarni VM, Neumar RW, Nikolaou NI, Perkins GD, Perlman JM, Singletary EM, Soar J, Travers AH, Welsford M, Wyllie J, Zideman DA. Part 1: Executive summary: 2015 International Consensus on Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care Science with Treatment Recommendations. Resuscitation. 2015 Oct;95:e1-31. doi: 10.1016/j.resuscitation.2015.07.039. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26477703</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rabe H, Diaz-Rossello JL, Duley L, Dowswell T. Effect of timing of umbilical cord clamping and other strategies to influence placental transfusion at preterm birth on maternal and infant outcomes. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Aug 15;(8):CD003248. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD003248.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22895933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Safarulla A. A review of benefits of cord milking over delayed cord clamping in the preterm infant and future directions of research. J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med. 2017 Dec;30(24):2966-2973. doi: 10.1080/14767058.2016.1269319. Epub 2017 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>27936996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Committee on Obstetric Practice, American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists. Committee Opinion No.543: Timing of umbilical cord clamping after birth. Obstet Gynecol. 2012 Dec;120(6):1522-6. doi: 10.1097/01.AOG.0000423817.47165.48.</citation>
    <PMID>23168790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wyckoff MH, Aziz K, Escobedo MB, Kapadia VS, Kattwinkel J, Perlman JM, Simon WM, Weiner GM, Zaichkin JG. Part 13: Neonatal Resuscitation: 2015 American Heart Association Guidelines Update for Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation and Emergency Cardiovascular Care. Circulation. 2015 Nov 3;132(18 Suppl 2):S543-60. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000267. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26473001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

