<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03203551</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FORP/USP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03203551</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical and Laboratorial Evaluation of the Desinfection Solutions in Candida Species From Total Prostheses and Palate of Total Edentulous.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical and Laboratorial Evaluation of the Effect of Sodium Hypochlorite, Chloramine T and Ricinus Communis Solutions in Candida Species Identified in the Biofilm of Total Prostheses and Palate of Total Edentulous Individuals.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This clinical study identified the Candida species from the palate and complete dentures of
      edentulous individuals with prostheses-related stomatitis (PRS) and evaluated the effect of
      disinfectant solutions for denture hygiene on Candida spp. Sixty participants were randomly
      assigned in 04 parallel groups (n = 15); They were oriented to brush their prostheses and the
      palate 3 times a day and immerse them in saline solution (C-control), 0.25% Sodium
      hypochlorite (HS0.25%), 10% Ricinus communis (RC10%) or 0.5% Chloramine T (CT 0.5%) for 20
      minutes. Biofilm samples were collected from the prostheses and palate in the baseline, after
      7 and 37 days of use of the solutions and seeded in CHROMagar Candida medium. After
      incubation period, the presumptive identification, incidence verification and quantification
      of Candida species growth (CFU count) were performed. To quantify biofilm with software
      ImageTool 3.0, the inner surface was disclosed (1% neutral red) and photographed at the end
      of each period. The Candidiasis remission was assessed by scores before and after the use of
      solutions by palate's phographs. Descriptive analyzes were used for the identification and
      incidence of Candida spp. Kruskal-Wallis and Friedman tests, with stepwise step-down
      post-test for cell growth; ANOVA and Tukey for biofilm removal; Frequency of scores for
      evolution of inflammation. Level of significance was 95%. The most incident species were C.
      albicans, followed by C. tropicalis, C. glabrata and C. krusei. HS 0.25% reduced the
      incidence of the three species on the prostheses and palate in the periods of 7 and 37 days;
      CT 0.5% promoted reduction of Candida spp. only in dentures. R. communis decreased the
      incidence of C. tropicalis in both collection sites. For CFU counts, HS 0.25% and CT 0.5%
      caused significant reduction. For biofilm removal, HS0.25% was the most effective (9.75 ±
      12.6) and RC10% (15.92 ± 14.8) intermediate. All groups decreased protheses-related
      stomatitis. HS0.25% has potential for clinical use as total denture disinfectants. RC10% and
      CT0.5% require further studies to be indicated as alternative solutions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 1, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical evaluation of the Candida species identified in the biofilm of total prostheses and palate of total edentulous individuals.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (without disinfection procedures)</time_frame>
    <description>Biofilm samples were collected from the prosthesis and palate in the baseline and seeded in CHROMagar Candida medium. After incubation period, the presumptive identification, incidence verification and quantification of Candida species growth (CFU count) were performed. The inner surface of the denture was disclosed (1% neutral red) and photographed at the end to quantify the biofilm with the software ImageTool 3.0. The palate with Candidiasis was photographed and assessed by scores.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical evaluation of the effect of Sodium hypochlorite, Chloramine T and Ricinus communis solutions after 7 days of use in Candida species identified in the biofilm of total prostheses and palate of total edentulous individuals.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days of disinfection</time_frame>
    <description>Biofilm samples were collected from the prostheses and palate after 7 days of use of the solutions and seeded in CHROMagar Candida medium. After incubation period, the presumptive identification, incidence verification and quantification of Candida species growth (CFU count) were performed. To quantify the denture biofilm with software ImageTool 3.0, the inner surface of the denture was disclosed (1% neutral red) and photographed at the end of 7 days. The Candidiasis remission was photographed and assessed by scores after 7 days of use solutions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical evaluation of the effect of Sodium hypochlorite, Chloramine T and Ricinus communis solutions after 37 days of use in Candida species identified in the biofilm of total prostheses and palate of total edentulous individuals.</measure>
    <time_frame>37 days of disinfection</time_frame>
    <description>Biofilm samples were collected from the prostheses and palate after 37 days of use of the solutions and seeded in CHROMagar Candida medium. After incubation period, the presumptive identification, incidence verification and quantification of Candida species growth (CFU count) were performed. To quantify the denture biofilm with software ImageTool 3.0, the inner surface of the denture was disclosed (1% neutral red) and photographed at the end of 37 days. The Candidiasis remission was photographed and assessed by scores after 37 days of use solutions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">108</enrollment>
  <condition>Candidiasis</condition>
  <condition>Biofilms</condition>
  <condition>Candida Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>C; Control; Saline solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Disinfection protocol:
brushing the palate (3 times a day/ 2 minutes);
brushing the total prostheses with neutral liquid soap (3 times a day/ 3 minutes);
immersing the total prostheses in Saline solution (once a day/ 20 minutes) before the last brushing of the day;
the prostheses must be conditioned in a vessel with water during the whole night period.
Periods of analysis (Baseline, 7 and 37 days):
the prostheses will be evidenced and photographed.
the biofilm present on the inner surface of the prostheses will be collected;
photographe of the participants' palate;
collected the palate biofilm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HS0.25%; 0.25% Sodium Hypochlorite</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Disinfection protocol:
brushing the palate (3 times a day/ 2 minutes);
brushing the total prostheses with neutral liquid soap (3 times a day/ 3 minutes);
immersing the total prostheses in 0.25% Sodium Hypochlorite (once a day/ 20 minutes) before the last brushing of the day;
the prostheses must be conditioned in a vessel with water during the whole night period.
Periods of analysis (Baseline, 7 and 37 days):
the prostheses will be evidenced and photographed.
the biofilm present on the inner surface of the prostheses will be collected;
photographe of the participants' palate;
collected the palate biofilm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RC10%; 10% Ricinus communis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Disinfection protocol:
brushing the palate (3 times a day/ 2 minutes);
brushing the total prostheses with neutral liquid soap (3 times a day/ 3 minutes);
immersing the total prostheses in 10% Ricinus communis (once a day/ 20 minutes) before the last brushing of the day;
the prostheses must be conditioned in a vessel with water during the whole night period.
Periods of analysis (Baseline, 7 and 37 days):
the prostheses will be evidenced and photographed.
the biofilm present on the inner surface of the prostheses will be collected;
photographe of the participants' palate;
collected the palate biofilm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CT0.5%; 0.5% Chloramine T</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Disinfection protocol:
brushing the palate (3 times a day/ 2 minutes);
brushing the total prostheses with neutral liquid soap (3 times a day/ 3 minutes);
immersing the total prostheses in 0.5% Choramine T (once a day/ 20 minutes) before the last brushing of the day;
the prostheses must be conditioned in a vessel with water during the whole night period.
Periods of analysis (Baseline, 7 and 37 days):
the prostheses will be evidenced and photographed.
the biofilm present on the inner surface of the prostheses will be collected;
photographe of the participants' palate;
collected the palate biofilm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Disinfection Protocol</intervention_name>
    <description>The participants assigned to this group carried out the disinfection protocol that recommended brushing the palate (3 times a day), brushing the total prosthesis with neutral liquid soap (3 times a day) and immersing in different desinfection solutions (once a day/ 20 minutes)</description>
    <arm_group_label>C; Control; Saline solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>HS0.25%; 0.25% Sodium Hypochlorite</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>RC10%; 10% Ricinus communis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CT0.5%; 0.5% Chloramine T</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Denture Hygiene Protocol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  providing consent prior to participation in the study;

          -  being at least 18 years of age;

          -  maxillary complete conventional denture in good state and 1 year of use;

          -  dentures with biofilm in a internal surface;

          -  moderate to severe signs of Candidiasis.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  presence oral mucosal lesions apart from Candidiasis;

          -  systemic or local conditions which predispose to Candida spp. infection;

          -  history of chemotherapy/ radiotherapy;

          -  having taken or used antibiotics, steroidal agents, or antifungal agents in the three
             months prior to the study;

          -  being scheduled to replace existing dentures with new ones during the period of the
             trial;

          -  dentures with adaptation or retention problems;

          -  already using palatal brushing or disinfectant solutions as a routine oral hygiene.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 23, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cláudia Helena Lovato da Silva</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator and Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dentures</keyword>
  <keyword>Biofilms</keyword>
  <keyword>Disinfection</keyword>
  <keyword>Candidiasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Candida</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Candidiasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sodium Hypochlorite</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>chloramine-T</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eusol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

