<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03001830</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UCL 13/0076</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-000925-38</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MR/L013185/1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03001830</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gene Therapy for Haemophilia A.</brief_title>
  <acronym>GO-8</acronym>
  <official_title>GO-8: Gene Therapy for Haemophilia A Using a Novel Serotype 8 Capsid Pseudotyped Adeno-associated Viral Vector Encoding Factor VIII-V3</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical Research Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College, London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The GO-8 study focuses on assessing safety and efficacy of gene therapy for patients with
      severe haemophilia A
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Haemophilia A is an x-linked, life threatening bleeding disorder arising from defects in the
      coagulation factor VIII (FVIII) gene. Current treatment for haemophilia A, the commonest
      inherited bleeding disorder (prevalence of 1 in 5000 individuals) consists of life-long,
      2-3X/week, intravenous injection of clotting factor concentrates, which is demanding,
      exceedingly expensive not widely available nor curative. In contrast, gene therapy offers the
      potential of a cure for haemophilia A as illustrated by our first unequivocal success in a
      related condition, haemophilia B. In that study the investigators showed that a single
      intravenous administration of a serotype 8 based adeno-associated virus, (AAV8) vector
      encoding the factor IX (FIX) gene resulted in stable (&gt;6 years) therapeutic expression of FIX
      without long-lasting toxicity. The investigators plan to use the same AAV8 platform to
      evaluate a novel FVIII expression cassette, AAV2/8-HLP-FVIII-V3, in patient with haemophilia
      A. Extensive preclinical studies demonstrate that AAV2/8-HLP-FVIII-V3 leads to long-term,
      endogenous expression of FVIII in mouse and non-human primate models without toxicity even
      when fifty-fold higher doses than the proposed starting clinical trial dose were used.
      Therefore, an open label, Phase I/II dose escalation study entailing a single systemic
      administration of AAV2/8-HLP-FVIII-V3 in adults (&gt;18 years of age) with severe haemophilia A
      who have baseline factor FVIII levels of &lt;1% of normal has been designed to establish safety
      and efficacy of our approach. Dosing will begin at 6x10^11 vector genome (vg)/kg progressing
      sequentially to 2x10^12vg/kg and ultimately 6x10^12vg/kg in the absence of toxicity. A
      minimum of 2 patients will be recruited at each dose with a possibility of expanding the dose
      cohort to a maximum of 6 patients based on safety and efficacy. The study duration for each
      patient will be 15 years after vector infusion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 14, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2034</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety - Dose Limiting Toxicity possibly attributable to the ATIMP development</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 years post-infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicity will be assessed according to CTCAE, version 4.03 based on the monitoring schedule which comprises a number of clinical and laboratory evaluations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety - Neutralising anti-hFVIII antibody development following gene therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 years post-infusion</time_frame>
    <description>The presence of neutralising hFVIII antibodies will be assessed by regular laboratory tests during patient follow up post infusion</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma hFVIII activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12 post-infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Assessments of plasma hFVIII activity using a validated chromogenic assay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>Annual review for 15 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of bleeding frequency using participant diaries before and after gene transfer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hFVIII concentrate usage</measure>
    <time_frame>Annual review for 15 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of hFVIII concentrate usage as per participant treatment records before and after gene transfer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune response to the AAV8 capsid.</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 3, 6, 9 &amp; 12 post-infusion &amp; Month 6 post-infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Immune response to the AAV8 capsid will be assessed by measurement of the AAV8 antibody titre (humoral response) in plasma samples collected at various time points after gene transfer. Cellular immune response to AAV capsid will be determined using gamma interferon (IFNγ) ELIspot assay to AAV8 capsid</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Viral shedding</measure>
    <time_frame>Weekly from 7 days post infusion until day 42.</time_frame>
    <description>Serum and bodily secretions will be collected to assess clearance of vector genomes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemophilia A</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment with AAV2/8-HLP-FVIII-V3</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AAV2/8-HLP-FVIII-V3</intervention_name>
    <description>Infusion of AAV2/8-HLP-FVIII-V3</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult males, aged 18 years or over, with a confirmed diagnosis of severe Haemophilia A
             defined as baseline plasma FVIII levels of &lt;1% of normal as assessed by a validated
             one-stage clotting assay or a chromogenic assay, resulting from intron 22 inversions,
             intron 1 inversions, splice-site mutations, small deletions/insertions and missense
             mutations.

          -  A severe bleeding phenotype as defined by at least one of the following:

               1. On prophylaxis for a history of bleeding, or

               2. On demand therapy with a current or past history of 4 or more bleeding
                  episodes/year, or

               3. Evidence of chronic haemophilic arthropathy (pain, joint destruction, and loss of
                  range of motion)

          -  Received treatment with human FVIII concentrates with at least &gt;50 exposure days;

          -  Able to give full informed consent and able to comply with all requirements of the
             trial including 15-year long-term follow-up;

          -  Willing to practice barrier contraception after vector administration until at least
             three consecutive semen samples are negative for vector sequences (may be for 2-3
             months).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of neutralising anti-hFVIII antibodies (inhibitor, determined by the Bethesda
             inhibitor assay) at the time of enrolment or a previous history of hFVIII inhibitor;

          -  Severe haemophilia A patients with large deletions (multiple exons) and nonsense
             mutations of the F8 gene.

          -  Use of investigational therapy for haemophilia within 30 days before enrolment;

          -  Subjects with active hepatitis B or C, and HBsAg or HCV RNA viral load positivity,
             respectively or currently on antiviral therapy for hepatitis B or C. (Negative viral
             assays in two samples, collected at least six months apart, will be required to be
             considered negative. Both natural clearers and those who have cleared HCV on antiviral
             therapy are eligible).

          -  Serological evidence of HIV-1 who have CD4 counts ≤ 200/mm3. Subjects who are
             HIV-positive and stable, with an adequate CD4 count (&gt; 200/mm3) and undetectable viral
             load measured twice in the six months prior to enrolment, on an antiretroviral drug
             regimen are eligible to enrol.

          -  Evidence of liver dysfunction (persistently elevated ALT &gt;1.5X upper limit of normal);

          -  Uncontrolled glaucoma, diabetes mellitus, or hypertension (systolic BP consistently
             ≥140 mmHg or diastolic BP consistently ≥90 mmHg);

          -  History of malignancy;

          -  Suspicious Lung lesions on CT scan that raise the possibility of cancer or
             premalignant pathology

          -  Presence of liver abnormality that is suspicious of malignancy on screening liver
             ultrasound

          -  Patients with uncontrolled cardiac failure or unstable angina;

          -  Detectable neutralising anti-AAV8 antibodies

          -  Received an AAV vector, or any other gene transfer agent in the previous 6 months

          -  History of active tuberculosis, fungal disease or other chronic infection

          -  Subjects who are unwilling to provide the required semen samples XVI. Poor performance
             status (WHO score &gt;1) XVII. Previous history or family history of venous or arterial
             thromboembolism
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pratima Chowdary, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Royal Free London NHS Foundation Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark Phillips</last_name>
    <phone>+442078302068</phone>
    <phone_ext>33768</phone_ext>
    <email>mark.phillips@ucl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Jude's Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105-3678</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ulrike Reiss, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew Davidoff, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Free Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW3 2QG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pratima Chowdary</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amit Nathwani</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edward Tuddenham</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 23, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemophilia A</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Factor VIII</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

