<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03007953</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NRI 15-456</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03007953</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Palliative Care Interventions for Outpatients Newly Diagnosed With Lung Cancer: Phase II</brief_title>
  <acronym>PCI2</acronym>
  <official_title>Palliative Care Interventions for Outpatients Newly Diagnosed With Lung Cancer: Phase II</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The focus of the study is to test a nurse-led telephone-based palliative care intervention on
      improving the delivery of care for patients with newly diagnosed lung cancer. The study is a
      three site randomized control trial to determine the efficacy of the intervention on
      improving patients' quality of life, symptom burden, and satisfaction of care. Additionally,
      the study will test an innovative care delivery model to improve patients' access to
      palliative care. The investigators will also determine the effect of the intervention on
      patient activation to discuss treatment preferences with their clinician and on clinician
      knowledge of patients' goals of care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients meeting entry criteria will be randomized to the intervention arm, palliative care
      plus usual care, or the usual care arm. Patients randomized to the intervention arm will
      receive usual oncologic care and phone calls from a nurse. Outcome measures will be collected
      at baseline and at the end of the patients' primary cancer treatment. The study will be
      performed at the Puget Sound Health Care System, Birmingham VA and Portland VA. The
      investigators will recruit individuals (n=138) with lung cancer over 2.5 years. The primary
      objective is to determine the efficacy of the nurse-led telephone-based palliative
      intervention on improving patients' quality of life, symptom burden, and satisfaction of
      care. In addition, using validated instruments, the investigators will assess the effect of
      the intervention on patient activation to discuss treatment preferences with their clinician
      and on clinician knowledge of patients' goals of care. The results of this study will inform
      a future effectiveness/implementation study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Lung Total Outcome Index Score at Final Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Quality of Life including symptoms as measured by the FACT-L (Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Lung Scale). The FACT-L outcome measure reported is the mean change in the TOI subscale (Total Outcome Index) of the instrument, computed as the differences between final and baseline visit scores. The TOI subscale range is 0-84, with a higher score indicating a better quality of life. Among patients with newly diagnosed lung cancer, provision of a telephone-based palliative care intervention will be associated with a change in FACT-L TOI score. The investigators will assess the difference in FACT-L TOI scores between the intervention and control subjects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Patient Satisfaction of Care at Final Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction with care will be assessed by using the FAMCARE-Patient Survey 13 (full unabbreviated scale name). The FAMCARE is a 13 item, 5 point likert-scale validated questionnaire measuring patient satisfaction with cancer care and assessing interactions with health care providers, performance status and symptom burden. Only total score are reported (no subscales). Scores range from 13-65 with scores of 52 &gt; being satisfied with care. In full randomized clinical trials the estimated MID is 5 points from baseline to 12 weeks. Among patients with newly diagnosed lung cancer, provision of a telephone-based palliative care intervention will be associated with a change in FAMCARE-P13 score. The investigators will assess the difference in FAMCARE-P13 scores between the intervention and control subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Patient Activation to Discuss Treatment Preferences with Providers at Final Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient activation will be assessed using the Health Care Communication Questions (HCC). The HCC is a 9-item adapted questionnaire developed and used by the investigators' research team for over 10 years. The questions were derived from patient focus groups about clinician communications skills and are about discussions patient may or may not have had with their lung cancer doctor or family related to their treatment preferences. The responses are &quot;yes&quot; &quot;no&quot; or &quot;I don't know&quot;. Among patients with newly diagnosed lung cancer, provision of a telephone-based palliative care intervention will be associated with a change in HCC score. The investigators will assess the difference in HCC scores between the intervention and control subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Clinician Knowledge of Patient Goals of Care at Final Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinician Knowledge of patients' goals of care will be assessed at baseline and at the final visits by asking 2 validated questions about patient preferences for life sustaining treatments, including mechanical ventilation and cardiopulmonary resuscitation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Clinician Knowledge of Patient Goals of Care at Final Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinician Knowledge of patients' goals of care will be assessed at baseline and at the final visits by asking two additional questions that capture patient values. There are no published psychometrics for these questions, however they were used in the SUPPORT study and other more recent palliative care studies. The difference between patient and provider responses from baseline to completion of the study will be measured and compared between treatment groups to test the effect of the intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">138</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a nurse-led telephone-based program integrating palliative care into usual oncologic care for patients diagnosed within 2 months of any type and stage of lung cancer, who will receive therapy other than solely surgical resection. The intervention lasts for the duration of patients' primary lung cancer treatment (usually 3-4 months).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to the usual care arm will receive medical oncology, radiation oncology, pulmonary, CT surgery, as indicated by the type and stage of cancer. At the completion of their primary lung cancer treatment, they will be disenrolled from the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Palliative Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Care delivered by a nurse, including symptom assessment and management, patient education on lung cancer and treatment options, discussion and communication about preferences for care, psychosocial assessment (including referrals to ancillary services), and patient-centered resources. A personalized treatment plan based on the patient's lung cancer stage, treatment, symptoms and psychosocial needs will be developed by the palliative care team (physician, study nurse) with input from the patient and family member. The study nurse will assess patient's symptoms, implement and monitor the treatment plan applying established End-of- Life Nursing Education Consortium (ELNEC) for Veterans protocols.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Supportive Care</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients diagnosed at the Puget Sound Health Care System, Birmingham VA, or Portland VA
        with a primary diagnosis of lung cancer that requires more than surgical resection:

          -  diagnosed within 8 weeks of recruitment

          -  must have telephone access

          -  ability to understand English

          -  able to participate in informed consent process

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients not eligible to participate in the study include those who are inpatients prior to
        randomization,

          -  those who are under the care of palliative care or hospice at the time of
             randomization

          -  those who have severe mental health disorders

          -  those who are unable to speak directly with the nurse over the telephone

          -  or those that have the inability to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lynn F. Reinke, PhD ARNP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Puget Sound Health Care System Seattle Division, Seattle, WA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lynn F Reinke, PhD ARNP</last_name>
    <phone>(206) 277-4186</phone>
    <email>lynn.reinke1@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Birmingham VA Medical Center, Birmingham, AL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patti H Smith, RN</last_name>
      <phone>205-933-2182</phone>
      <email>patti.smith2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark T. Dransfield</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Portland Health Care System, Portland, OR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sara Golden, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>503-220-8262</phone>
      <phone_ext>54434</phone_ext>
      <email>sara.golden1@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Christopher G Slatore</last_name>
      <phone>5032208262</phone>
      <phone_ext>52018</phone_ext>
      <email>christopher.slatore@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Puget Sound Health Care System Seattle Division, Seattle, WA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Erica V Tartaglione, BS</last_name>
      <phone>206-277-4154</phone>
      <email>erica.tartaglione@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lynn F. Reinke, PhD ARNP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Reinke LF, Vig EK, Tartaglione EV, Backhus LM, Gunnink E, Au DH. Protocol and pilot testing: The feasibility and acceptability of a nurse-led telephone-based palliative care intervention for patients newly diagnosed with lung cancer. Contemp Clin Trials. 2018 Jan;64:30-34. doi: 10.1016/j.cct.2017.11.013. Epub 2017 Nov 23.</citation>
    <PMID>29175560</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Reinke LF, Meier DE. Research Priorities in Subspecialty Palliative Care: Policy Initiatives. J Palliat Med. 2017 Aug;20(8):813-820. doi: 10.1089/jpm.2017.0303.</citation>
    <PMID>28777716</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Aslakson RA, Reinke LF, Cox C, Kross EK, Benzo RP, Curtis JR. Developing a Research Agenda for Integrating Palliative Care into Critical Care and Pulmonary Practice To Improve Patient and Family Outcomes. J Palliat Med. 2017 Apr;20(4):329-343. doi: 10.1089/jpm.2016.0567. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28379812</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 19, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 28, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 2, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Palliative Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Supportive Care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

