<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02953626</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-0032-B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02953626</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mother Matters Online Postpartum Support</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mother Matters: Pilot Randomized Waitlist Controlled Trial of an Online Postpartum Mental Health Support Group</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Women's College Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre for Addiction and Mental Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Women's College Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postpartum depression is common, yet only 20% of women seek treatment. Online support groups
      are a potential means of providing accessible mental health care during this time. Mother
      Matters is a 10-week online psychotherapy group for women with postpartum depression &amp;
      anxiety. The investigators aim to conduct a pilot RCT to demonstrate the feasibility of
      proceeding to a large-scale RCT evaluation of the Mother Matters intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The postpartum period is a particularly vulnerable time for the development of mental health
      concerns; postpartum depression (i.e. depression with onset between 0-12 months postpartum)
      affects approximately 13% of mothers in Canada. There are serious negative consequences to
      both mother and child during this period, yet only 20% of women seek treatment, citing
      significant systematic and personal barriers. Online support groups have been identified as a
      potential means of providing accessible mental health care during this time. Mother Matters
      is a 10-week online support group for women with postpartum depression and anxiety, run
      trained psychotherapists in the Reproductive Life Stages (RLS) program at Women's College
      Hospital in Toronto, Ontario. Mother Matters was designed to address barriers related to
      accessing postpartum mental health services: it can be accessed anywhere (online group), at
      any time (available 24/7), and with anonymity (to address the barrier of shame/stigma). The
      overall objective of the current pilot RCT is to determine the feasibility of conducting a
      large randomized controlled trial to evaluate the efficacy of the group, comparing outcomes
      among those with and without access to the program.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment Feasibility (Eligibility)</measure>
    <time_frame>One year from when the study starts enrolling participants</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of participants eligible to participate in Mother Matters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Edinburgh Postnatal Depressive Scale (EPDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (10 weeks post-randomization at the completion of the Mother Matters online support group for the immediate treatment condition arm)</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will measure depressive symptoms using the EPDS, a self-report depression screening measure that has been validated for use in pregnancy. EPDS scores &gt;12 are predictive of a diagnosis of major depressive disorder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (10 weeks post-randomization at the completion of the Mother Matters online support group for the immediate treatment condition arm)</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will measure anxious symptoms using the STAI, a self-report anxiety screening measure that has shown good discriminate validity in perinatal populations. STAI scores &gt;48 are predictive of having an anxiety disorder diagnosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Change in Eating Disorder Symptoms Scale (CHEDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (10 weeks post-randomization at the completion of the Mother Matters online support group for the immediate treatment condition arm)</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will measure eating disorder symptoms use the CHEDS, which is designed to assess change in eating disorder symptoms and their severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parenting Stress Index, Short Form (PSI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (10 weeks post-randomization at the completion of the Mother Matters online support group for the immediate treatment condition arm)</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will measure stress in the parent-child relationship using the PSI short form, a 36-item measure which consists of three sub-scales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Acceptability (Qualitative)</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (Immediate treatment condiction: 10 weeks post-randomization, i.e. at completion of the Mother Matters online support group; Waitlist control condition: 10 weeks after the waitlist Mother Matters group starts)</time_frame>
    <description>Mother Matters Program Evaluation Questionnaire. This is comprised of open- and closed-ended questions to elicit feedback on a) content, clarity and helpfulness of the group, b) acceptability of the group format, c) satisfaction with the group, including reasons for discontinuation, d) the facilitators availability and helpfulness, and e) whether or not participants would recommend it to other women experiencing depressive symptoms in the first postpartum year.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention Acceptability (Website Usage)</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (Immediate treatment condiction: 10 weeks post-randomization, i.e. at completion of the Mother Matters online support group; Waitlist control condition: 10 weeks after the waitlist Mother Matters group starts)</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of intervention weeks that participant logs in to the forum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trial Protocol Adherence (Study Measure Completion)</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (about 10 weeks post-randomization)</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants who complete follow-up measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment Feasibility (Recruitment)</measure>
    <time_frame>One year from when the study starts enrolling participants</time_frame>
    <description>The number of women recruited to the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trial Protocol Adherence (Weekly Posting)</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (Immediate treatment condiction: 10 weeks post-randomization, i.e. at completion of the Mother Matters online support group; Waitlist control condition: 10 weeks after the waitlist Mother Matters group starts)</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants who post in the forum at least on a weekly basis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trial Protocol Adherence (Posting Drop-Off)</measure>
    <time_frame>Follow-up (Immediate treatment condiction: 10 weeks post-randomization, i.e. at completion of the Mother Matters online support group; Waitlist control condition: 10 weeks after the waitlist Mother Matters group starts)</time_frame>
    <description>The drop-off rate for postings (i.e. the number of participants who post in the initial weeks but not in the latter half of the group)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Treatment Condition (ITC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mother Matters Online Postpartum Support Group. Participants will be assigned to begin immediately after randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist Control Condition (WLC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mother Matters Online Postpartum Support Group. Participants will receive the intervention after the Immediate Treatment Condition group completes the intervention, and after follow-up data are collected from both groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mother Matters Online Postpartum Support Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Mother Matters is a 10-week online support group for women with postpartum depression. It involves: 1) A private, online forum that can be accessed by participants 24-hours per day. During regular business hours (9:00 am to 5:00 pm on weekdays) it is moderated by a psychotherapist, and there is a weekly moderated &quot;live&quot; chat hour; 2) Weekly topics with readings are provided with questions to prompt discussion on the online forum. Topics incorporate symptom management (i.e. Interpersonal Therapy, Cognitive Behavioural Therapy) and affect regulation strategies (i.e. Mindfulness, DBT) with a supportive counselling approach. External resources related to each week's topic, are also shared.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Treatment Condition (ITC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

        The specific inclusion criteria for this group are women who are:

          1. Mothers of a baby/babies between 0 and 12 months old at enrollment, and

          2. Over 18 years old, and

          3. Have an Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale (EPDS) score of &gt;9, and

          4. Reside in Ontario.

        Exclusion Criteria

        Women will not be eligible to participate in the study if they are:

          1. Experiencing active suicidal ideation, or

          2. Have active substance use, mania or psychosis, or

          3. Unable to access the internet, or

          4. Unable to participate in English.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simone Vigod, MD,MSc,FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Women's College Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women's College Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5S 1B2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maternal depression and child development. Paediatr Child Health. 2004 Oct;9(8):575-598. English, French, English.</citation>
    <PMID>19680490</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marcus SM. Depression during pregnancy: rates, risks and consequences--Motherisk Update 2008. Can J Clin Pharmacol. 2009 Winter;16(1):e15-22. Epub 2009 Jan 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19164843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meltzer-Brody S, Jones I. Optimizing the treatment of mood disorders in the perinatal period. Dialogues Clin Neurosci. 2015 Jun;17(2):207-18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26246794</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roberta Anniverno, A.B., Claudio Mencacci and Federico Durbano, Anxiety Disorders in Pregnancy and the Postpartum Period, in New Insights into Anxiety Disorders, D.F. Durbano, Editor. 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Misri S, Abizadeh J, Sanders S, Swift E. Perinatal Generalized Anxiety Disorder: Assessment and Treatment. J Womens Health (Larchmt). 2015 Sep;24(9):762-70. doi: 10.1089/jwh.2014.5150. Epub 2015 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>26125602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farr SL, Dietz PM, O'Hara MW, Burley K, Ko JY. Postpartum anxiety and comorbid depression in a population-based sample of women. J Womens Health (Larchmt). 2014 Feb;23(2):120-8. doi: 10.1089/jwh.2013.4438. Epub 2013 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>24160774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Easter A, Solmi F, Bye A, Taborelli E, Corfield F, Schmidt U, Treasure J, Micali N. Antenatal and postnatal psychopathology among women with current and past eating disorders: longitudinal patterns. Eur Eat Disord Rev. 2015 Jan;23(1):19-27. doi: 10.1002/erv.2328. Epub 2014 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>25345371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Micali N, Simonoff E, Treasure J. Pregnancy and post-partum depression and anxiety in a longitudinal general population cohort: the effect of eating disorders and past depression. J Affect Disord. 2011 Jun;131(1-3):150-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2010.09.034. Epub 2010 Dec 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21146231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dennis CL, Chung-Lee L. Postpartum depression help-seeking barriers and maternal treatment preferences: a qualitative systematic review. Birth. 2006 Dec;33(4):323-31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17150072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paul IM, Downs DS, Schaefer EW, Beiler JS, Weisman CS. Postpartum anxiety and maternal-infant health outcomes. Pediatrics. 2013 Apr;131(4):e1218-24. doi: 10.1542/peds.2012-2147. Epub 2013 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>23460682</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yelland J, Sutherland G, Brown SJ. Postpartum anxiety, depression and social health: findings from a population-based survey of Australian women. BMC Public Health. 2010 Dec 20;10:771. doi: 10.1186/1471-2458-10-771.</citation>
    <PMID>21167078</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>National Collaborating Centre for Mental Health (UK). Antenatal and Postnatal Mental Health: Clinical Management and Service Guidance: Updated edition. Leicester (UK): British Psychological Society; 2014 Dec.</citation>
    <PMID>26180865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Evans M, Donelle L, Hume-Loveland L. Social support and online postpartum depression discussion groups: a content analysis. Patient Educ Couns. 2012 Jun;87(3):405-10. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2011.09.011. Epub 2011 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>22019021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spangler DL. The Change in Eating Disorder Symptoms scale: scale development and psychometric properties. Eat Behav. 2010 Aug;11(3):131-7. doi: 10.1016/j.eatbeh.2009.12.003. Epub 2009 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>20434058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haskett ME, Ahern LS, Ward CS, Allaire JC. Factor structure and validity of the parenting stress index-short form. J Clin Child Adolesc Psychol. 2006 Jun;35(2):302-12.</citation>
    <PMID>16597226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris AA. Practical advice for caring for women with eating disorders during the perinatal period. J Midwifery Womens Health. 2010 Nov-Dec;55(6):579-86. doi: 10.1016/j.jmwh.2010.07.008.</citation>
    <PMID>20974420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Micali N, Simonoff E, Stahl D, Treasure J. Maternal eating disorders and infant feeding difficulties: maternal and child mediators in a longitudinal general population study. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2011 Jul;52(7):800-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-7610.2010.02341.x. Epub 2010 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21073463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coker E, Abraham S. Body weight dissatisfaction before, during and after pregnancy: a comparison of women with and without eating disorders. Eat Weight Disord. 2015 Mar;20(1):71-9. doi: 10.1007/s40519-014-0133-4. Epub 2014 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>24906550</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hertzog MA. Considerations in determining sample size for pilot studies. Res Nurs Health. 2008 Apr;31(2):180-91. doi: 10.1002/nur.20247. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18183564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meltzer-Brody S, Zerwas S, Leserman J, Holle AV, Regis T, Bulik C. Eating disorders and trauma history in women with perinatal depression. J Womens Health (Larchmt). 2011 Jun;20(6):863-70. doi: 10.1089/jwh.2010.2360.</citation>
    <PMID>21671774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 31, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 3, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pilot RCT</keyword>
  <keyword>waitlist-controlled RCT</keyword>
  <keyword>postpartum depression</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

