<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02953808</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>205911</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02953808</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 1 Study of GSK2315698 in Healthy Japanese Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single Centre, Double-blind, Randomised, Placebo-controlled, and Single Dose-ascending Study to Investigate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics, of Single Intravenous Doses of GSK2315698 in Healthy Japanese Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is the first study in which GSK2315698 will be administered in Japanese population. The
      primary objective of the study is to investigate safety and tolerability, pharmacokinetics,
      and pharmacodynamics after single intravenous infusion in healthy subjects. This will be a
      single center, double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, dose-ascending study.

      Subjects in Cohort 1 will attend 3 dosing sessions, and will be randomized to one of the 3
      groups. Each group will receive GSK2315698 and Placebo in a defined sequence. The dose levels
      of GSK2315698 are set to 10 milligrams (mg) per hour (hr), 20 mg/hr, and 40 mg/hr, to be
      administered over 1 hour. Dosing sessions 1 and 2, and dosing sessions 2 and 3, will be
      separated by a washout period of at least 8 and 10 days, respectively.

      Subjects in Cohort 2 will attend a single dosing session, and will be randomized to receive
      either GSK2315698 20 mg/hr or Placebo, over a period of 15 hours.

      A sufficient number of subjects will be randomized such that 18 subjects (9 in each cohort)
      complete the study. The duration of participation for any subject in this study will be
      approximately 59 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events (AE) and serious adverse events (SAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Over a maximum period of approximately 29 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with abnormalities in clinical laboratory parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Over a maximum period of approximately 59 days</time_frame>
    <description>Abnormalities will be assessed in laboratory parameters of hematology, clinical chemistry, and routine urinalysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with abnormalities in vital sign parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Over a maximum period of approximately 59 days</time_frame>
    <description>Abnormalities will be assessed in the vital signs of respiratory rate, pulse rate, blood pressure, and body temperature. Vital signs will be measured in a supine position after 5 minutes of rest.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities</measure>
    <time_frame>Over a maximum period of approximately 59 days</time_frame>
    <description>Single 12-lead ECG will be obtained using an ECG machine that automatically calculates the heart rate and measures PR, QRS, QT, and QT interval corrected for heart rate by Fridericia's formula (QTcF) intervals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentration of GSK2315698</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24 hours post-dose in Cohort 1; Day 1 (pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 4, 12, 15, 18, 24 hours post-dose), and Days 5, 8, 14 in Cohort 2</time_frame>
    <description>Whole blood samples of approximately 2 milliliters (mL) will be collected for measurement of plasma concentrations of GSK2315698.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) of GSK2315698</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24 hours post-dose in Cohort 1; Day 1 (pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 4, 12, 15, 18, 24 hours post-dose), and Days 5, 8, 14 in Cohort 2</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax will be calculated if data permit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration-time curve from pre-dose to 24 hours (AUC0-24) of GSK2315698</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24 hours post-dose in Cohort 1; Day 1 (pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 4, 12, 15, 18, 24 hours post-dose), and Days 5, 8, 14 in Cohort 2</time_frame>
    <description>AUC0-24 will be calculated if data permit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to maximum observed plasma drug concentration (Tmax) of GSK2315698</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24 hours post-dose in Cohort 1; Day 1 (pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 4, 12, 15, 18, 24 hours post-dose), and Days 5, 8, 14 in Cohort 2</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax will be calculated if data permit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 2: Plasma concentration of GSK2315698 at 15 hours (C15hr)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 4, 12, and 15 hours post-dose in Cohort 2</time_frame>
    <description>C15hr will be calculated if data permit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in blood concentration of serum amyloid P component (SAP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24 hours post-dose), Day 5, and Day 8 in Cohort 1; Day 1 (pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 4, 12, 15, 18, 24 hours post-dose), and Days 5, 8, 14 in Cohort 2</time_frame>
    <description>Venous blood samples of approximately 2 mL will be collected for measurement of SAP.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimum blood concentration (Cmin) of SAP</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24 hours post-dose), Day 5, and Day 8 in Cohort 1; Day 1 (pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 4, 12, 15, 18, 24 hours post-dose), and Days 5, 8, 14 in Cohort 2</time_frame>
    <description>Cmin will be calculated if data permit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to minimum observed concentration (Tmin) of SAP</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24 hours post-dose), Day 5, and Day 8 in Cohort 1; Day 1 (pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 4, 12, 15, 18, 24 hours post-dose), and Days 5, 8, 14 in Cohort 2</time_frame>
    <description>Tmin will be calculated if data permit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cohort 2: Concentration of SAP at 15 hours (C15hr)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose and 0.25, 1, 4, 12, and 15 hours post-dose in Cohort 2</time_frame>
    <description>C15hr will be calculated if data permit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Amyloidosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In dosing sessions 1, 2, and 3, subjects will receive GSK2315698 10 mg/hr, GSK2315698 20 mg/hr, and Placebo, respectively, as intravenous infusion over 1 hour.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In dosing sessions 1, 2, and 3, subjects will receive GSK2315698 10 mg/hr, Placebo, and GSK2315698 40 mg/hr, respectively, as intravenous infusion over 1 hour.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 Group C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In dosing sessions 1, 2, and 3, subjects will receive Placebo, GSK2315698 20 mg/hr, and GSK2315698 40 mg/hr, respectively, as intravenous infusion over 1 hour.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 Group D</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In a single dosing session, subjects will receive GSK2315698 20 mg/hr as intravenous infusion over 15 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 Group E</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In a single dosing session, subjects will receive Placebo as an intravenous infusion over 15 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>0.9% weight by volume (w/v) saline solution for intravenous infusion over 1 hour (in Cohort 1) or over 15 hours (in Cohort 2).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 Group E</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 Group C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK2315698</intervention_name>
    <description>200 mg/mL stock solution for intravenous infusion over 1 hour (in Cohort 1) or over 15 hours (in Cohort 2). The stock solution will be diluted to obtain dosage levels of 10 mg/hr, 20 mg/hr, or 40 mg/hr.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 Group D</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 Group C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant must be 20 to 64 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the
             informed consent

          -  Participants who are overtly healthy as determined by medical evaluation including
             medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests, and cardiac monitoring. A
             subject with a clinical abnormality or laboratory parameter(s) which is/are not
             specifically listed in the inclusion or exclusion criteria, outside the reference
             range for the population being studied may be included only if the investigator in
             consultation with the Medical Monitor if required agree that the finding is unlikely
             to introduce additional risk factors and will not interfere with the study procedures

          -  Peripheral veins suitable for venous blood sampling and cannulation

          -  Body weight &gt;=50 kilograms (kg) and body mass index (BMI) within the range 18.5-24.9
             kg per meter (m) squared (inclusive)

          -  Male: A Japanese male participant must agree to use contraception during the treatment
             period and until follow up visit

          -  Capable of giving signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History or presence of cardiovascular, respiratory, hepatic, renal, gastrointestinal,
             endocrine, hematological, or neurological disorders capable of significantly altering
             the absorption, metabolism, or elimination of drugs; constituting a risk when taking
             the study treatment; or interfering with the interpretation of data

          -  Clinically abnormal hypotonia or hyperpiesia as determined by the investigator

          -  Previous surgical procedures on the upper digestive tract including cholecystectomy
             (gallbladder removal), and/or cholelithotomy (gallstone removal)

          -  Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;1.5 multiplied by upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Bilirubin &gt;1.5 times ULN (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5 times ULN is acceptable if bilirubin
             is fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%)

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary abnormalities
             (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones)

          -  QTcF &gt;450 millisecond (msec) QTcF is either machine-read or manually over-read. The
             specific formula that will be used to determine eligibility and discontinuation for an
             individual subject should be determined prior to initiation of the study. In other
             words, several different formulae cannot be used to calculate the corrected QT
             interval (QTc) for an individual subject and then the lowest QTc value used to include
             or discontinue the subject from the trial. For purposes of data analysis, QTcF,
             another QT correction formula, or a composite of available values of QTc will be used

          -  Past or intended use of over-the-counter or prescription medication including herbal
             medications within 14 days prior to dosing. Specific study-defined medications may be
             allowed

          -  History of donation of blood or blood products &gt;=400 mL within 3 months or &gt;=200 mL
             within 1 month prior to screening

          -  Exposure to more than 4 new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day

          -  Current enrollment or past participation within the last 3 months, 5 half-lives or
             twice the duration of the biological effect of the investigational product (whichever
             is longer) before signing of consent in this or any other clinical study involving an
             investigational study treatment or any other type of medical research

          -  The subject is positive for Serological test for syphilis (Rapid plasma reagin test
             [RPR] and Treponema pallidum Latex Agglutination [TPLA]), Human immunodeficiency virus
             (HIV) antigen/antibody, Hepatitis B surface antigen (HbsAg), Hepatitis C virus (HCV)
             antibody, or Human T-cell lymphotropic virus type 1 (HTLV-1) antibody at screening

          -  Positive pre-study drug screen

          -  Regular use of known drugs of abuse

          -  Regular alcohol consumption within 6 months prior to the study defined as an average
             weekly intake of &gt;14 units for males. One unit is equivalent to 350 mL of beer, 150 mL
             of wine or 45 mL of 80 proof distilled spirits

          -  Smoking or history or regular use of tobacco- or nicotine-containing products within 6
             months prior to screening; Sensitivity to any of the study treatments, or components
             thereof, or drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or Medical
             Monitor, contraindicates participation in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>171-0014</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 3, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GSK2315698</keyword>
  <keyword>Dose-ascending</keyword>
  <keyword>Systemic amyloidosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amyloidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

