<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02955420</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SBC007C101</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-005236-18</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02955420</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Investigate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Efficacy of BC 007 in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Three-part, Randomized Study to Investigate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics and Efficacy of BC 007 in Healthy, Young Subjects and Elderly Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Berlin Cures GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Berlin Cures GmbH</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Berlin Cures develops BC 007 to treat patients suffering from diseases (chronic heart
      failure, pulmonary hypertension, chronic fatigue syndrome etc.) which are associated with
      functional autoantibodies (AAB) directed against G-protein coupled receptors (GPCR).

      The first part of the study (part A) is designed to evaluate the safety and tolerability of
      ascending doses of BC 007. The study part is blinded and placebo controlled in order to
      better discriminate possible safety signals. The assessment of safety and tolerability in an
      elderly cohort is a bridge to dosing elderly GPCR AAB positive subjects in part B. The
      subjects in part A are confirmed to be GPCR AAB negative.

      The objective of the second part of the study (part B) is to evaluate the efficacy of BC 007
      in neutralizing AAB against GPCR shortly after dosing compared to baseline and to find the
      optimal dose for the neutralization of the AAB in all individuals. This dose shall be taken
      to progress into a Phase II/III trial with beta1-adrenergic receptor-AAB positive patients
      suffering from chronic heart failure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Part A

      Primary objective is:

        -  To assess safety and tolerability of BC 007 after a single ascending intravenous (i.v.)
           bolus + infusion in healthy, young and elderly subjects.

      Secondary objectives are:

        -  To determine the pharmacokinetic plasma and urine profiles of BC 007 in healthy, young
           and elderly subjects.

      Part B

      Primary objective is:

        -  To assess the neutralizing potency of BC 007 against GPCR autoantibodies alpha -1
           adrenergic receptor, beta-1 adrenergic receptor, beta-2 adrenergic receptor or
           endothelin-A-receptor following ascending i.v. bolus + infusion.

      Secondary objectives are:

        -  To assess safety and tolerability of BC 007 after a single ascending i.v. bolus +
           infusion in GPCR AAB (α(1)-adrenergic receptor AAB, ß(1)-adrenergic receptor AAB,
           ß(2)-adrenergic receptor AAB or endothelin-A-receptor AAB) positive healthy elderly
           subjects.

        -  To determine the pharmacokinetic plasma and urine profiles of BC 007 in GPCR AAB
           (α(1)-adrenergic receptor AAB, ß(1)-adrenergic receptor AAB, ß(2)-adrenergic receptor
           AAB or endothelin-A-receptor AAB) positive healthy elderly subjects.

      Part C

      Primary Objective

        -  To assess the neutralizing potency of BC 007 against GPCR autoantibodies alpha-1
           adrenergic receptor (α(1)-AR AAB), beta-1 adrenergic receptor (ß(1)-AR AAB), beta-2
           adrenergic receptor (ß(2)-AR AAB) or endothelin-A-receptor (ETA AAB) following ascending
           i.v. bolus + infusion.

      Secondary Objectives

        -  To assess safety and tolerability of BC 007 after a single ascending i.v. bolus +
           infusion in GPCR AAB (α(1)-AR AAB, ß(1)-AR AAB, ß(2)-AR AAB or ETA AAB) positive healthy
           elderly subjects.

        -  To determine the pharmacokinetic plasma and urine profiles of BC 007 in GPCR AAB
           (α(1)-AR AAB, ß(1)-AR AAB, ß(2)-AR AAB or ETA AAB) positive healthy elderly subjects.

      Explorative Objective

        -  To investigate the pharmacokinetic plasma and urine profiles of BC 007 metabolites in
           GPCR AAB (α(1)-AR AAB, ß(1)-AR AAB, ß(2)-AR AAB or ETA AAB) positive healthy elderly
           subjects
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A: Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values and/or Adverse Events That Are Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part B: Conversion rate from positive GPCR AAB to negative immune status</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Part C: Conversion rate from positive GPCR AAB to negative immune status</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours and 8-12 days post dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Area under the plasma concentration time curve (AUC) from time zero to the last quantifiable concentration (AUC0-t) derived from BC 007 plasma concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Area under the plasma concentration time curve (AUC) from time zero extrapolated to infinity (AUC0-inf) derived from BC 007 plasma concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: AUC from time zero to 24 hour post-dose (AUC0-24) derived from BC 007 plasma concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) derived from BC 007 plasma concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Apparent terminal half-life (t1/2) derived from BC 007 plasma concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Nominal time of Cmax (tmax) derived from BC 007 plasma concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Plasma clearance (CL) derived from BC 007 plasma concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Volume of distribution during terminal phase (Vz) derived from BC 007 plasma concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Terminal elimination rate constant (λz) derived from BC 007 plasma concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A, B and C: Cumulative amount of unchanged drug excreted into urine (Ae)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A, B and C: Fraction of intravenous administered drug that is excreted unchanged in urine (fe)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Renal clearance (CLR) of BC 007</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Part A, B and C: Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values and/or Adverse Events That Are Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours post dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BC 007 (15, 50, 150, 300, 450, 750, 1350, 1200 mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Part A:
BC 007 at doses of 15, 50 and 150 mg or matching placebo administered as i.v. bolus + infusion of 20 min (Cohorts 1 to 4). The sentinel pair of each cohort will be dosed without bolus.
NaCl 0.9% (matching placebo) administered as i.v. bolus + infusion of 20 min (Part A: Cohorts 1 to 4).
Part B:
BC 007 at doses of 50 and 150 mg administered (Cohort 1) or a single dose &lt; 50 mg or 150 mg (Cohort 2) as i.v. bolus + infusion of 20 min is administered to GPCR autoantibody positive subjects. The first subject in each dosing period of Cohort 1 will be dosed without bolus.
Part C:
BC007 administered at doses of 300 mg (Cohort 1), 450 mg (Cohort 2), 750 mg (Cohort 3), 1350 mg (Cohort 4) as i.v. bolus + infusion of 40 min to GPCR autoantibody positive subjects. The first three subjects in each dosing period of Cohort 1-4 will be dosed without bolus. In Cohort 5 BC007 dose of 1200 mg will be administered as a continuous infusion of 20 min.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BC 007</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>BC 007 (15, 50, 150, 300, 450, 750, 1350, 1200 mg)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NaCl 0.9 %</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>BC 007 (15, 50, 150, 300, 450, 750, 1350, 1200 mg)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (main):

          1. The subject is a healthy, male, non-smoker or slight/occasional smoker (less than or
             equal to 10 cigarettes per day), 18 to 45 years of age (Cohorts 1 to 3, Part A).

          2. The subject is a healthy, male or female, non-smoker or slight/occasional smoker (less
             than or equal to10 cigarettes per day), 55 to 70 years of age (Cohort 4 [only in Part
             A] and Part B).

          3. Female subjects are postmenopausal (verified by an appropriate serum FSH level and
             amenorrhea for at least one year).

          4. The subject has a body mass index (BMI) range of 18.5 to 29.9 kg/m2 inclusive,
             (healthy young males as well as elderly subjects) and weighs at least 50 kg and &lt; 100
             kg.

          5. The subject is positive for either one or the combination of GPCR α(1)- adrenergic
             receptor AAB, ß(1)-adrenergic receptor AAB, ß(2)-adrenergic receptor AAB and
             endothelin-A-receptor AAB (Part B only) at (pre-) screening prior to enrolment.

          6. The subject is negative for GPCR α(1)-adrenergic receptor AAB, ß(1)-adrenergic
             receptor AAB, ß(2)-adrenergic receptor AAB and endothelin-A-receptor AAB at
             (pre-)screening prior to enrolment (Part A only).

          7. Coagulation variables, uric acid, ALT, AST, alkaline phosphatase (ALP), GGT, bilirubin
             and creatinine must be within the normal laboratory reference ranges at screening.

          8. Thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) must be within the normal laboratory reference range
             at screening.

        Exclusion Criteria (main):

          1. Any history or evidence of any clinically significant cardiovascular,
             gastrointestinal, endocrinologic, hematologic, hepatic, immunologic, metabolic
             (specifically gout), urologic, pulmonary, neurologic, dermatologic, psychiatric,
             renal, and/or other major disease or malignancy, as judged by the Investigator.

          2. Any history or current intake of beta blockers.

          3. Any history of allergic reactions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angela Sinn, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Parexel</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Johannes Müller, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 1723103125</phone>
    <email>jmueller@berlincures.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Peter Göttel, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 30 88913640</phone>
    <phone_ext>61</phone_ext>
    <email>goettel@berlincures.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PAREXEL International GmbH, Early Phase Clinical Unit Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>14050</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Autoantibodies</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatigue Syndrome, Chronic</keyword>
  <keyword>Idiopathic Pulmonary Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiomyopathies</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autoantibodies</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

