<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02950025</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201611018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02950025</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Daily Online Adaptation Versus Localization for MRI-Guided SBRT for Unresectable Primary or Oligometastatic Abdominal Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Phase II Study of Daily Online Adaptation Versus Localization for MRI-Guided SBRT for Unresectable Primary or Oligometastatic Abdominal Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In light of this new technology and preliminary findings of low toxicity of online, adaptive,
      magnetic resonance (M)-guided stereotactic radiation on a single arm prospective study, the
      investigators propose to compare this technique to online MR-guided stereotactic body
      radiation therapy (SBRT) without adaptation. Online plan adaptation increases treatment times
      for patients and comprises an increased burden on technical and clinical staff. Although
      preliminary trial results are encouraging, it remains unclear if the dosimetric benefits of
      online-adaptive planning studies will translate to measurable improvements in clinical
      outcomes that merit its routine use. In our preliminary study, plan adaptation was most often
      required when tumors were adjacent to the gastrointestinal tract (the esophagus to the
      sigmoid colon), as those structures were most commonly the dose-limiting structures and were
      noted to change in location on a day-to-day basis. For these reasons, abdominal disease sites
      have historically highlighted the limitations of SBRT. Specifically, the investigators will
      enroll patients with oligometastatic or unresectable primary disease of the non-liver abdomen
      to a randomized, prospective trial.

      Patients will be randomized to one of two treatment arms, in which they will receive either
      online-adaptive, MRI-guided SBRT or non-adaptive MRI-guided SBRT. Both patient groups will
      undergo MRI simulation and MRI treatment localization with online MR monitoring and/or
      gating. All patients will be treated in five fractions over one to two weeks. By adhering to
      strict normal tissue constraints, the investigators expect toxicity to be within the current
      standard of care for the non-adaptive arm, with reduction in toxicity in the arm of patients
      who undergo adaptation based on daily anatomic changes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 19, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of grade 3 or greater toxicity occurring in patients receiving online, adaptive, MRI-guided SBRT to the abdomen and in patients receiving non-adaptive SBRT</measure>
    <time_frame>Up through 6 months post-treatment (approximately 6 months and 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The descriptions and grading scales found in the revised NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0 will be utilized for all toxicity reporting.
Grade 3 or higher toxicities that did not predate SBRT and are probably or definitely attributable to treatment
Statistical analysis will be powered to detect a reduction of toxicity from 35% Grade 3 or greater toxicity to 10% Grade 3 or greater toxicity using online-adaptive therapy. Statistical analysis will be one-sided test for independent proportions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response rate utilizing tests for proportion</measure>
    <time_frame>At six month follow-up (approximately 6 months and 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Complete Response (CR): Disappearance of the target lesion. Any pathological lymph nodes (whether target or non-target) must have reduction in short axis to &lt;10 mm.
Partial Response (PR): At least a 30% decrease in the (sum of the) diameter of the target lesion(s), taking as reference the baseline sum diameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At six month follow-up (approximately 6 months and 2 weeks)-up</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first.
Progressive Disease (PD): At least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study (this includes the baseline sum if that is the smallest on study). In addition to the relative increase of 20%, the sum must also demonstrate an absolute increase of at least 5 mm.
Utilizing Kaplan-Meier methodology</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease free survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At six month follow-up (approximately 6 months and 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The length of time, after treatment ends, that the participants survives without any signs or symptoms of cancer
Utilizing Kaplan-Meier methodology.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At six month follow-up (approximately 6 months and 2 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>-Utilizing Kaplan-Meier methodology.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported quality of life as measured by EORTC QLQ-C30 criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, six-weeks post treatment, and six months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Utilize both paired t-tests and repeated measures ANOVA to analyze QOL data
The QLQ-C30 is composed of both multi-item scales and single-item measures. These include five functional scales, three symptom scales, a global health status / QoL scale, and six single items.
Each of the multi-item scales includes a different set of items - no item occurs in more than one scale.
All of the scales and single-item measures range in score from 0 to 100. A high scale score represents a higher response level. Thus a high score for a functional scale represents a high / healthy level of functioning, a high score for the global health status / QoL represents a high QoL, but a high score for a symptom scale / item represents a high level of symptomatology / problems.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Pancreas Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Cancer of the Pancreas</condition>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Online-Adaptive MRI-guided SBRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will be initially planned for stereotactic body radiation therapy to a minimum dose of 50Gy in five fractions to the planning target volume (PTV)
Radiotherapy will consist of stereotactic body therapy, to be given over five fractions, delivered once daily or once every other day for a period of one to two weeks, for a total of five treatments
All patients will undergo both CT and MRI simulation in positioning appropriate for the specific treatment site
When patients present for their first SBRT treatment session, the treating physician will evaluate their individual anatomy to determine if adaptive planning is indicated. Patients randomized to the online-adaptive treatment planning arm will have all tumor volumes and critical structures within 3 axial slices of the PTV re-contoured on the MR-localization image of the day
Quality of life questionnaire baseline, 6 weeks after treatment conclusion, and 6 months after treatment conclusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Online non-adaptive MRI-guided SBRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will be initially planned for stereotactic body radiation therapy to a minimum dose of 50Gy in five fractions to the planning target volume (PTV)
Radiotherapy will consist of stereotactic body therapy, to be given over five fractions, delivered once daily or once every other day for a period of one to two weeks, for a total of five treatments
All patients will undergo both CT and MRI simulation in positioning appropriate for the specific treatment site
Quality of life questionnaire baseline, 6 weeks after treatment conclusion, and 6 months after treatment conclusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Online, adaptive MR-guided SBRT</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients randomized to the online-adaptive treatment planning arm will have all tumor volumes and critical structures within 3 axial slices of the PTV re-contoured on the MR-localization image of the day. The estimated delivered dose should be calculated using the software on the console. An adapted radiation therapy plan should be generated</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Online-Adaptive MRI-guided SBRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Online, non-adaptive MR-guided SBRT</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will not have online-adaptive treatment planning</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Online non-adaptive MRI-guided SBRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) QLQ-30</intervention_name>
    <description>30 questions
28 questions about various health issues with answers ranging from 1=Not At All to 4 = Very Much
1 question asking about overall health with answers ranging from 1=very poor to 7 excellent
1 question asking about overall quality of life with answers ranging from 1=very poor to 7=excellent</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Online-Adaptive MRI-guided SBRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Online non-adaptive MRI-guided SBRT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EORTC QLQ-30</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Oligometastatic disease or unresectable primary abdominal malignancy with
             biopsy-proven primary disease histology of solid tumor categorization. Patients with a
             diagnosis of hepatocellular carcinoma do not require a biopsy.

          -  No more than three progressive sites of disease, with at least one of the disease
             sites to be deemed suitable for treatment with MRI-guided, online adaptive SBRT to the
             non-liver abdomen as per radiation oncology evaluation.

          -  Must be treated per protocol to lesion(s) of a single abdominal site that can
             reasonably be encompassed within a single treatment field. Treatment of additional
             site(s) outside of the abdomen while the patient is on trial is acceptable.

          -  The treated lesion must be within 2 cm of the abdominal gastrointestinal tract
             (abdominal esophagus to sigmoid colon) on the basis of cross sectional imaging study
             such as computed tomography (CT), positron emission tomography (PET)/CT, or MRI.

          -  Must be deemed medically fit for SBRT by the treating physician.

          -  At least 18 years of age.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Must have completed any systemic therapy at least one week prior to planned start of
             SBRT (two weeks preferred), and must have no plans to initiate systemic therapy for at
             least one week following end of SBRT (two weeks preferred).

          -  Women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control, abstinence) prior to study entry and for
             the duration of study participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is
             pregnant while participating in this study, she must inform her treating physician
             immediately.

          -  Able to understand and willing to sign an Institutional Review Board (IRB) approved,
             written informed consent document (or that of legally authorized representative, if
             applicable).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary disease of hematologic origin, lymphoma, or small cell cancer.

          -  Past history of external beam radiotherapy within the projected treatment field of any
             of the disease sites to be treated by MRI-guided, online adaptive SBRT.

          -  Currently receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, or cardiac
             arrhythmia.

          -  Pregnant and/or breastfeeding. Patient must have a negative pregnancy test within 14
             days of study entry.

          -  Medical contraindication to undergoing MR imaging.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Parag Parikh, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Parag Parikh, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(314) 362-9703</phone>
    <email>parikh@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Percy Lee, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>310-825-9771</phone>
      <email>percylee@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Percy Lee, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dan Low, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Parag Parikh, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-9703</phone>
      <email>parikh@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Parag Parikh, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olga Green, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Bassetti, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>608-263-8500</phone>
      <email>bassetti@humonc.wisc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Bassetti, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Bayouth, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 27, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

