<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02955784</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>215019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02955784</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sinasprite: A Pilot Feasibility Study for Patients With Anxiety or Stress</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sinasprite: A Pilot Feasibility Study of a Casual Game for Primary Care Patients With Mild Stress, Anxiety or Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Madigan Army Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Madigan Army Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators are proposing a prospective one-arm cohort study testing the feasibility of
      a game designed to improve symptoms in adults with mild levels of stress, depression, and
      anxiety. The study will take place at Madigan Army Medical Center. Primary outcomes include
      usage data including time, frequency and duration of app use, participant satisfaction with
      the game, and comments and suggestions regarding participants' experiences using the
      Sinasprite game over a 12-week period. Participants will download Litesprite's game,
      Sinasprite, onto their personal smartphone. Elements of cognitive-behavioral therapies like
      cognitive strategies, diaphragmatic breathing, and visualization are embedded in the game
      enabling participants to learn to achieve the desired healthy habits. The game's goal is to
      help Socks the Fox become a Zen Master. Over six weeks, players help Socks to progress by
      describing and categorizing their concerns, entrusting Socks to &quot;hold&quot; these concerns, and
      engaging in bonding activities with Socks, such as fishing and meditation. The investigators
      currently have a prototype and have been told by insurance firms, providers, and self-funded
      employers that they need to see validated results from a pilot study that shows feasibility
      with subjects in the target audience before they can consider a commercial roll out.
      Participants will complete questions related to mood, stress, and well-being at baseline, 6
      weeks, and 12 weeks. Data will be evaluated in real-time and reports of participant progress
      will be provided to the participant's provider, with the participant's consent. Data and
      feedback from this pilot study will be used to update the design and inform the technical
      development team to further refine the game experience in preparation for a larger randomized
      controlled trial evaluating the effectiveness of Sinasprite.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the U.S. anxiety disorders cost over $55 billion, and major depression is second only to
      back and neck pain for having the greatest impact on disability days at 386.6 million
      days/year. Primary care providers (PCPs) are overwhelmingly responsible for screening and
      treating their patients for behavioral health conditions such as depression and anxiety, and
      approximately 70-80% of antidepressants are prescribed in primary care. Nearly 17% of the
      population will experience depression at some point in their lifetime, but of those treated
      for depression in the primary care setting, only 20-40% show substantial improvement over 12
      months. Insurance companies spend $1 trillion annually on behavioral health conditions. $250
      billion is spent on our target segment - those with high stress or mild to moderate
      depression/anxiety, but no serious mental illness requiring intensive or inpatient treatment.
      These populations have significantly adopted and use mobile technologies for health purposes.
      Current solutions, like AppsRx, ORCAS, or SuperBetter, are clinically-focused or, at best,
      use game elements as opposed to a full gaming experience and do not target payers or
      hospitals. LinkedWellness has a true gaming experience for anxiety/depression, but their
      target audience is solely focused on teens. None of these incorporate the player's social
      networks, biosensors, collect information from the phone, or provide predictive insights.
      Therefore, tools to enhance management of these patients in a primary care setting, such as
      the casual health-related game Sinasprite, may improve treatment of difficult-to-manage
      behavioral health conditions. The investigators are proposing a prospective one-arm cohort
      study testing the feasibility of a game designed to improve symptoms in adults with mild
      levels of stress, depression, and anxiety. The study will take place at Madigan Army Medical
      Center. Primary outcomes include usage data including time, frequency and duration of app
      use, participant satisfaction with the game, and comments and suggestions regarding
      participants' experiences using the Sinasprite game over a 12-week period. Participants will
      download Litesprite's game, Sinasprite, onto their personal smartphone. Elements of
      cognitive-behavioral therapies like cognitive strategies, diaphragmatic breathing, and
      visualization are embedded in the game enabling players to learn to achieve the desired
      healthy habits. The game's goal is to help Socks the Fox become a Zen Master. Over six weeks,
      players help Socks to progress by describing and categorizing their concerns, entrusting
      Socks to &quot;hold&quot; these concerns, and engaging in bonding activities with Socks, such as
      fishing and meditation. The investigators currently have a prototype and have been told by
      insurance firms, providers, and self-funded employers that they need to see validated results
      from a pilot study that shows feasibility with subjects in the target audience before they
      can consider a commercial roll out. Participants will complete questions related to mood,
      stress, and well-being at baseline, 6 weeks, and 12 weeks. Data will be evaluated in
      real-time and reports of participant progress will be provided to the participant's provider,
      with the participant's consent. Data and feedback from this pilot study will be used to
      update the design and inform the technical development team to further refine the game
      experience in preparation for a larger randomized controlled trial evaluating the
      effectiveness of Sinasprite.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 22, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction. These data will be collected via questionnaire at the end of the study only</measure>
    <time_frame>12 wks</time_frame>
    <description>Data is via a standardized satisfaction questionnaire developed by the authors that is a mixture of open ended and likert scale questions on satisfaction with the app.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of perceived stress (PSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre/post (0, 6 and 12 wks)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete the 10 item perceived stress scale (PSS validated questionnaire) at 0, 6 and 12 wks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (LiSAT-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre/post (0, 6 and 12 wks)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete the LiSAT-9 validated questionnaire at 0, 6, and 12 weeks to assess their quality of life during the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom reports: measure of depression symptoms (PHQ-9 score)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre/post (0, 6, and 12 wks)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete the 9 item PHQ-9 validated questionnaire at 0, 6, and 12 wks to assess participant symptoms of self-reported depression during the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom reports: measure of anxiety symptoms (GAD-7 score)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre/post (0, 6, and 12 wks)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete the 7 item GAD-7 validated questionnaire at 0, 6, and 12 wks to assess participant symptoms of self-reported anxiety during the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of coping self-efficacy (CSE) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre/post (0, 6 and 12 wks)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete the 26 item coping self-efficacy (CSE) validated questionnaire at 0, 6 and 12 wks to assess their coping self-efficacy during the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>App daily usage (minutes/day)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 wks</time_frame>
    <description>Time (minutes per day) app was used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>App frequency usage (days/week)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 wks</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency (days/week) app was used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>App duration of usage (total weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 wks</time_frame>
    <description>Weeks app was used</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sinasprite Mobile App</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mobile App</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sinasprite Mobile App</intervention_name>
    <description>Mobile App</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sinasprite Mobile App</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18 years or older

          2. Eligible to receive care at a MHS clinic

          3. English-speaking

          4. In possession of a personal smartphone capable of downloading the Sinasprite
             application for use during the study

          5. Self-reported PHQ-9 score ≤ 10 and no self-reported suicidal or homicidal ideation

          6. Self-reported GAD-7 score ≤ 10 and no self-reported suicidal or homicidal ideation

          7. No change in antidepressant or antianxiety medication and/or dosage in past 3 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Under 18 years of age

          2. English insufficient to interact with the game or complete assessments

          3. Residing in an institution or other living situation where health care decisions are
             not made by the participant (e.g., hospitalized, prisoners, people living in a
             rehabilitation facility)

          4. Self-reported PHQ-9 score &gt; 10 or self-reported suicidal or homicidal ideation

          5. Self-reported GAD-7 score &gt; 10 or self-reported suicidal or homicidal ideation

          6. Change in antidepressant or antianxiety medication and/or dosage in past 3 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Douglas M Maurer, DO, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>253-968-2911</phone>
    <email>douglas.m.maurer.mil@mail.mil</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Madigan Army Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tacoma</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Douglas M Maurer, DO, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>253-968-2911</phone>
      <email>douglas.m.maurer.mil@mail.mil</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 6, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Study still in data collection process</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

