<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02953743</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E7080-C086-107</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02953743</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetic Study of E7080/Lenvatinib in Chinese Patients With Unresectable Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetic Study of E7080/Lenvatinib in Chinese Patients With Unresectable Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eisai Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eisai Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to assess the single- and multiple-dose pharmacokinetic
      (PK) profile of lenvatinib in Chinese participants with unresectable Hepatocellular Carcinoma
      (HCC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 28, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean maximum observed concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 2 at pre-dose; Day 8 at pre-dose; Day 15 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 16 at pre-dose; and Day 22 at pre-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean time at which the highest drug concentration occurs (tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 2 at pre-dose; Day 8 at pre-dose; Day 15 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 16 at pre-dose; and Day 22 at pre-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean area under the concentration-time curve from zero time to time of last quantifiable concentration (AUC(0-t))</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 2 at pre-dose; Day 8 at pre-dose; Day 15 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 16 at pre-dose; and Day 22 at pre-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean maximum observed concentration at steady-state (Css,max )</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 2 at pre-dose; Day 8 at pre-dose; Day 15 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 16 at pre-dose; and Day 22 at pre-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean minimum observed concentration at steady-state (Css,min)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 2 at pre-dose; Day 8 at pre-dose; Day 15 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 16 at pre-dose; and Day 22 at pre-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average steady-state concentration (Css,av)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 2 at pre-dose; Day 8 at pre-dose; Day 15 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 16 at pre-dose; and Day 22 at pre-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean time at which the highest drug concentration occurs at steady-state (tss,max)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 2 at pre-dose; Day 8 at pre-dose; Day 15 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 16 at pre-dose; and Day 22 at pre-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean area under the concentration-time curve over the dosing interval on multiple dosing (AUC(0-τ))</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 2 at pre-dose; Day 8 at pre-dose; Day 15 at pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours; Day 16 at pre-dose; and Day 22 at pre-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after the administration of the last dose of study drug or up to approximately 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Unresectable Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lenvatinib 12 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants weighing ≥ 60 kg will be enrolled in this arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lenvatinib 8 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants weighing &lt; 60 kg will be enrolled in this arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenvatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Lenvatinib 4 mg capsules will be administered orally, once daily continuously 28-day cycles until disease progression, development of unacceptable toxicity or withdrawal of consent.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenvatinib 12 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Lenvatinib 8 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Participants must have confirmed diagnosis of unresectable Hepatocellular Carcinoma
             (HCC) with any of the following criteria:

               1. Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of HCC

               2. Clinically confirmed diagnosis of HCC according to American Association for the
                  Study of Liver Diseases (AASLD) criteria, including cirrhosis of any etiology or
                  with chronic hepatitis B or C infection criteria

          2. Participants categorized to stage B (not applicable for transarterial
             chemoembolization [TACE]) or stage C based on Barcelona Clinic Liver Cancer (BCLC)
             staging system

          3. Adequate bone marrow function, defined as:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 × 10^9/Liter (L)

               2. Hemoglobin (Hb) ≥ 8.5 gram per deciliter (g/dL)

               3. Platelet count ≥ 75 × 10^9/L

          4. Adequate liver function, defined as:

               1. Albumin ≥ 2.8 g/dL

               2. Bilirubin ≤ 3.0 milligram per deciliter (mg/dL)

               3. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), and alanine
                  aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 5 × the upper limit of normal (ULN)

          5. Adequate blood coagulation function, defined as international normalized ratio (INR) ≤
             2.3

          6. Adequate renal function defined as creatinine clearance &gt; 40 milliliter per min
             (mL/min) calculated per the Cockcroft-Gault formula

          7. Adequately controlled blood pressure (BP) with up to 3 antihypertensive agents,
             defined as systolic BP ≤ 150 millimeter of mercury (mm Hg) and diastolic BP ≤ 90 mm Hg
             at screening and no change in antihypertensive therapy within 1 week prior to the
             registration.

          8. Child-Pugh A (score 5-6)

          9. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)- performance status (PS) 0 or 1

         10. Survival expectation of 12 weeks or longer after starting study drug

         11. Males or females aged at least 18 years at the time of informed consent.

         12. Females must not be lactating or pregnant at Screening or Baseline (as documented by a
             negative beta-human chorionic gonadotropin [Beta-hCG] test with a minimum sensitivity
             of 25 International Unit/Liter [IU/L] or equivalent units of beta-hCG). A separate
             baseline assessment is required if a negative screening pregnancy test was obtained
             more than 72 hours before the first dose of study drug.

         13. All females will be considered to be of childbearing potential unless they are
             postmenopausal (amenorrheic for at least 12 consecutive months, in the appropriate age
             group and without other known or suspected cause) or have been sterilized surgically
             (ie, bilateral tubal ligation, total hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy, all with
             surgery at least one month before dosing).

         14. Females of childbearing potential must not have had unprotected sexual intercourse
             within 30 days before study entry and must agree to use a highly effective method of
             contraception (eg, total abstinence, an intrauterine device, a double-barrier method
             [such as condom plus diaphragm with spermicide], a contraceptive implant, an oral
             contraceptive, or have a vasectomized partner with confirmed azoospermia) throughout
             the entire study period and for 30 days after study drug discontinuation. If currently
             abstinent, the participant must agree to use a double barrier method as described
             above if she becomes sexually active during the study period or for 30 days after
             study drug discontinuation. Females who are using hormonal contraceptives must have
             been on a stable dose of the same hormonal contraceptive product for at least 4 weeks
             before dosing and must continue to use the same contraceptive during the study and for
             30 days after study drug discontinuation.

         15. Male participants must have had a successful vasectomy (confirmed azoospermia) or they
             and their female partners must meet the criteria above (ie, not of childbearing
             potential or practicing highly effective contraception throughout the study period and
             for 30 days after study drug discontinuation). No sperm donation is allowed during the
             study period and for 30 days after study drug discontinuation.

         16. Provide written informed consent

         17. Willing and able to comply with all aspects of the protocol as judged by the
             Investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Imaging findings for HCC corresponding to any of the following:

               1. HCC with ≥50% liver occupation

               2. Clear invasion into the bile duct

               3. Portal vein invasion at the main portal branch (Vp4)

          2. Participants who have received lenvatinib

          3. Participants who have received any anti-cancer therapy (including surgery,
             percutaneous ethanol injection, radio frequency ablation, transarterial [chemo]
             embolization, hepatic intra-arterial chemotherapy, biological, immunotherapy,
             hormonal, any investigational drugs or radiotherapy) or any blood enhancing treatment
             (including blood transfusion, blood products, or agents that stimulate blood cell
             production, eg, granulocyte colony-stimulating factor [G-CSF]) within 28 days prior to
             registration.

          4. Participants who have not recovered from toxicities as a result of prior anticancer
             therapy except alopecia and infertility. Recovery is defined as &lt; Grade 2 severity per
             Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events Version 4.0 (CTCAE v4.0).

          5. Significant cardiovascular impairment: history of congestive heart failure greater
             than New York Heart association (NYHA) Class II, unstable angina, myocardial
             infarction or stroke within 6 months of the first dose of study drug, or cardiac
             arrhythmia requiring medical treatment at screening

          6. Prolongation of Q wave and T wave interval corrected by the Fridericia formula (QTcF)
             interval to &gt; 480 milli second (msec)

          7. Gastrointestinal malabsorption, or any other condition in the opinion of the
             investigator that might affect the absorption of lenvatinib

          8. Bleeding or thrombotic disorders or use of anticoagulants requiring therapeutic INR
             monitoring, eg, warfarin or similar agents. Treatment with low molecular weight
             heparin and factor X inhibitors which do not require INR monitoring is permitted.
             Antiplatelet agents are prohibited throughout the study.

          9. Gastrointestinal bleeding event within 28 days prior to registration

         10. Gastric or esophageal varices that require interventional treatment within 28 days
             prior to randomization. Prophylaxis with pharmacologic therapy (eg, nonselective
             beta-blocker) is permitted.

         11. Active hemoptysis (bright red blood of at least 0.5 teaspoon) within 28 days prior to
             registration

         12. Active malignancy (except for HCC or definitively treated melanoma in-situ, basal or
             squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or carcinoma in-situ of the cervix) within the
             past 36 months from registration.

         13. Any history of or current brain or subdural metastases

         14. Participants having &gt; 1+ proteinuria on urine dipstick testing will undergo 24h urine
             collection for quantitative assessment of proteinuria. Participants with urine protein
             ≥ 1 gram (g)/24 hour (h) will be ineligible.

         15. Surgical arterial-portal venous shunt or arterial-venous shunt.

         16. Any medical or other condition that in the opinion of the investigator would preclude
             participation in a clinical study

         17. Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive, or active infection requiring treatment
             (except for hepatitis virus)

         18. History of drug or alcohol dependency or abuse within approximately 2 years prior to
             registration.

         19. Any participant who cannot be evaluated by dynamic CT because of allergic reaction to
             contrast agent of CT.

         20. Major surgery within 3 weeks prior to registration or scheduled for surgery during the
             study

         21. Participant who has had a liver transplant.

         22. Participants whose only tumor lesion(s) is in bone will be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harbin Medical University Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harbin</city>
        <state>Heilongjiang</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shanghai Cancer Hospital, Fudan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zhongshan Hospital Fudan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 3, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>E7080</keyword>
  <keyword>Lenvatinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetic study</keyword>
  <keyword>Chinese participants</keyword>
  <keyword>Unresectable Hepatocellular Carcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenvatinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

