<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02955927</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSEARS20160406005/UW 16-404</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02955927</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combined Atropine With Orthokeratology in Childhood Myopia Control (AOK) -A Randomized Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Combined Atropine With Orthokeratology in Childhood Myopia Control (AOK) -A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to compare effects in retardation of myopia progression of combined ortho-k
      and 0.01% atropine therapy with those of ortho-k alone.Myopia control methods mainly focus on
      optical and pharmaceutical interventions . Currently, overnight-wear orthokeratology
      (ortho-k), is used extensively in Hong Kong with approximately 50% retardation effect.
      Pharmaceutical methods have focused on the use of atropine eye drops to slow myopic
      progression.The use of 1% atropine was limited by the manifestation of side effects and
      rebound effect.However, both side effect and rebound effect was minimal with 0.01%
      atropine.It was suggested that 0.01% was the optimum concentration for controlling myopia.The
      mechanisms of neither ortho-k nor atropine in myopia control are fully understood.It is
      believed that ortho-k and atropine act via different mechanisms.It is possible that by
      combining these two methods, additional retardation of myopia progression could be achieved.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although it is believed that myopia is the result of an interplay between genetic and
      environmental factors and its progression has been attributed to the lack of outdoor
      activities and intensive school work, myopia control methods mainly focus on optical and
      pharmaceutical interventions. Use of bifocal and multifocal lenses have been shown to be
      ineffective in myopia control. Specially designed soft contact lenses for myopia control have
      recently been launched, but their effectiveness has yet to be confirmed. Currently,
      overnight-wear orthokeratology (ortho-k), which involves reshaping the cornea by overnight
      wear allowing for improved, frequently unaided, vision during the day, is used extensively in
      Hong Kong. Approximately 50% retardation in axial length elongation was observed in studies
      of patients receiving ortho-k (LORIC study, 46%, ROMIO study,43%, and TO-SEE study, 52%).

      Pharmaceutical methods have focused on the use of atropine eye drops to slow myopic
      progression. The use of 1% atropine was first suggested in the 1990's, but its application
      was limited by the manifestation of side effects such as pupil dilatation and loss of
      accommodation. The effectiveness of lower concentrations (0.5%, 0.1% and 0.01%) have been
      evaluated in a recent five-year randomized clinical trial, where the authors reported that
      0.01% atropine once daily was effective resulting in about 50% of spherical equivalent
      reduction. However, this was as a result of one year (3rd year) discontinuation of atropine
      in the five-year study. Rebound effect was minimal with 0.01% atropine and higher dosages
      were associated with more manifest rebound effects, which appeared to negate former myopia
      retardation effects. Only 24% of those receiving 0.01% progressed 0.50D or more after
      discontinuation for one year. By contrast, proportion of children progressed 0.50D or more in
      0.5% and 0.1% groups were 59% and 68% respectively. Moreover, use of 0.01% atropine showed
      sustained myopia reduction with clinically negligible effects on pupil dilatation and loss of
      accommodation. The authors suggested the use of 0.01% as the optimum concentration for
      controlling myopia.

      The mechanisms of neither ortho-k nor atropine in myopia control are fully understood. It is
      believed that ortho-k and atropine act via different mechanisms, with ortho-k slowing myopia
      progression by reducing peripheral hyperopic defocus, while atropine exerts effects on
      anti-muscarinic receptors of the retina and sclera. However, some subjects respond poorly to
      either atropine or ortho-k, as demonstrated in clinical trials, suggesting that a single
      treatment may be not enough. It is possible that by combining these two methods, additional
      retardation of myopia progression could be achieved. In this randomized trial, we will
      explore the effectiveness of combination of ortho-k and atropine therapy, and evaluate
      additional effects by comparing the combination with ortho-k treatment alone.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in axial length in 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 months for a period of 2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Myopia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ortho-k and 0.01% atropine eye drops</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>participants will receive treatment of ortho-k and 0.01% atropine eye drops</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ortho-k</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>participants will receive treatment of ortho-k alone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0.01% atropine eye drops</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>ortho-k and 0.01% atropine eye drops</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ortho-k</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>ortho-k and 0.01% atropine eye drops</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ortho-k</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Manifest myopia between 1.00-4.00D in both eyes at screening visit

          -  Manifest astigmatism ≤2.50D; with-the-rule astigmatism (axes 180 ± 30) ≤2.50D;
             astigmatism with other axes ≤0.50D in both eyes at screening visit

          -  &lt;1.00D difference in manifest spherical equivalent (SE) between the two eyes at
             screening visit

          -  Baseline cycloplegic objective refraction between 1.00-4.00D in sphere; astigmatism
             ≤2.50D; &lt;1.00D difference in manifest SE between the two eyes

          -  Best-corrected logMAR visual acuity 0.10 or better in both eyes

          -  Symmetrical corneal topography with corneal toricity &lt;2.00D in either eye

          -  Normal ocular health other than myopia

          -  Agree to be randomized and to attend the scheduled visits and aftercare

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Contraindications to atropine: known allergies or cardiovascular disease, epilepsy

          -  Contraindications to contact lens wear and ortho-k: corneal scar, history of ocular
             inflammation/infection, limbus-to-limbus corneal cylinder and dislocated corneal apex

          -  Strabismus or amblyopia

          -  History of myopia control treatment (e.g. soft contact lenses, progressive add
             spectacles, atropine eye drops)

          -  Rigid contact lens (including ortho-k) wear experience

          -  Systemic condition which might affect refractive development (for example, Down
             syndrome, Marfan's syndrome)

          -  Ocular conditions which might affect refractive error (for example, cataract, ptosis)

          -  Poor response to lens wear including poor lens handling, poor vision and/ocular
             response after lens modifications

          -  Poor compliance with schedule visits
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pauline Pauline, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pauline Cho, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+852 27666100</phone>
    <email>pauline.cho@polyu.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Qi Tan, Master</last_name>
    <phone>+852 53926417</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>School of Optometry, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kowloon</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pauline Cho, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+852)27666100</phone>
      <email>sopaulin@inet.polyu.edu.hk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Qi Tan, Master</last_name>
      <phone>(+852)53926417</phone>
      <email>kiki.tan@connect.polyu.hk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pauline Cho, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pan CW, Ramamurthy D, Saw SM. Worldwide prevalence and risk factors for myopia. Ophthalmic Physiol Opt. 2012 Jan;32(1):3-16. doi: 10.1111/j.1475-1313.2011.00884.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22150586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lam CS, Lam CH, Cheng SC, Chan LY. Prevalence of myopia among Hong Kong Chinese schoolchildren: changes over two decades. Ophthalmic Physiol Opt. 2012 Jan;32(1):17-24. doi: 10.1111/j.1475-1313.2011.00886.x.</citation>
    <PMID>22150587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fan DS, Lai C, Lau HH, Cheung EY, Lam DS. Change in vision disorders among Hong Kong preschoolers in 10 years. Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2011 Jul;39(5):398-403. doi: 10.1111/j.1442-9071.2010.02470.x. Epub 2011 Feb 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21105971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morgan IG, Ohno-Matsui K, Saw SM. Myopia. Lancet. 2012 May 5;379(9827):1739-48. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60272-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22559900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berntsen DA, Sinnott LT, Mutti DO, Zadnik K. A randomized trial using progressive addition lenses to evaluate theories of myopia progression in children with a high lag of accommodation. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2012 Feb 13;53(2):640-9. doi: 10.1167/iovs.11-7769. Print 2012 Feb.</citation>
    <PMID>22205604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Correction of Myopia Evaluation Trial 2 Study Group for the Pediatric Eye Disease Investigator Group. Progressive-addition lenses versus single-vision lenses for slowing progression of myopia in children with high accommodative lag and near esophoria. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2011 Apr 25;52(5):2749-57. doi: 10.1167/iovs.10-6631.</citation>
    <PMID>21282579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pauné J, Morales H, Armengol J, Quevedo L, Faria-Ribeiro M, González-Méijome JM. Myopia Control with a Novel Peripheral Gradient Soft Lens and Orthokeratology: A 2-Year Clinical Trial. Biomed Res Int. 2015;2015:507572. doi: 10.1155/2015/507572. Epub 2015 Oct 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26605331</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cho P, Cheung SW, Edwards M. The longitudinal orthokeratology research in children (LORIC) in Hong Kong: a pilot study on refractive changes and myopic control. Curr Eye Res. 2005 Jan;30(1):71-80.</citation>
    <PMID>15875367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cho P, Cheung SW. Retardation of myopia in Orthokeratology (ROMIO) study: a 2-year randomized clinical trial. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2012 Oct 11;53(11):7077-85. doi: 10.1167/iovs.12-10565.</citation>
    <PMID>22969068</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen C, Cheung SW, Cho P. Myopia control using toric orthokeratology (TO-SEE study). Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2013 Oct 3;54(10):6510-7. doi: 10.1167/iovs.13-12527.</citation>
    <PMID>24003088</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chua WH, Balakrishnan V, Chan YH, Tong L, Ling Y, Quah BL, Tan D. Atropine for the treatment of childhood myopia. Ophthalmology. 2006 Dec;113(12):2285-91. Epub 2006 Sep 25.</citation>
    <PMID>16996612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chia A, Chua WH, Cheung YB, Wong WL, Lingham A, Fong A, Tan D. Atropine for the treatment of childhood myopia: safety and efficacy of 0.5%, 0.1%, and 0.01% doses (Atropine for the Treatment of Myopia 2). Ophthalmology. 2012 Feb;119(2):347-54. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2011.07.031. Epub 2011 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>21963266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chia A, Lu QS, Tan D. Five-Year Clinical Trial on Atropine for the Treatment of Myopia 2: Myopia Control with Atropine 0.01% Eyedrops. Ophthalmology. 2016 Feb;123(2):391-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2015.07.004. Epub 2015 Aug 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26271839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brodstein RS, Brodstein DE, Olson RJ, Hunt SC, Williams RR. The treatment of myopia with atropine and bifocals. A long-term prospective study. Ophthalmology. 1984 Nov;91(11):1373-9.</citation>
    <PMID>6514306</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu Y, Wildsoet C. The effective add inherent in 2-zone negative lenses inhibits eye growth in myopic young chicks. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2012 Jul 31;53(8):5085-93. doi: 10.1167/iovs.12-9628.</citation>
    <PMID>22761258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arumugam B, McBrien NA. Muscarinic antagonist control of myopia: evidence for M4 and M1 receptor-based pathways in the inhibition of experimentally-induced axial myopia in the tree shrew. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2012 Aug 24;53(9):5827-37. doi: 10.1167/iovs.12-9943.</citation>
    <PMID>22836762</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pauline Cho</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myopia control,ortho-k, atropine eye drops, children</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ophthalmic Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tetrahydrozoline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atropine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

