<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02956200</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>YAN-2016-047</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02956200</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combinating Fingolimod With Alteplase Bridging With Mechanical Thrombectomy in Acute Ischemic Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>FAMTAIS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomised Controlled Trial of Combinating an Immune Modulator Fingolimod With Alteplase Bridging With Mechanical Thrombectomy in Acute Ischemic Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Second Affiliated Hospital, School of Medicine, Zhejiang University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Proof-of concept clinical trials have indicated that the sphingosine-1-phosphate receptor
      modulator fingolimod may be efficacious in attenuating brain inflammation and improving
      clinical outcomes in patients with AIS as a single therapy beyond 4.5 hours of disease onset,
      or in combination with alteplase within 4.5 hours of disease onset. So in this study the
      investigators try to determine whether the addition of fingolimod, administered within 6
      hours after the onset of symptoms in patients receiving alteplase bridging with mechanical
      thrombectomy, improves radiologic and clinical outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, randomized, open-label, blinded endpoint (PROBE) design clinical
      trial, in multiple stroke centers of China. The total sample size will be 98. Patients being
      treated with standard alteplase bridging and mechanical thrombectomy will be randomly
      assigned in a 1:1 ratio to receive oral fingolimod or standard care. The primary outcome will
      be the salvaged ischemic tissue from baseline to day 7. AIS patients with proximal cerebral
      arterial occlusions will have CT perfusion (CTP) before treatment, and multimodal MRI
      including diffusion and MR perfusion (MRP) at 24 hours and 7 days after receiving treatment.
      Clinical outcomes will be assessed using the National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale score
      (NIHSS) at baseline, day 1 and day 7 and the modified Rankin Scale (mRS) at 90 days.
      Circulating lymphocyte counts will be monitored with FACS at baseline, day 1 and day 7 to
      confirm the biological activity of fingolimod.

      Patients aged between 18 and 85 with anterior circulation AIS who are eligible for alteplase
      and mechanical thrombectomy commenced within 6 hours of stroke onset will be enrolled if they
      present with an infarct core volume between 15-100 mL with at least 20% mismatch (as
      evaluated by CTP) and intracranial occlusion in proximal cerebral arteries. Exclusion
      criteria are (1) standard contraindications to alteplase or mechanical thrombectomy; (2)
      evidence of other diseases of the CNS; (3) pre-existing neurologic disability (a score
      greater than 2 on the mRS); (4) swallowing difficulties that would prevent administration of
      oral fingolimod; (5) patients with any history of bradyarrhythmia, atrioventricular block or
      current use of beta-blockers or verapamil; (6) concomitant use of antineoplastic,
      immunosuppressive or immune modulating therapies; (7) macular edema.

      As standard care, all patients will receive standard dose intravenous alteplase (0.9 mg per
      kilogram, the first 10% administered as an initial bolus and the remainder over a 1-hour
      period, with a maximum dose of 90 mg) and mechanical thrombectomy delivered at the site of
      intracranial vessel occlusion. Patients randomized to fingolimod will also receive oral
      fingolimod (Gilenya, Novartis) at a dosage of 0.5 mg once daily, for three consecutive days,
      with the first dose being given at the time in which patients are enrolled which is about one
      hour prior to mechanical thrombectomy.

      The kinetics of lymphocyte subset alteration will be monitored in whole-blood samples from
      all fingolimod- treated patients at the baseline, which will precede the first dose, day 1
      and day 7. Mononuclear cells will be isolated from the whole-blood specimens and stained with
      antibodies to CD4-FITC, CD8-PE, CD19-PerCP, CD56-PE (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ,
      USA). Data will be acquired using a FACS Caliber (Becton Dickinson Immunocytometry Systems,
      San Jose, CA, USA) and analyzed with Flow Jo software (Tree Star, Ashland, OR, USA).

      The primary outcome is salvaged ischemic tissue((baseline ischemic lesion - 7d infarction
      lesion)/ baseline ischemic lesion) from baseline to day 7. Secondary outcomes are the growth
      in infarct volume between 24 hour DWI and day 7 FLAIR imaging, the penumbral salvage volume
      (baseline hypoperfusion volume - 24-hours infarct volume) between the baseline and day 1, the
      frequency of parenchymal hemorrhage (PH) at day 1 and the extent of clinical improvement at
      day 1 as measured by the change on the NIHSS score from baseline to day 1, the extent of
      clinical improvement from day 1 to day 7. The tertiary outcomes are the probability of
      excellent recovery at day 90 (mRS 0-1), independent recovery (mRS 0-2) and ordinal analysis
      of the modified Rankin scale.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>salvaged ischemic tissue index (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 7 day</time_frame>
    <description>100*(baseline CTP ischemic lesion (mL) - 7 day DWI infarction lesion (mL))/ baseline CTP ischemic lesion (mL)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the growth in infarct volume (mL)</measure>
    <time_frame>from 24 hour to 7 day</time_frame>
    <description>24 hour DWI infarct volume (mL) - 7 day FLAIR infarct volume (mL)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the penumbral salvage volume (mL)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 1 day</time_frame>
    <description>(baseline CTP hypoperfusion volume (mL) - 24 hour DWI infarct volume (mL))</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the frequency of parenchymal hemorrhage (PH) (%)</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 1</time_frame>
    <description>the presence of PH is defined according the standard from ECASS-2 study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the change on the NIHSS score</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 1 day</time_frame>
    <description>baseline NIHSS score - 1 day NIHSS score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the change on the NIHSS score</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 7 day</time_frame>
    <description>baseline NIHSS score - 7 day NIHSS score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>excellent recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 90</time_frame>
    <description>modefied Rankin Scale (mRS) score of 0-1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>independent recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 90</time_frame>
    <description>mRS score of 0-2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>fingolimod with standard therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be treated with standard alteplase bridging and mechanical thrombectomy with fingolimod.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>standard therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be treated with standard alteplase bridging and mechanical thrombectomy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fingolimod</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients randomized to fingolimod will also receive oral fingolimod (Gilenya, Novartis) at a dosage of 0.5 mg once daily, for three consecutive days, with the first dose being given at the time in which patients are enrolled which is about one hour prior to mechanical thrombectomy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>fingolimod with standard therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fingolimod Hydrochloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients presenting with anterior circulation acute ischaemic stroke who are eligible
             for alteplase and mechanical thrombectomy commenced within 6 hours of stroke onset.

          2. Patient, family member or legally responsible person depending on local ethics
             requirements has given informed consent.

          3. Patient‟s age is 18-85 years.

          4. Arterial occlusion on CTA of the ICA, M1 or M2.

          5. Imaging inclusion criteria: infarct core volume between 15-100 mL with at least 20%
             mismatch (as evaluated by CTP).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Standard contraindications to alteplase or mechanical thrombectomy.

          2. Evidence of other diseases of the CNS.

          3. Pre-existing neurologic disability (a score greater than 2 on the mRS).

          4. Swallowing difficulties that would prevent administration of oral fingolimod.

          5. Patients with any history of bradyarrhythmia, atrioventricular block or current use of
             beta-blockers or verapamil.

          6. Patients with serious acute or chronic infection, or hepatic injury (over 3 times
             value of normal ALS or AST).

          7. Concomitant use of antineoplastic, immunosuppressive or immune modulating therapies.

          8. Macular edema.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Min Lou, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Second Affiliated Hospital of Zhejiang University, School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Min Lou, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <email>loumingxc@vip.sina.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The second affiliated hospital of Zhejiang University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hangzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>310000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 7, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fingolimod Hydrochloride</keyword>
  <keyword>Intravenous thrombolysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Mechanical thrombectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute ischemic stroke</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fingolimod Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tissue Plasminogen Activator</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

