<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03148795</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MDV3800-06</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>C3441006</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-002036-32</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03148795</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Talazoparib in Men With DNA Repair Defects and Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Talapro-1: A Phase 2, Open Label, Response Rate Study Of Talazoparib In Men With Dna Repair Defects And Metastatic Castration Resistant Prostate Cancer Who Previously Received Taxane Based Chemotherapy And Progressed On At Least 1 Novel Hormonal Agent (Enzalutamide And/or Abiraterone Acetate/Prednisone)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medivation, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pfizer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this international, phase 2, open-label, response rate study of talazoparib is
      to assess the efficacy and safety of talazoparib in men with DNA repair defects metastatic
      castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC) who previously received taxane-based chemotherapy
      and progressed on at least 1 novel hormonal agent (enzalutamide and/or abiraterone
      acetate/prednisone).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 4, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 3, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>The best ORR is defined as the proportion of patients with a best overall soft tissue response of CR (complete response) or PR (partial response) per RECIST 1.1 by independent central review.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to objective response</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>The time from enrollment to the first objective evidence of soft tissue response with no evidence of confirmed bone disease progression on bone scan per PCWG3.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of response is defined as the time from the first objective evidence of soft tissue response (subsequently confirmed) per RECIST 1.1 by independent central review and no evidence of confirmed bone disease progression per PCWG3 (the Prostate Cancer Clinical Trials Working Group 3) to the first subsequent objective evidence of radiographic progression or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with prostate-specific antigen (PSA) response ≥ 50%</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>PSA response will be calculated as a decline from baseline PSA (ng/mL) to the maximal PSA response with a threshold of 50%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with conversion of circulating tumor cell (CTC) count</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>The CTC count conversion rate will be defined as the proportion of patients with a CTC count ≥ 5 CTC per 7.5 mL of blood at study entry that decreases to &lt; 5 CTC per 7.5 mL of blood anytime on study. In addition, proportion of patients with a CTC count of 1 or more (detectable) per 7.5 mL of blood at study entry that decreases to CTC=0 (undetectable) per 7.5 mL of blood any time on study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to PSA progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>The time to PSA progression is defined as the time from enrollment to the date that a ≥ 25% increase in PSA with an absolute increase of ≥ 2 μg/L (2 ng/mL) above the nadir (or baseline for patients with no PSA decline) is documented, confirmed by a second consecutive PSA value obtained ≥ 3 weeks (21 days) later.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiographic progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>Radiographic PFS is defined as the time from enrollment to radiographic progression in soft tissue per RECIST 1.1 by independent central review, in bone per PCWG3 by independent central review, or death on study (defined as death within 168 days of study drug discontinuation without evidence of radiographic progression), whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from enrollment to death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported pain as assessed by the Brief Pain Inventory Short Form (BPI-SF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>Patient-reported pain assessed by the BPI-SF will be summarized descriptively by study visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported health-related quality of life as assessed by the European Quality of Life 5-Domain 5-Level Scale (EQ-5D-5L)</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>Patient-reported health-related quality of life assessed by the EQ-5D-5L will be summarized descriptively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as assessed by percentage of patients with any Adverse Event (AE), AE leading to Study Drug Discontinuation, AE leading to death, Serious Adverse Event (SAE), AE related to study drug, SAE related to study drug</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>All safety analyses will be performed using the safety population, defined as all patients in the ITT population who receive any amount of any study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) of talazoparib as assessed by trough plasma concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Anticipated in about 34 months following first patient enrolled</time_frame>
    <description>PK data analyses will include descriptive summary statistics of the predose Cmin and postdose concentrations of talazoparib by study visit for each treatment group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Talazoparib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Talazoparib 1 mg daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Talazoparib</intervention_name>
    <description>1 mg daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Talazoparib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MDV3800</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. At least 18 years of age.

          2. Histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate without
             signet cell, or small cell features.

          3. Patients must have measurable soft tissue disease per RECIST 1.1

          4. DNA damage repair deficiency as assessed centrally by a gene mutation biomarker panel
             (testing of de novo or archiaval tumor tissue (via central laboratory) or prior
             historical testing (with Sponsor approval) using the Foundation Medicine,
             FoundationOne® NGS gene panel test.

          5. Consent to a saliva sample collection for a germline comparator, unless prohibited by
             local regulations or ethics committee (EC) decision.

          6. Serum testosterone ≤ 1.73 nmol/L (50 ng/dL) at screening.

          7. Bilateral orchiectomy or ongoing androgen deprivation therapy with a
             gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) agonist/antagonist (surgical or medical
             castration).

          8. Progressive disease at study entry defined as 1 or more of the following 3 criteria:

               -  A minimum of 3 rising PSA values with an interval of at least 1 week between
                  determinations. The screening central laboratory PSA value must be ≥ 2 μg/L (2
                  ng/mL) if qualifying solely by PSA progression.

               -  Soft tissue disease progression as defined by RECIST 1.1.

               -  Bone disease progression defined by PCWG3 with 2 or more new metastatic lesions
                  on bone scan.

          9. Metastatic disease.

         10. Previous treatment with 1 or 2 chemotherapy regimens including at least 1 taxane-based
             regimen for metastatic (non castrate or castrate) prostate cancer. Patients may have
             received radium-223 and/or cabazitaxel, or were deemed unsuitable, declined, or did
             not have access to these therapies.

         11. Documented disease progression (either radiographic or biochemical) on at least 1
             novel hormonal therapy (enzalutamide and/or abiraterone acetate/prednisone) for the
             treatment of metastatic CRPC, irrespective of prior NHT treatment for non castrate
             prostate cancer or nonmetastatic (M0) CRPC.

         12. Bisphosphonate or denosumab dosage must have been stable for at least 4 weeks before
             day 1 for patients receiving these therapies.

         13. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 2.

         14. Estimated life expectancy of ≥ 6 months as assessed by the investigator.

         15. Able to swallow the study drug, have no known intolerance to study drugs or
             excipients, and comply with study requirements.

         16. Must use a condom when having sex with a pregnant woman from the time of the first
             dose of study drug through 105 days after last dose of study drug. An additional
             highly effective form of contraception must be used from the time of the first dose of
             study drug through 105 days after last dose of study drug when having sex with a non
             pregnant female partner of childbearing potential.

         17. Must agree not to donate sperm from the first dose of study drug to 105 days after the
             last dose of study drug.

         18. Patients must be willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan,
             laboratory tests and other study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. 1. Use of systemic chemotherapeutic (including but not limited to taxanes), hormonal,
             biologic, or radionuclide therapy for treatment of metastatic prostate cancer (other
             than approved bone targeting agents and GnRH agonist/antagonist) or any other
             investigational agent within 4 weeks before day 1.

          2. Prior treatment with a PARP inhibitor, cyclophosphamide, or mitoxantrone chemotherapy.
             Patients who discontinued prior platinum based chemotherapy &lt;=6 months prior to
             screening or whose disease previously progressed on platinum based therapy at any time
             in the past are also excluded.

          3. Treatment with any concurrent cytotoxic chemotherapy or investigational drug(s) within
             4 weeks or 5 half lives of the drug (whichever is longer) before Day 1 and/or during
             study participation

          4. Radiation therapy within 3 weeks (within 2 weeks, if single fraction of radiotherapy)
             before day 1.

          5. Major surgery within 2 weeks before day 1.

          6. Clinically significant cardiovascular disease.

          7. Significant renal, hepatic, or bone marrow organ dysfunction.

          8. Known or suspected brain metastasis or active leptomeningeal disease.

          9. Symptomatic or impending spinal cord compression or cauda equina syndrome.

         10. Diagnosis of MDS (Myelodysplastic syndromes).

         11. History of another cancer within 3 years before enrollment with the exception of
             nonmelanoma skin cancers, or American Joint Committee on Cancer stage 0 or stage 1
             cancer that has a remote probability of recurrence in the opinion of the investigator
             and the sponsor.

         12. Gastrointestinal disorder affecting absorption.

         13. Current or anticipated use of the following P gp inhibitors (amiodarone, carvedilol,
             clarithromycin, cobicistat, darunavir, dronedarone, erythromycin, indinavir,
             itraconazole, ketoconazole, lapatinib, lopinavir, propafenone, quinidine, ranolazine,
             ritonavir, saquinavir, telaprevir, tipranavir, verapamil, and valspodar), P gp
             inducers (avasimibe, carbamazepine, phenytoin, rifampin, and St. John's wort), or BCRP
             inhibitors (curcumin, cyclosporine, elacridar [GF120918] and eltrombopag).

         14. Any other acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition (concurrent disease,
             infection, or comorbidity) that interferes with ability to participate in the study,
             causes undue risk, or complicates the interpretation of data, in the opinion of the
             investigator or medical monitor, including recent (within the past year) or active
             suicidal ideation or behavior or laboratory abnormality that may increase the risk
             associated with study participation or investigational product administration or may
             interfere with the interpretation of study results and, in the judgment of the
             investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into this study.

         15. Investigator site staff members directly involved in the conduct of the study and
             their family members, site staff members otherwise supervised by the investigator, or
             patients who are Pfizer employees, including their family members, directly involved
             in the conduct of the study.

         16. Fertile male subjects who are unwilling or unable to use a highly effective method of
             contraception as outlined in this protocol for the duration of the study and for at
             least 105 days after the last dose of investigational product.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pfizer Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pfizer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pfizer Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-718-1021</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrials.gov_Inquiries@pfizer.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope (City of Hope National Medical Center, City of Hope Medical Center)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope Investigational Drug Service (IDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope-Antelope Valley</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lancaster</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>93534</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Piedmont Cancer Institute, PC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30318</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Piedmont Cancer Institute, PC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fayetteville</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30214</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Oncology Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hampton</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23666</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Oncology Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norfolk</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23502</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Product Shipment Edmonds</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonds</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98026</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Swedish Cancer Institute Edmonds Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonds</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98026</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Product Shipment Issaquah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Issaquah</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Swedish Cancer Institute Issaquah Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Issaquah</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Product Shipment</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Swedish Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Product Shipment Ballard</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Swedish Cancer Institute Ballard Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Swedish Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Trials Pharmacy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darlinghurst</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2010</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Vincents Hospital Sydney</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darlinghurst</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2010</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westmead Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Northmead</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2152</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westmead Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westmead</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2145</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icon Cancer Care Wesley</name>
      <address>
        <city>Auchenflower</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4066</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>River City Pharmacy (IP Shipment Address)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Auchenflower</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4066</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icon Cancer Care Chermside</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chermside</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4032</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icon Cancer Care South Brisbane</name>
      <address>
        <city>South Brisbane</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4101</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ion Cancer Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>South Brisbane</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4101</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icon Cancer Care Southport</name>
      <address>
        <city>Southport</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4215</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Box Hill Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Box Hill</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3128</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Monash Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clayton</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3168</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Olivia Newton John Cancer Wellness and Research Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3084</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pharmacy Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelbert</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3084</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cliniques Universitaires Saint-Luc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>1200</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Algemeen Ziekenhuis Sint-Lucas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Gasthuisberg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Besançon - Hôpital Jean Minjoz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Besancon Cedex</city>
        <state>Doubs</state>
        <zip>25030</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Strasbourg - Nouvel Hopital Civil</name>
      <address>
        <city>Strasbourg</city>
        <state>Rhone</state>
        <zip>67091</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Gustave-Roussy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif Cedex</city>
        <state>VAL DE Marne</state>
        <zip>94805</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IP Shipment address: CHRU Besancon-Hopital Jean Minjoz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Besancon</city>
        <zip>25030</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Bergonie (IP Address)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux cedex</city>
        <zip>33076</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Bergonie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <zip>33076</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Hospitalier Departmentemental Les Oudairies</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Roche sur Yon</city>
        <zip>85925</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IP Shipment address</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Roche sur Yon</city>
        <zip>85925</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Jean Bernard - Clinique Victor Hugo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Le Mans Cedex 02</city>
        <zip>72015</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IP Shipment address: Clinique Victor Hugo-Centre Jean Bernard</name>
      <address>
        <city>Le Mans Cedex 02</city>
        <zip>72015</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Civil - IP Address</name>
      <address>
        <city>Strasbourg</city>
        <zip>67091</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Foch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suresnes</city>
        <zip>92151</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IP Shipment address: Hopital Foch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suresnes</city>
        <zip>92151</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Sanitaria Ospedaliera S. Luigi Gonzaga</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orbassano (TO)</city>
        <zip>10043</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera San Camillo Forlanini</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00152</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboud UMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <state>THE Netherlands</state>
        <zip>6525 GA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radbound UMC - Apotheek,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <zip>6525 GA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Vall d'Hebron</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <state>Cataluna</state>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Quironsalud Madrid</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pozuelo de Alarcon</city>
        <state>Madrid</state>
        <zip>28223</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinica Universidad de Navarra Departamento de Oncologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Virgen de la Victoria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Malaga</city>
        <zip>29010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Vernon Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Northwood</city>
        <state>Middlesex</state>
        <zip>HA6 2RN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Marsden Foundation Trust Sutton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sutton</city>
        <state>Surrey</state>
        <zip>SM2 5PT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cambridge University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <zip>CB2 0QQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://trialinfoemail.pfizer.com/pages/landing.aspx?StudyID=MDV3800-06&amp;StudyName=A+Phase+2%2C+Open-label%2C+2-arm%2C+Response+Rate+Study+Of+Talazoparib+In+Men+With+Dna+Repair+Defects+And+Metastatic+Castration-resistant+Prostate+Cancer+Who+Previously+Received+Taxane-based+Chemotherapy+And+Progressed+On+At+Least+1+Novel+Hormonal+Agent+%28enzalutamide+And%2For+Abiraterone+Acetate%2Fprednisone%29</url>
    <description>To obtain contact information for a study center near you, click here.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://trialinfoemail.pfizer.com/pages/landing.aspx?StudyID=MDV3800-06&amp;StudyName=Talapro+1%3A+A+Phase+2%2C+Open+Label%2C+Response+Rate+Study+Of+Talazoparib+In+Men+With+Dna+Repair+Defects+And+Metastatic+Castration+Resistant+Prostate+Cancer+Who+Previously+Received+Taxane+Based+Chemotherapy+And+Progressed+On+At+Least+1+Novel+Hormonal+Agent+%28enzalutamide+And%2For+Abiraterone+Acetate%2Fprednisone%29</url>
    <description>To obtain contact information for a study center near you, click here.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://trialinfoemail.pfizer.com/pages/landing.aspx?StudyID=MDV3800-06&amp;StudyName=Talapro-1%3A+A+Phase+2%2C+Open+Label%2C+Response+Rate+Study+Of+Talazoparib+In+Men+With+Dna+Repair+Defects+And+Metastatic+Castration+Resistant+Prostate+Cancer+Who+Previously+Received+Taxane+Based+Chemotherapy+And+Progressed+On+At+Least+1+Novel+Hormonal+Agent+%28enzalutamide+And%2For+Abiraterone+Acetate%2Fprednisone%29</url>
    <description>To obtain contact information for a study center near you, click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Talazoparib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Information relating to our policy on data sharing and the process for requesting data can be found at the following link: http://www.pfizer.com/research/clinical_trials/trial_data_and_results/data_requests</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

