<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03149328</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00068365</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03149328</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Electronic Patient-Reported Outcomes in Clinical Kidney Practice (ePRO Kidney)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Electronic Patient-Reported Outcomes in Clinical Kidney Practice (ePRO Kidney)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cambian Business Services, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Intogrey Research and Development Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alberta Health Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      People living with end-stage kidney disease (ESKD) need dialysis or transplantation in order
      to stay alive. This illness and treatment significantly impact peoples' health, emotions,
      work and relationships. To promote person-centred care, healthcare professionals should be
      asking patients about what matters to them and using this feedback to plan and deliver care.
      Patient-reported outcome and experience questionnaires (jointly referred to as PROs) allow
      patients to provide information about their quality of life, symptoms and experiences with
      care. PROs are increasingly used to help healthcare professionals learn about what is
      important to patients and the impacts of illness or treatments from patients' point of view.
      Embedding feedback from patients into routine clinical practice is important in end-stage
      kidney disease because of the physical and quality of life challenges these patients face
      when living with kidney failure.

      PROs provide vital and often missing information that the healthcare team can use to support
      patients. However, PROs administered via paper questionnaires have been perceived as
      cumbersome, difficult to integrate with other health information and do not provide immediate
      feedback.

      In this research, home dialysis patients will have the opportunity to complete electronically
      administered PROs (ePROs) and healthcare professionals will receive education about how to
      use PRO information. The goal is to learn how to support healthcare professionals to
      routinely use this information to inform patient care, and see if this makes a difference in
      patients' symptoms, person-centred care, quality of life and satisfaction with care.

      Learning what matters most to patients is essential for healthcare professionals to provide
      person-centred care. This research will address the gap in our understanding of how to best
      use patients' reports in healthcare. Findings of this research may ultimately improve the
      quality of healthcare for Canadians living with end-stage kidney disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives:

        1. Understand the process of supporting clinicians to utilize PROs in multidisciplinary,
           home dialysis practice.

        2. Examine to what extent utilization of PRO information is associated with differences in
           symptoms and person-centred care [primary outcomes], as well as satisfaction with care,
           utilization of health services, mental health, and QOL [secondary outcomes].

      Approach:

      To achieve these goals, a mixed methods design of process evaluation will be used to compare
      two groups: Northern and Southern Alberta Renal Programs, NARP (Edmonton) and SARP (Calgary).
      In Edmonton (Intervention group), patients and clinicians will be invited to participate in
      the study. Only patients will be invited to take part in the study in Calgary (Comparison
      group). The research study will be undertaken collaboratively with a Patient Advisory
      Committee and knowledge users.

      Setting:

      This research will be conducted among patients receiving home dialysis across Alberta Kidney
      Care, from its two units: Aberhart Clinic in the Northern Alberta Renal Program (NARP), and
      Sheldon M. Chumir Health Centre in the Southern Alberta Renal Program (SARP). NARP and SARP
      have 305 and 350 home dialysis patients respectively.

      Methods:

      The study is divided into two phases: Phase 1-Year 1 (Usability Testing) and Phase 2-Year 2
      (Evaluation). SARP and NARP participants will be invited to complete ePROs for each of their
      scheduled appointments, every three months, throughout Phases 1 and 2.

      Phase 1:

      In NARP, the intervention group, interested patients will be approached and consent will be
      obtained. Before the clinic visit, the patient will complete a demographic survey, and the
      Edmonton Symptom Assessment Scale revised for renal patients (ESASr:Renal) using Cambian
      Navigator, a web-based ePRO system hosted by Cambian Business Services Inc. Survey results
      will be printed and given to the nurse, transcribed and placed in the patient' chart as well
      as on their electronic chart. NARP patients will also complete the Kidney Disease Quality of
      Life (KDQOL-36), the Patient Assessment of Care for Chronic Conditions (PACIC-20), and the
      EQ-5D-5L after their clinic appointment. These 3 outcome evaluation measures will not be
      included in patient charts, or be used by clinicians at point of care. Usability testing and
      formative evaluation with NARP patients will also include up to 5 focus groups and 10
      interviews to discuss how they would like their PRO information to be used by clinicians.
      Usability testing and formative evaluation with NARP multidisciplinary clinicians will
      include a series of focus groups (3-4) to discuss the ideal process for ePROs surveys to be
      integrated in existing work structures. Findings from these focus groups will be used to
      refine the targeted education sessions provided as an intervention in Phase 2.

      In SARP, the comparator group, all patients meeting inclusion criteria will be invited to
      complete the consent form, demographic survey, and the ePRO survey tools collected in NARP,
      but not to participate in focus groups and interviews. The ePRO surveys will not be seen by
      the clinicians, but they will be informed of the study.

      Phase 2:

      Using a prospective design, the educational sessions (intervention) will occur in NARP.
      Clinicians will receive ePRO feedback as well as targeted education about how to use PRO
      information. Education sessions will be offered every 3 months over the 1-year intervention
      period. Evaluation survey feedback will be sought at the end of each education session to
      tailor information to clinicians' needs. In NARP, patients will continue to complete the PRO
      surveys before and after their clinic appointments. If other PRO measures are requested by
      clinicians in Phase 1, these will be added to Phase 2 data collection. Additionally,
      clinicians will be asked to tick a box on the survey printouts indicating if they reviewed
      the PRO information, and changed their decision-making based on the PRO information. All NARP
      clinicians will also be invited to participate in 2 interviews. They will be asked to share
      examples of how they have used PRO information in their practice, and the challenges,
      benefits and facilitators of integrating ePROs in practice. Patient participants will also be
      invited to take part in a focus group (n=5) or interview (n=10) to discuss how they see
      clinicians following up on their PRO information.

      In SARP, clinicians will provide usual care. Clinicians will not receive PRO information or
      participate in education sessions. Education will be provide to SARP clinicians following
      completion of the study, as a form of knowledge translation.

      Quantitative Evaluation:

      Descriptive methods and statistical tests will be used to examine the trajectories of outcome
      measures for patients in the comparator and intervention groups. The area under the curve
      (AUC) will be calculated for each trajectory during the period that the patient is
      participating to create a summary score. Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) will be used as the
      method of analysis to compare AUC scores of outcomes of both groups while controlling for
      within- and between-group differences, such as comorbidities, gender, age and dialysis type.

      Qualitative Evaluation:

      Qualitative data from focus groups and interviews will be recorded, transcribed verbatim and
      analyzed using the methodology of interpretive description. NVIVO, a qualitative software
      system, will be used to create a filing system and coding database. The first focus
      group/interview transcript in each phase will be read and re-read to generate an initial
      codebook. The codebooks will be iteratively refined throughout the analysis. Codes will be
      categorized and analyzed thematically. Patient and clinician data will be analyzed
      separately. Differences between pre- and post-implementation in NARP will also be examined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 28, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Process evaluation with two phases (Phase 1: Usability Testing; Phase 2: Evaluation)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed using the symptoms/problems domain of the KDQOL-36</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Person-centred care</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed using the PACIC-20 scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Utilization of health services</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed using health services data (i.e., hospital admissions, trips to emergency room) determined through Alberta Health Services database</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with care</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed using one item added to the end of the PACIC-20 related to care received. This item is from the NHS Outpatient Survey (2011)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mental health</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed using the SF-12 mental component summary (MCS) subscale in the KDQOL-36</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed using the EQ-5D-5L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">459</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Disease, End-Stage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Northern Alberta Renal Program (NARP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Provide in NARP (intervention group), 1) an electronic tool (ePRO) that facilitates real time PRO data collection and feedback in clinical practice, and 2) educational support to multidisciplinary home dialysis clinicians about how to use PROs routinely in their practice.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Southern Alberta Renal Program (SARP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In SARP (comparator group), clinicians will not receive PRO feedback or education sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Educational Support</intervention_name>
    <description>In the intervention group, clinicians will be provided with PRO feedback for use in their clinical practice. They will also receive educational support on how to use PRO data at point of care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Northern Alberta Renal Program (NARP)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patient inclusion:

          -  home dialysis patients attending regularly scheduled appointments in Edmonton at the
             Aberhart Clinic (NARP) or in Calgary at the Sheldon M. Chumir Health Centre (SARP)

          -  ≥18 years old

          -  able to read and speak English

          -  can provide written informed consent

          -  if a patient changes dialysis modality, they can continue to participate

        Clinician inclusion:

          -  all clinical staff working with home dialysis patients at the Aberhart clinic in
             Edmonton (NARP)

          -  study co-investigators/collaborators who are NARP clinicians may choose to participate

        Patient exclusion criteria:

          -  visual impairment

          -  cannot read or speak English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kara Schick-Makaroff, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kara Schick-Makaroff, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>780-492-9043</phone>
    <email>Kara.schickmakaroff@ualberta.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Joanna Czupryn</last_name>
    <phone>780-248-1096</phone>
    <email>jczupryn@ualberta.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sheldon M. Chumir Health Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2R 0X7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kara Schick-Makaroff, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>780.492.9043</phone>
      <email>kara.schickmakaroff@ualberta.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aberhart Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2J3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kara Schick-Makaroff, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>780.492.9043</phone>
      <email>kara.schickmakaroff@ualberta.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alberta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kara Schick-Makaroff</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Home Dialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Person-Centred Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient-Reported Outcome Measures</keyword>
  <keyword>Process Evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>Educational Support</keyword>
  <keyword>Electronic Patient-Reported Outcome Measures</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient-Reported Experience Measures</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Upon completion of analysis, anonymous, quantitative data will be made available online indefinitely to the public on a database, such as Dataverse. Dataverse is a public repository and the University of Alberta provides the infrastructure support for sharing datasets. (See (http://dataverse.org/)</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

