<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03145272</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SI407/2016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03145272</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Population Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacogenomics of Oral Oxycodone in Thai Pediatric Surgical Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>PedPK</acronym>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacogenomics of Oral Oxycodone in Thai Pediatric Surgical Patients : a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mahidol University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mahidol University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed as an experimental trial which collect prospective data at Mahidol
      university. It aims to characterize the responses of Thai pediatric population,age 1 - 6
      years, to oxycodone oral syrup and its metabolites (oxymorphone, noroxymorphone and
      noroxycodone) with specific respect to the pharmacogenomics (How drug affects patients).

      A total of 20 generally healthy, opioid-naive children, aged 1-6 years, scheduled as
      in-patient surgery for non-emergency surgery, non-gastrointestinal tract surgery are
      involved.

      The patients are divide into 2 groups (1) 10 patients in 12 months - 1.9 years, and (2) 10
      patients in the 2 - 5.9 years age group.

      Every patient will receive inhalational or intravenous induction of anesthesia as decided by
      the anesthesia team on the day of surgery, as is routine clinical care. An intravenous
      cannula (IV) will be inserted in every patient as part of their routine clinical care. No
      additional intravenous line will be required for this study.

      As part of the study protocol, a blood sample (5 mL) will be taken from the IV and sent for
      genetic analysis. (However, in order to limit the amount of blood drawn from small babies, 3
      ml will be drawn, not 5 ml, if the patient is less than 6 months or less than 10kg.) The
      genetic testing is specifically to analyze the following genotypes only: CYP2D6 and CYP3A4,
      which represent the differences in cytochrome P450 metabolism of oxycodone.

      An orogastric tube will be placed in the stomach under anesthesia as is part of standard
      routine clinical care to remove gastric contents. The same orogastric tube will be used for
      intragastric liquid oxycodone administration in a dose of 0.1 mg/kg before the surgical
      incision. This weight-adjusted dose of 0.1 mg/kg is administered as per standard clinical
      dosing guidelines. 10 blood samples (51mL/sample) will be taken from the IV and sent for
      drug-level analysis. A total of 11 blood samples will be drawn for the study. The first
      sample will be sent for genetic testing. The other 10 samples will be drawn at the following
      time points: 30 minutes, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 hours post-dose in every patient and the
      other 2 samples anytime between 6 and 24 hours post-dose .

      Oxycodone, oxymorphone, noroxymorphone and noroxycodone levels, at 10 time points, will be
      used to determine the individual responses to oxycodone. CYP2D6 genotype will be determined
      to identify the ultra-rapid metabolizers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Oxycodone is the most commonly used analgesic for the management of moderate and severe
      postoperative pain. The efficacy of Oxycodone as a potent opioid has been confirmed in
      children.

      The principal metabolic pathway of oxycodone in humans is N-demethylation via enzyme CYP3A4
      to generate inactive noroxycodone. A smaller amount (approximately 11%) is O-demethylated by
      cytochrome P450 enzyme CYP2D6 to become oxymorphone, the active and potent metabolite which
      exhibits about 40 times the affinity and 8 times the potency on μ-opioid receptors compared
      to the mother substance. Approximate frequencies of cytochrome P450 enzyme CYP2D6 phenotypes
      for the Caucasian population are: poor metabolizers 5 - 10%, extensive/intermediate
      metabolizers 65-90%, and ultra-rapid metabolizers 5 - 10%. Kirchheiner and colleagues noticed
      more codeine-related sedative side-effects in ultra-rapid metabolizers. In studies
      investigating extensive and poor metabolizers, codeine side-effects do not seem to be related
      to CYP2D6 genotype. However, clinical investigations of CYP2D6 genotype in the postoperative
      pain setting have shown conflicting results, and well-designed prospective studies are
      lacking. Taken together, these results demonstrate the need for careful pharmacokinetic
      studies in children who received a pharmacologic agent, such as oxycodone, which is
      metabolized by the enzyme CYP2D6.

      The population PK of oxycodone and its metabolites has not been fully established for oral
      oxycodone in pediatric patients. In addition, there is a group of ultra-rapid metabolizers
      (approximately 4.5% of the population, but as high as 20% in some particular ethnic groups;
      East African and Saudi Arabian populations) which may be at risk for serious side effects in
      the commonly prescribed dose (which is extrapolated from adult recommendations). It is
      important to further investigate oral oxycodone to optimize dosing recommendations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics metric (serum level of oxycodone and its metabolites at different time points)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Oxycodone, oxymorphone, noroxymorphone and noroxycodone serum levels [ Time Frame: The 10 samples will be drawn at the following time points: 8 blood samples will be taken at 30 minutes, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 hours post-dose in every patient along other 2 samples at approximately either 8 and 12 or 10 and 24 hours post-dose. ] Oxycodone, oxymorphone, noroxymorphone and noroxycodone levels in blood (ng/ml), at 10 time points, will be used to determine the effects of single-dose oral oxycodone administration in children.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Pharmacokinetics</condition>
  <condition>Pharmacogenomics</condition>
  <condition>Oxycodone</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Age group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>An orogastric tube will be placed in the stomach (placement verified by routine accepted clinical guidelines) under anesthesia as is part of standard routine clinical care to remove gastric contents. The same orogastric tube will be used for intragastric liquid oxycodone administration in a dose of 0.1 mg/kg before the surgical incision. This weight-adjusted dose of 0.1 mg/kg is administered as per standard clinical dosing guidelines.
This arm can be divided into 2 subgroups; (1)12 months - 1.9 years age group. (2) 2 - 5.9 years age group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxycodone</intervention_name>
    <description>A single weight-adjusted oxycodone dose of 0.1 mg/kg is administered as per standard clinical dosing guidelines</description>
    <arm_group_label>Age group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inpatient who scheduled for non-emergency surgery

          -  Aged between 1 - 6 years

          -  Healthy volunteer

          -  Body weight more than 4.5 kilograms

          -  Opioid naive

          -  Schedule for pediatric non- GI tract surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently taking CYP 3A4 or CYP 2D6 inhibitors/inducers

          -  Known history of allergy to oxycodone

          -  Known GI, hepatic, or renal dysfunction

          -  Known sleep apnea or impaired respiratory reserve
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patcharee Srisawasdi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mahidol University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sirirat Rattanaarpa, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6681-909-9242</phone>
    <email>mednoonr@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Patcharee Srisawasdi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>662419-7989</phone>
    <email>pat.si.research@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 24, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pharmacogenomics</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Oxycodone</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oxycodone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

