<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03143049</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AMN003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03143049</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pomalidomide-Cyclophosphamide-Dexamethasone (PCD) Versus Pomalidomide-Dexamethasone (PD) in Relapse or Refractory Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Phase 3 Study of Pomalidomide-Cyclophosphamide-Dexamethasone (PCD) Versus Pomalidomide-Dexamethasone (PD) in Relapse or Refractory Myeloma. An AMN Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University Hospital, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>International Myeloma Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University Hospital, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Myeloma patients who relapse after prior treatment with bortezomib and lenalidomide have
      survival of less than 1 year. Recently, a randomized study of Pomalidomide and dexamethasone
      conducted in compared with placebo and dexamethasone showed that pomalidomide can improve
      survival of this group of patients. As a result, pomalidomide is now approved by the FDA and
      EMA for use in patients with relapsed/refractory myeloma previously treated with bortezomib
      and lenalidomide. We have conducted a study using Pomalidomide plus Dexamethasone (PD) in
      Asian patients, which showed good efficacy and safety profile. More important for patients
      with suboptimal response to PD will achieve a clinically meaningful response with the
      addition of oral cyclophosphamide (PCD). In the United States, a small randomised phase 2
      study of PCD versus PD showed that PCD have a higher response rates, produce deeper response
      and correspondingly longer progression free survival. There is till date no randomised phase
      3 study between these regimens. This will be important to determine what is the best
      combination including pomalidomide for use in relapse myeloma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this study, we will prospectively enrol 120 Asian patients with relapsed myeloma after
      prior treatment with bortezomib and lenalidomide, and randomised them between PCD and PD (60
      in each arms). Centers in Singapore, Korea, Taiwan, and Hong Kong will participate in this
      study.

      Pomalidomide is a new immunomodulatory drug, which has been shown to be active in myeloma
      patients who relapse after bortezomib and lenalidomide. A recent phase III study comparing
      pomalidomide plus dexamethasone with placebo plus high dose dexamethasone in patients with
      prior exposure to bortezomib and lenalidomide, showed that the use of pomalidomide
      significantly improve the overall survival of these patients. In an Asian study, it appears
      that the addition of cyclophosphamide can induce further response in patients without a
      response to PD. In the United States, a small randomised phase 2 study of PCD versus PD
      showed that PCD have a higher response rates, produce deeper response and correspondingly
      longer progression free survival. Our hypothesis is therefore that PCD will be better than PD
      and should be the standard pomalidomide containing regimen for relapse myeloma patients. This
      combination will also be highly relevant to Asian patients because cyclophosphamide is a
      relatively cheap drug and the combination will be cost effective if proven to be better than
      PD.

      Rationale for the Study Purpose There is a relative lack of data on the efficacy and
      tolerability of PCD in Asian Patients. The current study will also allow us to test if PCD is
      better than PD in the treatment of relapse myeloma patients.

      Rationale for Study Population The study population will be myeloma patients who have
      relapsed following prior treatment with bortezomib and lenalidomide. Pomalidomide is the
      current approved treatment choice for this group of patients and a common indication for us
      in Asia.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a randomised phase 3 study in Asian patients with relapse multiple myeloma after prior bortezomib and lenalidomide who will be treated by PD or PCD. Randomisation will be 1:1 using a computer algorithm. There will be no blinding. The patient in the 2 arms will be stratified according to ISS stage 1 or 2 versus stage 3.
Cross-over for patients randomised to Pomalidomide and Dexamethasone at progression:
Upon progression, patients randomized to pomalidomide and dexamethasone (PD) can cross-over to the PCD arm and have cyclophosphamide added to their regimen according to the PCD regimen. Cyclophosphamide should be added at the beginning of a cycle. They can continue on PCD until further progression. However for these PD patients that cross-over to PCD, the primary endpoint for analysis will be based on response and progression on PD.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed up to 100 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the time from commencement of treatment with either PCD or PD to disease progression or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed up to 100 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the percentage of patients enrolled that achieve a complete response (CR), or stringent complete response (sCR), or very good partial response (VGPR), or partial response (PR) based on the International Myeloma Working Group criteria anytime from commencement of treatment to the end of study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>An average of 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the time from commencement of treatment to the date of death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed up to 100 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the time from first evidence of PR or VGPR, or CR, or sCR to confirmation of disease progression or death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants affected by Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of enrolment into study till 3 years from the date of the last patient randomized</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed on the basis of the frequency and severity of adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapse Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pomalidomide, Cyclophosphamide, Dex (PCD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pomalidomide, Dex (PD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PCD</intervention_name>
    <description>For PCD, patients will be treated as follows: PO pomalidomide 4mg from D1-21, PO cyclophosphamide 400mg on D1, 8 and 15, and PO or IV dexamethasone 40mg D1, 8, 15 and 22 in a 28-day cycle.
Patients will be assessed every 28 days (+/- 10 days). Patients shall receive the treatment until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity as determined by treating physician, withdrawal of consent or mortality (whichever occurs first).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pomalidomide, Cyclophosphamide, Dex (PCD)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PD</intervention_name>
    <description>For PD, Patients will be treated as follows: PO pomalidomide 4mg from D1-21 and PO or IV dexamethasone 40mg D1, 8, 15 and 22 in a 28-day cycle.
Patients will be assessed every 28 days (+/- 10 days). Patients shall receive the treatment until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity as determined by treating physician, withdrawal of consent or mortality (whichever occurs first).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pomalidomide, Dex (PD)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Multiple myeloma, diagnosed according to standard criteria, with relapsing and
             refractory disease at study entry

          2. Patients must have evaluable multiple myeloma with at least one of the following
             (within 21 days of starting treatment)

               1. Serum M-protein ≥ 0.5g/dL, or

               2. In subjects without detectable serum M-protein, Urine M-protein ≥ 200mg/24 hour,
                  or serum free light chai (sFLC) &gt; 100mg/L (involved light chain) and an abnormal
                  kappa/Lambda ratio

          3. Can receive up to 6 lines of prior treatment. (Induction therapy followed by stem cell
             transplantation and consolidation/maintenance therapy will be considered as one line
             of treatment)

          4. Must be relapse refractory to prior lenalidomide and bortezomib. Refractoriness is
             defined as disease progression on treatment or progression within 6 months after the
             last dose of a given therapy. Relapse is defined according to the criteria of IMWG

          5. Males and females ≥ 18 years of age or &gt; country's legal age for adult consent

          6. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0 to 2

          7. Patients must meet the following clinical laboratory criteria with 21 days of starting
             treatment:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,000/mm3 and platelet ≥ 50,000/mm3 (≥
                  30,000/mm3 if myeloma involvement in the bone marrow is &gt;50%)

               2. Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x the upper limit of the normal range (ULN). Alanine
                  aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 3 x ULN.

               3. Calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 30mL/min or creatinine &lt; 3mg/dL.

          8. Female patients who:

               1. Are naturally postmenopausal for at least 2 year before enrolment

               2. Are surgically sterile

               3. If they are of childbearing potential**, agree to

                    -  adhere to the pomalidomide pregnancy prevention risk management program in
                       Appendix 8 :

                    -  All women of childbearing potential must agree to have two negative
                       pregnancy test within 10-14 days and 24hrs before commencing pomalidomide
                       and use two reliable methods of contraception simultaneously or practice
                       complete abstinence from any heterosexual intercourse during the following
                       time periods related to this study: 1) for at least 28 days before starting
                       study; 2) while participating in the study; 3) dose interruptions; and 4)
                       for at least 28 days after study treatment discontinuation. The two methods
                       of reliable contraception must include one highly effective method and one
                       additional effective method to prevent pregnancy, not plan on conceiving
                       children during or within 6 months following pomalidomide. (See Appendix 8
                       Pregnancy Prevention and Risk Management Program)

          9. Male patients, even if surgically sterilized (i.e. status post-vasectomy), who:

               1. Agree to practice effective barrier contraception during the entire study
                  treatment period and through 28 days after the last dose of study treatment, OR

               2. Agree to completely abstain from heterosexual intercourse, AND

               3. Must also adhere to the guidelines of the pomalidomide pregnancy prevention and
                  risk management program

         10. Written informed consent in accordance with federal, local and institutional
             guidelines

               -  A female of childbearing potential (FCBP) is defined as a sexually mature woman
                  who: 1 has not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy or 2, has not
                  been naturally post-menopausal (amenorrhea following cancer therapy does not rule
                  out childbearing potential) for at least 24 consecutive months (I.E, has had
                  menses at any time in the preceding 24 consecutive months).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Female patients who are lactating or pregnant

          2. Multiple Myeloma of IgM subtype

          3. Glucocorticoid therapy (prednisolone &gt; 30mg/day or equivalent) within 14 days prior to
             informed consent obtained

          4. POEMS syndrome

          5. Plasma cell leukemia or circulating plasma cells ≥ 2 x 109/L

          6. Waldenstrom's Macroglobulinaemia

          7. Patients with known amyloidosis

          8. Chemotherapy with approved or investigation anticancer therapeutics within 21 days
             prior to starting pomalidomide treatment

          9. Focal radiation therapy within 7 days prior to start of pomalidomide. Radiation
             therapy to an extended field involving a significant volume of bone marrow within 21
             days prior to start of pomalidomide

         10. Immunotherapy (excluding steroids) 21 days prior to start of pomalidomide

         11. Major surgery (excluding kyphoplasty) within 28 days prior to start of pomalidomide

         12. Active congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association [NYHA] Class III or IV),
             symptomatic ischaemia, or conduction abnormalities uncontrolled by conventional
             intervention. Myocardial infarction within 4 months prior to informed consent obtained

         13. Known HIV seropositive, hepatitis C infection, and/or hepatitis B (except for patients
             with hepatitis B surface antigen or core antibody receiving and responding to
             antiviral therapy directed at hepatitis B: these patients are allowed)

         14. Patients with known cirrhosis

         15. Second malignancy within the past 3 years except:

               1. Adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer

               2. Carcinoma in situ of the cervix

               3. Breast carcinoma in situ with full surgical resection

         16. Patients with myelodysplastic syndrome

         17. Patients with steroid or lenalidomide hypersensitivity

         18. Prior treatment with pomalidomide

         19. Ongoing graft-versus-host disease

         20. Patients with pleural effusions requiring thoracentesis or ascites requiring
             paracentesis within 14 days prior to starting pomalidomide treatment

         21. Contraindication to any of the required concomitant drugs or supportive treatments

         22. Any clinically significant medical disease or psychiatric condition that, in the
             investigator's opinion, may interfere with protocol adherence or a patient's ability
             to give informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wee Joo Chng</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National University Hospital, Singapore</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wee Joo Chng</last_name>
    <phone>6779 5555</phone>
    <email>mdccwj@nus.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Adeline Lin</last_name>
    <email>adeline_hf_lin@nuhs.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Mary Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Japan</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>South Korea</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Taiwan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Singapore</country>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miguel JS, Weisel K, Moreau P, Lacy M, Song K, Delforge M, Karlin L, Goldschmidt H, Banos A, Oriol A, Alegre A, Chen C, Cavo M, Garderet L, Ivanova V, Martinez-Lopez J, Belch A, Palumbo A, Schey S, Sonneveld P, Yu X, Sternas L, Jacques C, Zaki M, Dimopoulos M. Pomalidomide plus low-dose dexamethasone versus high-dose dexamethasone alone for patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma (MM-003): a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol. 2013 Oct;14(11):1055-1066. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(13)70380-2. Epub 2013 Sep 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24007748</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larocca A, Montefusco V, Bringhen S, Rossi D, Crippa C, Mina R, Galli M, Marcatti M, La Verde G, Giuliani N, Magarotto V, Guglielmelli T, Rota-Scalabrini D, Omedé P, Santagostino A, Baldi I, Carella AM, Boccadoro M, Corradini P, Palumbo A. Pomalidomide, cyclophosphamide, and prednisone for relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma: a multicenter phase 1/2 open-label study. Blood. 2013 Oct 17;122(16):2799-806. doi: 10.1182/blood-2013-03-488676. Epub 2013 Aug 16.</citation>
    <PMID>23954889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pomalidomide</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Recurrence</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pomalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

