<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03140189</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>YZhang</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03140189</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Robot-assisted IVOR-LEWIS Esophagectomy</brief_title>
  <acronym>RAILE</acronym>
  <official_title>Robot- Assisted Ivor-Lewis Esophagectomy for Esophageal Cancer: Short- Term and Long Term Outcomes of a Single-Arm Phase II Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ruijin Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ruijin Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Minimally invasive esophagectomy (MIE) have become increasingly popular in esophageal cancer.
      It is generally accepted that comparing to open resections, MIE results in decreased
      postoperative pain, faster recovery times, and shorter hospital stays with comparable
      oncologic outcomes. However, MIE poses an important challenge for established thoracic
      surgeons as it is a difficult technique to become skilled at with an protracted learning
      curve. Standard laparoscopic and thoracoscopic instruments are rigid and provide a finite
      freedom of movement with a two dimensional visualization of the operating field. Such a
      difficulty is increased even more when the Ivor-Lewis esophagectomy with an intrathoracic
      anastomosis is needed.

      Robot- assisted surgical system has opened a new era of minimally invasive surgery. Robot-
      assisted surgery offers some advantages including high- definition three- dimensional
      visualization and 7 degrees of freedom with the use of its surgical wrists, motion scaling,
      and tremor filtration, allowing the surgeon to perform complex operations comfortably in the
      domain of urinary tract, hepatobiliary and gynecological surgery. Although a robot-assisted
      thoraco- laparoscopic minimally invasive esophagectomy (RAMIE) was initiated from 2003, the
      published experience with RAMIE remains small, especially for Ivor- Lewis approaches. The aim
      of this study was to investigate the short- term and long-term outcomes of RAILE to identify
      any clinical or oncologic benefits of RAILE in esophageal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This confirmatory, nonrandomized, single-arm trial (phase II) will be conducted to evaluate
      short-and long-term outcomes of robot-assisted thoraco- laparoscopic minimally invasive
      esophagectomy for esophageal cancer. Patients will registered preoperatively. The planned
      sample size was 51. Preoperative endoscopic biopsy was performed in all patients to confirm
      the histological diagnosis of esophageal cancer. Staging workup included thorough history and
      physical examination, esophagogastroduodenoscopy, endoscopic ultrasonography, and integrated
      positron emission tomography/computed tomography scan. Patients with histologically proven
      malignancy were candidates for surgical procedures. Operability criteria were defined
      according to the National Comprehensive Cancer Network guidelines. All patients were within
      the American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) class I to III. In general, neoadjuvant
      chemoradiotherapy was offered to patients with T2-3 or N1-2 disease. The primary endpoint in
      the first stage is the short-term postoperative complications, and that in the second stage
      is overall survival; patients continue to be followed up for this endpoint.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 14, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>5 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>short-term postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after surgery</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>long-term overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>five years after surgery</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>perioperative outcomes except for postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Clinical or Oncologic Benefits of Robot-assisted IVOR-LEWIS in Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with histologically proven malignancy were candidates for surgical procedures.
        Operability criteria were defined according to the National Comprehensive Cancer Network
        guidelines. All patients were within the American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) class
        I to III. In general, neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy was offered to patients with T2-3 or
        N1-2 disease.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with histologically proven esophageal malignancy

          2. All patients were within the American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) class I to
             III

          3. neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy was offered to patients with T2-3 or N1-2 disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Cancer located at the cervical esophageal Cancer located at the gastroesophageal junction
        history of surgery in the right thorax
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yajie Zhang, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(+86)64370045-666112</phone>
    <email>zhangyajieryan@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jie Xiang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(+86)64370045-666111</phone>
    <email>jiexiang021@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yajie Zhang</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <zip>200000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wee JO, Bravo-Iñiguez CE, Jaklitsch MT. Early Experience of Robot-Assisted Esophagectomy With Circular End-to-End Stapled Anastomosis. Ann Thorac Surg. 2016 Jul;102(1):253-9. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2016.02.050. Epub 2016 May 4.</citation>
    <PMID>27154153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Park S, Hwang Y, Lee HJ, Park IK, Kim YT, Kang CH. Comparison of robot-assisted esophagectomy and thoracoscopic esophagectomy in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma. J Thorac Dis. 2016 Oct;8(10):2853-2861.</citation>
    <PMID>27867561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 2, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ruijin Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hecheng Li M.D., Ph.D</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Esophageal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Robotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Ivor-Lewis esophagectomy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

