<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03144245</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AMV564-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03144245</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of AMV564 in Patients With AML</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, First in Human, Open Label, Dose Escalation Study of AMV564, a CD33 x CD3 Tandem Diabody in Patients With Relapsed or Refractory Acute Myeloid Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amphivena Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amphivena Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a first in human, non randomized, open-label, dose escalation study to investigate
      the safety, tolerability and preliminary efficacy of AMV564.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a first in human, Phase 1, open label, multicenter, dose escalation study of
      AMV564 in patients with relapsed or refractory AML. Patients must have documented diagnosis
      of AML according to World Health Organization (WHO) criteria. After providing signed informed
      consent, patients will be screened for entry into the study. The study will be conducted in 2
      stages. In a dose escalation stage, approximately 32 patients will be enrolled. Escalation
      cohorts of 3 to 6 patients will receive repeat doses of AMV564 to determine the MTD and RP2D.
      AMV564 will be administered daily for 14 days. In a second expansion phase, a total of 18
      patients will receive AMV564 at the established RP2D.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 20, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 20, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose escalation + expansion stage: incidence of all adverse events and serious adverse events (safety and tolerability)</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Expansion stage: Efficacy - Remission Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants who achieve complete remission, complete remission with incomplete recovery or partial remission</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AMV564</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Continuous infusion of AMV564 at increasing dose levels</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMV564</intervention_name>
    <description>AMV564 for administration via continuous intravenous daily infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AMV564</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years of age at the time of signing informed consent

          -  Diagnosis of AML according to the World Health Organization (WHO) 2008 criteria

          -  Relapsed or refractory disease meeting the following criteria: (a) Primary refractory,
             ie, refractory to induction with a standard anthracycline-based regimen or a
             hypomethylating agent (e.g. decitabine or azacitidine) for patients ineligible for
             anthracycline-based therapy; (b) First relapse after a first complete remission (CR)
             lasting less than 12 months; or (c) Second or later relapse. Relapse is defined as the
             reappearance of leukemic blasts in the peripheral blood or ≥ 5% leukemic blasts in the
             bone marrow after prior achievement of a CR or CRi.

          -  Blasts at least 5% in bone marrow

          -  Peripheral white blood cell (WBC) count: no upper limit at Screening, but must be &lt; 10
             x 109/L on Day 1 prior to treatment; patients with excessive blasts may be treated
             with hydroxyurea to bring counts down.

          -  Chemistry laboratory parameters within the following range:

               1. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2x the
                  upper limit of normal (ULN)

               2. Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5x the ULN; patients with Gilbert's syndrome can enroll if
                  conjugated bilirubin is within normal limits.

               3. Creatinine clearance &gt; 50 mL/min (measured or calculated by Cockcroft-Gault
                  method)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1. Patients with
             ECOG score of 2 may be included, after discussion with the Sponsor Medical Monitor, if
             score is influenced by symptoms attributable to underlying AML disease.

          -  Able to read, understand and provide written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from the study.

          -  History of, or known, central nervous system (CNS) disease involvement, or prior
             history of National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Events
             (CTCAE) Grade ≥ 3 drug-related CNS toxicity

          -  Prior allogeneic transplant is excluded during Dose Escalation Stage;

          -  Prior solid organ transplantation

          -  Treatment with anti-thymocyte globulin (ATG) within 14 days prior to start date

          -  Treatment with any local or systemic antineoplastic therapy or radiation within 14
             days prior to the initiation of AMV564 administration (hydroxyurea is exempted if used
             to reduce total WBC counts)

          -  Clinically significant cardiac disease,

          -  Pulmonary, renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, neurological or psychiatric disease that
             would limit compliance with study requirements

          -  Evidence of active, uncontrolled, viral, bacterial, or systemic fungal infection.
             Prophylactic therapy according to institutional protocols is acceptable.

          -  Known positive test result for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or acquired immune
             deficiency syndrome (AIDS)

          -  Active hepatitis C virus (HCV) or hepatitis B virus (HBV).

          -  Second primary malignancy that has not been in remission for greater than 3 years.
             Exceptions that do not require a 3-year remission include: non-melanoma skin cancer;
             cervical carcinoma in situ on biopsy or squamous intraepithelial lesion on
             Papanicolaou (PAP) smear; localized prostate cancer (Gleason score &lt; 6); or resected
             melanoma in situ.

          -  Any serious underlying medical or psychiatric condition (e.g. alcohol or drug abuse),
             dementia or altered mental status or any issue that would impair the ability of the
             patient to understand informed consent or that in the opinion of the investigator
             would contraindicate the patient's participation in the study or confound the results
             of the study.

          -  Ability to become pregnant. However, female patients who have a negative serum or
             urine pregnancy test before enrollment and agree to use two highly effective forms of
             contraception (oral, injected or implanted hormonal contraception and condom;
             intrauterine device and condom; diaphragm with spermicidal gel and condom) during the
             trial and for 90 days afterward (90 days after the end of AMV564 treatment) are
             considered eligible.

          -  Male patients with partners of childbearing potential.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eric J. Feldman, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>206-773-3568</phone>
    <email>efeldman@amphivena.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical College, The New York Presbyterian Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center, The University of Texas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>70030-4009</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>AML</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>relapsed</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>phase 1</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

