<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03141437</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-0758</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1UG1CA189823</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03141437</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient-Centered Decision Counseling for Women at Risk of Cancer-Related Infertility</brief_title>
  <official_title>Patient-Centered Decision Counseling for Women at Risk of Cancer-Related Infertility: Efficacy Study and Comparative-Effectiveness Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Duncan Family Institute for Cancer Prevention and Risk Assessment</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this research study is to learn if a decision aid website that provides
      information about fertility preservation (maintaining participant's ability to have children
      of participant's own after cancer treatment) can help women with cancer make
      fertility-preservation decisions. Researchers will also use information learned in this study
      to help improve the website. This website was developed at MD Anderson.

      There are several ways to preserve fertility, including taking drugs to stop or control ovary
      function in order to freeze eggs and/or embryos. Freezing eggs and/or embryos may increase
      the chances of having a child of participant's own in the future. Participant may also choose
      to have children using other methods, such as adoption. This website is designed to help
      women learn more about these options and consider which of them may be best for them.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There are 2 parts to this study. In Part 1, researchers will learn if the fertility
      preservation website can help women make decisions about fertility. In Part 2, researchers
      will compare the current standard care to standard care in combination with the fertility
      preservation website.

      If participant is receiving treatment at MD Anderson, participant will take part in Part 1 of
      the study. If participant is receiving treatment at a Houston-area MD Anderson satellite
      office, participant will take part in Part 2 of the study.

      Part 1:

      If participant is in Part 1 of the study, participant will be given the option to either view
      the decision aid website about fertility preservation at home or participant can come to
      participant's routine fertility consultation visit about 30 minutes early and view the
      website at the office in a private room. Whichever participant chooses, participant will
      complete a questionnaire before viewing the website about healthcare decision making and
      fertility. This questionnaire should take about 30 minutes to complete.

      About 1 week after participant views the website, participant will complete another
      questionnaire about participant's opinions on the decision aid website and if participant
      thinks the website is useful in making fertility preservation decisions. This questionnaire
      should take about 30 minutes to complete.

      Participant will then have participant's fertility consultation visit as scheduled and
      participant may or may not choose to use fertility preservation treatments or methods. About
      2 months after participant's consultation visit, participant will complete a questionnaire
      about which methods of fertility preservation participant chooses to use (if any), what
      influenced participant's decision-making, and if participant has any ideas on how to improve
      the fertility preservation process. This will be completed online and may take about 30
      minutes to complete.

      Part 2:

      If participant agrees to take part in this study, the type of educational information
      participant receives will depend on where participant is receiving treatment. Participant
      will either receive standard care or standard care plus the use of the decision-making
      website. Standard of care includes receiving patient education materials about fertility
      preservation from the Livestrong organization and receiving a referral for fertility
      preservation, if requested.

      All participants will complete the questionnaires described below.

      Participant will complete 3 sets of questionnaires when participant enrolls in the study and
      then at 1 week and then 2 months after participant enrolls. These questionnaires include
      questions about participant's demographic information (for example, age, sex, and race). They
      also include questions about participant's preferred role in making healthcare decisions,
      participant's knowledge about fertility preservation, and any concerns participant has about
      reproduction. Each set of questionnaires should take about 30 minutes to complete. All
      questionnaires will be completed online.

      The research staff may call participant to remind participant to complete the questionnaires
      and/or to learn more information about participant's fertility status that may not be found
      in participant's medical record.

      All Participants:

      The study staff may also review participant's medical records for information about what, if
      any, fertility preservation options participant chooses to do. The study staff will also
      review participant's medical record to collect data about participant's fertility status. The
      study staff may contact participant to collect information that may not be included in
      participant's medical record.

      Length of Study Participation:

      Participation in this study will be over after participant completes the 2-month
      questionnaire.

      This is an investigational study.

      Up to 160 participants will be enrolled in this multicenter study. Up to 160 may be enrolled
      at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 23, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of Patients Achieving a Score &lt; 25 on the Decision Conflict Scale (DCS) in the Decision Aid Website - MDACC Group</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of Patients Achieving a Score &lt; 25 on the Decision Conflict Scale (DCS) in the Multicomponent Decision Support (DS) - HALs Group and Standard Care - HALs Group</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasm of Breast</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasm of Female Genital Organs</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Aid Website - MDACC Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Questionnaire completed before viewing the website about healthcare decision making and fertility.
Participant views the decision aid website about fertility preservation at home or at routine fertility consultation visit.
Questionnaire completed 1 week after viewing the website about opinions on the decision aid website.
Questionnaire completed 2 months after consultation visit about which methods of fertility preservation that were chose (if any).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multicomponent Decision Support (DS) - HALs Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Multicomponent DS intervention at selected MD Anderson Houston Area Locations (HALs)
Participant completes 3 questionnaires before viewing the website about healthcare decision making and fertility, and then at 1 week and then 2 months after viewing the website.
Participant views the decision aid website about fertility preservation at home.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care - HALs Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard Care intervention at selected MD Anderson Houston Area Locations (HALs)
Participants receive education materials about fertility preservation from the Livestrong organization and receive a referral for fertility preservation, if requested.
Participants complete 3 sets of questionnaires at enrollment in the study, and then at 1 week and 2 months after enrollment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>MDACC Group: Participants complete questionnaire before viewing the website about healthcare decision making and fertility. Questionnaire completed 1 week after viewing the website about opinions on the decision aid website.
Questionnaire completed 2 months after consultation visit about which methods of fertility preservation that were chose (if any).
HALs Group: Participant completes 3 questionnaires before viewing the website about healthcare decision making and fertility, and then at 1 week and then 2 months after viewing the website.
Standard Care HALs Group: Participants complete 3 sets of questionnaires at enrollment in the study, and then at 1 week and 2 months after enrollment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Aid Website - MDACC Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Multicomponent Decision Support (DS) - HALs Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care - HALs Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surveys</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Decision Aid Website</intervention_name>
    <description>MDACC Group: Participant views the decision aid website about fertility preservation at home or at routine fertility consultation visit.
HALs Group: Participant views the decision aid website about fertility preservation at home.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Decision Aid Website - MDACC Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Multicomponent Decision Support (DS) - HALs Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Educational Materials</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard Care HALs Group: Participants receive education materials about fertility preservation from the Livestrong organization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Care - HALs Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Woman aged 18-45 years old

          2. Newly diagnosed breast tumor, female genital system tumor, colorectal tumor, and/or
             lymphoma/myeloma

          3. At risk for cancer-related infertility, as assessed by their clinician(s), including
             the oncofertility specialist.

          4. Must be able to speak, read, and write English

          5. Must have internet access and a valid email address

          6. Have not previously viewed the Pathways decision aid

          7. For clinical provider participants: Clinical provider at a Houston Area Location of MD
             Anderson assigned to the intervention.

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Terri L. Woodard, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Terri L. Woodard, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-745-7591</phone>
    <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Research Operations</last_name>
      <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 5, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malignant Neoplasm of Breast</keyword>
  <keyword>Malignant Neoplasm of Female Genital Organs</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>Decision Aid Website</keyword>
  <keyword>DA</keyword>
  <keyword>Fertility preservation support</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>Surveys</keyword>
  <keyword>Educational materials</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Genital Neoplasms, Female</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

