<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03146767</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MAZ0816</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03146767</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Staircase Phenomenon Implications on Neuromuscular Block Monitoring</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Staircase Phenomenon and His Implications on Neuromuscular Block Monitoring During General Anesthesia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario La Fe</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Universitario La Fe</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The staircase phenomenon could have repercussions on the onset and recovery time following
      administration of a neuromuscular blocking agent. The investigators aim to assess the
      magnitude of the staircase phenomenon and its impact on various aspects of neuromuscular
      blockade with a randomized controlled double blind trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in Block Onset time difference (seconds)</measure>
    <time_frame>rom 0 seconds up to 240 seconds after neuromuscular block administration at the beginning of surgery. Time frame is the duration of general anesthesia before, during and after surgery (up to 4 hours).</time_frame>
    <description>Onset time is the time between Train of Four (TOF) at the moment of injection of neuromuscular blocking drug and the minimum value reached (onset of neuromuscular block)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in time until recovery of a TOF ratio (TOFr) of 0.9</measure>
    <time_frame>From administration of neuromuscular blocking drug until spontaneous reversal (up to 4 hours). Time frame is the duration of general anesthesia before, during and after surgery (up to 4 hours).</time_frame>
    <description>Time until recovery of a TOF ratio of 0.9 (reversal of neuromuscular block as assessed by the monitor). During recovery phase stimuli regain height until all four stimuli of the Train-of-Four are present. Train-of-Four ratio is the ratio between the fourth and the first stimuli (T4/T1).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in TOFr 0.9 Normalized</measure>
    <time_frame>From administration of neuromuscular blocking drug until spontaneous reversal at this specified point (up to 4 hours). Time frame is the duration of general anesthesia before, during and after surgery (up to 4 hours).</time_frame>
    <description>Time until recovery of a TOF ratio of 0.9 normalized to baseline TOR ratio after calibration. (e.g. if baseline TOF ratio is 1.1, normalized TOF ratio 0.9 is: 1.1 x 0.9 = 0.99)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in time until recovery of 25% of maximum twitch height ot T1 stimulus (DUR25)</measure>
    <time_frame>From administration of neuromuscular blocking drug until spontaneous reversal at this specified point (up to 4 hours). Time frame is the duration of general anesthesia before, during and after surgery.(up to 4 hours)</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in time until recovery of 25% of maximum twitch height ot T1 stimulus during recovery phase. During recovery phase stimuli begin to recover and their height increases. This outcome is the time between the beginning of neuromuscular block until recovery of 25% of height of the first stimulus of the Train-of-Four.recovery phase. During recovery phase stimuli begin to recover and their height increases. This outcome is the time between the beginning of neuromuscular block until recovery of 25% of height of the first stimulus of the Train-of-Four (TOF)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time between 25% and 75% of maximum twitch height recovery of T1 stimulus</measure>
    <time_frame>From administration of neuromuscular blocking drug until spontaneous reversal (up to 4 hours). Time frame is the duration of general anesthesia before, during and after surgery (up to 4 hours).</time_frame>
    <description>Time between 25% and 75% height recovery of maximum twitch height in the recovery phase.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between first stimulus of Train-of-Four ratio at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Single measurement of muscle response after calibration procedure at the beginning of data recording after randomization. It is not a time-to-event variable</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between T1 at baseline. Train-of-Four ratio is the administration of four consecutive stimuli to the monitored muscle. These stimuli are named T1,T2,T3,T4. This is the difference between tow arms oh T1 height at baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between T1 height after stabilization period of 20 minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>Single measurement after 20 minutes stabilization period after beginning of neuromuscular stimulation. It is not a time-to-event variable</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between T1 height after stabilization period of 20 minutes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between TOF ratio at baseline time</measure>
    <time_frame>Single measurement of muscle response after calibration procedure at the beginning of data recording.</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between TOF ratio at baseline time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between TOF ratio after stabilization period time</measure>
    <time_frame>Single measurement after 20 minutes stabilization period after beginning of neuromuscular stimulation.</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between TOF ratio after stabilization period time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitor Sensitivity difference between groups</measure>
    <time_frame>Single value no time frame. Sensitivity is internally set by the monitor during calibration (at the beginning of data recording after randomization)</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity parameter is set by monitor after calibration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitor Amperage Intensity after calibration difference (milliAmperes, mA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Single value no time frame. Sensitivity is internally set by the monitor during calibration (at the beginning of data recording after randomization)</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor Amperage Intensity is set by the monitor after calibration</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T1/TOFratio relationship difference</measure>
    <time_frame>Ratio of specified values recorded by the monitor at the beginning of surgery until onset of neuromuscular block (up to 180 seconds) and during spontaneous recovery up to 4 hours until end of anesthesia</time_frame>
    <description>During recovery phase T1 over TOF ratio will be calculated and the difference between two groups will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuromuscular Blockade Monitoring</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tetanic Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A Tetanic stimulation (Tetanus stabilization of baseline) is administered to the monitorized arm before calibrating the neuromuscular block monitor. Then Train-of-four (TOF) stimuli are administered every 20 seconds for 20 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional monitor baseline stabilization: Train-of-four stimuli are administered every 20 seconds for 20 minutes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tetanus stabilization of baseline</intervention_name>
    <description>Administering a Tetanic stimulus before baseline stabilization shortens the stabilization period of baseline of a neuromuscular block monitor. This acts on the baseline value</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tetanic Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ASA (American Society of Anesthesiology surgical risk scale) grade I - II

          -  Surgery not involving airway performed under general anaesthesia with neuromuscular
             blocker

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  BMI (Body Mass Idex) &gt; 35 Kg/m2

          -  Anticipated difficult airway

          -  Chronic kidney or hepatic failure

          -  Neuromuscular disease

          -  Medication that has known interactions with neuromuscular blockers

          -  Hemodynamic failure

          -  Anticipated large blood loss
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario La Fe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Universitario La Fe</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Oscar Diaz-Cambronero</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Anesthesiology Consultant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

