<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03145935</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ANSM 2017-A01334-49.</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03145935</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diagnosis Accuracy of Abdominal Compression and Hemoconcentration to Detect Diuretic Induced Fluid Removal Intolerance.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diagnosis Accuracy of Abdominal Compression and Hemoconcentration to Detect Diuretic Induced Fluid Removal Intolerance.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hopital Louis Pradel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hopital Louis Pradel</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fluid overload increases morbidity and mortality of pediatrics patients in intensive care
      unit (ICU). It could be interesting to predict the decrease in stroke volume when diuretics
      are prescribed. Nevertheless, no test predict a decrease of stroke volume in a context of a
      diuretics induced depletion. Abdominal compression (AC) coupled with echocardiographic
      measurement of the stroke volume can predict fluid responsiveness and is a good tool to
      assess preload dependency. Another point is that during depletion refilling can occur. We aim
      to assess the diagnostic accuracy of abdominal compression to predict a decrease of the
      stroke volume of 15 % during diuretic-induced depletion of 10 ml/kg of diuresis. Secondary
      outcome will assess the hemoconcentration during depletion to diagnose a decrease of stroke
      volume during diuretic induced depletion
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fluid overload increases morbidity and mortality of pediatrics patients in intensive care
      unit (ICU). The pediatric intensivist has a priority to decrease unnecessary fluid load and
      to make the fluid balance negative in case of fluid overload. Diuretics help to make the
      fluid balance negative but can lead to a reduction of volemia that can lead to hypovolemia.
      Hypovolemia can induce a reduction of stroke volume and cardiac index that can alter tissue
      perfusion and increase organ dysfunction.

      It could be interesting to predict the decrease in stroke volume when diuretics are
      prescribed. Nevertheless, no test predict a decrease of stroke volume in a context of a
      diuretics induced depletion.

      The concept of preload dependency described by frank-starling is interesting in that context.

      Preload dependency is a state of the working heart characterized by a modification of stroke
      volume when a modification of preload is done. Conversely, no preload dependency is a state
      of the working heart characterized by no modification of stroke volume when a modification of
      preload is done.

      If the heart is in a state of preload dependency, a reduction of preload induced by diuretics
      depletion might induce a reduction of stroke volume. Conversely, if the heart is in a state
      of no preload dependency a reduction of preload induced by a diuretics depletion might not
      induce a reduction of stroke volume Abdominal compression coupled with echocardiographic
      measurement of the stroke volume can predict fluid responsiveness and is a good tool to
      assess preload dependency.

      Another point is that during depletion refilling can occur. Studies performed during
      hemodialysis have shown that refilling maintains a stable hematocrit during depletion. the
      absence of refilling is characterized by an hemoconcentration

      We aim to assess the diagnostic accuracy of abdominal compression to predict a decrease of
      the stroke volume of 15 % during diuretic induced depletion of 10ml/kg of diuresis. Secondary
      outcome will assess the hemoconcentration during depletion to diagnose a decrease of stroke
      volume during diuretic induced depletion
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 10, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke volume index (SVi) variation induced by abdominal compression ΔSVi-AC</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of stroke volume index measured with echocardiography induced by abdominal compression. We will test if stroke volume index variation during abdominal compression can predict a decrease of 15 % of the stroke volume during a 10 ml/kg diuresis induced by diuretics administration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoconcentration with protides</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>proteinemia variation. We will test if proteinemia variation can predict a diagnose a reduction of 15 % of the stroke volume during a 10 ml/kg diuresis induced by diuretics administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoconcentration with hematocrit</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Hematocrit variation. We will test if hematocrit variation can predict a diagnose a reduction of 15 % of the stroke volume during a 10 ml/kg diuresis induced by diuretics administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory variation of the maximum aortic velocity of the left ventricular outflow tractΔVpeak</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of the maximum velocity of the left ventricular outflow tract induced by ventilation. We will test if ΔVpeak can predict a decrease of 15 % of the stroke volume during a 10 ml/kg diuresis induced by diuretics administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory variation of the inferior vena cava diameter ΔIVC</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Variation of inferior vena cava diameter induced by ventilation. We will test if ΔIVC can predict a decrease of 15 % of the stroke volume during a 10 ml/kg diuresis induced by diuretics administration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypovolemia</condition>
  <condition>Diuretic Toxicity</condition>
  <condition>Fluid Overload</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abdominal compression (AC)</intervention_name>
    <description>An echocardiography with stroke volume measurement coupled with an abdominal compression will be performed before and after ta diuretics induced diuresis of 10ml/kg in pediatric patients hospitalized in a pediatric intensive care unit (PICU) diagnosed with fluid overload</description>
    <other_name>Echocardiographic assessement of volume status</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>blood sample</intervention_name>
    <description>proteinemia and hematocrit will be measured before and after a diuretics induced diuresis of 10ml/kg</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pediatric patients under 8 years old, hospitalized in the pediatric intensive care unit of
        investigation center.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Height year old or less

          -  Patient hospitalized in the pediatric intensive care unit of the investigation center.

        presenting symptoms of fluid overload characterized with:

          -  Peripheral edema.

          -  An increase of 10% between the first day in ICU and inclusion date

               -  the attending physician should have decided to evaluate hemodynamic with
                  iterative echocardiography

               -  the attending physician, who is not the investigator has decided to administer
                  diuretics

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient or Holder of parental authority refusal to participate

          -  Dehydration with natremia over 150 mmol/L or clinical signs of dehydration

          -  Suspected abdominal hypertension

          -  recent abdominal surgery with abdominal pain induced by abdominal examination.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>8 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matthias Jacquet-Lagreze, M.D., M.Sc.</last_name>
    <phone>+33 6 89 10 99 59</phone>
    <email>matthias.jl@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jean-Luc Fellahi, M.D.,Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+33 4 72 11 89 33</phone>
    <email>jean-luc.fellahi@chu-lyon.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Louis Pradel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bron</city>
        <state>Rhone Alpes</state>
        <zip>69100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matthias Jacquet-Lagrèze, M.D., M.Sc.</last_name>
      <phone>+ 33 6 89 10 99 59</phone>
      <email>matthias.jl@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jean-Luc Fellahi, M.D., pH.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+33 4 72 11 89 33</phone>
      <email>matthias.jl@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Foland JA, Fortenberry JD, Warshaw BL, Pettignano R, Merritt RK, Heard ML, Rogers K, Reid C, Tanner AJ, Easley KA. Fluid overload before continuous hemofiltration and survival in critically ill children: a retrospective analysis. Crit Care Med. 2004 Aug;32(8):1771-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15286557</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sinitsky L, Walls D, Nadel S, Inwald DP. Fluid overload at 48 hours is associated with respiratory morbidity but not mortality in a general PICU: retrospective cohort study. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2015 Mar;16(3):205-9. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0000000000000318.</citation>
    <PMID>25581632</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Li Y, Wang J, Bai Z, Chen J, Wang X, Pan J, Li X, Feng X. Early fluid overload is associated with acute kidney injury and PICU mortality in critically ill children. Eur J Pediatr. 2016 Jan;175(1):39-48. doi: 10.1007/s00431-015-2592-7. Epub 2015 Jul 24.</citation>
    <PMID>26206387</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Monnet X, Cipriani F, Camous L, Sentenac P, Dres M, Krastinova E, Anguel N, Richard C, Teboul JL. The passive leg raising test to guide fluid removal in critically ill patients. Ann Intensive Care. 2016 Dec;6(1):46. doi: 10.1186/s13613-016-0149-1. Epub 2016 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>27207178</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 5, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hopital Louis Pradel</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Matthias Jacquet-Lagrèze</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical doctor, Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypovolemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diuretics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

