<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03149809</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N2293-I</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03149809</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Behavioral or Solifenacin Therapy for Urinary Symptoms in Parkinson Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>BOSS PD</acronym>
  <official_title>Behavioral or Solifenacin Therapy for Urinary Symptoms in Parkinson Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The impact of urinary symptoms in Parkinson disease (PD) extends beyond worsened well-being.
      Urinary symptoms common in PD, especially incontinence and nocturia, are major risk factors
      for falls likely due to the combination of urinary urgency and impaired mobility (and falls
      are a leading cause of mortality in PD), for spouse/caregiver stress due to decreased
      mutuality in the relationship, and for institutionalization, largely due to increased
      disability. Additionally, most medications currently recommended for urinary symptoms in PD
      are anticholinergic and have the potential to worsen the progressive cognitive and autonomic
      burdens of the disease. Veterans with PD are also more likely to rely solely on VA for their
      health care than Veterans without PD. Thus, optimizing the care of urinary symptoms for
      Veterans with PD becomes imperative, particularly for VA. Using a non-inferiority design,
      this proposal seeks to demonstrate the comparative effectiveness of pelvic floor muscle
      exercise-based behavioral therapy versus drug therapy to treat urinary symptoms in PD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The number of persons with Parkinson Disease (PD) in the United States is expected to double
      by 2030 as the population ages. Importantly, this increase in the prevalence of PD will have
      greater impact within the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) because the Veteran population
      is older than the general population and Veterans with PD are more likely than those without
      PD to rely solely on VA for their health care. While PD is often characterized by the motor
      symptoms of the disease (tremor, bradykinesia, rigidity), non-motor symptoms such as urinary
      symptoms correlate more closely with impaired well-being as the disease progresses. However,
      the impact of urinary symptoms in PD extends beyond worsened well-being. The urinary symptoms
      of overactive bladder (OAB), including urgency, frequency, and nocturia, with or without
      urinary incontinence, are the most common urinary symptoms of PD. OAB symptoms are associated
      with falls (a cause of increased mortality in PD), with spouse/caregiver stress, and,
      ultimately with institutionalization, thus it is critical that we optimize the care of
      urinary symptoms for Veterans with PD.

      Several studies suggest abnormal central nervous system processing of sensory input from
      bladder afferent nerves contributes to OAB symptoms in PD, possibly because of delayed
      recognition of bladder fullness. This mirrors findings in non-PD populations with OAB. In the
      non-PD OAB population, pelvic floor muscle contractions diminish bladder muscle contraction
      and recent evidence demonstrates that behavioral training with pelvic floor muscle exercises
      improves the cortical integration of bladder afferent signals. Pelvic floor muscle
      exercise-based behavioral therapy for OAB symptoms requires individuals to learn a motor
      skill and implement an adaptive behavioral strategy to delay the need to void. Because of its
      effectiveness compared to drug therapy, pelvic floor muscle exercise-based behavioral therapy
      is recommended first-line in men and women with OAB who do not have PD. However, the most
      recent clinical guidelines for the treatment of urinary symptoms in PD recommend treatment
      with anticholinergic drugs. While some anticholinergic drugs are effective in reducing
      symptoms of OAB, it is important to note that there is a glaring lack of an empirical
      evidence base to promote these drugs in the setting of PD given that they add to the
      anticholinergic burden of antiparkinsonian therapy, and may worsen the cognitive and
      autonomic burdens of the illness. Therefore, randomized controlled trials (RCTs) are needed
      to optimize treatment paradigms for urinary symptoms in PD.

      The investigators propose a three-site, RCT conducted at the Atlanta (lead site), Birmingham
      and Richmond VA's to establish non-inferiority of pelvic floor muscle exercise-based
      behavioral therapy compared to drug therapy for OAB symptoms in adults with PD. Groups will
      be stratified by OAB symptom severity, PD motor symptom severity, gender, and site. The
      investigators will randomize 90 participants in order to complete the study in 80
      participants, assuming 85% power and a non-inferiority margin for the OAB symptom score of
      15% at 12-weeks. The primary outcome measure will be urinary symptom severity as measured by
      the International Consultation on Incontinence Questionnaire (ICIQ)-OAB symptom score
      collected at 3 time points during the study: baseline, 6 weeks, and 12 weeks. The
      investigators' benchmark for successful treatment will be a 2 point reduction in the ICIQ-OAB
      symptom score, which corresponds with perceived benefit in preliminary studies of behavioral
      therapy treatment for OAB symptoms in PD. To evaluate the primary efficacy outcome, the
      investigators will utilize a random effects mixed model and adjust for baseline OAB symptom
      score severity. Additionally, in order to better understand central control mechanisms of
      bladder function, the investigators will determine if domain-specific cognitive function
      impacts the response to exercise-based behavioral therapy or drug therapy for urinary
      symptoms. At baseline and 12 weeks, randomized participants will undergo a brief
      neuropsychological battery. Understanding how domain-specific cognitive function impacts
      response to treatment may inform new targets for rehabilitation therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized Controlled Non-Inferiority Trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Blinded assessor</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ICIQ-OAB questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline in symptom score at 12 weeks within and between groups</time_frame>
    <description>The ICIQ-OAB questionnaire is a 4-question assessment of OAB symptoms and the degree to which they bother the respondent (urgency, frequency, nocturia, UI).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bladder diary</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline in weekly incontinence frequency at 12 weeks within and between groups</time_frame>
    <description>7-day bladder diary includes daily participant-reported voids and incontinent episodes, with ratings of associated urgency, and wake time and bedtime to assess daytime frequency and nocturia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICIQ-OAB QOL</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline in QOL score at 12 weeks within and between groups</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of quality of life related to the impact of overactive bladder symptoms on daily activities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Overactive Bladder</condition>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pelvic floor muscle exercise-based behavioral therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Daily solifenacin drug therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>solifenacin</intervention_name>
    <description>Antimuscarinic bladder relaxant, antagonizes bladder muscarinic receptors</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vesicare</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pelvic floor muscle exercise-based behavioral therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Multicomponent intervention including fluid management, constipation management and behavioral techniques incorporating pelvic floor muscle-exercise based urge suppression and self-monitoring to reduce overactive bladder symptoms</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of PD determined by a board-certified neurologist with specialty
             training in movement disorders

          -  An ICIQ-OAB Symptom Score of 7, which indicates clinically significant symptoms of
             OAB, defined as presence of urinary urgency with or without urgency incontinence
             usually with increased daytime frequency and nocturia in the absence of infection or
             other obvious pathology

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Significant cognitive impairment, as indicated by a Montreal Cognitive Assessment
             (MoCA) score of &lt; 18, which is the recommended diagnostic cutpoint for dementia in PD.

          -  Previous intensive pelvic floor muscle exercise training

          -  Clinically significant depression as measured by a Geriatric Depression Scale-Short
             Form score 10 which could affect motivation to fully engage in the intervention

          -  Use of an indwelling urinary catheter

          -  Post-void residual (PVR) urine measurement by bladder ultrasound of 150 mL

          -  Severe uterine prolapse past the vaginal introitus

          -  Poorly controlled diabetes defined by a hemoglobin A1c (HgbA1c) of &gt;9.0% within the
             last 3 months. Participants with poorly controlled diabetes will be offered enrollment
             if the OAB symptoms persist after improvement in diabetes control

          -  Chronic renal failure and on hemodialysis

          -  Genitourinary cancer with ongoing surgical or external beam radiation treatment

          -  Previous artificial urinary sphincter, sling procedure or implanted sacral
             neuromodulation device

          -  History of bladder-injection of botulinum toxin in the last 12 months

          -  Any unstable health condition expected to result in hospitalization or death within in
             the next 3 months as determined by site principal investigator.

          -  Hypersensitivity to drug class

          -  Contraindication to the study drug (solifenacin) including: narrow angle glaucoma,
             history of gastric retention, history of acute urinary retention requiring
             catheterization

          -  Current use of a bladder relaxant - permitted to enroll after two week washout

          -  Hematuria on microscopic examination in the absence of infection. A urologic
             consultation will be recommended and enrollment will depend on clearance by a
             urologist and agreement by the site PI that entry into the treatment protocol is not
             contraindicated

          -  If on diuretic, dose should be stable for at least 4 weeks

          -  If taking an alpha-blocker, dose should be stable for at least 4 weeks

          -  If taking dutasteride or finasteride, dose should be stable for at least 6 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Camille Vaughan, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Atlanta VA Medical and Rehab Center, Decatur, GA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Taressa Sergent</last_name>
    <phone>(404) 321-1611</phone>
    <phone_ext>5023</phone_ext>
    <email>taressa.sergent@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Birmingham VA Medical Center, Birmingham, AL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Galen Hale</last_name>
      <phone>205-933-8101</phone>
      <phone_ext>5637</phone_ext>
      <email>galen.hale@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alayne D Markland, MD</last_name>
      <phone>2055587067</phone>
      <phone_ext>6365</phone_ext>
      <email>alayne.markland@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlanta VA Medical and Rehab Center, Decatur, GA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth C Vaughan, MD MS</last_name>
      <phone>(404) 321-6111</phone>
      <phone_ext>3710</phone_ext>
      <email>elizabeth.vaughan2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Camille Vaughan, MD MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hunter Holmes McGuire VA Medical Center, Richmond, VA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23249</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peggy Roberge, RN</last_name>
      <phone>804-675-5000</phone>
      <phone_ext>6285</phone_ext>
      <email>peggy.roberge@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jessica Lehosit, MD</last_name>
      <phone>8046755000</phone>
      <phone_ext>1570</phone_ext>
      <email>jessica.lehosit@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Urinary incontinence</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Overactive urinary bladder</keyword>
  <keyword>Nocturia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder, Overactive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Solifenacin Succinate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Final data sets underlying publications resulting from the proposed research will be shared outside VA through a de-identified, anonymized Dataset under a written agreement that adheres to any applicable Informed Consent provisions and prohibits the recipient from identifying or re-identifying (or taking steps to identify or re-identify) any individual whose data are included in the dataset.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

