<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03145181</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR108206</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-002122-36</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>64007957MMY1001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03145181</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose Escalation Study of JNJ-64007957, a Humanized BCMA CD3 DuoBody® Antibody, in Participants With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, First-in-Human, Open-Label, Dose Escalation Study of JNJ-64007957, a Humanized BCMA x CD3 DuoBody® Antibody in Subjects With Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to identify the recommended Phase 2 dose(s) (RP2Ds) and schedule
      assessed to be safe for JNJ-64007957 and to characterize the safety and tolerability of
      JNJ-64007957 at the RP2Ds.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be conducted in 2 parts: dose escalation (Part 1) and dose expansion (Part 2).
      It will evaluate safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics and preliminary antitumor activity of
      JNJ-64007957 administered to adult participants with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma.
      The overall safety of the study drug will be assessed by physical examinations, Eastern
      Cooperative Oncology Group performance status, laboratory tests, vital signs,
      electrocardiograms, adverse event monitoring, and concomitant medication usage. Disease
      evaluations will include peripheral blood and bone marrow assessments at screening (performed
      within 28 days) and to confirm stringent complete response (sCR), complete response (CR), or
      relapse from CR. The end of study (study completion) is defined as the last study assessment
      for the last participant on study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 16, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>The Dose Limiting Toxicities (DLTs) are based on drug related adverse events and defined as any of the following events: hematological / non hematological toxicity of Grade 3 or higher.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Adverse Events (AEs) as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>From signing of Informed Consent Form (ICF) up to follow up (approximately up to 6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a participant participating in a clinical study that does not necessarily have a causal relationship with the pharmaceutical/biological agent under study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>JNJ-64007957 Serum Concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Concentration assessment will be done to evaluate the effect of JNJ-64007957.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with JNJ-64007957 Antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Antibodies to JNJ-64007957 will be assessed to evaluate potential immunogenicity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary Antitumor Activity of JNJ‑64007957 at the RP2D(s) in Part 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to End of Treatment (Approximately 91 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Preliminary antitumor activity of JNJ‑64007957 will be done using the International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) response criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarker Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Biomarker assessment may be done to evaluate the effect of JNJ‑64007957.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Hematological Malignancies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive intravenous infusion of JNJ-64007957 until the completion of the End of Treatment Visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive intravenous (IV) infusion of JNJ-64007957 at each RP2D(s).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JNJ-64007957</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive IV infusion of JNJ-64007957.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented initial diagnosis of multiple myeloma according to International Myeloma
             Working Group (IMWG) diagnostic criteria

          -  Measurable multiple myeloma that is relapsed or refractory to established therapies
             with known clinical benefit in relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma or be intolerant
             of those established multiple myeloma therapies, and a candidate for JNJ-64007957
             treatment in the opinion of the treating physician. Prior lines of therapy must
             include a proteasome inhibitor and an immunomodulatory drug in any order during the
             course of treatment. Participants who could not tolerate a proteasome inhibitor or
             immunomodulatory drugs are allowed

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status score of 0 or 1

          -  Women of childbearing potential and fertile men who are sexually active must agree to
             use a highly effective method of contraception (less than [&lt;] 1 percent [%] / year
             failure rate) during the study and for 90 days after the last dose of study drug.
             Contraception must be consistent with local regulations regarding the use of birth
             control methods for participants participating in clinical trials. When a woman is of
             childbearing potential the following are required: Participants must agree to practice
             a highly effective method of contraception (failure rate of &lt;1% per year when used
             consistently and correctly). Examples of highly effective contraceptives for women
             include user-independent methods (for example, implantable progestogen-only hormone
             contraception associated with inhibition of ovulation; intrauterine device;
             intrauterine hormone-releasing system; vasectomized partner) and user-dependent
             methods (for example: combined [estrogen- and progestogen-containing] hormonal
             contraception associated with inhibition of ovulation [oral/intravaginal/
             transdermal]; progestogen-only hormone contraception associated with inhibition of
             ovulation [oral/injectable]. In addition to the highly effective method of
             contraception, a man who is sexually active with a woman of childbearing potential
             must agree to use a barrier method of contraception (for example a condom with
             spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/suppository). Additionally, a man who is sexually
             active with a woman who is pregnant must use a condom. Women and men must agree not to
             donate eggs (ova, oocytes) or sperm, respectively, during the study and for 90 days
             after the last dose of study drug

          -  Participants must sign an informed consent form (ICF) indicating that he or she
             understands the purpose of and procedures required for the study and is willing to
             participate in the study. Consent is to be obtained prior to the initiation of any
             study-related tests or procedures that are not part of standard-of-care for the
             participant's disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior treatment with any therapy that is targeted to B cell maturation antigen (BCMA)
             or any other CD3-redirecting drug

          -  Prior antitumor therapy as follows, before the first dose of study drug: Targeted
             therapy, epigenetic therapy, or treatment with an investigational drug or used an
             invasive investigational medical device within 21 days or at least 5 half-lives,
             whichever is less; Monoclonal antibody treatment for multiple myeloma within 21 days;
             Cytotoxic therapy within 21 days; Proteasome inhibitor therapy within 14 days;
             Immunomodulatory agent therapy within 7 days; Radiotherapy within 21 days. However, if
             the radiation portal covered less than or equal to (&lt;=) 5% of the bone marrow reserve,
             the participant is eligible irrespective of the end date of radiotherapy

          -  Toxicities from previous anticancer therapies should have resolved to baseline levels
             or to Grade 1 or less except for alopecia or peripheral neuropathy

          -  Received a cumulative dose of corticosteroids equivalent to greater than or equal to
             (&gt;=) 140 milligram (mg) of prednisone within the 14-day period before the first dose
             of study drug

          -  Known active central nervous system (CNS) involvement or exhibits clinical signs of
             meningeal involvement of multiple myeloma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Study Contact</last_name>
    <phone>844-434-4210</phone>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai Program for the Protection of Human Subjects</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Levine Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarah Cannon Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VU Medisch Centrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1081 HV</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinica Univ. de Navarra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hosp. Clinico Univ. de Salamanca</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salamanca</city>
        <zip>37007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Haematology Centre, R 51</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>SE-141 86</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://pam.sylogent.com/cr/CR108206</url>
    <description>To learn how to participate in this trial please click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

