<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03147443</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>haiyinhuang</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03147443</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Effects of Traditional Chinese Medicine by N-of-1 Trials</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Study on the Effects of Traditional Chinese Medicine Through a Series of N-of-1 Trials Based on the Mathematical Model of &quot;Carryover Effect&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Treatment based on syndrome differentiation is the essence of traditional Chinese
      Medicine(TCM) and forms the individualized treatment. N-of-1 trials may be a good clinical
      effect evaluation method for the individualized treatment of TCM. This study aims to compare:
      (1) the efficacy of syndrome differentiation(individualized decoction) with placebo, (2)the
      efficacy of syndrome differentiation(individualized decoction) with the same prescription
      minus heat-clearing Chinese herbs, for patients with stable bronchiectasis through N-of-1
      trials.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Traditional Chinese medicine is one of the important part of complementary and alternative
      medicine in the world, and it plays increasingly important role in the international medical
      practice. Treatment based on syndrome differentiation is the essence of traditional Chinese
      Medicine (TCM) and forms the individualized treatment. However, this individualized TCM
      intervention often makes it difficult for population-based RCTs to carry out a standard form.
      N-of-1 trials may be a good clinical effect evaluation method for the individualized
      treatment of TCM.

      The key hypothesis of this study is that: (1) the efficacy of syndrome
      differentiation(individualized decoction) will be better than placebo in patients with stable
      bronchiectasis through N-of-1 trials. (2) the efficacy of syndrome
      differentiation(individualized decoction) will be better than the same prescription minus
      heat-clearing Chinese herbs in patients with stable bronchiectasis through N-of-1 trials. The
      difference of efficacy may be various according to the individual severity of phlegm-heat.

      In this study, We will conduct a single center N-of-1 trials in 36 patients with stable
      bronchiectasis without hemoptysis and respiratory failure. These N-of-1 trials will be
      randomized, double-blind, crossover comparisons of individualized herbal decoction with
      control decoction within individual patients. Each n-of-1 trial has 3 pairs of treatment
      periods. The duration of each treatment period will be 4 weeks. We will compare :(1) the
      efficacy of syndrome differentiation(individualized decoction) with placebo, (2) the efficacy
      of syndrome differentiation(individualized decoction) with the same prescription minus
      heat-clearing Chinese herbs, in patients with stable bronchiectasis through N-of-1 trials.
      The primary outcome is patient self-reported symptoms(such as cough, expectoration, shortness
      of breath, chest pain, and fatigue) scores on a 7 point visual analogue scale. Secondary
      outcomes are 24-hour sputum volume and CAT（The COPD Assessment Test） scores. We use paired t
      test for single case. Mixed effects model taking account of &quot;Carryover Effects&quot; and
      meta-analysis will be used for a series of N-of-1 trials as a group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>randomized, double-blind, crossover comparisons of individualized herbal decoction with control decoction within individual patients. Each n-of-1 trial has 3 pairs of treatment periods. The duration of each treatment period will be 4 weeks.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Placebo is made by dextrin, bitter agent, edible pigment etc and added 5% test drug. The test drug and control drug have no differences in dosage form, appearance, color, specification, label, and so forth.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Self-Rated Symptom Score</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Patients rated the severity of the symptoms (such as cough, expectoration, shortness of breath, chest pain, and fatigue) on a 7 point visual analogue scales. The higher the score, the more severe the symptom.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>24 h Sputum Volume</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>We measured the 24h sputum volume at the beginning and the end of each treatment period of the trial. To ensure the accuracy of the measurement, we asked the patients to spit sputum into a collector with scales from 8:00 am to the next 8:00 am. We used the mean value of the sputum volume for 3 consecutive days as the outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>COPD Assessment Test</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>COPD Assessment Test questionnaire is composed of 8 items. Each item has a score ranging from 0 to 5, thereby making the total score range from 0 to 40. Score of 0 represents the best quality of life and 40 does the worst.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Bronchiectasis</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <condition>Traditional Chinese Medicine</condition>
  <condition>Sputum</condition>
  <condition>Symptoms</condition>
  <condition>Individuality</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Individualized Decoction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>It is the highly individualized treatment of traditional Chinese medicine,the modification of Bronchiectasis Stabilization Decoction(Radix Lithospermi 15 g, Rhizoma Fagopyri Cymosi 30 g, Radix Ophiopogonis 15 g, Poria cocos 15 g, Radix Astragali 20 g, Rhizoma Bletillae 10 g, Platycodon grandiflorum 10 g, and Semen Coicis 30 g) based on syndrome differentiation. For example,for patients with qi and yin deficiency syndrome, we added Radix Adenophorae, and Radix Rehmanniae Recens. Besides, the herbs in a prescription could be changed according to different symptoms of individual patients.
The Chinese herbal decoction is taken by one decoction a day and divided into 2 doses, for 3 weeks in each observation period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo is made by dextrin, bitter agent, edible pigment etc and added 5% test drug. The placebo and test drug have no differences in dosage form, appearance, color, specification, label, and so forth.
The placebo is taken by one decoction a day and divided into 2 doses, for 3 weeks in each observation period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tested drug minus heat-clearing herbs</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>It is the decoction of the Individualized Syndrome Differentiation Decoction(tested drug) minus heat-clearing herbs. For example, heat-clearing herbs such as Scutellaria baicalensis or Herba Violae will be removed from the Syndrome Differentiation Decoction.
This control Chinese herbal decoction is taken by one decoction a day and divided into 2 doses, for 3 weeks in each observation period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Individualized Decoction</intervention_name>
    <description>Applied in the Tested Drug Observation Period. It is the highly individualized treatment of traditional Chinese medicine,the modification of Bronchiectasis Stabilization Decoction(Radix Lithospermi 15 g, Rhizoma Fagopyri Cymosi 30 g, Radix Ophiopogonis 15 g, Poria cocos 15 g, Radix Astragali 20 g, Rhizoma Bletillae 10 g, Platycodon grandiflorum 10 g, and Semen Coicis 30 g) based on syndrome differentiation. For example,for patients with qi and yin deficiency syndrome, we added Radix Adenophorae, and Radix Rehmanniae Recens. Besides, the herbs in a prescription could be changed according to different symptoms of individual patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Individualized Decoction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tested drug minus heat-clearing herbs</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Applied in the placebo Observation Period. Placebo is made by dextrin, bitter agent, edible pigment etc and added 5% test drug. The test drug and control drug have no differences in dosage form, appearance, color, specification, label, and so forth.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Individualized Decoction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tested drug minus heat-clearing herbs</intervention_name>
    <description>It is the decoction of the Syndrome Differentiation Decoction(tested drug) minus heat-clearing herbs. For example, heat-clearing herbs such as Scutellaria baicalensis or Herba Violae will be removed from the Syndrome Differentiation Decoction.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tested drug minus heat-clearing herbs</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  the diagnostic criteria based on the consensus of Chinese experts and the guidelines
             for noncystic fibrosis bronchiectasis issued by the British Thoracic Society in 2010;

          -  male or female, aged 18-70 years;

          -  being in the stable stage, and no acute exacerbation of bronchiectasis within the past
             three weeks;

          -  frequency of acute exacerbation of bronchiectasis ≤ 3 times every year;

          -  signed informed consent for participation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  having developed respiratory failure with estimated survival time less than one year;

          -  having hemoptysis as a comorbidity;

          -  having complications by active tuberculosis;

          -  being pregnant or with severe heart, liver,and kidney dysfunctions;

          -  participating in other pharmacological clinical trials within the past 3 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Haiyin Huang, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>008602165161782</phone>
    <email>haiyin_huang@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yueyang Hospital of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine,Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200437</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Haiyin Huang, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>008602165161782</phone>
      <email>haiyin_huang@126.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Haiyin Huang, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang H, Yang P, Xue J, Tang J, Ding L, Ma Y, Wang J, Guyatt GH, Vanniyasingam T, Zhang Y. Evaluating the Individualized Treatment of Traditional Chinese Medicine: A Pilot Study of N-of-1 Trials. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med. 2014;2014:148730. doi: 10.1155/2014/148730. Epub 2014 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25477988</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee BY, Lee S, Lee JS, Song JW, Lee SD, Jang SH, Jung KS, Hwang YI, Oh YM. Validity and Reliability of CAT and Dyspnea-12 in Bronchiectasis and Tuberculous Destroyed Lung. Tuberc Respir Dis (Seoul). 2012 Jun;72(6):467-74. doi: 10.4046/trd.2012.72.6.467. Epub 2012 Jun 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23101012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 6, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>haiyinhuang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>chief physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>traditional Chinese medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Drugs, Chinese Herbal</keyword>
  <keyword>N-of-1 trials</keyword>
  <keyword>sputum</keyword>
  <keyword>symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>individualized treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>stable bronchiectasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bronchiectasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

