<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03399981</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>101MS411</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03399981</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tysabri Observational Cohort Study - Multiple Sclerosis (MS) Registries</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Observational Study Utilising Data From the US Tysabri TOUCH Programme and Select EU MS Registries to Estimate the Risk of Progressive Multifocal Leukoencephalopathy (PML) and Other Serious Opportunistic Infections Among Patients Who Were Exposed to an MS Disease Modifying Treatment Prior to Treatment With Tysabri</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Biogen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Biogen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to estimate the incidence of progressive multifocal
      leucoencephalopathy (PML) among patients who switched to Tysabri from disease modifying
      therapies (DMTs), including newer DMTs (including fingolimod, dimethyl fumarate and
      teriflunomide) and the established DMTs (interferon beta and glatiramer acetate). Researchers
      will also look to estimate the incidence of other serious opportunistic infections among
      patients who switch to Tysabri from newer DMTs (including fingolimod, dimethyl fumarate and
      teriflunomide) and the established DMTs (interferon beta and glatiramer acetate)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an observational cohort study utilising all available data from the Tysabri TOUCH
      (TYSABRI Outreach: Unified Commitment to Health) prescribing programme (US) supplemented with
      data from European Union (EU) multiple sclerosis (MS) registries to estimate the risk of PML
      and other serious opportunistic infections (OIs) among patients on Tysabri who have switched
      from newer DMTs (including fingolimod, dimethyl fumarate and teriflunomide) and the
      established DMTs (interferon beta and glatiramer acetate).

      This study will provide cumulative data from its two components separately: a retrospective
      component (data captured prior to 1 January 2016) and a prospective component (data captured,
      and patients followed up, from 1 January 2016 through 31 December 2023; total prospective
      study duration of 8 years). All patients who switched to Tysabri from another DMT through 31
      December 2020 will be included. The study will continue to follow-up patients until 31
      December 2023 to allow for a minimal follow-up of 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 24, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prospective and Retrospective Analyses: Number of Participants with Confirmed Progressive Multifocal Leukoencephalopathy (PML)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrospective: from the time of switching to Tysabri to 31 December 2015; Prospective: from the time of switching to Tysabri (on or after 01 January 2016) to 31 December 2023 (up to 8 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Confirmed cases of PML must have one of the following:
• Brain biopsy or brain from post mortem examination showing evidence of viral cytopathic changes on hematoxylin and eosin (H &amp; E) staining associated with either positive immunohistochemistry for SV40 or in-situ hybridization for John Cunningham Virus (JCV) deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) OR
All of the following criteria:
• Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) with evidence of JCV DNA, preferably by ultra-sensitive quantitative polymerase chain reaction (PCR) testing (limit of quantification of ≤ 50 copies/ml), or JCV DNA on brain biopsy by PCR AND detailed description of brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) findings that are consistent with PML AND PREFERABLY new or progressive clinical symptoms suggestive of PML</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prospective and Retrospective Analyses: Number of Participants with Serious Adverse Events of Other Serious Opportunistic Infections (OIs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrospective: from the time of switching to Tysabri to 31 December 2015; Prospective: from the time of switching to Tysabri (on or after 01 January 2016) to 31 December 2023 (up to 8 years)</time_frame>
    <description>An SAE is any untoward medical occurrence at any dose that results in death, immediate risk of death, hospitalization, disability, or congenital anomaly/birth defect.
Opportunistic infections (OIs) are infections that occur more frequently and are more severe in individuals with weakened immune systems.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34600</enrollment>
  <condition>Progressive Multifocal Leukoencephalopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tysabri (TOUCH Cohort)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients from the Tysabri TOUCH prescribing programme who have switched to Tysabri from newer DMTs (including fingolimod, dimethyl fumarate and teriflunomide) and the established DMTs (interferon beta and glatiramer acetate).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tysabri (EU MS Cohort)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients from the EU MS registry who have switched to Tysabri from newer DMTs (including fingolimod, dimethyl fumarate and teriflunomide) and the established DMTs (interferon beta and glatiramer acetate).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tysabri</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered as specified in the treatment arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tysabri (TOUCH Cohort)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tysabri (EU MS Cohort)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Natalizumab BG00002</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All TOUCH and available EU MS registry patients who have switched from DMTs (including
        fingolimod, dimethyl fumarate, teriflunomide, interferon beta and glatiramer acetate) and
        have one or more infusion(s) of Tysabri.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All TOUCH and available EU MS registry patients who have switched from DMTs (including
             fingolimod, dimethyl fumarate, teriflunomide, interferon beta and glatiramer acetate)
             and have one or more infusion(s) of Tysabri.

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

        NOTE: Other protocol defined Inclusion/Exclusion criteria may apply
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Biogen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02142</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukoencephalopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukoencephalopathy, Progressive Multifocal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glatiramer Acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dimethyl Fumarate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Natalizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

