<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03391869</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-0311</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2018-00825</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03391869</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Local Consolidation Therapy (LCT) After Nivolumab and Ipilimumab (LONESTAR)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Phase III Trial of Local Consolidation Therapy (LCT) After Nivolumab and Ipilimumab for Immunotherapy-Naive Patients With Metastatic Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (LONESTAR) -Strategic Alliance: BMS</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if local consolidation treatment (LCT--
      surgery and/or radiation) plus immunotherapy (ipilimumab and nivolumab) is more effective
      than ipilimumab and nivolumab alone in treating patients with metastatic (has spread)
      non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) who have not previously received immunotherapy.

      This is an investigational study. LCT is FDA approved and commercially available for the
      treatment of NSCLC. Nivolumab and ipilimumab are FDA approved and commercially available for
      treatment of many types of cancer. It is considered investigational to use nivolumab and
      ipilimumab to treat metastatic NSCLC.

      The study doctor can explain how the study drugs and LCT are designed to work.

      Up to 270 participants will be enrolled in this study. All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Groups:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in the study, you will be randomly assigned (as
      in the flip of a coin) to 1 of 2 treatment arms. This is done because no one knows if one
      group is better, the same, or worse than the other.

        -  If you are in Arm A, you will receive ipilimumab and nivolumab.

        -  If you are in Arm B, you will receive LCT plus ipilimumab and nivolumab.

      You will have an equal chance (50/50) of being assigned to either arm. The study doctor will
      tell you to which arm you have been assigned. Before you are randomized to a study group, you
      will complete a questionnaire about any symptoms you may be having and how those symptoms are
      affecting your daily living. This questionnaire should take about 5 minutes to complete.

      Study Drug Administration:

      Each study cycle will be 6 weeks (42 days). Ipilimumab is given by vein over about 90 minutes
      and nivolumab is given by vein over about 60 minutes.

      All participants will receive 2 cycles of ipilimumab and nivolumab treatment alone before
      being assigned to either Arm A or Arm B. This is called Induction. If you have a complete
      response (meaning the disease goes away), you will continue to receive nivolumab and
      ipilimumab as part of your standard care and you will not be randomized as described above.
      However, you will continue to take part in follow-up for this study.

      After Induction, you will receive nivolumab on Days 1, 15, and 29 of each cycle (about every
      2 weeks) and ipilimumab on Day 1 of each cycle (about every 6 weeks).

      If you are in Arm B, you will receive LCT within 14 days after your last dose of nivolumab
      during Induction. The study doctor, surgeon, and radiation oncologist will decide if you will
      have surgery and/or radiation therapy. You will sign a separate consent for surgery and/or
      radiation therapy which describes the treatment in more detail, including its risks. After
      you receive LCT, you will begin to receive nivolumab and ipilimumab as described above.

      Length of Study:

      You may receive nivolumab/ipilimumab for up to 2 years. You will receive LCT one time. You
      will no longer be able to take the study drugs if the disease gets worse, if intolerable side
      effects occur, or if you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation in this study will be over after follow-up (described below).

      Treatment Beyond Progression:

      If the disease appears to be getting worse (progression) or the tumor(s) appear to be getting
      larger, and you agree, you may still be able to receive ipilimumab and nivolumab if you and
      your doctor decide it is in your best interest. You may continue taking the study drugs for
      as long as possible as described below. Sometimes the disease appears to get worse but the
      study drugs are actually working.

      However, there are risks of continuing to receive the study drugs if the disease is actually
      getting worse. You are still at risk for side effects due to study drugs. This could also
      delay starting other treatments. The disease may get worse to the point that you are no
      longer able to receive other treatments.

      If you choose to receive the study drugs after the disease appears to get worse, you will
      continue to have study visits as described below. The study doctor will discuss this option
      with you.

      Study Visits:

      Induction:

      Before starting Induction therapy and after completing Induction therapy, you will complete
      the symptoms and daily living questionnaire and blood (about 6 tablespoons) will be drawn for
      biomarker testing, including genetic biomarkers.

      Within 3 days before Days 1, 15, and 29 of each cycle:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 1½ tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      At least 10 days after your last dose of nivolumab, you will have a CT scan or PET/CT to
      check the status of your disease. If the doctor thinks it is needed, you will have an MRI/CT
      scan of your brain.

      Post-Induction:

      Every 1-2 weeks during LCT (if you are in Arm B), you will have a physical exam.

      At the end of LCT (if you are in Arm B) or after completing 3 doses of nivolumab (if you are
      in Arm A), blood (about 6 tablespoons) will be drawn for biomarker testing.

      If you have a certain side effect and the doctor thinks it is needed, blood (about 6
      tablespoons) will be drawn for biomarker testing.

      Within 3 days before Days 1, 15, and 29 of each cycle:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 1½ tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests. On days you also receive
           ipilimumab, this sample will be used for thyroid function testing.

      Every 8 weeks, you will have a CT scan or PET/CT to check the status of your disease and you
      will complete the symptom and daily living questionnaire. If the doctor thinks it is needed,
      you will have an MRI/CT scan of your brain.

      If the disease gets worse at any time while on study, you will complete the symptom and daily
      living questionnaire, and blood (about 6 tablespoons) will be drawn for biomarker testing.

      End-of-Study Visit:

      Within 8 weeks after your last dose of study drugs:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  You will complete the symptom and daily living questionnaire.

        -  Blood (about 6 tablespoons) will be drawn for biomarker testing.

      Long-Term Follow-Up:

      After you have completed treatment or the disease has gotten worse, you or a family member
      may be contacted by phone, letter, e-mail, or during a clinic visit to learn how you are
      doing and if you have started any new therapies. If you are called, this call should last
      about 5-10 minutes. This follow-up will continue for as long as you are taking part in this
      study.

      You will be called at least every 3 months for at least 1 year after the end of radiation
      therapy. During these calls, you will be asked if you have had any side effects related to
      radiation.

      Treatment Beyond Progression:

      If the disease appears to be getting worse or the tumors appear to be getting larger, you may
      still be able to receive the study drugs if you and your doctor decide it is in your best
      interest. Sometimes the disease appears to get worse but the study drug is actually working.
      This is not considered standard in the treatment of cancer. Your doctor will discuss with you
      alternative treatment options which will include available FDA approved therapies as well as
      participation in other clinical trials.

      However, there are risks of continuing to receive the study drug because the disease may
      actually be getting worse. You are still at risk for side effects due to the study drug. This
      could also delay starting other treatments. The disease may get worse to the point that you
      are no longer able to receive other treatments.

      If you choose to receive the study drug after the disease gets worse, you will continue to
      have study visits as described above. The study doctor will discuss this option with you.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 29, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>for up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival (OS) determined from randomization to a) death or b) last contact date (if alive).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS) in Oligometastatic Patients</measure>
    <time_frame>for up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>OS in oligometastatic patients determined from randomization to: a) death, or b) last contact date (if alive) in patients with ≤3 lesions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-free survival (PFS) determined from randomization to the earliest of the three endpoints: a) progression, b) last imaging study, or c) death Progression measured using RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Appearance of New Metastases (TANM)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time to appearance of new metastases (TANM) determined from randomization to the earliest of the two endpoints: a) development of a new lesion, or b) last imaging study per RECIST 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression of Target lesions Defined by RECIST 1.1 Criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression of Non-Target Lesions by RECIST 1.1 Criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity Evaluated Using CTCAE v4.0 Criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicity evaluated using CTCAE v4.0 criteria, with a specific focus on ≥3 toxicity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>After 12 weeks of therapy and then every 3 months for up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>QOL assessed using the lung-MD Anderson symptom inventory (MDASI-LC) questionnaire in collaboration with the MD Anderson symptom management group, at the following timepoints: 1) prior to induction treatment, 2) prior to randomization, 3) every 12 weeks, and 4) after progression/off study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">270</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasms of Respiratory and Intrathoracic Organs</condition>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Ipilimumab + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each study cycle is 6 weeks (42 days).
Induction: All participants receive 2 cycles of Ipilimumab and Nivolumab treatment alone.
After Induction, participants receive Nivolumab on Days 1, 15, and 29 of each cycle (about every 2 weeks) and Ipilimumab on Day 1 of each cycle (about every 6 weeks) until progression or up to 2 years.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: LCT + Ipilimumab + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each study cycle is 6 weeks (42 days).
Induction: All participants receive 2 cycles of Ipilimumab and Nivolumab treatment alone.
After Induction, participants receive LCT within 14 days after last dose of Nivolumab during Induction. The study doctor, surgeon, and radiation oncologist will decide if participant will have surgery and/or radiation therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ipilimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction: Ipilimumab 1 mg/Kg by vein every 6 hours for 12 weeks.
After randomization: Ipilimumab 1 mg/Kg by vein every 6 hours for up to 2 years.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Ipilimumab + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: LCT + Ipilimumab + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Yervoy</other_name>
    <other_name>BMS-734016</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX010</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction: Nivolumab 3 mg/Kg by vein every 2 weeks for 12 weeks.
After randomization: Nivolumab 3 mg/Kg by vein every 2 weeks for up to 2 years.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Ipilimumab + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: LCT + Ipilimumab + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BMS-936558</other_name>
    <other_name>Opdivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Local Consolidative Therapy (LCT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive LCT within 14 days after last dose of Nivolumab during Induction. The study doctor, surgeon, and radiation oncologist decide if participant will have surgery and/or radiation therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: LCT + Ipilimumab + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &gt;/= 18

          2. Histologically or cytologically confirmed non-small cell lung cancer. If a diagnostic
             biopsy is available, a pre-treatment biopsy is not required. Patients with a suspected
             lung cancer may be consented, but pathology must be confirmed prior to initiating
             treatment on study. Neuroendocrine carcinomas (e.g. SCLC, carcinoid tumors) are not
             eligible. Carcinomas with neuroendocrine differentiation are eligible.

          3. Stage IV (according to AJCC 8th edition).

          4. Signed and dated written informed consent prior to admission to the study in
             accordance with ICH-GCP guidelines and to the local legislation.

          5. For lung adenocarcinoma patients, patients must be wild-type for EGFR and ALK. For
             patients with histologies other than adenocarcinoma, EGFR and ALK status is not
             required. Adenocarcinoma patients may be consented prior to the EGFR and ALK status
             being known, but EGFR and ALK status must be determined prior to initiating therapy.
             EGFR and ALK status may be determined using either tumor- or plasma-based,
             CLIA-certified assays. For patients with NSCLC, not otherwise specified (NOS),
             EGFR/ALK testing is not required, as the frequency of alterations is exceedingly rare
             in this histology. Also, note that patients with ROS1/RET alterations can be enrolled,
             as TKIs/crizotinib aren't established as first line therapy for patients with these
             alterations.

          6. One prior line of chemotherapy and/or targeted agents for metastatic disease are
             permitted. This chemotherapy can include maintenance therapy, as long as it was given
             in the front line setting. In addition, prior antiangiogenic therapy (e.g.
             bevacizumab) is permitted if used as frontline treatment.

          7. Patients must have organ and marrow function as defined below: a) Performance Status
             of 0 or 1 if using ECOG/Zubrod. b) Screening laboratory values must meet the following
             criteria and should be obtained within 14 days prior to randomization/registration i)
             WBC &gt;/= 2000/µL ii) Neutrophils &gt;/= 1500/µL iii) Platelets &gt;/= 100 x 10 ^3/µL iv)
             Hemoglobin &gt; 9.0 g/dL v) Serum creatinine &lt;/=1.5 x ULN or creatinine clearance (CrCl)
             &gt;/= 50 mL (if using the Cockcroft-Gault formula): Female CrCl = (140 - age in years) x
             weight in kg x 0.85 ÷ 72 x serum creatinine in mg/dL; Male CrCl = (140 - age in years)
             x weight in kg x 1.00 ÷ 72 x serum creatinine in mg/dL vi) AST/ALT &lt;/= 3 x ULN vii)
             Total Bilirubin &lt;/= 1.5 x ULN (except subjects with Gilbert Syndrome, who can have
             total bilirubin &lt; 3.0 mg/dL)

          8. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must use appropriate method(s) of
             contraception. Appropriate methods of contraception are as follows. Women will be
             instructed to adhere to contraception for a period of 26 weeks after the last dose of
             investigational product. Men receiving nivolumab and who are sexually active with
             WOCBP will be instructed to adhere to contraception for a period of 35 weeks after the
             last week of nivo/ipi. Note: WOCBP is defined as any female who has experienced
             menarche and who has not yet undergone surgical sterilization (hysterectomy or
             bilateral oophorectomy) or who is not postmenopausal. Menopause is defined clinically
             as 12 months of amenorrhea in a woman over 45 in the absence of other biological or
             physiological causes. In addition, women under the age of 55 must have a documented
             negative serum or urine test.

          9. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test
             within 48 hours prior to the start of nivolumab.

         10. Men who are sexually active with WOCBP must use any contraceptive method with a
             failure rate of less than 1% per year. Men receiving nivolumab and who are sexually
             active with WOCBP will be instructed to adhere to contraception for a period of 35
             weeks after the last dose of investigational product Women who are not of childbearing
             potential (ie, who are postmenopausal or surgically sterile) as well as azoospermic
             men do not require contraception.

         11. Subjects with brain metastases are eligible if metastases have been treated and there
             is no MRI evidence of disease progression for 4 weeks after treatment is complete and
             within 28 days prior to the first dose of nivolumab. Subjects with asymptomatic brain
             metastases are eligible, though if treated with radiation or surgery the above
             criteria apply regarding a 28-day washout and MRI to assess for progression after 4
             weeks.

         12. Subjects may receive radiotherapy for symptomatic metastases prior to enrollment
             provided that there is at least one other non-irradiated lesion amenable to LCT at the
             time of enrollment. When feasible, stereotactic body radiation therapy (SBRT) or other
             hypofractionated techniques are strongly encouraged.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Systemic immunotherapy for metastatic NSCLC. Immunotherapy agents include, but are not
             limited to, agents targeting the PD1/PD-L1 axis (e.g. nivolumab, pembrolizumab,
             atezolizumab, durvalumab) or CTLA-4 (ipilimumab, tremelimumab) pathways.

          2. Any approved anti-cancer therapy, including chemotherapy, or hormonal therapy within 3
             weeks prior to the initiation of study treatment; the following exceptions are
             allowed: Hormone-replacement therapy or oral contraceptives

          3. Women must not be breastfeeding.

          4. Patients excluded with any prior treatment of pneumonitis requiring corticosteroids.

          5. Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures required in the protocol.

          6. Any serious or uncontrolled medical disorder that, in the opinion of the investigator,
             may increase the risk associated with study participation or study drug
             administration, impair the ability of the subject to receive protocol therapy, or
             interfere with the interpretation of study results.

          7. Prior malignancy active within the previous 2 years. Patients with locally curable
             cancers that have been apparently cured, such as basal or squamous cell skin cancer,
             superficial bladder cancer, or carcinoma in situ of the prostate, cervix, or breast
             with local control measures (surgery, radiation) are eligible.

          8. Patients should be excluded if they have an active, known or suspected autoimmune
             disease. Subjects are permitted to enroll if they have vitiligo, type I diabetes
             mellitus, residual hypothyroidism due to autoimmune condition only requiring hormone
             replacement, psoriasis not requiring systemic treatment, or conditions not expected to
             recur in the absence of an external trigger.

          9. Patients should be excluded if they have a condition requiring systemic treatment with
             either corticosteroids (&gt; 10 mg daily prednisone equivalents) or other
             immunosuppressive medications within 14 days of study drug administration (i.e.
             disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs). Inhaled or topical steroids and adrenal
             replacement doses &gt; 10 mg daily prednisone equivalents are permitted in the absence of
             active autoimmune disease. Note that subjects are permitted to use topical, ocular,
             intra-articular, intranasal, and inhalational corticosteroids (with minimal systemic
             absorption). Physiologic replacement doses of systemic corticosteroids are permitted,
             even if &gt;10 mg/day prednisone equivalents. A brief course of corticosteroids for
             prophylaxis (e.g. contrast dye allergy) or for treatment of non-autoimmune conditions
             (e.g. delayed-type hypersensitivity reaction caused by contact allergen) is permitted.

         10. As there is potential for hepatic toxicity with nivolumab or nivolumab/ipilimumab
             combinations, drugs with a predisposition to hepatoxicity should be used with caution.

         11. Patients should be excluded if they are known to be positive for hepatitis B virus
             surface antigen (HBV sAg) or hepatitis C virus ribonucleic acid (HCV antibody)
             indicating acute or chronic infection.

         12. Patients should be excluded if they have known history of testing positive for human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or known acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS).

         13. History of allergy to study drug components.

         14. History of severe hypersensitivity reaction to any monoclonal antibody.

         15. Prisoners or subjects who are involuntarily incarcerated.

         16. Subjects who are compulsorily detained for treatment of either a psychiatric or
             physical (infection disease) illness.

         17. Psychological, familial, sociological or geographical factors potentially hampering
             compliance with the study protocol and follow-up schedule.

         18. Any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with the study
             treatment or interpretation of the study results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Heymach, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John Heymach, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-6363</phone>
    <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center Memorial City</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77024</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Research Operations</last_name>
      <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center Katy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77094</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center Bay Area</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nassau Bay</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77058</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center Sugar Land</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sugar Land</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77478</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center The Woodlands</name>
      <address>
        <city>The Woodlands</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77384</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Malignant neoplasms of respiratory and intrathoracic organs</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>NSCLC</keyword>
  <keyword>Ipilimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Yervoy</keyword>
  <keyword>BMS-734016</keyword>
  <keyword>MDX010</keyword>
  <keyword>Nivolumab</keyword>
  <keyword>BMS-936558</keyword>
  <keyword>Opdivo</keyword>
  <keyword>Local Consolidative Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>LCT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

