<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03395730</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ppsi</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03395730</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intraumbilical Oxytocin Versus Placental Cord Drainage in the Management of 3rd Stage of Labor</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intraumbilical Oxytocin Compared to Placental Cord Drainage in the Management of Third Stage of Labor: A Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eslam Mohammed Abbas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ain Shams University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to compare the effectiveness of intraumbilical oxytocin and
      placental cord drainage in the management of third stage of labor.

      Does the use of intraumbilical vein oxytocin injection or the use of Placental cord drainage
      can cause a reduction of blood loss, Hb level drop, the length of the third stage of labor
      and the incidence of manual removal of the retained placenta during the third stage of labor
      in pregnant women after delivery of the infant?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study:

      Study Design: A prospective randomized clinical trial. Study setting: The study will be
      conducted in Ain Shams University Maternity Hospital.

      All pregnant women in the delivery ward will be submitted to:

        1. Detailed complete history taking with special emphasis to maternal age, Parity, Maternal
           weight, as well as presence of any disease.

        2. Clinical Examination:

           a. General examination. b. Abdominal examination (Symphysis-fundal height) and pelvic
           examination.

        3. Investigation

             1. Ultrasound assessment to evaluate GA, fetal weight, AFI and Placental site.

             2. Basal complete blood picture, urine analysis and random blood sugar.

                The selected patients will fulfill the following criteria:

                • Pregnant women between 18-35 years of age with normal pregnancy.

                • A singleton fetus at a gestational age of 37 - 42 weeks in a cephalic
                presentation.

                • Neonatal birth weight of 2500 to 4500 grams.

                Exclusion criteria:

                • Medical disorders and hypertensive disorders of pregnancy.

                • Intrauterine fetal death.

                • Known or suspected fetal anomalies.

                • Oxytocin induction or Augmented cases.

                  -  Obstetrical complications (bleeding, premature rupture of membranes).

                  -  Previous CS or Previous Myomectomy.

                Study population:

                The present study will be conducted on 150 women recruited from the delivery ward
                of our hospital after they had received information on the purpose and course of
                the study from the medical investigator and had provided the written consent during
                routine prenatal visits , The 150 study participants will be divided into three
                groups using simple random distribution technique. After monitoring the duration of
                active phase and second stage of labor by following the partograph.

                Randomization and Allocation concealment:

                Randomization will be based on the sequence generation created by computer and the
                randomization tables will be kept with the study supervisor. Consenting patients
                fulfilling inclusion criteria will be randomized into one of the following 3
                groups. Randomized allocation will be kept in opaque sealed envelopes, with
                enrollment numbers written on the envelopes. The envelopes will contain a card on
                with the designated study group will be written. After enrollment of the patients
                in the study, the envelopes marked with study number will be unsealed and the
                patients allocated to either groups:

                • Group (A) &quot;Study Group 1&quot;: In the labor room women in Group A (n = 50) receive
                intraumbilical vein injection oxytocin 20 units diluted in 20 ml of 0.9% saline
                solution immediately after delivery of the baby, clamping and cutting the cord.

                • Group (B) &quot;Study Group 2&quot;: The women in Group B (n = 50) have placental drainage
                immediately after delivery. This scenario will include placental cord clamping and
                cutting after delivery of the baby followed by immediately unclamping of the
                maternal side, allowing the blood to drain freely for a duration of three minutes.

                • Group (C) &quot;Control Group&quot;: The women in Group C (n = 50) as a control group
                receive no intervention. Placenta will be delivered spontaneously after appearance
                of clinical signs of placental separation, which include strong uterine
                contraction, vaginal bleeding, and descending of umbilical cord through the vulva.
                This scenario will include placental cord clamping and cutting after 2 minutes of
                delivery of the baby.

                Outcome:

                Retained placenta is defined as a placenta that remained in the uterus for 30
                minutes or more after delivery (Begley et al., 2014).

                  -  1ry outcome: Duration of the third stage of labor.

                  -  2ry outcome: Retained placenta, need for manual removal of placenta and the
                     drop in Hb will be recorded.

                Sample size calculation:

                Sample size was calculated using PASS® version 11 program, sample size calculation
                was based on study carried out by (Güngördük et al., 2011). A preliminary power
                analysis was carried out to calculate the sample size using a formula: d = Δ/SD,
                where d is standardized difference, Δ is the smallest clinically significant
                difference and SD is standard deviation of the test group. Duration of 1.6 minutes
                was considered as the smallest clinically significant difference, and the SD (1.6
                minutes) was selected the study performed by (Güngördük et al., 2011). Also, a
                standardized difference of 1.0 was obtained using nomogram. The power analysis
                suggested that a sample of 50 women in each group would provide a power of 95%, at
                5% significance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 30, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The present study will be conducted on 150 women recruited from the delivery ward of our hospital after they had received information on the purpose and course of the study from the medical investigator and had provided the written consent during routine prenatal visits , they will be randomly divided into:
Group (A) &quot;Study Group 1&quot;: (n = 50)
Group (B) &quot;Study Group 2&quot;: (n = 50)
Group (C) &quot;Control Group&quot;: (n = 50)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>Randomization will be based on the sequence generation created by computer and the randomization tables will be kept with the study supervisor. Consenting patients fulfilling inclusion criteria will be randomized into one of the following 3 groups. Randomized allocation will be kept in opaque sealed envelopes, with enrollment numbers written on the envelopes. The envelopes will contain a card on with the designated study group will be written. After enrollment of the patients in the study, the envelopes marked with study number will be unsealed and the patients allocated to either groups</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of the third stage of labor.</measure>
    <time_frame>5-15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of placental expulsion from the uterus after delivery of the fetus. by the use of a stop watch to calculate the time in minutes and seconds passing starting from the delivery of the baby till delivery of the placenta outside the the vagina.
To compare How long does the 3rd stage of labor persist with each intervention (in minutes and seconds).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retained placenta</measure>
    <time_frame>&gt;30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>defined as a placenta that remained in the uterus for 30 minutes or more after delivery.
by the use of a stop watch to calculate the time in minutes and seconds needed for placental expulsion.
To compare which intervention can result in delayed expulsion of placenta (in minutes and seconds) and cause a retained placenta.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the Need for manual removal of placenta</measure>
    <time_frame>&gt; 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>manual removal of the placenta under general anesthesia if the placental expulsion is delayed for more than 30 minutes.
to compare which intervention will require manual removal of the retained(by the percentage of yes and no) placenta.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the drop in hemoglobin in gm/dl</measure>
    <time_frame>after 2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>hemoglobin concentration in gm/dl will be measured for all participants before onset of delivery of the baby and 2 hours after labour and compare which maneuver included increased blood loss determined by the difference of hemoglobin concentration in gm/dl in the basal Hb level and the 2hr later Hb level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Postpartum Haemorrhage With Retained Placenta</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>• Group (A) &quot;Study Group 1&quot;:</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the labor room women in Group A (n = 50):
Clamping and cutting the placental cord after delivery of the baby.
Immediate intraumbilical vein injection of Oxytocin (Syntocinon®) 20 units diluted in 20 ml of 0.9% saline solution</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>• Group (B) &quot;Study Group 2&quot;:</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the labor room women in Group B (n = 50):
Clamping and cutting the placental cord after delivery of the baby.
Immediate unclamping of the maternal side, allowing the blood to drain freely for a duration of three minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>• Group (C) &quot;Control Group&quot;:</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the labor room women in Group C (n = 50):
Clamping and cutting the placental cord after 2 minutes of delivery of the baby.
Placenta will be delivered spontaneously after appearance of clinical signs of placental separation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intraumbilical vein injection oxytocin</intervention_name>
    <description>intraumbilical vein injection of oxytocin 20 units diluted in 20 ml of 0.9% saline solution immediately after delivery of the baby, clamping and cutting the cord.</description>
    <arm_group_label>• Group (A) &quot;Study Group 1&quot;:</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placental cord drainage</intervention_name>
    <description>placental cor drainage immediately after delivery. This scenario will include placental cord clamping and cutting after delivery of the baby followed by immediately unclamping of the maternal side, allowing the blood to drain freely for a duration of three minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>• Group (B) &quot;Study Group 2&quot;:</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Expectant managment of 3rd stage of labour</intervention_name>
    <description>Placenta will be delivered spontaneously after appearance of clinical signs of placental separation, which include strong uterine contraction, vaginal bleeding, and descending of umbilical cord through the vulva. This scenario will include placental cord clamping and cutting after 2 minutes of delivery of the baby.</description>
    <arm_group_label>• Group (C) &quot;Control Group&quot;:</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women between 18-35 years of age with normal pregnancy.

          -  A singleton fetus at a gestational age of 37 - 42 weeks in a cephalic presentation.

          -  Neonatal birth weight of 2500 to 4500 grams.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical disorders and hypertensive disorders of pregnancy.

          -  Intrauterine fetal death.

          -  Known or suspected fetal anomalies.

          -  Oxytocin induction or augmented cases.

          -  Obstetrical complications (bleeding, premature rupture of membranes).

          -  Previous CS or Previous Myomectomy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Pregnant women between 18-35 years of age with normal pregnancy</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tamer F Borg, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ain Shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bassem I Ali, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ain Shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Islam M Abbas, MBBch</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ain Shams University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Islam M Abbas, MBBch</last_name>
    <phone>00201025864906</phone>
    <email>dr.eslamabbas@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ain Shams Maternity Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <zip>11311</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tamer F Borg, PHD</last_name>
      <phone>00201001457437</phone>
      <email>tamerborg1975@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Bassem A Islam, PHD</last_name>
      <phone>00201002412634</phone>
      <email>aly.bassem74@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tamer F Borg, Professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bassem A Islam, Lecturer</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Islam M Abbas, MBBCH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ain Shams University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eslam Mohammed Abbas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postpartum Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Placenta, Retained</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oxytocin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 20, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>May 21, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>May 24, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

