<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03391336</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TSGHIRB 2-105-05-110</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03391336</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Median Nerve Injury in US-guided Carpal Tunnel Injections</brief_title>
  <official_title>Median Nerve Injury in US-guided Carpal Tunnel Injections</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>yi-chih HSU</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tri-Service General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Carpal tunnel syndrome (CTS) is the most common nerve compression disorder in the upper
      extremity. It can be treated with surgical or nonsurgical methods. When nonsurgical treatment
      is indicated, local corticosteroid injection into the carpal tunnel can be used to reduce
      pain and tingling sensation.

      Currently, the most widely used ultrasound (US)-guided CTS-injection method are transverse
      and longitudinal approach. Although we can accurately place needle within the carpal tunnel
      using this approach and this approach is easy to learn, median nerve injury (MNI) is still an
      inevitable complication and difficult to be treat.

      MNI is the most serious complication associated with a local corticosteroid injection for CTS
      among them. A MNI will be presented with shooting pain at the injection time or transient
      exacerbation of CTS symptoms following the corticosteroid injection because of the pain which
      often masked by anesthetic during injection. Permanent damage of MN should be considered if
      the symptoms persist and exacerbate for more than 48 hours. A surgical intervention such as
      neurolysis, resection or graft repair or a gentle debridement of the crystal from the nerve
      may be performed in the patients with median nerve damage. Hence, early recognition of MNI
      before corticosteroid injection may avoid the permanent damage of MN.

      Accordingly, the aim of this study is to determine the relationship between the MNI with the
      possible influencing factors and findings in the US-guided corticosteroid injection for
      patients with CTS with and to compare the therapeutic efficacy in the patients with and
      without MNI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients:

      This study was approved by our institutional review board (Tri-Service General Hospital);
      however, patient consent was not required for the retrospective review of records and images
      because patient anonymity was preserved. The patients with clinically suspected CTS evaluated
      by the referring neurologist (F. C. Y.), and the clinical tests included (1) typical
      symptoms, eg, hand numbness and pain in the distribution of the median nerve, nocturnal
      worsening of symptoms, worsening symptoms while driving or gripping, (2) positive Tinel's
      and/or Phalen's sign, (3) failure of splinting and/or hand rest. Patients with clinically
      suspected CTS underwent US examination. The diagnoses of CTS in these patients were confirmed
      by US and/or electrodiagnostic investigations.

      Ultrasonography:

      The US was provided using a scanner (Xario 100; Toshiba, Tokyo, Japan) with a 7~18 MHz linear
      transducer (PLU-1204BT). The US examinations were performed by an experienced technician
      (C.Y. H.) with 6 years of musculoskeletal experience in US. The technician received
      specialized training on the procedure used to scan the MN regarding the CTS and to record the
      images and was directly supervised by the attending radiologist (Y.C.H.). The US images after
      the US-guided hydrodissection were recorded by the attending radiologist (Y.C.H.). The
      diagnosis of CTS was based on qualitative US criteria, with a cutoff value of ≥12 mm2
      regarding the cross-sectional area (CSA) of the MN (CSA-MN) at the inlet of the carpal
      tunnel. The diagnoses of CTS were confirmed by electrodiagnostic investigations in the
      patients with US findings of the CSA-MN &lt; 12 mm2 at the inlet of the carpal tunnel. The
      flowchart illustrating patient selection is shown in Fig. 1. All US images and the
      measurements of cross sectional area (CSA) of the median nerve at the inlet of carpal tunnel
      were saved in the picture archiving and communication system (PACS). All the patients with
      clinically suspected CTS during the study period were examined using a standardized US
      protocol previously described to assess the MN at the wrist level (Figure. 1). Within 1 month
      after US-guided corticosteroid injection, we assessed the MN again with this manner.

      Ultrasound needle guidance:

      The US-guided injection procedure was performed in a standardized manner. The one-needle
      two-syringe technique with US guidance was used where (1) one needle is used for anesthesia,
      hydrodissection, and intra-carpal tunnel injection; (2) the first syringe is used to
      anesthetize, hydrodissect, and dilate the intra-carpal tunnel space; and (3) the second
      syringe is used to inject the corticosteroid therapy into the new hydrodissected space
      (Figure 2). After hydrodissection, the empty lidocaine syringe was detached from the needle
      while still in the carpal tunnel, and a 3-ml syringe prefilled with 10 mg triamcinolone
      acetonide suspension was attached to the indwelling needle, and the treatment was slowly
      injected into the hydrodissected neutral space that was closest to the MN. The injections
      were performed in a standardized fashion by a musculoskeletal radiologist (Y.C.H.) with 13
      years of experience in US.

      Smith et al have recommended the needle should be passed above and below the median nerve to
      fill the injectate around the median nerve with an ulnar approach. Although we can accurately
      place needle within the carpal tunnel using this ulnar approach and this approach is easy to
      learn, neurovascular injury may happened in the conditions of well-described anatomic
      variation (eg, persistent median artery, bifida of MN), and unable supination of wrists. In
      these patients with difficulty in performing hydrodissection, The investigators may abandon
      needle redirection deep to the median nerve or chose the radial approach when clearly
      identifying the fascial passage of the palmar cutaneous branch (PCB) of the MN (Figure 3).
      The only mater in the radial approach the investigators need attention is the avoidance of
      damage of the PCB of the MN.

      Data collection The patients' medical records were reviewed by a neurologist (F.C.Y.).
      Routinely, the investigators recorded clinical data (including sex, age, and side of
      injection, height and weight [which were used to estimate BMI]), complications, and the
      effect of treatment. Blood in the needle after US-guided hydrodissection was recorded as
      vascular injury in the US-guided corticosteroid injection. The US images were analyzed by two
      musculoskeletal radiologists (Y.C.H.) and (G.S.H.) who were blinded to the occurrence of MNI.
      The investigators determined the absence of hyperechoic rim of MN on pre-injection US, the
      inter-scan change of nerve echogenicity of MN at the inlet of carpal tunnel in consensus. The
      investigators determined the swelling of MN including the flattening ratio (largest
      diameter/smallest diameter) and cross-sectional area at the inlet of carpal tunnel at the
      time of before and after the hydrodissection on the procedure US. The rater (Y.C.H.)
      performed duplicate measurements, with the second measurement obtained 2 weeks after the
      first. All measurements were performed with the aid of a PACS, a mouse pointer (cursor), and
      automated computer calculation. The mean of two measurements was considered to be the final
      value.

      The investigators hypothesized that multiple pre-injection factors, including sex, age, side
      of injection, patient BMI, diabetes mellitus, anatomic variation of MN (eg, persistent median
      artery, bifida of MN), site of needle passed into the skin; and findings after
      hydrodissection such as vascular injury and the US findings of MN after hydrodissection may
      have relevance to MNI (Figure 4). To evaluate the relevance of these pre-injection factors to
      MNI, we decided to convert these continuous variables into dichotomous variables. Subjects
      were divided into old and young groups on the basis of a cutoff age of 40 years, thin and
      obese groups on the basis of a cutoff BMI of 30, ulnar and radial approaches groups on the
      basis of site of needle passed into the skin, hydrodissection in the superficial and deep to
      the median nerve groups on the basis of needle redirection.

      Boston Carpal Tunnel Syndrome Questionnaire (BCTQ) is the most commonly used questionnaire
      for the measurement of the severity of symptoms and functional status with reproducibility,
      internal consistency, and validity in patients with CTS. The symptom severity subscale of
      BCTQ (BCTQs) consists of 11 questions with scores from 1 point (mildest) to 5 points (most
      severe), and the functional status of BCTQ (BCTQf) subscale is made up of 8 questions with
      scores from 1 point (no difficulty in activity) to 5 points (unable to perform the activity
      at all). Patients were seen in the subsequent clinical visit to determine outcomes. The
      investigators also recorded the decrease of BCTQ between the before and after US-guided
      corticosteroid injection as decrement of BCTQ.

      Statistical analysis All the measurements regarding the change of MN were presented as mean ±
      standard deviation. Intra-rater agreement was evaluated using the intra-class correlation
      coefficient (ICC). Fisher's exact test was used to determine the association between MNI to
      these independent factors before injection and findings after hydrodissection. Receiver
      operating characteristic (ROC) analysis was used to determine the &quot;cut-off point&quot; for
      predicting the presence of MNI. The patients with and without the diagnosis of MNI were
      defined as 2 groups. The therapeutic efficacy of these 2 groups were compared by using a
      Student t test (for BCTQ before corticosteroid injection, BCTQ after corticosteroid
      injection, and decrement of BCTQ), as appropriate.

      All the statistical tests were performed with the SPSS software (v. 16; SPSS, Inc. Chicago,
      IL, USA). Significance testing was conducted using a two-tailed alternative hypothesis.
      Differences were considered statistically significant for a p value of &lt; 0.05.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The observation of median nerve injury</measure>
    <time_frame>July 2017 to September 2017</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators observed if patient had symptoms of shooting pain after the corticosteroid injection along with numbness, paresthesia and other sensory deficits and distributions in the median nerve supply area.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The intra-rater agreement of measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>July 2017 to September 2017</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators determined the intra-rater agreement for these quantitative measurements (flattening ratio and cross-sectional area of the MN) for the before and after hydrodissection US.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The relationship between pre-injection factors and MNI</measure>
    <time_frame>July 2017 to September 2017</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators determined the associations between MNI and the pre-injection factors. The factors includes sex, age, side of injection, site of needle passed into the skin, BMI, anatomic variation of MN, absence of hyperechoic rim of MN, and whether or not they have diabetes mellitus.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The relationship between post-injection factors and MNI</measure>
    <time_frame>July 2017 to September 2017</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators determined the associations between MNI and the post-injection factors. The hydrodissection findings includes vascular injury during hydrodissection, altered echogenicity, decrease flattening ratio, and increase cross-sectional area (CSA) of MN on US after hydrodissection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The symptoms relief after corticosteroid injection in the groups of MNI or not</measure>
    <time_frame>July 2017 to September 2017</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators observed the symptoms relief, which was rated using a Boston Carpal Tunnel Syndrome Questionnaire (BCTQ) scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">126</enrollment>
  <condition>Injury of Median Nerve Distal to Forearm</condition>
  <condition>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patient with carpal tunnel syndrome in a single center (TSGH)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The clinical tests included (1) typical symptoms, eg, hand numbness and pain in the
             distribution of the median nerve, nocturnal worsening of symptoms, worsening symptoms
             while driving or gripping, (2) positive Tinel's and/or Phalen's sign, (3) failure of
             splinting and/or hand rest.

          -  Patients with clinically suspected CTS underwent US examination.

          -  The diagnoses of CTS in these patients were confirmed by US and/or electrodiagnostic
             investigations.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  prior carpal tunnel release

          -  loss of follow-up US examinations

          -  previous US-guided carpal tunnel injections

          -  US-guided carpal tunnel injections with recurrence on ipsilateral hands
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yi-Chih Hsu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>IRB of TSGH, Taipei, Taiwan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>No. 325, Sec. 2, Cheng-kung Rd., Neihu 114</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <state>Taiwan, R.o.c.</state>
        <zip>886</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 23, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 29, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 29, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 29, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tri-Service General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>yi-chih HSU</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Radiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Carpal tunnel syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Median nerve injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Steroids</keyword>
  <keyword>Ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>Injections</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

