<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03392584</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016/865</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03392584</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Detection and Inflammatory Characterization of Deep Infection After Surgery for Locally Advanced Rectal Cancer With Microdialysis Catheters</brief_title>
  <official_title>Detection and Inflammatory Characterization of Deep Infection After Surgery for Locally Advanced Rectal Cancer With Microdialysis Catheters</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Oslo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oslo University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The intention of the study is to explore metabolic and inflammatory parameters in the pelvis
      after abdominoperineal resection for locally advanced rectal cancer in patients that have
      received radiation therapy before surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Locally advanced rectal cancers (LARC) threaten the normal surgical margins and therefore
      needs neoadjuvant (chemo-) radiotherapy to down-stage the tumor before surgery. The Norwegian
      Radium Hospital Oslo University Hospital is a regional center for treatment of LARC in the
      south-eastern part of Norway and treat approximately 80-100 patients in this category
      annually. About 50 of these patients receive abdominoperineal resection (APR) as the main
      surgical treatment. A very high rate of deep surgical site infections is reported in the APR
      group internationally, particularly in the patients that have received chemo-radiotherapy.
      The knowledge of why these patients have such a high rate of infections is scarce.

      Microdialysis is a technique which enables close to real-time monitoring of the tissues and
      organs of interest.

      The investigators want to utilize the microdialysis method to describe and monitor metabolic
      and inflammatory parameters, after extensive oncological surgery for LARC in patients that
      have undergone chemoradiotherapy before surgery. With the knowledge of how the normal biology
      is, the investigators hypothesize that infection can be readily detected by the biomarkers
      retrieved by microdialysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitoring intermediate metabolites in the remnant muscular tissue of the pelvis floor with microdialysis catheters after neoadjuvant CRT and subsequent APR for LARC.</measure>
    <time_frame>August 2023</time_frame>
    <description>Lactate (mM), pyruvate (µM), lactate/pyruvate ratio, glycerol (µM) and glucose (mM) will be measured in microdialysis fluid from catheters inserted in the remnant muscular tissue of the pelvis floor after neoadjuvant CRT and subsequent APR for LARC to detect deep pelvic surgical site infection. The results will be compared to current standard monitoring. The measures will be done bedside on Iscus analyzer, M Dialysis AB, Stockholm, Sweden. The Iscus analyzer will calculate the lactate/pyruvate ratio.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitoring inflammatory mediators in the remnant muscular tissue of the pelvis floor with microdialysis catheters after neoadjuvant CRT and subsequent APR for LARC.</measure>
    <time_frame>August 2023</time_frame>
    <description>Microdialysis fluid will be analysed using a multiplex cytokine assay (Bio-Plex Human Cytokine 27-Plex Panel, Bio-Rad Laboratories Inc., Hercules, CA). The following cytokines, chemokines and growth factors will be measured (all in pg/mL): Activated complement component 5 (C5a), Interleukin (IL) 1 beta (IL-1β), IL-1 receptor antagonist (IL-1Ra), IL-2, IL-4, IL-5, IL-6, IL-7, IL-8 (CXCL8), IL-9, IL-10, IL-12p70, IL-13, IL-15, IL-17, Eotaxin (CCL11), basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF), granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF), granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF), interferon gamma (IFNG), interferon gamma inducible protein-10 (IP-10 or CXCL10), monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1 or CCL2), macrophage inflammatory protein-1-alpha (MIP-1α or CCL3), macrophage inflammatory protein-1-beta (MIP-1β or CCL4), platelet-derived growth factor-BB (PDGF-BB), regulated upon activation, normal T cell expressed and secreted (RANTES or CCL5), TNF-α and VEGF.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitoring inflammatory mediators in blood after neoadjuvant CRT and subsequent APR for LARC.</measure>
    <time_frame>August 2023</time_frame>
    <description>Blood be analysed using a multiplex cytokine assay (Bio-Plex Human Cytokine 27-Plex Panel, Bio-Rad Laboratories Inc., Hercules, CA). The following cytokines, chemokines and growth factors will be measured (all in pg/mL): Activated complement component 5 (C5a) Interleukin (IL) 1 beta (IL-1β), IL-1 receptor antagonist (IL-1Ra), IL-2, IL-4, IL-5, IL-6, IL-7, IL-8 (CXCL8), IL-9, IL-10, IL-12p70, IL-13, IL-15, IL-17, Eotaxin (CCL11), basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF), granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF), granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF), interferon gamma (IFNG), interferon gamma inducible protein-10 (IP-10 or CXCL10), monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1 or CCL2), macrophage inflammatory protein-1-alpha (MIP-1α or CCL3), macrophage inflammatory protein-1-beta (MIP-1β or CCL4), platelet-derived growth factor-BB (PDGF-BB), regulated upon activation, normal T cell expressed and secreted (RANTES or CCL5), TNF-α and VEGF.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure inflammatory mediators in pelvic drain fluid after neoadjuvant CRT and subsequent APR for LARC.</measure>
    <time_frame>August 2023</time_frame>
    <description>Pelvic drain fluid will be analysed using a multiplex cytokine assay (Bio-Plex Human Cytokine 27-Plex Panel, Bio-Rad Laboratories Inc., Hercules, CA). The following cytokines, chemokines and growth factors will be measured (all in pg/mL): Activated complement component 5 (C5a), Interleukin (IL) 1 beta (IL-1β), IL-1 receptor antagonist (IL-1Ra), IL-2, IL-4, IL-5, IL-6, IL-7, IL-8 (CXCL8), IL-9, IL-10, IL-12p70, IL-13, IL-15, IL-17, Eotaxin (CCL11), basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF), granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF), granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF), interferon gamma (IFNG), interferon gamma inducible protein-10 (IP-10 or CXCL10), monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1 or CCL2), macrophage inflammatory protein-1-alpha (MIP-1α or CCL3), macrophage inflammatory protein-1-beta (MIP-1β or CCL4), platelet-derived growth factor-BB (PDGF-BB), regulated upon activation, normal T cell expressed and secreted (RANTES or CCL5), TNF-α and VEGF.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the common innate immune defect MBL deficiency in blood in the study population.</measure>
    <time_frame>August 2023</time_frame>
    <description>Measure MBL (ng/mL) in serum by an enzyme immunoassay. Compare differences in the frequency of MBL-deficiency in patients with or without deep pelvic infections.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure intermediate metabolites and inflammatory mediators after neoadjuvant CRT and subsequent APR for LARC with reconstruction of the perineum with VRAM.</measure>
    <time_frame>August 2023</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the above mentioned parameters and evaluate whether reconstruction with VRAM contribute to differences in these in patients after neoadjuvant CRT and subsequent APR for LARC, in comparison with patients without VRAM reconstruction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Locally Advanced Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Abdominoperineal Resection</condition>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>APR</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with locally advanced rectal cancer treated with neoadjuvant (chemo-) radiotherapy (CRT) and operated with abdominoperineal resection (APR)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>APR with VRAM</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with locally advanced rectal cancer treated with neoadjuvant (chemo-) radiotherapy (CRT) and operated with abdominoperineal resection (APR) and subsequent reconstruction of the perineum with a vertical rectus abdominis myocutaneous flap (VRAM)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Microdialysis samples 6-10 times every day. Regularly standard blood samples. Daily samples
      from pelvic drain. EDTA plasma 3 times a week.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with locally advanced rectal cancer who receive radiotherapy &gt;25 Gy prior to
        surgery.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with primary rectal adenocarcinoma that have received radiation ≥25 Gy to the
             pelvis.

          -  operation with APR.

          -  have accepted and signed the consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  APR for other reasons
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ebbe B Thorgersen, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Surgeon, The Department of Gastroenterological Surgery, The Norwegian Radium Hospital, Oslo University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ebbe B Thorgersen, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+4722934001</phone>
    <email>Ebbe.Billmann.Thorgersen@rr-research.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jørund Asvall, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+4722935608</phone>
    <email>joeasv@ous-hf.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Norwegian Radium Hospital Oslo University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <zip>0379</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ebbe B Thorgersen, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+4722934615</phone>
      <email>Ebbe.Billmann.Thorgersen@rr-research.no</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Stein G Larsen, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+4722934052</phone>
      <email>STL@ous-hf.no</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 2, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oslo University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ebbe Billmann Thorgersen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Locally advanced rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Deep infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Microdialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgical site infection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

