<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03399760</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UDDS-Ortho-01-2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03399760</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Injectable Platelet Rich Fibrin (i-PRF) in Enhancing Bone Quality</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation the Dento-alveolar Changes After Platelet Rich Fibrin (i-PRF) Injection During Upper Canine Retraction Using Cone-beam Computed Tomography (CBCT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Damascus University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Damascus University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Twenty patients need therapeutic extraction of the maxillary first premolars with subsequent
      retraction of the maxillary canines, will be divided randomly into two groups, and will
      randomly assigned to one side of the maxillary arch at the first premolar region, and the
      other side served as the control. Canine retraction will be initiated after completion of the
      leveling and alignment phase via closed nickel-titanium coil springs applying 150 g of force
      per side. Soldered transpalatal arch will be used as an anchor unit. The dento-alveolar
      changes will be assessed immediately before retraction and after 6 months using CBCT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Extraction is a procedure that is currently performed in orthodontics, either in the context
      of early treatment or for adolescents with severe crowding or protrusion/overjet. The
      consequences of this ''simple'' procedure may show up many mucosal and osseous complications
      such as: bone resorption with collapse of the alveolar process, a gingival cleft or gingival
      recession in the area surrounding the extraction site. Besides the potential esthetic
      repercussions, these periodontal defects also give rise to a clinical problem with achieving
      some orthodontic movements, such as complete closure of the space or uprighting a root.

      A systematic review evaluating alveolar bone dimension changes of extraction sockets showed a
      range of width reduction of 2.6-4.6mm, Two-thirds of the loss occurred in the first 3 months,
      the remodeling of alveolar bone in the extraction site always decreases ridge volume and
      deforms the ridge configuration which impairs orthodontic movement of the tooth posteriorly.

      Endogenously produced biologicals have been tested based on their roles in the turnover of
      alveolar bone in response to orthodontic tooth movement as well as during wound healing.

      From here it has been thought about using a method to enhance bone quality after extraction.
      The platelet rich fibrin (PRF) has the ability to enhance tissue regeneration, accelerate
      wound healing and inducing stem cells differentiation through its growth factors (GFs).

      PRF characteristics in comparison to platelet rich plasma PRP are:

        1. its preparation is completely natural and there is no need for thrombin addition so
           there isn't immune reaction

        2. it contains stem cells

        3. it requires one stage centrifugation

        4. PRF has been reported to gradually release autologous growth factors and expressed
           stronger and more durable effect on the cellular proliferation and differentiation than
           PRP in vitro This is the first study in the world that will use i-PRF with Orthodontic
           treatment, because of its benefits and easiness of using in dental clinic Study sample
           that consists of 20 patients, Allocation of the sides of intervention (PRF injection)
           and control sides is made by computer program (Excel).

      After ensuring of the patients compliance with the terms and conditions of this study, the
      purpose and methods of the study will be explained to the patients using Information Sheet.
      In case of approval to participate, the patients asked to sign the Informed Consent.

      Extra &amp; Intra-oral photographs, impressions and clinical examination will be made.

      Canine retraction will be initiated after completion of the leveling and alignment phase via
      closed nickel-titanium coil springs applying 150 g of force per side at the same time 20ml of
      patients' blood will be withdrawn and centrifuged (700 rpm within 3 minutes) to get 4ml
      i-PRF. PRF will be injected at the area of the extracted first premolar, The first point
      place is in the buccal interventional side (supra periosteal injection) and the second point
      place is in the palatal interventional side(sub periosteal injection). PRF will be injected
      twice at the beginning and at the middle of the canine retraction.

      High resolution CBCT will be taken before the beginning of canine retraction (T0) and after 6
      months (T1).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two Arms injectable platelet rich fibrin group: consisted of two subgroups
Experimental group : injectable platelet rich fibrin assisted upper canine retraction
Control group: conventional upper canine retraction</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>One blinded</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Canine root resorption</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months from the beginning of canine retraction</time_frame>
    <description>Root length measurement from a reference line between buccal and palatal cemento-enamel junction (CEJ) to apex. These lines are perpendicular to the long axis of the canine. The levels of CEJ and root apex were assessed using a combination of axial, sagittal, and coronal images.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alveolar bone height in the first premolar region</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months from the beginning of canine retraction</time_frame>
    <description>By measuring the distance between two lines:
The first line: the line passing through the distal and mesial cemento-enamel junction of the canine The second line: the line passing through the crest of the alveolus distal to the canine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone density</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months from the beginning of canine retraction</time_frame>
    <description>By using Hounsfield Unites (Gray Values)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Malocclusion, Angle Class II, Division 1</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>i-PRF assisted upper canine retraction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>I-PRF assisted upper canine retraction will be performed in one side of patients with Class II Division 1 malocclusion patients requiring therapeutic extraction of the maxillary first premolars</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>conventional upper canine retraction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional upper canine retraction will be performed in the other side of patients with Class II Division 1 malocclusion patients requiring therapeutic extraction of the maxillary first premolars</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>i-PRF</intervention_name>
    <description>i-PRF (injectable platelet rich fibrin) assisted upper canine retraction</description>
    <arm_group_label>i-PRF assisted upper canine retraction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>canine retraction</intervention_name>
    <description>upper canine retraction will be performed in one side of patients with Class II Division 1 malocclusion patients requiring therapeutic extraction of the maxillary first premolars</description>
    <arm_group_label>i-PRF assisted upper canine retraction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>conventional upper canine retraction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult healthy patients, Male and female, Age range: 15-27 years.

          2. Class II Division 1 malocclusion:

               -  Mild / moderate skeletal Class II (ANB ≤7)

               -  Overjet ≤10

               -  Normal or excessive facial height (Clinically and then cephalometry assessed
                  using these angles : SN-MP , MM , Y axis)

               -  Mild to moderate crowding ≤ 4

          3. permanent occlusion.

          4. Exist all the upper teeth (except third molars).

          5. Good oral and periodontal health:

               -  Probing depth &lt; 4 mm

               -  No radiographic evidence of bone loss.

               -  Gingival index ≤ 1

               -  Plaque index ≤ 1

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Medical problems that affect tooth movement (corticosteroid, NSAIDs, …)

          2. patients have anti indication for oral surgery ( medical - social - psycho)

          3. Presence of primary teeth in the maxillary arch

          4. Missing permanent maxillary teeth (except third molars).

          5. Poor oral hygiene or Current periodontal disease:

               -  Probing depth ≥ 4 mm

               -  radiographic evidence of bone loss

               -  Gingival index &gt; 1

               -  Plaque index &gt; 1

          6. Patient had previous orthodontic treatment

          7. Craniofacial anomalies (cleft lip and palate patients)

          8. Smokers

          9. coagulation disorders and patients treated with anticoagulants.

         10. patients with immunodeficiency disorders
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>27 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rania Haddad, PhD.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Orthodontics, Faculty of Dentistry, Damascus University, Damascus, Syria</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Talar Zeitounlouian, MSc. Student</last_name>
    <phone>+963 990253494</phone>
    <email>talarzeitounian@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rania Haddad, PhD.</last_name>
    <phone>+963 988403404</phone>
    <email>rania_haddad234@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Damascus University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Damascus</city>
        <zip>00963</zip>
        <country>Syrian Arab Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ahmad S Burhan, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>00963944302075</phone>
      <email>dr.burhan-a@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Syrian Arab Republic</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malmgren O, Goldson L, Hill C, Orwin A, Petrini L, Lundberg M. Root resorption after orthodontic treatment of traumatized teeth. Am J Orthod. 1982 Dec;82(6):487-91.</citation>
    <PMID>6961819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lund H, Gröndahl K, Gröndahl HG. Cone beam computed tomography for assessment of root length and marginal bone level during orthodontic treatment. Angle Orthod. 2010 May;80(3):466-73. doi: 10.2319/072909-427.1.</citation>
    <PMID>20050738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dohan Ehrenfest DM, de Peppo GM, Doglioli P, Sammartino G. Slow release of growth factors and thrombospondin-1 in Choukroun's platelet-rich fibrin (PRF): a gold standard to achieve for all surgical platelet concentrates technologies. Growth Factors. 2009 Feb;27(1):63-9. doi: 10.1080/08977190802636713.</citation>
    <PMID>19089687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naik B, Karunakar P, Jayadev M, Marshal VR. Role of Platelet rich fibrin in wound healing: A critical review. J Conserv Dent. 2013 Jul;16(4):284-93. doi: 10.4103/0972-0707.114344.</citation>
    <PMID>23956527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van der Weijden F, Dell'Acqua F, Slot DE. Alveolar bone dimensional changes of post-extraction sockets in humans: a systematic review. J Clin Periodontol. 2009 Dec;36(12):1048-58. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.2009.01482.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19929956</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>i-PRF (injectable platelet rich fibrin)</keyword>
  <keyword>alveolar bone height</keyword>
  <keyword>canine root resorption</keyword>
  <keyword>bone density</keyword>
  <keyword>cone-beam computed tomography</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malocclusion</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malocclusion, Angle Class II</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overbite</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Individual participant data will be only available for the researchers in the department of Orthodontics, Damascus University</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

