<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03396861</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12338</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03396861</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Macular Edema After Cataract Surgery With Subconjunctival Aflibercept</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACME</acronym>
  <official_title>Subconjunctival Aflibercept Injection for Pseudophakic Cystoid Macular Edema</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tufts Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Regeneron Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tufts Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is being conducted to determine the safety and tolerability of
      subconjunctival injections of aflibercept in the treatment of pseudophakic cystoid macular
      edema that has not responded well to first-line standard of care treatment (eye drops).

      Pseudophakic cystoid macular edema (CME) is swelling of the retina that can occur weeks or
      years after cataract surgery and typically results in decreased vision. Subconjunctival
      injections are injections placed just beneath the clear membrane (conjunctiva) of the eye.

      A recent report of one patient who received two subconjunctival injections of a similar
      medication to the one being studied here indicated that subconjunctival injections of this
      class of medication may be an effective and less invasive alternative to intravitreal
      injections for pseudophakic CME. Because of the similarity of the drugs and the patient's
      treatment success, we would like to see if subconjunctival injection(s) of aflibercept will
      work in treating pseudophakic CME. If successful, the risk of an intraocular infection and
      glaucoma that comes with standard of care treatments might be greatly reduced.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 2</time_frame>
    <description>Systemic and ocular adverse events of subconjunctivally administered aflibercept injection in the treatment of pseudophakic cystoid macular edema at Month 2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in visual acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 2 and Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>Change in best-corrected visual acuity at Months 2 and 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in central retinal thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 2 and Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>Change in central retinal thickness as measured by optical coherence tomography at Months 2 and 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients needing re-treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 1</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients needing subconjunctival aflibercept injection treatment at Month 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients needing additional non-study treatment though Month 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients receiving additional non-study treatment (e.g. periocular or intravitreal steroid) through Month 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events - end of study period</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence and severity of systemic and ocular events at Month 6</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Irvine-Gass Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subconjunctival aflibercept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subconjunctival aflibercept 2 milligrams (mg) /0.05 milliliters (mL) administered at baseline visit and possibly again at Month 1 visit depending on initial response.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aflibercept</intervention_name>
    <description>Subconjunctival aflibercept</description>
    <arm_group_label>Subconjunctival aflibercept</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosed with pseudophakic CME defined as central retinal thickness (CRT)&gt;300
             microns, presence of intraretinal cysts on optical coherence tomography (OCT) and
             visual acuity &lt;=20/32 with petaloid leakage on fluorescein angiogram and late leakage
             at the disc

          2. Diagnosed with &quot;recalcitrant&quot; CME, defined as less than a 15% decrease in CRT after at
             least 6 weeks of topical non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drug

          3. Has had cataract surgery in the study eye with posterior chamber or anterior chamber
             intraocular lens implantation

          4. Willing and able to comply with clinic visits and study-related procedures

          5. Provide signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Retinal diseases (including diabetic retinopathy, retinal vein or artery occlusion,
             neovascular age-related macular degeneration, radiation retinopathy, vitreomacular
             traction, epiretinal membrane).

          2. Active intraocular inflammation (grade trace or above) in the study eye, or history of
             idiopathic or autoimmune-associated uveitis in either eye.

          3. Active infectious conjunctivitis, keratitis, scleritis or endophthalmitis in either
             eye.

          4. Prior treatment with sub-Tenon's or intravitreal steroids.

          5. Prior treatment with an intravitreal anti-vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF)
             agent in the study eye or systemic administration of anti-VEGF.

          6. Use of topical prostaglandin analogues or pilocarpine.

          7. Uncontrolled glaucoma in the study eye (defined as intraocular pressure ≥30 mmHg
             despite treatment with glaucoma medications.

          8. Previous subfoveal focal laser photocoagulation involving the foveal center in the
             study eye.

          9. Vision loss in the study eye, determined by the investigator to be from a cause other
             than CME, e.g. optic neuropathy, end-stage glaucoma.

         10. Any significant media opacity including vitreous hemorrhage or corneal scarring.

         11. Fluorescein dye allergy or intolerance

         12. Allergy to aflibercept or any of the components

         13. Cerebrovascular accident or myocardial infarction within 1 year of the screening
             visit.

         14. Pregnant or breast-feeding women

         15. Sexually active men or women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to practice
             adequate contraception starting at least 2 menstrual cycles prior to the baseline
             visit, during the study and in the 3 months immediately following the last dose of
             study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elias Reichel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tufts Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elias Reichel, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-636-1648</phone>
    <email>ereichel@tuftsmedicalcenter.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michael Dixon</last_name>
    <phone>617-636-1051</phone>
    <email>mdixon3@tuftsmedicalcenter.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muakkassa NW, Klein KA, Hamrah P, Reichel E. Subconjunctival Bevacizumab for the Treatment of Keratoprosthesis-Associated Cystoid Macular Edema. Ophthalmic Surg Lasers Imaging Retina. 2016 Mar;47(3):276-9. doi: 10.3928/23258160-20160229-11.</citation>
    <PMID>26985802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guo S, Patel S, Baumrind B, Johnson K, Levinsohn D, Marcus E, Tannen B, Roy M, Bhagat N, Zarbin M. Management of pseudophakic cystoid macular edema. Surv Ophthalmol. 2015 Mar-Apr;60(2):123-37. doi: 10.1016/j.survophthal.2014.08.005. Epub 2014 Sep 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25438734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arevalo JF, Garcia-Amaris RA, Roca JA, Sanchez JG, Wu L, Berrocal MH, Maia M; Pan-American Collaborative Retina Study Group. Primary intravitreal bevacizumab for the management of pseudophakic cystoid macular edema: pilot study of the Pan-American Collaborative Retina Study Group. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2007 Dec;33(12):2098-105.</citation>
    <PMID>18053911</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin CJ, Tsai YY. USE OF AFLIBERCEPT FOR THE MANAGEMENT OF REFRACTORY PSEUDOPHAKIC MACULAR EDEMA IN IRVINE-GASS SYNDROME AND LITERATURE REVIEW. Retin Cases Brief Rep. 2018 Winter;12(1):59-62. doi: 10.1097/ICB.0000000000000414. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27617392</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raghava S, Hammond M, Kompella UB. Periocular routes for retinal drug delivery. Expert Opin Drug Deliv. 2004 Nov;1(1):99-114. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16296723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bahar I, Yeung SN, Sella R, Slomovic A. Anterior segment uses of bevacizumab. Curr Opin Ophthalmol. 2012 Jul;23(4):303-16. doi: 10.1097/ICU.0b013e3283548459. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22634640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Papadopoulos N, Martin J, Ruan Q, Rafique A, Rosconi MP, Shi E, Pyles EA, Yancopoulos GD, Stahl N, Wiegand SJ. Binding and neutralization of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) and related ligands by VEGF Trap, ranibizumab and bevacizumab. Angiogenesis. 2012 Jun;15(2):171-85. doi: 10.1007/s10456-011-9249-6.</citation>
    <PMID>22302382</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stewart MW, Rosenfeld PJ. Predicted biological activity of intravitreal VEGF Trap. Br J Ophthalmol. 2008 May;92(5):667-8. doi: 10.1136/bjo.2007.134874. Epub 2008 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18356264</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kitchens JW, Do DV, Boyer DS, Thompson D, Gibson A, Saroj N, Vitti R, Berliner AJ, Kaiser PK. Comprehensive Review of Ocular and Systemic Safety Events with Intravitreal Aflibercept Injection in Randomized Controlled Trials. Ophthalmology. 2016 Jul;123(7):1511-20. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2016.02.046. Epub 2016 Apr 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27084563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>macular edema</keyword>
  <keyword>pseudophakia</keyword>
  <keyword>pseudophakic macular edema</keyword>
  <keyword>retinal swelling</keyword>
  <keyword>aflibercept</keyword>
  <keyword>anti-vascular endothelial growth factor</keyword>
  <keyword>subconjunctival injection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Macular Edema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

