<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03394209</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FAVI-PK-2017001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03394209</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pharmacokinetics Study of Favipiravir in Patients With Severe Influenza</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Adaptive Study of the Pharmacokinetics of Favipiravir in Patients With Severe</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Capital Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beijing Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, China</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Capital Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Title: An adaptive study of the pharmacokinetics of favipiravir in patients with severe
      influenza Study Design: An open label, single group assignment, adaptive study to evaluate
      the pharmacokinetics of favipiravir in adult patients with severe influenza.

      In the first stage, participants will receive favipiravir 1600mg BID on day 1, followed by
      favipiravir 600mg BID for 9 days.

      If the proportion of patients with a minimum observed plasma trough concentration above the
      MEC (20μg/ml) at all measured time points after the second dose is less than 80% then a
      second patient cohort will be recruited and will receive favipiravir 1800mg BID on day 1,
      followed by favipiravir 800mg BID for 9 days.

      Intervention: The 1st stage: 1600mg BID on day 1, followed with 600mg BID for 9 days. Sample
      size: 15 The 2nd stage: 1800mg BID on day 1, followed with 800mg BID for 9 days. Sample size:
      15 Population: Males and females aged 18 years or older admitted to hospital with a positive
      PCR test for influenza and a PaO2/FiO2≤300mmHg or/and on mechanical ventilation for severe
      lung infection on admission.

      Sample size 15 or 30 severe influenza patients Research hypothesis The administration of oral
      favipiravir at either 1600mg/600mg BID or 1800/800mg BID will result in ≥ 80% patients
      achieving a minimum observed plasma trough concentration above the MEC (20μg/ml) at all
      measured time points after the second dose.

      Phase: Phase 2a, PK, safety and feasibility study. Description of Study Agent: Favipiravir
      (T-705) a viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase inhibitor.

      Study Duration: 1 year Participant Duration: 38 days
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 6, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 10, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 10, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a adaptive study, which include two steps.
1st step: 1600mg BID on day 1, followed by 600mg BID for 9 days. Sample size: 15 PK analysis: If the proportion of patients with a minimum observed plasma trough concentration above the MEC (20μg/ml) at all measured time points after the second dose is greater than or equal to 80% then the dose is considered adequate and the study will be completed. If not, then a second patient cohort will be recruited and will receive favipiravir 1800mg BID on day 1, followed by favipiravir 800mg BID for 9 days. Sample size: 15</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with minimum plasma of Favipiravir trough concentration above the MEC (20μg/ml) at all measured time points after the second dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days during the intervention period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum plasma concentration observed over the treatment period (Cmax )</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days during the intervention period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimum plasma concentration observed over the treatment period (Cmin)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days during the intervention period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average pre-dose plasma concentration (Trough)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days during the intervention period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients whose favipiravir plasma concentration at least one time exceeds MEC in study days</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days during the intervention period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients falling into each category of a five-point ordinal scale on day 10 and day 28 after starting favipiravir</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days from starting intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The category of a five-point ordinal scale: death; hospitalised on ECMO and/or mechanical ventilation; hospitalised on supplemental oxygenation; hospitalised not on supplemental oxygenation; discharged.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration (days) of mechanical ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>from reception of mechanical ventilation to ventilator weening, an average of 10 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration (days) of extracorporeal membrane oxygenation</measure>
    <time_frame>from starting ECMO to weening, an average of 9 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration (days) of supplemental oxygenation</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration (days) of hospitalization with oxygen therapy，an average of 13 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration (days) of hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>Days from admission to discharge，an average of 19 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with a negative RT-PCR for influenza from upper and/or lower respiratory tract samples on day 10 after starting treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of viral shedding,an average of 15 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The time (days) to negative RT-PCR for influenza from upper and/or lower respiratory tract samples (capped at day 10)</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of viral shedding,an average of 15 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with drug related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>38 days from starting intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with genetic and phenotypic markers of resistance to favipiravir and/or oseltamivir</measure>
    <time_frame>Days from admission to discharge，an average of 19 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza, Human</condition>
  <condition>Critical Illness</condition>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Favipiravir+oseltamivir</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Favipiravir+oseltamivir will be given twice daily for a 10-day period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Favipiravir</intervention_name>
    <description>In first step: favipiravir tablet is orally administered. This drug will be given twice daily for a 10-day period. For the First day, the dosage is 1600 mg twice daily. Starting from the second day, the dosage is 600 mg twice daily.
In second step: favipiravir tablet is orally administered. This drug will be given twice daily for a 10-day period. For the First day, the dosage is 1800 mg twice daily. Starting from the second day, the dosage is 800 mg twice daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Favipiravir+oseltamivir</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>T-705</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oseltamivir 75Mg Capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>oseltamivir will be administered at 75mg twice daily orally for 10 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Favipiravir+oseltamivir</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Hospitalized males or females with a positive PCR test for influenza virus infection

          2. Adults aged ≥18years

          3. PaO2/FiO2≤300mmHg or on mechanical ventilation

          4. &lt; 10 days since symptom onset

          5. Negative pregnancy testing for childbearing age females (under 60 years)

          6. Willingness to use contraception for 7 days after end of treatment

          7. Informed consent

          8. In addition, male subjects must:

               1. Agree not to donate sperm during the study and for 7 days following the last dose
                  of study drug, and

               2. Agree to adhere strictly to one of the following contraceptive measures from the
                  Screening Visit until 7 days after the last dose of study drug:

             i. abstain from sexual intercourse or ii. have a female partner using effective means
             of birth control as noted below or iii. use a condom with spermicide or a second
             barrier method by female partner.

        Female subjects

        a. Of child-bearing potential must agree to adhere strictly to one of the following
        approved contraceptive measures during the study and for 7 days after the last dose of
        study drug: i. abstain from sexual intercourse or ii. have a male partner incapable of
        fathering a child (eg, had a vasectomy at least 6 months with history of negative semen
        analysis prior Screening or iii. use of one of the following methods, in combination with
        condom and spermicide use by a male partner: nonhormonal intrauterine device (IUD);
        diaphragm; or hormonal contraceptives including oral contraceptives, injectable subdermal
        implants, hormonal IUD, or vaginal ring b. Be unable to bear children defined as one of the
        following: i. absence of a menstrual period for ≥12 consecutive months with FSH
        confirmation, ii. be 60 years of age or greater, iii. had surgical removal of uterus or
        removal of both ovaries, or iv. had undergone tubal ligation &gt;6 weeks prior to Day 1 dosing

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any condition that does not allow for safely following the protocol

          2. Patient refusal to accept invasive organ support treatment if needed

          3. Pregnant or breastfeeding

          4. Any condition resulted to reception of renal replacement therapy

          5. AST &gt; 5 times upper of limit or Child Pugh score ≥ C

          6. Serum uric acid level &gt; 3 times upper level of normal (430 ummol/L) associated with
             symptoms of gout

          7. Has a history of gout or is under treatment for: gout or hyperuricemia; hereditary
             xanthinuria; hypouricemia or xanthine calculi of the urinary tract

          8. Has a history of hypersensitivity to an anti-viral nucleoside-analog drug targeting a
             viral RNA polymerase

          9. Physician makes a decision that trial involvement is not in patients' best interest.

         10. Currently or have been involved in another anti-influenza treatment trial in the last
             28 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yeming Wang, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>86 18810663558</phone>
    <email>wwyymm_love@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Bin Cao, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>86 010 84206264</phone>
    <email>caobin_ben@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>China-Japan Friendship Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <zip>100029</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bin Cao, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>86 010 84206264</phone>
      <email>caobin_ben@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Yeming Wang, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>86 18810663558</phone>
      <email>wwyymm_love@163.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bin Cao, Ph.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/influenza/human_animal_interface/2017_10_30_tableH5N1.pdf?ua=1</url>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gao HN, Lu HZ, Cao B, Du B, Shang H, Gan JH, Lu SH, Yang YD, Fang Q, Shen YZ, Xi XM, Gu Q, Zhou XM, Qu HP, Yan Z, Li FM, Zhao W, Gao ZC, Wang GF, Ruan LX, Wang WH, Ye J, Cao HF, Li XW, Zhang WH, Fang XC, He J, Liang WF, Xie J, Zeng M, Wu XZ, Li J, Xia Q, Jin ZC, Chen Q, Tang C, Zhang ZY, Hou BM, Feng ZX, Sheng JF, Zhong NS, Li LJ. Clinical findings in 111 cases of influenza A (H7N9) virus infection. N Engl J Med. 2013 Jun 13;368(24):2277-85. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1305584. Epub 2013 May 22. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2013 Nov 7;369(19):1869.</citation>
    <PMID>23697469</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zheng S, Tang L, Gao H, Wang Y, Yu F, Cui D, Xie G, Yang X, Zhang W, Ye X, Zhang Z, Wang X, Yu L, Zhang Y, Yang S, Liang W, Chen Y, Li L. Benefit of Early Initiation of Neuraminidase Inhibitor Treatment to Hospitalized Patients With Avian Influenza A(H7N9) Virus. Clin Infect Dis. 2018 Mar 19;66(7):1054-1060. doi: 10.1093/cid/cix930.</citation>
    <PMID>29077848</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Li H, Yang SG, Gu L, Zhang Y, Yan XX, Liang ZA, Zhang W, Jia HY, Chen W, Liu M, Yu KJ, Xue CX, Hu K, Zou Q, Li LJ, Cao B, Wang C; National Influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 Clinical Investigation Group of China. Effect of low-to-moderate-dose corticosteroids on mortality of hospitalized adolescents and adults with influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 viral pneumonia. Influenza Other Respir Viruses. 2017 Jul;11(4):345-354. doi: 10.1111/irv.12456. Epub 2017 Jun 9.</citation>
    <PMID>28464462</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wang X, Jiang H, Wu P, Uyeki TM, Feng L, Lai S, Wang L, Huo X, Xu K, Chen E, Wang X, He J, Kang M, Zhang R, Zhang J, Wu J, Hu S, Zhang H, Liu X, Fu W, Ou J, Wu S, Qin Y, Zhang Z, Shi Y, Zhang J, Artois J, Fang VJ, Zhu H, Guan Y, Gilbert M, Horby PW, Leung GM, Gao GF, Cowling BJ, Yu H. Epidemiology of avian influenza A H7N9 virus in human beings across five epidemics in mainland China, 2013-17: an epidemiological study of laboratory-confirmed case series. Lancet Infect Dis. 2017 Aug;17(8):822-832. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30323-7. Epub 2017 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>28583578</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dunning J, Baillie JK, Cao B, Hayden FG; International Severe Acute Respiratory and Emerging Infection Consortium (ISARIC). Antiviral combinations for severe influenza. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014 Dec;14(12):1259-70. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(14)70821-7. Epub 2014 Sep 8. Review. Erratum in: Lancet Infect Dis. 2014 Dec;14(12):1174.</citation>
    <PMID>25213733</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kumar A. Early versus late oseltamivir treatment in severely ill patients with 2009 pandemic influenza A (H1N1): speed is life. J Antimicrob Chemother. 2011 May;66(5):959-63. doi: 10.1093/jac/dkr090. Epub 2011 Mar 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21406435</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kile JC, Ren R, Liu L, Greene CM, Roguski K, Iuliano AD, Jang Y, Jones J, Thor S, Song Y, Zhou S, Trock SC, Dugan V, Wentworth DE, Levine MZ, Uyeki TM, Katz JM, Jernigan DB, Olsen SJ, Fry AM, Azziz-Baumgartner E, Davis CT. Update: Increase in Human Infections with Novel Asian Lineage Avian Influenza A(H7N9) Viruses During the Fifth Epidemic - China, October 1, 2016-August 7, 2017. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2017 Sep 8;66(35):928-932. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.mm6635a2.</citation>
    <PMID>28880856</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 25, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>China-Japan Friendship Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bin Cao</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr.Bin Cao</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Favipiravir, Influenza, Human, Critical Illness, Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oseltamivir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

