<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03396510</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-567</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03396510</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Electronic Symptom Monitoring Intervention for Hospitalized Patients With Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Electronic Symptom Monitoring Intervention for Hospitalized Patients With Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alliance for Clinical Trials in Oncology Cancer Control Program (CCP)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is evaluating a new way to deliver oncology care for patients with cancer
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with cancer may experience a considerable symptom burden, often requiring
      hospitalizations for symptom management. The study doctors want to know if daily electronic
      monitoring of the symptoms, such as pain, nausea, constipation, and diarrhea may improve care
      while participants are hospitalized.

      The goal of this study is to evaluate a new way to deliver oncology care where patients'
      symptoms are systematically monitored during their hospital admission. The investigators are
      studying whether patients whose clinicians receive their patients' detailed symptom reports
      each day have improved symptom management compared to those whose clinicians do not receive
      their patients' detailed symptom reports each day.

      The study will use questionnaires to measure the participant symptoms and involves
      participating in a study for as long as the participants are admitted to the hospital. The
      information the investigators collect will help them determine if electronic symptom
      monitoring improves the care of patients with cancer
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of days with improved symptoms between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Using ESAS and PHQ symptoms, the investigators will compare the proportion of days that symptoms improved in standard care versus IMPROVED.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of days with worsened symptoms between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Using ESAS and PHQ symptoms, the investigators will compare the proportion of days that symptoms worsened in standard care versus IMPROVED.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in patients' symptom scores from baseline to discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Using ESAS and PHQ symptoms, the investigators will compare the average change in symptom burden for patients in standard care versus IMPROVED.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay (measured continuously as days admitted to the hospital) between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare hospital length of stay (measured continuously as days admitted to the hospital) between study arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital readmissions within 30 days of prior hospital discharge between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare readmissions within 30 days of prior hospital discharge between study arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital readmissions within 90 days of prior hospital discharge between study arms</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare readmissions within 90 days of prior hospital discharge between study arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Age as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on symptom burden</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore age as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on symptom burden.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Age as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore age as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on hospital length of stay.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Age as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore age as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sex as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on symptom burden</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore sex as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on symptom burden.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sex as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore sex as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on hospital length of stay.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sex as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore sex as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer type as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on symptom burden</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore cancer type as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on symptom burden.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer type as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore cancer type as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer type as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore cancer type as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on hospital length of stay.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline symptom burden as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore baseline symptom burden as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline symptom burden as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore baseline symptom burden as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on hospital length of stay.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline symptom burden as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on symptom burden</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore baseline symptom burden as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on symptom burden.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on symptom burden</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore hospital length of stay as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on symptom burden.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital length of stay as a moderator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore hospital length of stay as a potential moderator on the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom burden as a mediator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore whether improvements in symptom burden mediate the benefit of the intervention on hospital length of stay.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom burden as a mediator of the effect of IMPROVED on hospital readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will explore whether improvements in symptom burden mediate the benefit of the intervention on hospital readmissions.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">320</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IMPROVED intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to the IMPROVED intervention will self-report their symptoms each day using a tablet computer. If any patient refuses or is unable to complete the symptom assessment on the computer, the study team will permit them to use paper versions. At morning rounds each day, the clinical team will view reports detailing their patients' symptom burden. Patients randomized to IMPROVED will have their symptoms presented to their inpatient oncology team, but the study team will not provide guidance about what actions to take in response to patients' symptoms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual Care per hospital standard will be administered. Participants receiving usual care will also self-report their symptoms each day using tablet computers. However, these patients' clinicians will not receive their symptom reports.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IMPROVED intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients randomized to IMPROVED will self-report their symptoms each day using a tablet computer. If any patient refuses or is unable to complete the symptom assessment on the computer, the investigators will permit them to use paper versions. At morning rounds each day, the clinical team will view reports detailing their patients' symptom burden. Patients randomized to IMPROVED will have their symptoms presented to their inpatient oncology team, but the investigators will not provide guidance about what actions to take in response to patients' symptoms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>IMPROVED intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 or older

          -  Diagnosed with advanced cancer (defined as receiving treatment with palliative intent
             as per chemotherapy order entry designation, oncology clinic notes, and/or trial
             consent forms, or not receiving chemotherapy but followed for incurable disease as per
             oncology clinic notes)

          -  Admitted to the oncology service at Massachusetts General Hospital

          -  Verbal fluency in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unwilling or unable to participate in the study

          -  Admitted electively

          -  Participated during a previous admission
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ryan Nipp</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ryan Nipp</last_name>
    <phone>6177244000</phone>
    <email>rnipp@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ryan Nipp, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-4000</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ryan Nipp, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 11, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ryan Nipp</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer Care</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

