<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03399357</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DSRB 2016/00248</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03399357</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Metabolic Predictors of Influenza Vaccine Immune Response in the Singapore Elderly Population - the DYNAMIC Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Metabolic Predictors of Influenza Vaccine Immune Response in the Singapore Elderly Population- the DYNAMIC Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tan Tock Seng Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Singapore Immunology Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Healthcare Group, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tan Tock Seng Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The trial aims to evaluate role of metabolic factors including systemic 25-OH D and diabetes
      in the adaptive immune response (haemagluttination inhibition titer) to influenza vaccine in
      the elderly. The influenza vaccine administered in this study will be licensed trivalent
      inactivated influenza vaccine. Elderly who are age above 65 including those with
      co-morbidities such as diabetes mellitus will be included. The study has its inclusion and
      exclusion criteria to determine eligibility for participation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Novel, effective influenza vaccination strategies are needed in the elderly who have the
      highest rate of influenza-related morbidity and mortality. Vaccine efficacy in the elderly is
      reduced due to immunosenescence and/or, inflamm-aging. This phase IV clinical trial in 240
      participants aims to evaluate metabolic predictors of influenza-vaccine specific immune
      response in a multi-ethnic elderly community cohort in Singapore. Specifically, our novel
      approach is to evaluate the immunomodulatory roles of vitamin D, diabetes and other metabolic
      predictors. This study has translational implications (e.g. using vitamin D as an 'adjuvant',
      evaluating biomarkers of vaccine efficacy) to enhance influenza vaccine immunogenicity in the
      vulnerable elderly.

      Potential benefit: there is a possibility the vaccine may prevent influenza illness or
      influenza related complication that might have otherwise occurred. This study will contribute
      to body of knowledge of impact of metabolic factors (vitamin D, DM status) on influenza
      vaccine immune response, and will be the first study of its kind to be done in an Asian
      elderly population. Potential risks related to the blood draw and local/systemic side effects
      from influenza vaccine are anticipated to be minimal.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 31, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Humoral immune response measure</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 28 post vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Haemagglutination inhibition (HAI) titer for each of the three influenza vaccine strains in response to influenza vaccine at day 28 compared to baseline (pre-vaccination) titer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza Vaccine</condition>
  <condition>Immune Response</condition>
  <condition>Elderly</condition>
  <condition>Vitamin D Deficiency</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Disease</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>≥ 65 Years old</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy community-dwelling elderly (men and women) age 65 and above who are eligible for influenza vaccine and fulfil inclusion and exclusion criteria</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Influenza Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Inactivated Trivalent Influenza Vaccine (IIV3) 2017 containing: A (H1N1): an A/Michigan/45/2015 (H1N1) - like virus (new strain); A (H3N2): an A/Hong Kong/4801/2014 (H3N2) - like virus; B/Brisbane/60/2008 - like virus</description>
    <arm_group_label>≥ 65 Years old</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Influvac(R) SH 2017</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      1. Blood samples at &quot;baseline&quot; i.e. Day 0 to D -7 from Vaccination Day (designated as Day
           0) and Day 28 +/- 3 post-vaccination to assess HAI (hemagglutinin inhibition) response.

           PBMCs to be stored for future studies.

        2. Baseline blood sample to be tested for 25-OH D assay.

        3. Stool samples (optional part of study) to be studied for stool microbiome and relation
           to immune response and Vitamin D status.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy elderly population with stable comorbidities (in particular diabetes mellitus) is
        chosen for this study to evaluate metabolic factors and predictors related to
        immunosenescence, inflamm-aging and immune response to vaccination. Vaccination is one of
        our key preventive measures for influenza yet additional insight is needed regarding
        adaptive response in this vulnerable population, to ultimately lead to novel vaccination
        strategies.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 65 and above at time of enrollment (up to age 100) and able to give informed
             consent

          -  Determined by medical history, physical examination, and clinical judgment to be
             generally healthy, with no immunosuppressive conditions and having stable current
             medical conditions. Subjects with preexisting, stable disease, defined as not
             requiring significant change in therapy or hospitalization for worsening of disease 12
             weeks prior to receipt of study vaccine are eligible. A change in dose or therapy
             within a treatment category (e.g., change from one non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
             drug to another) is allowed. A change to a new therapy category (e.g., surgery or
             addition of a new pharmacological class) is only allowed if it is not caused by
             worsening disease.

          -  Is eligible for seasonal influenza vaccine

          -  Is available for all planned study visits

          -  Is willing to follow study procedures

          -  Able to follow study procedures (questionnaires, blood draws, vaccination) in the
             opinion of the investigator

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A change to a new therapy category caused by worsening disease is considered
             significant and will disqualify subject from participating in the study

          -  Subjects reporting any symptoms suggestive of influenza, influenza-like illness, or
             respiratory illness

          -  Vaccination with any licensed or experimental influenza vaccine within the past 10
             months

          -  Intent to receive any other investigational vaccine or agent during the course of the
             study

          -  Intent to receive other licensed vaccines during the course of the study (does not
             apply for pandemic or post-exposure prophylaxis scenario

          -  History of severe adverse reaction associated with an influenza vaccine

          -  Allergic to egg proteins (egg or egg products) and chicken proteins

          -  Known or suspected immunodeficiency or receiving treatment with immunosuppressive
             therapy including cytotoxic agents in past 6 months e.g., transplant recipients on
             active immunosuppression, patients with cancer, HIV, or autoimmune disease.

          -  Long-term systemic corticosteroid therapy (prednisolone ≥ 7.5mg/day or equivalent for
             more than 2 consecutive weeks within the past 3 months) Note: If systemic
             corticosteroids have been administered short term for treatment of an acute illness,
             subjects will be excluded from the study until corticosteroid therapy had been
             discontinued for at least 30 days.

          -  History of Guillain-Barré syndrome

          -  Serious chronic medical condition including: metastatic malignancy, severe chronic
             obstructive pulmonary disease requiring supplemental oxygen, CKD stage 3 and above,
             end stage renal disease with or without dialysis, clinically unstable cardiac disease,
             or any other disorder that in the investigator's opinion should preclude the subject
             from participating in the study

          -  Bariatric surgery, GI malabsorption disorders

          -  Recurrent Falls (≥2 falls in the past 12 months)

          -  Osteoporosis with or without pathological fractures

          -  Current or recently completed high dose vitamin D supplementation within the past 3
             months (defined as daily cholecalciferol dose of 2000 IU or higher, weekly 50,000 IU
             or intramuscular calcitriol)

          -  Receipt of any blood products, including immunoglobulin, within six months of study
             enrollment

          -  Donated blood within last 58 days

          -  Current anticoagulant therapy or a history of bleeding diathesis (including
             thrombocytopenia with platelet count &lt; 50,000) that would contraindicate intramuscular
             (IM) injection (Note: antiplatelet drugs such as aspirin and clopidogrel are
             permitted)

          -  Moderate or severe acute illness/infection (according to investigator judgement) on
             the day of vaccination, or febrile illness (temperature ≥ 37.5°C). A prospective
             subject should not be included in the study until the condition has resolved or the
             febrile event has subsided.

          -  Any medical condition that would, in the opinion of the investigator, interfere with
             the evaluation of the study objectives
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sapna P. Sadarangani, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>88091301</phone>
    <phone_ext>63577442</phone_ext>
    <email>Sapna_Sadarangani@ttsh.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tan Tock Seng Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>308433</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sapna P. Sadarangani, MBBS</last_name>
      <phone>88091031</phone>
      <phone_ext>63577442</phone_ext>
      <email>Sapna_Sadarangani@ttsh.com.sg</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mei Xuan Tan</last_name>
      <phone>+65-85229946</phone>
      <phone_ext>64783062</phone_ext>
      <email>Mei_Xuan_Tan@ttsh.com.sg</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sapna P Sadarangani, MBBS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Barnaby Young, MB BChir, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rinkoo Dalan, MBBS</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ezlyn Izzharudin, MBBS</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anis Larbi, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 16, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D Deficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

