<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03395119</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-2960</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03395119</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Fish Oil or Olive Oil Supplementation on the Health Effects of Ozone Exposure in Healthy Young Subjects</brief_title>
  <acronym>OMEGOZ</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Fish Oil or Olive Oil Supplementation on the Health Effects of Ozone Exposure in Healthy Young Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: A growing body of epidemiological data suggests an increased risk of cardiovascular
      events associated with air pollution. One of the common air pollutants, ozone, has been shown
      to induce oxidative stress and inflammation in the cardiovascular and respiratory systems.
      This proposed study is to examine the efficacy of fish oil and olive oil in modulating
      cardiovascular and pulmonary functions after ozone exposure. The objective is to understand
      the mechanistic basis for the health effects of ozone relative to those air pollutants.
      Treatment groups will include forty healthy young adults who will be given dietary
      supplementation of fish oil or olive oil. A control group will consist of 20 healthy
      volunteers who will receive no supplements. After 4 weeks, subjects will be exposed to clean
      air for 2 hours on the first day, then ozone for 2 hours on the second day. Cardiac rhythm,
      pulmonary function, vascular responses, endothelial function, and markers of coagulation and
      airway inflammation pre- and post- ozone exposure will be measured. This study is designed to
      build on the previous nutritional supplement interventional studies (UNC IRB # 07-0190 and
      UNC IRB # 11-1807), in order to understand the mechanism of action of particulate pollutants
      in comparison to that of ozone, a known oxidant air contaminant.

      Participants: A total of sixty healthy 18-35 year-old male and female subjects will be
      involved in the study.

      Procedures (methods): Forty healthy young adults will receive dietary supplementation
      consisting of fish oil or olive oil for 4 weeks. The control group includes 20 healthy
      volunteers who will receive no supplements in the study. After 4 weeks of supplementation or
      control regiment, each subject will be exposed to clean air for 2 hours on the first day,
      then ozone for 2 hours on the second day.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 18, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 18, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 18, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in forced expired volume in the first second (FEV1) from air exposure (Day 1) to ozone exposure (Day 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, Day 2</time_frame>
    <description>FEV1 is determined by spirometry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>endothelial cell function 1 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour pre-exposure, 1 hour post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Brachial artery ultrasound will be used to evaluate flow-mediated dilatation which will be performed in the Human Studies Facility (HSF) at U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) using an ultrasound instrument. The diameter of the brachial artery will be measured at baseline and during reactive hyperemia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>endothelial cell function 18 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour pre-exposure, 18 hour post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Brachial artery ultrasound will be used to evaluate flow-mediated dilatation which will be performed in the HSF at EPA using an ultrasound instrument. The diameter of the brachial artery will be measured at baseline and during reactive hyperemia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>diameters of retinal arteries and veins 1 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>30 min pre-exposure, 1 hour post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Retinal images will be taken using an FDA-approved, commercially available, non-mydriatic fundus camera. Images will be taken from both eyes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>diameters of retinal arteries and veins 18 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>30 min pre-exposure, 18 hour post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Retinal images will be taken using an FDA-approved, commercially available, non-mydriatic fundus camera. Images will be taken from both eyes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>airway inflammation 4 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks prior to the exposure, 4 hour post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Sputum induction will be performed to determine the airway inflammation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate variability 1 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour pre-exposure, 1 hour post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate variability will be collected by the Holter monitor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate variability 18 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour pre-exposure, 18 hour post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Heart rate variability will be collected by the Holter monitor.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood fatty acids 2 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks prior to the exposure, 2 hours pre-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Blood sample will be collected for fatty acids analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood fatty acids 30 min post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hour pre-exposure, 30 min post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Blood sample will be collected for fatty acids analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood fatty acids 18 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>2-hour pre-exposure, 18 hour post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Blood sample will be collected for fatty acids analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood cholesterol 2 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks prior to the exposure, 2 hours pre-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Blood sample will be collected for measuring the cholesterol level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood cholesterol 30 min post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hour pre-exposure, 30 min post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Blood sample will be collected for measuring the cholesterol level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood cholesterol 18 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>2-hour pre-exposure, 18 hour post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Blood sample will be collected for measuring the cholesterol level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced expired volume in the first second (FEV1) 18 hour post-exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>immediate post-exposure to ozone within 30 min, 18 hour post-exposure</time_frame>
    <description>Forced expired volume in the first second (FEV1) is determined by the spirometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Dietary Supplement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Supplements</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group includes 20 healthy volunteers who will receive no supplements in the study. After 4 weeks, subjects will be exposed to clean air for 2 hours on the first day, then ozone for 2 hours on the second day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fish oil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Twenty healthy young adults will receive fish oil supplements for 4 weeks. After 4 weeks, subjects will be exposed to clean air for 2 hours on the first day, then ozone for 2 hours on the second day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Olive oil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Twenty healthy young adults will receive olive oil supplements for 4 weeks. After 4 weeks, subjects will be exposed to clean air for 2 hours on the first day, then ozone for 2 hours on the second day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ozone</intervention_name>
    <description>After the four-week supplementation period, each subject will be blindly exposed on consecutive days to filtered air for 2 hours and to 0.3 ppm ozone for 2 hours, while undergoing intermittent moderate exercise (minute ventilation of 20 L/min/m²).</description>
    <arm_group_label>No Supplements</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fish oil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Olive oil</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Filtered air</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fish Oil</intervention_name>
    <description>3 (1-gram) soft-gels daily Commercially available, enteric-coated, soft-gels formulated to deliver &gt;60% eicosapentaenoic/docosahexaenoic acids (EPA/DHA)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fish oil</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>omega-3 fatty acids (eicosapentaenoic/docosahexaenoic)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Olive Oil</intervention_name>
    <description>3 soft-gels daily Commercially available soft-gels containing 1 gram of USDA organic certified, cold pressed, extra virgin, olive oil</description>
    <arm_group_label>Olive oil</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>extra virgin olive oil</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-35 years old healthy male and female (19≤BMI≤30).

          -  Physical conditioning allowing intermittent, moderate exercise for 2 hours, and
             ability to complete the exposure exercise regimen chosen to induce a minute
             ventilation rate of 20 L/min/m² for 15 minutes without exceeding 80% of predicted
             maximal heart rate.

          -  Normal resting electrocardiography (ECG)

          -  Normal lung function

          -  Oxygen saturation greater than 94% at the time of physical exam.

          -  Individuals whose blood omega-3 index is 5% or lower at the time of screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Individuals with a history of acute or chronic cardiovascular disease, chronic
             respiratory disease, cancer (possible exception for history of non-melanoma skin
             cancer), rheumatologic disease, neuromuscular disease, or immunodeficiency state.

          2. Individuals with a cardiovascular disease risk score greater than 10% using the
             American College of Cardiology and the American Heart Association Atherosclerotic
             Cardiovascular Disease risk calculator. (Based on the 10-year risk of heart disease or
             stroke using the Atherosclerotic Cardiovascular Disease algorithm published in 2013
             American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Guideline on the Assessment
             of Cardiovascular risk.)

          3. Uncontrolled hypertension (&gt;150 systolic, &gt;90 diastolic).

          4. Individuals who are diabetic (previously diagnosed or with hemoglobin A1c level
             &gt;6.4%).

          5. Individuals with asthma or a history of asthma.

          6. Individuals who are allergic to chemical vapors or gases.

          7. Individuals who have skin allergy to tape or electrodes.

          8. Individuals is pregnant, attempting to become pregnant or breastfeeding.

          9. Individuals who are currently smoking (including vaping, hookah and e-cigarette) or
             have smoking history within 1 year of study (defined as more than 1 pk/yr in the past
             year) or have a greater than/equal to a 5 pack year smoking history.

         10. Individuals living with a smoker who smokes inside the house.

         11. Individuals who are regularly exposed to high levels of vapors, dust, gases, or fumes.

         12. Individuals that do not understand or speak English.

         13. Individuals that are unable to perform the exercise required for the study.

         14. Individuals who are taking Î2-blocker medications.

         15. Individuals who are allergic to fish or omega-3 fatty acids, or are on prescription of
             taking omega-3 fish oil as therapy.

         16. Individuals that are unwilling or unable to stop taking medications that may impact
             the results of ozone challenge for the duration of the study. Medications not
             specifically mentioned here may be reviewed by the investigators prior to an
             individuals inclusion in the study.

         17. Individuals who are unwilling or unable to stop taking any current dietary supplements
             for the duration of the study. Prebiotics and probiotics are acceptable.

         18. Individuals who are unwilling or unable to adhere to study specific dietary
             restrictions (see details under A.4.2 dietary instruction).

         19. Individuals who have unspecified illnesses, which in the judgment of the investigators
             might increase the risk associated with ozone inhalation will be a basis for
             exclusion.

         20. Individuals with bleeding/clotting disorders.

         21. Individuals who are not willing to participate the induced sputum procedure on the
             training day.

        Temporary exclusion criteria:

          1. Individuals who have recent (within 6 month) abdominal and/or eye surgery, or with any
             types of hernia, as well as any other contraindications for raised intra-abdominal
             pressure.

          2. Individuals who have had an acute respiratory illness within 4 weeks.

          3. Individuals who are currently taking systemic steroids, oral anticoagulants, over-the
             counter pain medications (such as aspirin, Advil, Aleve) or nonsteroidal
             anti-inflammatory drugs, or have taken these medications within the last 14 days.

          4. Individuals who have active allergies.

        Use of other medications will be evaluated on a case-by-case basis. There is the potential
        that an individuals current medication use will preclude them from participating in the
        study at the current time, but they may be reassessed and potentially rescheduled for
        participation at a later time.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Samet, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Environmental Protection Agency, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hil</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patrice Ratliffe</last_name>
    <phone>919-966-0607</phone>
    <email>Ratliffe.Patrice@epa.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>James Samet, PhD</last_name>
    <email>Samet.James@epa.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>U.S. Environmental Protection Agency Human Studies Facility</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27514</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>James Samet</last_name>
      <phone>919-966-0665</phone>
      <email>samet.james@epa.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>David Diaz-Sanchez</last_name>
      <phone>919 308 1538</phone>
      <email>diaz-sanchez.david@epa.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 3, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ozone exposure</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Adults</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

