<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00316550</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AV608-107</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00316550</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study to Assess the Effects of AV608 on Irritable Bowel Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Cross-Over Pilot Study to Assess the Effects of AV608 on Central Processing of Visceral Stimuli in Subjects With Irritable Bowel Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Avera Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Avera Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the effects of AV608, a neurokinin 1 (NK-1)
      antagonist, in subjects with Irritable Bowel Syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, cross-over study to
      assess the effects of AV608 on brain processing of visceral stimuli and emotional visual cues
      in subjects with IBS. Female subjects between 18 and 65 years of age who meet diagnostic
      criteria for Irritable Bowel Syndrome will be eligible for the study.

      Eligible subjects will complete a baseline fMRI imaging procedure that includes both
      emotional visual cues and visceral stimulation. All subjects who participate in the study
      will receive 3 weeks of treatment with AV608 and 3 weeks of treatment with placebo during the
      course of the study; the order of the two treatments for each subject will be randomly
      determined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Animal Safety Data
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary efficacy endpoint is the effect of AV608 on regional brain responses as measured by fMRI during conditioned and unconditioned visceral pain due to rectal distension.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of AV608 on regional brain responses to emotional visceral cues as measured by fMRI and the visceral pain threshold during rectal distension will be evaluated as secondary efficacy endpoints.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS)</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AV608</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female, 18 to 65 years of age, inclusive

          -  Current diagnosis of Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS)

          -  Subjects 50 years of age or older must have had a barium enema and flexible
             sigmoidoscopy or a colonoscopy and provide a record of this test

          -  Willing to participate in this study as evidenced by a signed, written informed
             consent form (ICF)

          -  If female and of child-bearing potential, willing to avoid pregnancy and practice
             adequate birth control from the time of study enrollment through at least 30 days
             after the final dose of study medication

          -  If female, negative pregnancy test results

          -  Right handed

          -  Ambulatory outpatient

          -  Agrees to refrain from blood donation during the course of the study

          -  Written and oral fluency in the English language

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence of structural abnormality of the gastrointestinal tract or GI
             diseases/conditions

          -  Current evidence or diagnosis of peptic ulcer

          -  Endoscopic bowel evaluation with evidence of cancer, inflammatory bowel disease, or
             other structural disease

          -  History of abdominal surgery such as adhesion lysis or any gastrointestinal surgery

          -  History of gastroesophageal reflux disease not controlled by a stable dose of
             medication

          -  Any evidence of or treatment of malignancy within the previous 5 years

          -  Clinical evidence of any disease that may interfere with participation in the study

          -  Existence of surgical or medical conditions which interfere with the absorption,
             distribution, metabolism and excretion of the study drug

          -  Symptoms of a significant clinical illness within the 2 weeks prior to Screening

          -  Type 1 diabetes mellitus, insulin-dependent Type 2 diabetes mellitus, and thyroid
             disorders or other endocrine disorders that are not well controlled by appropriate
             therapy

          -  A QTc interval of greater than or equal to 450 msec at Screening

          -  Presence of a psychotic disorder, bipolar disorder, alcohol or substance dependence
             (other than nicotine dependence) or eating disorder within the previous year according
             to DSM-IV-TR criteria

          -  Seizure disorder

          -  Subjects who have previously participated in a clinical trial for AV608 (previously
             known as NKP608 and CGP608)

          -  Positive drug test result at Screening

          -  Use of investigational drugs, products or devices within 30 days prior to Screening

          -  Planned use of certain drugs during the study that affect the central nervous system,
             gastrointestinal motility, autonomic activity or pain sensation

          -  Use of pimozide, terfenadine, astemizole, or cisapride during the study

          -  Presence of moderate or severe allergy

          -  Regular intake of more than 2 units of alcohol per day

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding

          -  Subjects with morbid obesity

          -  Subjects with metal implants or large tattoo

          -  Any clinically significant abnormalities on the Screening physical examination, ECG or
             laboratory tests

          -  Members of the investigative staff or their immediate family members

          -  Any other condition that the investigator believes would jeopardize the safety or
             rights of the subject or would render the subject unable to comply with the study
             protocol

          -  Regular use of more than 10 cigarettes per day
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joao Siffert, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Avera Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kirsten Tillisch, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCLA Center for Neurovisceral Sciences and Women's Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA Center for Neurovisceral Sciences and Women's Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 19, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 21, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 15, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 15, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 25, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

