<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00310414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>060128</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>06-N-0128</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00310414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>fMRI Studies of Task Specificity in Focal Hand Dystonia</brief_title>
  <official_title>fMRI Studies of Task Specificity in Focal Hand Dystonia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine how the brain makes involuntary spasms and contractions in patients
      with focal hand dystonia (FHD). Patients with dystonia have muscle spasms that cause
      uncontrolled twisting and repetitive movement or abnormal postures. In FHD, only the hand is
      involved. The study will use functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI, see below) to study
      which areas of the brain are primarily affected in FHD and better understand how brain
      changes produce dystonia symptoms.

      Normal right-handed volunteers and patients with FHD who are 18-65 years of age may be
      eligible for this study. Candidates are screened with a medical history and physical and
      neurological examinations. Women who can become pregnant have a urine pregnancy test.

      All participants undergo fMRI. This test uses a strong magnetic field and radio waves to
      obtain images of body organs and tissues. The subject lies on a table that is moved into the
      scanner (a metal cylinder), wearing earplugs to muffle loud knocking and thumping sounds that
      occur during the scanning process. The procedure lasts about 90 minutes, during which time
      the patient is asked to lie still for 10-15 minutes at a time. During the procedure, subjects
      are asked to perform some tasks, including writing, tapping with their hand, and drawing in a
      zigzag motion. Each task is performed using the right hand, left hand and right foot.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      Writer's cramp, a form of focal hand dystonia, is the most frequently observed task specific
      dystonia. Symptoms of writer's cramp often appear as soon as the pen is picked up, or after a
      few words of writing. Patients with simple writer's cramp have difficulties writing, but
      carry out other tasks with the affected hand without spasms. Little is known about why the
      hand spasms when writing, while performing other tasks normally.

      The purpose of this study is to identify brain areas of activation associated specifically
      with the task of handwriting with the dystonic hand, in patients with simple writer's cramp.
      Simple writer's cramp can be defined by a patient exhibiting the symptoms only when writing
      and symptoms are not present in any other task performance. Specifically for this study,
      patients should be able to write for 20 seconds consecutively in a run. We plan to use
      functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) to identify the pattern of blood oxygenation
      level-dependent (BOLD) activation in the brain when different tasks are performed by
      different limbs in healthy volunteers and patients with focal hand dystonia.

      Study Population:

      This research will be conducted using 22 patients diagnosed with simple writer's cramp and 32
      healthy volunteers matched for age and gender.

      Design:

      Using a block design in functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), we will examine the
      brain activity of patients and healthy volunteers while they execute three tasks: writing,
      tapping and a zigzagging motion, with three separate limbs: the dystonic hand, the opposite
      hand, and the right foot.

      Outcome Measures:

      The changes in signal intensity of the brain activity correlated with the motor program (task
      of handwriting) and effector (dystonic hand) will be collected and analyzed.

      The findings we expect to obtain with this experiment may contribute to basic knowledge of
      the linkage between task specificity and the dystonic hand, and may provide a better
      understanding of the pathophysiology of writer's cramp.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 30, 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 13, 2012</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Actual">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Focal Dystonia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Focal Dystonia Subjects must be:

          -  Right hand dominant

          -  Between 18 and 65 years old

          -  Diagnosed with mild, simple focal hand dystonia. For this study mild, simple focal
             hand dystonia suggests that the patient does not present symptoms when performing
             tasks other than writing. Additionally, the patient should be able to write for 20
             seconds consecutively

          -  Willing to abstain from alcohol 48 hours prior to the study

        Volunteers must be:

          -  Healthy right-handed dominant individuals

          -  Between 18 and 65 years old

          -  Willing to abstain from alcohol 48 hours prior to the study

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Subjects with implanted devices such as pacemakers, medication pumps or
             defibrillators, metal in the cranium except mouth, intracardiac lines, history of
             shrapnel injury or any other condition/device that may be contraindicated or prevent
             the acquisition of MRI

          -  Subjects with any finding on the MRI safety questionnaire which prevents them from
             safely undergoing an MRI scan

          -  Subjects who are pregnant.

          -  Subjects with claustrophobia or other restrictions which prevent them from undergoing
             a scan in a confined space for up to 60 minutes

          -  Subjects with any visual, motor, or hearing difficulties

          -  Subjects with severe focal hand dystonia i.e., subjects who experience dystonic spasms
             in tasks other than/in addition to writing

          -  Subjects with mirror dystonia

          -  Subjects without the capacity to give consent

          -  Subjects with any history of a severe medical condition, such as cardiovascular
             disease, which will prevent them from lying flat for up to 60 minutes.

          -  Subjects with any history of brain tumor, stroke, head trauma or vascular malformation
             as obtained by history or from imaging studies.

          -  Subjects who have had recent (within 3 months) Botulinum Toxin (Botox) injections.

          -  Subjects who are on anti-parkinsonian drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kenneth H Fischbeck, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berardelli A, Rothwell JC, Hallett M, Thompson PD, Manfredi M, Marsden CD. The pathophysiology of primary dystonia. Brain. 1998 Jul;121 ( Pt 7):1195-212. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9679773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Butterworth S, Francis S, Kelly E, McGlone F, Bowtell R, Sawle GV. Abnormal cortical sensory activation in dystonia: an fMRI study. Mov Disord. 2003 Jun;18(6):673-82.</citation>
    <PMID>12784271</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blood AJ, Flaherty AW, Choi JK, Hochberg FH, Greve DN, Bonmassar G, Rosen BR, Jenkins BG. Basal ganglia activity remains elevated after movement in focal hand dystonia. Ann Neurol. 2004 May;55(5):744-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15122718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 13, 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 31, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 31, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 3, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Imaging Studies</keyword>
  <keyword>Botulinum Toxin</keyword>
  <keyword>Writer's Cramp</keyword>
  <keyword>Focal Hand Dystonia</keyword>
  <keyword>FHD</keyword>
  <keyword>Writer Cramp</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dystonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

