<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00316069</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>060142</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>06-DK-0142</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00316069</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stem Cell Collection</brief_title>
  <official_title>Peripheral Blood Collection of Adult Stem Cells</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed for the collection of stem cells from the bloodstream for use in
      research studies. These cells will be studied to determine if they have unique features
      particular to the donor that may or may not affect their use for developing new treatments.

      Volunteers with or without a blood disease may be eligible to donate stem cells for this
      study. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding may not enroll.

      Donors are evaluated with a medical history and physical examination, blood tests and an
      ultrasound examination of the spleen. They then undergo stem cell mobilization and apheresis
      as follows:

      Donors are given injections of a hormone called G-CSF every day for 5 days to stimulate
      release of stem cells from the bone marrow into the bloodstream for collection. On the day of
      the last injection, donors undergo apheresis to obtain white cells and stem cells. For this
      procedure, blood is withdrawn through a catheter (plastic tube) placed in a vein and directed
      into a machine where the white cells and stem cells are separated from the rest of the blood
      by a spinning process. These cells are extracted and collected in a bag inside the machine,
      and the rest of the blood is returned to the donor through a second catheter in a vein in the
      other arm. The procedure takes 4 to 5 hours.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent advances in the area of stem cell research suggest that redirected differentiation of
      stem cells may prove useful for the treatment of a variety of diseases including diabetes and
      other systemic diseases. In the hematopoietic system, recent studies have also demonstrated
      the ability of adult erythroid stem cells to undergo differentiation toward a fetal-like
      phenotype. This fetal-like phenotype is crucial in eliminating the clinical sequelae of
      sickle syndromes and beta hemoglobinopathies. However, additional studies are needed to
      determine if these results can be applied to patients with diseases involving hematopoietic
      stem cells or other blood cells. In addition, it is clear that the stem cells from separate
      donors do not possess identical properties of growth and differentiation.

      The immediate aim of this protocol is to obtain hematopoietic stem cells from many human
      donors for examination of the biological properties of those cells. The study is also
      designed to determine if the donor-specific factors can influence the properties of their
      hematopoietic stem cells. Each volunteer will undergo stem cell mobilization after
      administration of granulocyte-colony stimulating factor (G-CSF) for five consecutive days
      followed by a large volume apheresis on the 5th day after G-CSF injection. The harvested
      product will be purified for the primitive hematopoietic progenitor cells and viably
      preserved in multiple aliquots. The cells will then be studied in-depth for a better
      understanding of their biological properties, growth and differentiation. Donor-specific
      information will be correlated with these research studies to identify factors that may
      assist with the understanding of adult stem cell biology.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 12, 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date>August 2, 2017</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">429</enrollment>
  <condition>Stem Cells</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

        Ability to give informed consent to participate in the protocol.

        Meets NIH Department of Transfusion Medicine (DTM) eligibility criteria for blood component
        donation for in vitro research use (including minimum HCT of 28%, platelet count greater
        than 50,000/uL). Negative serologic tests for syphilis, hepatitis B and C, HIV, and HTLV-1.

        Listed below are acceptable medical conditions for inclusion in this protocol. They are
        derived from donor criteria that pertain to stem cell mobilization and peripheral blood
        leukapheresis described by the National Marrow Donor Program. Medical conditions that limit
        bone marrow harvest or re-infusion of cells into stem cell recipients do not apply to this
        protocol.

        Age: Volunteers of adult age including those over 60 years old who have no significant
        cardiovascular disease will be allowed to enroll.

        Allergies: If volunteers suffer from common allergies to animals, the environment, or
        medications other than G-CSF, they will be allowed to enroll.

        Arthritis: In general, if volunteers have mild to moderate osteoarthritis or degenerative
        arthritis, they will be allowed to enroll.

        Cancer: If volunteers have a history of cancer or currently have cancer that does not
        affect their cardiovascular status, they will be allowed to enroll.

        Mental health conditions: If volunteers have mental health conditions that are
        well-controlled, they will be allowed to enroll.

        Diabetes: If volunteers have diabetes, a careful evaluation of their current health status
        will be necessary. In general, if their diabetes is well-controlled by either diet or oral
        medications, and have no significant cardiovascular disease, they will be allowed to
        enroll.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

        Any concomitant condition or illness that will result in an inability to undergo G-CSF
        mobilization or apheresis listed below.

        Allergy to G-CSF or bacterial E. coli products.

        Autoimmune diseases, such as immune thrombocytopenic purpura, rheumatoid arthritis or
        systemic lupus erythematosus.

        Patients with active pulmonary disease.

        Significant cardiovascular disease or related symptoms such as chest pain, shortness of
        breath, or uncontrolled hypertension. If volunteers have heart conditions such as
        well-controlled arrhythmias, or mitral valve prolapse that does not require medication or
        restrictions, they will be allowed to enroll. If volunteers have elevated blood pressure
        that is well-controlled by medication or diet and if there is no associated heart disease,
        they will be allowed to enroll.

        Epilepsy: If volunteers have had more than one seizure in the past year, they will not be
        allowed to enroll. If volunteers have well-controlled epilepsy and have had no seizures in
        the past year, they will be allowed to enroll.

        Active infections.

        Pregnant and lactating women.

        Splenomegaly: Patients having splenic diameters greater than 13.0 cm at the time of initial
        assessment will be excluded from the protocol.

        Sickle cell disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffery L Miller, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pomerantz J, Blau HM. Nuclear reprogramming: a key to stem cell function in regenerative medicine. Nat Cell Biol. 2004 Sep;6(9):810-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15340448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gershengorn MC, Hardikar AA, Wei C, Geras-Raaka E, Marcus-Samuels B, Raaka BM. Epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition generates proliferative human islet precursor cells. Science. 2004 Dec 24;306(5705):2261-4. Epub 2004 Nov 25.</citation>
    <PMID>15564314</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhanu NV, Trice TA, Lee YT, Gantt NM, Oneal P, Schwartz JD, Noel P, Miller JL. A sustained and pancellular reversal of gamma-globin gene silencing in adult human erythroid precursor cells. Blood. 2005 Jan 1;105(1):387-93. Epub 2004 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>15367428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 18, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 18, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 19, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Erythropoiesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukapheresis</keyword>
  <keyword>G-CSF</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobilization</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem Cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Apheresis</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood Donation</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

