<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00311948</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5R01CA098685-02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01CA098685-01A2</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00311948</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telephone and Web-based Teen Tobacco Cessation in HMOs</brief_title>
  <acronym>QWIThelper</acronym>
  <official_title>Telephone and Web-based Teen Tobacco Cessation in HMOs</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaiser Permanente</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to look at both the clinicians' ability to reach out to the teen
      smokers and to evaluate the efficacy of providing tobacco cessation support using a proactive
      telephone quitline combined with an interactive Web-based program for teens within a managed
      care environment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Health maintenance organizations have the mission, incentive, communication tools, and
      credibility with patients to reach out to teen members who use tobacco. The overall aim of
      this project is to refine and test both the potential reach and the efficacy of tobacco
      cessation support using a proactive telephone quitline combined with an interactive Web-based
      program for teens within a managed care environment. As part of a clinician-directed outreach
      effort, we will work closely with pediatric clinicians to maximize the program's reach into
      the teen smoker population as identified through the electronic data base of a large HMO. We
      will use letters and proactive outreach calls to assess current smoking status and recruit
      600 15- to 18-year-old teen smokers who are interested in quitting and would be willing to
      receive cessation support via telephone and the Web. A second aim will be to randomly assign
      interested teen smokers to receive a proactive telephone- and Web-based tobacco cessation
      program or access to a website with cessation materials (control condition) to test the
      efficacy of the program on long-term cessation rates at 6- and 12-months. We will use several
      process measures to assess our ability to implement and consistently deliver both the
      telephone and Web components of the intervention. We will measure mediating variables to
      determine they support the hypothesized linkages between the theoretical constructs described
      by our cognitive behavioral model of action. An effective managed care partnership with
      clinicians to assess, recruit, and intervene with teen smokers would be of great interest to
      clinicians and health plan managers, highly exportable, and would be given high priority for
      implementation at the population level.

      Our specific aims are as follows:

        1. Compare the population-based recruitment yields and costs of three proactive outreach
           approaches: 1) outreach calls only to those teen smokers who are seen, advised, and
           referred to us by their clinician; 2) outreach calls to a random sample of teens shown
           as being smokers in the EMR; and 3) outreach calls to a sample of all teens

        2. Assess efficacy/effectiveness in a randomized trial with 600 teen smokers to evaluate
           the hypothesis that proactive telephone-based counseling integrated with an interactive
           website will increase 6- and 12-month abstinence rates (30-day point prevalence)
           relative to a control condition receiving mailed cessation materials alone

        3. Assess the hypothesis that the telephone and web-based intervention will improve
           longer-term maintenance of abstinence at an 12-month follow-up point compared to the
           control condition

        4. Describe use patterns for key intervention process measures (e.g., calls completed, use
           of website) and determine if intervention affects outcome through theoretical mediators
           (e.g., pros/cons, stage, efficacy)

        5. Determine the total costs of the telephone and web-based program from the perspective of
           the HMO and replication costs in other settings, and report costs as incremental costs
           per member per month, per program participant, and per quit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants' self-report of smoking one or more cigarettes in the past month at the 6-month and 12-month follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>self report of smoking in last 30 days</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>12-month measure to determine long-term assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Self report smoking or not smoking.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A six-month assessment to determine short-term effects</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the prevalence of smoking on 25 or more days per month</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess sustained abstinence (e.g., three and six months) at each follow-up,</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>No smoking - yes or no at 3 month timeframe and 6 months timeframe</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess change in stage of change</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess amount smoked, and use of other tobacco products (including smokeless tobacco) in the last week, 30 days, three months, and six months prior to the follow-up assessment.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the proportion of teen smokers who are recruited through direct physician referral versus proactive outreach</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the population-based recruitment yields and costs of three proactive outreach approaches that health plans might implement</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Tobacco Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone counseling + interactive website</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Teen has access to interactive website and receives tailored telephone counseling</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control with interactive website</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Teen only has access to interactive website.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telephone counseling + interactive website = more abstinence</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone counseling + interactive website</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral: interactive website</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Control with interactive website</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  15-18 years old

          -  both males and females

          -  smoking cigarettes at least four days a month

          -  some interest in quitting (will take all teen regardless of stage of readiness

          -  no evidence of treatment for depression, alcohol, or drugs in last year

          -  must consent

          -  have physician's approval for outreach to their panel

          -  have (or able to get) Internet access and phone access

          -  willingness to participate in study and follow-up procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt;15 years old

          -  &gt;18 years old

          -  treated within 1 year for depression, alcohol, or drugs

          -  No internet access or phone access
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jack F Hollis, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Eugene</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97403</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Permanente Center for Health Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97227</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Free &amp; Clear, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Committee on Substance Abuse. American Academy of Pediatrics: Tobacco's toll: implications for the pediatrician. Pediatrics. 2001 Apr;107(4):794-8. Erratum in: Pediatrics 2001 Aug;108(2):502.</citation>
    <PMID>11335763</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aveyard P, Cheng KK, Almond J, Sherratt E, Lancashire R, Lawrence T, Griffin C, Evans O. Cluster randomised controlled trial of expert system based on the transtheoretical (&quot;stages of change&quot;) model for smoking prevention and cessation in schools. BMJ. 1999 Oct 9;319(7215):948-53.</citation>
    <PMID>10514156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balch GI. Exploring perceptions of smoking cessation among high school smokers: input and feedback from focus groups. Prev Med. 1998 Sep-Oct;27(5 Pt 3):A55-63.</citation>
    <PMID>9808818</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bandura A. Self-efficacy: toward a unifying theory of behavioral change. Psychol Rev. 1977 Mar;84(2):191-215.</citation>
    <PMID>847061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benuck I, Gidding SS, Binns HJ. Identification of adolescent tobacco users in a pediatric practice. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2001 Jan;155(1):32-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11177059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernard HR, Ryan GW. Text analysis: Qualitative and Quantitative Methods. In Handbook of Methods in Cultural Anthropology. Walnut Creek, CA: AltaMira Press; 1998</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Botvin GJ, Baker E, Dusenbury L, Tortu S, Botvin EM. Preventing adolescent drug abuse through a multimodal cognitive-behavioral approach: results of a 3-year study. J Consult Clin Psychol. 1990 Aug;58(4):437-46.</citation>
    <PMID>2212181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bowen DJ, Kinne S, Orlandi M. School policy in COMMIT: a promising strategy to reduce smoking by youth. J Sch Health. 1995 Apr;65(4):140-4.</citation>
    <PMID>7603051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bracken AC, Hersh AL, Johnson DJ. A computerized school-based health assessment with rapid feedback to improve adolescent health. Clin Pediatr (Phila). 1998 Nov;37(11):677-83.</citation>
    <PMID>9825212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Breslau N, Peterson EL. Smoking cessation in young adults: age at initiation of cigarette smoking and other suspected influences. Am J Public Health. 1996 Feb;86(2):214-20.</citation>
    <PMID>8633738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burt RD, Peterson AV Jr. Smoking cessation among high school seniors. Prev Med. 1998 May-Jun;27(3):319-27.</citation>
    <PMID>9612822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burton D. Tobacco cessation programs for adolescents. In: Richmond R, editor. Interventions for Smokers, an International Perspective. Baltimore, MD: Williams &amp; Wilkins; 1994. p. 95-105.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cannell M. Generation Online: Internet use of teenagers. Science World 1999;55(9):5</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chassin L, Presson CC, Rose JS, Sherman SJ. The natural history of cigarette smoking from adolescence to adulthood: demographic predictors of continuity and change. Health Psychol. 1996 Nov;15(6):478-84.</citation>
    <PMID>8973929</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen PH, White HR, Pandina RJ. Predictors of smoking cessation from adolescence into young adulthood. Addict Behav. 2001 Jul-Aug;26(4):517-29.</citation>
    <PMID>11456075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coambs RB, Li S, Kozlowski LT. Age interacts with heaviness of smoking in predicting success in cessation of smoking. Am J Epidemiol. 1992 Feb 1;135(3):240-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1546699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Curry SJ, Grothaus LC, McAfee T, Pabiniak C. Use and cost effectiveness of smoking-cessation services under four insurance plans in a health maintenance organization. N Engl J Med. 1998 Sep 3;339(10):673-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9725926</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Curry SJ, McBride C, Grothaus LC, Louie D, Wagner EH. A randomized trial of self-help materials, personalized feedback, and telephone counseling with nonvolunteer smokers. J Consult Clin Psychol. 1995 Dec;63(6):1005-14.</citation>
    <PMID>8543703</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dent CW, Sussman S, Stacy AW, Craig S, Burton D, Flay BR. Two-year behavior outcomes of project towards no tobacco use. J Consult Clin Psychol. 1995 Aug;63(4):676-7.</citation>
    <PMID>7673547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Department of Commerce. Falling Through the Net: Defining the Digital Divide, 1999; Online at http://www.ntia.doc.gov/ntiahome/fttn99/contents.html. Last viewed January, 2002.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Digiusto E. Pros and cons of cessation interventions for adolescent smokers at school. In R Richmond (ed). Interventions for smokers: An international perspective. Baltimore: MD: Williams &amp; Wilkins;107 136, 1994.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drummond MF, O'Brien B, Stoddart GL, Torrance GW. Methods for the Economic Evaluation of Health Care Programmes. 2nd Edition. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1997.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elder JP, Wildey M, de Moor C, Sallis JF Jr, Eckhardt L, Edwards C, Erickson A, Golbeck A, Hovell M, Johnston D, et al. The long-term prevention of tobacco use among junior high school students: classroom and telephone interventions. Am J Public Health. 1993 Sep;83(9):1239-44.</citation>
    <PMID>8362998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engels RC, Knibbe RA, de Vries H, Drop MJ. Antecedents of smoking cessation among adolescents: who is motivated to change? Prev Med. 1998 May-Jun;27(3):348-57.</citation>
    <PMID>9612825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>A clinical practice guideline for treating tobacco use and dependence: A US Public Health Service report. The Tobacco Use and Dependence Clinical Practice Guideline Panel, Staff, and Consortium Representatives. JAMA. 2000 Jun 28;283(24):3244-54. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10866874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flay BR, Hu FB, Richardson J. Psychosocial predictors of different stages of cigarette smoking among high school students. Prev Med. 1998 Sep-Oct;27(5 Pt 3):A9-18.</citation>
    <PMID>9808813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fleiss JL. Statistical methods for rates and proportions. Second Ed. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons; 1981.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flynn BS, Worden JK, Secker-Walker RH, Pirie PL, Badger GJ, Carpenter JH. Long-term responses of higher and lower risk youths to smoking prevention interventions. Prev Med. 1997 May-Jun;26(3):389-94.</citation>
    <PMID>9144764</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, Mullooly JP, Vogt TM, Stevens VJ, Lichtenstein E, Hollis JF, Lando HA, Severson HH, Pearson KA, Vogt MR. Biochemical validation of smoking status: pros, cons, and data from four low-intensity intervention trials. Addict Behav. 1993 Sep-Oct;18(5):511-27.</citation>
    <PMID>8310871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, Toobert DJ, Hampson SE. Effects of a brief office-based intervention to facilitate diabetes dietary self-management. Diabetes Care. 1996 Aug;19(8):835-42.</citation>
    <PMID>8842601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, La Chance PA, Toobert DJ, Brown J, Hampson SE, Riddle MC. Long-term effects and costs of brief behavioural dietary intervention for patients with diabetes delivered from the medical office. Patient Educ Couns. 1997 Nov;32(3):175-84.</citation>
    <PMID>9423499</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, Fisher EB, Anderson BJ, LaGreca A, Marrero D, Johnson SB, Rubin RR, Cox DJ. Behavioral science in diabetes. Contributions and opportunities. Diabetes Care. 1999 May;22(5):832-43. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10332691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, Vogt TM, Boles SM. Evaluating the public health impact of health promotion interventions: the RE-AIM framework. Am J Public Health. 1999 Sep;89(9):1322-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10474547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, Wagner EH, Kaplan RM, Vinicor F, Smith L, Norman J. If diabetes is a public health problem, why not treat it as one? A population-based approach to chronic illness. Ann Behav Med. 1999 Spring;21(2):159-70. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10499137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, Eakin EG. Medical office-based interventions. In: Snoek FJ, Skinner CS., Eds. Psychological Aspects of Diabetes Care. New York: John Wiley and Sons; 2000</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gold MR, Siegel JE, Russell LB, Weinstein MC. Cost-Effectiveness in Health and Medicine. New York: Oxford University Press, 1996.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richard L, Breton ER, Lehoux P, Martin C, Roy D. [Public health professionals' perceptions regarding two dimensions of health promotion: the ecological approach and community participation]. Can J Public Health. 1999 Mar-Apr;90(2):99-103. French.</citation>
    <PMID>10349215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grzywacz JG, Fuqua J. The social ecology of health: leverage points and linkages. Behav Med. 2000 Fall;26(3):101-15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11209591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hines D. Young smokers' attitudes about methods for quitting smoking: barriers and benefits to using assisted methods. Addict Behav. 1996 Jul-Aug;21(4):531-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8830912</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hollis JF, Bills R, Whitlock E, Stevens VJ, Mullooly J, Lichtenstein E. Implementing tobacco interventions in the real world of managed care. Tob Control. 2000;9 Suppl 1:I18-24.</citation>
    <PMID>10688926</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hollis JF, Lichtenstein E, Mount K, Vogt TM, Stevens VJ. Nurse-assisted smoking counseling in medical settings: minimizing demands on physicians. Prev Med. 1991 Jul;20(4):497-507.</citation>
    <PMID>1871078</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hollis JF, Lichtenstein E, Vogt TM, Stevens VJ, Biglan A. Nurse-assisted counseling for smokers in primary care. Ann Intern Med. 1993 Apr 1;118(7):521-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8442622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hollis JF, Polen MR, Lichtenstein E, Whitlock EP. Tobacco use patterns and attitudes among teens being seen for routine primary care. Am J Health Promot. 2003 Mar-Apr;17(4):231-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12640779</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hollis JF, Vogt TM, Stevens VJ, Biglan A, Severson H, Lichtenstein E. The Tobacco Reduction and Cancer Control (TRACC) Program: Team approaches to counseling in medical and dental settings. In US Department of Health and Human Services, Tobacco and the Clinician: Interventions for Medical and Dental Practice, pp. 143 185. Smoking and Tobacco Control: Monograph 5. US Department of Health and Human Services, Public Health Service, National Institutes of Health. NIH Publication No. 94 3693, January 1994.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hu TW, Lin Z, Keeler TE. Teenage smoking, attempts to quit, and school performance. Am J Public Health. 1998 Jun;88(6):940-3.</citation>
    <PMID>9618625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jaén CR, Stange KC, Tumiel LM, Nutting P. Missed opportunities for prevention: smoking cessation counseling and the competing demands of practice. J Fam Pract. 1997 Oct;45(4):348-54.</citation>
    <PMID>9343057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein JD. Incorporating effective smoking prevention and cessation counseling into practice. Pediatr Ann. 1995 Dec;24(12):646-52. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8747707</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein JD, Levine LJ, Allan MJ. Delivery of smoking prevention and cessation services to adolescents. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2001 May;155(5):597-602.</citation>
    <PMID>11343505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kottke TE, Battista RN, DeFriese GH, Brekke ML. Attributes of successful smoking cessation interventions in medical practice. A meta-analysis of 39 controlled trials. JAMA. 1988 May 20;259(19):2883-9.</citation>
    <PMID>3367456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lamb JM, Albrecht SA, Sereika S. Consideration of factors prior to implementing a smoking cessation program. J Sch Nurs. 1998 Feb;14(1):14-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9505644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lamkin LP, Houston TP. Nicotine dependency and adolescents: preventing and treating. Prim Care. 1998 Mar;25(1):123-35. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9469919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lichtenstein E, Glasgow RE, Lando HA, Ossip-Klein DJ, Boles SM. Telephone counseling for smoking cessation: rationales and meta-analytic review of evidence. Health Educ Res. 1996 Jun;11(2):243-57.</citation>
    <PMID>10163409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Institute of Medicine (US) Committee on Preventing Nicotine Addiction in Children and Youths; Lynch BS, Bonnie RJ, editors. Growing up Tobacco Free: Preventing Nicotine Addiction in Children and Youths. Washington (DC): National Academies Press (US); 1994.</citation>
    <PMID>25144107</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAfee T, Wilson J, Dacey S, Sofian N, Curry S, Wagener B. Awakening the sleeping giant: mainstreaming efforts to decrease tobacco use in an HMO. HMO Pract. 1995 Sep;9(3):138-43.</citation>
    <PMID>10151099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McIlvain HE, Crabtree BF, Gilbert C, Havranek R, Backer EL. Current trends in tobacco prevention and cessation in Nebraska physicians' offices. J Fam Pract. 1997 Feb;44(2):193-202.</citation>
    <PMID>9040523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller WL, Crabtree BF. Clinical research. In: Handbook of Qualitative Research. NK Denzin &amp; YS Lincoln (eds.) Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage Publications; 1994.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller WR, Rollnick S. Motivational Interviewing: Preparing People to Change Addictive Behavior. New York: The Guilford Press; 1991.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moolchan ET, Ernst M, Henningfield JE. A review of tobacco smoking in adolescents: treatment implications. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2000 Jun;39(6):682-93. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10846302</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morgan DL, ed. The Focus Group Guidebook. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage; 1998.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>National Cancer Institute. Scientific priorities for cancer research: NCI's extraordinary opportunities. Online at: http://2001.cancer.gov/communications.htm. Last viewed: January 2002.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nielsen NetRatings. (2001, May) [On-line]. http://www.eratings.com/news/20010430.htm. Report available at: http://www.nwcn.com/cybernews/329373_TSportlandwired040301.html</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nichter M, Nichter M, Vuckovic N, Quintero G, Ritenbaugh C. Smoking experimentation and initiation among adolescent girls: qualitative and quantitative findings. Tob Control. 1997 Winter;6(4):285-95.</citation>
    <PMID>9583626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nichter M, Vuckovic N, Parker S. The looking good, feeling good program: A multi-ethnic intervention for healthy body image, nutrition and physical activity. In Preventing Eating Disorders: A Handbook of Intervention and Special Challenges. E Piran, MP Levine and C Steiner-Adair, eds. Philadelphia: Brunner-Mozel; 1999, 173-93.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Connor EA, Hollis JF, Polen MR, Lichtenstein E. Adolescent health care visits: opportunities for brief prevention messages. Eff Clin Pract. 1999 Nov-Dec;2(6):272-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10788025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oregon Youth Risk Behavior Survey. Health Division, Oregon Department of Human Resources. Portland, Oregon, Dec. 1993.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Orleans CT, Schoenbach VJ, Wagner EH, Quade D, Salmon MA, Pearson DC, Fiedler J, Porter CQ, Kaplan BH. Self-help quit smoking interventions: effects of self-help materials, social support instructions, and telephone counseling. J Consult Clin Psychol. 1991 Jun;59(3):439-48.</citation>
    <PMID>2071729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paavola M, Vartiainen E, Puska P. Smoking cessation between teenage years and adulthood. Health Educ Res. 2001 Feb;16(1):49-57.</citation>
    <PMID>11252283</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pallonen UE, Velicer WF, Prochaska JO, Rossi JS, Bellis JM, Tsoh JY, Migneault JP, Smith NF, Prokhorov AV. Computer-based smoking cessation interventions in adolescents: description, feasibility, and six-month follow-up findings. Subst Use Misuse. 1998 Mar;33(4):935-65.</citation>
    <PMID>9548631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pallonen UE, Prochaska JO, Velicer WF, Prokhorov AV, Smith NF. Stages of acquisition and cessation for adolescent smoking: an empirical integration. Addict Behav. 1998 May-Jun;23(3):303-24.</citation>
    <PMID>9668929</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perry CL, Griffin G, Murray DM. Assessing needs for youth health promotion. Prev Med. 1985 May;14(3):379-93.</citation>
    <PMID>4059190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peterson AV Jr, Kealey KA, Mann SL, Marek PM, Sarason IG. Hutchinson Smoking Prevention Project: long-term randomized trial in school-based tobacco use prevention--results on smoking. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2000 Dec 20;92(24):1979-91.</citation>
    <PMID>11121460</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pew Internet &amp; American Life Project. The Internet and Education: Findings of the Pew Internet &amp; American Life Project. Online at: http://www.pewinternet.org/reports/toc.asp?Report=39. Last viewed: January 2002</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plummer BA, Velicer WF, Redding CA, Prochaska JO, Rossi JS, Pallonen UE, Meier KS. Stage of change, decisional balance, and temptations for smoking: measurement and validation in a large, school-based population of adolescents. Addict Behav. 2001 Jul-Aug;26(4):551-71.</citation>
    <PMID>11456077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prince F. The relative effectiveness of a peer-led and adult-led smoking intervention program. Adolescence. 1995 Spring;30(117):187-94.</citation>
    <PMID>7625255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prochaska JO, DiClemente CC, Norcross JC. In search of how people change. Applications to addictive behaviors. Am Psychol. 1992 Sep;47(9):1102-14.</citation>
    <PMID>1329589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prochaska JO, DiClemente CC, Velicer WF, Ginpil S, Norcross JC. Predicting change in smoking status for self-changers. Addict Behav. 1985;10(4):395-406.</citation>
    <PMID>4091072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prochaska JO, DiClemente CC. Stages and processes of self-change of smoking: toward an integrative model of change. J Consult Clin Psychol. 1983 Jun;51(3):390-5.</citation>
    <PMID>6863699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roberts DF, Foehr UB, Rideout VJ, Brodie M. Kids, Media @ The New Millennium. A Kaiser Family Foundation Report, November; 1999.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rost K, Burnam MA, Smith GR. Development of screeners for depressive disorders and substance disorder history. Med Care. 1993 Mar;31(3):189-200.</citation>
    <PMID>8450677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sargent JD, Mott LA, Stevens M. Predictors of smoking cessation in adolescents. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 1998 Apr;152(4):388-93.</citation>
    <PMID>9559717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Secker-Walker RH, Worden JK, Holland RR, Flynn BS, Detsky AS. A mass media programme to prevent smoking among adolescents: costs and cost effectiveness. Tob Control. 1997 Autumn;6(3):207-12.</citation>
    <PMID>9396105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Senn S. Testing for baseline balance in clinical trials. Stat Med. 1994 Sep 15;13(17):1715-26.</citation>
    <PMID>7997705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siqueira LM, Rolnitzky LM, Rickert VI. Smoking cessation in adolescents: the role of nicotine dependence, stress, and coping methods. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2001 Apr;155(4):489-95.</citation>
    <PMID>11296077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith TA, House RF Jr, Croghan IT, Gauvin TR, Colligan RC, Offord KP, Gomez-Dahl LC, Hurt RD. Nicotine patch therapy in adolescent smokers. Pediatrics. 1996 Oct;98(4 Pt 1):659-67.</citation>
    <PMID>8885942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>SRNT Subcommittee on Biochemical Verification. Biochemical verification of tobacco use and cessation. Nicotine Tob Res. 2002 May;4(2):149-59.</citation>
    <PMID>12028847</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Solas V.3.0. Cork, Ireland; Statistical Solutions Ltd., 2001.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strecher VJ. Computer-tailored smoking cessation materials: a review and discussion. Patient Educ Couns. 1999 Feb;36(2):107-17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10223016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sussman S. Effects of sixty six adolescent tobacco use cessation trials and seventeen prospective studies of self-initiated quitting. Tob Induc Dis. 2002 Jan 15;1(1):35-81. doi: 10.1186/1617-9625-1-1-35.</citation>
    <PMID>19570247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sussman S, Dent CW, Stacy AW, Sun P, Craig S, Simon TR, Burton D, Flay BR. Project towards no tobacco use: 1-year behavior outcomes. Am J Public Health. 1993 Sep;83(9):1245-50.</citation>
    <PMID>8362999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sussman S, Lichtman K, Ritt A, Pallonen UE. Effects of thirty-four adolescent tobacco use cessation and prevention trials on regular users of tobacco products. Subst Use Misuse. 1999 Sep;34(11):1469-503. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10468104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sussman S, Dent CW, Severson H, Burton D, Flay BR. Self-initiated quitting among adolescent smokers. Prev Med. 1998 Sep-Oct;27(5 Pt 3):A19-28.</citation>
    <PMID>9808814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Kaiser Family Foundation. Generation Rx.com How Young people Use the Internet for Health Information. Online at: http://www.kff.org/content/2001/20011211a/. 2001. Last viewed January 2002.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thorndike AN, Ferris TG, Stafford RS, Rigotti NA. Rates of U.S. physicians counseling adolescents about smoking. J Natl Cancer Inst. 1999 Nov 3;91(21):1857-62.</citation>
    <PMID>10547392</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>US Department of Health and Human Services. Preventing Tobacco Use Among Young People: A Report of the Surgeon General. Atlanta, Georgia: US Department of Health and Human Services, Public Health Service, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health; 1994.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Velicer WF, Prochaska JO, Rossi JS, Snow MG. Assessing outcome in smoking cessation studies. Psychol Bull. 1992 Jan;111(1):23-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1539088</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vuckovic N, Polen MR, Hollis JF. The problem is getting us to stop. What teens say about smoking cessation. Prev Med. 2003 Sep;37(3):209-18.</citation>
    <PMID>12914826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woodruff SI, Edwards CC, Conway TL, Elliott SP. Pilot test of an Internet virtual world chat room for rural teen smokers. J Adolesc Health. 2001 Oct;29(4):239-43.</citation>
    <PMID>11587907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Worden JK, Flynn BS, Solomon LJ, Secker-Walker RH, Badger GJ, Carpenter JH. Using mass media to prevent cigarette smoking among adolescent girls. Health Educ Q. 1996 Nov;23(4):453-68.</citation>
    <PMID>8910024</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zapka JG, Fletcher K, Pbert L, Druker SK, Ockene JK, Chen L. The perceptions and practices of pediatricians: tobacco intervention. Pediatrics. 1999 May;103(5):e65.</citation>
    <PMID>10224209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhu SH, Sun J, Billings SC, Choi WS, Malarcher A. Predictors of smoking cessation in U.S. adolescents. Am J Prev Med. 1999 Apr;16(3):202-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10198659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 4, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 4, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 6, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 27, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 27, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 28, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Teen smokers</keyword>
  <keyword>Quithelper</keyword>
  <keyword>Tobacco</keyword>
  <keyword>Tobacco Website</keyword>
  <keyword>Website Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Tobacco counseling</keyword>
  <keyword>Tobacco abstinence</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

