<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01793194</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00047720</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01793194</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preventing the Development of Venous Insufficiency in Pregnant Women Through Use of Compression Stockings</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preventing the Development of Venous Insufficiency in Pregnant Women Through Use of Compression Stockings: A Randomized Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sigvaris Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Problem: Approximately 4 million live births occur in the United States each year. Pregnancy
      causes many physical changes in the mother, including venous distension, increased ability to
      form blood clots, and hormonal changes. Data suggest that these factors help cause venous
      insufficiency (when the veins do not adequately return blood from the extremities to the
      torso). As venous insufficiency progresses, complications follow, the most severe of which
      include superficial thrombophlebitis and deep venous thrombosis (DVT, or blood clots).
      Although the fear of DVT has been well publicized, its prevention and prevalence in pregnant
      women has not been well-studied.

      The exact cause of venous insufficiency is not known. However, known risk factors include
      being female and hormonal changes associated with oral contraceptive use, certain hormone
      replacement medications, and pregnancy. Being pregnant places the mother at additional risk
      for developing venous insufficiency.

      Compression stockings are used to manage the condition, but this is by no means standard of
      care despite their easy use and safety. The medical community's understanding of how
      compression stockings work is largely theoretical; however, it is believed that the
      compression works by preventing venous hypertension in the lower legs, thereby preventing
      venous insufficiency and its associated complications.

      Research hypothesis: The investigators hypothesize that compression stocking use will be
      associated with lower incidence of varicose veins and, in those patients who already have
      varicose veins, lower incidence of complications associated with venous insufficiency.
      Further, the investigators believe that compression stocking use will be associated with a
      lower incidence or lessening of symptoms associated with venous insufficiency.

      Importance: An undetected DVT can be fatal. Even if detected promptly, DVT is associated with
      long term health problems. Treatment of a DVT requires anticoagulation which can be risky to
      both mother and fetus. The prevention or reduction of DVT in pregnant women through use of
      compression stockings would revolutionize their care. Further, this intervention is safe and
      noninvasive.

      The investigators propose to conduct a randomized, pilot study comparing pregnant women
      without and with varicose veins randomized to wear compression stockings to a similar group
      of participants randomized to no compression stocking use.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Problem: There are approximately four million live births in the United States annually.
      Pregnancy induces multisystemic physiologic changes in the mother as her body accommodates
      the growing fetus. Known physiologic alterations include venous distension,
      hypercoagulability, and hormonal changes. Anecdotal data suggests that these particular
      factors precipitate the development of venous insufficiency. As venous insufficiency
      progresses, complications ensue, the most severe of which include superficial
      thrombophlebitis and deep venous thrombosis. Although the fear of deep venous thrombus (DVT)
      has been well publicized, its prevention and actual prevalence in the pregnant population has
      not been adequately studied.

      The precise mechanism of venous insufficiency has yet to be elucidated. However, several
      known risk factors exist. They include female gender and hormonal changes associated with
      elevated progesterone levels such as oral contraceptive use, certain exogenous hormonal
      replacement medications, and pregnancy. Clearly, the pregnant state places the mother at
      additive risk for subsequent development of venous insufficiency.

      Medical management of venous insufficiency consists of compression stocking use, and some
      physicians do recommend their use to pregnant patients. However, this practice is by no means
      standard of care, despite its noninvasive application and safety. The precise mechanism
      through which compression stockings work is largely theoretical; however, it is believed that
      the extrinsic graduated compression works by preventing venous hypertension in the distal
      lower extremity, thereby preventing venous insufficiency and its associated complications.

      Research hypothesis: The investigators hypothesize that compression stocking use will be
      associated with lower incidence of varicose veins and, in those patients who already have
      varicose veins, lower incidence of complications associated with venous insufficiency,
      particularly superficial thrombophlebitis and deep venous thrombosis (DVT). Further, the
      investigators believe that compression stocking use will be associated with a lower incidence
      or lessening of symptoms associated with venous insufficiency, such as edema, fatigue, venous
      stasis dermatitis, and venous neuropathy (burning).

      Importance: While some may feel that varicose veins, edema, fatigue, and other outcomes are
      unimportant, an undetected DVT is commonly a fatal event. Even if detected promptly, DVT is
      associated with long term morbidity, such as post thrombotic syndrome which can occur in up
      to 30% of those patients diagnosed with a DVT. Treatment of a DVT requires anticoagulation
      which, although essential, carries significant risk to both mother and fetus. The prevention
      or reduction in incidence of DVT in this population merely with compression stocking use
      would revolutionize care in the pregnant population. Further, this intervention is safe and
      noninvasive.

      The investigators propose to conduct a randomized, pilot study comparing pregnant women
      without (Group 1) and with (Group 2) varicose veins randomized to wear compression stockings
      (Treatment Subgroup A) to a similar group of participants randomized to no compression
      stocking use (Control Subgroup B).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 24, 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 24, 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of varicose veins</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks post-partum</time_frame>
    <description>In pregnant women who do not have varicose veins (Group 1): To quantify and compare the incidence of varicose veins between participants randomized to the compression stocking use group (Group 1A) and those randomized to the no compression stocking use group (Group 1B).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of superficial thrombophlebitis and DVT</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks post-partum</time_frame>
    <description>In pregnant women who already have varicose veins (Group 2): To quantify and compare the incidence of superficial thrombophlebitis and DVT between those randomized to the compression stocking use group (Group 2A) and those randomized to the no compression stocking use group (Group 2B).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of symptoms of venous insufficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks post-partum</time_frame>
    <description>For All Groups: To quantify and compare the incidence of symptoms of venous insufficiency in pregnant women between the treatment and control groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Venous Insufficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Stocking Use</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>For pregnant women randomized to the no stocking use group, no compression stockings will be worn.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Compression Stocking Use</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who are randomized to the stocking use group (Treatment Subgroup A) will be formally measured for their stockings by a certified stocking fitter, given (at no charge) two pair of 20-30mmg Hg maternity pantyhose compression stockings, and will undergo a brief tutorial regarding how to put the stockings on. Each patient will be instructed to wear the stockings on a daily basis, during the day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Compression Stockings</intervention_name>
    <description>20-30mmg Hg maternity pantyhose compression stockings</description>
    <arm_group_label>Compression Stocking Use</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women 18-45 years of age.

          -  Fetal gestation between 8-20 weeks.

          -  Patient is seeking care for the pregnancy at one of the study locations (Johns Hopkins
             East Baltimore Campus, Johns Hopkins Bayview Medical Center, and Johns Hopkins at
             White Marsh).

          -  Ability to complete informed consent and willingness to comply with protocol (return
             for all follow-up visits &amp; participate in phone interviews).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to wear compression stockings.

          -  Women who currently have been prescribed to wear compression stockings by a medical
             professional.

          -  Chronic dermatological condition (i.e. psoriasis).

          -  Chronic deep vein thrombus or chronic phlebitis.

          -  In women with varicose veins: Presence of primary outcome (superficial
             thrombophlebitis or DVT) on first visit ultrasound.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Heller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Div. of Vascular Surgery, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Bayview Medical Center and Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 15, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>venous insufficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>varicose veins</keyword>
  <keyword>pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>DVT</keyword>
  <keyword>superficial thrombophlebitis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Venous Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

