<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01795430</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12391</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-00439</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01795430</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Whole-Body Radiation Therapy, Systemic Chemotherapy, and High-Dose Chemotherapy Followed By Stem Cell Rescue in Treating Patients With Poor-Risk Ewing Sarcoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Whole-body MRI-guided Intensity Modulated Radiation Therapy Combined With Systemic Chemotherapy Followed by High-Dose Chemotherapy With Busulfan, Melphalan and Topotecan and Stem Cell Rescue in Patients With Poor Risk Ewing's Sarcoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>City of Hope Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>City of Hope Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot clinical trial studies whole-body radiation therapy, systemic chemotherapy, and
      high-dose chemotherapy followed by stem cell rescue in treating patients with poor-risk Ewing
      sarcoma. Giving chemotherapy and radiation therapy before a peripheral blood stem cell or
      bone marrow transplant stops the growth of tumor cells by stopping them from dividing or
      killing them. After treatment, stem cells are collected from the patient's blood and stored.
      More chemotherapy is given to prepare the bone marrow for stem cell transplant. The stem
      cells are then returned to the patient to replace the blood-forming cells that were destroyed
      by the chemotherapy
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the safety and feasibility of whole-body magnetic resonance imaging
      (WB-MRI)-guided intensity modulated radiation therapy delivered concurrently with systemic
      chemotherapy to sites of metastatic disease in patients with relapsed, refractory and/or poor
      risk Ewing sarcoma.

      II. To assess the safety and feasibility of a novel consolidation regimen consisting of
      busulfan, melphalan and topotecan (topotecan hydrochloride) followed by autologous stem cell
      rescue, to be administered immediately after completion of radiation therapy in patients with
      relapsed, refractory and/or poor risk Ewing sarcoma.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To characterize the timing of myeloid and platelet engraftment.

      II. To estimate the overall and progression free survival probabilities.

      III. To estimate the cumulative incidence of relapse/progression and non-relapse related
      mortality.

      IV. To report the overall response rate (overall response rate [ORR]: complete response
      [CR]+partial response [PR]) and response duration.

      V. To descriptively compare the diagnostic imaging results (number and site of bone
      metastases) of whole-body MR imaging to those obtained by skeletal scintigraphy.

      OUTLINE:

      BLOCK I: Patients receive etoposide intravenously (IV) over 1-2 hours and ifosfamide IV over
      1 hour on days 1-5. Patients also undergo WB-MRI-guided intensity-modulated radiation therapy
      twice daily (BID), 5 days a week, for approximately 4 weeks. Patients may also undergo 4
      fractions of stereotactic radiation therapy (SRT) every other day (QOD), 3-8 fractions of
      stereotactic body radiation therapy (SBRT) QOD, or 10 fractions of 3-dimensional radiation
      therapy (3D RT) daily to sites of metastatic disease.

      BLOCK II: Patients receive high-dose chemotherapy comprising topotecan hydrochloride IV
      continuously over 24 hours on days -8 to -4, busulfan IV over 2 hours every 6 hours on days
      -8 to -4, and melphalan IV over 30 minutes on days -3 and -2. Patients undergo autologous
      peripheral blood or bone marrow stem cell infusion on day 0.

      After the stem cell infusion, patients are followed up for up to 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    No participants enrolled.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients who experience grade 4-5 non-hematologic toxicities assessed by National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 100 of Block II</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicities will be summarized as type, severity, date of onset, duration, reversibility, and attribution.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR) by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Objective tumor response for all patients will be summarized, including the number and percent responding.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from stem cell infusion to the first observation of disease progression or death from any cause, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>PFS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier product-limit method; 95% confidence intervals (CIs) will be calculated using the logit transformation and the Greenwood variance estimate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from stem cell infusion to death from any cause, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>OS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier product-limit method; 95% confidence intervals (CIs) will be calculated using the logit transformation and the Greenwood variance estimate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-relapse mortality (NRM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from stem cell infusion to death event where the cause of death is not attributable to the underlying disease, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative relapse incidence will be estimated treating non-relapse related death events as competing risks and, conversely, NRM will be calculated controlling for relapse as a competing risk. Cumulative incidence of NRM and relapse-related mortality will be calculated using the method of Goole et al. Cumulative incidence differences will be assessed by Gray's test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Supratentorial Primitive Neuroectodermal Tumor (PNET)</condition>
  <condition>Ewing Sarcoma of Bone</condition>
  <condition>Extraosseous Ewing Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Ewing Sarcoma/Peripheral Primitive Neuroectodermal Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Childhood Supratentorial Primitive Neuroectodermal Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Ewing Sarcoma/Peripheral Primitive Neuroectodermal Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Untreated Childhood Supratentorial Primitive Neuroectodermal Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (radiation therapy/chemotherapy, stem cell infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BLOCK I: Patients receive etoposide IV over 1-2 hours and ifosfamide IV over 1 hour on days 1-5. Patients also undergo WB-MRI-guided intensity-modulated radiation therapy BID, 5 days a week, for approximately 4 weeks. Patients may also undergo 4 fractions of SRT QOD, 3-8 fractions of SBRT QOD, or 10 fractions of 3D RT daily to sites of metastatic disease.
BLOCK II: Patients receive high-dose chemotherapy comprising topotecan hydrochloride IV continuously over 24 hours on days -8 to -4, busulfan IV over 2 hours every 6 hours on days -8 to -4, and melphalan IV over 30 minutes on days -3 and -2. Patients undergo autologous peripheral blood or bone marrow stem cell infusion on day 0.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>etoposide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (radiation therapy/chemotherapy, stem cell infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EPEG</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16</other_name>
    <other_name>VP-16-213</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ifosfamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (radiation therapy/chemotherapy, stem cell infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cyfos</other_name>
    <other_name>Holoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>IFF</other_name>
    <other_name>IFX</other_name>
    <other_name>IPP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>intensity-modulated radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo WB-MRI-guided IMRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (radiation therapy/chemotherapy, stem cell infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IMRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>topotecan hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (radiation therapy/chemotherapy, stem cell infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>hycamptamine</other_name>
    <other_name>Hycamtin</other_name>
    <other_name>SKF S-104864-A</other_name>
    <other_name>TOPO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>busulfan</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (radiation therapy/chemotherapy, stem cell infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BSF</other_name>
    <other_name>BU</other_name>
    <other_name>Misulfan</other_name>
    <other_name>Mitosan</other_name>
    <other_name>Myeloleukon</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>melphalan</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (radiation therapy/chemotherapy, stem cell infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alkeran</other_name>
    <other_name>CB-3025</other_name>
    <other_name>L-PAM</other_name>
    <other_name>L-phenylalanine mustard</other_name>
    <other_name>L-Sarcolysin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo autologous peripheral blood stem cell or bone marrow transplant</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (radiation therapy/chemotherapy, stem cell infusion)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>peripheral blood stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo autologous peripheral blood stem cell transplant</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (radiation therapy/chemotherapy, stem cell infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PBPC transplantation</other_name>
    <other_name>PBSC transplantation</other_name>
    <other_name>peripheral blood progenitor cell transplantation</other_name>
    <other_name>transplantation, peripheral blood stem cell</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>autologous bone marrow transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo autologous bone marrow transplant</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (radiation therapy/chemotherapy, stem cell infusion)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ABMT</other_name>
    <other_name>bone marrow transplantation, autologous</other_name>
    <other_name>transplantation, autologous bone marrow</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with relapsed Ewing's sarcoma or primitive neuroectodermal tumor (PNET) with
             bony/soft tissue metastasis who achieved at least partial response (PR) to
             chemotherapy, surgery or radiotherapy

          -  Newly diagnosed patients with metastatic disease to the bones: patients with
             metastatic Ewing's or metastatic PNET who achieved at least partial response (PR) to
             chemotherapy, surgery or radiotherapy are eligible

          -  Ewing's sarcoma/PNET histology confirmed by Anatomic Pathology Department;
             histological confirmation of relapse is highly recommended but not mandatory

          -  Patients must have documented at least partial response (PR) to previous therapy
             regimens; previous modalities may include surgery, chemotherapy, or radiation therapy;
             radiation must not include lung fields; only patients in CR or PR at the primary site
             will be eligible

          -  Patients must have metastatic/recurrent disease identified by WB-MRI at the time of
             study entry; intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) can be delivered per
             protocol guidelines to at least one but not more than five primary/metastatic sites

          -  Patients must have Karnofsky performance status &gt; 60% OR Lansky performance status &gt;
             50% for patients younger than 16 years old

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control or abstinence) prior to study entry and
             for six months following duration of study participation; should a woman become
             pregnant or suspect that she is pregnant while participating on the trial, she should
             inform her treating physician immediately

          -  Adequate number of autologous stem cells collected and cryopreserved prior to starting
             the study treatment

          -  Creatinine clearance (12 or 24 hour urine collection) or glomerular filtration rate
             (GFR) &gt; 60 ml/min/1.73 m^2

          -  Ejection fraction &gt; 50% by echocardiogram or multiple gated acquisition (MUGA)

          -  Bilirubin &lt; 2 x upper limit of normal

          -  Serum glutamic oxalo-acetic transaminase (SGOT) and serum glutamate pyruvate
             transaminase (SGPT) &lt; 5 x upper limit of normal

          -  Platelet count &gt; 50,000/ul

          -  Absolute granulocyte count &gt;= 750/ul

          -  Forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) &gt; 2 liters adults (older than 16 years)

          -  Room air arterial oxygen pressure (PaO2) &gt; 70 mm Hg adults (older than 16 years)

          -  Room air partial pressure of carbon dioxide (PaCO2) &lt; 42 mm Hg adults (older than 16
             years)

          -  Diffusion capacity of carbon monoxide (DLCO) &gt; 50% predicted

          -  If unable to cooperate with pulmonary function testing due to young age, then pulse
             oximetry &gt;= 94% children (younger than 16 years)

          -  Pretreatment tests must have been performed within 4 weeks prior to initiation of
             protocol treatment

          -  No other medical and/or psychosocial problems which, in the opinion of the primary
             physician or principal investigator, would place the patient at unacceptable risk from
             this regimen

          -  Greater than 2 week period of recovery from prior modality used to control primary or
             recurrent site

          -  All subjects or their legal guardians must have the ability to understand and the
             willingness to sign a written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients should not have any uncontrolled illness including ongoing or active
             infection

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents, concurrent biological
             agents, or chemotherapy

          -  Patients must not have received prior chemotherapy or radiation within 2 weeks before
             study enrollment, and those who have not recovered from the adverse events due to
             agents administered more than 2 weeks earlier are excluded

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated on this study

          -  Patients with other active malignancies are ineligible for this study

          -  Patients with prior treatment with myeloablative therapy are excluded

          -  Karnofsky performance status &lt; 60% or Lansky performance status &lt; 50% for patients
             younger than 16 years old

          -  Patients who require irradiation to more than 5 disease sites are excluded

          -  Subjects who, in the opinion of the investigator, may not be able to comply with the
             safety monitoring requirements of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anna Pawlowska</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>City of Hope Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 9, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma, Ewing</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroectodermal Tumors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroectodermal Tumors, Primitive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroectodermal Tumors, Primitive, Peripheral</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isophosphamide mustard</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Melphalan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Busulfan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Topotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ifosfamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

