<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01798537</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0401-12-RMB CTIL</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NIHP Israel</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01798537</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Simplified Selective Digestive Tract Decontamination for the Prevention of Intensive Care Unit Acquired Infections</brief_title>
  <acronym>SDDICU</acronym>
  <official_title>Simplified Selective Digestive Tract Decontamination for the Prevention of ICU Infections in the Setting of High-level Antibiotic Resistance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rambam Health Care Campus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rambam Health Care Campus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A simplified graded gut decontamination protocol combined with rigorous bi-weekly screening
      and appropriate bacterial prophylaxis, will lead to a 25% reduction in the acquisition of
      blood stream infections and to a 25% reduction in lower airway colonization with multi drug
      resistant organisms. There will be no concomitant rise in gram-positive or fungal infection
      or a surgency of new resistance patterns.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Simplified Selective Digestive Tract Decontamination for the prevention of ICU infections in
      a setting of high-level antibiotic resistance

      Scientific Background:

      Aerobic gram-negative bacilli (AGNB), Gram-positive bacteria and fungi are responsible for
      hospital acquired infections. This problem is especially typical in intensive care units
      (ICUs) due to the complexity of disease and wide use of invasive procedures. The common use
      of empiric wide-range antibiotic therapy had lead to the development significant resistance
      of these pathogens and this group of bacteria was defined as Multi-Drug Resistant Organisms
      (MDRO). Among these bacteria the most important and virulent are: Carbapenem Resistant
      Enterobacteriaceae (CRE), Extended Spectrum Beta Lactamases (ESBL), Methicillin Resistant
      Staphylococcus Aureus (MRSA), Vancomycin Resistant Enterococci (VRE) as well as Fluconazol
      resistant Candida.

      The main reservoir of these organisms is the intestinal tract, which raises the possibility
      that their primary eradication may lead to control of the MDRO epidemic.

      Selective Digestive tract Decontamination (SDD) has been studied extensively over the last
      10-15 years and there is a body of evidence that shows that this method can reduce acquired
      infections, bacterial drug resistance and mortality in various ICU settings. It should be
      pointed out however that many of these studies were performed in units with a low prevalence
      of infection from MDROs and that they were never performed in units were CREs are endemic.
      According to the described protocols, SDD was performed as a combination of an a oral
      antibiotic paste - Selective Oropharyngeal Decontamination (SOD) together with enteral
      medication given through a gastric feeding tube, as well as a few days of prophylactic
      intra-venous treatment with an early generation cephalosporin.

      This treatment method did not become a standard of care - mostly due to the concern that new
      resistance will develop to the prescribed enteral antibiotics, or that there will be a rise
      in the prevalence of other enteral infections as VRE, Clostridium difficile or MRSA acquired
      infections. Despite evidence that during the SDD treatment period there was actually a
      reduction of drug resistance, the Center for Disease Control and prevention (CDC) and the
      protocols of the surviving sepsis campaign do not recommend SDD as a means of coping with the
      MDRO epidemic. In published SDD protocols there was a use of wide-spectrum antibiotics that
      covered the range of gram-positive, gram-negative bacteria and fungi, without correlation to
      the results of primary screening in these patients. Even though this approach did not lead to
      a rise in bacterial resistance, it raised enough anxiety and resistance within the caregivers
      to prevent its penetration to daily use. The endemic spread of CRE infection at Rambam
      Medical Center has lead us to focus on these pathogens in our SDD program, while performing
      rigorous bi-weekly screening for all bacteria. We gave enteral antibiotic treatment (Neomycin
      + Polymixin E) targeting AGNB, and only if the primary screening found MRSA or Fungi, did we
      prescribe enteral preventive treatment against them (Vancomycin or Nystatin). Therefore, a
      prospective study was performed during 2011 at Rambam department of critical care medicine,
      on the influence of a simplified SDD protocol on the acquisition of AGNB infection in the
      ICU. The results show a significant reduction in blood stream infections and a change in the
      epidemiology of colonization of the respiratory tract - from resistant to sensitive bacteria.
      There was a concomitant reduction in the use of MDRO- targeted antibiotics.

      The proposed multi-center study is based on this successful experience and will focus on the
      influence of a simplified SDD protocol on colonization and infection with MDROs in israeli
      ICUs where CREs are endemic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Intensive care acquired infections per 1000 device days</measure>
    <time_frame>two years</time_frame>
    <description>A simplified graded SDD protocol combined with rigorous bi-weekly screening and appropriate bacterial prophylaxis, will lead to a reduction in the acquisition of central venous line blood-stream infections and to a reduction in ventilator associated pneumonia. There will be no concomitant rise in gram-positive or fungal infection or a surgency of new resistance patterns.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of SDD on the morbidity and mortality from MDRO on israeli ICU patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>two years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of SDD on bacteriological screening of Israeli ICU patients</measure>
    <time_frame>two years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2400</enrollment>
  <condition>Bacteremia Associated With Intravascular Line</condition>
  <condition>Ventilator Associated Pneumonia</condition>
  <condition>Bacteremia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neomycin Colistin Nystatin Vancomycin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participating study arm patients will receive SDD from admission to discharge according to the following plan:
ENTERAL MEDICATION (via feeding tube) x 4 times daily:
375 mg Neomycin 100 mg Colistin Sulphate
1 million units Nystatin * 250 mg Vancomycin *
Nystatin will be prescribed only if there is a positive sputum or urine culture for yeast or candida Vancomycin will be prescribed only in case of a positive screen or culture for MRSA</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No SDD given for 1 year Screening performed as in intervention arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neomycin Colistin Nystatin Vancomycin</intervention_name>
    <description>All participating study arm patients will receive SDD from admission to discharge</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neomycin Colistin Nystatin Vancomycin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>375 mg Neomycin</other_name>
    <other_name>100 mg Colistin Sulphate</other_name>
    <other_name>1 million units Nystatin *</other_name>
    <other_name>250 mg Vancomycin *</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Expected to be in the ICU &gt; 72 hours

          2. Has an enteral feeding tube and can receive enteral medication

          3. Has a tracheal tube

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pt. is moribund - not expected to survive &gt; 28 days

          2. Pt. or legal representative refuse to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yaron P Bar-Lavie, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Rambam Health Care Campus, Haifa, Israel</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mical Paul, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rambam Health Care Campus, Haifa, Israel</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yaron P Bar-Lavie, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>++972-50-206-2027</phone>
    <email>y_barlavie@rambam.health.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mical Paul, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>++972-50-206-2140</phone>
    <email>m_paul@rambam.health.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rambam Health Care Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haifa</city>
        <zip>31096</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yaron P Bar-Lavie, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>++972-50-206-2027</phone>
      <email>y_barlavie@rambam.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mical Paul, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>++972-50-206-2140</phone>
      <email>m_paul@rambam.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yaron P Bar-Lavie, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mical Paul, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Jonge E, Schultz MJ, Spanjaard L, Bossuyt PM, Vroom MB, Dankert J, Kesecioglu J. Effects of selective decontamination of digestive tract on mortality and acquisition of resistant bacteria in intensive care: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2003 Sep 27;362(9389):1011-6.</citation>
    <PMID>14522530</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Smet AM, Kluytmans JA, Cooper BS, Mascini EM, Benus RF, van der Werf TS, van der Hoeven JG, Pickkers P, Bogaers-Hofman D, van der Meer NJ, Bernards AT, Kuijper EJ, Joore JC, Leverstein-van Hall MA, Bindels AJ, Jansz AR, Wesselink RM, de Jongh BM, Dennesen PJ, van Asselt GJ, te Velde LF, Frenay IH, Kaasjager K, Bosch FH, van Iterson M, Thijsen SF, Kluge GH, Pauw W, de Vries JW, Kaan JA, Arends JP, Aarts LP, Sturm PD, Harinck HI, Voss A, Uijtendaal EV, Blok HE, Thieme Groen ES, Pouw ME, Kalkman CJ, Bonten MJ. Decontamination of the digestive tract and oropharynx in ICU patients. N Engl J Med. 2009 Jan 1;360(1):20-31. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0800394.</citation>
    <PMID>19118302</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Smet AM, Kluytmans JA, Blok HE, Mascini EM, Benus RF, Bernards AT, Kuijper EJ, Leverstein-van Hall MA, Jansz AR, de Jongh BM, van Asselt GJ, Frenay IH, Thijsen SF, Conijn SN, Kaan JA, Arends JP, Sturm PD, Bootsma MC, Bonten MJ. Selective digestive tract decontamination and selective oropharyngeal decontamination and antibiotic resistance in patients in intensive-care units: an open-label, clustered group-randomised, crossover study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2011 May;11(5):372-80. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(11)70035-4. Epub 2011 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21420908</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schultz MJ, Haas LE. Antibiotics or probiotics as preventive measures against ventilator-associated pneumonia: a literature review. Crit Care. 2011;15(1):R18. doi: 10.1186/cc9963. Epub 2011 Jan 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21232110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Saene HK, Petros AJ, Ramsay G, Baxby D. All great truths are iconoclastic: selective decontamination of the digestive tract moves from heresy to level 1 truth. Intensive Care Med. 2003 May;29(5):677-90. Epub 2003 Apr 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12687326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silvestri L, van Saene HK, Milanese M, Gregori D, Gullo A. Selective decontamination of the digestive tract reduces bacterial bloodstream infection and mortality in critically ill patients. Systematic review of randomized, controlled trials. J Hosp Infect. 2007 Mar;65(3):187-203. Epub 2007 Jan 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17244516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 26, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 26, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bacteremia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia, Ventilator-Associated</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vancomycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colistin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nystatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neomycin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

