<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01793350</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BC-222</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01793350</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy Study of BC-DN-01 in Painful Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Combined Phase 1 + 2 Clinical Trial Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of BC-DN-01 in the Treatment of Painful Diabetic Peripheral Neuropathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>BioChemics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Harrison Clinical Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>BioChemics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A combined Phase 1 &amp; 2 study to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of a new diabetic
      neuropathy topical cream, containing benfotiamine, will be performed at 5 clinical sites and
      plans for BC-DN-01 administration in up to 135 volunteer patients using a standard Phase 1 +
      2 design. Up to 15 subjects will receive BC-DN-01 in Study Phase 1 and up to 120 subjects
      will receive BC-DN-01 or placebo in Study Phase 2.

      In Phase 1, a BC-DN-01 dose delivering 160mg benfotiamine/day (80mg twice daily) will be
      administered for the first 7 days. On visit day 0, patients will commence study treatment.
      Patients will be interviewed by phone on day 3 and return to clinic on day 7 for safety
      assessments. If the drug is well-tolerated and no significant adverse events experienced, the
      total daily BC-DN-01 dose will be increased on days 7-14 to 320mg benfotiamine/day (160mg
      b.i.d.). Patients will be interviewed by telephone on day 10 and return to clinic on day 14
      for safety assessments.

      Once the safety profile has been determined in Phase 1 as acceptable, the Phase 2 study will
      be initiated to evaluate clinical efficacy of BC-DN-01. Phase 2 is a randomized,
      placebo-controlled, double-blind, parallel study. Participants receive placebo or BC-DN-01
      based on 1:1 randomization. Each patient will apply 4g of the study medication to each leg
      twice-a-day administering 320mg benfotiamine dose/day for 12 weeks.

      Participants will be evaluated in the clinic at baseline and at 4, 8, and 12-week time
      points; study staff will interview the patients by telephone on weeks 2, 6, and 10.

      The primary endpoint of the phase 2 trial is reduction in DPN pain measured by the Brief Pain
      Inventory. Phase 2 patients will be invited to give written consent to take part in biopsy
      sampling and additional gene expression analysis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be performed at 5 clinical sites and plans for BC-DN-01 administration in up
      to 135 volunteer patients using a standard Phase 1 + 2 design. Based on conservative but
      approximate drop-out estimates of 20% in Study Phase 1 and 30% in Study Phase 2, up to 15
      subjects will receive BC-DN-01 in Study Phase 1 and up to 120 subjects will receive either
      BC-DN-01 or placebo in Study Phase 2. It is anticipated that the enrolment of 135 subjects
      will allow for 12 and 84 evaluable in Study Parts 1 and 2, respectively.

      Patient screening for study eligibility, randomisation, treatment administration, and safety
      and efficacy evaluations will be conducted at clinic visits in a qualified clinical research
      facility. It is anticipated that up to fifteen patients will be enrolled in the Phase 1
      portion of the study intended to evaluate the safety and tolerability of daily, escalating
      doses of BC-DN-01 for two weeks. This portion of the study is not blinded and non-randomized.
      Upon completion of Phase 1, results will be used for the decision to initiate the Phase 2
      portion of the study. It is anticipated that up to one hundred twenty (120) patients will be
      enrolled in Phase 2 and randomized to receive either placebo or a fixed BC-DN-01 dose for
      twelve weeks. Phase 2 will be double-blind to minimize bias.

      All clinical safety measurements, observations, reported adverse symptoms, and laboratory
      safety data for each patient will be reviewed and clinically relevant findings reported to
      the Data Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB) at the end of the Phase 1 and the end of the Phase 2
      trials. The decision to continue trial conduct will be made by BioChemics, Inc., and may be
      based on recommendations provided by a study continuation/study termination opinion by the
      DSMB. At no time will individual patient data or commentary thereon, from the blinded Phase 2
      portion of the trial be shared by the DSMB with BioChemics, Inc. personnel or their study
      conduct partners.

      This study is not formally powered to test a statistical hypothesis. The primary objective is
      to determine the magnitude of pain relief following a daily administration of 16g BC-DN-01
      (320mg benfotiamine) compared to Placebo (Phase 2). This value will be used to determine the
      sample size needed in future clinical trials to ensure adequate analytical power to
      demonstrate efficacy.

      Phase 1

      Patients considered eligible for enrolment to the phase 1 study will be required to comply
      will all of the inclusion and exclusion criteria, including:

        -  Consented to phase 1 trial participation

        -  Met the protocol criteria for inclusion and exclusion (except inc criterion #8, #9 and
           exc criteria #3))

        -  Have not taken neuropathy pain medication for at least 2 weeks

      Visit 1 (Screening) After providing written informed consent patients will undergo a physical
      examination, including leg and feet assessment, vital signs measured and safety blood samples
      taken including serum pregnancy test for women of child bearing potential.

      Visit 2 (Baseline - Day 0) Patients will undergo a physical examination, including leg and
      feet assessment, vital signs measured and safety blood samples taken including urine
      pregnancy test for women of child bearing potential.

      Patients will be dispensed BC-DN-01 study medication to provide 1 week of treatment, of 2g
      doses per leg, twice daily giving a total dose of 160mg benfotiamine/day (80mg b.i.d.). The
      first dose will be given by the study nurse, to demonstrate the correct way to apply the
      cream.

      If the drug is well-tolerated and no significant adverse events are experienced, the total
      daily body BC-DN-01 dose will be increased following the clinic visit on day 7 (with the
      first increased dose of 160mg being applied on the evening of day 7)and then twice daily up
      to day 14, to 320mg benfotiamine/day (160mg b.i.d.).

      Visit 3 (Day 7) Patients will undergo a leg and feet assessment, vital signs measured and
      safety blood samples taken including urine pregnancy test for women of child bearing
      potential.

      Patients will be dispensed BC-DN-01 study medication to provide 1 week of treatment, of 4g
      doses per leg, twice daily.

      Visit 4 (Day 14) Patients will undergo a physical examination, including leg and feet
      assessment, vital signs measured and safety blood samples taken including urine pregnancy
      test for women of child bearing potential. Patients will be contacted on days 3, 10 and 21-28
      by telephone to be interviewed to discuss the medication, general health and any adverse
      events since the last clinic visit.

      Phase 2

      Once the safety profile has been determined in Phase 1 and considered acceptable, the Phase 2
      study will be initiated to evaluate clinical efficacy of BC-DN-01. Patients participating in
      the Phase 1 safety evaluation may also participate in the randomised Phase 2 portion of the
      trial, at least four (4) months after completing the phase 1 trial. At that time, those
      patients, will be required to comply will all of the inclusion and exclusion criteria,
      including:

        -  Consented to phase 2 trial participation

        -  Met the protocol criteria for inclusion and exclusion

        -  Have not taken neuropathy pain medication for at least 2 weeks

      Phase 2 is a randomised, placebo-controlled, double-blind, parallel study in up to 120
      patients. Study participants will receive either placebo or BC-DN-01 based on 1:1
      randomisation (at least 42 evaluable patients per treatment arm). Each volunteer patient will
      apply 4g of the study medication to each leg twice-a-day administering 320mg benfotiamine
      dose/day for 12 weeks.

      The primary endpoint of the phase 2 trial is the reduction in pain level associated with DPN
      as measured by the Brief Pain Inventory (BPI). The duration of pain reduction will also be
      assessed.

      The secondary efficacy endpoints include the evaluation of Sural and Peroneal motor nerve
      conduction velocities, Neuropathy Symptom Score, Neuropathy Disability Score, ,
      Intra-epidermal nerve fibre density in the legs of these patients, hyperaesthesia and changes
      in lack of sensation in the leg and foot. Xerosis and changes in diabetes-related skin
      pathology, such as infiltration by inflammatory cells and mast cell degranulation as well as
      changes in the gene expression profiles of these tissues will also be assessed.

      Visit 1 (Screening) After providing written informed consent patients will undergo a physical
      examination, including leg and feet assessment, vital signs measured and safety blood samples
      taken including serum pregnancy test for women of child bearing potential.

      Visit 2 (Baseline - Day 0) Patients will undergo a physical examination, including leg and
      feet assessment, vital signs measured and safety blood samples taken including urine
      pregnancy test for women of child bearing potential.

      Patients will be randomised to a 50:50 BC-DN-01:placebo arm and dispensed study medication to
      provide 4 weeks of treatment, of 4g doses per leg, twice daily giving the equivalent total
      dose of 320mg benfotiamine/day (80mg b.i.d.). The first dose of study medication will be
      given by the study nurse, to demonstrate the correct way to apply the cream.

      Visits 3 (Week 4) 4 (Week 8) and 5 (Week 12) Patients will undergo a leg and feet assessment,
      vital signs measured and safety blood samples taken including urine pregnancy test for women
      of child bearing potential.

      Patients will be asked to complete questionnaires regarding DPN pain, sensory tests and
      visual assessments of the skin on your legs and feet will be made Patients will undergo a
      nerve conduction velocity test, which tests how fast electrical signals move through the
      nerves on the leg.

      Patients will be contacted on weeks 2, 6, 10 and 14 by telephone to be interviewed to discuss
      the medication, general health and any adverse events since the last clinic visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of BC-DN-01</measure>
    <time_frame>120 days</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective of this study is to assess the magnitude and duration of pain relief resulting from a fixed dose of BC-DN-01, compared to placebo, in patients with painful DPN as measured by the Brief Pain Inventory (BPI).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of BC-DN-01</measure>
    <time_frame>120 days</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary objectives for this study include assessing the safety and tolerability of 160mg b.i.d. of benfotiamine and determining the number of participants with adverse events as a measure of safety and tolerability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Neuropathy, Painful</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BC-DN-01 topically applied cream, DPN</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>4g topically applied BC-DN-01 cream applied twice daily to each leg and foot, for 12 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo topically applied cream, DPN</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>4g topically applied cream applied twice daily to each leg and foot, for 12 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BC-DN-01 topically applied cream</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase 1 - week 1 - total daily dose 160mg benfotiamine as 8g BC-DN-01 Phase 1 - week 2 - total daily dose 320mg benfotiamine as 16g BC-DN-01 Phase 2 - for 12 weeks - total daily dose 320mg benfotiamine as 16g BC-DN-01</description>
    <arm_group_label>BC-DN-01 topically applied cream, DPN</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>active ingredient of BC-DN-01 : benfotiamine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Current diagnosis of Type I or II diabetes mellitus according to the American Diabetes
             Association Criteria of FPG≥ 7.0 mmol/l (126 mg/dl)

          2. A current or historical reading of HbA1c 6.5-11%, using a test performed in a clinical
             laboratory using a method that is NGSP certified and standardised to the DCCT assay.

          3. Ability to understand the nature of the trial and willingness to participate,
             documented by written informed consent.

          4. Willingness and ability to comply with the study protocol requirements for the
             duration of the study.

          5. Males and females of any ethnic origin and ≥18 years of age.

          6. Negative serum pregnancy test at screening and a negative urine pregnancy test at
             randomisation, for women of childbearing potential only and assurance from the patient
             (males and females) of using satisfactory contraception methods (refer to section
             4.9.6).

          7. If on anti-diabetic medication, must have been on a stable therapeutic regimen for at
             least 30 days prior to randomisation.

          8. Phase 2 - Peroneal Motor Nerve Conduction Velocity measurements 30-40 m/s. indicating
             a mild to moderate case of diabetic peripheral neuropathy

          9. Phase 2 - Scores on the Brief Pain Inventory of ≥4.

         10. An ability to apply topical medication to both legs from the knee to the toes, either
             by themselves or have a documentation of an assistant or partner to help with the
             administration of the trial drug product twice a day for the 12-week treatment period.

         11. Patient must be willing to sign a Consent form to participate in this clinical trial.

         12. Patient must be willing to sign a consent form to be sent to their primary physician
             to inform that the patient will stop taking disallowed concomitant medications
             prescribed by the physician.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participation in any investigational drug study within 4 months preceding
             randomisation of this study.

          2. Pregnancy, lactation, fertility without adequate protection against pregnancy (refer
             to section 4.9.6).

               1. A serum pregnancy test will be performed for women of childbearing potential with
                  the haematological and clinical chemistry evaluations at screening and a urine
                  pregnancy test immediately prior to randomisation.

               2. If the patient becomes pregnant during the study, the patient's participation in
                  the remainder of the study will be terminated.

          3. Phase 2 - Severe neuropathy (PMNCV &lt; 30 m/s, prior amputations at the foot level and
             Charcot disease).

          4. Current severe peripheral arterial disease requiring surgical intervention (however
             patients with previous successful intervention 12 weeks or more prior to randomisation
             will be eligible for the study (See Section 4.2.2.1 Peripheral Arterial Disease
             Determination).

          5. End stage renal failure requiring dialysis or renal transplantation and patients who
             are expected to receive dialysis or transplantation in the near future should be
             excluded from the study.

          6. Presence of any serious disease, including those of hepatic, hematologic, neurologic,
             or immune origin or an active malignant disease, which in the opinion of the
             investigator would affect response to pain relief treatment.

          7. Presence of peripheral pain not associated with DPN, mono-neuropathies or proximal
             neuropathies, or central pain, which in the opinion of the investigator would affect
             response to pain relief treatment.

          8. Presence of a medical condition diagnosed with other known causes of non-Diabetic
             Peripheral Neuropathy.

          9. Known to be currently abusing alcohol or drugs.

         10. Presence of acute skin disease or infection such as erysipelas and vasculitis of the
             lower extremities.

         11. Current oral or topical use of benfotiamine or BC-DN-01 products.

         12. Hypersensitivity to benfotiamine or any component of BC-DN-01.

         13. Concurrent administration or use of Lyrica, Cymbalta, or capsaicin use within the 2
             weeks prior to randomisation (see Appendix 12.3 for full list of disallowed
             concomitant medications).

         14. Any factors which, in the opinion of the investigator, will affect the patient's
             ability to safely participate in the study and meet study objectives.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Solomon Tesfaye, MD, FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Royal Hallamshire Hospital, Sheffield, England</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Hallamshire Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sheffield</city>
        <state>South Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>S10 2JF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ipswich Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ipswich</city>
        <state>Suffolk</state>
        <zip>IP4 5PD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Birmingham Heartlands Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>West Midlands</state>
        <zip>B9 5SS</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MAC Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M32 0UT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Manchester Royal Infirmary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 5, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 15, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 25, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Painful</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Peripheral</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Neuropathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Benphothiamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

