<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01797731</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10137</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01797731</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Conventional Alignment System Versus Surgical Navigation System in Total Knee Arthroplasty</brief_title>
  <official_title>Conventional Tibial Extramedullary Alignment System Versus a Hand-Held, Surgical Navigation System for Tibial Component Placement in Total Knee Arthroplasty: A Randomized, Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital for Special Surgery, New York</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital for Special Surgery, New York</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, controlled, blinded prospective study comparing the use of the usual
      cutting guides with a palm-sized digital surgical navigation system in unilateral total knee
      arthroplasty. Analysis of pre- and post-operative X-rays will be used to compare alignment of
      the tibial (shinbone) implant components. The investigators expect that the FDA-approved
      hand-held surgical navigation device will increase the accuracy and precision of the tibial
      cut by telling the surgeon the exact position of the cutting block before the surgeon makes
      the cut, allowing minor adjustments to be made. The investigators expect the conventional
      device to take less time to use, but that this difference will decrease as the surgeon
      becomes more familiar with the device. The investigators expect the intraoperative
      measurements acquired by the KneeAlign system to strongly correlate with the radiographic
      alignments measured postoperatively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Medical records, private office charts, and electronic medical records will be utilized by
      the co-investigators to review data on patients who fit the previously stated inclusion
      criteria. Demographic data including age, gender, height (cm), and weight (kg) will be
      collected. Preoperative, standing anteroposterior hip-to-ankle radiographs will be measured
      for the lower extremity mechanical axis, the tibiofemoral anatomic alignment, and the distal
      femoral and proximal tibial anatomic angles. Intraoperative time measurements for use of both
      the conventional extramedullary alignment guide, and the KneeAlignTM system will be measured
      and recorded. The time required to utilize each alignment guide will be measured in seconds,
      starting from the time at which the surgeon is handed the alignment guide (KneeAlignTM or
      conventional, extramedullary), to the time at which the surgeon is handed the oscillating saw
      to make the tibial cut. Of note, no intraoperative alignment measurements are required or
      will be recorded for the conventional, extramedullary systems, while intraoperative
      alignments reported by the KneeAlignTM system will be recorded when the KneeAlignTM device is
      used. In addition, regarding the use of conventional, extramedullary tibial guides, each
      surgeon will utilize the guide (regardless of manufacturer) which they currently use most
      frequently when performing a total knee arthroplasty. While there may be minimal differences
      with regards each of the surgeon's conventional guides, they are all essentially the same
      with regards to utilizing an extramedullary rod for alignment of the tibial resection.

      Currently, a total knee replacement requires an average tourniquet time of 30-50 minutes
      depending on the surgeon. We estimate an approximate increase in total tourniquet time of 5-6
      minutes when using the hand-held surgical navigation system.

      For each procedure (either KneeAlignTM or conventional, extramedullary guides), after making
      the initial cut, if at any point in the procedure the surgeon re-cuts the tibia, they will be
      asked a series of questions postoperatively as to why they re-cut the tibia as part of the
      data collection. These questions will include:

        1. Did you re-cut the tibia because you thought more varus or valgus was required?

        2. Did you re-cut the tibia to increase or decrease the posterior slope?

        3. Did you re-cut the tibia to increase the amount of bone resected?

        4. Were you happy with the overall tibial alignment? Postoperative radiographs will be
           obtained as part of each surgeon's postoperative protocol, and will include a standing
           anteroposterior hip-to-ankle radiograph and a standing lateral knee-to-ankle radiograph,
           from which the lower extremity mechanical axis, the tibiofemoral anatomic alignment, the
           tibial component mechanical alignment, and the tibial component posterior slope will be
           measured.

      This study has the potential to provide significant information regarding the clinical
      accuracy and precision of the KneeAlignTM system compared to that of conventional,
      extramedullary alignment systems. If mechanical and tibial mechanical alignment is
      significantly improved with the use of the KneeAlignTM system, this may encourage surgeons to
      utilize this device to improve postoperative alignment in total knee arthroplasty. In
      addition, surgeon's may find this type of hand-held system more user-friendly (in contrast to
      a large console, computer-assisted surgical system), and this may stimulate future
      investigations into similar devices for femoral component alignment, and also total hip
      arthroplasty.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 16, 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative Tibial Component Alignment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome will be the number of patients (percentage of patients) that met a predetermined criteria for Alignment as defined by within 2° of perpendicular to the tibial mechanical axis or 2° of a 3° posterior slope, postoperative tibial component alignment (mechanical varus/valgus, and posterior slope) as measured on postoperative standing anteroposterior hip-to-ankle radiographs, and standing, lateral knee-to-ankle radiographs, respectively.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time Required to Utilize System</measure>
    <time_frame>Minutes during surgery ( Estimated time per surgery 1 hour)</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of time required to utilize conventional, tibial extramedullary alignment guides versus the KneeAlignTM system, which will be recorded intraoperatively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system used by surgeon during surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>KneeAlign System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Digital hand-held surgical navigation system for tibial component placement used by surgeon during surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Digital hand-held surgical navigation system</intervention_name>
    <description>Digital hand-held surgical navigation system used for tibial component placement in total knee arthroplasty</description>
    <arm_group_label>KneeAlign System</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>KneeAlign</other_name>
    <other_name>OrthAlign</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system</intervention_name>
    <description>This is the standard of care for total knee arthroplasty.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional System</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  a history of osteoarthritis, rheumatoid arthritis, or post-traumatic arthritis

          -  patients who have been indicated for a primary, posterior-stabilized, total knee
             arthroplasty

          -  patients have had a preoperative standing anteroposterior hip-to-ankle radiograph and
             standing lateral knee-to-ankle radiographs

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with proximal tibial defects requiring either a metal or allograft augment

          -  inadequate radiographic studies as required by the study protocol

          -  if they do not receive a total knee arthroplasty, or receive a unicondylar
             arthroplasty
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Mayman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital for Special Surgery, New York</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital for Special Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nam D, Weeks KD, Reinhardt KR, Nawabi DH, Cross MB, Mayman DJ. Accelerometer-based, portable navigation vs imageless, large-console computer-assisted navigation in total knee arthroplasty: a comparison of radiographic results. J Arthroplasty. 2013 Feb;28(2):255-61. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2012.04.023. Epub 2012 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>22704226</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nam D, Jerabek SA, Cross MB, Mayman DJ. Cadaveric analysis of an accelerometer-based portable navigation device for distal femoral cutting block alignment in total knee arthroplasty. Comput Aided Surg. 2012;17(4):205-10. doi: 10.3109/10929088.2012.689335. Epub 2012 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22681247</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nam D, Nawabi DH, Cross MB, Heyse TJ, Mayman DJ. Accelerometer-based computer navigation for performing the distal femoral resection in total knee arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2012 Oct;27(9):1717-22. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2012.02.007. Epub 2012 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22440228</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nam D, Dy CJ, Cross MB, Kang MN, Mayman DJ. Cadaveric results of an accelerometer based, extramedullary navigation system for the tibial resection in total knee arthroplasty. Knee. 2012 Oct;19(5):617-21. doi: 10.1016/j.knee.2011.09.008. Epub 2011 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22032868</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nam D, Jerabek SA, Haughom B, Cross MB, Reinhardt KR, Mayman DJ. Radiographic analysis of a hand-held surgical navigation system for tibial resection in total knee arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2011 Dec;26(8):1527-33. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2011.01.012. Epub 2011 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21397455</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 21, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 22, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>March 28, 2017</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2017</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Orthalign</keyword>
  <keyword>KneeAlign</keyword>
  <keyword>Total Knee Replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>Total Knee Arthroplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>Degenerative joint disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Unilateral</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Conventional System</title>
          <description>Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system used by surgeon during surgery.
Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system: This is the standard of care for total knee arthroplasty.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>KneeAlign System</title>
          <description>Digital hand-held surgical navigation system for tibial component placement used by surgeon during surgery.
Digital hand-held surgical navigation system: Digital hand-held surgical navigation system used for tibial component placement in total knee arthroplasty</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="50"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="50"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="47">3 were excluded due to not having proper radiographs for adequate follow up</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="47">3 excluded due to not having proper radiographs for adequate follow up</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Didn't have proper radiographs required</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <population>A sample size of 47 patients in each cohort would provide appropriate power (beta level = 0.80, alpha level = 0.05) to detect a 20% improvement in accuracy between the two groups (i.e. a 20% decrease or increase in the number of “outliers”).</population>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Conventional System</title>
          <description>Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system used by surgeon during surgery.
Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system: This is the standard of care for total knee arthroplasty.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>KneeAlign System</title>
          <description>Digital hand-held surgical navigation system for tibial component placement used by surgeon during surgery.
Digital hand-held surgical navigation system: Digital hand-held surgical navigation system used for tibial component placement in total knee arthroplasty</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="47"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="47"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="94"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="27"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="17"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="44"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="30"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="50"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="66.1" spread="10.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="67.1" spread="7.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="66.12" spread="10.66"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="29"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="49"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="27"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="18"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="45"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Postoperative Tibial Component Alignment</title>
        <description>The primary outcome will be the number of patients (percentage of patients) that met a predetermined criteria for Alignment as defined by within 2° of perpendicular to the tibial mechanical axis or 2° of a 3° posterior slope, postoperative tibial component alignment (mechanical varus/valgus, and posterior slope) as measured on postoperative standing anteroposterior hip-to-ankle radiographs, and standing, lateral knee-to-ankle radiographs, respectively.</description>
        <time_frame>6 weeks after surgery</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Conventional System</title>
            <description>Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system used by surgeon during surgery.
Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system: This is the standard of care for total knee arthroplasty.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>KneeAlign System</title>
            <description>Digital hand-held surgical navigation system for tibial component placement used by surgeon during surgery.
Digital hand-held surgical navigation system: Digital hand-held surgical navigation system used for tibial component placement in total knee arthroplasty</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Postoperative Tibial Component Alignment</title>
          <description>The primary outcome will be the number of patients (percentage of patients) that met a predetermined criteria for Alignment as defined by within 2° of perpendicular to the tibial mechanical axis or 2° of a 3° posterior slope, postoperative tibial component alignment (mechanical varus/valgus, and posterior slope) as measured on postoperative standing anteroposterior hip-to-ankle radiographs, and standing, lateral knee-to-ankle radiographs, respectively.</description>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="47"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="47"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="68.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="95.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Time Required to Utilize System</title>
        <description>The amount of time required to utilize conventional, tibial extramedullary alignment guides versus the KneeAlignTM system, which will be recorded intraoperatively.</description>
        <time_frame>Minutes during surgery ( Estimated time per surgery 1 hour)</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Conventional System</title>
            <description>Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system used by surgeon during surgery.
Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system: This is the standard of care for total knee arthroplasty.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>KneeAlign System</title>
            <description>Digital hand-held surgical navigation system for tibial component placement used by surgeon during surgery.
Digital hand-held surgical navigation system: Digital hand-held surgical navigation system used for tibial component placement in total knee arthroplasty</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time Required to Utilize System</title>
          <description>The amount of time required to utilize conventional, tibial extramedullary alignment guides versus the KneeAlignTM system, which will be recorded intraoperatively.</description>
          <units>seconds</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="50"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="50"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="289.92" spread="125.34"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="70.58" spread="28.14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Conventional System</title>
          <description>Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system used by surgeon during surgery.
Conventional tibial extramedullary alignment system: This is the standard of care for total knee arthroplasty.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>KneeAlign System</title>
          <description>Digital hand-held surgical navigation system for tibial component placement used by surgeon during surgery.
Digital hand-held surgical navigation system: Digital hand-held surgical navigation system used for tibial component placement in total knee arthroplasty</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="47"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="47"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="47"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="47"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="47"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="47"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>David Mayman</name_or_title>
      <organization>Hospital for Special Surgery</organization>
      <phone>2127742024</phone>
      <email>maymand@hss.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

