<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00136721</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>9HD01H</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01NS041723-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00136721</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Parkin Mutations and Their Functional Consequences</brief_title>
  <official_title>Parkin Mutations and Their Functional Consequences</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease (PD) is the most frequent neurodegenerative disease with a prevalence of
      2% over 65 years and because of this high prevalence as the population ages, it is a major
      problem of public health.

      An exhaustive repertory of not only parkin mutations in autosomal recessive forms of PD but
      also in other known genes such as DJ-1, PINK1 and LRRK2, is of major importance for both
      genetic counseling in families affected with PD and physiopathological approaches to this
      disease.

      Through a French network for the study of Parkinson's disease genetics and extended
      collaborations with European, Mediterranean and other various countries, a total of 2934
      subjects including 1683 patients and 1251 unaffected individuals has been collected since
      2002. These samples consisted of 122 families with autosomal recessive PD, 285 cases of
      isolated early onset PD, 110 autosomal recessive and 129 autosomal dominant families with
      late onset PD, 201 isolated late onset PD cases and 250 matched controls.

      DNAs from all subjects are now available, lymphocytes and lymphoblastoid cell lines have been
      stored for most patients from France and recently, fresh fibroblasts have been obtained for
      some individuals.

      The genetic approach to autosomal recessive PD is focused on the identification of mutations
      in the parkin gene but also on the screening of DJ-1, PINK1 and LRRK2 genes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>June 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>May 2006</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>2500</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients presenting with Parkinson's disease, with a family history or not,

          -  Minors presenting clinical signs of the disease,

          -  Controls (without signs of the disease, matched by sex and age with the patients,
             relatives for the familial cases)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Persons refusing to sign the informed consent,

          -  Lack of clinical information
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexis Brice, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris, University Paris 6</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Pitié-Salpêtrière</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75013</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.inserm.fr</url>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rawal N, Periquet M, Lohmann E, Lücking CB, Teive HA, Ambrosio G, Raskin S, Lincoln S, Hattori N, Guimaraes J, Horstink MW, Dos Santos Bele W, Brousolle E, Destée A, Mizuno Y, Farrer M, Deleuze JF, De Michele G, Agid Y, Dürr A, Brice A; French Parkinson's Disease Genetics Study Group; European Consortium on Genetic Susceptibility in Parkinson's Disease. New parkin mutations and atypical phenotypes in families with autosomal recessive parkinsonism. Neurology. 2003 Apr 22;60(8):1378-81.</citation>
    <PMID>12707451</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Periquet M, Latouche M, Lohmann E, Rawal N, De Michele G, Ricard S, Teive H, Fraix V, Vidailhet M, Nicholl D, Barone P, Wood NW, Raskin S, Deleuze JF, Agid Y, Dürr A, Brice A; French Parkinson's Disease Genetics Study Group; European Consortium on Genetic Susceptibility in Parkinson's Disease. Parkin mutations are frequent in patients with isolated early-onset parkinsonism. Brain. 2003 Jun;126(Pt 6):1271-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12764050</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ibáñez P, Lohmann E, Pollak P, Durif F, Tranchant C, Agid Y, Dürr A, Brice A; French Parkinson's Disease Genetics Study Group. Absence of NR4A2 exon 1 mutations in 108 families with autosomal dominant Parkinson disease. Neurology. 2004 Jun 8;62(11):2133-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15184637</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ibáñez P, De Michele G, Bonifati V, Lohmann E, Thobois S, Pollak P, Agid Y, Heutink P, Dürr A, Brice A; French Parkinson's Disease Genetics Study Group. Screening for DJ-1 mutations in early onset autosomal recessive parkinsonism. Neurology. 2003 Nov 25;61(10):1429-31.</citation>
    <PMID>14638971</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lücking CB, Chesneau V, Lohmann E, Verpillat P, Dulac C, Bonnet AM, Gasparini F, Agid Y, Dürr A, Brice A. Coding polymorphisms in the parkin gene and susceptibility to Parkinson disease. Arch Neurol. 2003 Sep;60(9):1253-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12975291</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lohmann E, Periquet M, Bonifati V, Wood NW, De Michele G, Bonnet AM, Fraix V, Broussolle E, Horstink MW, Vidailhet M, Verpillat P, Gasser T, Nicholl D, Teive H, Raskin S, Rascol O, Destée A, Ruberg M, Gasparini F, Meco G, Agid Y, Durr A, Brice A; French Parkinson's Disease Genetics Study Group; European Consortium on Genetic Susceptibility in Parkinson's Disease. How much phenotypic variation can be attributed to parkin genotype? Ann Neurol. 2003 Aug;54(2):176-85.</citation>
    <PMID>12891670</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lesage S, Dürr A, Tazir M, Lohmann E, Leutenegger AL, Janin S, Pollak P, Brice A; French Parkinson's Disease Genetics Study Group. LRRK2 G2019S as a cause of Parkinson's disease in North African Arabs. N Engl J Med. 2006 Jan 26;354(4):422-3.</citation>
    <PMID>16436781</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ibáñez P, Lesage S, Lohmann E, Thobois S, De Michele G, Borg M, Agid Y, Dürr A, Brice A; French Parkinson's Disease Genetics Study Group. Mutational analysis of the PINK1 gene in early-onset parkinsonism in Europe and North Africa. Brain. 2006 Mar;129(Pt 3):686-94. Epub 2006 Jan 9.</citation>
    <PMID>16401616</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lesage S, Janin S, Lohmann E, Leutenegger AL, Leclere L, Viallet F, Pollak P, Durif F, Thobois S, Layet V, Vidailhet M, Agid Y, Dürr A, Brice A; French Parkinson's Disease Genetics Study Group, Bonnet AM, Borg M, Broussolle E, Damier P, Destée A, Martinez M, Penet C, Rasco O, Tison F, Tranchan C, Vérin M. LRRK2 exon 41 mutations in sporadic Parkinson disease in Europeans. Arch Neurol. 2007 Mar;64(3):425-30.</citation>
    <PMID>17353388</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Leutenegger AL, Salih MA, Ibáñez P, Mukhtar MM, Lesage S, Arabi A, Lohmann E, Dürr A, Ahmed AE, Brice A. Juvenile-onset Parkinsonism as a result of the first mutation in the adenosine triphosphate orientation domain of PINK1. Arch Neurol. 2006 Sep;63(9):1257-61.</citation>
    <PMID>16966503</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lesage S, Magali P, Lohmann E, Lacomblez L, Teive H, Janin S, Cousin PY, Dürr A, Brice A; French Parkinson Disease Genetics Study Group. Deletion of the parkin and PACRG gene promoter in early-onset parkinsonism. Hum Mutat. 2007 Jan;28(1):27-32.</citation>
    <PMID>17068781</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brice A, Lohmann E, Ibanez P, Periquet M, Laine S, Debarges B, Lesage S, Dürr A. Phenotype/genotype correlations in Parkinson's disease. In: Relationships in Neurodegenerative Diseases, Cummings, Hardy, Poncet and Christen (Eds), Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg Eds, 153-64, 2005.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lohmann E, Dürr A, Ruberg M, Brice A. Parkin. In: Parkinson's Disease: Genetic and Pathogenesis, Dawson Eds, in press, 2006.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brice A. [What can we learn from genes responsible for familial forms of Parkinson's disease?]. Bull Acad Natl Med. 2006 Feb;190(2):485-96; discussion 497-8. Review. French.</citation>
    <PMID>17001874</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ishihara L, Warren L, Gibson R, Amouri R, Lesage S, Dürr A, Tazir M, Wszolek ZK, Uitti RJ, Nichols WC, Griffith A, Hattori N, Leppert D, Watts R, Zabetian CP, Foroud TM, Farrer MJ, Brice A, Middleton L, Hentati F. Clinical features of Parkinson disease patients with homozygous leucine-rich repeat kinase 2 G2019S mutations. Arch Neurol. 2006 Sep;63(9):1250-4.</citation>
    <PMID>16966502</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Foroud T, Pankratz N, Martinez M; PROGENI/GSPD-European Consortium. Chromosome 5 and Parkinson disease. Eur J Hum Genet. 2006 Oct;14(10):1106-10. Epub 2006 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>16736031</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 26, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 26, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 29, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 3, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 3, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Alexis Brice</name_title>
    <organization>Inserm</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>phenotype-genotype correlations</keyword>
  <keyword>mutations spectrum</keyword>
  <keyword>candidate genes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

