<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00131586</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SP-11-0033/ethics 17173</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00131586</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cisplatin, Carboplatin, and Oxaliplatin Interactions With Plasma Proteins</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cisplatin, Carboplatin, and Oxaliplatin Interactions With Plasma Proteins</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AHS Cancer Control Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AHS Cancer Control Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cisplatin is a widely used anti-tumor agent for the treatment of testicular and ovarian
      cancers. Carboplatin is used extensively for small cell, non small cell lung cancer and
      ovarian cancer. Oxaliplatin has recently been approved in the United States (US) for
      treatment of colorectal cancer. A large portion (in the range of 65% to 98%) of cisplatin in
      the blood plasma was bound to protein within a day after intravenous administration. The
      binding of cisplatin and other analogues to proteins and enzymes is generally believed to be
      the cause of several severe side effects such as ototoxicity and nephrotoxicity. The
      interactions between platinum based chemotherapy drugs and proteins is proposed to play
      important roles in both drug activity and toxicity. Therefore, a better understanding of the
      molecular mechanism of platinum-protein interactions may have an impact on optimization of
      strategies for treatment. The objective is to develop novel approaches and techniques to
      provide detailed mechanistic, kinetic and high-resolution structural information on the
      binding of platinum analogues to blood proteins, and to improve treatment efficacy and reduce
      side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cisplatin, cis-[Pt(NH3)2Cl2], is a widely used antitumor agent for the treatment of
      testicular and ovarian cancers. Carboplatin is used extensively for small cell, non small
      cell lung cancer and ovarian cancer. Oxaliplatin has recently been approved in the US for
      treatment of colorectal cancer. All of these analogues are administered by intravenous
      injection, and within one day, 65-98% of the platinum in the blood plasma is bound to
      protein. Binding of cisplatin to proteins reduces urinary excretion of platinum, and causes
      deposition of platinum in tissues. Binding of cisplatin to proteins and enzymes is generally
      believed to be the cause of several severe side effects exhibited by these drugs, especially
      ototoxicity and nephrotoxicity.

      Despite numerous studies of platinum-protein binding in the last few decades, the roles of
      platinum-protein adducts in drug action, and in toxicity of these drugs are not known.
      Although cisplatin-protein adducts are widely believed to cause the drug's side effects,
      there are also claims that platinum-protein adducts are important for the drug's activity.
      Therefore, a better understanding of the molecular mechanism of platinum-protein interactions
      may have an impact on the optimization of strategies for platinum treatment. It is important
      to understand basic principles that govern formation and reactivity of platinum-protein
      adducts because these adducts may be important in defining the therapeutic profile of these
      drugs. In this quest, the first goal is to develop a reliable technique for these studies. To
      date, ultraviolet/visible (UV-Vis), fourier transform infrared (FT-IR), and nuclear magnetic
      resonance (NMR) studies of cisplatin-protein interactions have provided only low-resolution
      information on the mechanism of the binding or on the nature of the adducts. The researchers
      propose to investigate the role of platinum-protein adducts in the mechanisms of the drug
      action and their contributions towards the toxicity of these drug. The short-term objective
      is to investigate platinum interaction with serum proteins using both nanoelectrospray mass
      spectrometry (nanoESI-MS) and a combination of size exclusion high performance liquid
      chromatography with inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (HPLC/ICP-MS). The long-term
      objective of this research is to develop biomarkers based on platinum-protein adducts for
      clinical monitoring.

      Initially, metallothionein and human hemoglobin were used as model proteins to develop
      nESI/MS and HPLC/ICP-MS techniques for studying cisplatin-protein interactions in vitro. The
      researchers have demonstrated that the combination of size exclusion HPLC/ICP-MS and
      nanoESI/MS provided new information on the adduct formation and potential reaction mechanism.
      The size exclusion HPLC with ICP-MS enables monitoring of cisplatin-protein binding under
      physiological conditions. Nanospray tandem MS offers information on formation of specific
      complexes and on characteristics of binding. This information is useful for a better
      understanding of drug toxicity and treatment resistance. The information on platinum-protein
      interactions allows us to evaluate the utility of both nanoESI/MS and size exclusion
      HPLC/ICP-MS techniques in providing mechanistic, kinetic and structural information on the
      binding of platinum to other proteins. The methodology will be further validated by studying
      the platinum-blood protein adducts in cancer patients undergoing chemotherapeutic treatments.
      The correlation between the levels of platinum-protein adducts and clinical outcomes will be
      studied.

      The successful completion of this research program should provide the researchers with a
      better understanding of mechanisms of the drug action and toxicity. This knowledge will be of
      great importance in clinical monitoring of cancer patients to assist doctors to improve
      cancer chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        community sample
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  To have lung or colorectal cancer and be treated with either oxaliplatin, carboplatin
             or cisplatin
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Sawyer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>AHS Cancer Control Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cross Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 1Z2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 17, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 17, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 26, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>platinum analogues</keyword>
  <keyword>cisplatin, carboplatin, oxaliplatin</keyword>
  <keyword>proteomics</keyword>
  <keyword>hemoglobin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

