<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00134368</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4489</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00134368</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Efficacy and Safety of Etanercept in Adults With Vitiligo</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot, Investigator-Initiated, Proof-of-Concept, Study of the Efficacy and Safety of Etanercept (Enbrel) in Adults With Vitiligo</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the efficacy and safety of etanercept in adults
      with vitiligo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects will self-administer etanercept 50 mg SQ twice weekly for 6 months. Lesion
      repigmentation will be evaluated at monthly visits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2007</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of subjects achieving 50% or more repigmentation at 6 months (Good or better on Physician's Global Assessment [PGA] score)</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects achieving 75% or more repigmentation at 6 months (Excellent or better on PGA score)</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-Generated Global Assessment</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin texture assessment</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>40</enrollment>
  <condition>Vitiligo</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etanercept</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Vitiligo patients aged 18 years and older

          -  Vitiligo patients with evaluable lesions; duration of 3 months to 10 years.

          -  Disease interferes significantly with quality of life and/or involving 3% or more body
             surface area

          -  Subjects must have a negative tuberculin (TB) skin test at entry into the study

          -  If subject is a female of childbearing potential, she must agree to use adequate
             contraception (adequate contraception can include abstinence) and must have a negative
             serum pregnancy test the day of administration of study medication.

          -  If subject is a male and has reached puberty, he must agree to use adequate
             contraception during the study and for 1 month after discontinuation from study.

          -  Subject or designee must have the ability to self-inject investigational product or
             have a care giver at home who can administer subcutaneous injections

          -  Subject must be able to give informed consent; must authorize release and use of
             protected health information; and, if applicable, must assent to participate prior to
             enrollment to this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to consent

          -  History of non-compliance with other therapies

          -  Concurrent therapy for vitiligo

          -  Systemic or photo-therapy within 4 weeks

          -  Topical therapy within 2 weeks

          -  Any medical condition in which etanercept would be contraindicated

          -  Any internal malignancy within 5 years (fully excised cutaneous, basal cell carcinoma
             or squamous cell carcinoma are exceptions)

          -  Pregnancy, not practicing effective birth control, or inability to practice safe sex
             during the length of the study.

          -  Lactation

          -  History of alcohol or drug abuse one year before and during the study.

          -  Any participation in another investigational drug study during the 4 weeks preceding
             this study.

          -  Known HIV-positive status; known history of any other mycobacterial disease or any
             other immuno-suppressing disease.

          -  Presence of a grade 3 or 4 infection &lt; 30 days prior to the screening visit; between
             the screening visit and the first day of treatment on study; or any time during the
             study that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would preclude participation in the
             study.

          -  Patients should not receive live vaccines for 3 months prior to, or while on, study.

          -  A prior history of tuberculosis, and/or a positive PPD skin test and positive CXR at
             screening.

          -  Patients with previous or current exposure to any of the following TNF antagonists:

               -  etanercept (Enbrel);

               -  adalimumab (Humira); or

               -  infliximab (Remicade).

        These patients will not be eligible, even with a wash-out. Patients with previous or
        current exposure to Kineret will NOT be eligible, even with a wash-out. However, patients
        with prior or current exposure to biologics directed against T-cells (e.g. alefacept,
        efalizumab, siplizumab, etc.) will be eligible for enrollment into the study after a
        wash-out period of 4 weeks before first dose of study drug (baseline visit). It has to be
        protocol specific also.

          -  The subject has, in the Investigator's opinion, a chronic, severe, progressive, or
             uncontrolled renal, hepatic, hematological, gastrointestinal, pulmonary,
             cardiovascular (congestive heart failure [CHF] of any severity; myocardial infarction
             [MI], cerebrovascular accident [CVA] or transient ischemic attack [TIA] within 3
             months of screening visit; unstable angina pectoris; uncontrolled hypertension
             [sitting systolic blood pressure (BP) &lt; 80 mm Hg or &gt; 160 or diastolic BP &gt; 100 mm
             Hg]), or neurological disease; known systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE); diabetes; or
             any other concomitant medical condition that places the participant at risk by
             participating this study and/or that may interfere with the conduct of the study.

          -  Chronic hepatitis B or hepatitis C, SLE, history of multiple sclerosis, transverse
             myelitis, optic neuritis or epilepsy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alice Gottlieb, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMDNJ-RWJMS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMDNJ Psoriasis Center of Excellence</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Brunswick</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 24, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 6, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 6, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>vitiligo</keyword>
  <keyword>etanercept</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitiligo</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etanercept</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

