<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03339635</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201600107</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03339635</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Short-term Testosterone Replacement in Testicular Cancer Survivors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Short-term Testosterone Replacement in Testicular Cancer Survivors to Treat Overweight and Improve Cardiometabolic Risk: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Medical Center Groningen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Medical Center Groningen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the effects of testosterone replacement therapy on fat mass and other components of
      the metabolic syndrome. A randomized double-blind placebo controlled intervention study,
      followed by an open-label treatment phase. Results of this pilot study will be used to design
      a multicenter randomized controlled study in a large group of TC survivors
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Testicular cancer (TC) survivors have an increased risk of hypogonadism (decreased
      testosterone and/or increased luteinizing hormone levels) and cardiovascular disease (CVD).
      Metabolic syndrome develops early after chemotherapy in 20-30% of long-term TC survivors and
      is associated with an increased risk of atherosclerotic disease in the general population. TC
      survivors who develop the metabolic syndrome have a higher body mass index (BMI)
      pretreatment, a larger BMI increase during follow-up, and lower total testosterone levels
      than patients without the metabolic syndrome. Testosterone replacement therapy as a
      short-term intervention during a limited time period may be an important strategy to reduce
      body weight and fat mass, restore cardiometabolic balance, and decrease the prevalence of the
      metabolic syndrome in TC survivors.

      Objective: to assess the effects of testosterone replacement therapy on fat mass and other
      components of the metabolic syndrome.

      Study design: randomized double-blind placebo controlled intervention study, followed by an
      open-label treatment phase. Results of this pilot study will be used to design a multicenter
      randomized controlled study in a large group of TC survivors

      Study population: 40 TC patients, aged 18-55 years, at least 12 months after completion of
      curative treatment with unilateral orchidectomy and platinum-based chemotherapy, and having a
      fasting total testosterone level ≤12 nmol/l and a BMI ≥25 kg/m2.

      Intervention: Patients will be randomized to treatment with transdermal testosterone gel
      (Androgel) or placebo gel once daily during 20 weeks, followed by 20 weeks of active Androgel
      treatment in all participants. The treatment dose will be 50 mg daily, adjusted to 25 mg in
      case of increased testosterone concentrations (average of 2 measurements &gt;25 nmol/L) or signs
      of overdosing. Patients will be stratified according to testosterone level (8-12 nmol/L
      versus &lt;8 nmol/L) and BMI (25-30 kg/m2 versus 30-35 kg/m2).

      Main study parameters/endpoints: Primary endpoint is the change in fat mass as measured by
      Dual-Energy X-ray Absorption (DEXA) scan after 20 weeks of Androgel compared to placebo.
      Secondary endpoints are changes in fat mass between 20 and 40 weeks, and changes in abdominal
      visceral fat, BMI, adipocytokines, metabolic syndrome parameters, bone mass density, semen
      quality, sexual function, and quality of life between Androgel and placebo-treated patients.

      Nature and extent of the burden and risks associated with participation, benefit and group
      relatedness: The study will provide an answer to the question whether testosterone
      replacement therapy as a short-term intervention has significant effects on obesity and fat
      metabolism and may, thus, reduce the prevalence of the metabolic syndrome in this population
      of young men with excellent long-term cancer-related prognosis, but an increased CVD risk. At
      various time points during the intervention, patients will be subjected to history taking and
      physical examination. Furthermore, blood will be drawn to: measure hormone levels,
      adipocytokines, lipids, glucose, insulin, and bone markers; to extract DNA for determination
      of gene polymorphisms; and to measure hematocrit and PSA as safety parameters. Semen analysis
      and a full body DEXA scan will be performed at 0, 20 and 40 weeks only. Patients will be
      asked to fill out questionnaires regarding quality of life, sexual health, and androgen
      deficiency symptoms at various time points during the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>percent change in fat mass as measured using using full body dual X-ray absorptiometry</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effects of 20 weeks of treatment with testosterone gel on fat mass as measured using full body dual X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA scan).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of treatment with testosterone gel</measure>
    <time_frame>20 and 40 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effects of 20 and 40 weeks of treatment with testosterone gel on obesity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of treatment with testosterone gel</measure>
    <time_frame>20 and 40 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effects of 20 and 40 weeks of treatment with testosterone gel on signs and symptoms of hypogonadism</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Testicular Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Testosterone gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to treatment with transdermal testosterone gel (Androgel) once daily during 20 weeks, followed by 20 weeks of active Androgel treatment in all participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to treatment with placebo gel once daily during 20 weeks, followed by 20 weeks of active Androgel treatment in all participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Androgel (Testosterone gel)</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to treatment with transdermal testosterone gel (Androgel) once daily during 20 weeks, followed by 20 weeks of active Androgel treatment in all participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Testosterone gel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo gel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Androgel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to treatment with transdermal placebo gel once daily during 20 weeks, followed by 20 weeks of active Androgel treatment in all participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo gel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with metastatic testicular cancer after unilateral orchidectomy and
             chemotherapy, at least 12 months after completion of last treatment and without
             evidence of disease. Combination chemotherapy should have contained a platinum
             compound, either cisplatin or carboplatin. In TC survivors, testosterone levels are
             routinely measured in blood during follow-up once every two years.

          -  Patients are eligible for screening if they are between 18 and 55 years of age

          -  have a documented low or low-normal total testosterone level ≤14 nmol/L, as measured
             during any of the follow-up visits, irrespective of signs and symptoms of androgen
             deficiency.

        Eligible for actual study participation and randomization between Androgel and placebo will
        be:

          -  survivors of TC not using testosterone supplements, having biochemical evidence of
             hypogonadism (defined as a serum total testosterone concentration ≤ 12 nmol/L (345
             ng/dL) measured after an overnight fast between 8:00 and 10:00 AM), and being
             overweight (as defined by a BMI ≥ 25 and &lt;35 kg/m2).

          -  Patients should be able to understand and abide to the study protocol and sign written
             informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with a history of extragonadal testicular cancer

          -  patients planning to father children within the next 12 months

          -  patients taking corticosteroids or hormone replacement other than testosterone within
             3 months of randomization

          -  patients taking medication with any antiandrogenic effects (e.g. spironolactone)

          -  patients with signs or history of hormone-dependent cancer (prostate or breast cancer)

          -  patients with severe lower urinary tract symptoms (as defined by International
             Prostate Symptom Score &gt;19)

          -  patients with a history of coronary artery disease (angina pectoris, myocardial
             infarction) or heart failure

          -  patients with hematocrit &gt;50%

          -  patients with untreated severe obstructive sleep apnea

          -  patients with uncontrolled hypertension

          -  patients with a BMI &gt; 35 kg/m2

          -  patients with a history of epilepsy

          -  patients with debilitating psychiatric illness or inability to understand the study
             protocol, according to the opinion of the investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janine Nuver, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Center Groningen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Janine Nuver, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+31 50 3612821</phone>
    <email>j.nuver@umcg.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center Groningen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Groningen</city>
        <zip>9713 GZ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Janine Nuver, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+31 50 3612821</phone>
      <email>j.nuver@umcg.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Janine Nuver, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Medical Center Groningen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>J. Nuver</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Testicular Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Testosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone enanthate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone undecanoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methyltestosterone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

