<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03339843</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IJB-MULTI-MIME-A-2017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03339843</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multiorgan Metabolic Imaging Response Assessment of Abemaciclib</brief_title>
  <acronym>MiMe-A</acronym>
  <official_title>Multiorgan Metabolic Imaging Response Assessment of Abemaciclib</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jules Bordet Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jules Bordet Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Open-label, phase II, basket trial. This trial is a screening program for abemaciclib
      efficacy in multiple platinum-resistant tumour types by using metabolic imaging (PERCIST) and
      RECIST v1.1 criteria.

      Based on the rate of FDG-avidity and the absence of deactivation of the Rb gene function in
      more than 95% of cases, we propose to define 5 tumour types of interest in a preliminary
      stage:

        1. Platinum-refractory esophageal adenocarcinoma (ADC)

        2. Platinum-refractory esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (SCC)

        3. Platinum-refractory cholangiocarcinoma

        4. Platinum-refractory and progressive after immunotherapy urothelial cancer

        5. Platinum-refractory endometrial cancer
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In various solid tumour types FDG-PET/CT has been shown to identify treatment-refractory
      diseases with a high negative predictive value (NPV) through a whole-body quantitative
      assessment of treatment-induced changes in tumour glucose uptake soon after treatment
      initiation, before any structural changes are observed. Progress in the standardisation of
      FDG-PET/CT imaging and response analysis now allow its use in multicentric trials opening the
      possibilities for trials where treatment allocation will be based on early metabolic
      response. MiMe has been built on the assumption that a medication which does not induce any
      metabolic changes in a given clinical setting is unlikely to induce a significant benefit and
      does consequently not deserve further investigation as a single agent in this setting.

      MiMe, by assessing metabolic response early during the treatment course, will hopefully
      provide useful information about the drug activity in various cancer types, and about
      mechanisms of resistance through a potential ambitious translational research program with
      serial collection of circulating-tumour DNA (ct-DNA).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a two step, open-label, basket trial looking at 5 different tumour types.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the anti-tumour activity of abemaciclib in the five tumour types studied in this trial using FDG-PET/CT during the first cycle of therapy (early FDG- PET/CT).</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Therapy success rate defined as: PERCIST 15%-assessed Metabolic Response at early FDG-PET/CT (D12-D16)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the anti-tumour activity of abemaciclib in the five tumour types studied in this trial using RECISTv1.1 after 2 cycles of therapy as a screening tool.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Therapy success rate defined as: RECISTv1.1-assessed Disease Control (DC) after 2 treatment cycles (CR or PR or SD)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate Progression-free survival (PFS define as the time from treatment start until disease progression or death) at 24 weeks from treatment start</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>RECIST v1.1-based radiological response assessment performed at 24 weeks from the treatment start to determine the PFS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate Overall Survival (OS defined as the time from treatment start until death) at 24 weeks from treatment start</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>RECIST v1.1-based radiological response assessment performed at 24 weeks from the treatment start to determine the OS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate median progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Progression Free Survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate median overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall Survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate toxicity profile</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicity profile according to CTCAE version 4.03</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the correlation of early metabolic response using FDG-PET/CT with morphological response to treatment assessed by RECIST</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>RECIST v1.1-based radiological response assessment performed at 24 weeks from the treatment start to determine the PFS and OS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">85</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Esophagus SCC</condition>
  <condition>Cholangiocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Urothelial/Bladder Cancer, Nos</condition>
  <condition>Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Abemaciclib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study contains 2 stages; during the 1st stage, a maximum of 17 patients will be enrolled in each tumour type cohort. After 13 evaluable patients have been enrolled, an interim analysis will be performed. If 3 or more patients are seen to have experienced a treatment success, then the cohort will pass into the 2nd stage in which a maximum of 20 more patients are enrolled. If 2 or less patients are seen to have experienced a treatment success, then that cohort will be closed and will not proceed into the 2nd stage.
Subjects will receive 200 mg of abemaciclib orally, twice a day, during cycles of 28 days each. The subject will undergo: A baseline FDG-PET/CT and a baseline CT scan and A blinded early FDG-PET/CT at D14 +/- 2 days of study treatment.
A treatment success is defined as a patient who has metabolic response according to PERCIST with a response cut off set at 15% at the early FDG-PET/CT and a morphological disease control after 2 cycles measured by RECIST v1.1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abemaciclib</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive 200 mg of abemaciclib orally, two times a day, during cycles of 28 days each. An early FDG-PET/CT will be performed at cycle 1 day 14 to search for any new lesions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Abemaciclib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FDG-PET/CT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 years old

          2. Female or male

          3. ECOG performance status ≤ 1

          4. Life expectancy of greater than 12 weeks

          5. Must have histologically confirmed cancer corresponding to the predefined tumour
             subtypes (esophageal adenocarcinoma, esophageal squamous cell carcinoma,
             cholangiocarcinoma, urothelial cancer (progressive after immunotherapy), endometrial
             cancer) and metastatic or non-resectable and refractory to standard platinum regimens
             (and progressive after immunotherapy for the urothelial cancer).

          6. Presence of at least one metabolically measurable tumour lesion on FDG-PET/CT,
             according to PERCIST. If previously irradiated, must have been more than 2 months
             before the baseline FDG PET/CT.

          7. Measurable disease according to RECIST v 1.1

          8. Serum pregnancy test (for subjects of childbearing potential) negative

          9. Women of childbearing potential must agree to the use a highly effective method of
             contraception prior to study entry, during the course of the study and at least 3
             months after the last administration of study treatment.

         10. Men with childbearing potential partner must agree to use condom during the course of
             this study and for at least 3 months after the last administration of the study
             treatment.

         11. Adequate coagulation: International Normalized Ratio (INR) ≤ 1.5 x ULN unless subject
             is receiving anticoagulant therapy as long as INR and activated partial thromboplastin
             time [aPTT] are within therapeutic range of intended use of anticoagulants

         12. Adequate bone marrow function as defined below:

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 10 g/dL

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1500/µL or 1.5x109/L

               -  Platelets ≥ 100000/µL or 100x109/L

               -  Leukocytes ≥ 3,000/µL

         13. Adequate liver function as defined below:

               -  Serum total bilirubin within 1.5 × normal institutional limits (except for
                  Gilbert syndrome where direct bilirubin should be &lt;1.5 institutional ULN)

               -  AST/ALT/ALP) levels &lt; 3 × institutional upper limit of normal (or ALT and AST &lt;5
                  times upper limit of normal if liver metastases are present).

         14. Adequate renal function as defined below: Cockcroft-Gault creatine clearance &gt;50ml/min

         15. Completion of all necessary screening procedures

         16. Ability to swallow capsules

         17. Grade ≤ 1 toxicity due to any previous cancer therapy according to the National Cancer
             Institute Common Terminology Criteria of Adverse Events (NCI-CTCAE, v.4.03). Grade 2
             is allowed in case of alopecia and peripheral sensory neuropathy

         18. Availability of primary archived tumour tissue block (1 FFPE tumour tissue)

         19. Signed Informed Consent form (ICF) obtained prior to any study related procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects meeting one of the following criteria are not eligible for this
             studyParticipants who have had chemotherapy, radiotherapy, immunotherapy, or targeted
             therapy within 3 weeks prior study enrolment

          2. Participants receiving concomitantly any other experimental agents

          3. Patients who have received prior therapy with other CDK4/6 inhibitors

          4. Subjects with known brain metastasis; unless the metastasis are asymptomatic and have
             been stable since at least 2 months prior to treatment start.

          5. Patient with meningeal carcinomatosis

          6. Have had major surgery within 28 days prior to the start of the treatment to allow for
             post-operative healing of the surgical wound

          7. History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition

          8. Bleeding diathesis, thromboembolic event, history of cardiovascular ischemic disease
             or cerebrovascular incident within the last six months

          9. Uncontrolled concurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia

         10. Substance abuse, psychiatric illness/social situations, any psychological, familial,
             sociological, geographical condition, significant medical or surgical condition
             currently uncontrolled by treatment that would limit compliance with study
             requirements or interfere with the patient's ability to understand informed consent
             and participation in the study

         11. Pregnant and/or lactating women

         12. Uncontrolled Diabetes

         13. Known history of HIV infection, or active hepatitis B or C requiring treatment with
             anti-viral therapy

         14. Have received recent (within 28 days prior the enrolment) yellow fever vaccination

         15. Individuals with a history of a different malignancy are ineligible except for the
             following circumstances. Individuals with a history of other malignancies are eligible
             if they have been disease-free and are deemed by the investigator to be at low risk
             for recurrence of that malignancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laura Polastro, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Jules Bordet Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Laura Polastro, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+3225413279</phone>
    <email>laura.polastro@bordet.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholangiocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

