<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03333226</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RF-2013-02358165</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03333226</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Axillary Reverse Mapping (ARM) in Breast Cancer Surgery to Prevent Lymphedema. (ARMtrial)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Axillary Reverse Mapping (ARM). Identification of the Arm Lymphatic Pathways in Breast Cancer Surgery to Prevent Breast Cancer Related Lymphedema (BCRL): a Randomized Clinical Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital of Ferrara</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital of Ferrara</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Breast cancer related lymphedema (BCRL) is a debilitating and distressing condition affecting
      approximately one out of five breast cancer survivors. BCRL is a chronic swelling of the
      upper arm following axillary lymph nodes dissection, and it is associated to a significant
      functional, psychological and social morbidity, with an heavy impact on life quality. Several
      studies reported BCRL incidence between 6.7% and 62.5% for different population cohorts.
      Randomized clinical trials (RCTs) reported that sentinel lymph node biopsy (SLNB) when
      compared with axillary lymph node dissection (ALND) leads to a significant reduction in
      postoperative complications. However, the advent of SLNB does not solve the problem of BCRL
      with a concrete chance to develop a lymphedema after single SLNB around 7%. Health care cost
      of BCRL rehabilitative treatment is not available in literature yet. Few studies considered
      incidence, risk factors and treatment costs of BCRL among working-age women after breast
      cancer treatment, reporting that BCRL population had significantly higher rehabilitative
      medical costs ($14,877 to $23,167) with twice as much risk to develop BCRL complications,
      such as lymphangitis or cellulitis when compared to &quot;BCRL free&quot; population (OR = 2.02, P =
      .009).

      Axillary reverse mapping (ARM) procedure claims to map and preserve arm lymphatic drainage
      during ALND and/or during SLNB, reducing BCRL development. ARM is developed as result of
      assumption that arm's lymphatic pathway is not involved by metastatic tumor cells of the
      primary breast cancer. However, when the arm lymph node correspond to the SLN it should be
      removed for correct tumor staging, thus a lymphatic drainage disruption onset will be
      expected with BCRL risk increase.

      During the ARM procedure, a fluorescence imaging technique (photodynamic procedure) is useful
      for detecting lymphatic drainage of the upper limb and it allows in differentiating the
      fluorescent ARM node from the SLN identified by the radioguided technique (99mTC-Nanocoll).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will conduct a randomized clinical trial (RCT) at the S. Anna University
      Hospital of Ferrara (Italy) on consecutive patients undergoing SLNB for breast cancer and
      subsequent ALND in case of SLN metastases. Eligible patients for radioguided sentinel lymph
      node biopsy (rSLNB) will be randomly divided in two groups: 1) experimental group in which
      patients undergoing rSLNB and ARM photodynamic procedure; and, in case of SLN metastases,
      subsequent ALND with ARM node preservation; 2) control group in which patients undergoing
      rSLNB and ARM photodynamic procedure; and, in case of SLN metastases, subsequent ALND with
      ARM node removal.

      Consent procedure

      Patients will be visited in the outpatient clinic by one of the treating surgeon, who will
      approach the subject and explain the study. If the patient is interested in participating,
      further details will be provided and consent will be obtained.

      Experimental design

      Step 1

      Patients enrolled in both groups will be subjected to rSLNB associated to ARM photodynamic
      procedure.

      Radioguided SLNB technique:

      The day before surgery, four peri-areolar subcutaneous injections of Tc-99m Nanocoll® will be
      performed for an overall volume of 0.4 ml (standard activity of 74 MBq). Pre-operative
      imaging of SLN consists of an anterior and lateral static acquisition, generally performed
      between 1 and 5 hours post-injection (max. 18 hours), by means of a double head gammacamera
      (Siemens, ECAM). The gamma camera energy selection peak is centered on the 140 KeV of 99mTc
      (with a window of ± 10%), and the use of high-resolution collimators and of a 256x256
      acquisition matrix. Acquisition time varies between 2 and 8 minutes. Cutaneous projection of
      SLN will be marked with a skin-marking pen. The day of surgery, after intraoperative routine
      prep and drape, a handheld gamma probe (EuroProbe III, EURORAD, Chennevières-sur-Marne,
      France) will be used to localize radioactivity before skin incision and during axillary
      dissection to identify SLN, that is defined by counts &gt;10% of background.

      ARM photodynamic procedure:

      The day of surgery, 15 minutes before surgical incision, patients will be subjected to
      injection of 1 ml of ICG (5mg/ml) in the upper forearm and during SLNB we will perform an
      evaluation of lymphatic arm pathways with fluorescence (IC-Flow Diagnostic Green, SEDA
      S.p.a., Milano, Italy). If a crossover between SLN of the breast and the arm's lymph node
      will be find, the ARM lymph node identified by the photodynamic technique will be excised for
      pathological evaluation.

      Step 2

      Patients with tumor positive SLN, eligible for ALND, will undergo to preoperative arm
      lymphoscintigraphy in order to asses possible changes in lymphatic drainage pathways of the
      arm after rSLNB.

      The day before ALND, an injection of a volume of 0.4 ml of Tc-99m Nanocoll® in each hand will
      be performed, fractioned in all interdigital space. The subsequent scintigraphic planar
      acquisition is performed using a double head gamma-camera (Siemens, Ecam) according the
      following protocol:

        -  5 minutes post injection: imaging acquisition on hands and forearms positioned over
           collimator with a marker near right arm;

        -  10 minutes post injection :anterior acquisition with gamma camera head 1 on elbows and
           shoulders;

        -  15 minutes post injection : anterior acquisition on both axilla and thorax using cobalt
           wires markers drawing cranium profile;

        -  20 minutes post injection :marking with skin-marking pen of skin projection of most
           radioactive axillary nodes;

        -  120/180 minutes post injection : acquisition in the same position for checking of
           possible number and/or site changes of nodes marked before.

      Step 3

      Experimental group:

      In case of SLN metastases, during radical ALND (I, II,III levels of Berg), the ARM lymph node
      identified with both radioguided and photodynamic methods will be isolated from the other
      axillary lymph nodes and preserved. Photodynamic method will also allow us to visualize the
      lymphatic drainage of the arm that will be preserved.

      Control group:

      In case of SLN metastases, during radical ALND (I, II,III levels of Berg), the ARM lymph node
      identified with both radioguided and photodynamic method will be isolated from the other
      axillary lymph nodes and removed.

      Step 4

      The post-operative follow up will be conducted in inpatient setting and after discharge in
      outpatient setting (surveillance for early and delayed surgical complications). All patients
      will be clinically evaluated at 10, 30, 60, and 180 days after surgery and undergoing
      bilateral arms lymphoscintigraphy at 60 days after surgery to determine possible
      lymphoscintigraphic changes underlying a subclinical BCRL. Clinically follow-up will include
      the clinical presentation (pain, integumentary abnormalities, paresthesia, hypoesthesia,
      neuro-vascular deficits), measurement of 7 records [diameters of the upper limb (hand, wrist,
      15 cm and 10 cm distally to olecranon, elbow (olecranon), 10 cm and 15 cm proximally to
      olecranon)] and final conversion into volumes. In case of BCRL diagnosis patients will be
      addressed to rehabilitative center for therapy.

      Statistical analysis

      A prospective analysis will be obtained from database in which patients data will be
      collected, with details of the patients and tumors characteristics, lymphatic drainage of the
      upper extremity, intra- and post-operative outcome, and follow up. The power analysis, based
      on preliminary results, reports that 150 women in each group are required to achieve a power
      of 0.9 and to detect a significant difference (p&lt;0.05). Data will be expressed as mean ±
      standard deviation or median (interquartile range - IQR 25-75) according to the distribution.
      The Shapiro-Wilk test will be used to assess the assumption of normality. Categorical data
      will be presented as number (%). Data will be analyzed using the Chi-square test to compare
      percentages, t-Student test will be used to compare the means and Mann-Whitney test to
      compare non parametric data. Logistic regression analysis will be employed to construct a
      model predicting BCRL using factors regarding the patient [age, gender, BMI, American Society
      of Anesthesiology (ASA) classification], the tumor (size, stage, bio-molecular
      characteristics ), crossover, type of intervention (preservation of ARM lymph node vs.
      dissection), and post-operative treatment (chemotherapy, radiotherapy). Significance will be
      considered for values of p&lt;0.05. Statistical analysis will be performed with IBM SPSS
      Statistics for Windows, Version 24.0 (IBM Corp. Armonk, NY: IBM Corp.).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 17, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Eligible patients for radioguided sentinel lymph node biopsy (rSLNB) will be randomly divided in two groups:
experimental group in which all patients will be sent to both rSLNB and photodynamic Axillary Reverse Mapping (ARM) to evaluate the crossover between SLN and ARM lymph node. In case of SLN metastases, an ALND with ARM lymph node preservation will be performed.
control group in which all patients will be sent to both rSLNB and photodynamic Axillary Reverse Mapping (ARM) to evaluate the crossover between SLN and ARM lymph node. In case of SLN metastases, an ALND with ARM lymph node removal will be performed.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Patients will be randomized before the SLNB procedure. Due to the type of intervention, the blinding of the treating surgeon will not be possible, thus the surgeon will be aware of both the intraoperative crossover between ARM lymph node and SLN (secondary outcome) and the allocation to ARM lymph node preservation or removal. Data about BCRL (primary outcome) will be collected by the physiatrist and the physiotherapist that will be blinded about the allocation (ARM lymph node preservation/removal) and the crossover between SLN of the breast and the arm's lymph node. The assessment of lymphoscintigraphic subclinical modification in the arm lymphatic drainage after SLNB and ALND (secondary outcomes) will be performed by a blinded nuclear medicine physician that will not be aware of the allocation (ARM lymph node preservation/removal) and the crossover between ARM lymph node and breast's SLN.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Breast Cancer Related Lymphedema (BCRL) after Axillary Lymph Node Dissection (ALND)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the day of surgery to 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of BCRL in patients in whom the ARM lymph node is preserved compared to those in which it is removed. Clinically follow-up will include the clinical presentation (pain, integumentary abnormalities, paresthesia, hypoesthesia, neuro-vascular deficits), standardized measurement of 7 records [diameters of the upper limb (hand, wrist, 15 cm and 10 cm distally to olecranon, elbow (olecranon), 10 cm and 15 cm proximally to olecranon)] and final conversion into volumes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Breast Cancer Related Lymphedema (BCRL) after Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy (SLNB) alone</measure>
    <time_frame>From the day of surgery to 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Clinically follow-up will include the clinical presentation (pain, integumentary abnormalities, paresthesia, hypoesthesia, neuro-vascular deficits), standardized measurement of 7 records [diameters of the upper limb (hand, wrist, 15 cm and 10 cm distally to olecranon, elbow (olecranon), 10 cm and 15 cm proximally to olecranon)] and final conversion into volumes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Crossover between Sentinel Lymph Node (SLN) of the Breast and the ARM lymph node</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Intraoperatively, the radioguided technique (Tc-99m Nanocoll) will be used to identify the SLN of the breast; at the same time, the Axillary Reverse Mapping (ARM) of the upper limb will be carried out by Indocyanine Green, and the ARM lymph node will be identified and preserved. If a crossover between SLN of the breast and the arm's lymph node will be find, the ARM lymph node identified by the photodynamic technique will be excised for pathological evaluation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lymphoscintigraphic sub-clinical modifications of arm lymphatic drainage after ALND</measure>
    <time_frame>The day before ALND and at 60 days after ALND</time_frame>
    <description>Bilateral arms lymphoscintigraphy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer Lymphedema</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM lymph node preservation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will be sent to both rSLNB and photodynamic Axillary Reverse Mapping (ARM) to evaluate the crossover between SLN and ARM lymph node. In case of SLN metastases, an ALND with ARM lymph node preservation will be performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARM lymph node removal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will be sent to both rSLNB and photodynamic Axillary Reverse Mapping (ARM) to evaluate the crossover between SLN and ARM lymph node. In case of SLN metastases, an ALND with ARM lymph node removal will be performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Axillary Reverse Mapping (ARM)</intervention_name>
    <description>ARM lymph node preservation versus removal</description>
    <arm_group_label>ARM lymph node preservation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ARM lymph node removal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  T1-T2 stage breast cancer

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  axillary lymph node metastasis;

          -  previous surgery on the ipsilateral axilla;

          -  neoadjuvant chemo-radiotherapy;

          -  presence of primitive lymphedema of the arm;

          -  allergy to Iodine, thyroid disease, renal and hepatic impairment (for issues related
             to Indocyanine Green)

          -  pregnancy;

          -  patients refusing to participate in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paolo Carcoforo, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0039 0532 236123</phone>
    <email>paolo.carcoforo@unife.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mattia Portinari, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0039 0532 236100</phone>
    <email>mattia.portinari@unife.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero Universitaria S. Anna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cona</city>
        <state>Ferrara</state>
        <zip>44124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paolo Carcoforo, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0039 0532 236123</phone>
      <email>paolo.carcoforo@unife.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mattia Portinari, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0039 0532 236100</phone>
      <email>mattia.portinari@unife.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sakorafas GH, Peros G, Cataliotti L, Vlastos G. Lymphedema following axillary lymph node dissection for breast cancer. Surg Oncol. 2006 Nov;15(3):153-65. Epub 2006 Dec 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17187979</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McWayne J, Heiney SP. Psychologic and social sequelae of secondary lymphedema: a review. Cancer. 2005 Aug 1;104(3):457-66.</citation>
    <PMID>15968692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Purushotham AD, Upponi S, Klevesath MB, Bobrow L, Millar K, Myles JP, Duffy SW. Morbidity after sentinel lymph node biopsy in primary breast cancer: results from a randomized controlled trial. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Jul 1;23(19):4312-21.</citation>
    <PMID>15994144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilke LG, McCall LM, Posther KE, Whitworth PW, Reintgen DS, Leitch AM, Gabram SG, Lucci A, Cox CE, Hunt KK, Herndon JE 2nd, Giuliano AE. Surgical complications associated with sentinel lymph node biopsy: results from a prospective international cooperative group trial. Ann Surg Oncol. 2006 Apr;13(4):491-500. Epub 2006 Mar 2.</citation>
    <PMID>16514477</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shih YC, Xu Y, Cormier JN, Giordano S, Ridner SH, Buchholz TA, Perkins GH, Elting LS. Incidence, treatment costs, and complications of lymphedema after breast cancer among women of working age: a 2-year follow-up study. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Apr 20;27(12):2007-14. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2008.18.3517. Epub 2009 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>19289624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ponzone R, Mininanni P, Cassina E, Sismondi P. Axillary reverse mapping in breast cancer: can we spare what we find? Ann Surg Oncol. 2008 Jan;15(1):390-1; author reply 392-3. Epub 2007 Nov 8.</citation>
    <PMID>17990039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boneti C, Korourian S, Diaz Z, Santiago C, Mumford S, Adkins L, Klimberg VS. Scientific Impact Award: Axillary reverse mapping (ARM) to identify and protect lymphatics draining the arm during axillary lymphadenectomy. Am J Surg. 2009 Oct;198(4):482-7. doi: 10.1016/j.amjsurg.2009.06.008.</citation>
    <PMID>19800452</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Britton TB, Solanki CK, Pinder SE, Mortimer PS, Peters AM, Purushotham AD. Lymphatic drainage pathways of the breast and the upper limb. Nucl Med Commun. 2009 Jun;30(6):427-30. doi: 10.1097/MNM.0b013e328315a6c6.</citation>
    <PMID>19319006</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Noguchi M, Noguchi M, Nakano Y, Ohno Y, Kosaka T. Axillary reverse mapping using a fluorescence imaging system in breast cancer. J Surg Oncol. 2012 Mar;105(3):229-34. doi: 10.1002/jso.22094. Epub 2011 Sep 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21913193</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Han C, Yang B, Zuo WS, Zheng G, Yang L, Zheng MZ. The Feasibility and Oncological Safety of Axillary Reverse Mapping in Patients with Breast Cancer: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Prospective Studies. PLoS One. 2016 Feb 26;11(2):e0150285. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0150285. eCollection 2016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26919589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yue T, Zhuang D, Zhou P, Zheng L, Fan Z, Zhu J, Hou L, Yu F, Dong X, Xiao L, He Q. A Prospective Study to Assess the Feasibility of Axillary Reverse Mapping and Evaluate Its Effect on Preventing Lymphedema in Breast Cancer Patients. Clin Breast Cancer. 2015 Aug;15(4):301-6. doi: 10.1016/j.clbc.2015.01.010. Epub 2015 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>25776198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sarri AJ, Dias R, Laurienzo CE, Gonçalves MC, Dias DS, Moriguchi SM. Arm lymphoscintigraphy after axillary lymph node dissection or sentinel lymph node biopsy in breast cancer. Onco Targets Ther. 2017 Mar 6;10:1451-1457. doi: 10.2147/OTT.S117830. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28331338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital of Ferrara</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paolo Carcoforo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Neoplasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymph Node Excision</keyword>
  <keyword>Technetium Tc 99m</keyword>
  <keyword>Indocyanine Green</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphatic System</keyword>
  <keyword>Secondary Prevention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphedema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Cancer Lymphedema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Formal requests will be evaluated.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

