<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03332537</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H16-152</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1P20NR016605-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03332537</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Precision Pain Self-Management in Young Adults With Irritable Bowel Syndrome</brief_title>
  <acronym>IBS-SM</acronym>
  <official_title>Precision Pain Self-Management in Young Adults With Irritable Bowel Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Connecticut</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Connecticut</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot project will provide foundational information about the contextual factors of
      irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) related pain (pain catastrophizing, perceived stress,
      reactivity pain sensitivity, genetic and microbiome) on pain self-management (SM) process and
      outcomes. In addition, the investigators will gain insight on the potential impact of the
      personalized IBS-pain SM approach on pain SM behaviors and health outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intense, recurrent abdominal (visceral) pain is a predominant symptom of irritable bowel
      syndrome (IBS), a functional gut disorder that typically manifests in the early adult years.
      IBS is common with prevalence reaching over 20% in some regions of the world, and affects
      more women than men. While women report more severe IBS-related pain, both younger men and
      women report more severe pain compared to older adult cohorts. Direct costs of care and lost
      productivity in the U.S. exceed $21 billion annually, and individuals with IBS utilize more
      healthcare services than the general population, including outpatient visits, diagnostic
      testing and over-the-counter and prescription medications. Individuals with IBS report that
      pain is the most distressing symptom and has the greatest impact on quality of life, however,
      current approaches to improve self- management of IBS-related pain do not target individual,
      context-specific factors of pain. Therefore, individuals with IBS-related pain often endure a
      long and frustrating course of learning how to manage pain on their own accord. The proposed
      pilot project was developed based on this common situation and will provide feasibility data
      about the influence of providing a personalized pain SM intervention to individuals with
      IBS-related pain. IBS-related pain is associated with sensitization of the central nervous
      system, and approximately half of all patients with IBS have visceral hypersensitivity. These
      alterations in pain processing escalate pain perception, and can increase vulnerability to
      other co-morbid pain disorders which individuals with IBS frequently suffer. Pain
      sensitization is influenced by pain-sensitivity genes and, specific to IBS-related pain, the
      gut microbiome. Therefore, as contextual factors of pain associated with IBS, the
      investigators will measure peripheral and central sensitivity, single-nucleotide
      polymorphisms (SNPs) of candidate pain-sensitivity genes and the gut microbiome. The SM
      intervention was designed to provide factual information about IBS pain, triggers of pain and
      pain SM skills. The experimental group will receive one-on-one consultation tailored around
      the individual's assessment results of peripheral and central pain sensitivity as measured by
      quantitative sensory testing (QST) and targeted toward increasing pain self-efficacy and
      self-regulation skills and abilities. The proposed pilot project will provide foundational
      information about the contextual factors of IBS pain (pain catastrophizing, perceived stress,
      reactivity pain sensitivity, genetic and microbiome) on pain SM process and outcomes. In
      addition, the investigators will gain insight on the potential impact of the personalized
      IBS-pain SM approach on pain SM behaviors and health outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Using a stratified and blocked randomization scheme.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 weeks and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative sensory testing - Change over time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in gut microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 weeks and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change over time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic variations (Pain-susceptibility SNPs genotyping)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>related to IBS-related pain and gut microbiome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be provided an online interactive platform to access electronic modules (total of 10) on: IBS-related pain neurophysiology and the brain-gut axis and self-management strategies. There is no additional intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Personalized IBS Pain SM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be enrolled in the online platform. After completion of the modules, they will be scheduled for a consultation with a research nurse about their level of peripheral and central sensitivity, self-evaluation of IBS-pain SM, goal setting and self-monitoring of IBS-pain and physical activity. They will be asked to document their pain and all symptom SM behaviors daily for the next 10 weeks. At the 6-week follow-up visit, the researcher will review the online activities of the participant, go over the previously selected goals with the participants. The study nurse will acknowledge accomplishment of goals and assist in problem-identification and solving.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Personalized IBS Pain SM</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Personalized IBS Pain SM</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women ages 18-29 years of age

          -  Diagnosis of IBS from a healthcare provider with a current report of pain

          -  Able to read and write in English

          -  Daily access to a computer connected to the internet

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other chronic painful conditions (i.e. fibromyalgia, chronic pelvic pain, or chronic
             interstitial cystitis)

          -  Infectious disease (hepatitis, HIV, MRSA)

          -  Celiac disease or inflammatory bowel disease

          -  Diabetes Mellitus

          -  Serious mental health conditions (ex. Bipolar disorder, schizophrenia, mania)

          -  Women who are pregnant or post-partum in last 3 months

          -  Regular use of opioids, iron supplements, prebiotics/probiotics or antibiotics, or
             substance abuse.

          -  Injury to non-dominant hand or presence of open skin lesions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>29 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xiaomei Cong, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Connecticut</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xiaomei Cong, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <phone>(860) 486-2694</phone>
    <email>xiaomei.cong@uconn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Angela Starkweather, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <phone>860 486 0549</phone>
    <email>angela.starkweather@uconn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UConn Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Farmington</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xiaomei Cong, PhD, RN</last_name>
      <phone>860-486-2694</phone>
      <email>xiaomei.cong@uconn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xiaomei Cong, PhD, RN</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Connecticut</name>
      <address>
        <city>Storrs</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06269</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xiaomei Cong, PhD, RN</last_name>
      <phone>860-486-2694</phone>
      <email>xiaomei.cong@uconn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Angela Starkweather, PhD, RN</last_name>
      <phone>(860) 486-0549</phone>
      <email>angela.starkweather@uconn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xiaomei Cong, PhD, RN</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://painresearch.uconn.edu/capps-m/</url>
    <description>Center for Accelerating Precision Pain Self-management (CAPPS-M) website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 1, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Connecticut</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Xiaomei Cong</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Young Adults</keyword>
  <keyword>IBS</keyword>
  <keyword>Self Management</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Gut microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Online education</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All of the individual participant data that are part of National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR) designated common data elements collected during the trial, after de-identification have been submitted to NIH repository at the Common Data Repository for Nursing Science (cdRNS). Data can be accessed by directly submitting requests at that website.
When will data be available (start and end dates)? Immediately. No end date.
With whom? Anyone who wishes to access the data and creates an account on cdRNS.nih.gov.
By what mechanism will data be made available? Data are available at cdRNS.nih.gov</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

