<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03331198</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>017004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03331198</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study Evaluating Safety and Efficacy of JCAR017 in Subjects With Relapsed or Refractory CLL or SLL (TRANSCEND-CLL-004)</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Phase 1 Safety and Phase 2 Randomized Study of JCAR017 in Subjects With Relapsed or Refractory Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma (017004)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Juno Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Juno Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1/2, open-label, multicenter study to determine the efficacy and safety of
      JCAR017 in adult subjects with relapsed or refractory CLL or SLL. The study will include a
      Phase 1 part to determine the recommended dose of JCAR017 monotherapy in subjects with
      relapsed or refractory CLL or SLL, followed by a Phase 2 randomized part to assess JCAR017
      monotherapy treatment versus standard of care. A separate Phase 1 cohort will assess the
      combination of JCAR017 and concurrent ibrutinib. In all subjects, the safety, efficacy, and
      pharmacokinetics (PK) of JCAR017 will be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 26, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Phase 1: subjects will be assigned to receive JCAR017, or JCAR017 + ibrutinib Phase 2: subjects will be randomized to receive JCAR017 or standard of care. Patients who receive standard of care may cross over to receive JCAR017 in the event of disease progression.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1 monotherapy arm: recommended dose</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Recommended dose based on assessment of data from each dose level</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1 combination therapy arm: adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of subjects experiencing adverse events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 1 combination therapy arm: laboratory abnormalities</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of subjects experiencing laboratory abnormalities</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: antitumor activity</measure>
    <time_frame>through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>Complete response rate based on Independent Review Committee assessment using iwCLL 2008 guidelines</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of subjects experiencing adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: laboratory abnormalities</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of subjects experiencing laboratory abnormalities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>Overall response rate based on Independent Review Committee assessment using iwCLL 2008 guidelines</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: minimal residual disease (MRD)-negative response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>MRD will be measured via IgHV deep sequencing and flow cytometry of peripheral blood and bone marrow</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-free survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: PK</measure>
    <time_frame>Through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of JCAR017 in blood and bone marrow</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: PK</measure>
    <time_frame>Through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax of JCAR017 in blood and bone marrow</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: PK</measure>
    <time_frame>Through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax of JCAR017 in blood and bone marrow</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: health-related quality of life and health economics and outcomes research</measure>
    <time_frame>Through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>EuroQol instrument EQ-5D-5L Numbers of intensive care unit (ICU) inpatient days and non-ICU inpatient days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: health-related quality of life and health economics and outcomes research</measure>
    <time_frame>Through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>EORTC QLQ-C30 Numbers of intensive care unit (ICU) inpatient days and non-ICU inpatient days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase 2: health-related quality of life and health economics and outcomes research</measure>
    <time_frame>Through post-randomization Month 24</time_frame>
    <description>CLL-specific module QLQ-CLL Numbers of intensive care unit (ICU) inpatient days and non-ICU inpatient days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">205</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Small Lymphocytic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 JCAR017 monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be assigned to receive JCAR017 (lisocabtagene maraleucel)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 JCAR017 + ibrutinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receiving ibrutinib at baseline will be assigned to receive JCAR017 (lisocabtagene maraleucel) at the recommended dose + ibrutinib</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 JCAR017</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive JCAR017 (lisocabtagene maraleucel) at the recommended dose from the Phase 1 monotherapy arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive standard of care treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JCAR017 (lisocabtagene maraleucel)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will undergo leukapheresis to isolate peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) for the production of JCAR017. During JCAR017 production, participants may receive bridging chemotherapy for disease control. Upon successful generation of JCAR017 product, participants will receive treatment with JCAR017 therapy. Each cycle will include lymphodepleting chemotherapy followed by one dose of JCAR017 administered by intravenous (IV) injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 JCAR017 monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 JCAR017</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JCAR017 (lisocabtagene maraleucel) + ibrutinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants eligible for this cohort should be receiving ibrutinib at the time of screening, and ibrutinib treatment will continue. Participants will undergo leukapheresis to isolate peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) for the production of JCAR017. During JCAR017 production, participants may receive bridging chemotherapy for disease control. Upon successful generation of JCAR017 product, participants will receive treatment with JCAR017 therapy. Each cycle will include lymphodepleting chemotherapy followed by one dose of JCAR017 administered by intravenous (IV) injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 1 JCAR017 + ibrutinib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of care</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive standard-of-care therapy. These participants may cross over to receive treatment with JCAR017 at the time of progression.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase 2 control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of:

               1. CLL with an indication for treatment based on iwCLL guidelines and clinical
                  measurable disease, or

               2. SLL (lymphadenopathy and/or splenomegaly and &lt; 5×10^9 CD19+ CD5+ clonal B
                  lymphocytes/L [&lt; 5000/µL] in the peripheral blood at diagnosis with measurable
                  disease that is biopsy-proven SLL)

          -  Subjects (other than those in the ibrutinib + JCAR017 combination therapy arm) must
             have received and failed Bruton tyrosine kinase inhibitor (BTKi) treatment or have
             been deemed ineligible for BTKi therapy.

          -  Subjects (other than those in the ibrutinib + JCAR017 combination therapy cohort) must
             have received previous treatment as follows:

               1. Subjects with CLL or SLL and high-risk features must have failed at least 2 lines
                  of prior therapy, including a BTKi.

               2. Subjects with CLL or SLL and standard-risk features must have failed at least 3
                  lines of prior therapy, including a BTKi.

               3. Subjects with CLL or SLL who are BTKi intolerant and have received &lt; 6 months of
                  BTKi therapy or are ineligible for BTKi must have failed at least 1 (high-risk)
                  or 2 (standard-risk) other lines of non-BTKi therapy.

          -  Subjects in the ibrutinib + JCAR017 combination therapy cohort must be either:

               1. receiving ibrutinib and progressing at the time of study enrollment

               2. receiving ibrutinib for at least 6 months with a response less than CR and have
                  high-risk features as defined in inclusion criterion 5a

               3. have BTK or PLCgamma2 mutations per local laboratory assessment, with or without
                  progression on ibrutinib

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of ≤ 1

          -  Assessed by the Investigator to have adequate bone marrow function to receive
             lymphodepleting chemotherapy

          -  Adequate organ function, defined as:

               1. Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 × age-adjusted upper limit of normal (ULN) OR calculated
                  creatinine clearance &gt; 30 mL/min

               2. Alanine aminotransferase ≤ 5 × ULN and total bilirubin &lt; 2.0 mg/dL (or &lt; 3.0
                  mg/dL for subjects with Gilbert's syndrome or leukemic infiltration of the liver)

               3. Adequate pulmonary function, defined as ≤ Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse
                  Events (CTCAE) Grade 1 dyspnea and saturated oxygen (SaO2) ≥ 92% on room air

               4. Adequate cardiac function, defined as left ventricular ejection fraction ≥ 40% as
                  assessed by echocardiogram or multiple uptake gated acquisition scan performed
                  within 30 days prior to determination of eligibility

          -  Subject either currently has central vascular access or is a candidate to receive
             central vascular access or peripheral vascular access for leukapheresis procedure.

          -  If prior CD19-targeted therapy has been administered, subject must have CD19-positive
             disease confirmed by immunohistochemistry or flow cytometry since completing the prior
             CD19-targeted therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with known active CNS involvement by malignancy. Those with prior CNS disease
             that has been effectively treated will be eligible if treatment was completed at least
             3 months prior to enrollment with no evidence of symptomatic disease and stable
             abnormalities on repeat imaging.

          -  History of another primary malignancy that has not been in remission for at least 2
             years. (The following are exempt from the 2-year limit: nonmelanoma skin cancer,
             completely resected stage 1 solid tumor with low risk for recurrence, curatively
             treated localized prostate cancer, cervical carcinoma in situ on biopsy or a squamous
             intraepithelial lesion on Pap smear, and in situ breast cancer that has been
             completely resected.)

          -  Subjects with Richter's transformation

          -  Prior treatment with any gene therapy product

          -  Active hepatitis B, active hepatitis C, or any human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)
             infection

          -  Systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or other infection that is not controlled

          -  Presence of acute or extensive chronic graft versus host disease (GVHD)

          -  History of any one of the following cardiovascular conditions within the past 6
             months: Class III or IV heart failure as defined by the New York Heart Association
             (NYHA), cardiac angioplasty or stenting, myocardial infarction, unstable angina, or
             other clinically significant cardiac disease

          -  History or presence of clinically relevant CNS pathology such as epilepsy, generalized
             seizure disorder, paresis, aphasia, stroke with current neurologic sequelae, severe
             brain injuries, dementia, Parkinson's disease, cerebellar disease, or psychosis

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women

          -  Use of any of the following medications or treatments within the noted time prior to
             leukapheresis:

               1. Alemtuzumab within 6 months prior to leukapheresis

               2. Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant within 100 days prior to
                  leukapheresis

               3. Cladribine within 3 months prior to leukapheresis

               4. Donor lymphocyte infusions (DLI) within 2 months prior to leukapheresis

               5. Radiation including large bone marrow fields such as sternum or pelvis within 6
                  weeks prior to leukapheresis

               6. Fludarabine within 4 weeks prior to leukapheresis

               7. GVHD therapies such as calcineurin inhibitors, methotrexate or other
                  chemotherapeutics, mycophenolate mofetil, rapamycin, or immunosuppressive
                  antibodies (such as anti-tumor necrosis factor-α [TNFα], anti-interleukin-6
                  [IL-6], or anti-interleukin-6 receptor [IL 6R]) within 4 weeks prior to
                  leukapheresis

               8. Cyclophosphamide, ifosfamide, bendamustine, chlorambucil, or melphalan within 2
                  weeks prior to leukapheresis

               9. Therapeutic doses of corticosteroids (defined as &gt; 20 mg/day prednisone or
                  equivalent) within 7 days prior to leukapheresis

              10. Anti-CD20 monoclonal antibodies within 7 days prior to leukapheresis

              11. Venetoclax within 4 days prior to leukapheresis

              12. Idelalisib within 2 days prior to leukapheresis

              13. Lenalidomide within 1 day prior to leukapheresis

              14. Experimental agents, including off-label use of approved drugs, within 4 weeks
                  prior to leukapheresis unless progression is documented on the experimental
                  therapy and at least 3 half-lives have elapsed prior to leukapheresis

          -  Uncontrolled medical, psychological, familial, sociological, or geographical
             conditions that do not permit compliance with the protocol, as judged by the
             Investigator; or subject unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures required
             in the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Heidi Gillenwater, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Juno Therapeutics, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Juno Medical Information</last_name>
    <phone>866-599-JUNO (5866)</phone>
    <email>medicalinformation@junotherapeutics.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cara Nolan</last_name>
      <phone>626-218-3241</phone>
      <email>canolan@coh.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tanya Siddiqi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sadi Dixon, RN</last_name>
      <phone>773-702-2070</phone>
      <email>sdixon2@medicine.bsd.uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Preeti Karmali</last_name>
      <phone>773-702-9440</phone>
      <email>pkarmali@medicine.bsd.uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Riedell, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacob D Soumerai, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-4000</phone>
      <email>jsoumerai@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jacob D Soumerai, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emma Logan, RN</last_name>
      <phone>617-667-5984</phone>
      <email>eklogan@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jon Arnason, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UPMC Hillman Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Linda Fukas</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <phone>412-623-6037</phone>
      <email>fukaslj@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kathleen Dorritie, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William G Wierda, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-7026</phone>
      <email>wwierda@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William G Wierda, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>JCAR017</keyword>
  <keyword>chimeric antigen receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>CLL</keyword>
  <keyword>SLL</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic lymphocytic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>small lymphocytic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>CAR</keyword>
  <keyword>CAR T cells</keyword>
  <keyword>autologous T cell therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>immunotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

