<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03336541</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017[36]</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03336541</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Low-dose Ketamine and Postpartum Depression in Parturients With Prenatal Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Intraoperative Low-dose Ketamine on Incidence of Postpartum Depression in Parturients With Prenatal Depression Undergoing Cesarean Delivery: a Double-blind, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking University First Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University First Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postpartum depression is common in mothers early after childbirth and produces harmful
      effects not only on mothers, but also on infants and young children. Parturients with
      prenatal depression are at increased of postpartum depression. Low-dose ketamine can be used
      for antidepressant therapy. We hypothesize that low-dose ketamine has a therapeutic effect on
      parturients with prenatal depression. This study is designed to investigate whether low-dose
      ketamine administered during cesarean delivery can decrease the incidence of postpartum
      depression in parturients with prenatal depression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postpartum depression refers to maternal depression developed early after childbirth, with
      reported incidences varied from 15% to 20%. The development of postpartum depression produces
      harmful effects not only on mothers, but also on infants and young children. Prenatal
      depression or high depression score is an independent risk factor for the development of
      postpartum depression.

      Ketamine is commonly used as an general anesthetic. In addition, low-dose ketamine is
      recommended for antidepressant therapy. We hypothesize that low-dose ketamine has a
      therapeutic effect on parturients with prenatal depression. However, evidences in this aspect
      are insufficient. The purpose of this study is to investigate whether low-dose ketamine
      administered during cesarean delivery can decrease the incidence of postpartum depression in
      parturients with prenatal depression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 24, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The score of postpartum depression at 48 hous after childbirth.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 48 hours after delivery.</time_frame>
    <description>Postpartum depression is assessed with Edinburgh postnatal depression scale (EPDS) at 48 hours after childbirth. The EPDS is a 10-item self-rating post-natal depression scale. Each item is scored from 0 to 3, resulting an overall score ranging from 0-30; a high score indicates severe depression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of first breast feeding.</measure>
    <time_frame>From delivery to 24 hours after delivery.</time_frame>
    <description>Time of first breast feeding.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of neonates with breast feeding.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 24 hours after delivery.</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of neonates with breast feeding.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of neonatal sleep within 24 hours after delivery.</measure>
    <time_frame>During the first 24 hours after delivery.</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of neonatal sleep within 24 hours after delivery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay in hospital after delivery.</measure>
    <time_frame>From childbirth up to 30 days after delivery.</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay in hospital after delivery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The score of postpartum depression at 42 days after delivery.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 42 days after delivery.</time_frame>
    <description>Postpartum depression is assessed with EPDS at 42 days after childbirth.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of postpartum depression at 42 days after delivery.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 42 days after delivery.</time_frame>
    <description>Postpartum depression is assessed with EPDS at 42 days after childbirth. A EPDS score of 10 or above is defined as postpartum depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of maternal complications with 42 days after delivery.</measure>
    <time_frame>From childbirth up to 42 days after delivery.</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of maternal complications with 42 days after delivery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of neonatal complications with 42 days after delivery.</measure>
    <time_frame>From childbirth up to 42 days after delivery.</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of neonatal complications with 42 days after delivery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Perinatal Depression</condition>
  <condition>Ketamine</condition>
  <condition>Cesarean Delivery</condition>
  <condition>Postpartum Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low-dose ketamine (0.5 mg/kg in 50 ml normal saline) is intravenously infused in 40 minutes after childbirth during cesarean delivery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo (50 ml normal saline) is intravenously infused in 40 minutes after childbirth during cesarean delivery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Ketamine (0.5 mg/kg in 50 ml normal saline) will be administered by intravenous infusion in 40 minutes after childbirth during cesarean delivery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ketamine hydrochloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo (50 ml normal saline) will be administered by intravenous infusion in 40 minutes after childbirth during cesarean delivery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Normal saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Parturients with age from 18 to 34 years and scheduled for elective cesarean delivery;

          -  Prenatal depression score (EPDS) of 10 or higher;

          -  Provide written informed consents.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Refused to participate in the study;

          -  History of schizophrenia or other disease that prevent normal communication before
             delivery;

          -  Presence of contraindications to neuraxial anesthesia, including central nervous
             system diseases (such as poliomyelitis), spinal diseases (such as spinal canal tumor,
             lumbar disc prolapse, history of spinal trauma), systemic infection (such as sepsis,
             bacteremia), local infection in the site of puncture, or coagulopathy;

          -  Severe complications during pregnancy (such as severe preeclampsia, placenta accreta,
             HELLP syndrome);

          -  Severe comorbidity before pregnancy (such as severe cardiac dysfunction);

          -  Scheduled to undergo cesarean delivery under general anesthesia;

          -  Other reasons that are considered unsuitable for study participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>34 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dong-Xin Wang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University First Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dong-Xin Wang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>86 13910731903</phone>
    <email>wangdongxin@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yuan Zeng, MD</last_name>
    <phone>8610 83572460</phone>
    <email>yuan_zeng@sina.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Anesthesiology and Critical Care Medicine, Peking University First Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100034</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dong-Xin Wang, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+ 86 (10) 83572784</phone>
      <email>wangdongxin@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Shuo Wang, Master</last_name>
      <phone>+86 13521869490</phone>
      <email>13521869490@163.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patel M, Bailey RK, Jabeen S, Ali S, Barker NC, Osiezagha K. Postpartum depression: a review. J Health Care Poor Underserved. 2012 May;23(2):534-42. doi: 10.1353/hpu.2012.0037. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22643605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein A, Pearson RM, Goodman SH, Rapa E, Rahman A, McCallum M, Howard LM, Pariante CM. Effects of perinatal mental disorders on the fetus and child. Lancet. 2014 Nov 15;384(9956):1800-19. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61277-0. Epub 2014 Nov 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25455250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Verbeek T, Bockting CL, van Pampus MG, Ormel J, Meijer JL, Hartman CA, Burger H. Postpartum depression predicts offspring mental health problems in adolescence independently of parental lifetime psychopathology. J Affect Disord. 2012 Feb;136(3):948-54. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2011.08.035. Epub 2011 Sep 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21930302</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feldman R, Granat A, Pariente C, Kanety H, Kuint J, Gilboa-Schechtman E. Maternal depression and anxiety across the postpartum year and infant social engagement, fear regulation, and stress reactivity. J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009 Sep;48(9):919-27. doi: 10.1097/CHI.0b013e3181b21651.</citation>
    <PMID>19625979</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kersten-Alvarez LE, Hosman CM, Riksen-Walraven JM, van Doesum KT, Smeekens S, Hoefnagels C. Early school outcomes for children of postpartum depressed mothers: comparison with a community sample. Child Psychiatry Hum Dev. 2012 Apr;43(2):201-18. doi: 10.1007/s10578-011-0257-y.</citation>
    <PMID>22011810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raposa E, Hammen C, Brennan P, Najman J. The long-term effects of maternal depression: early childhood physical health as a pathway to offspring depression. J Adolesc Health. 2014 Jan;54(1):88-93. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2013.07.038. Epub 2013 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24060574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naicker K, Wickham M, Colman I. Timing of first exposure to maternal depression and adolescent emotional disorder in a national Canadian cohort. PLoS One. 2012;7(3):e33422. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0033422. Epub 2012 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22461893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schiller CE, Meltzer-Brody S, Rubinow DR. The role of reproductive hormones in postpartum depression. CNS Spectr. 2015 Feb;20(1):48-59. doi: 10.1017/S1092852914000480. Epub 2014 Sep 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25263255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hart AR, Farber KG, Kellner ChH. Postpartum Depression. N Engl J Med. 2017 Mar 2;376(9):895. doi: 10.1056/NEJMc1616547.</citation>
    <PMID>28252268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kingston D, McDonald S, Austin MP, Tough S. Association between Prenatal and Postnatal Psychological Distress and Toddler Cognitive Development: A Systematic Review. PLoS One. 2015 May 21;10(5):e0126929. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0126929. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25996151</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Layer RT, Popik P, Olds T, Skolnick P. Antidepressant-like actions of the polyamine site NMDA antagonist, eliprodil (SL-82.0715). Pharmacol Biochem Behav. 1995 Nov;52(3):621-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8545484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meloni D, Gambarana C, De Montis MG, Dal Prá P, Taddei I, Tagliamonte A. Dizocilpine antagonizes the effect of chronic imipramine on learned helplessness in rats. Pharmacol Biochem Behav. 1993 Oct;46(2):423-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7903459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moryl E, Danysz W, Quack G. Potential antidepressive properties of amantadine, memantine and bifemelane. Pharmacol Toxicol. 1993 Jun;72(6):394-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8361950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Papp M, Moryl E. Antidepressant activity of non-competitive and competitive NMDA receptor antagonists in a chronic mild stress model of depression. Eur J Pharmacol. 1994 Sep 22;263(1-2):1-7.</citation>
    <PMID>7821340</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Przegaliński E, Tatarczyńska E, Dereń-Wesołek A, Chojnacka-Wojcik E. Antidepressant-like effects of a partial agonist at strychnine-insensitive glycine receptors and a competitive NMDA receptor antagonist. Neuropharmacology. 1997 Jan;36(1):31-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9144639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trullas R, Skolnick P. Functional antagonists at the NMDA receptor complex exhibit antidepressant actions. Eur J Pharmacol. 1990 Aug 21;185(1):1-10.</citation>
    <PMID>2171955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanacora G, Gueorguieva R, Epperson CN, Wu YT, Appel M, Rothman DL, Krystal JH, Mason GF. Subtype-specific alterations of gamma-aminobutyric acid and glutamate in patients with major depression. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2004 Jul;61(7):705-13.</citation>
    <PMID>15237082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanacora G, Zarate CA, Krystal JH, Manji HK. Targeting the glutamatergic system to develop novel, improved therapeutics for mood disorders. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2008 May;7(5):426-37. doi: 10.1038/nrd2462. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18425072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McCullumsmith RE, Kristiansen LV, Beneyto M, Scarr E, Dean B, Meador-Woodruff JH. Decreased NR1, NR2A, and SAP102 transcript expression in the hippocampus in bipolar disorder. Brain Res. 2007 Jan 5;1127(1):108-18. Epub 2006 Nov 17.</citation>
    <PMID>17113057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paul IA, Nowak G, Layer RT, Popik P, Skolnick P. Adaptation of the N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor complex following chronic antidepressant treatments. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1994 Apr;269(1):95-102.</citation>
    <PMID>8169857</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boyer PA, Skolnick P, Fossom LH. Chronic administration of imipramine and citalopram alters the expression of NMDA receptor subunit mRNAs in mouse brain. A quantitative in situ hybridization study. J Mol Neurosci. 1998 Jun;10(3):219-33.</citation>
    <PMID>9770644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aan Het Rot M, Zarate CA Jr, Charney DS, Mathew SJ. Ketamine for depression: where do we go from here? Biol Psychiatry. 2012 Oct 1;72(7):537-47. doi: 10.1016/j.biopsych.2012.05.003. Epub 2012 Jun 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22705040</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiazGranados N, Ibrahim LA, Brutsche NE, Ameli R, Henter ID, Luckenbaugh DA, Machado-Vieira R, Zarate CA Jr. Rapid resolution of suicidal ideation after a single infusion of an N-methyl-D-aspartate antagonist in patients with treatment-resistant major depressive disorder. J Clin Psychiatry. 2010 Dec;71(12):1605-11. doi: 10.4088/JCP.09m05327blu. Epub 2010 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>20673547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katalinic N, Lai R, Somogyi A, Mitchell PB, Glue P, Loo CK. Ketamine as a new treatment for depression: a review of its efficacy and adverse effects. Aust N Z J Psychiatry. 2013 Aug;47(8):710-27. doi: 10.1177/0004867413486842. Epub 2013 May 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23661785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 6, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 6, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking University First Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dong-Xin Wang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Chairman, Department of Anesthesiology and Critical Care Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prenatal depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Ketamine</keyword>
  <keyword>Cesarean delivery</keyword>
  <keyword>Postpartum depression</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression, Postpartum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

