<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03338699</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1611017762</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03338699</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the ShangRing vs. Mogen Clamp for Early Infant Male Circumcision (EIMC) in Sub-Saharan Africa</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the ShangRing vs. Mogen Clamp for Early Infant Male Circumcision (EIMC) in Sub-Saharan Africa</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>EngenderHealth Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jhpiego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>George Washington University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rakai Health Sciences Program</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will evaluate the safety and acceptability of the topical anesthesia-based, no-flip
      ShangRing technique vs. Mogen clamp for Early Infant Male Circumcision (EIMC) in neonates and
      infants up to 60 days of life.

      The study will consist of 2 phases; a pilot phase and a field study. In the pilot phase, male
      infants of up to 60 days of life will be enrolled in three sub-Saharan countries,
      specifically Kenya, Tanzania, and Uganda. Infants will be randomized in 1:1 fashion to
      undergo EIMC using either the Mogen clamp or no-flip ShangRing technique using topical
      anesthesia. Upon completion of the pilot trial and assuming satisfactory safety results, a
      larger non-comparative field study of ShangRing EIMC will be initiated, as performed by
      non-physician providers in routine practice settings in the three sub-Saharan African
      countries.

      Total study duration will be 3 years. The pilot phase is anticipated to encompass a total of
      1 year. Completion of the field study is expected to take 2 years.

      Study Endpoints include:

        1. To compare the rates of adverse events (AEs) with the ShangRing or Mogen clamp

        2. To compare pain control, time to complete wound healing and parent satisfaction with
           EIMC using the ShangRing or Mogen clamp

        3. To compare operative time and provider preference.

        4. To assess the rate of spontaneous ring detachment with the ShangRing as a method to
           decrease the need for follow-up visits after circumcision.

        5. To assess the subpreputial microbiome of the infants prior to and after the initiation
           of circumcision

      Three correlative studies will be conducted:

        1. Penile microbiome study: In the pilot trial, the subpreputial microbiome of the infants
           undergoing circumcision will be assessed to better understand the spectrum of bacteria
           that may exist and play a role in infant circumcision.

        2. Demand creation study: During both the pilot phase and the field study, it will be
           assessed whether device-driven EIMC can be safely and effectively integrated into
           maternal and child health services as a method to promote demand creation.

        3. Cost impact study: During both the pilot phase and the field study, a comparative cost
           analysis of EIMC with ShangRing versus Mogen clamp will be performed, in addition to a
           cost analysis of ShangRing EIMC as performed in routine clinical settings in the field
           study. The costing of demand creation will also be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Male circumcision (MC) has been shown to reduce HIV incidence in men by 50-60% in three
      randomized trials, and observational studies of men circumcised in infancy or childhood have
      shown long-term protection from HIV acquisition in adulthood. MC also reduces the risk of
      human papilloma virus, herpes simplex virus type 2 in men; and Trichomonas vaginalis and
      bacterial vaginosis infections in their female partners, genital ulcer disease in both sexes,
      and reduces the risk of cervical and penile cancers. In children, circumcision also provides
      immediate benefits by protecting against urinary tract infections, phimosis, and balanitis.

      Though HIV prevention may be achieved through continued scale-up of MC in adolescents and
      adults, long-term sustainability will likely be better achieved through early infant male
      circumcision (EIMC). EIMC is technically simpler, safer, and less expensive compared to MC
      performed in older children or adults. In addition, EIMC has the benefit of more rapid wound
      healing and does not carry the risk of premature resumption of sexual activity before
      complete wound healing that has been reported in 7 to 28% of adult men after circumcision
      which may increase transmission to female partners. In several African countries, EIMC
      services have been found to be highly acceptable among parents and other caregivers.The
      long-term benefits of EIMC have led experts to recommend population-wide neonatal
      circumcision, as the benefits accrued over a child's life greatly outweigh any short-term
      risks, and delaying circumcision until adulthood places the child at risk of disease
      acquisition before the procedure can be performed. Despite these advantages, however, EIMC
      has not been significantly deployed in African countries. Part of the barrier to wider use of
      EIMC stems from the scarcity of trained providers and resources in sub-Saharan Africa.
      Device-assisted MC has therefore been proposed to simplify the procedure, enable safe
      task-shifting, and reduce the burden on healthcare providers, thus increasing the
      availability of EIMC services. While several devices are currently in use for patients of
      various ages, the use of a single device requiring only topical anesthesia across all age
      ranges would dramatically simplify supply chain logistics, streamline personnel training, and
      most importantly enhance patient/parent acceptability and demand uptake.

      This study seeks to accomplish three major goals. First, the study would evaluate the safety
      of the ShangRing vs. the Mogen clamp for EIMC. The ShangRing is the only MC device requiring
      topical anesthesia that is capable of being used across all age ranges from newborns to
      adults; its use would dramatically simplify supply chain logistics, streamline personnel
      training, and most importantly enhance patient/parent acceptability and demand uptake. The
      Mogen clamp is a pre-existing device already in use for EIMC in Africa and will serve as an
      important comparator. The use of an EIMC device that enables safe task-shifting would allow
      the integration of circumcision services into pre-existing maternal and child health (MCH)
      service infrastructure and would thereby further facilitate rapid scale-up of MC services
      throughout Africa. A penile microbiome study will also be performed to better understand the
      spectrum of bacteria present at the time of EIMC. Next, the study attempts to ascertain
      whether device-driven EIMC can be safely and effectively integrated into MCH services as a
      method to promote demand creation. As sub-Saharan countries have deployed MC services on a
      national basis, the issue of insufficient patient demand has begun to take greater prominence
      as a barrier to achieving the goal of 20.8 million MC as proposed by the World Health
      Organization (WHO) and the Joint United Nations Program on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS). The study will
      therefore examine the ability of EIMC to stimulate demand for circumcision through MCH
      services as well as identify potential barriers and strategies for wider scale programmatic
      roll-out. Finally, the study will also attempt to assess the economic burden of device-driven
      EIMC. In a context of limited resources, understanding the economic burden of a device-driven
      EIMC program will be critical in ascertaining its long-term feasibility and sustainability in
      sub-Saharan Africa.

      All subjects will be recruited for the study at the 3 designated study sites; Homa Bay,
      Kenya; Iringa, Tanzania; and Rakai, Uganda. Subjects will be registered to take part in the
      study through their parents/legally acceptable representatives (LARs) who will be required to
      sign an informed consent after they agree to the enrollment of their infant. Parents/LARs are
      first familiarized with the procedures and provided with the information on the risks and
      benefits of EIMC using WHO/JHPIEGO guidelines.

      Each infant will be enrolled in this study for a total of 42 days (or longer if wound healing
      is incomplete). Circumcision will take place on day 0, and weekly follow-up visits will be
      conducted until complete wound healing is documented for the pilot study. For the field
      study, follow-up will occur on days 7 and 42 only.

      Participation in this study is voluntary. Any parent/LAR is free to discontinue their
      infant's participation at any point in time. When further participation in the study is not
      desired, even while the ring is still on, treatment will be administered as if the infant was
      in the study. However, participation for the entire length of the study is encouraged until
      the infant is fully healed.

      The study doctor or his designee can stop an infant's participation in a study if:

        -  Continuing in the study could harm the infant

        -  The study is stopped.

      Clinical data will be obtained and recorded using either 1) electronic Clinical Research
      Forms (eCRFs) that are loaded on mobile tablets or 2) paper forms. The information that will
      be obtained includes questionnaires, medical history, physical exam findings, details of the
      EIMC procedure, and clinical follow-up parameters. Once an eCRF is completed, the data will
      be encrypted on the collecting devices and submitted through a secure connection to the
      database server. No copy of the information will be left on the electronic device after it
      has been transferred to the database server. This will ensure that there will be no risk of
      unauthorized access to the data even in the case of device misplacement. All devices that
      will be used to collect data shall, upon completion of the day's activity, be locked in the
      study cabinets in a locked room. All electronic data will be backed-up on paper, and security
      will be ensured by storing the data in a locked cabinet. Data access will only be provided to
      primary researchers or their designees, and the data set will only be used for the research
      question asked.

      Informed consent forms and participant contact information will not be obtained using
      electronic media but will instead be obtained using written forms that will be stored in
      locked cabinets at the study sites.

      -Pilot Phase A total sample size of 460 eligible infants in Homa Bay, Kenya, 460 eligible
      infants in Rakai, Uganda, and 460 eligible infants in Iringa, Tanzania will be enrolled,
      assuming successful recruitment and follow-up of a total of 1200 (87%) patients, or 400
      patients per site. The anticipated accrual rate is 115 infants per month across the three
      sites. Infants will be randomized in a 1:1 fashion using a randomization software to EIMC
      with the ShangRing or the Mogen clamp, resulting in 200 infants receiving ShangRing
      circumcision and 200 receiving Mogen clamp per site.

      This sample size exceeds the recommendations from the World Health Organization for the
      comparative trial component of the clinical evaluation of MC devices, which is based on an
      ability to rule out an adverse event (AE) rate of about 5% or more with a new use of a device
      that has already been shown to be previously safe in a larger group of men in randomized
      controlled trials (RCTs) and demonstration studies. The primary endpoint will be safety as
      determined by the rate of moderate to severe AEs using an intention to treat analysis.

      Sample size justification: The goal of this study is to determine if the AE rate using
      ShangRing is not inferior to that for Mogen clamp. The control arm is the Mogen clamp and the
      anticipated moderate/severe AE rate is 2%. It is felt that the benefits of ShangRing in terms
      of convenience and acceptability will allow a non-inferiority margin of 2% (absolute). A
      sample size of 1200 infants (600 per arm), with one formal interim analysis for futility, has
      approximately 80% power with a (one-sided) alpha = 0.05. The null hypothesis for the
      non-inferiority test is that the moderate/severe AE rate for the ShangRing is at least 2%
      (absolute) greater than that of Mogen clamp, which is assumed to be 2%. The alternative
      hypothesis is that the rate of the ShangRing is less than 2% great than that of the Mogen
      clamp.

      -Field Study The WHO recommends that the field study component of clinical assessment involve
      at least 500 clients per country in two countries of intended use. As such, a total sample
      size of 600 eligible infants in Homa Bay, Kenya; 600 eligible infants in Rakai, Uganda; and
      600 eligible infants in Iringa, Tanzania will be enrolled, assuming successful recruitment
      and follow-up of a total of 1500 (83%) patients, or 500 patients per country.

      Sample size justification: A sample size of 1500 patients will have a 95% confidence interval
      margin-of-error of 0.007 to 0.010 for the moderate/severe AE rate estimate, assuming the
      observed rate is between 0.02 and 0.04. This provides adequate precision for the estimate of
      the severe AE rate in order to make decisions as to whether this device is safe when used in
      the field.

      AEs will be pre-specified based on WHO/JHPIEGO definitions of the nature and severity of AEs,
      and classified as related or unrelated to EIMC.

      -Statistical considerations and data analysis AE rates, pain control, wound healing, and
      parent/provider satisfaction between groups will be compared using chi-square tests,
      two-group t-tests. If the variable distributions violate the underlying assumptions of these
      tests, the corresponding non-parametric tests will be used (e.g. Wilcoxon rank sum test,
      Fisher's exact test). Analyses will be for all sites, and site-specific. Multivariable models
      will be used to adjust for imbalances in baseline characteristics significant at p&lt;0.10 using
      logistic regression to estimate adjusted odds ratios of moderate/severe AEs by arm. For
      outcomes with an incidence &lt;10%, the modified Poisson regression will be used to estimate
      adjusted prevalence rate ratios.

      A formal interim analysis will be conducted after 200 circumcisions have been completed.
      Study accrual will be suspended for the interim analysis. The analysis will be for futility
      only. If after 200 infants have been enrolled and followed for 42 days it is found that the
      (non-inferiority) p-value is 0.97 or greater (corresponding to a z-statistic of 1.91 or
      greater) the trial will be recommended to stop due to futility.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In the pilot phase of the study, participating infants will be allocated to circumcision with either the ShangRing or Mogen clamp. Infants will be randomized in a 1:1 fashion.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and severity of adverse events in participants undergoing circumcision with either device based on WHO/JHPIEGO definitions and guidelines.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 weeks post-circumcision.</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events will be pre-specified based on WHO/JHPIEGO definitions of the nature and severity of adverse events, and classified as related or unrelated to EIMC. Adverse events will also include device-related malfunctions and displacements.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain scores associated with the circumcision procedure by either device, assessed using the Neonatal Infant Pain Scale (NIPS).</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of circumcision procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>Pain scores will be recorded at the time of circumcision procedure using NIPS. NIPS is based on facial expression, crying, breathing patterns, movement of arms and legs, and state of arousal of the infant. A score of 0 is classified as no pain while a score of 6 is most severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to complete wound healing based on having an intact clean scar with no dehiscence.</measure>
    <time_frame>Till complete wound healing is reported, up to 8 weeks post-circumcision.</time_frame>
    <description>Circumcision wound is examined at each follow-up visit to check for complete healing. Additional follow-up visits may be needed if complete healing was not reported at the end of scheduled visits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent satisfaction based on post-circumcision interviews.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 weeks post-circumcision.</time_frame>
    <description>Parents will be interviewed after their infant had undergone circumcision to express their views on the procedure. They will be required to note whether they are satisfied or dissatisfied about different aspects relating to the procedure and the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operative time measured in minutes.</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of circumcision on procedure day.</time_frame>
    <description>Providers will record, in minutes, the amount of time required to complete the circumcision procedure with the ShangRing and Mogen clamp. Recorded time will not include duration of anesthesia administration, or duration for the anesthetic to take effect.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Provider preference of circumcision device based on post-circumcision interviews.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 weeks post-circumcision.</time_frame>
    <description>Health providers who will perform the circumcision procedures using the ShangRing and Mogen clamp will be interviewed to express their views and degree of satisfaction with the devices.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spontaneous detachment as a measure to decrease the need of follow-up visits based on the amount of time, in days, it takes for the device to fall off on its own.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks post-circumcision.</time_frame>
    <description>Parents/LARs of infants who underwent ShangRing circumcision will be asked about the date of device detachment if the device is no longer attached at the time of visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1380</enrollment>
  <condition>Circumcision</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ShangRing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Topical anesthesia based, no-flip ShangRing circumcision.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mogen clamp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mogen clamp circumcision.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ShangRing</intervention_name>
    <description>Topical anesthesia based, no-flip ShangRing circumcision.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ShangRing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mogen clamp</intervention_name>
    <description>Mogen clamp circumcision</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mogen clamp</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male infants from 24 hours up to 60 days of life

          2. Gestational age ≥37 weeks

          3. Normal birth weight (≥2.5 Kg)

          4. No illness requiring medical treatment

          5. No penile abnormality requiring surgical repair (e.g. hypospadias, chordee)

          6. No family history of bleeding disorders

          7. Consent provided by at least one parent/legally acceptable representative (LAR) of the
             infant

               1. Parent or LAR must be able to understand study procedures and requirements of
                  study participation;

               2. Parent or LAR must agree to return the client to the study site for the full
                  schedule of follow-up visits after his circumcision;

               3. Parent or LAR must have a cell phone or access to a cell phone

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not meeting one or more of the inclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>All participants in this study are male who will undergo early infant circumcision.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard K Lee, MD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philip S Li, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard K Lee, MD, MBA</last_name>
    <phone>+1 212-746-4811</phone>
    <email>ril9010@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Philip S Li, MD</last_name>
    <email>psli@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Homa Bay County Teaching and Referral Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Homa Bay</city>
        <country>Kenya</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Quentin Awori, MD MPH</last_name>
      <phone>+254 722 913616</phone>
      <email>qawori@engenderhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Iringa Regional Referral Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iringa</city>
        <country>Tanzania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alice Christensen, RN MSc CNS</last_name>
      <phone>+255 766 698 097</phone>
      <email>alice.christensen@jhpiego.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rakai Health Sciences Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kalisizo</city>
        <state>Rakai</state>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Godfrey Kigozi, MbChB PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+256 701 444144</phone>
      <email>gkigozi@rhsp.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Kenya</country>
    <country>Tanzania</country>
    <country>Uganda</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/hiv/pub/malecircumcision/manual_infant/en/</url>
    <description>Manual for early infant male circumcision under local anaesthesia</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/hiv/topics/malecircumcision/male-circumcision-info-2014/en/</url>
    <description>WHO Progress Brief - Voluntary medical male circumcision for HIV prevention in priority countries of East and Southern Africa</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bailey RC, Moses S, Parker CB, Agot K, Maclean I, Krieger JN, Williams CF, Campbell RT, Ndinya-Achola JO. Male circumcision for HIV prevention in young men in Kisumu, Kenya: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2007 Feb 24;369(9562):643-56.</citation>
    <PMID>17321310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gray RH, Kigozi G, Serwadda D, Makumbi F, Watya S, Nalugoda F, Kiwanuka N, Moulton LH, Chaudhary MA, Chen MZ, Sewankambo NK, Wabwire-Mangen F, Bacon MC, Williams CF, Opendi P, Reynolds SJ, Laeyendecker O, Quinn TC, Wawer MJ. Male circumcision for HIV prevention in men in Rakai, Uganda: a randomised trial. Lancet. 2007 Feb 24;369(9562):657-66.</citation>
    <PMID>17321311</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Auvert B, Taljaard D, Lagarde E, Sobngwi-Tambekou J, Sitta R, Puren A. Randomized, controlled intervention trial of male circumcision for reduction of HIV infection risk: the ANRS 1265 Trial. PLoS Med. 2005 Nov;2(11):e298. Epub 2005 Oct 25. Erratum in: PLoS Med. 2006 May;3(5):e298.</citation>
    <PMID>16231970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tobian AA, Kigozi G, Wawer MJ, Serwadda D, Quinn TC, Gray RH. Herpes simplex virus type-2 assay specificity and male circumcision to reduce herpes simplex virus type-2 acquisition. AIDS. 2013 Jan 2;27(1):147-9. doi: 10.1097/QAD.0b013e32835aa181.</citation>
    <PMID>23221430</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tobian AA, Serwadda D, Quinn TC, Kigozi G, Gravitt PE, Laeyendecker O, Charvat B, Ssempijja V, Riedesel M, Oliver AE, Nowak RG, Moulton LH, Chen MZ, Reynolds SJ, Wawer MJ, Gray RH. Male circumcision for the prevention of HSV-2 and HPV infections and syphilis. N Engl J Med. 2009 Mar 26;360(13):1298-309. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0802556.</citation>
    <PMID>19321868</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tobian AA, Gray RH. The medical benefits of male circumcision. JAMA. 2011 Oct 5;306(13):1479-80. doi: 10.1001/jama.2011.1431.</citation>
    <PMID>21972310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pintye J, Baeten JM, Manhart LE, Celum C, Ronald A, Mugo N, Mujugira A, Cohen C, Were E, Bukusi E, Kiarie J, Heffron R; Partners PrEP Study Team. Association between male circumcision and incidence of syphilis in men and women: a prospective study in HIV-1 serodiscordant heterosexual African couples. Lancet Glob Health. 2014 Nov;2(11):e664-71. doi: 10.1016/S2214-109X(14)70315-8. Epub 2014 Oct 22.</citation>
    <PMID>25442691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tobian AA, Gray RH, Quinn TC. Male circumcision for the prevention of acquisition and transmission of sexually transmitted infections: the case for neonatal circumcision. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2010 Jan;164(1):78-84. doi: 10.1001/archpediatrics.2009.232.</citation>
    <PMID>20048246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>UNAIDS/WHO/SACEMA Expert Group on Modelling the Impact and Cost of Male Circumcision for HIV Prevention. Male circumcision for HIV prevention in high HIV prevalence settings: what can mathematical modelling contribute to informed decision making? PLoS Med. 2009 Sep;6(9):e1000109. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1000109. Epub 2009 Sep 8. Review. Erratum in: PLoS Med. 2009 Dec;6(12). doi: 10.1371/annotation/f1c3679d-18d8-4fbd-bd3f-59db0b284b19.</citation>
    <PMID>19901974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Binagwaho A, Pegurri E, Muita J, Bertozzi S. Male circumcision at different ages in Rwanda: a cost-effectiveness study. PLoS Med. 2010 Jan 19;7(1):e1000211. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1000211.</citation>
    <PMID>20098721</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalichman SC. Neonatal circumcision for HIV prevention: Cost, culture, and behavioral considerations. PLoS Med. 2010 Jan 19;7(1):e1000219. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1000219.</citation>
    <PMID>20098515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kigozi G, Gray RH, Wawer MJ, Serwadda D, Makumbi F, Watya S, Nalugoda F, Kiwanuka N, Moulton LH, Chen MZ, Sewankambo NK, Wabwire-Mangen F, Bacon MC, Ridzon R, Opendi P, Sempijja V, Settuba A, Buwembo D, Kiggundu V, Anyokorit M, Nkale J, Kighoma N, Charvat B. The safety of adult male circumcision in HIV-infected and uninfected men in Rakai, Uganda. PLoS Med. 2008 Jun 3;5(6):e116. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.0050116.</citation>
    <PMID>18532873</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hewett PC, Hallett TB, Mensch BS, Dzekedzeke K, Zimba-Tembo S, Garnett GP, Todd PE. Sex with stitches: assessing the resumption of sexual activity during the postcircumcision wound-healing period. AIDS. 2012 Mar 27;26(6):749-56. doi: 10.1097/QAD.0b013e32835097ff.</citation>
    <PMID>22269970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mugwanya KK, Whalen C, Celum C, Nakku-Joloba E, Katabira E, Baeten JM. Circumcision of male children for reduction of future risk for HIV: acceptability among HIV serodiscordant couples in Kampala, Uganda. PLoS One. 2011;6(7):e22254. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0022254. Epub 2011 Jul 20.</citation>
    <PMID>21799805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Westercamp N, Bailey RC. Acceptability of male circumcision for prevention of HIV/AIDS in sub-Saharan Africa: a review. AIDS Behav. 2007 May;11(3):341-55. Epub 2006 Oct 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17053855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plank RM, Makhema J, Kebaabetswe P, Hussein F, Lesetedi C, Halperin D, Bassil B, Shapiro R, Lockman S. Acceptability of infant male circumcision as part of HIV prevention and male reproductive health efforts in Gaborone, Botswana, and surrounding areas. AIDS Behav. 2010 Oct;14(5):1198-202. doi: 10.1007/s10461-009-9632-0.</citation>
    <PMID>19924526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waters E, Li M, Mugisa B, Bowa K, Linyama D, Stringer E, Stringer J. Acceptability and uptake of neonatal male circumcision in Lusaka, Zambia. AIDS Behav. 2013 Jul;17(6):2114-22. doi: 10.1007/s10461-012-0297-8.</citation>
    <PMID>22968397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young MR, Odoyo-June E, Nordstrom SK, Irwin TE, Ongong'a DO, Ochomo B, Agot K, Bailey RC. Factors associated with uptake of infant male circumcision for HIV prevention in western Kenya. Pediatrics. 2012 Jul;130(1):e175-82. doi: 10.1542/peds.2011-2290. Epub 2012 Jun 18.</citation>
    <PMID>22711723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albert LM, Akol A, L'Engle K, Tolley EE, Ramirez CB, Opio A, Tumwesigye NM, Thomsen S, Neema S, Baine SO. Acceptability of male circumcision for prevention of HIV infection among men and women in Uganda. AIDS Care. 2011 Dec;23(12):1578-85. doi: 10.1080/09540121.2011.579939. Epub 2011 Jul 7.</citation>
    <PMID>21732902</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mavhu W, Hatzold K, Laver SM, Sherman J, Tengende BR, Mangenah C, Langhaug LF, Hart G, Cowan FM. Acceptability of early infant male circumcision as an HIV prevention intervention in Zimbabwe: a qualitative perspective. PLoS One. 2012;7(2):e32475. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0032475. Epub 2012 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>22384258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jarrett P, Kliner M, Walley J. Early infant male circumcision for human immunodeficiency virus prevention: knowledge and attitudes of women attending a rural hospital in Swaziland, Southern Africa. SAHARA J. 2014;11:61-6. doi: 10.1080/17290376.2014.929530. Epub 2014 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24957082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young MR, Bailey RC, Odoyo-June E, Irwin TE, Obiero W, Ongong'a DO, Badia JA, Agot K, Nordstrom SK. Safety of over twelve hundred infant male circumcisions using the Mogen clamp in Kenya. PLoS One. 2012;7(10):e47395. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0047395. Epub 2012 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>23082162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kankaka EN, Murungi T, Kigozi G, Makumbi F, Nabukalu D, Watya S, Kighoma N, Nampijja R, Kayiwa D, Nalugoda F, Serwadda D, Wawer M, Gray RH. Randomised trial of early infant circumcision performed by clinical officers and registered nurse midwives using the Mogen clamp in Rakai, Uganda. BJU Int. 2017 Jan;119(1):164-170. doi: 10.1111/bju.13589. Epub 2016 Sep 6.</citation>
    <PMID>27597563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Early infant male circumcision</keyword>
  <keyword>ShangRing</keyword>
  <keyword>sub-Saharan Africa</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>WHO</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data will only be shared among study investigators and authorized personnel at the designated study sites. IPD will not be shared with anyone not involved in the design, planning, or execution of the study.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

