<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03338517</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REC/012/001255</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03338517</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Helium-Neon Laser Therapy Versus Infrared Laser Therapy in Treating Patients With Diabetic Foot Ulcer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial Comparing Helium-Neon Laser Therapy and Infrared Laser Therapy in Patients With Diabetic Foot Ulcer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ahlia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ahlia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Diabetic patients are frequently showed with foot ulceration as a common
      complication which increases to 20% in admission. Low-level laser therapy is used to control
      foot ulcer, but there is very limited data to compare the effects of Helium-Neon Laser
      therapy (HNLT) and Infrared Laser therapy (ILT) on diabetic foot ulcer.

      Objectives: This study aimed to compare the effects of (HNLT) and (ILT) on diabetic foot
      ulcer.

      Methods: Sixty-five patients with diabetic foot ulcer (51 males and 14 females) aged
      50-60years. The participants were classified randomly to two groups, Helium-Neon Laser
      therapy (HNLT) and Infrared Laser therapy (ILT) groups. HNLT group received medical treatment
      with Helium-Neon Laser therapy and ILT group received medical treatment with Infrared Laser
      therapy for 8 weeks. Ulcer surface area was assessed using a sheet of cellophane paper at the
      beginning of the study, after four weeks, and after eight weeks at the end of the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study was carried out after obtaining ethical approval from the Department of surgery,
      Cairo University Hospitals, Egypt. Patients with varying stages of diabetic foot ulcers in
      the hospital were screened and included in the study. 65 diabetic patients with Grade I and
      II ulcers were selected according to Wagner classification, ages ranged between 50 to 60
      years of age, BMI of 30 free from any metabolic-related medical conditions such as
      nephropathy, cardiomyopathy, recent myocardial infarction and pulmonary problems. Patients
      were randomized into two groups; Group (I) who received medical treatment with Helium-Neon
      Laser therapy (HNLT), (ASA Medical laser device (manufactured by ASA Terza- Via Alessandro,
      Italy) and Group (II) who received medical treatment with Infrared Laser therapy (ILT),
      (PHYACTION 792/796 manufactured in The Netherlands by Uniphy BV). The nature of the therapy
      was described and explained to the patient. A written informed consent was obtained prior to
      implementation of the study. Patients were subjected to detailed medical examination.
      Glucosylated Homoglobin (HbA1c) was obtained for patient screening.

      Outcome measures Ulcer surface area was calculated by getting the impression of the ulcer
      floor using a sheet of cellophane paper. The imprint of the ulcer floor is transferred to
      graphing paper where ulcer size was plotted and diameter was recorded. Ulcer size was
      measured at the beginning of the study, after 4 weeks, and after 8 weeks at the end of study.

      The position of patient was a comfortable position with disclosure of the affected foot.
      Transparent plastic films were double sterilized and directly placed flat and connected to
      the skin at the ulcer area with nullifing any motion or misrepresentation of the affected
      foot. The margins of the ulcer were followed by the same investigator to set up the
      measurements reliability16.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 4, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 3, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 3, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Group (I) who received medical treatment with Helium-Neon Laser therapy (HNLT), (ASA Medical laser device (manufactured by ASA Terza- Via Alessandro, Italy) and Group (II) who received medical treatment with Infrared Laser therapy (ILT), (PHYACTION 792/796 manufactured in The Netherlands by Uniphy BV). The nature of the therapy was described and explained to the patient.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ulcer surface area</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Laser</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Helium Neon Laser</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Helium Neon Laser</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with Grade I and II ulcers were selected according to Wagner classification
             ages ranged between 50 to 60 years of age, BMI of 30

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  nephropathy, cardiomyopathy, recent myocardial infarction and pulmonary problems
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sayed A A Tantawy</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Cairo University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 5, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ahlia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Sayed Tantawy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Foot</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

