<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03335449</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10398/14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03335449</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects on Respiratory Mechanics of Two Different Ventilation Strategies During Robotic-Gynecological Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects on Respiratory Mechanics of Two Different Ventilation Strategies During Robotic-Gynecological Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>dott giorgia spinazzola</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Policlinico Universitario Agostino Gemelli</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Randomized controlled clinical study, entitled &quot;Effects on Respiratory mechanics of two
      different ventilation strategies during Robotic- Gynecological surgery&quot;, is an original
      paper. The study was performed in Rome, Italy, from September 2014 to September 2015.

      Nowadays several studies evaluated the effects of &quot;open lung strategy&quot; and the positive
      effect of Recruitment Maneuvers and Positive End Expiratory Pressure (PEEP) application
      during general anesthesia, especially during open abdominal surgery and in elderly patients.

      This is the first study aimed at evaluating two different ventilation strategies in healthy
      respiratory women undergoing Robotic surgery. In particular, the investigators evaluated the
      effects of protective ventilation strategy on respiratory mechanics, gas exchange and
      post-operative respiratory complications compared to standard ventilation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The ventilation protocol consisted in volume-controlled mechanical ventilation through
      Ventilator, inspiratory to expiratory ratio of 1:2, and a respiratory rate adjusted to
      normocapnia (end-tidal carbon dioxide partial pressure between 30 and 40 mmHg). The were
      randomly assigned to Standard (SV) or Protective (PV) group.

      participants in the SV group received a Tidal Volume (Vt) of 10 ml/kg of Ideal Body Weight
      (IBW) and a PEEP of 5 cmH2O, the participants in the PV group a Vt of 6 ml/kg of IBW and a
      PEEP of 8-10 cmH2O, associated to recruitment maneuvers (RMs).

      RMs were performed only in hemodynamic stable conditions and at pre-set moments: after the
      induction of anesthesia, after any disconnection from the mechanical ventilator, each hour
      during the surgical procedures and immediately before extubation. RMs were performed in
      Pressure Control mode as follows: the limit of peak inspiratory pressure was set at 45 cmH2O
      and the pressure control was set at 30 cmH2O, therefore three consecutive thirty seconds
      lasting inspiratory pauses were performed. At the end of RMs, respiratory rate, inspiratory
      to expiratory ratio, inspiratory pause, and Vt were set back at values preceding the RMs.

      Air Flow (V') was measured with a heated pneumotachograph, inserted between the Y-piece of
      the ventilator circuit and the endotracheal tube. The pneumotachograph was linear over the
      experimental range of flow. Volume was obtained by numerical integration of the flow signal.
      Airway pressure (Paw) was measured proximal to the endotracheal tube with a pressure
      transducer with a differential pressure of ± 100 cm H2O. The end-inspiratory and
      end-expiratory occlusions were performed through specific maneuver of ventilator.

      Following end-inspiratory occlusion there is an immediate drop of the airway pressure from a
      maximal value (Pmax) to airway pressure at zero flow (P1), followed by a further decrease to
      plateau pressure (P2). The plateau pressure usually arrived within 3 seconds. Therefore,
      airway pressure 3 seconds after occlusion was taken as the static end-inspiratory elastic
      recoil pressure (P2) of the respiratory system. The use of the interrupter method for the
      measurement of respiratory mechanics allows possible quantification of the airway and
      viscoelastic properties of the respiratory system. The difference between Pmax and P1 divided
      by flow provides major information about minimal airway resistance (Rmin), while the
      difference between P1 and P2 (ΔP) divided by flow stands for viscoelastic resistance or
      Pendelluft effect of the respiratory system (ΔR). Maximal respiratory resistance (Rmax) is
      the sum of Rmin and ΔR. The inspiratory volume divided by P2- Total PEEP yields respiratory
      system compliance. Mechanical respiratory measurements and arterial blood gases were
      performed immediately after intubation, after pneumoperitoneum (AP), every hour during the
      procedure and before extubation (Ext). A further arterial blood gas sample was analyzed 1
      hour after extubation.

      The day after the surgical procedure, clinical patient examination and chest x ray were
      performed, in order to detect eventual pulmonary adverse events.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 30, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 1, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory Compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>inspiratory Volume/Plateau Pressure-PEEP (ml/cmH2O)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Mechanics</condition>
  <condition>Mechanical Ventilation Complication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Protective ventilation group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Protective ventilation (PV group) (Vt 6 ml/Kg of ideal body weight, PEEP 8-10 cmH 2 O and repeated recruitment maneuvers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard ventilation group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard ventilation (SV group) (Tidal Volume, Vt 10 ml/Kg of ideal body weight, Positive End Expiratory Pressure, PEEP 5 cmH 2 O, no recruitment maneuvers)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Protective ventilation group</intervention_name>
    <description>Application of a protective ventilation strategy in order to improve gas exchange and respiratory mechanics during Robotic surgery in deep Trendelenburg position.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Protective ventilation group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Low tidal volume, high PEEP and recruitment maneuvers</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Gynecological cancer elegible for laparoscopic surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Respiratory disease

          -  Obesity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serpa Neto A, Cardoso SO, Manetta JA, Pereira VG, Espósito DC, Pasqualucci Mde O, Damasceno MC, Schultz MJ. Association between use of lung-protective ventilation with lower tidal volumes and clinical outcomes among patients without acute respiratory distress syndrome: a meta-analysis. JAMA. 2012 Oct 24;308(16):1651-9. doi: 10.1001/jama.2012.13730.</citation>
    <PMID>23093163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Valenza F, Chevallard G, Fossali T, Salice V, Pizzocri M, Gattinoni L. Management of mechanical ventilation during laparoscopic surgery. Best Pract Res Clin Anaesthesiol. 2010 Jun;24(2):227-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20608559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fahy BG, Barnas GM, Flowers JL, Nagle SE, Njoku MJ. The effects of increased abdominal pressure on lung and chest wall mechanics during laparoscopic surgery. Anesth Analg. 1995 Oct;81(4):744-50.</citation>
    <PMID>7574004</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perilli V, Sollazzi L, Bozza P, Modesti C, Chierichini A, Tacchino RM, Ranieri R. The effects of the reverse trendelenburg position on respiratory mechanics and blood gases in morbidly obese patients during bariatric surgery. Anesth Analg. 2000 Dec;91(6):1520-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11094011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maracajá-Neto LF, Verçosa N, Roncally AC, Giannella A, Bozza FA, Lessa MA. Beneficial effects of high positive end-expiratory pressure in lung respiratory mechanics during laparoscopic surgery. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2009 Feb;53(2):210-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1399-6576.2008.01826.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19175578</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Talab HF, Zabani IA, Abdelrahman HS, Bukhari WL, Mamoun I, Ashour MA, Sadeq BB, El Sayed SI. Intraoperative ventilatory strategies for prevention of pulmonary atelectasis in obese patients undergoing laparoscopic bariatric surgery. Anesth Analg. 2009 Nov;109(5):1511-6. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e3181ba7945.</citation>
    <PMID>19843790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Policlinico Universitario Agostino Gemelli</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>dott giorgia spinazzola</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Physician, specialist in Anesthesia and Intensive Care Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

