<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01154868</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00035937</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01154868</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical and Histological Evaluation of Healos® for Alveolar Ridge Augmentation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical and Histological Evaluation of Healos® for Alveolar Ridge Augmentation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>William Giannobile</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to document and evaluate how a bone graft material (Healos®) can
      help rebuild bone width. Dental implants can only be placed when enough bone is found and
      this bone graft may help to rebuild bone width for dental implant placement. The ultimate
      goal of this study is to evaluate how this graft material can help bone healing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Sponsor withdrew funding of study.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>horizontal (width) bone gain or loss in millimeters.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>radiographic bone changes measured using computer tomography</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>percentage of new bone formation in the alveolar bone core biopsies.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Implantation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healos</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alveolar ridge augmentation</intervention_name>
    <description>Under local anesthesia, full-thickness mucoperiosteal flaps will be elevated, followed by degranulation, and collection of all clinical measurements. Crestal and vertical releasing cuts will be performed using diamond-coated discs on the edentulous ridge in need of augmentation. A sequence of bone chisels and osteotomes will be used to split the alveolar ridge in half until a desirable width for implant placement is achieved. Healos® will then be inserted between both osseous plates. Fixation screws will be used as needed to stabilize the expanded alveolar ridge. Collagen barrier membranes (Ossix Plus) will be used to cover the osseous wound. Flaps will be approximated to achieve primary wound closure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healos</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Healos</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age 21 and older

          -  2-4 ADJACENT maxillary front teeth missing

          -  require ridge augmentation and dental implant

          -  nonsmoker for at least 6 months

          -  willing to follow oral hygiene instruction and other study instruction

          -  able to read, understand and sign informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Residual upper jaw bone equal to or narrower than 3mm.

          -  Insufficient gum tissue to obtain wound closure after surgery.

          -  Clinically significant or unstable (as defined by the investigators) systemic diseases
             affecting bone or soft tissue growth; or other kidney, liver, heart, thyroid, blood,
             autoimmune or acute infectious diseases that makes interpretation of the data more
             difficult

          -  A history of head &amp; neck radiation treatment due to certain medical conditions.

          -  Taking steroids, tetracycline or tetracycline analogs, bone therapeutic levels of
             fluorides, bisphosphonates, medications affecting bone turnover, antibiotics for &gt;7
             days or any investigational drug

          -  Pregnancy or become pregnant during the length of the study

          -  Wearing removable partial dentures that may put pressure over the area where the bone
             graft will be placed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Giannobile, DDS, DMedSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michigan Center for Oral Health Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engler WO, Ramfjord SP, Hiniker JJ. Healing following simple gingivectomy. A tritiated thymidine radioautographic study. I. Epithelialization. J Periodontol. 1966 Jul-Aug;37(4):298-308.</citation>
    <PMID>4287364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ramfjord SP, Engler WO, Hiniker JJ. A radioautographic study of healing following simple gingivectomy. II. The connective tissue. J Periodontol. 1966 May-Jun;37(3):179-89.</citation>
    <PMID>4956575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>HURLEY LA, STINCHFIELD FE, BASSETT AL, LYON WH. The role of soft tissues in osteogenesis. An experimental study of canine spine fusions. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 1959 Oct;41-A:1243-54.</citation>
    <PMID>13852565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>MURRAY G, HOLDEN R, ROSCHLAU W. Experimental and clinical study of new growth of bone in a cavity. Am J Surg. 1957 Mar;93(3):385-7.</citation>
    <PMID>13403056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buser DA, Tonetti M. Clinical trials on implants in regenerated bone. Ann Periodontol. 1997 Mar;2(1):329-42. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9151565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scipioni A, Calesini G, Micarelli C, Coppè S, Scipioni L. Morphogenic bone splitting: description of an original technique and its application in esthetically significant areas. Int J Prosthodont. 2008 Sep-Oct;21(5):389-97.</citation>
    <PMID>18950058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simion M, Baldoni M, Zaffe D. Jawbone enlargement using immediate implant placement associated with a split-crest technique and guided tissue regeneration. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 1992;12(6):462-73.</citation>
    <PMID>1298734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engelke WG, Diederichs CG, Jacobs HG, Deckwer I. Alveolar reconstruction with splitting osteotomy and microfixation of implants. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 1997 May-Jun;12(3):310-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9197095</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coatoam GW, Mariotti A. The segmental ridge-split procedure. J Periodontol. 2003 May;74(5):757-70.</citation>
    <PMID>12816307</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basa S, Varol A, Turker N. Alternative bone expansion technique for immediate placement of implants in the edentulous posterior mandibular ridge: a clinical report. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2004 Jul-Aug;19(4):554-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15346753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neen D, Noyes D, Shaw M, Gwilym S, Fairlie N, Birch N. Healos and bone marrow aspirate used for lumbar spine fusion: a case controlled study comparing healos with autograft. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2006 Aug 15;31(18):E636-40.</citation>
    <PMID>16915079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 30, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 1, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 11, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 11, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 14, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>William Giannobile</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>William Giannobile, D.D.S., D.Med.Sc.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

