<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01151384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LE-DT-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01151384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Liposome Encapsulated Docetaxel (LE-DT) in Patients With Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <acronym>LE-DT</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study of Liposome Encapsulated Docetaxel (LE-DT) in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>INSYS Therapeutics Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>INSYS Therapeutics Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Liposome Encapsulated Docetaxel (LE-DT) is a novel proprietary delivery system of docetaxel
      developed by NeoPharm, Inc. In this Phase I study, the LE-DT was evaluated for the maximum
      tolerated dose and dose limiting toxicity (DLT) in patients with advance solid tumors. It was
      also evaluated for pharmacokinetic and anti-tumor effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Liposome Entrapped Doxetaxel (LE-DT) is a novel, proprietary delivery system of docetaxel
      developed by NeoPharm, Inc. Docetaxel (currently marketed as Taxotere®) is an
      anti-microtubule agent that prevents cell division by promoting the assembly and
      stabilization of microtubules and is used for the treatment of malignancies from breast,
      prostate, lung, gastric, head and neck. By removing toxic detergent used in Taxotere®, LE-DT
      showed reduced toxicity and comparable therapeutic efficacy in preclinical studies. In
      clinic, it is believed that LE-DT will offer advantages to the patient of fewer side effects
      at similar doses, and possibly greater effectiveness when used at higher doses. In addition,
      routine premedication to prevent hypersensitivity may not be required.

      This study is designed to determine the following:

        -  The maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and dose limiting toxicity (DLT) of LE-DT.

        -  The pharmacokinetics of docetaxel following intravenous administration of LE-DT.

        -  Any anti-tumor effects of LE-DT.

      Up to 5 dose levels have been studied.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the tolerability and safety</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>This Phase I, open-label, dose-escalation study was designed to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of LE-DT in patients with advanced cancer. LE-DT was administered by intravenous infusion, over 1 hour, once every 21 days until occurrence of disease progression or toxicity requiring early treatment discontinuation. Dose escalation was not done until the safety and tolerability at a given dose level has been confirmed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the pharmacokinetic and anti-tumor effect</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The patients were evaluated for pharmacokinetic profile upto 48 hours post treatment after cycle 1. The anti-tumor effects were evaluated after every two cycles of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LE-DT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LE-DT</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravenous infusion, Upto 5 dose levels have been studied i.e. 50, 65, 85, 110 and 132 mg/m2, Every 3 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>LE-DT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Liposome Entrapped Docetaxel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  To be included in this study, patients must meet the following criteria:

          -  Be ≥18 years of age.

          -  Have advanced (local and/or metastatic) histologically documented cancer considered
             unresponsive to available conventional modalities or treatments.

          -  Have an ECOG Performance Status of 0-2.

          -  Have recovered from acute toxicities of prior treatment:

               -  4 weeks must have elapsed since receiving any investigational agent.

               -  4 weeks must have elapsed since receiving any radiotherapy, or treatment with
                  cytotoxic or biologic agents (≥6 weeks for mitomycin or nitrosoureas). Chronic
                  treatment with non-investigational gonadotropin-releasing hormone analogs or
                  other hormonal or supportive care is permitted.

          -  &gt;6 months must have elapsed since receiving a high-dose chemotherapy regimen with stem
             cell support.

               -  2 weeks must have elapsed since any prior surgery or granulocyte-stimulating
                  growth factor therapy.

               -  12 months must have elapsed since any prior treatment with docetaxel. 5. Be in
                  adequate condition as evidenced by the following clinical laboratory values:

                    -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1,500/mm3.

                    -  Platelets ≥100,000/mm3.

                    -  Hemoglobin ≥9.0 g/dL.

                    -  Albumin ≥3.0 g/dL.

                    -  Serum creatinine ≤2.0 mg/dL.

                    -  Total bilirubin ≤1.5 x institutional upper limit normal (ULN).

                    -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), and
                       alkaline phosphatase ≤2.5 x ULN.

                       6. Patients (male and female) must be willing to practice an effective
                       method of birth control during the study.

                       7. Patient or legal representative must understand the investigational
                       nature of this study and sign an Institutional Review Board
                       (IRB)/Independent Ethics Committee approved written informed consent form
                       prior to treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients are excluded from this study for the following:

               1. Active uncontrolled bleeding or bleeding diathesis (e.g., active peptic ulcer
                  disease).

               2. Any active infection requiring parenteral or oral antibiotic treatment.

               3. Known infection with human immunodeficiency virus or hepatitis virus.

               4. Active heart disease including myocardial infarction or congestive heart failure
                  within the previous 6 months, symptomatic coronary artery disease, or arrhythmias
                  currently requiring medication.

               5. Known or suspected active central nervous system metastasis. (Patients stable 8
                  weeks after completion of treatment for central nervous system metastasis are
                  eligible.)

               6. Impending or symptomatic spinal cord compression or carcinomatous meningitis.

               7. Having pre-existing clinically significant neuropathy (NCI CTCAE Grade ≥ 2
                  neuromotor or Grade ≥ 2 neurosensory) except for abnormalities due to cancer.

               8. Having failed a docetaxel-containing regimen.

               9. Having known non-controllable hypersensitivity to docetaxel or liposomes.

              10. Currently receiving any other standard or investigational treatment for cancer or
                  any other investigational agent for any indication.

              11. Requiring immediate palliative treatment of any kind including surgery and/or
                  radiotherapy.

              12. Female patients who are pregnant or breast-feeding.

              13. Unwilling or unable to follow protocol requirements.

              14. Any condition which, in the Investigator's opinion, deems the patient an
                  unsuitable candidate to receive study drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John L Marshall, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Georgetowm University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>TGEN/Scottsdale Clinical Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85258</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lombardi Comprehensive Cancer Center, Georgetown University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20057</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 23, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr. Aquilur Rahman; President &amp; Chief Executive Officer (CEO).</name_title>
    <organization>NeoPharm Inc.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer Patients</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

