<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01772225</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>116913</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01772225</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NSCLC Burden of Illness Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>LuCaBIS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Burden-of Illness Study in Patients With Stage IB-IIIA Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>RTI Health Solutions</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this observational study is to identify and quantify the humanistic and economic
      burden of illness of patients with complete resection (no residual disease) of stage IB-IIIA
      NSCLC in three European countries (France, Germany, and the United Kingdom [UK]). Data
      collection will be conducted through patient medical record abstraction and patient survey.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study procedures will have no effect on the medical care delivered to enrolled patients.
      Physicians will continue to provide usual medical care to patients. There is no study
      intervention, and no drug or other intervention will be provided to the site as part of the
      study.

      Methodology: the study will consist of two components:

        -  Medical record abstraction. Medical records of eligible patients (both living and
           deceased) will be reviewed, and data will be extracted for the study. Data collected
           will include patient demographic and disease characteristics, details of medical care
           received (including adjuvant treatment), and information about disease
           recurrence/progression.

        -  Patient survey. Living patients will be asked to participate in a patient survey. Living
           patients who agree to participate will be administered a brief patient questionnaire to
           collect information that is not available in the clinical sites' medical records [e.g.,
           local medical care, patient out-of-pocket expenses, work loss, and health-related
           quality of life (HRQOL)]. The site may exclude individual patients from the survey if
           site staff feel that it would be inappropriate for that individual; the study will not
           collect patient survey information from the families of deceased patients.

      Informed consent will be collected from living patients who participate in the patient
      survey, apart from the abstraction of their medical records. Country-specific requirements
      will be followed.

      The medical records of patients (living or deceased) with complete resection of stage IB-IIIA
      NSCLC between 01 August 2009 and 31 July 2012 will be identified. No vaccine or drug was
      administered during this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the adjuvant therapies used in routine practice in the target countries along with the durations of treatment, doses, dose reduction rates, discontinuation rates, and reasons for discontinuation.</measure>
    <time_frame>Observation of retrospective data between 2009-2012.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determinations of the proportions of patients receiving each type of adjuvant chemotherapy and proportions receiving no adjuvant chemotherapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>Observation of retrospective data between 2009-2012.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the level of medical resource utilization and the direct healthcare costs of managing these patients during adjuvant treatment, prior to disease recurrence/progression, and post disease recurrence/progression.</measure>
    <time_frame>Observation of retrospective data between 2009-2012.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the characteristics of patients receiving chemotherapy compared with those not receiving chemotherapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>Observation of retrospective data between 2009-2012.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the proportion of patients with selected co morbidities (e.g., chronic obstructive pulmonary disease [COPD], cardiovascular disease, asthma).</measure>
    <time_frame>Observation of retrospective data between 2009-2012.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the national cost-of-illness estimates for France, Germany, and the UK.</measure>
    <time_frame>Observation of retrospective data between 2009-2012.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of indirect costs incurred.</measure>
    <time_frame>Observation of retrospective data between 2009-2012.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the effect of the disease on Health related quality of life (HRQOL) based on EuroQol 5 Dimensions quality-of-life questionnaire (EQ-5D).</measure>
    <time_frame>Observation of retrospective data between 2009-2012.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimation of overall and disease-free survival of patients with resected stage IB-IIIA NSCLC observed retrospectively.</measure>
    <time_frame>Between 01 Aug 2009 and 31 July 2012.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer, Non-Small Cell</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Deceased Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects in this group will include the deceased patients from each of the three countries.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Living Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects in this group will include living patients aged 18 years or older from each of the three countries.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Data collection</intervention_name>
    <description>Medical record abstraction form and patient survey questionnaire.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Living Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Deceased Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients (living or deceased) with complete resection (no residual disease) of stage
        IB-IIIA NSCLC.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patient medical records will be screened using the following criteria:

          -  Patients must be aged 18 years or older at the time of first presentation with
             clinical stage IB-IIIA NSCLC.

          -  Patients must have complete resection of pathologic stage IB-IIIA NSCLC at least 1
             calendar month prior to the date of screening, according to the current classification
             recommended by the International Association for the Study of Lung Cancer (2009). The
             investigator/study site must have been the main care provider for the patient during
             the period of treatment or management of the patient's NSCLC.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who underwent wedge resection.

          -  Patients whose resection was less than 1 calendar month before the date of screening.
             Patients who received adjuvant systemic treatment within a clinical trial if the type
             of adjuvant treatment is either unknown or is not recommended by international
             clinical guidelines [European Society for Medical Oncology (ESMO), National
             Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN)].

          -  Patients who are lost to follow-up:

               -  Living patients who are no longer under the care of the site or can no longer be
                  contacted.

               -  Deceased patients who were transferred to another NSCLC treatment centre before
                  death.

        Patients with concomitant malignancies who received treatment for other cancers at any time
        during their treatment or follow-up for NSCLC.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 17, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 17, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 21, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 31, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Observational Retrospective</keyword>
  <keyword>Health-related quality of life (HRQoL)</keyword>
  <keyword>Patients</keyword>
  <keyword>Stage IB-IIIA</keyword>
  <keyword>Burden of Illness</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

