<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01774318</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KKS-01-2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01774318</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Development of Sleep-wake Cycles in Premature Infants and Its Impact on Neurodevelopmental Outcome</brief_title>
  <acronym>SWC</acronym>
  <official_title>Early Development of Sleep-wake Cycles in Premature Infants and Its Impact on Neurodevelopmental Outcome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Austrian Science Fund (FWF)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Due to the development of neonatal intensive care the number of surviving premature infants
      increased significantly. The immature brain undergoes a fair amount of external stimuli,
      which have a great impact on later cognitive development. Increasingly data show, that a
      delayed emergence of sleep-wake-cycling in newborns can be the first sign of brain injury.
      Studies have shown that clearly defined sleep states can be identified from 31-32 weeks of
      gestation onwards. But a few studies show, that also extremely premature infants already show
      cyclical variations of the background pattern within amplitude-integrated EEG (aEEG= a
      time-compressed, simplified EEG) and conventional EEG. This might resemble early
      sleep-wake-states and their presence correlates to the integrity of the central nervous
      system, although no clearly defined &quot;sleep states&quot; according to the classical definition can
      be identified. Complex EEG analysis needs the use of automated methods to exclude personal
      bias and to ensure gestational age specific data analysis. The newly developed NLEO algorithm
      was specially designed for EEG analysis of premature infants. Conventional EEG within this
      study will be analyzed visually and with the automated algorithm. In our research project we
      will study the emergence of Sleep-wake-cycling in extremely premature infants and its impact
      on their neurodevelopmental outcome prospectively. The different sleep and wake states will
      be derived from analysis of the conventional Video-EEG, aEEG and polysomnographic
      measurements. Visual analysis will include assessment of amplitudes and frequencies as well
      as the latencies and durations of EEG-Bursts and Interburst intervals. The automated
      NLEO-algorithm will be firstly used for comparison with above described visual analysis and
      secondly to find regions of interest involved in the organization of these early sleep
      states. The aim of this study is first to understand and analyze in detail the emergence of
      sleep-wake cycling including its disturbances in premature infants and to compare automated
      NLEO algorithm to conventional visual analysis methods. Secondly to correlate
      neurodevelopmental outcome to the emergence of sleep-wake-cycling.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      General description - Aim of the study

      Due to development of intensive care the number of surviving premature infants increased
      significantly.Delayed emergence of sleep-wake-cycling in newborns can be the first sign of
      brain injury. Clearly defined sleep-states can be identified from 32 weeks of gestation
      onwards. Few studies show, that extremely premature infants (&lt;26 weeks of gestation) may
      already show early sleep-states. In our project we are aiming to study the emergence of
      sleep-wake-cycling in extremely premature infants, prospectively collecting
      electroencephalographic (EEG) data. Premature infants &lt;29 weeks of gestation will be included
      and measured for a 3 hour period every second week with conventional and amplitude-integrated
      EEG. New analytical methods (automatic neonatal EEG algorithm) will be used and compared to
      conventional visual analysis. In an international and interdisciplinary cooperation between
      physicians, electrophysiologist and mathematicians we will be able to deduct conclusions
      providing important prognostic information for patient, parents and physicians.

      State of the art and scientific challenge Increasingly data show, that a delayed emergence of
      sleep-wake cycling in newborns can be the first sign of brain injury and is associated to
      later adverse neurodevelopmental outcome. Due to increasing survival rates among the very
      premature population the prevention from later neurological deficit currently becomes even
      more important. Rates of cerebral palsy and ouvert cerebral lesions (cystic periventricular
      leukomalacia and peri/intraventricular haemorrhage) are decreasing, but the incidence of
      neurodevelopmental impairment remains high in preterm infants. This is explained by the
      understanding of different mechanisms in brain injury (for example inflammation, oxidative
      stress, impaired connectivity) and results in mainly cognitive impairment (1). Therefore
      greater attention needs to be directed toward preterm neonatal populations to better
      understand brain adaptation both with and without medical complications. Neurophysiologic
      surveillance is necessary in these infants to adequately asses cerebral function and is
      difficult within this population by clinical aspects only. Conventional EEG is today´s gold
      standard for neurophysiologic diagnosis. Nevertheless it is not suitable for continuous
      recording since it is producing large data volumes which cannot be assessed directly at the
      bedside. In an effort to solve this problem, various methods of reducing and compressing the
      EEG signal have been developed, the amplitude-integrated EEG (aEEG), being one of them.

      Emergence of sleep-wake-cycling The concept of state during early brain ontogenesis of the
      preterm infant is controversial. It is generally accepted that patterns representing sleep in
      preterm infants are highly variable and less organized than patterns described for full-term
      infants. Well organized sleep states do not appear before 31 weeks of gestation and are not
      well established until 36 weeks postconceptional age. However several researchers have
      questioned this assumption based on studies of sleep in preterm infants (4-7). They support
      that rudimentary state differentation might be present as early as 26 weeks of gestation. In
      our study from 2001 we observed cyclical variations of EEG background activity resembling
      early sleep-wake cycles as early as at 24/25 weeks of gestation (2).

      Neurophysiological methods - amplitude-integrated EEG For early identification of infants at
      high risk and to optimize treatment, it is mandatory to have access to a reliable validated
      diagnostic method with excellent predictive value for later neurodevelopmental outcome. The
      aEEG is a readily available, informative and reliable technique for continuous non-invasive
      monitoring of brain activity even in extremely premature infants. Our research group has more
      than ten years of experience using of the amplitude-integrated EEG and it is a simple method
      for continuous bedside monitoring in the neonatal intensive care unit setting. Our group has
      recently shown aEEG has a predictive value for later outcome in preterm infants and can
      therefore be used as an early prognostic tool for neurodevelopmental outcome (3).

      We have found emerging sleep-wake cycles as early as 24-25 weeks of gestation in
      neurologically healthy premature infants. On the contrary premature infants with
      intraventricular haemorrhage exhibited a significant delay in emergence of their sleep-wake
      cycles, on average with 32 weeks of gestation (8). We know that at this early age the
      development of intercellular connections of the brain and synaptic branching is still in
      development and that these processes take place mainly during sleep.

      Neurophysiological methods - conventional EEG Conventional visual classification of the EEG
      signal of different brain regions has been the standard of analysis since the 1960s when
      first neonatal recordings were performed. Today more than 80% of extremely premature infants
      between 24-28 weeks of gestation survive. Within the analysis of EEG signal there has been a
      growing need for more reliable automatic methods, being suitable for this specific
      population. New nomenclature has emerged specifically for the premature population such as
      spontaneous activity transients (SATs), which constitute the most salient feature on EEG
      during the preterm period (9-11).These spontaneous bursts of activity, which are related to
      the excitatory role of GABAergic transmission during early development not only characterize
      the premature EEG, but have been linked to the development of intracortical connections and
      neuronal wiring. SATs constitute of a very slow activity (0,1-0,5 Hz), with nesting activity
      at several higher frequencies. This activity represents the organization and development of
      thalamo-cortical connections, when neurons migrate from the subplate into the cortical plate
      in the primary sensory cortices. The cooperation with a finnish expert on the field within
      this study, who is experienced with automated EEG algorithm analysis will allow even further
      analysis of the emergence of early sleep-wake-cycling as allows only conventional, visual
      analysis of the EEG.

      As far as we know this would be the first study to evaluate in detail the emergence of
      sleep-wake-cycles in preterm infants using different methods and the first study, trying to
      identify the role of SATs in the development of sleep organization in extremely premature
      infants.

      Research questions/ Objectives/ Hypotheses We plan to conduct a prospective single-center
      cohort trial with an international cooperation in order to analyze the emergence of
      sleep-wake rhythm in very premature infants in detail using conventional video-EEG and
      amplitude-integrated EEG monitoring.

      First objective of the study will be a detailed description of early sleep states, to analyze
      which cortical regions and deeper structures are responsible and involved in their
      development and describe the sequence of their emergence and study these EEG features in a
      prospective &quot;healthy&quot; cohort with no drug bias or pathology. (Infants should show no
      neurological disease and not use any neurologically active medication during analysis) Second
      objective of the study will be to analyze the feasibility of automated conventional EEG
      analysis using the NLEO-based algorithm (nonlinear energy operator) designed for the
      automated detection of SATs in premature infants and to correlate the results with the
      different sleep-wake-states.

      Third aim of the study is to compare the two methods (automated versus visual analysis) in
      order to develop evidence based analysis for early sleep-stage development.

      The fourth aim of the study is to correlate sleep organisation to later neuromotor and
      cognitive outcome.

      Hypotheses:

        1. Video-EEG Polysomnography in combination with aEEG information is a reliable tool to
           identify sleep development even in extremely premature infants.

        2. Early sleep-wake cycles appear from early gestation onwards in healthy premature
           infants. They can be distinguished visually as well as automatically by NLEO algorithm.

        3. The onset of sleep-wake cycles and their regular cyclicity in extremely premature
           infants are a good indicator of normal brain function and intact brain development,
           reflecting maturing neural networks.

        4. Early sleep-wake cycles and their development do have an impact on later
           neurodevelopmental and cognitive outcome in premature infants.

      Methodological approaches

      Patients During a study period of 36 months consecutively all infants born below 29 weeks of
      gestation who are admitted to our neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) will be enrolled in
      this study. Approvement of the local ethics committee has already be obtained (EK-Nr.
      67/2008) and written parental consent will be acquired for each patient. At least 3 hours of
      sleep monitoring will be performed every second week until 36 weeks of gestation using
      conventional video-EEG and aEEG. Thus there will be six different timepoints of data
      acquisition: 24-25; 26-27; 28-29; 30-31; 32-33 and 34-35 weeks of gestation. The first
      measurement will be performed during the first week of life after stabilization of clinical
      state.

      Amplitude-integrated EEG (aEEG) The aEEG is recorded as a single channel EEG from biparietal
      surface disk electrodes using a CFM 6000 (Olympic Medical, USA). The obtained signal is
      filtered, rectified, smoothed and amplitude-integrated before it is written out or digitally
      available on the monitor at a slow speed (6 cm/h), directly at the bed side.

      Tracings are evaluated visually and classified according to the method previously described
      by Hellström-Westas et al. (12) Descriptive analysis of the background activity of the aEEG
      tracings will be done by dividing each trace in 10-minute epochs. These 10-minute epochs wil
      be classified into five pattern categories (&quot;continuous pattern&quot;, &quot;discontinuous pattern&quot;,
      &quot;burst suppression pattern&quot;, &quot;low voltage activity&quot; and &quot;flat trace&quot;).

      The presence of sleep-wake-cycles and seizure activity will be described seperately.

      The percentage of the different patterns and the length of quiet-sleep and active
      sleep/wakefulness will be calculated for the entire aEEG trace.

      Conventional EEG and Video-Polysomnography For the assessment of conventional EEG we will use
      the Micromed System-Plus program. The Video-EEG will be evaluated according to the methods
      previously published by Ludington-Hoe/Scher (4,6). EEG signals are registered from electrodes
      located on Fp1, C3, T3, O1, Fp2, C4, T4, O2 according to the International 10-20 System of
      electrode placement adapted for recording of neonates.

      &quot;Quiet Sleep&quot; is defined as a discontinuous pattern in all channels, where low amplitude
      (&lt;20µV) bursts (bursts are defined as a distinct occurrence of cerebral activity with a slow
      component and associated faster activity) are often present and they are approximately 2-10s
      long (=Interburst Interval).

      The beginning and the end of such a &quot;discontinuous EEG-Segment&quot; is to be marked and the
      Bursts and Interburst-intervals and its amplitudes and frequencies will be described in
      detail. They will be measured 20x in a 10min representative EEG epoch and data will be
      averaged. Also clinical data like body movements, eye movements, heart rate and respiratory
      rate will be measured 20 x in a 10min representative EEG epoch and data will be averaged.

      &quot;Active sleep&quot; is defined as a continuous EEG-activity lasting longer than 60s. Similarly
      amplitudes and frequencies of the bursts and interburst intervals will be measured as well as
      the above mentioned clinical parameters.

      &quot;Wakefulness&quot; is defined electrophysiologically identical to the definition of &quot;active
      sleep&quot;, differences can only be determined according to the behaviour analysis noted on the
      video recordings.

      &quot;Indeterminate sleep&quot;: EEG-segments, which do not fully meet the definitons above and last
      longer than &gt;30s will be classified into &quot;indeterminate sleep&quot;.

      &quot;Arousals&quot; are defined as sudden asynchronuous changes within the EEG-pattern during a sleep
      state, with associated body movements, muscle activity and eye-openings which last shorter
      than 30s.

      Behavioral states will be classified by Videomonitoring according to Holditch-Davies (5).

      Quiet waking state is defined by eyes being open or opening, low motor activity and even
      respiration.

      Active waking is defined by eyes being open, crying, fussing and generalized motor activity.

      Active sleep is defined as eyes being closed, uneven respiration and intermittent rapid eye
      movements (REM).

      Quiet sleep is defined as eyes beingt closed and even respiration

      Automated EEG analysis - NLEO algorithm The NLEO-based algorithm for automated detection of
      spontaneous activity transients (SATs; also called bursts) will also be used to analyze the 8
      channel EEG data. The algorithm consists of feature extraction and a classification
      algorithm, with the idea that every sample of the EEG will be automatically characterized as
      either SAT or inter-SAT based on a detection that uses Nonlinear Energy Operator
      transformation (NLEO). This methodology has been implemented for adults previously, but it
      was recently adapted further for preterm EEG signals by the Vanhatalo group in Helsinki
      (9-11). The newly revised algorithm was shown to agree well with an expert visual
      classification. SAT detection can be used to calculate cumulative (or time-varying)
      percentage of SATs, the length of the inter-SAT interval and the number of SATs per minute.
      In the context of the present study, this approach has offered a possibility to design
      algorithms for an automated and objective assessment of SWC. Our core interest is the
      endogenous cyclicity of the EEG pattern, which will be further analyzed with the automated
      software, where SATs, their spatial characteristics and their regulation will be
      characterized. The NLEO enables to analyze the spatial characteristics of these oscillations
      in different sleep-stages in the developing brain of the premature infant.

      Cranial Ultrasound All infants will be routinely assessed using cranial ultrasound
      examinations every week until the 32th week of gestation and after that every second week.
      Pathologies such as periventricular leukomalacia (PVL) and intraventricular haemorrhage
      (IVH), or other appearing abnormalities will be documented and followed up.

      Neurodevelopmental follow up All study patients will be involved in our neonatal follow up
      program to assess their neurodevelopmental outcome. Neurodevelopmental outcome will be
      assessed at 1,2 and 3,5 years of age by assessment of the Bayley Scales of Infant Development
      II and at the age of 5,5 years by Kaufmann´s Assessment Battery for Children (K-ABC) and
      Beery-Buktenica Developmental Test of Visual-Motor Integration (VMI) done by an experienced
      staff (developmental psychologist and pediatrician).

      The Bayley Scales will be classified as normal when psychomotor (PDI) and mental
      developmental index (MDI) scores were &gt; 85; K-ABC and VMI will also be considered normal when
      &gt; 85 (within 2 standard deviations of reference values) and severely impaired when &lt; 70
      (below 3 standard deviation variance Cerebral Palsy will be defined as a nonprogressive
      central nervous system disorder characterized by abnormal muscle tone in at least one
      extremity and abnormal control of movement or posture and was defined due to location as
      hemiplegia, diplegia and tetraplegia.

      Other included outcome variables will be visual and acoustic impairment, where any form of
      abnormality will be included (need of glasses/hearing aid, as well as blindness/deafness).

      Also detailed information regarding environmental and social and perinatal risk factors will
      be collected.

      Statistical Analysis Occurrence and duration of different amplitude-integrated EEG pattern
      (=continuous, discontinuous patterns) will be given as percentages and descriptively compared
      to already published reference values. Occurrence and duration of above described
      conventional EEG features (=quiet sleep, active sleep and indetermined sleep) and its
      established detailed components (duration and amplitudes and frequencies of bursts and
      interburst intervals) will be given as means per 10 minute epochs. In another step EEG
      activity will be correlated to neurodevelopmental outcome by Pearson´s correlation.

      The effect of the following factors: &quot;percentage of continuous pattern&quot;, &quot;percentage of
      discontinuous pattern, &quot;percentage of burst suppression pattern&quot;, , &quot;occurrence of
      sleep-wake-cycling at aEEG&quot;, occurrence of seizure activity&quot;, &quot;mean amplitude of burst&quot;,
      &quot;mean amplitude of interburst interval &quot;, &quot;mean frequency of burst&quot;, &quot;mean frequency of
      interburst interval&quot;, &quot;appearance of Delta Brush&quot; ,&quot;appearance of Theta Bursts&quot;, &quot;mean heart
      rate&quot;, &quot;mean respiratory rate&quot;, &quot;occurrence of rapid eye movements&quot; and &quot;mean of body
      movements&quot; on neurodevelopmental outcome will be estimated in a multinomial regression model
      and ANOVA in SPSS Statistics Version 17.0 for Windows.

      P-values lower than 5% will be considered as indicating significance. Classification of the
      conventional EEG and video-polysomnography will be done by two of the authors (K.K and Z.R)
      and interrater reliability (Cohen´s Kappa) will be determined.

      Detection of SAT epochs by NLEO-based detector will be assessed, by using sample by sample
      method. This aims to verify the comparability to prior studies (10) that used EEG signals
      from EEG amplifiers with different specifications. In the next phase, the NLEO-based indexes
      will be compared to visual classification (either raw EEG or aEEG trend) by using an
      epoch-based comparison and by using time series methods in cases where both (the index and
      visual classification) output time series with comparable features.

      Expected results/deliverables Project success will be measured by inclusion of 60-80
      patients, measuring their aEEG and Polysomnography as described above and their
      neurodevelopmental follow-up at least at the age of two years corrected age, allowing
      statistical analysis as described above.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>description of Sleep-wake-cycles in aEEG and conventional EEG</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>parallel assessment of sleep-wake cycles in aEEG and conventional EEG</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of occurrance of sleep-wake-cycles to neurodevelopmental outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>correlation of sleep-wake-cycles to Bayley Scales of Infant Development assessed at the age of 2 years</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Sleep Disorders, Circadian Rhythm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>preterm cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>preterm infants born at medical university of vienna and born at gestational age 23+0 - 28+6 weeks of gestation intervention: aEEG and conventional EEG measurements will be performed every two weeks untill 36 weeks of gestation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>aEEG and conventional EEG measurement</intervention_name>
    <description>aEEG and conventional EEG measurement including video-polysomnography</description>
    <arm_group_label>preterm cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: preterm infant born below 29+0 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria:

        severe cerebral malformation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>23 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>29 Weeks</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Katrin Klebermass-Schrehof, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University Vienna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katrin Klebermass-Schrehof, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043/1/40400/2930</phone>
      <email>katrin.klebermass-schrehof@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Katrin Klebermass-Schrehof, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 4, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 24, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 20, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 20, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 24, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Katrin Klebermass-Schrehof</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sleep-wake-cycles</keyword>
  <keyword>preterm infants</keyword>
  <keyword>aEEG</keyword>
  <keyword>conventional EEG</keyword>
  <keyword>polysomnography</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sleep Wake Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parasomnias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Disorders, Circadian Rhythm</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

