<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01777230</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL43062.041.13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01777230</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Value of Preoperative Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping by Pelvic MR Lymphangiography and SPECT-CT in Cervical Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Value of Preoperative Sentinel Lymph Node Mapping by Pelvic MR Lymphangiography and SPECT-CT in Cervical Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UMC Utrecht</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UMC Utrecht</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective of the study: To study the concordance of sentinel node (SN) localization between
      preoperative Magnetic Resonance Lymphangiography and SPECT-CT SN mapping and the
      intra-operative SN procedure for low stage cervical cancer.

      Background: The SN procedure for surgically treated cervical cancer is promising.
      Unfortunately, efficient and direct intra-operative SN localisation, without an extensive
      surgical exploration, remains a challenge even with combined use of patent blue dye en
      technetium-99m (99mTc). Preoperative imaging (= mapping) with 99mTc based SPECT-CT, which is
      increasingly adopted, has partly alleviated this problem. The investigators aim to
      investigate the feasibility of a new SN mapping modality, which visualises the (sentinel)
      lymph nodes using a Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) technique (so called; Magnetic Resonance
      Lymphangiography), and compare it to SPECT-CT.

      Design: Prospective, feasibility type diagnostic study. 40 subjects targeted. Via vaginal
      speculum exam, a specific MRI contrast-agent will be intracervically injected. Subsequently,
      on a wide bore 1.5T MRI system multiplanar imaging is performed, followed by a blinded review
      (experienced radiologist) for bilateral SN localization. Standard care with a preoperative
      SPECT-CT (after intracervical 99mTc administration). A blinded nuclear medicine specialist
      will localize the SN on the SPECT-CT images. Open or (robot-assisted) laparoscopy performed
      for localization of the blue stained and/or 99mTc-hot SN. Excision of the SN with freeze
      sectioning and histological review. Statistical analysis with intrapatient testing for
      concordance of MR Lympangiography and SPECT-CT based SN localization against the reference
      standard: the intra-operative sentinel node procedure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background of the study: The sentinel procedure (SN) for surgically treated cervical cancer
      is promising. Unfortunately, efficient and direct intra-operative SN localisation, without an
      extensive retroperitoneal exploration, remains a challenge even with combined use of patent
      blue dye en 99mTc. The draining lymph nodes are positioned around the retroperitoneal pelvic
      vasculature, in close relation to the ureters and nerves innervating bladder, rectum and
      sexual functionality (inferior hypogastric plexus, genitofemoral nerve, etc), which makes
      exploration hazardous and time consuming. Furthermore, complete retroperitoneal exploration
      often necessitates dissection of lymph vessels (to find the SN) which would have been spared
      in a selective SN excision. The use of technetium-99m(99mTc) enables preoperative SN mapping
      with SPECT(-CT) to localise SN and partly alleviate this issue. Some clinics perform
      preoperative SPECT(-CT), despite its disadvantages of prolonged hospital admission, radiation
      exposure, limited spatial resolution (SPECT) and the limited soft tissue differentiation in
      the female pelvis (CT). The investigators postulate that Magnetic Resonance (MR)
      Lymphangiography is a better technique for preoperative SN mapping in cervical cancer. It
      allows for integration with regular work-up pelvic MRI and could make SPECT-CT unnecessary.

      Objective of the study: To study the concordance of sentinel node localization between
      preoperative MR Lymphangiography and SPECT-CT SN mapping and the intra-operative sentinel
      node procedure (patent blue and 99mTc) for low stage cervical cancer.

      Study design: Prospective, feasibility type diagnostic study with the experimental test (MR
      Lymphangiography) added to standard clinical care (SPECT-CT, intra-operative SN procedure).

      Methods: 40 subjects targeted. Via a vaginal speculum exam 1ml of MR contrastmedium will be
      intracervically injected peripheral of the cervical tumor at 3, 6, 9 and 12 o'clock (suspine
      position). On a wide bore digital 1.5T MRI multiplanar T1w imaging is performed, followed by
      a blinded review (experienced radiologist) for bilateral SN localization with a standardized
      anatomical system. Standard procedure with a preoperative 220 MBq 99mTc SPECT-CT, a blinded
      nuclear medicine specialist will localize the SN. Standard peri-operative care; under general
      anesthesia 1ml injection of patent blue V in each of the four quadrants. Open or
      (robot-assisted) laparoscopy performed for visual localization of the blue SN's. Introduction
      of a gamma-probe and localization 'hot and blue' SN. For both methods anatomical locations of
      the SN are registered. Excision SN for freeze sectioning and histological review. Statistical
      analysis with intrapatient testing for concordance of SPECT-CT and MR Lympangiography based
      SN localization against the reference standard: the intra-operative sentinel node procedure
      (Patent blue and 99mTc).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Unable to get required research materials
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of concordance in sentinel node (SN) localization between Magnetic Resonance Lymphangiography and SPECT-CT SN mapping with the intra-operative SN detection (based on blue dye and Tc-99m-nanocolloid).</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1 week</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The absolute number of SN detected and uni/bilateral SN detection rates by MR lymphangiography, SPECT-CT, intra-operative SN procedure with patent blue only and combined patent blue / 99mTc.</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1 week</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The false negative rates in SN localization by MR lymphangiography, SPECT-CT, intra-operative SN procedure with patent blue only and combined patent blue / 99mTc.</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1 week</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disagreement between the; concordance SN localization SPECT-CT and intra-operative SN procedure (blue + 99mTc) with the concordance MR lymphangiography and intra-operative blue dye only SN procedure (strategy without 99mTc).</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>The difference in concordance (imaging to intra-operative results) between two strategies are compared.
The 1st strategy entails preoperative imaging with SPECT-CT and 'standard' intra-operative SN procedure (= with 99mTc use).
The 2nd strategy is with preoperative MR lymphangiography and an intra-operative 'blue dye only' SN procedure (= without 99mTc).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Alle subjects included retain in one cohort.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SPECT-CT sentinel node mapping</intervention_name>
    <description>sentinel node localisation using the nuclear medicine technique SPECT-CT</description>
    <arm_group_label>All patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Single Photon Emission Computed Tomography</other_name>
    <other_name>Computed Tomography</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic Resonance Lymphangiography sentinel node mapping</intervention_name>
    <description>Sentinel node localisation using Magnetic Resonance Lymphangiography</description>
    <arm_group_label>All patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intra-operative sentinel node procedure</intervention_name>
    <description>Open or (robot-assisted) laparoscopic sentinel node detection and resection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>None Retained</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      no biospecimens are to be retained.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult patients with histologically proven cervical cancer which are a candidate for
        surgery, which includes an intra-operative SN procedure and pelvic lymph node dissection.
        Subjects are derived form a tertiary referral center.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically proven primary malignancy of the cervix uteri;

          2. Primary therapy is surgery with minimally an intra-operative SN procedure and pelvic
             lymph node dissection;

          3. ≥18 years of age and written inform consent provided.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Contra-indications to MR lymphangiography, defined as:

               -  All MRI incompatible electronic and/or ferromagnetic objects;

               -  Presence of any object in the pelvic area prohibiting good image quality;

               -  Severe claustrophobia;

               -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding;

               -  Unable to lie still and in complete supine position for 45 minutes;

               -  Body weight &gt;150kg;

               -  History of an allergic reaction to any gadolinium based contrast agent;

               -  Renal disease with a glomerular filtration rate (GFR) ≤ 30 mL/min/1.73m2;

          2. History of an allergic reaction to patent blue V dye;

          3. Any type of neo-adjuvant chemo and/or radiotherapy for cervical cancer;

          4. Altered anatomy of pelvic lymph nodal drainage system (e.g. history of retroperitoneal
             pelvic surgery or trauma).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ronald Zweemer, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMC Utrecht</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMC Utrecht</name>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <zip>3508 GA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 17, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 17, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 17, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>UMC Utrecht</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ronald Zweemer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Gynaecological oncologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

