<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01779869</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PET/MR-Perfusion</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01779869</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development of a PET-MR Myocardial Perfusion Examination Using Regadenoson</brief_title>
  <acronym>PET/MR-P</acronym>
  <official_title>Development of a PET-MR Myocardial Perfusion Examination Using Regadenoson</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Astellas Pharma US, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective for this pilot study is to develop an optimized, clinically usable myocardial
      PET-MR perfusion protocol and to determine which of all data potentially available should be
      acquired for a clinical myocardial perfusion examination. Hypothesis: The hypothesis is that
      high resolution, high sensitivity DCE MRI could replace the rest PET myocardial perfusion
      imaging, significantly decreasing examination time and patient radiation dose while
      maintaining the comprehensive reference-quality PET myocardial stress perfusion coverage.

      The primary outcome will be comparison of diagnostic accuracy of each combination of imaging
      to detect clinically significant coronary artery stenosis (≥70% diameter stenosis). The
      secondary outcome will be comparison of confidence for presence of disease among data sets.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Simultaneous acquisition PET-MRI is a new technology that has the potential to significantly
      impact diagnostic patient care. It combines high signal resolution MRI anatomic imaging and
      PET biological measurements, with the added benefit of radiation dose reduction in comparison
      to PET-CT. As the incidence of false positive SPECT-MPI studies secondary to attenuation
      artifact is relatively high and MRI coverage of the left ventricular myocardium is limited,
      it is likely that one of the immediate applications of PET-MRI technology is myocardial
      ischemia assessment.

      PET has long been considered the noninvasive reference standard for myocardial perfusion.
      However, delayed contrast enhanced (DCE) MRI is very sensitive for infarct detection. Indeed,
      both PET and MR imaging have the potential to provide comprehensive whole heart ischemia and
      infarct detection.

      PET-MR technology, with its ability to obtain simultaneous perfusion information via both PET
      and MRI, has the potential to obtain multiple, possibly redundant, data sets. On the other
      hand, it also has the potential to combine the best of both techniques to provide a highly
      robust examination that is both shorter and of lower radiation dose than the standard
      myocardial PET perfusion examination. Optimization of a protocol is necessary to develop a
      comprehensive protocol without redundancy. Because of its single injection capability,
      regadenoson is ideally suited to a protocol that will assess and employ dual-modality
      myocardial perfusion data collection.

      It is expected that the best candidates for PET-MR myocardial perfusion imaging will likely
      be a) patients whose body habitus suggests that their SPECT-MPI examination would be limited
      by attenuation artifact -- women with large breasts and patients (usually men) with abdominal
      obesity and/or b) patients who may have a smaller region of ischemia that might be missed on
      an MRI examinations with limited perfusion coverage.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnostic accuracy of cardiac PET-MRI examination</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 days after SPECT-MPI examination</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome will be comparison of diagnostic accuracy of each combination of imaging to detect clinically significant coronary artery stenosis (≥70% diameter stenosis).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reader confidence for disease presence</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 days after SPECT-MPI examination</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary outcome will be comparison of confidence for presence of disease among data sets.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemic Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single group assignment - imaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will undergo PET-MR myocardial perfusion imaging during rapid intravenous administration of 0.4 mg regadenoson.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Regadenoson</intervention_name>
    <description>Regadenoson 400 micrograms will be administered in a single IV bolus (&lt;10 seconds) via an antecubital cannula and followed by 5 mL of saline flush. 10-20 seconds after the regadenoson is administered, 10 mCi of 13N-ammonia as a bolus, and 0.075 mmol/Kg of gadobenate dimeglumine MR contrast agent at a rate of 5 mL/sec followed by a 15 mL normal saline flush will be administered simultaneous, each into an antecubital vein, and a 15 min list-mode PET acquisition will be acquired simultaneously with the MR perfusion imaging.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single group assignment - imaging</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lexiscan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had a clinically ordered rest/regadenoson single-isotope SPECT-MPI
             study within 10 days prior to cardiac PET-MRI examination

          -  Reversible perfusion abnormalities on SPECT imaging in at least 2 contiguous
             myocardial segments

          -  Patients for whom standard of care coronary ICA is planned

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  An clinical event (ie; worsening angina pectoris or myocardial infarction) occuring
             after the SPECT-MPI and before the cardiac MRI examination

          -  Myocardial revascularization occuring after the SPECT-MPI and before the cardiac MRI
             examination

          -  Contraindications to MR imaging (pacemaker, brain aneurysm clips, shrapnel, etc.)

          -  Renal insufficiency (GFR &lt; 60 mL/min/1.73m2)

          -  Allergy or other contraindication to gadolinium-based MR contrast agent

          -  Second or third degree atrioventricular (AV) block

          -  Active asthma

          -  Seizures

          -  Current hypotension (&lt;100/60)

          -  Current hypertension (&gt;160/90)

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Breast feeding

          -  Use of caffeine, nicotine or over the counter cold medicines within 12 hours of the
             cardiac PET-MRI examination

          -  Use of the medication dipyridamole within 48 hrs of the cardiac PET-MRI examination
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pamela K Woodard, MD, BA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Clinical Imaging Research at Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 23, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 27, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 30, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pamela Woodard, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Center for Clinical Imaging Research (CCIR)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PET MR myocardial perfusion imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Regadenoson</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Analyzed data will be shared with other researchers after publication of manuscript.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>January 21, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>February 14, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>February 15, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>March 16, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>April 9, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>May 10, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>May 15, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

