<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01777490</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIR 11-345</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01777490</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Helping Invested Families Improve Veterans Experiences Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>HI-FIVES</acronym>
  <official_title>Helping Invested Families Improve Veterans Experiences Study (HI-FIVES)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate a caregiver skill training program (HI-FIVES),
      offered as a part of a randomized control trial to caregivers of Veterans referred to home
      and community-based long-term care. Of primary interest is to examine whether participating
      in HI-FIVES leads to clinically significant increases in days spent at home for Veterans
      compared to caregivers in usual care. The investigators aim, through the training, to
      decrease the number of days over 12 months post-intervention that Veterans spend in the
      emergency department, hospital, or nursing home. Days spent in these settings reduces the
      Veteran's quality of life and increases health care costs to the VA. The investigators also
      will evaluate whether caregivers in HI-FIVES have clinically significant reductions in
      depressive symptoms post-intervention compared to caregivers in usual care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Anticipated Impacts on Veteran's Healthcare: Designing and implementing a training program
      for informal caregivers of functionally impaired Veterans (HI-FIVES) will enhance Veterans'
      ability to remain in their homes and satisfaction with care, as well as lower VA costs.
      Caregiver training can also improve caregiver wellbeing by alleviating feelings of depression
      and burden, which can also improve the care they provide to veterans. The investigators'
      caregiver training program is consistent with features of two recent national policy changes
      aimed to improve quality of care for veterans. First, providing training to informal
      caregivers of functionally impaired veterans is consistent with the 2000 Millennium Health
      Care Act, which mandated an unprecedented expansion in long-term care benefits to Veterans,
      and stipulated that, whenever possible, care be provided in the least restrictive environment
      possible-the home. Second, The Caregivers and Veterans Omnibus Health Services Act of 2010
      mandated unprecedented support for informal caregivers of severely injured OEF/OIF Veterans,
      including providing caregiver training to informal caregivers of any era veteran. Achieving
      higher quality informal care supports both of these mandates. By partnering with VA
      providers, HI-FIVES will improve the skill of caregivers, thereby improving veteran health
      care quality and the ability for veterans to remain at home.

      Project Background: Caregiver burnout, strain and burden are associated with caregiver
      depression and patient institutionalization. Furthermore, lack of skills among caregivers can
      lead to depression and anxiety as well as patient institutionalization. The investigators
      propose to evaluate an innovative program that supports and trains informal caregivers when
      veterans are referred to VHA home and community-based care (HCBC), a critical moment in a
      veteran's VHA health care use trajectory. Referral to HCBC is a time when caregivers may face
      personal strain and uncertainty about demands involved in caregiving. As such, it presents a
      teachable moment to train caregivers to better meet the demands imposed by caregiving.

      Project Objectives: To evaluate whether over 12 months, veterans with caregivers in the skill
      training program have clinically significant increases in days at home than veterans in usual
      care (e.g. days not in emergency department, hospital, or nursing home). In addition, the
      investigators will evaluate whether veterans in the skill training program have significantly
      lower VA costs of medical care or higher satisfaction with VHA over 6 and 12 months than
      veterans in usual care. Finally, the investigators will evaluate whether caregivers in the
      skill training program have clinically significant reductions in depressive symptoms,
      subjective burden, or increased satisfaction with VA healthcare at 6 and12 months than
      caregivers in usual care.

      Project Methods: The study is a randomized controlled trial with data collection from
      caregiver-patient dyads before and after training, and at 6 and 12 months after program
      completion. Piloted in early 2012, the setting is the Social Work Service at the Durham VAMC.
      Patient inclusion criteria are patient referred to home and community-based services in the
      past 3 months, not eligible for hospice, residing at home, has an informal caregiver, and
      willing to let investigators contact the caregiver. Caregivers must be cognitively and
      physically capable to participate, understand English, not be treated for a substance abuse
      disorder, not be in another caregiver interventional study, and willing to participate in 3
      phone call trainings and attend five group sessions at the VA. Caregivers in the control
      group will receive the training and support usually provided by HCBC and VA medical
      providers. To be referred successfully to HCBC, patients will have a minimum of 2 activity of
      daily living limitations, and are likely to have multimorbidity, including high rates of
      cognitive impairment (44% in the pilot). The target sample size will be 146 caregivers in
      each arm. Patient involvement will be limited to four short phone assessments (with
      mechanisms established for proxy respondents). Caregivers in the treatment arm will take part
      in three phone training sessions and five group sessions, and in both arms caregivers will be
      asked to provide four phone assessments. Descriptive statistics will be used to summarize all
      study variables. Of primary importance will be to examine the distribution of patient days
      spent at home during the first 3 months, the first 6 months, and over the entire 12 months of
      the post-intervention period (e.g. days not in ED, inpatient, or nursing home setting).
      Investigators will use the count-data regression model which best fits the investigators'
      data (Poisson, Negative Binomial or zero-inflated versions of Poisson or Negative Binomial)
      to test the primary hypothesis that veterans with caregivers in the skill training program
      will have significantly more days spent at home than veterans in usual care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 5, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 29, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 10, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Research Assistant conducting follow-up interviews is blinded as to dyad arm assignment</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient days in the community (e.g. days not in emergency department, inpatient, or nursing home setting)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Days at home up to12 months post-treatment is simply 365 minus the total number of days of VA or non-VA ED, inpatient, and nursing home care, whereas days not at home is the count of days in ED, inpatient or nursing home care.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total costs to the VA</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>VA utilization costs will be summarized across VA and non-VA contracted care and will capture all outpatient costs (laboratory, radiology, pharmacy, surgery, nursing, and treat and release ED visits) and inpatient costs (similar categories). Intervention costs will include labor and capital costs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with healthcare</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>CAHPS. Used by the VA Office of Performance and Quality, this outcome is considered a key measure of patient satisfaction with inpatient and outpatient care. The investigators will focus on a global satisfaction measure about the health plan: Using any number from 0 to 10, where 0 is the worst health care possible and 10 is the best health care possible, what number would the patient use to rate all of his/her health care in the VA in the last 3 months?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiver depressive symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators selected the Center for Epidemiological Studies-Depression 10 scale (CESD-10) measure of depressive symptoms because the respondent burden is low and in order to maximize comparability with REACH I and REACH II.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Caregiver</condition>
  <condition>Disabled Veterans</condition>
  <condition>Referred to Long-term Care</condition>
  <condition>Residing at Home</condition>
  <condition>Hospice Ineligible</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Caregivers in the control arm will be referred to the VA Caregiver Support Program (usual care), as a resource for them as they care for the patient in the home. The patient of each caregiver will also be enrolled and contact will be limited to assessments.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: HI FIVES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Caregivers will take part in three phone training sessions and will attend four group training sessions at the VA. They will also be given the option of participating in 2 booster phone training sessions post-group sessions. Caregivers will be asked to provide one in-person (baseline) and three phone assessments (3, 9, and 15 months). Patients will also be enrolled and contact will be limited to assessments</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Helping Invested Families Improve Veterans Experiences Study - Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Usual care will be the Veteran patient care and caregiver support that are normally offered once the Geriatrics and Extended Care (GEC) referral process has occurred. This process entails the patient and caregiver work with the social worker assigned to the patient to obtain home and community based care (HCBC) services. The patients in the usual care group will be free to seek medical, psychological, social support, and social services that are available through VAMCs or any other source. In addition to this, caregivers in the usual care arm will be told about the caregiver support programs in the VHA and the caregiver will receive the national VA caregiver hotline phone number (see Appendix VI for this pamphlet). The information provided mirrors efforts to support caregivers in the VA nationally and new standards of care for VA caregivers. This will be the only contact with the usual care subjects besides the scheduled data collection assessments.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Helping Invested Families Improve Veterans Experiences Study - HI FIVES</intervention_name>
    <description>Caregivers in the HI-FIVES group will receive individual calls with a nurse educator to address topics he/she identified as being the highest priority learning areas. After the phone calls, caregivers will participate in evidence-based group sessions aimed to improve clinical care skills, psychological care skills, and support-seeking skills. The curriculum will be delivered by a trained nurse educator on the research team and the PI and VA Caregiver Support Staff. Three individual telephone training calls will be tailored to the individual needs of Veteran-caregiver dyad. Four group training sessions will be targeted to address common needs of Veterans and their caregivers. Given that all Veteran care recipients will have at least 2 or 3 activities of daily living (ADL) limitations. After the final group session, there will be two optional booster calls at one and three months. Four assessments in all will be collected, baseline (in person), and at 3, 9, and 15 months (by phone).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: HI FIVES</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Experimental</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient referred to home and community-based services in the past 3 months,

          -  not eligible for hospice,

          -  residing at home,

          -  has an informal caregiver, and willing to let us contact the caregiver.

        To be referred successfully to HCBC,

          -  patients will have a minimum of 2 activity of daily living limitations,

          -  and are likely to have multimorbidity, including high rates of cognitive impairment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cognitively impaired Caregiver

          -  Caregiver does not have access to a telephone.

          -  Severely impaired hearing or speech (Caregivers must be able to respond to phone
             calls).

          -  English Language Impaired - Caregiver

          -  Substance Abuse Disorders - Caregiver

          -  Caregiver participating in other caregiver intervention

          -  Patient referred only for physical or occupational therapy

          -  Patient or caregiver refuses informed consent

          -  Patient in hospital
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Courtney H Van Houtven, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Durham VA Medical Center, Durham, NC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Durham VA Medical Center, Durham, NC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Van Houtven CH, Oddone EZ, Hastings SN, Hendrix C, Olsen M, Neelon B, Lindquist J, Weidenbacher H, Boles J, Chapman J, Weinberger M. Helping Invested Families Improve Veterans' Experiences Study (HI-FIVES): study design and methodology. Contemp Clin Trials. 2014 Jul;38(2):260-9. doi: 10.1016/j.cct.2014.05.003. Epub 2014 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24837544</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 23, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Caregivers - Not professionals</keyword>
  <keyword>Frail Elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>Long-term Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of Life</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>January 8, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

