<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01779102</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TESEC-07</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01779102</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study Investigating if Concomitant Injections of C-Tb and 2 T.U Tuberculin Affect Induration Responses</brief_title>
  <acronym>TESEC-07</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II/III Trial Investigating if Concomitant Injections of the Diagnostic Agents C-Tb and 2 T.U Tuberculin PPD RT 23 SSI Affect the Induration Responses in Combination With a Safety Assessment of C-Tb</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Statens Serum Institut</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Statens Serum Institut</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A new, more specific skin test to detect tuberculosis has been developed by Statens Serum
      Institut in Denmark. The new skin test is named C-Tb and like the current Tuberculin a
      positive test result will show as redness and/or induration at the injection site, while a
      negative test will leave no reactions.

      The aim of this study is to address if the size of induration and the sensitivity of C-Tb is
      influenced by concomitant injections of C-Tb and Tuberculin. Furthermore, the intention is to
      evaluate the safety of C-Tb when injected alone or concomitantly with Tuberculin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The TESEC-07 trial is a GCP double blind randomised controlled phase II/III trial
      investigating if concomitant injections of the diagnostic agents C-Tb and 2 T.U Tuberculin
      PPD RT 23 SSI affect the induration responses in combination with a safety assessment of
      C-Tb. TESEC-07 is a multi-centre trial and will be conducted in South Africa in patients
      recently diagnosed with TB comprising 360 HIV negative and 90 HIV positive adults allocated
      to 3 trial groups.

        -  A within group paired comparison of 0.1 μg/0.1 mL C-Tb and PPD RT 23 in 150 TB patients.
           The C-Tb and PPD RT 23 agents are given concomitantly to each volunteer in the RIGHT AND
           LEFT forearms according to a randomisation scheme.

        -  A group of 150 TB patients will only receive the C-Tb agent randomised to either RIGHT
           or LEFT forearm.

        -  A group of 150 TB patients will only receive the reference agent PPD RT 23 randomised to
           either RIGHT or LEFT forearm.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the size of induration of C-Tb and PPD RT 23 if injected alone or concomitantly in Tuberculosis infected patients (HIV positives and HIV negatives)</measure>
    <time_frame>Onset from the injection(s) to 28 days after the injections</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess if concomitant injections of C-Tb and PPD RT 23 influence the tests abilities to identify positive results of Tuberculosis in Tuberculosis infected patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Onset from the injection(s) to 28 days after the injections</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the C-Tb test's ability to identify positive results in Tuberculosis infected patients with the in vitro QuantiFERON®TB Gold In Tube assay in blood collected immediately before application of the C-Tb skin test</measure>
    <time_frame>Onset from the injection(s) to 28 days after the injections</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the C-Tb test's ability to identify positive results in Tuberculosis infected patients with the PPD RT 23 test</measure>
    <time_frame>Onset from the injection(s) to 28 days after the injections</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety of C-Tb skin test by investigating laboratory safety parameters and assessing all adverse events (local and systemic) occurring within 28 days after administration of the C-Tb and/or PPD RT 23 tests</measure>
    <time_frame>Onset from the injection(s) to 28 days after the injections</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">456</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>0.1 µg C-Tb</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The C-Tb agent is given alone to volunteers in the RIGHT or LEFT forearm according to a double blind randomisation scheme</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2 T.U Tuberculin PPD RT 23 SSI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The 2 T.U Tuberculin PPD RT 23 SSI agent is given alone to volunteers in the RIGHT or LEFT forearm according to a double blind randomisation scheme</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>0.1 µg C-Tb / 2 T.U Tuberculin PPD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The C-Tb and 2 T.U Tuberculin PPD RT 23 SSI agents are given concomitantly to volunteers in the RIGHT and LEFT forearms according to a double blind randomisation scheme</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>C-Tb</intervention_name>
    <description>C-Tb is administered by the Mantoux injection technique to each volunteer in the RIGHT or LEFT forearm according to a double blind randomisation scheme</description>
    <arm_group_label>0.1 µg C-Tb</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tuberculin PPD RT 23 SSI</intervention_name>
    <description>Tuberculin is administered by the Mantoux injection technique to each volunteer in the RIGHT or LEFT forearm according to a double blind randomisation scheme</description>
    <arm_group_label>2 T.U Tuberculin PPD RT 23 SSI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>C-Tb / Tuberculin PPD RT 23 SSI</intervention_name>
    <description>The C-Tb and Tuberculin agents are administered by the Mantoux injection technique to each volunteer in the RIGHT and LEFT forearm according to a double blind randomisation scheme</description>
    <arm_group_label>0.1 µg C-Tb / 2 T.U Tuberculin PPD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (HIV Negative patients):

          -  Has signed an informed consent

          -  Aged 18 to 65 years

          -  Has been diagnosed with active pulmonary TB:

               1. has a compatible clinical picture of TB according to South African guidelines
                  with the intention to treat and 1 documented positive culture result or

               2. has a compatible clinical picture of TB according to South African Guidelines
                  with the intention to treat and 1 documented positive GeneXpert analysis

          -  Is HIV negative confirmed by 2 two rapid tests

          -  Is willing and likely to comply with the trial procedures

          -  Is prepared to grant authorized persons access to their medical record

        Inclusion Criteria (HIV Positive patients):

          -  Has signed an informed consent

          -  Aged 18-65 years

          -  Has been diagnosed with active pulmonary TB:

               1. has a compatible clinical picture of TB according to South African guidelines
                  with the intention to treat and 1 documented positive culture result or

               2. has a compatible clinical picture of TB according to South African Guidelines
                  with the intention to treat and 1 documented positive GeneXpert analysis

          -  Is HIV positive confirmed by:

               1. 2 positive rapid tests or

               2. 1 positive rapid tests and an additional confirmatory ELISA

          -  A CD4 count has been performed

          -  Is willing and likely to comply with the trial procedures

          -  Is prepared to grant authorized persons access to their medical records

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has been in treatment for TB for more than 2 weeks

          -  Has a known MDR/XDR-TB

          -  Has been vaccinated with a live vaccine within 6 weeks prior to the day of inclusion
             (e.g. MMR, yellow fever, oral typhoid vaccines) except BCG vaccine

          -  Has been tuberculin (TST) tested &lt; 12 months prior to the day of inclusion

          -  Is pregnant, breastfeeding or intending to get pregnant

          -  Is a female of child bearing potential not willing to use effective barrier (including
             spermicidal gel), hormonal or intrauterine contraceptive measures during the trial
             period

          -  Has an active disease affecting the lymphoid organs except for HIV (e.g., Hodgkin's
             disease, lymphoma, leukaemia, sarcoidosis)

          -  Has a current skin condition which interferes with the reading of the skin tests e.g.
             tattoos, severe scarring, burns/sunburns, rash, eczema, psoriasis, or any other skin
             disease at or near the injection sites

          -  Has a condition where blood drawings pose more than minimal risk for the patient, such
             as haemophilia, other coagulation disorders, or significantly impaired venous access

          -  Currently participating in another clinical trial with an investigational or non
             investigational drug or device, or has participated in another clinical trial within
             the 3 months prior to dosing

          -  Has participated in previous clinical trials investigating the ESAT-6 and/or CFP-10
             antigens

          -  Has a condition which in the opinion of the investigator is not suitable for
             participation in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pernille N Tingskov, BN, RN</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Statens Serum Institut</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Keertan Dheda, MD, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCT Lung Institute, University of Cape Town</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Be Part Yoluntu Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paarl</city>
        <state>Western Cape</state>
        <zip>7626</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>TASK, M2, Karl Bremer Hospital,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <zip>7530</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tiervlei Trial Centre, Karl Bremer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <zip>7530</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCT Lung Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <zip>7925</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Primecure Medicentre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port Elizabeth</city>
        <zip>6014</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Synexus Stanza Bopape Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pretoria</city>
        <zip>0122</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Setshaba Research Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pretoria</city>
        <zip>0152</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 30, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 17, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

