<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03241940</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PEDSCCT5007</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2017-01415</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>PEDSCCT5007</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA124435</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03241940</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CD19/CD22 Chimeric Antigen Receptor T Cells and Chemotherapy in Treating Children or Young Adults With Recurrent or Refractory CD19 Positive B Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Dose Escalation Study of CD19/CD22 Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T Cells in Children and Young Adults With Recurrent or Refractory B Cell Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the best dose and side effects of CD19/CD22 chimeric antigen
      receptor (CAR) T cells when given together with chemotherapy, and to see how well they work
      in treating children or young adults with CD19 positive B acute lymphoblastic leukemia that
      has come back or does not respond to treatment. A CAR is a genetically-engineered receptor
      made so that immune cells (T cells) can attack cancer cells by recognizing and responding to
      the CD19/CD22 proteins. These proteins are commonly found on B acute lymphoblastic leukemia.
      Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as fludarabine phosphate and cyclophosphamide, work in
      different ways to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping
      them from dividing, or by stopping them from spreading. Giving CD19/CD22-CAR T cells and
      chemotherapy may work better in treating children or young adults with B acute lymphoblastic
      leukemia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine the feasibility of producing CD19/CD22-CAR T cells meeting the established
      release criteria.

      II. Assess the safety of administering escalating doses of autologous CD19/CD22-CAR
      engineered T cells that meet established release specifications in children and young adults
      with hematologic malignancies following a cyclophosphamide/fludarabine phosphate
      (fludarabine) conditioning regimen.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Evaluate the ability of CD19/CD22-CAR T cells to mediate clinical activity in children and
      young adults with B-acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL).

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Analyze alterations in early B cell development induced by immune pressure exerted via
      CD19/CD22-CAR T cells.

      II. Evaluate whether subjects receiving CD19/CD22-CAR T cells relapse with loss or diminished
      expression of CD19 and/or CD22, when feasible.

      III. Measure persistence of CD19/CD22-CAR T cells in the blood, bone marrow and cerebral
      spinal fluid (CSF), and explore correlations between CD19/CD22-CAR T cell properties and CAR
      T cell efficacy and persistence.

      IV. Establish the utility of chromatin structure and epigenomic technology to characterize
      CAR T cell therapies.

      V. Explore the ability of CD19/CD22-CAR T cells to mediate clinical activity in children and
      young adults with refractory B cell lymphoma in a non-statistical cohort due to expectations
      of low accrual.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of CD19/CD22-CAR T cells.

      Patients receive fludarabine phosphate intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes on days -4 to -2
      and cyclophosphamide IV over 60 minutes on day -2. Patients then receive CD19/CD22-CAR T
      cells IV over 10-20 minutes on day 0. Patients that benefited from the first dose of
      CD19/CD22-CAR T cells, had no unacceptable side effects, and have enough cells left over may
      receive 2 or 3 additional doses of CD19/CD22-CAR T cells.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up daily until day 14, twice
      weekly until day 28, at 2 and 3 months, every 3 months until month 12, every 6-12 months up
      to year 5, and then annually for years 6-15.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2035</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and severity of dose limiting toxicities (DLTs) following chemotherapy preparative regimen and infusion of CD19/CD22 chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Will be recorded and graded according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.03 at three dose levels until the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) is determined.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of successful manufacture and expansion of the CD19/CD22 chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cells to satisfy the targeted dose level and meet the required release specifications outlined in the Certificate of Analysis (COA)</measure>
    <time_frame>10-14 days after apheresis or thawing of cryopreserved peripheral blood mononuclear cell</time_frame>
    <description>The number of subjects which can successfully manufacture the targeted dose number will be determined for each dose cohort.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The ability to achieve a clinical response after administration of CD19/CD22 chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be assessed by the Response Criteria for Lymphoma and the Response Criteria for Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Alterations in early B cell development induced by immune pressure exerted via CD19/CD22-CAR T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be analyzed.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>CD19/CD22 chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cell properties</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will explore correlations with CAR T cell efficacy and persistence.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of CD22+ expression on lymphoma cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will determine site density when possible.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Persistence of CD19/CD22 chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cells blood, bone marrow, and cerebral spinal fluid (CSF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse with loss or diminished expression of CD19 and/or CD22</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be evaluated when feasible.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">47</enrollment>
  <condition>B Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>CD19 Positive</condition>
  <condition>Minimal Residual Disease</condition>
  <condition>Philadelphia Chromosome Positive</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CD19/CD22-CAR T cells, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive fludarabine phosphate IV over 30 minutes on days -4 to -2 and cyclophosphamide IV over 60 minutes on day -2. Patients then receive CD19/CD22-CAR T cells IV over 10-20 minutes on day 0. Patients that benefited from the first dose of CD19/CD22-CAR T cells, had no unacceptable side effects, and have enough cells left over may receive 2 or 3 additional doses of CD19/CD22-CAR T cells.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chimeric Antigen Receptor T-Cell Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Given CD19/CD22-CAR T cells IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CD19/CD22-CAR T cells, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CAR T-cell therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CD19/CD22-CAR T cells, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(-)-Cyclophosphamide</other_name>
    <other_name>2H-1,3,2-Oxazaphosphorine, 2-[bis(2-chloroethyl)amino]tetrahydro-, 2-oxide, monohydrate</other_name>
    <other_name>Carloxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Ciclofosfamida</other_name>
    <other_name>Ciclofosfamide</other_name>
    <other_name>Cicloxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Clafen</other_name>
    <other_name>Claphene</other_name>
    <other_name>CP monohydrate</other_name>
    <other_name>CTX</other_name>
    <other_name>CYCLO-cell</other_name>
    <other_name>Cycloblastin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cycloblastine</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophospham</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphamid monohydrate</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphamidum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphan</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphane</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphanum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclostin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclostine</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytophosphan</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytophosphane</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Fosfaseron</other_name>
    <other_name>Genoxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Genuxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Ledoxina</other_name>
    <other_name>Mitoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Neosar</other_name>
    <other_name>Revimmune</other_name>
    <other_name>Syklofosfamid</other_name>
    <other_name>WR- 138719</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine Phosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CD19/CD22-CAR T cells, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2-F-ara-AMP</other_name>
    <other_name>9H-Purin-6-amine, 2-fluoro-9-(5-O-phosphono-.beta.-D-arabinofuranosyl)-</other_name>
    <other_name>Beneflur</other_name>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
    <other_name>SH T 586</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CD19/CD22-CAR T cells, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (CD19/CD22-CAR T cells, chemotherapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  In view of the principal investigator (PI) and the primary oncologist, there must be
             no available alternative curative therapies and subjects must be either ineligible for
             allogeneic stem cell transplant (SCT), have refused SCT, recurred after SCT, or have
             disease activity that prohibits SCT at the time of enrollment

               -  Chemotherapy refractory disease in subjects with B-ALL is defined as progression
                  or stable disease after two lines of standard therapies (two induction regimens),
                  or relapsed disease after 2 established induction regimens

               -  Subjects with persistent or relapsed minimal residual disease (MRD)/next
                  generation sequencing (NGS) relapse require verification of relapse on two
                  occasions at least 4 weeks apart

               -  Subjects with Philadelphia chromosome positive acute lymphoblastic leukemia (Ph+
                  ALL) subjects are eligible if they progressed, had stable disease or relapsed
                  after two lines of therapy, including tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs)

               -  Subjects with lymphoma must have progressed, had stable disease (SD), or recurred
                  after two standard treatment regimens

          -  CD19 expression is required and must be detected on greater than 50% of the malignant
             cells by immunohistochemistry or &gt;= 90% by flow cytometry; the choice of whether to
             use flow cytometry or immunohistochemistry will be determined by what is the most
             easily available tissue sample in each subject; in general, immunohistochemistry will
             be used for lymph node biopsies, flow cytometry will be used for peripheral blood and
             bone marrow samples

          -  Subjects who have undergone autologous SCT will be eligible if all other eligibility
             criteria are met; subjects who have undergone allogeneic SCT will be eligible if, in
             addition to meeting other eligibility criteria, they are at least 100 days
             post-transplant, they have no evidence of active graft versus host disease (GVHD) and
             have been without immunosuppressive agents for at least 30 days

          -  For patients with lymphoma, evaluable or measurable disease according to the revised
             International Working Group (IWG) Response Criteria for Malignant Lymphoma must be
             present; lesions that have been previously irradiated will be considered measurable
             only if progression has been documented following completion of radiation therapy

          -  At least 2 weeks or 5 half-lives, whichever is shorter, must have elapsed since any
             prior systemic therapy at the time the subject is planned for leukapheresis, except
             for systemic inhibitory/stimulatory immune checkpoint therapy, which requires 5
             half-lives

               -  Exceptions:

                    -  There is no time restriction with regard to prior intrathecal chemotherapy
                       provided there is complete recovery from any acute toxic effects of such

                    -  Subjects receiving hydroxyurea may be enrolled provided there has been no
                       increase in dose for at least 2 weeks prior to starting apheresis

                    -  Subjects who are on standard ALL maintenance type chemotherapy (vincristine,
                       6-mercaptopurine or oral methotrexate) may be enrolled provided that
                       chemotherapy is discontinued at least 1 week prior to apheresis

                    -  Subjects receiving steroid therapy at physiologic replacement doses only are
                       allowed provided there has been no increase in dose for at least 2 weeks
                       prior to starting apheresis

                    -  For radiation therapy: radiation therapy must have been completed at least 3
                       weeks prior to enrollment, with the exception that there is no time
                       restriction if the volume of bone marrow treated is less than 10% and also
                       the subject has measurable/evaluable disease outside the radiation port

          -  Toxicities due to prior therapy must be stable and recovered to =&lt; grade 1 (except for
             clinically non-significant toxicities such as alopecia)

          -  NOTE: the first subject in the first dose cohort must be &gt;= 18 years of age if an
             adult has not been treated at that dose cohort on the companion Stanford protocol
             &quot;Phase 1 Dose Escalation Study of CD19/CD22 Chimeric Antigen Receptor (CAR) T Cells in
             Adults with Recurrent or Refractory B Cell Malignancies&quot; and undergone safety
             evaluation at day 28 without evidence of dose limiting toxicity (DLT)

          -  Subjects &gt; 10 years of age: Karnofsky &gt;= 50%; Subjects =&lt; 10 years of age: Lansky
             scale &gt;= 50%

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 750/uL if these cytopenias are not judged by the
             investigator to be due to underlying disease (i.e. potentially reversible with
             anti-neoplastic therapy); a subject will not be excluded because of pancytopenia &gt;=
             grade 3 if it is due to disease, based on the results of bone marrow studies

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 50,000/uL if these cytopenias are not judged by the investigator to
             be due to underlying disease (i.e. potentially reversible with anti-neoplastic
             therapy); a subject will not be excluded because of pancytopenia &gt;= grade 3 if it is
             due to disease, based on the results of bone marrow studies

          -  Absolute lymphocyte count &gt;= 150/uL

          -  Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT)/aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 2.5 upper
             limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 mg/dl, except in subjects with Gilbert's syndrome

          -  Cardiac ejection fraction &gt;= 45%, no evidence of physiologically significant
             pericardial effusion as determined by an echocardiogram (ECHO), and no clinically
             significant electrocardiogram (ECG) findings

          -  No clinically significant pleural effusion

          -  Baseline oxygen saturation &gt; 92% on room air

          -  Creatinine: within age adjusted normal institutional limits:

               -  Age =&lt; 5 years - maximum serum creatinine 0.8 mg/dL

               -  Age 5 years &lt; age =&lt; 10 years - maximum serum creatinine 1.0 mg/dL

               -  Age &gt; 10 years - maximum serum creatinine 1.2 mg/dL OR

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt;= 60 mL/min/1.73 m^2 (as estimated by Cockcroft Gault equation)
             for subjects with creatinine levels above institutional normal

          -  Central nervous system (CNS) status

               -  Subjects with ALL

                    -  Subjects with the following CNS status are eligible only in the absence of
                       neurologic symptoms suggestive of CNS leukemia, such as cranial nerve palsy:

                         -  CNS 1, defined as absence of blasts in cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) on
                            cytospin preparation, regardless of the number of white blood cells
                            (WBCs)

                         -  CNS 2, defined as presence of &lt; 5/uL WBCs in CSF and cytospin positive
                            for blasts, or &gt; 5/uL WBCs but negative by Steinherz/Bleyer algorithm:

                              -  CNS 2a: &lt; 10/uL red blood cells (RBCs); &lt; 5/uL WBCs and cytospin
                                 positive for blasts

                              -  CNS 2b: &gt;= 10/uL RBCs; &lt; 5/uL WBCs and cytospin positive for
                                 blasts

                              -  CNS 2c: &gt;= 10/uL RBCs; &gt;= 5/uL WBCs and cytospin positive for
                                 blasts but negative by Steinherz/Bleyer algorithm

               -  Subjects with lymphoma

                    -  Subjects must have no signs or symptoms of CNS disease or detectable
                       evidence of CNS disease on magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) at the time of
                       screening; subjects who have been previously treated for CNS disease but
                       have no evidence of disease at screening are eligible

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test
             (females who have undergone surgical sterilization or who have been postmenopausal for
             at least 2 years are not considered to be of childbearing potential)

          -  Subjects of child-bearing or child-fathering potential must be willing to practice
             birth control from the time of enrollment on this study and for four (4) months after
             receiving the preparative regimen; females of child-bearing potential must have a
             negative pregnancy test

          -  Ability to give informed consent; all subjects &gt;= 18 years of age must be able to give
             informed consent; for subjects &lt; 18 years old their legal authorized representative
             (LAR) (i.e. parent or guardian) must give informed consent; pediatric subjects will be
             included in age appropriate discussion and verbal assent will be obtained for those &gt;
             7 years of age, when appropriate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Recurrent or refractory ALL limited to isolated testicular or isolated central nervous
             system (CNS) disease

          -  Subjects with radiologically-detected CNS lymphoma or CNS 3 disease (presence of &gt;=
             5/uL WBCs in CSF and cytospin positive for blasts [in the absence of a traumatic
             lumbar puncture] and/or clinical signs of CNS leukemia)

          -  Hyperleukocytosis (&gt;= 50,000 blasts/uL) or rapidly progressive disease that in the
             estimation of the investigator and sponsor would compromise ability to complete study
             therapy

          -  History of malignancy other than non-melanoma skin cancer or carcinoma in situ (e.g.
             cervix, bladder, breast) unless disease free for at least 3 years

          -  Presence of fungal, bacterial, viral, or other infection that is uncontrolled or
             requiring IV antimicrobials for management; simple urinary tract infection (UTI) and
             uncomplicated bacterial pharyngitis are permitted if responding to active treatment;
             ongoing infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or hepatitis B (hepatitis B
             surface antigen [HBsAg] positive) or hepatitis C virus (anti hepatitis C virus [HCV]
             positive); a history of hepatitis B or hepatitis C is permitted if the viral load is
             undetectable per quantitative polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and/or nucleic acid
             testing

          -  CNS disorder such as cerebrovascular ischemia/hemorrhage, dementia, cerebellar
             disease, or autoimmune disease with CNS involvement

          -  History of myocardial infarction, cardiac angioplasty or stenting, unstable angina, or
             other clinically significant cardiac disease within 12 months of enrollment, or have
             cardiac atrial or cardiac ventricular lymphoma involvement

          -  Subjects receiving anticoagulation therapy

          -  Any medical condition that in the judgement of the sponsor investigator is likely to
             interfere with assessment of safety or efficacy of study treatment

          -  History of severe immediate hypersensitivity reaction to any of the agents used in
             this study

          -  Women of child-bearing potential who are pregnant or breastfeeding; females who have
             undergone surgical sterilization or who have been postmenopausal for at least 2 years
             are not considered to be of childbearing potential

          -  In the investigator's judgment, the subject is unlikely to complete all
             protocol-required study visits or procedures, including follow-up visits, or comply
             with the study requirements for participation

          -  May not have primary immunodeficiency or history of systemic autoimmune disease (e.g.
             Crohns, rheumatoid arthritis, systemic lupus) resulting in end organ injury or
             requiring systemic immunosuppression/systemic disease modifying agents within the last
             2 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Crystal Mackall</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christin New</last_name>
    <phone>650-497-8815</phone>
    <email>newc@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lucile Packard Children's Hospital Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christin New</last_name>
      <phone>650-497-8815</phone>
      <email>newc@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Crystal L. Mackall</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 3, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 3, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Crystal Mackall, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Philadelphia Chromosome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm, Residual</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

