<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03240601</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>696</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03240601</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Spinal Cord Stimulation to Augment Activity Based Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Combined Influence of Transcutaneous Spinal Cord Stimulation and Locomotor Training on Spasticity and Walking Outcomes After Spinal Cord Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shepherd Center, Atlanta GA</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Foundation Wings For Life</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shepherd Center, Atlanta GA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Involuntary muscle activity, often called spasticity, is a common problem following spinal
      cord injury (SCI) that can make it hard to move. Many things can cause spasticity including:
      muscle stretch, movement, or it can happen for no reason, and it is often described as an
      uncontrolled muscle spasm or feeling of stiffness. Drugs are typically used to treat
      spasticity, but they often have side effects, like muscle weakness, which can add to movement
      problems. Rehabilitation therapies offer alternatives to drugs for treating involuntary
      muscle activity, and rehabilitation can also improve daily function and quality of life.
      These benefits may be greater when several rehabilitation therapies are used together.

      Walking ability can be improved with a type of therapy called &quot;locomotor training&quot;. This type
      of therapy may also have the benefit of decreasing spasticity. When locomotor training is
      combined with electrical stimulation, the benefits of training may be increased. In this
      study, investigators will use a kind of stimulation called transcutaneous spinal cord
      stimulation (&quot;tcSCS&quot;) to stimulate participants' spinal cord nerves during locomotor
      training.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Involuntary muscle activity, often referred to as spasticity, is a common problem following
      spinal cord injury. Spasticity can be evoked by stimuli or occur spontaneously, and it can
      manifest as spasms, clonus, or the stiffness associated with hypertonia. While medications
      are typically used to treat the general symptoms of spasticity, they often have additional
      side effects, like muscle weakness, that can impede rehabilitation. Physical therapeutics
      offer an alternative to these drug treatments, but the most effective therapeutic strategy
      for managing spasticity has not yet been identified. A combination of physical therapeutics
      may provide the best strategy for managing spasticity while also improving general motor
      control for functional movements.

      Walking ability can be improved through locomotor training, which has also been shown to
      reduce spasticity. When locomotor training is combined with electrical stimulation, the
      benefits of training may be increased. To investigate the potential benefits of this
      combinatorial treatment strategy, investigators will use a kind of electrical stimulation
      called transcutaneous spinal cord stimulation (&quot;tcSCS&quot;) to stimulate spinal cord nerves
      during locomotor training.

      In order to facilitate the translation of study findings into clinical practice, this study
      uses a pragmatic design, meaning that the study will involve the use of real world clinical
      settings and practices. Participants will undergo their standard physical therapist directed
      locomotor training program while receiving transcutaneous spinal cord stimulation (tcSCS) as
      an additional treatment. The effects of locomotor training alone will be compared to the
      combination of locomotor training with tcSCS, specifically comparing the effects of these
      treatments on spasticity and walking function.

      Investigators expect that the combination of tcSCS with locomotor training will provide 1) a
      greater reduction in spasticity and 2) a greater improvement of walking function compared to
      locomotor training alone.

      The findings from this study have the potential to rapidly facilitate the translation of a
      novel combination treatment for the management of spasticity and improvement of walking
      function into real world clinical practice.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spasticity - Pendulum/Leg-drop Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This test measures the amount of spasticity in your leg muscles. You will sit at the edge of a mat with your lower legs hanging over the edge of the mat. Motion capture sensors (Xsens) will be placed on both of your legs to record changes in your knee joint angles when your leg is dropped. The examiner will straighten your leg and then allow it to drop and swing over the edge of the mat. The angle of your knee and the movement of your leg will be recorded as it drops. This will be performed three times for each leg separately.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Walking Function - 10m Walk/Walking Speed</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>You will walk over a mat that contains sensors to measure your walking speed as well as wear motion tracking sensors. You will be allowed to use whatever assistive devices you typically use (e.g., braces, walker, forearm crutches). In addition to walking speed, we will also assess your gait kinematics.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spasticity - Ankle Clonus Test/Foot-drop test</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This test measures the amount of spasticity in your ankle. We will use the motion capture sensors to record your ankle joint angles. For this test you will sit upright. Your leg will be raised and released allowing the front of your foot to land on the edge of a box. The angle of your ankle and movement of your foot will be recorded as it drops and catches on the box. This will be performed three times for each leg separately.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spasticity - Co-contraction</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Muscle activity will be recorded using electromyography (EMG) during activities where you move your legs, and activities where your legs are moved by the examiner. Electrodes will be placed on four muscles of your legs (front and back of your thigh and lower leg). you will be asked to move your ankles and extend your legs while we record your muscle activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spasticity - Persistent Involuntary Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>You will be asked to lie on your back for 5 minutes and relax while we record the activity in your muscles using EMG.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spasticity - Spinal Cord Assessment Tool for Spastic Reflexes (SCATS) Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A trained therapist will perform the SCATS assessment before and after each training session. SCATS assesses 3 aspects of spasticity:</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spasticity - Questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>You will be asked a series of questions about your perception of spasticity and how it affects your daily life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Walking Function - 2 Minute Walk</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>You will walk for 2 minutes overground and we will measure how far you walk.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Walking Function - Stepping Task</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>If you are able to take a step without an assistive device, we will test your reaction time and stepping pattern. You will take a step when you hear a sound. You will be wearing motion capture sensors and your muscle activity will be recorded in the same muscles as above, with the addition of muscles at your hips.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Heart Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Your heart rate will be recorded during your training sessions to monitor your effort during training.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Borg Rating of Perceived Exertion (RPE) Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion at 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Borg RPE scale will be used to assess your perception of the level of exertion during training.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Stimulation</condition>
  <condition>Walking</condition>
  <condition>Spasticity</condition>
  <condition>Human</condition>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subthreshold</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals will undergo their standard physical therapist directed locomotor training while receiving transcutaneous spinal cord stimulation. The stimulation intensity will briefly ramp up to the lowest intensity that is first detected by the participant and then ramped down to a level no longer detected by the participant. Participants will continue their locomotor training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals will undergo their standard physical therapist directed locomotor training while receiving transcutaneous spinal cord stimulation. The stimulation intensity will ramp up slowly to a level that produces parasthesia (tingling) throughout the lower extremity. This intensity will be applied for 30 minutes while participants continue their locomotor training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcutaneous spinal cord stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>For tcSCS, a transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS) unit is used. A 2 inch diameter round electrode is placed on the skin over T11/T12 (cathode), and a large butterfly electrode is placed on the skin over the umbilicus (anode). Pulse width is set to 400 microseconds at 50 Hz.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Subthreshold</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Active</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>tcSCS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability and willingness to consent and/or authorize use of protected health
             information

          -  Be between 18-65 years of age

          -  Be enrolled in Spinal Cord Injury Day Program at the Shepherd Center

          -  Be eligible for locomotor training at the Shepherd Center

          -  Be able to take a step, with or without an assistive device

          -  Have a spinal cord injury, completed in-patient rehabilitation, and have been
             discharged to home

          -  Have at least mild &quot;spasticity&quot; affecting leg muscles

          -  You may participate if you use prescription medications, including baclofen for
             control of spasticity

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability or unwillingness to consent and/or authorization for use of protected health
             information

          -  Progressive or potentially progressive spinal lesions, including degenerative, or
             progressive vascular disorders of the spine and/or spinal cord

          -  Neurologic level at or below spinal level T12

          -  History of cardiovascular irregularities

          -  Problems with following instructions

          -  Orthopedic problems that would limit your participation in the protocol (e.g. knee or
             hip flexion contractures of greater than 10 degrees)

          -  Women who are pregnant, or who have reason to believe they are or may become pregnant
             due to unknown risks to the fetus associated with tcSCS

          -  Persons who have implanted stimulators/electronic devices of any type will be excluded
             due to unknown potential of tcSCS effects

          -  Active infection of any type, as infection may exacerbate spasticity resulting in
             inability to identify the influence of the treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen P Estes, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shepherd Center, Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Stephen P Estes, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>4046034967</phone>
    <email>stephen_estes@shepherd.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shepherd Center, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30309</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathy Kreger, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>404-350-7397</phone>
      <email>Kathy_Kreger@Shepherd.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 7, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscle Spasticity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

