<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01258933</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2010-0266</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2011-00274</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01258933</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ofatumumab for Minimal Residual Disease (MRD) and Maintenance Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ofatumumab for Residual Disease and Maintenance Following Chemotherapy or Chemoimmunotherapy in Patients With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) or Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma (SLL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to find out if ofatumumab can control CLL or SLL
      that is left after chemotherapy or chemoimmunotherapy. The safety of the drug will also be
      studied.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Study Drug:

      Ofatumumab is designed to bind to the surface of some white blood cells (B-cells) and to kill
      these cells. It can destroy cancer cells that come from B-cells, and can be used to treat
      cancers of B-cells such as B-CLL.

      Study Drug Administration:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will receive ofatumumab up to
      20 times during this study. You will receive 8 weekly infusions and then an infusion every 2
      months for 2 years or until the disease gets worse. You will receive ofatumumab by vein over
      about 6 ½ hours the first time and over 4 hours for all the following infusions. The first
      infusion will be the smallest dose. The second and later infusions will be 3 times larger
      than the first.

      Before you receive the study drug each time, you will receive Tylenol (acetaminophen) by
      mouth to reduce the risk of fever. You will receive Benadryl (diphenhydramine) by mouth or
      vein and prednisolone (a steroid) by vein over about 30 minutes to reduce the risk of an
      allergic reaction or an infusion reaction.

      During the infusions, you will be monitored closely. You will be expected to stay in clinic
      for about 71/2 hours on the day of the first infusion and 5 hours for all other infusions.

      You will be seen at MD Anderson for mandatory visits for enrollment, ofatumumab infusions,
      for response assessment after 8 weekly ofatumumab doses (Month 3), during maintenance every 6
      months and for follow-up at least once a year. Your local doctor may perform other visits and
      laboratory studies.

      If you decide to have your local doctor perform study visits and laboratory studies, a letter
      will be sent to your doctor, describing your participation in this study and asking for your
      doctor's agreement to help manage your care.

      Study Visits:

      The following tests and procedures will be performed every other week during Weeks 1- 8
      (Weeks 1, 3, 5 and 7):

        -  You will have a complete physical exam including measurement of your vital signs.

        -  Your medical history will be recorded.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      Starting at Month 3, you will have the following tests and procedures every 2 Months:

        -  You will have a complete physical exam including measurement of your vital signs.

        -  Your medical history will be recorded.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      Starting at Month 3, you will also have the following tests and procedures every 6 months, in
      addition to the ones performed every 2 months:

        -  Blood (about an additional 1 teaspoon) will be drawn for other routine tests.

        -  You may have CT scans to check the status of the disease, if your doctor thinks that
           this test is needed (at Month 3 only).

        -  You will have a bone marrow aspirate/biopsy to check the status of the disease.

      Length of Study:

      You may continue taking the study drug for up to 20 doses (up to 24 months). You will no
      longer be able to take the study drug if the disease gets worse or intolerable side effects
      occur.

      Your participation on the study will be over once you have completed the follow-up visits,
      which will last until you begin receiving any other treatment.

      Follow Up Visits:

      Every 3 Months:

        -  You will have a complete physical exam including measurement of your vital signs.

        -  Your medical history will be recorded.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons every 3 months, about 1 teaspoon every 6 months) will be drawn
           for routine tests.

        -  If your doctor thinks it is needed, blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for
           hepatitis testing.

      Every 6 Months, you will have a bone marrow aspirate/biopsy to check the status of the
      disease.

      This is an investigational study. Ofatumumab is FDA approved for CLL resistant to standard
      chemotherapy. Ofatumumab's use in patients with residual CLL or SLL is investigational.

      Up to 42 patients will take part in this study. All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients with Objective Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Response assessment according to 2008 International Working Group for CLL (IWCLL), prior to 9th dose of ofatumumab (prior to first bimonthly dose). Responses of (complete remission (CR) conversion to minimal residual disease (MRD) negative, partial remission (PR) conversion to nodular partial remission nPR or CR, and nPR conversion to complete remission (CR)) evaluated by physical examination, CBC, CT of chest, abdomen, pelvis, and bone marrow aspirate and biopsy with evaluation of residual disease (MRD) by 4-color flow cytometry.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time-to-Treatment Failure (TTF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of study drug up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>TTF assessed according to the 2008 IWCLL recommendations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Start of study drug up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>PFS assessed according to the 2008 IWCLL recommendations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ofatumumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ofatumumab 300 mg dose 1, then 1,000 mg weekly * 7, (treatment) then 1,000 mg every 2 months beginning on week 12 for a total of 2 years of treatment or until progression (maintenance) of disease. The follow-up period will be the period after completion of maintenance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ofatumumab</intervention_name>
    <description>300 mg Dose 1, then 1,000 mg weekly x 7, (treatment) then 1,000 mg every 2 months beginning on week 12</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ofatumumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Arzerra</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of CD20+ chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) or small lymphocytic lymphoma
             (SLL) treated with chemotherapy or chemoimmunotherapy: Post-frontline therapy,
             patients must have non-progressing disease and be 4 months to 1 year post treatment.
             Post-treatment for relapsed CLL, eligible patients must have non-progressing disease
             and be 3 months to 1 year post treatment.

          2. Patients (CR, nPR, or PR at enrollment) must have measurable disease, which may
             include MRD by 4-color flow cytometry.

          3. Adequate renal and hepatic function (creatinine &lt; 2 mg/dL, bilirubin &lt; 2 mg/dL).
             Patients with renal or liver dysfunction due to organ infiltration by lymphocytes may
             be eligible after discussion with the study chairman. Patients with Gilbert's syndrome
             are eligible.

          4. Age &gt;/= 18 years.

          5. ECOG performance status of 0-2.

          6. Provide informed consent indicating patient is aware of the investigational nature of
             this study according to the policies of the MDACC IRB.

          7. Patients of childbearing potential (females who have not been postmenopausal for at
             least 12 consecutive months or who have not undergone previous surgical sterilization
             or males who have not been surgically sterilized) must be willing to practice birth
             control during the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Positive serology for Hepatitis B virus (HB) defined as a positive test for HBsAg. In
             addition, if negative for HBsAg but HBcAb positive (regardless of HBsAb status), a HB
             DNA test will be performed and if positive the subject will be excluded.

          2. Concurrent chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or immunotherapy, including other monoclonal
             antibodies. Localized radiotherapy to an area not comprising bone marrow function does
             not apply.

          3. Active infection or significant medical illness, including current active hepatic or
             biliary disease (with exception of patients with asymptomatic gallstones, liver
             involved with CLL or stable chronic liver disease per investigator assessment).

          4. Pregnant and breastfeeding females are excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William G Wierda, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 9, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 10, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 13, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>CLL</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>SLL</keyword>
  <keyword>Ofatumumab</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm, Residual</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ofatumumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

