<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01253668</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UPCC 04810</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01253668</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brivanib Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Brivanib (BMS-582664, Brivanib Alaninate) in Treatment of Refractory Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma - A Phase II Pharmacodynamic and Baseline Biomarker Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase II study of an investigational agent, brivanib, in patients with refractory
      metastatic renal cell carcinoma. This study will evaluate the safety and effectiveness of
      brivanib in renal cell carcinoma, and explore the activity of this drug in this population to
      determine whether imaging and molecular features of the tumors can be used to predict
      response. Approximately 30 people with advanced kidney cancer will be enrolled on this study
      at the University of Pennsylvania.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objectiveof this clinical trial is to determine the efficacy of brivanib in the
      treatment of metastatic renal cell carcinoma in terms of progression-free survival (PFS) in
      patients whi have progressed on treatment with sunitinib, sorafenib, bevacizumab, or
      pazopanib. The primary endpoint of the trial will be PFS at 16 weeks. The secondary
      objectives are to further examine the safety and tolerability profile of brivanib, to examine
      the efficacy of brivanib in this population in terms of best overall response, response rate,
      progression-free survival, and overall survival, to describe baseline and changes in I-cG250
      PET/CT in relation to observed therapeutic effects., to describe novel baseline histologic
      features of these tumors in relation to observed therapeutic effects. Modalities will include
      VHL and HIF expression assessment and a novel 'histocytometric' assessment of the tumor
      microenvironment in terms of p-STAT3, p-ERK, Ki67, VEGFR2, FGFR1 expression., to describe
      changes in circulating collagen IV on brivanib in relation to therapeutic effects., to
      explore the relationship between single nucleotide polymorphisms in angiogenesis-related
      genes and the activity of brivanib in the treatment of these patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>All patients will be followed through the entire 16-week period and will be given a binary outcome assignment: progressive disease or not.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best overall response rate dfor each patients as assessed by RECIST 1.1 guidelines</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The best overall radiographic response to therapy as measured and assessed using RECIST 1.1 guidelines will be captured for each research subject.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Will record deaths on study, and, to the extent possible, after the study follow-up period is completed for each patient, will be captured. Reason for death will be identified and recorded where possible.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in total antibody binding as assessed by 124I-cG250 PET/CT imaging (correlative studies)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Will determine the baseline and change in total antibody binding in lesions from baseline to the time on treatment that patients are assessed. The analysis dataset will be quantitated radiotracer uptake data obtained via I-cG250 PET/CT for all evaluable patients who complete the trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate for all patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Response Rate for all patients as assessed by RECIST 1.1 guidelines</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Molecular markers</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Molecular markers expressed in patient tumor specimens as assessed by IHC and histocytometry (e.g., VHL, HIF, p-STAT3, p-ERK, and Ki67, VEGFR2, and FGFR1) (correlative studies)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in collagen IV levels</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and week 3</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in collagen IV levels for each patient (correlative studies)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Germline polymorphisms and assessment of relationship to toxicty and clinical outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and week 3</time_frame>
    <description>Germline polymorphisms and assessment of relationship to toxicity and clinical outcome (crrelative studies)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure data</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, day 1 weeks 3,6,8,12,16 and every 6-8 weeks thereafter</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity as assessed by NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, weeks 3,6,9,12,16, and every 6-8 weeks thereafter</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicity as assessed by NCI CTCAE version 4.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Male and Female Subjects 18 Years of Age and Older With Metastatic Renal Cell Carcinoma. Eligible Patients Must Have Undergone and Failed Prior Treatment.</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive oral brivanib alaninate daily in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brivanib alaninate</intervention_name>
    <description>Brivanib by mouth daily at a dose of 800mg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Polymerase chain reaction</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo 1241-cG250 PET/CT imaging (correlative studies)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PCR</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Iodine I 124 chimeric monoclonal antibody G250</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo 124I-cG250 PET/CT imaging (correlative studies)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Positron emission tomography/computed tomography</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo 1241-cG250 PET/CT imaging (correlative studies)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Protein expression analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Immunohistochemistry</intervention_name>
    <description>correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>immunohistochemistry staining method</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female adults with metastatic renal cell carcinoma

          -  Patients will have tumors that bear a clear cell component that comprises greater than
             or equal to 50% of the tumor.

          -  Disease must be measureable in accord with RECIST 1.1 guidelines.

          -  Patients who have developed progressive disease or intolerance on treatment with
             sorafenib, sunitinib, bevacizumab, or pazopanib over a 60 day period who have not
             discontinued this therapy more than 100 days prior to study enrollment. Progressive
             disease per RECIST 1.1 guidelines will be preferred

          -  Therapy with up to three prior systemic regimens will be allowed.

          -  Patients may have been treated with any of the following: sorafenib, sunitinib,
             bevacizumab, pazopanib, temsirolimus, everolimus, interferon alpha, interleuken-2.

          -  Treatment with up to one priorregimen that included cytotoxiv chemotherapy will be
             allowed.

          -  Patients may have been treated with more than 1 antiangiogenic therapy (e.g., patients
             may have been treated with both sorafenib and sunitinib or sunitinib and bevacizumab,
             or sequential combinations that include pazopanib).

          -  Life expectancy of at least 3 months

          -  ECOG performance status of 0 or 1.

          -  Tumor tissue must be available for correlative studies.

          -  Patients must consent to allow the acquisition of FFPE material (block or unstained
             slides) by study personnel for performance of correlative tissue studies.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known brain metastases

          -  Prior therapy with brivanib, or anti-FGFR (fibroblast growth factor receptor)therapy.

          -  History of thrombotic or embolic events within the last six months such as a
             cerebrovascular accident (including transient ischemic attacks), pulmonary embolism.

          -  Gastointestinal bleeding or any other hemmorrhage/bleeding event CTCAE version 4.0
             Grade greater than 3 within 30 days prior to study entry.

          -  Uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease.

          -  QTc greater than 450 msec on two consecutive ECGs (Baseline ECG should be repeated if
             QTc is found to be greater than 450 msec.).

          -  Active infection, less than 7 days after completing systemic antibiotic therapy.

          -  History of non-healing wounds or ulcers or bone fractures within 3 months of fracture.

          -  Major surgical procedure, open biopsy, or significant traumatic injury less than 3
             weeks prior to study enrollment or those who receive minor surgical procedures (e.g.
             core biopsy or fine needle aspiration)within 1 week prior to study enrollment.

          -  Cytotoxic chemotherapy within 3 weeks, bevacizumab within 2 months, or radiation
             therapy within 2 weeks, other targeted therapies (e.g., sorefenib, sunitinib,
             temsirolimus, everolimus)within 2 days.

          -  Inability to swallow tabletsor untreated malabsorption syndrome.

          -  Pre-existing thyroid abnormality with thyroid function that cannot be controlled with
             medication.

          -  History of HIV

          -  Patients with centrally cavitating lung lesions.

          -  Patients requiring therapeutic anticoagulation with warfarin at baseline. However,
             prophylactic therapy with a low molecular weight heparin at baseline is acceptable.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Keefe, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abramson Cancer Center of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 30, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 2, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 14, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 14, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

