<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01255280</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3293841</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01255280</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Behavioral Activation and HIV Risk Reduction for Men Who Have Sex With Men With Crystal Meth Abuse</brief_title>
  <official_title>Behavioral Activation and HIV Risk Reduction for MSM With Crystal Methamphetamine Abuse</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fenway Community Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to research a new behavioral treatment to reduce sexual
      risk-taking in men who have sex with men (MSM) who abuse crystal methamphetamine (crystal
      meth), and are at risk for HIV acquisition. This study proposes using a treatment based on
      our original pilot study that incorporates risk reduction and behavioral activation therapy.
      In order to help learn what types of treatment programs best help individuals who abuse
      crystal meth and engage in sexual risk-taking, we will compare our treatment to a control
      group. The treatment group will receive therapy incorporating behavioral risk reduction
      counseling with behavioral activation therapy to treat depression, helping individuals
      reengage in their life. The control group will receive the risk reduction counseling without
      the behavioral activation therapy. The current study hopes to explore the efficacy of this
      previous developed treatment in a two-arm pilot randomized controlled trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. To estimate, in a two-arm pilot randomized controlled trial (RCT), the effect size of
           the proposed intervention on reductions in sexual risk taking and crystal meth use. The
           primary outcome is the number of unprotected anal sex acts and a secondary outcome is
           reduction in crystal meth use episodes over the follow up period.

        2. To explore the degree to which improvements in sexual risk taking are associated with
           the conceptual mediators of the effects of the intervention: reductions in crystal meth
           use and increases in pleasurable (but safe) activities, BAT skills, use of risk
           reduction skills, and reductions in depressed mood.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sexual risk</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and three months post-treatment; baseline and six months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>We will ask about number of unprotected and protected insertive and receptive anal, vaginal and oral sex acts with male and female sex partners separately for HIV seropositive, seronegative, and partners of unknown HIV status with questions from measures used in previous studies. We will use this to calculate the ratio of protected to unprotected acts, by serostatus partner, and by whether or not crystal meth was being used before or during sex. Baseline and three and six-month follow-up assessments will assess sexual risk taking in the previous 3-months to the assessment being completed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in crystal methamphetamine use</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and three months post-treatment; baseline and six months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>For the present study, we will administer relevant sections of the Drug and Alcohol sections of the NIDA-CTN Addictions Severity Index Lite (ASI-Lite). We will use this methodology to determine the number of days of drug use, specifically crystal meth, and the number of distinct crystal meth episodes between study assessment visits (i.e., separate crystal meth binges).In addition to the ASI-Lite, we will also collect participant self-report measures of substance use via the ACASI. We have adapted and will also use the CDC's National HIV Behavioral Surveillance Survey, MSM cycle.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Crystal Methamphetamine Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Crystal Methamphetamine Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Information, Motivation, Behavioral skills</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The comparison condition will only receive the two IMB risk reduction sessions. The intervention will begin with modules that focus directly with sexual risk reduction practices. It will begin with a discussion of one's sexual history, sexual risk limits, and barriers (e.g., motivation or skills) to staying in their sexual risk limits. This session will also involve a Q&amp;A discussion and the use of a fact sheet regarding HIV acquisition risk behaviors (information). The next session will involve motivational interviewing and the formulation of an individualized behavioral skills plan as needed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation Therapy and Risk Reduction Counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This intervention is given to patients in the experimental condition only and is comprised of 10 sessions—1 baseline session focused on orienting and rationale, 2 focused on risk reduction (consistent with the IMB model: information, motivation, and behavioral skills), 6 incorporating behavioral activation therapy/risk reduction counseling, and 1 final session on relapse prevention. Each session will last approximately fifty minutes in length; and will also involve a review of the previous materials,and hence the behavioral activation approach will be woven back into the risk reduction content.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral Activation Therapy and Risk Reduction Counseling (BAT-RR)</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention is given to patients in the experimental condition only and is comprised of 10 sessions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Activation Therapy and Risk Reduction Counseling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Information, Motivation, Behavioral skills change approach to sexual risk reduction</intervention_name>
    <description>The comparison condition will only receive the two IMB risk reduction sessions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Information, Motivation, Behavioral skills</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: 18 years or older

          -  Self-reports as a man who has sex with men

          -  HIV-uninfected and verifies serostatus at baseline (HIV antibody testing and positive
             tests will be confirmed by Western Blots; see Human Subjects for operational aspects)

          -  Meets DSM-IV diagnostic criteria for crystal meth abuse/dependence

          -  Self reported unprotected anal intercourse—receptive or insertive—with a
             non-monogamous male sexual partner, while concurrently using crystal meth (use of meth
             must be a few hours prior to, or during, sex) in the prior three months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to provide informed consent due to severe mental or physical illness, or
             substance intoxication at the time of interview

          -  Has lived in the greater Boston area for three months or less (as a means to enhance
             participant retention)

          -  Discovery of active suicidal ideation at the time of interview (these patients will be
             referred immediately for treatment, but may join the study when this is resolved)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew Mimiaga, ScD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fenway Community Health and Massachusetts General Hospital/Harvard Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matthew Mimiaga, ScD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>617-927-6084</phone>
    <email>MMimiaga@fenwayhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Janna Gordon</last_name>
    <phone>617-643-1168</phone>
    <email>jrgordon@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fenway Community Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jaclyn White, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>617-927-6101</phone>
      <email>jwhite@fenwayhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rajasingham R, Mimiaga MJ, White JM, Pinkston MM, Baden RP, Mitty JA. A systematic review of behavioral and treatment outcome studies among HIV-infected men who have sex with men who abuse crystal methamphetamine. AIDS Patient Care STDS. 2012 Jan;26(1):36-52. doi: 10.1089/apc.2011.0153. Epub 2011 Nov 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22070609</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 6, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 7, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 31, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 31, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 1, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Matthew James Mimiaga</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Crystal methamphetamine abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>Crystal methamphetamine dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>Sexual risk behavior</keyword>
  <keyword>Men who have sex with men (MSM)</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral activation</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methamphetamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

