<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00010868</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01AT000161-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00010868</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00008957</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Omega-3 Fatty Acids in Bipolar Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Omega-3 Fatty Acids in Bipolar Disorder Prophylaxis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pronova BioPharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 12 month study of omega-3 fatty acids in bipolar disorder. This study will be a
      12-month, parallel group, double-blind comparison of the prophylactic efficacy of omega-3
      fatty acids vs. placebo in 120 bipolar I patients. All subjects entering the primary
      prophylactic study will be euthymic or have only subsyndromal mood symptoms for at least 4
      weeks. In addition, their concomitant medication (only lithium, divalproex, or no medication
      will be permitted) will also be stable and at accepted therapeutic levels for at least 4
      weeks. An 8-week lead-in phase will be available to subjects who do not meet the current
      symptom and concomitant medication inclusion criteria (however, subjects must meet all of the
      other inclusion/exclusion criteria): 1. 4 weeks of euthymic or subsyndromal mood. 2. Subjects
      who are not already receiving lithium or divalproex. 3. Subjects receiving other psychotropic
      medications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Omega-3 Fatty Acids</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Meet DSM-IV criteria for bipolar disorder, type I.

          -  Have had an episode of mania, hypomania, mixed mania, or major depression within the
             preceding 12 months, as defined by SCID criteria.

          -  Able to give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with significant medical co-morbidity, such as active hepatic or renal
             disease, any type of coagulopathy, lipidoses, dementia, history of significant head
             injury, active cancer or cancer treatment, or other medical problems which may
             interfere with the absorption and metabolism of omega-3 fatty acids. In addition, any
             medical disorder with symptoms (e.g. aphasia, encephalopathy, etc.) which would make
             it difficult to determine the clinical response to the study drugs.

          -  Patients with significant psychiatric co-morbidity, such as another currently active
             Axis 1 or 2 disorder requiring treatment. Patients with other, active mental disorders
             may have psychiatric symptoms that would make it difficult to assess mood response to
             the study drugs. For example, a patient with significant anxiety or panic symptoms
             requiring medication would be excluded, whereas a patient with past or currently very
             mild anxiety symptoms not requiring active treatment would be eligible.

          -  Patients receiving Coumadin, or other drugs with strong effects on coagulation will be
             excluded due to the theoretical increased risk of bleeding on omega-3 fatty acid
             therapy. Low dose or intermittent NSAIDs will be permitted.

          -  Patients receiving drugs which affect lipid metabolism, such as HMG CoA inhibitors,
             high-dose niacin, gemfibrozil, and others.

          -  Pregnant patients - due to the unknown effects of high dose omega-3 fatty acids on the
             fetus.

          -  Patients who, in the investigator's judgment pose a current serious suicidal or
             homicidal risk, or patients who will not likely be able to comply with the study
             protocol.

          -  Bipolar patients receiving clozapine. These patients will be excluded due to the
             likelihood of extreme treatment resistance in clozapine-treated bipolar disorder. It
             may be unwise to discontinue the patient's clozapine, since recurrence may occur.
             Also, based on uncontrolled data, clozapine may be a uniquely effective mood
             stabilizer, which would add a potential confound to the study.

          -  Patients who meet DSM-IV criteria for substance abuse within 1 month of this trial or
             substance dependence within 3 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew L. Stoll, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mclean Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McLean Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belmont</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02478</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stoll AL, Severus WE, Freeman MP, Rueter S, Zboyan HA, Diamond E, Cress KK, Marangell LB. Omega 3 fatty acids in bipolar disorder: a preliminary double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1999 May;56(5):407-12.</citation>
    <PMID>10232294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 2, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 5, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 17, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 17, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 18, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>bipolar disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>omega-3 fatty acids</keyword>
  <keyword>eicosapentaenoic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>docosahexaenoic acid</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

