<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00010751</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P50 AT000011-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00010751</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00009412</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Reiki on Painful Neuropathy and Cardiovascular Risk Factors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Chronic Diabetic Painful Neuropathy and Cardiovascular Risk Factors in NIDDM: An Alternative Approach.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The object of this study is to determine if Reiki will improve glycemic control and cardiac
      autonomic function diabetic patients with painful neuropathy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of coronary heart disease(CHD) in type II diabetes is currently at least 20% in
      subjects 65 years and older. Numerous data suggest that hyperglycemia may be an independent
      risk factor for macrovascular complications. Diabetic painful neuropathy (DPN) affects 5-50%
      of patients with diabetes and is exacerbated by poor glycemic control. DPN is characterized
      by acute functional abnormalities in nerve fibers followed by chronic nerve fiber loss and
      blunted nerve fiber regeneration. Symptoms include tingling and burning sensations in the
      calves, ankles and feet. Pharmacological treatment of diabetic autonomic neuropathy (DAN) and
      DPN include tricyclic antidepressants, which are cardiotoxic and have a low efficacy rate.
      The ADA recommends the utilization of diet and exercise as the primary means of glycemic
      control, and therefore of DPN. Because of the increased levels of extremity pain, patients
      with DPN are less likely to include exercise as a part of their health regimen. Diabetic
      autonomic neuropathy (DAN) commonly complicates diabetes and has been invoked as a cause of
      sudden death in diabetic patients. The excess cardiac mortality in diabetics appears to be
      augmented by the presence of DAN in patients with advanced deficits in sympathetic
      cardiovascular enervation which may augment cardiac arrhythmogenesis. An bio-energy modality
      known as Reiki is an energy manipulation technique similar to Therapeutic Touch, a hands-on
      modality familiar in nursing for the relief of chronic pain, as well as accelerate healing in
      full thickness dermal wounds. The study approach is to apply Reiki to patients with DPN +/-
      DAN in a semi-double blind, randomized, crossover study to ascertain if glycemic control and
      cardiac autonomic function are improved in these patients. Outcome measures will include
      HBA1c values, the McGill-Melzack Pain Questionnaire, and a quality of life questionnaire.
      Participants will also be tested as to their ability to tolerate exercise by a 6 minute walk
      test. This study will help elucidate whether an bio-energy technique can reduce pain levels,
      improve glycemic control by increasing exercise tolerance and improve cardiac autonomic
      function, both major contributors to CHD mortality.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Non-Insulin-Dependent</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Reiki</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  NIDDM as defined by the World Health Organization

          -  Diagnosed with DPN +/- DAN for a duration of no less than six months

          -  Women of childbearing potential must be using an acceptable method of contraception to
             prevent pregnancy when they are enrolled in the study and must agree to continue to
             practice an acceptable method of contraception for the duration of their participation

          -  Stability of diabetes control by documentation of &lt;1% fluctuation of HbA1c levels over
             the last twelve months and 3 or less mild hypoglycemic reactions per week. All
             subjects must be prepared to monitor blood glucose values three to four times daily

          -  HbA1c should be &lt;10%

          -  Ability to give informed consent and willingness to sign the Institutional Review
             Board approved consent form

          -  Willingness to cooperate with medical therapy and follow up for the 12 months of the
             study duration

          -  Have the ability to understand English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martin Stevens, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Taubman Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109-0344</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 2, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 5, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 17, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 17, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 18, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

