<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00019760</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>990093</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>99-C-0093</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000067199</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00019760</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00001809</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Isolated Hepatic Perfusion With Melphalan Followed By Chemotherapy in Treating Patients With Unresectable Colorectal Cancer That is Metastatic to the Liver</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Isolated Hepatic Perfusion With Melphalan Followed By Postoperative Hepatic Arterial Chemotherapy in Patients With Unresectable Colorectal Cancer Metastatic to the Liver</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so
      they stop growing or die. Combining more than one drug and giving them in different ways may
      kill more tumor cells.

      PURPOSE: Phase II trial to study the effectiveness of melphalan given as an isolated hepatic
      perfusion followed by chemotherapy infused into the liver in patients who have unresectable
      colorectal cancer that is metastatic to the liver.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine the response rate and response duration in patients with
      unresectable colorectal cancer metastatic to the liver treated with isolated hepatic
      perfusion with melphalan followed by postoperative hepatic arterial chemotherapy.

      II. Determine the patterns of recurrence in this patient population with this treatment
      regimen.

      III. Evaluate the disease-free survival and overall survival in these patients.

      IV. Evaluate health related quality of life and determine whether baseline correlates with
      the length of survival.

      PROTOCOL OUTLINE: Patients undergo surgery and hyperthermic isolated hepatic perfusion with
      melphalan given intra-arterially over 60 minutes.

      At six weeks post-hepatic perfusion, patients receive floxuridine and leucovorin calcium
      intra-arterially as a continuous infusion over 14 days. Treatment repeats every 28 days in
      the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      Quality of life is assessed prior to study and then at each followup visit. Patients are
      followed every 3-4 months for 3 years and then every 6 months thereafter or until disease
      progression.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL:

      A total of 50 patients will be accrued for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Recurrent Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Liver Metastases</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Colon Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>floxuridine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>leucovorin calcium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>melphalan</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        PROTOCOL ENTRY CRITERIA:

        --Disease Characteristics-- Histologically or cytologically proven measurable metastatic
        colorectal cancer limited to the parenchyma of the liver No evidence of unresectable
        extrahepatic disease Limited resectable extrahepatic disease allowed Unresectable liver
        disease defined as: Greater than 3 sites of liver disease OR Bilobar disease OR Tumor
        abutting major vascular or ductal structures, impeding resection with preservation of liver
        function OR Limited extrahepatic disease No biopsy-proven cirrhosis No significant portal
        hypertension --Prior/Concurrent Therapy-- Biologic therapy: At least 4 weeks since prior
        biologic therapy for colorectal cancer and recovered Chemotherapy: At least 4 weeks since
        prior chemotherapy for colorectal cancer and recovered No prior intrahepatic arterial
        infusional therapy using floxuridine Endocrine therapy: Not specified Radiotherapy: At
        least 4 weeks since prior radiotherapy for colorectal cancer and recovered Surgery: See
        Disease Characteristics Other: No concurrent immunosuppressive drugs No concurrent chronic
        anticoagulants --Patient Characteristics-- Age: Not specified Performance status: ECOG 0-2
        Life expectancy: Not specified Hematopoietic: Platelet count greater than 100,000/mm3
        Hematocrit greater than 27.0% WBC greater than 3,000/mm3 Hepatic: Bilirubin less than 2.0
        mg/dL PT no greater than 2 seconds over upper limit of normal Elevated hepatic
        transaminases secondary to liver metastases allowed No veno-occlusive disease Renal:
        Creatinine no greater than 1.5 mg/dL OR Creatinine clearance greater than 60 mL/min
        Cardiovascular: No congestive heart failure with LVEF less than 40% Pulmonary: No chronic
        obstructive pulmonary disease No other chronic pulmonary disease with pulmonary function
        test less than 50% predicted Other: No active infections HIV negative Body weight greater
        than 30 kg Not pregnant or nursing Negative pregnancy test
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>H. Richard Alexander, Jr.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Surgery Branch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 2, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 5, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>adult solid tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>body system/site cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>colon cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>gastrointestinal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>genetic condition</keyword>
  <keyword>liver and intrahepatic biliary tract cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>liver metastases</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent colon cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>site, metastatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>solid tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV colon cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage, colon cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage, rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>unclassified/other cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melphalan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Floxuridine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

