<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00015782</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>010166</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>01-N-0166</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00015782</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Natural History and Pathogenesis of Mucolipidosis Type IV</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Natural History and Pathogenesis of Mucolipidosis Type IV</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Mucolipidosis Type IV (ML-IV) is a metabolic disorder that causes mental and motor
      retardation as well as visual impairment. There is storage of material in practically all the
      cells of the body, causing problems in the brain and the eyes. The disease is caused by a
      defect in a gene that makes a protein called mucolipin. Patients with ML-IV do not make
      enough normal mucolipin.

      More than 80 patients have been diagnosed, most of whom are Ashkenazi Jews. The disease often
      appears in the first year of life as either delayed motor development or corneal clouding.
      There are conflicting reports concerning the progressive nature of the disease. Some patients
      have clear deterioration, while others seem to stay at the same level of the disease for a
      long time. This study may lead to a better understanding of the disease, the medical
      difficulties of patients, and better ways of diagnosing ML-IV.

      Patients with a definite diagnosis of this disease, as well as those patients who need
      confirmation of the disease, are candidates for this study. Patients will be admitted
      annually to the Clinical Center for a maximum of five days. A history will be taken and a
      physical exam done. Blood and urine tests will be done along with brain wave recording,
      complete eye examination, psychological tests, and speech and language and rehabilitation
      evaluations. A maximum of 3 mL/kg of blood will be drawn from children and a total of 60 mL
      from adults. Various eye tests will also be done, some under sedation. DNA will be extracted
      for possible use in other studies. A skin biopsy will be taken on the first visit.

      There is a possibility of improved medical management and rehabilitative treatment as a
      result of participating in this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this protocol is to study patients with various neurometabolic disorders.
      Mucolipidosis type IV (ML-IV), is a developmental and degenerative disease caused by
      mutations in the MCOLN1 gene leading to an absent or dysfunctional protein called mucolipin.
      The goal of this protocol is to assess the neurological and medical status of these patients
      and characterize the clinical and laboratory abnormalities in order to determine the natural
      history of the disease. Patients will be followed at least yearly with comprehensive
      clinical, neurological and ophthalmological examinations combined with neuropsychological,
      blood, urine and radiological tests.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 27, 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 3, 2008</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>30</enrollment>
  <condition>Mucolipidosis Type IV</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA: Mucolipidosis type IV

        All patients with a definitive diagnosis of mucolipidosis type-IV will be considered as
        potential candidates for this study. Patients with compatible clinical history who need
        clinical or laboratory confirmation of ML-IV will be considered as well.

        The general health and well being of each candidate must be sufficient to allow travel to
        the National Institutes of Health (NIH), modest amount of blood drawing, collection of
        appropriate urine samples, performance of necessary roentgenographic and magnetic resonance
        (MR) imaging studies and ophthalmological examinations under monitored sedation.

        The patient must be able to return to the NIH at least once a year on a regular basis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chitayat D, Meunier CM, Hodgkinson KA, Silver K, Flanders M, Anderson IJ, Little JM, Whiteman DA, Carpenter S. Mucolipidosis type IV: clinical manifestations and natural history. Am J Med Genet. 1991 Dec 1;41(3):313-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1789285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 3, 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 7, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Metabolic</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic</keyword>
  <keyword>Storage</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinal Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Degenerative</keyword>
  <keyword>Mucolipidosis Type IV</keyword>
  <keyword>ML-IV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mucolipidoses</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

