<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00016783</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P1015</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PACTG P1015</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ACTG P1015</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>11650</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00016783</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stopping and Restarting Anti-HIV Drugs in Children and Adolescents With Low Blood Levels of HIV</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intensification of HIV-Specific CD4 and CD8 Activity by Cycling Highly Active Antiretroviral Therapy (HAART) in Pediatric/Adolescent Patients With Less Than 50 HIV RNA Copies/ml</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Some patients taking anti-HIV drugs as part of highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART)
      do not show any HIV in the blood; however, some HIV will remain hidden in the body and, if
      the drugs are stopped, will return to the blood. The purpose of this study is to determine if
      short periods of stopping HAART increase the activity of CD8 and CD4 cells (cells of the
      immune system that fight infection), if repeated stopping of these drugs for longer periods
      of time and restarting them will increase effectiveness of HAART, and if the increased immune
      system activity as a result of stopping treatment leads to lower levels of HIV over time.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Some HIV infected patients taking HAART have been able to achieve prolonged suppression of
      HIV viral load for extended periods of time. However, discontinuing HAART has consistently
      resulted in HIV's return to plasma. Both CD8 and CD4 cells are markedly reduced in
      individuals with prolonged HIV suppression; control of and response to cell-associated HIV is
      dependent on immune-mediated mechanisms involving these cells. It is hypothesized that a
      brief and low-level increase in HIV levels resulting from HAART interruption might boost
      HIV-specific CD8 and CD4 T-cell counts. After suppression of viral load with the
      reintroduction of HAART, the expanded CD8 population might be able to better control viral
      replication and better respond to cell-associated HIV. Future treatment interruption may lead
      to longer periods of undetectable viral loads.

      Patients are divided into 2 age cohorts, with Cohort 1 consisting of children and adolescents
      4 years and older up to 21 years of age, and Cohort 2 consisting of children and adolescents
      2 years and older up to 4 years of age. Patients will be assigned to one of 2 groups. Group A
      patients will participate in drug holiday cycles from HAART and then back to HAART; Group B
      is a control group that remains on continuous HAART throughout the study. Cycle 1 for Group A
      patients begins with 18 days of HAART and a 3-day drug holiday. At the end of the drug
      holiday, viral load is measured and HAART is resumed for 28 days (detectable virus cycle) if
      viral load is detectable after the drug holiday. If viral load remains below the level of
      detection, the patient begins the next drug holiday cycle. With each subsequent drug holiday
      cycle, time off HAART will increase by 2 days. Patients failing 4 repeated detectable virus
      (28-day treatment) cycles will be taken off study.

      Patients will be enrolled in this study for a minimum of 142 weeks. For Group A, HIV viral
      load and CD4 cell count are measured at the end of each drug holiday and each HAART
      resumption; HIV-specific CD4 and CD8 responses are measured every 3 cycles; and
      cell-associated HIV is assessed at entry, at 12-week intervals, and at the end of the study.
      For Group B, physical exams are conducted and HIV viral load and other blood work are
      measured every 12 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2006</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>39</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Note: A Study Monitoring Committee (SMC) recommended on 06/22/05 that this study close,
        because the primary objectives in this proof-of-concept study could not be achieved. As of
        06/28/05, Group A participants will discontinue their drug holiday cycles and will be given
        the best possible therapy. All participants in this study will have a final study visit to
        be scheduled as soon as possible, prior to 07/29/05.

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV infected

          -  For Cohort 1, CD4 T-cell percent greater than 20

          -  For Cohort 2, CD4 T-cell percent greater than 25

          -  Viral load less than 400 copies/ml in the year prior to study entry and less than 50
             copies/ml at screening

          -  Taking anti-HIV drugs (including at least 1 protease inhibitor) and have been on
             anti-HIV drugs for at least 1 year prior to study entry

          -  Have been on their current drug regimen for at least 4 months

          -  Willing to follow study procedures

          -  Parental or guardian consent if under 18 years old

          -  Acceptable forms of contraception

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Taking abacavir, nevirapine, efavirenz, or delavirdine

          -  AIDS-related or other infections needing drug treatment at study entry

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Have, or have had in the past, diseases (other than HIV infection) or other conditions
             that, in the doctor's opinion, would interfere with the study

          -  Taking experimental drugs without the consent of the protocol team
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Borkowsky, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>New York University Medical Center, Pediatric Infectious Diseases</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Los Angeles County - USC Med Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hosp of Denver</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>802181088</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Howard Univ Hosp</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20060</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ of Miami (Pediatric)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33161</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chicago Children's Memorial Hosp</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>606143394</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Hosp - Pediatric</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hosp of Boston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>021155724</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ of Medicine &amp; Dentistry of New Jersey / Univ Hosp</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newark</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>071032714</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bronx Lebanon Hosp Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10457</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Lukes/Roosevelt Hosp Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10025</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia Presbyterian Med Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harlem Hosp Ctr</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642-0001</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>State Univ of New York at Stony Brook</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stony Brook</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>117948111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SUNY Health Sciences Ctr at Syracuse / Pediatrics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Syracuse</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Children's Hosp / Baylor Univ</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Juan City Hosp</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Juan</city>
        <zip>009367344</zip>
        <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Puerto Rico</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chun TW, Davey RT Jr, Engel D, Lane HC, Fauci AS. Re-emergence of HIV after stopping therapy. Nature. 1999 Oct 28;401(6756):874-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10553903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davey RT Jr, Bhat N, Yoder C, Chun TW, Metcalf JA, Dewar R, Natarajan V, Lempicki RA, Adelsberger JW, Miller KD, Kovacs JA, Polis MA, Walker RE, Falloon J, Masur H, Gee D, Baseler M, Dimitrov DS, Fauci AS, Lane HC. HIV-1 and T cell dynamics after interruption of highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) in patients with a history of sustained viral suppression. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1999 Dec 21;96(26):15109-14.</citation>
    <PMID>10611346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>García F, Plana M, Vidal C, Cruceta A, O'Brien WA, Pantaleo G, Pumarola T, Gallart T, Miró JM, Gatell JM. Dynamics of viral load rebound and immunological changes after stopping effective antiretroviral therapy. AIDS. 1999 Jul 30;13(11):F79-86.</citation>
    <PMID>10449278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neumann AU, Tubiana R, Calvez V, Robert C, Li TS, Agut H, Autran B, Katlama C. HIV-1 rebound during interruption of highly active antiretroviral therapy has no deleterious effect on reinitiated treatment. Comet Study Group. AIDS. 1999 Apr 16;13(6):677-83.</citation>
    <PMID>10397562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruiz L, Martinez-Picado J, Romeu J, Paredes R, Zayat MK, Marfil S, Negredo E, Sirera G, Tural C, Clotet B. Structured treatment interruption in chronically HIV-1 infected patients after long-term viral suppression. AIDS. 2000 Mar 10;14(4):397-403.</citation>
    <PMID>10770542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 4, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 4, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 7, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy, Combination</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug Administration Schedule</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Protease Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>CD4 Lymphocyte Count</keyword>
  <keyword>CD8-Positive T-Lymphocytes</keyword>
  <keyword>Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-HIV Agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Viral Load</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiretroviral Therapy, Highly Active</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Experienced</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Interruption</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

