<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00011505</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>010097</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>01-H-0097</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00011505</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mobilization of Stem Cells With G-CSF for Collection From Patients With Diamond-Blackfan Anemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of G-CSF-Induced Stem Cell Mobilization Potential in Patients With Diamond-Blackfan Anemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will provide information needed to develop more effective treatments for patients
      with Diamond-Blackfan anemia (DBA). Current treatments include steroids, such as prednisone,
      and blood transfusions. These treatments have potential long-term risk and side effects,
      including osteoporosis and impaired growth from steroids or iron overload from transfusions.
      In addition, as patients reach adulthood, they can develop acute leukemia or bone marrow
      failure. The only cure for DBA is bone marrow transplant, a procedure that itself carries
      serious risks and is an option for only about 25 percent of patients.

      DBA is caused by a mutation (error) in a gene that codes for producing red blood cells from
      stem cells (blood-forming cells produced by the bone marrow). In 5 to 10 years, gene transfer
      therapy may prove to be an effective treatment for DBA. Before this treatment can be
      considered, however, more information is needed about DBA patients and how their stem cells
      function. This study will examine: 1) whether stem cells of patients with DBA respond to
      G-CSF the same way those of healthy people do. (G-CSF is a drug that causes stem cells to
      move from the bone marrow to the blood stream, where they can be collected more easily and in
      larger numbers by a procedure called leukapheresis, described below. If G-CSF does not work
      well in DBA patients, other collection strategies will have to be explored); and 2) whether
      the genetic error in DBA can be corrected by gene transfer into patients' stem cells.

      Patients with Diamond-Blackfan anemia 4 years of age and older who weigh at least 27 pounds
      and who are dependent on red blood cell transfusions may be eligible for this study.
      Candidates will have a medical history taken and a physical examination and will be seen by
      the Clinical Center's Department of Medicine Transfusion for leukapheresis evaluation. They
      will have a bone marrow aspiration and biopsy to confirm the diagnosis of DBA. For these
      tests, the hip area is anesthetized and a needle is used to draw bone marrow from the
      hipbone. If needed, the procedure will be done under sedation.

      Patients will be given G-CSF by injection under the skin for up to 6 days. Blood and stem
      cell counts will be measured from a teaspoon of blood drawn each morning. On the morning of
      the fifth dose, the patient will undergo leukapheresis for collection of stem cells. For this
      procedure, a large catheter (with a diameter no larger than that of a straw) is placed in an
      arm vein to allow blood to flow into a cell separator machine. Most children and some adults
      do not have veins large and strong enough for this tubing, so a large intravenous line called
      a &quot;central line&quot; is placed into a large vein in the neck or groin. This is done under
      sedation and with a local anesthetic. While the patient lies on a bed or recliner, whole
      blood is collected through a catheter in one arm or the central line, the stem cells are
      separated out by spinning, then the red cells, platelets and plasma are returned through a
      second catheter in the other arm or a second opening in the central line. The procedure takes
      about 3 to 5 hours, during which the patient can watch television or videos and have family
      members at the bedside for company. When the procedure is completed, the patient's
      participation in the protocol ends.

      Some of the stem cells collected by leukapheresis will be used for research and some will be
      frozen and stored for possible future transplantation into the patient, if required.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Diamond-Blackfan anemia (DBA) is a congenital hypoproliferative anemia that generally
      presents in infancy. The mainstays of treatment, prednisone and transfusion therapy, have
      long-term toxicity in many patients, and bone marrow transplantation with an HLA-matched
      donor is an option for only a minority of patients. Most importantly, patients with DBA have
      an increased risk of progression of myelodysplastic syndrome, leukemia, and aplastic anemia
      compared to the general population.

      The characterization of potentially mutated genes in DBA is an area of active research, and
      at least one mutation present in about one-fourth of DBA patients may cause disease due to
      decreased production of a ribosomal protein. This finding raises the possibility that the
      disease, at least in some patients, may be correctable by genetic therapy, by which a normal
      copy of the mutated gene can be introduced into the &quot;stem cells&quot; which give rise to red
      cells.

      It is therefore of interest to identify any particular characteristics of DBA patients which
      might delay or hinder the application of gene therapy to their disease. This pilot study of
      15 patients is designed to evaluate: 1) the CD34+ cell mobilization response to
      administration of standard doses of granulocyte-colony stimulating factor (G-CSF), 2) the
      potential for stem cells from DBA patients to be collected by large volume leukapheresis of
      subjects who have been given G-CSF, and 3) the ability of these G-CSF mobilized cells to be
      transduced with vectors being developed for gene therapy applications. Outcome parameters to
      be monitored are the mobilization response to G-CSF, the safety profile and tolerance of
      G-CSF and leukapheresis, and the efficiency of transduction of DBA stem cells with standard
      gene therapy vectors. Effectiveness will be gauged by historical comparison of these
      parameters to normal healthy age-matched volunteer.

      It is important to point out that there is no therapeutic intent to the majority of this
      protocol or direct benefit for enrolled patients. We do plan, however, to cryopreserve the
      remainder of the mobilized cells collected by apheresis for possible autologous
      transplantation in the event of the patient's progression to leukemia of bone marrow failure
      in the future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>April 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>15</enrollment>
  <condition>Diamond Blackfan Anemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>G-CSF</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Leukapheresis</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Male or female patients greater than or equal to 4 years of age and weighing at least 12 kg
        (27 lbs) will be included.

        Diagnosis of DBA as defined by the onset of anemia before age 2; or, if after age 2, a
        positive family history of classical DBA or typical physical anomalies

        Low reticulocyte counts (less than 30,000/ul)

        Absent or blocked maturation of erythroid precursors in the bone marrow.

        Red-cell transfusion dependence

        Adequate birth control while on protocol

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Female patients that are pregnant or lactating

        Neutrophil count less than 1000/uL or platelet count less than 100,000/uL

        Positive DEB stimulation test

        Evidence of transformation to MDS or AML on pre-study marrow aspiration and biopsy, or
        abnormal marrow cytogenetics.

        History or evidence of clinically significant autoimmune inflammatory disease or
        significant cardiopulmonary disease by history or physical exam

        Uncorrected coagulopathy

        Renal disease (GFR less than 100mL/min/1/73 M(2)) as estimated for children by Schwartz
        formula. Adults (age greater than 21) excluded for serum Cr less than 2.5 mg/dL.

        Hepatic disease (bilirubin greater than 2 mg/dL or transaminases greater than 7 times the
        upper limit of normal).

        Seropositivity for hepatitis B (HbsAg), hepatitis C, or HIV will be excluded.

        Other medical illness or condition which, in the opinion of the Investigators, may
        contraindicate participation in this study due to risk to patient or comprise of study
        integrity.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kynaston JA, West NC, Reid MM. A regional experience of red cell aplasia. Eur J Pediatr. 1993 Apr;152(4):306-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8482277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ball SE, McGuckin CP, Jenkins G, Gordon-Smith EC. Diamond-Blackfan anaemia in the U.K.: analysis of 80 cases from a 20-year birth cohort. Br J Haematol. 1996 Sep;94(4):645-53.</citation>
    <PMID>8826887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Willig TN, Gazda H, Sieff CA. Diamond-Blackfan anemia. Curr Opin Hematol. 2000 Mar;7(2):85-94. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10698294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>G-CSF</keyword>
  <keyword>Leukapheresis</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem Cell Cryopreservation</keyword>
  <keyword>Central Line Placement</keyword>
  <keyword>G-CSF Administration</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem Cell Preservation</keyword>
  <keyword>Diamond Blackfan Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Diamond-Blackfan</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenograstim</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

