<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02691312</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201501086</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02691312</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pediatric Type 1 Diabetes and Retinopathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevalence and Characterization of Retinopathy in Children With Type 1 Diabetes Using a Non-mydriatic Fundus Camera</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diabetic retinopathy (DR) causes more new cases of blindness among young adults than any
      other disease. More than 90% of individuals with type 1 diabetes (T1D) will have some form of
      DR by 20 years after their diagnosis. DR is associated with long-term hyperglycemia and blood
      glucose variability, which induces vascular endothelial dysfunction and destruction in the
      retina, eventual retinal ischemia, and in the end, widespread neovascularization of the
      retina and optic disk. When these fragile vessels bleed, they can cause vitreous hemorrhage
      and loss of vision. Eventually the friable vessels fibrose and can result in retinal
      detachment or further retinal ischemia.

      Major risk factors for the development of diabetic retinopathy are time since diagnosis, age
      at diagnosis, and severity of hyperglycemia. Retinopathy most commonly occurs at least three
      years after diagnosis and most cases are diagnosed more than five years after the onset of
      T1D. Current guidelines from the American Diabetes Association (ADA) and American Academy of
      Ophthalmology (AAO) recommend that patients with T1D undergo an initial comprehensive dilated
      fundoscopic evaluation once the individual has had diabetes for 3-5 years and has either
      reached puberty or 10 years of age, whichever is earlier. These patients should receive a
      yearly exam thereafter, or every two years based upon the recommendation of an eye care
      professional. However, the prevalence of retinopathy in children is unknown and adherence to
      these guidelines, especially in youth, has proven difficult. Thus, it is important to make
      these guidelines more evidence based, as retinopathy is often asymptomatic until vision loss
      occurs. The first step in this process is the determination of the prevalence of retinopathy
      in a general population of youth with diabetes. This should be followed by determining which
      children are most at risk, so the guidelines can provide realistic and pertinent guidance to
      practitioners.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will be a prospective cross-sectional study of pediatric participants who have had
      T1D for one year or more. Pediatric participants will be recruited at the Florida Diabetes
      Camps, the Children With Diabetes Friends for Life Orlando Conference, and the University of
      Florida Pediatric Endocrinology Clinics. The participants will be tested for diabetic
      retinopathy using a Digital Retinography System (DRS)
      (http://www.centervue.com/producta556.html?id=637). The DRS is a portable non-mydriatic
      fundus camera in which the participants places their chins on the chin-rest and the device
      takes a digital image of their eyes for evaluation by an ophthalmologist remotely. These
      photographs will be examined by an ophthalmologist (specializing in retinal disease) to
      assess for evidence of diabetic retinopathy.

      As part of their informed consent, all participants will be asked as part of their informed
      consent to allow study staff to contact their local ophthalmologist for their eye exam
      results following a positive or inconclusive portable retinal screening. Participants or
      their guardians will also be asked to fill out a study questionnaire during the screening
      visit. When available, the study subjects' medical record will be accessed to identify their
      BMI, time since T1D diagnosis, previous hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) levels over the last 12 months
      (or longer if available), insulin regimen, Tanner staging, serum lipids, urine
      microalbumin:creatinine, presence or absence of hypertension, and previous diagnoses of
      diabetic retinopathy, microalbuminuria, hyperlipidemia or hypertension.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 20, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants diagnosed with retinopathy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Using a CenterVue Digital Retinography System (DRS) the participants with a positive or inconclusive screen will be called with the results and recommended to undergo a dilated eye examination by a skilled ophthalmologist. The results from the ophthalmologist will be compared to the DRS results.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Retinopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Type 1 diabetes (T1D)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Pediatric patients with type 1 diabetes (T1D) will have an eye exam using the Digital Retinography System (DRS) taking non-mydriatic fundus images. If the test is positive or inconclusive, subjects will be notified and referred to an ophthalmologist for a dilated retinal exam. A chart review and questionnaire will be completed to evaluate for risk factors predisposing subjects to diabetic retinopathy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Digital Retinography System</intervention_name>
    <description>The DRS is a portable non-mydriatic fundus camera in which children place their chin on a chin rest and the camera, after auto-focusing, takes photographs of their retinas. These photographs will be examined by an ophthalmologist (specializing in retinal disease) to assess for evidence of diabetic retinopathy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Type 1 diabetes (T1D)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CenterVue Digital Retinography System</other_name>
    <other_name>DRS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        People with type 1 diabetes and a duration of 1 year or greater will be asked to
        participate. Potential participants will be approached at the Pediatric Endocrinology
        clinic visits, Florida Diabetes Camp and the Children With Diabetes annual meeting.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of type 1 diabetes

          -  Duration of diabetes 1 year or greater

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diabetes less than 1 year duration

          -  Age &lt; 9 years and &gt;26 years of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>9 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>26 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janet H Silverstein, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Diabetes Camps</name>
      <address>
        <city>De Leon Springs</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatrics Endocrinology/Diabetes at UF Health Medical Plaza and Children's Medical Services Building</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children With Diabetes Friends For Life Conference</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32821</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 25, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>type 1 diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>retinopathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_type>FDA 501(k)</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/cdrh_docs/pdf10/K101935.pdf</doc_url>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

