<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02695459</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>M14NEC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02695459</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cisplatinum and Everolimus in Patients With Metastatic or Unresectable NEC of Extrapulmonary Origin</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Cisplatinum and Everolimus in Patients With Metastatic or Unresectable Neuroendocrine Carcinomas (NEC) of Extrapulmonary Origin</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Netherlands Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Netherlands Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase II, open-label, multicentre national study. Patients with metastatic neuroendocrine
      carcinomas of extrapulmonary origin will be eligible. Treatment will be performed as
      indicated in the section &quot;Investigational drug and reference therapy&quot;. Cisplatinum and
      everolimus dosing is based upon earlier phase 1 studies (Fury et al. 2012). CTs will be done
      at 9 weekly intervals (after 3 courses of chemotherapy;). Patients will be treated until
      documented progression according to RECIST 1.1. Enrolment is expected to take between 14 - 16
      months. The total study duration is estimated to be 2 to 3 years until publication. Three NET
      centres in The Netherlands will participate, (Erasmus Medical Center in Rotterdam,
      Netherlands Cancer Institute in Amsterdam and , the University Medical Center of Groningen) A
      pre-treatment (and optional post-treatment) tumour biopsy will be included for DNA/RNA
      analyses and organoid culture. An additional 5cc of blood will be withdrawn as a germline DNA
      reference. A second 5 cc of blood will be included for measuring circulating tumour
      transcripts to identify all types of GEP-NET (NETTest).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 30, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>disease control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>every 9 weeks until up to 16 months</time_frame>
    <description>patients having a complete response, partial response or stable disease are considered successes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time to relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Time from registration until the date of death from any cause, assessed up to 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on the markers chromogranin A (CgA) and neuron-specific enolase (NSE);</measure>
    <time_frame>from registration in the study markers will be taken every cycle until a maximum of 6 cycles is reached (cycle is every 3 weeks), until a maximum of 18 weeks.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of everolimus in combination with cisplatin (AEs according to CTCAE v4.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 30 days after end of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>discovery of biomarkers (including circulating neuroendocrine tumour transcripts: NETTest) for treatment response;</measure>
    <time_frame>during the 6 cycles of treatment until 30 days post-treatment</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">39</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuroendocrine Carcinomas</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>cisplatinum and everolimus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cisplatinum : 75 mg/m2 days 1,iv Everolimus : 7.5 mg daily: days 1-21 orally</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cisplatinum and everolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Cisplatinum : 75 mg/m2 days 1,iv Everolimus : 7.5 mg daily: days 1-21 orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>cisplatinum and everolimus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>cisplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>everolimus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Pathologically confirmed unresectable locally advanced and/or metastatic NEC of
             extrapulmonary origin (WHO 2010 classification; Ki67 &gt;20 %) where no curative
             (chemoradiation) treatment options are available(including merkel cell carcinoma).

          2. Measurable disease according to RECIST 1.1, on CT-scan or MRI

          3. ECOG Performance status 0-2 (see Appendix 2)

          4. Adequate bone marrow function as shown by: ANC≥1.5 x 109/L, Platelets ≥100 x 109/L, Hb
             &gt;6 mmol/L

          5. Adequate liver function as shown by:

               -  Total serum bilirubin ≤1.5 ULN

               -  ALT and AST ≤2.5x ULN (≤5x ULN in patients with liver metastases)

          6. Adequate renal function: calculated creatinin clearance &gt; 60ml/min. (Cockcroft-Gault
             formula)

          7. Life expectancy of at least 3 months.

          8. Male or female age ≥ 18 years.

          9. Signed informed consent.

         10. Able to swallow and retain oral medication.

         11. Locally advanced or metastatic lesion(s) of which a histological biopsy can safely be
             obtained:

               -  Patients with safely accessible locally advanced or metastatic lesion(s)
                  including bone lesions.

               -  Patients not known with bleeding disorders (such as hemophilia) or bleeding
                  complications from biopsies, dental procedures or surgeries.

               -  Patients not using any anti-coagulant medication at the time of biopsy: all
                  aspirin derivatives, NSAID's, coumarines, platelet function inhibitors, heparins
                  (including LMWHs) and oral factor Xa inhibitors are not allowed, unless
                  medication can either be safely stopped or counteracted.

               -  Adequate coagulation status as measured by:

                    -  PT &lt; 1.5 x ULN or PT-INR &lt; 1.5

                    -  APTT &lt; 1.5 x ULN

                    -  On the day of biopsy in patients using coumarines: PT-INR &lt; 1.5

         12. Patients not known with contraindications for lidocaine (or its derivatives)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous chemotherapy for metastatic or unresectable NEC of extrapulmonary origin.
             (prior peri-operative chemotherapy or chemoradiation for curative intention is allowed
             if at least 6 months have elapsed between completion of this therapy and enrolment
             into the study).

          2. Prior therapy with mTOR inhibitors (e.g. sirolimus, temsirolimus, deforolimus,
             everolimus)

          3. Other malignancy within the last 5 years, except for carcinoma in situ of the cervix,
             or basal cell carcinoma.

          4. Known intolerance or hypersensitivity to everolimus or other rapamycin analogs (e.g.
             sirolimus, temsirolimus) or cisplatinum

          5. Known impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of oral everolimus

          6. Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus as defined by HbA1c &gt;8% despite adequate therapy.
             Patients with a known history of impaired fasting glucose or diabetes mellitus (DM)
             may be included, however blood glucose and antidiabetic treatment must be monitored
             closely throughout the trial and adjusted as necessary

          7. Patients who have any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions such as: a.
             unstable angina pectoris, symptomatic congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction
             ≤6 months prior to randomization, serious uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia and poorly
             controlled hypertension (systolic BP &gt;180 mmHg or diastolic BP &gt;100 mmHg);. b. active
             or uncontrolled severe infection, c. liver disease such as cirrhosis, decompensated
             liver disease, and known history chronic hepatitis d. known severely impaired lung
             function (spirometry and DLCO 50% or less of normal and O2 saturation 88% or less at
             rest on room air), e. active, bleeding diathesis;

          8. Chronic treatment with corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive agents

          9. Known history of HIV seropositivity

         10. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women

         11. Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, unless they are using highly effective methods of contraception
             during dosing and for 6 months after stopping study treatment.

         12. Sexually active males, unless they use a condom during intercourse while taking study
             medication and for 6 months after stopping study medication.

         13. Patients with dyspnoea at rest due to complications of advanced malignancy or other
             disease, or who require supportive oxygen therapy.

         14. History or clinical evidence of brain metastases.

         15. Any investigational drug treatment within 4 weeks of start of study treatment.

         16. Radiotherapy within 4 weeks of start of study treatment (2 week interval allowed if
             palliative radiotherapy given to bone metastatic site peripherally and patient
             recovered from any acute toxicity).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>M. Tesselaar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NKI-AvL</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>M. Tesselaar, MD</last_name>
    <email>m.tesselaar@nki.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NKI-AVL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1066CX</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>M. Tesselaar, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMCG</name>
      <address>
        <city>Groningen</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>A.M.E. Walenkamp, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Erasmus Medisch Centrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>F. Eskens, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Neuroendocrine</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

