<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02694432</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO15120045</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R34HL123500-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02694432</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Minding GOALS: An Internet-Assisted Mind-Body-Behavior Program for Blood Pressure Control</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Internet-Assisted Mind-Body-Behavior Program for Blood Pressure Control</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot study will evaluate the feasibility of adding an online mind-body-behavior program
      to an existing behavioral self-management support platform that has been modified to promote
      achievement of blood pressure goals.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Efficacious hypertension therapies are well-documented, yet 40% of treated patients do not
      meet the blood pressure goals set by the Joint National Committee. This gap between
      scientific evidence and clinical outcomes in part reflects low patient adherence to lifestyle
      recommendations (e.g., physical activity, weight and diet), as well as medication
      non-adherence. Accordingly, growing attention is focused on the need to provide patients with
      effective self-management support tools. In addition to finding ways to help patients adhere
      to currently prescribed hypertension care, it is useful to consider the range of treatment
      options that are offered. Evidence-based reviews have identified stress reduction as an
      effective tool for reducing blood pressure, yet such approaches are typically not implemented
      in practice. This omission represents a chance to improve the quality of hypertension care by
      adding stress management self-management tools. Furthermore, since patients have demonstrated
      a clear interest in mindfulness, the incorporation of a holistic mind-body intervention is an
      innovative approach to inherently patient-centered care. Increasing data supports the use of
      mindfulness for treating health concerns. Its holistic nature may be particularly well-suited
      to developing and maintaining healthy lifestyles, since lifestyle impacts diverse aspects of
      physical and psychological health. Yet the potential for mindfulness in health
      self-management has not been realized.

      Limited but promising data demonstrate the effectiveness of web-based counseling for behavior
      modification to improve common chronic disease risk factors. It is an ideal solution to
      provider time constraints and a potential solution to patient non-adherence to lifestyle
      recommendations. Health information technology provides a way to make self-management support
      affordable, convenient and feasible. The investigators have developed a convenient behavioral
      self-management support platform, &quot;Goal‐oriented Online Access to Lifestyle Support&quot; (GOALS)
      for primary care patients, which has promoted weight loss and improved blood pressure control
      among primary care patients with weight-related cardiovascular risk factors. To maximize the
      ability of patients to achieve blood pressure goals, the investigators propose to add an
      online mind-body-behavior program to GOALS: &quot;Minding GOALS.&quot; The investigators will evaluate
      the feasibility of using this program for self-management support, in coordination with
      primary care, in a group of 76 patients with uncontrolled hypertension. In preparation for a
      randomized clinical trial comparing the online tool to online traditional self-management
      support, the investigators will assess implementation and determine 1) the availability of
      eligible and willing subjects using the proposed recruitment methods, 2) the feasibility of
      delivering the proposed interventions in the population of interest, and 3) the viability of
      the proposed measurement protocols.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in systolic blood pressure and diastolic blood pressure (mm Hg)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4- and 12-months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sodium excretion (mmol/24 hr.)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>From 24-hr urine collection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body weight (kg)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4- and 12-months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Mass Index (kg/m2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4- and 12-months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity (steps/day)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4- and 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by pedometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4- and 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>PROMIS (Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System)-29 Profile v2.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Stress Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4- and 12-months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4- and 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>PROMIS-29 Profile v2.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mindful Attention Awareness Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4- and 12-months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Morisky Medication Adherence Scale (MMAS-8)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4- and 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported scale to measure medication adherence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Credibility/Expectancy Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4- and 12-months</time_frame>
    <description>For measuring treatment expectancy and rationale credibility in clinical trials</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">76</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GOALS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will use for approximately four months an online platform, GOALS, consisting of weekly lessons designed to enhance blood pressure control. Recommended lifestyle changes for hypertension, including a low-sodium diet, physical activity, weight loss (if appropriate) and behavioral self-management skills will be offered. Attention to medication adherence and pharmacist support as well as that of a dedicated online health coach and ongoing collaboration with the primary care physician are also provided.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Minding GOALS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will also use the GOALS standard tools for blood pressure control. To further maximize success, they will receive additional online behavioral training throughout the 4-month intervention that focuses on mind-body approaches. Weekly topics, for example, will include meditation lessons, mindfulness-based stress reduction and mindfulness-based eating awareness.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GOALS</intervention_name>
    <description>16 weeks of online support to improve blood pressure using traditional behavioral lifestyle approaches and medication adherence support.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GOALS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Minding GOALS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Minding GOALS</intervention_name>
    <description>16 weeks of online support to improve blood pressure using traditional behavioral lifestyle approaches and medication adherence support, coupled with a mind-body-behavior program to further enhance improvements in blood pressure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Minding GOALS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Stress reduction</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Systolic blood pressure &gt;/= 150 mmHg and/or

          -  Diastolic blood pressure &gt;/= 90 mmHg and

          -  At least one other cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk factor (i.e., diabetes,
             dyslipidemia, family history of premature CVD, current smoking, obesity)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known secondary hypertension of any etiology, malignant hypertension or hypertensive
             encephalopathy

          -  Severe edema

          -  A primary care physician (PCP) of the opinion that the patient is unable to safely
             undertake moderately intense unsupervised physical activity (equivalent of 30 minutes
             brisk walking)

          -  A PCP of the opinion that the patient has inadequate cognitive function to participate

          -  Previous participation in a mindfulness meditation program

          -  An inability to learn adequately from English language materials

          -  Current pregnancy or planned pregnancy within the next year

          -  A prior diagnosis of post-traumatic stress disorder

          -  Prior use of GOALS
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>79 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Natalia Morone, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathleen M McTigue, MD, MS, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Research on Health Care, University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>McTigue KM, Conroy MB, Hess R, Bryce CL, Fiorillo AB, Fischer GS, Milas NC, Simkin-Silverman LR. Using the internet to translate an evidence-based lifestyle intervention into practice. Telemed J E Health. 2009 Nov;15(9):851-8. doi: 10.1089/tmj.2009.0036.</citation>
    <PMID>19919191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McTigue KM, Bhargava T, Bryce CL, Conroy M, Fischer GS, Hess R, Simkin-Silverman LR, Zickmund S. Patient perspectives on the integration of an intensive online behavioral weight loss intervention into primary care. Patient Educ Couns. 2011 May;83(2):261-4. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2010.05.009. Epub 2010 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21459256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McTigue KM, Conroy MB. Use of the internet in the treatment of obesity and prevention of type 2 diabetes in primary care. Proc Nutr Soc. 2013 Feb;72(1):98-108. doi: 10.1017/S0029665112002777. Epub 2012 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23098133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morone NE, Greco CM, Weiner DK. Mindfulness meditation for the treatment of chronic low back pain in older adults: a randomized controlled pilot study. Pain. 2008 Feb;134(3):310-9. Epub 2007 Jun 1.</citation>
    <PMID>17544212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morone NE, Lynch CS, Greco CM, Tindle HA, Weiner DK. &quot;I felt like a new person.&quot; the effects of mindfulness meditation on older adults with chronic pain: qualitative narrative analysis of diary entries. J Pain. 2008 Sep;9(9):841-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2008.04.003. Epub 2008 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>18550444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simkin-Silverman LR, Conroy MB, Bhargava T, McTigue KM. Development of an online diabetes prevention lifestyle intervention coaching protocol for use in primary care practice. Diabetes Educ. 2011 Mar-Apr;37(2):263-8. doi: 10.1177/0145721710396587.</citation>
    <PMID>21421991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morone NE, Greco CM, Rollman BL, Moore CG, Lane B, Morrow L, Glynn NW, Delaney J, Albert SM, Weiner DK. The design and methods of the aging successfully with pain study. Contemp Clin Trials. 2012 Mar;33(2):417-25. doi: 10.1016/j.cct.2011.11.012. Epub 2011 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22115971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Natalia Morone</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine &amp; Clinical and Translational Science</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>high blood pressure, systolic, diastolic</keyword>
  <keyword>complementary therapies, meditation</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

