<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02693717</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-0592</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2016-00390</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02693717</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial to Evaluate Pemetrexed Clinical Responses in Relation to Tumor MTAP Gene Status in Patients With Previously Treated Metastatic Urothelial Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial to Evaluate Pemetrexed Clinical Responses in Relation to Tumor MTAP Gene Status in Patients With Previously Treated Metastatic Urothelial Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if Altima (pemetrexed) can help to
      control urothelial cancer (bladder, urethra, and/or ureters) that has spread or cannot be
      controlled with surgery. The safety of this drug will also be studied. Researchers will also
      study how a gene called MTAP may affect the way the study drug works.

      This is an investigational study. Pemetrexed is FDA approved for the treatment of
      mesothelioma and non small cell lung cancer. Pemetrexed is not FDA approved for urothelial
      cancer. It is being used for research purposes only.

      Up to 25 participants will be enrolled in this study. All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Drug Administration:

      The day of your first dose of pemetrexed:

        -  You will start a vitamin pill (folic acid). You will continue to take folic acid every
           day by mouth while you are receiving pemetrexed. Folic acid has been found to decrease
           some of the side effects of pemetrexed.

        -  You will start vitamin B12. B12 is given by injection into the muscle. It will be given
           every 9 weeks during your treatment. B12 has been found to decrease some of the side
           effects of pemetrexed.

        -  You will start receiving dexamethasone. You will receive dexamethasone by vein over
           about 5-15 minutes on Day 1 of each 21-day cycle. You will also take it by mouth twice a
           day for 2 days after each dose of pemetrexed to help prevent skin rash.

        -  If you are able to become pregnant and the study doctor thinks it is needed, the
           pregnancy blood test (about 1 tablespoon) will be repeated.

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will receive pemetrexed by
      vein over about 10 minutes on Day 1 of each 21-day cycle.

      Study Visits:

      On Day 1 of all cycles. If you have had these performed within 7 days, they need not be
      repeated.

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 1-2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

      Every 3 cycles:

        -  You will have a bone scan and CT scans and/or MRI to check the status of the disease.

        -  You will have a PET scan if you had one at screening.

        -  You will have bone scan if the disease has spread to your bones.

      Length of Dosing:

      You may take pemetrexed for as long as the doctor thinks it is in your best interest. You may
      no longer be able to take the study drug if intolerable side effects occur, or if you are
      unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation on the study will be over after the follow-up visits.

      End-of-Study Visit:

      If the study drug is stopped early, or when you are taken off study for any reason, within 3
      weeks of your last dose of study drug the following tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  If the doctor thinks it is needed, you will have the PET scan, CT scan and/or MRI to
           check the status of the disease.

      Follow-Up Visits/Calls:

      You will have additional follow up visits every 3 months for a total of 5 years. If you are
      not able to travel someone will call you to find out how you are doing. The call will last
      about 5-10 minutes each time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 9, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (ORR) of Participants with MTAP-deficient vs. MTAP Wild-Type Bladder Cancer Treated With Pemetrexed</measure>
    <time_frame>63 days</time_frame>
    <description>ORR defined as the number of subjects with a best response of complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) at any protocol evaluation by RECIST 1.1 criteria divided by the total number of subjects receiving their first dose of trial therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS) of Participants with MTAP-deficient vs. MTAP Wild-Type Bladder Cancer Treated With Pemetrexed</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>PFS defined as the time from trial entry to the first documented tumor progression as determined by the investigator using the RECIST 1.1 criteria or death from any cause, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS) of Participants with MTAP-deficient vs. MTAP Wild-Type Bladder Cancer Treated With Pemetrexed</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>OS defined as the time from trial entry to death from any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Urothelial Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MTAP-deficient (MTAP-/-) Bladder Cancer (Cohort 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pemetrexed 500 mg/m2 administered as an intravenous infusion over 10 minutes on Day 1 of each 21-day cycle.
5 daily doses of Folic acid 400 µg taken during the 7-day period preceding the first dose of Pemetrexed; and dosing continues during the full course of therapy, and for 3 weeks after the last dose of Pemetrexed.
Vitamin B12 1000 μg administered as an intramuscular injection approximately 1 to 2 weeks prior to first dose of Pemetrexed and repeated approximately every 9 weeks until 3 weeks after the last dose of study therapy.
Dexamethasone (4 mg of oral or equivalent) given twice daily should be taken on the day of, and two days after each dose of Pemetrexed, for rash prophylaxis unless medically contraindicated.
Dexamethasone 10 mg administered as an intravenous infusion on Day 1 of each 21-Day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MTAP-normal (MTAPwt) Bladder Cancer (Cohort 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pemetrexed 500 mg/m2 administered as an intravenous infusion over 10 minutes on Day 1 of each 21-day cycle.
5 daily doses of Folic acid 400 µg taken during the 7-day period preceding the first dose of Pemetrexed; and dosing continues during the full course of therapy, and for 3 weeks after the last dose of Pemetrexed.
Vitamin B12 1000 μg administered as an intramuscular injection approximately 1 to 2 weeks prior to first dose of Pemetrexed and repeated approximately every 9 weeks until 3 weeks after the last dose of study therapy.
Dexamethasone (4 mg of oral or equivalent) given twice daily should be taken on the day of, and two days after each dose of Pemetrexed, for rash prophylaxis unless medically contraindicated.
Dexamethasone 10 mg administered as an intravenous infusion on Day 1 of each 21-Day cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pemetrexed</intervention_name>
    <description>500 mg/m2 by vein on Day 1 of each 21-day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MTAP-deficient (MTAP-/-) Bladder Cancer (Cohort 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MTAP-normal (MTAPwt) Bladder Cancer (Cohort 2)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LY231514</other_name>
    <other_name>Alimta</other_name>
    <other_name>MTA</other_name>
    <other_name>Multitargeted Antifolate</other_name>
    <other_name>NSC-698037</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Folic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>5 daily doses of Folic Acid 400 µg by mouth taken during the 7-day period preceding the first dose of Pemetrexed; and dosing should continue during the full course of therapy and for 3 weeks after the last dose of Pemetrexed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MTAP-deficient (MTAP-/-) Bladder Cancer (Cohort 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MTAP-normal (MTAPwt) Bladder Cancer (Cohort 2)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Folinic Acid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin B12</intervention_name>
    <description>1000 μg administered as an intramuscular injection approximately 1 to 2 weeks prior to first dose of Pemetrexed and repeated approximately every 9 weeks until 3 weeks after the last dose of study therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MTAP-deficient (MTAP-/-) Bladder Cancer (Cohort 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MTAP-normal (MTAPwt) Bladder Cancer (Cohort 2)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>4 mg of oral or equivalent given twice daily should be taken on the day of, and two days after each dose of Pemetrexed, for rash prophylaxis unless medically contraindicated.
10 mg administered as an intravenous infusion on Day 1 of each 21-Day cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MTAP-deficient (MTAP-/-) Bladder Cancer (Cohort 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MTAP-normal (MTAPwt) Bladder Cancer (Cohort 2)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Decadron</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must have histological confirmation of metastatic urothelial carcinoma.
             Patients must have sufficient tumor tissues for future MTAP testing and research.
             Histological variants such as glandular, squamous, sarcomatoid, micropapillary,
             plasmacytoid, and small cell changes will not be allowed for this trial unless these
             tumors are MTAP-deficient.

          2. All patients must have measurable disease and tumors of sufficient sizes for biopsy.
             In general, liver and lung lesions should be at least 1.0 cm, and patients with lymph
             node-only disease should have lesions of &gt;/= 1.5 cm in shortest dimension. Patients
             with disease confined to bone may be eligible if a measurable lytic defect is present.
             The study PI is the final arbiter in questions related to measurability. Patients with
             a three-dimensional mass or pelvic sidewall fixation on bladder examination under
             anesthesia are considered to have measurable disease.

          3. Patients who have received any non-anti-folate containing neoadjuvant or systemic
             chemotherapy are eligible. Any prior intravesical therapy, or immunotherapy is
             allowed.

          4. Patients must have an ECOG performance status &lt;/= 2.

          5. Adequate liver function as defined by AST or ALT &lt;/= 3 x ULN, or &lt;/= 5 x ULN if
             documented liver metastases are present.

          6. Total bilirubin &lt;/= 1.5 x ULN, except subjects with Gilbert's syndrome or liver
             metastases, who must have a baseline total bilirubin &lt;/= 3.0 mg/dL.

          7. Adequate bone marrow reserves as define by an ANC &gt;/= 1500, and platelets &gt;/= 100,000.

          8. Adequate renal function as defined by a normal serum creatinine, or a creatinine
             clearance &gt;/= 40 ml/min [either measured using a 24 hour urine, calculated using
             Cockcroft-Gault, or estimated using the MDRD method from the National Kidney Disease
             Education Program (NKDEP) (the method reported by MDACC laboratories)]

          9. Females of childbearing potential who are sexually active with a non-sterilized male
             partner and non-sterilized males must use a highly effective method of contraception
             for 28 days prior to the first dose of investigational product, and must agree to
             continue using such precautions for 180 days after the final dose of investigational
             product; cessation of contraception after this point should be discussed with a
             responsible physician.

         10. inclusion 9 continued: They must also refrain from egg cell donation for 180 days
             after the final dose of investigational product; a) Females of childbearing potential
             are defined as those who are not surgically sterile (ie, bilateral tubal ligation,
             bilateral oophorectomy, or complete hysterectomy) or postmenopausal (defined as 12
             months with no menses without an alternative medical cause)

         11. inclusion 9 continued: b) A highly effective method of contraception is defined as one
             that results in a low failure rate (ie, less than 1% per year) when used consistently
             and correctly. The acceptable methods of contraception are: Barrier Method (e.g. male
             condom with spermicide, copper T intrauterine device, or levonorgestrel-releasing
             intrauterine system - Mirena®) or Hormonal Methods (e.g. implants, hormone shot or
             injection, combined pill, minipill, or patch).Non-sterilized males who are sexually
             active with a female partner of childbearing potential must use a highly effective
             method of contraception from Days 1-180 post last dose. In addition, they must refrain
             from sperm donation for 180 days after the final dose of investigational product.

         12. The ability to interrupt NSAIDS 2 days before (5 days for long-acting NSAIDs), the day
             of, and 2 days following administration of Pemetrexed.

         13. The ability to take folic acid, Vitamin B12, and dexamethasone according to protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Primary central nervous system (CNS) malignancies or CNS metastases, including
             leptomeningeal metastases, are not allowed. Subjects with previously treated brain
             metastases will be allowed if the brain metastases have been stable for at least 3
             months following prior treatment (radiotherapy or surgery).

          2. Patients who received previous anti-folate-containing chemotherapy.

          3. Any other malignancy from which the patient has been disease-free for less than 3
             years, except for non-melanoma skin cancer, controlled localized prostate cancer, in
             situ carcinoma of any site.

          4. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          5. Presence of third space fluid which cannot be controlled by drainage. For patients who
             develop or have baseline clinically significant pleural or peritoneal effusions (on
             the basis of symptoms or clinical examination) before or during initiation of
             Pemetrexed therapy, consideration should be given to draining the effusion prior to
             dosing. However, if, in the investigator's opinion, the effusion represents
             progression of disease, the patient should be discontinued from study therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jianjun Gao, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jianjun Gao, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-2830</phone>
    <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Research Operations</last_name>
      <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Katy Regional Care Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77094</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Wang, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Sugarland Regional Care Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sugar Land</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77478</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Wang, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer of urethra</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer of ureters</keyword>
  <keyword>MTAP-deficient bladder cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>MTAP wild-type bladder cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic</keyword>
  <keyword>Pemetrexed</keyword>
  <keyword>LY231514</keyword>
  <keyword>Alimta</keyword>
  <keyword>MTA</keyword>
  <keyword>Multitargeted Antifolate</keyword>
  <keyword>NSC-698037</keyword>
  <keyword>Folic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Folinic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin B12</keyword>
  <keyword>Dexamethasone</keyword>
  <keyword>Decadron</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Transitional Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Folic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B 12</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxocobalamin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Folic Acid Antagonists</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B Complex</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

