<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02694393</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO15040062</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02694393</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Inhaled Sodium Nitrite as an Antimicrobial for Cystic Fibrosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Study of Inhaled Sodium Nitrite as an Antimicrobial for Pseudomonas Infection in Cystic Fibrosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Schmidhofer, Mark, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mast Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cystic Fibrosis Foundation Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will assess the safety of inhaled sodium nitrite in adults with Cystic Fibrosis
      and chronic Pseudomonas infections, and determine the ability of sodium nitrite to reduce the
      burden of Pseudomonas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pseudomonas aeruginosa infects the airways of 80% of adults with Cystic Fibrosis (CF). In
      these patients, P. aeruginosa forms extremely antibiotic resistant biofilm communities that
      accelerate progression of obstructive lung disease. Current treatment of airway infection
      focuses on monthly cycles of inhaled antibiotics. However up to 20% of adults are infected
      with multi drug resistant P. aeruginosa for which we have no effective inhaled treatments.
      These isolates are more common as patients age so with the increasing life expectancy of the
      CF population, MDR P. aeruginosa is likely to remain a clinical problem. Another 10% of
      patients are infected with other Gram-negative organisms such as Burkholderia cepacia and
      Achromobacter species, for which we have inadequate suppressive treatment. Following lung
      transplant, MDR airway infections remain a problem as the allografts are colonized by strains
      carried in the paranasal sinuses. Sodium nitrite may present a new antimicrobial approach to
      treating respiratory infection with Gram-negative organisms, because it is able to prevent
      biotic biofilm formation.

      Within the CF lung, P. aeruginosa grows as a biotic biofilm in association with airway
      epithelial cells and mucous plaques. This environment has an acidic pH and low oxygen tension
      with many bacteria subsisting through denitrification (both conditions where traditional
      antibiotics are less effective). Because biotic biofilms can be up to 500-fold more resistant
      than biofilms grown on abiotic surfaces, with support from our CF Research Development
      Program (RDP) Cores, we showed that nitrite prevents biofilm formation on the surface of
      primary CF airway epithelial cells. Moreover, nitrite dose-dependently potentiates the
      effects of colistin sulfate in liquid culture, and in biotic biofilms on airway epithelial
      cells. These data support the hypothesis that nebulized sodium nitrite will inhibit growth of
      Pseudomonas aeruginosa in CF airways, and identify a potential therapeutic benefit for
      nitrite alone and cooperatively with colistin as a novel therapy to inhibit P. aeruginosa in
      CF airways. Nebulized nitrite has been through extensive animal toxicology, and is well
      tolerated by subjects with pulmonary arterial hypertension where it is being studied as a
      pulmonary vasodilator.

      To determine the therapeutic potential of sodium nitrite for CF, we propose two specific
      aims:

      Aim 1: 1. Determine the safety of nebulized sodium nitrite administered in two doses to
      patients with CF and chronic P. aeruginosa infection.

      Aim 2: 2. Explore the effects of inhaled sodium nitrite on measures of lung function, exhaled
      airway nitric oxide, and bacterial burden as measured by quantitative sputum cultures for P.
      aeruginosa.

      To accomplish these aims, we propose a Phase I/II open-label study of sodium nitrite in CF.
      Key inclusion criteria include individuals over the age 18 with cystic fibrosis as documented
      by clinical features of CF, and genotyping or a positive sweat test. Study participants must
      additionally have had 2 positive respiratory cultures for Pseudomonas aeruginosa within the
      past 12 months. Exclusion criteria include advanced lung disease, inability to discontinue
      inhaled antibiotics for eight weeks, hospitalization or medication change within 4 weeks of
      dosing, baseline systemic hypotension (SBP&lt;90 mm hg), chronic kidney disease (Cr &gt;2.5),
      severe anemia (Hgb &lt;9 gm/dL in the last six months). The primary outcome is safety, defined
      as FEV1 measured before and after initial doses on days 0 and 7, and at week 4. Other safety
      data for the initial doses include pulse oximetry and transcutaneous methemoglobin levels.
      Secondary endpoints include quantitative sputum cultures, exhaled nitric oxide, sputum
      nitrite concentration, and patient symptoms as assessed by a CF specific respiratory
      questionnaire.

      Completion of this study will guide the development of sodium nitrite as a single agent for
      CF infections, and inform future studies examining the effects of sodium nitrite in
      combination with inhaled colistin for patients with drug resistant bacterial pathogens that
      are an increasing problem. In addition, the study will provide important safety and efficacy
      data that may inform future development of inhaled sodium nitrite as a therapy in young
      patients to augment airway host defense and prevent biofilm formation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary Function</measure>
    <time_frame>three times over 4 weeks (Day 0, Day 7, and Week 4)</time_frame>
    <description>change in forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) after inhalation will assess safety</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>exhaled Nitric Oxide</measure>
    <time_frame>three times over 4 weeks (Day 0, Day 7, and Week 4)</time_frame>
    <description>concentration of nitric oxide in exhaled breath</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>sputum nitrite concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>three times over 4 weeks (Day 0, Day 7 and Week 4)</time_frame>
    <description>concentration of nitrite in sputum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pseudomonas density in sputum</measure>
    <time_frame>two times over 4 weeks (Day 0 and Week 4)</time_frame>
    <description>density of Pseudomonas in sputum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CF questionnaire - Respiratory</measure>
    <time_frame>two times over 4 weeks (Day 0 and Week 4)</time_frame>
    <description>respiratory symptom questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sodium nitrite</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Inhalation of 46 or 80 mg of sodium nitrite twice daily for four weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sodium nitrite</intervention_name>
    <description>inhalation of 46 or 80 mg of sodium nitrite by electronic nebulization</description>
    <arm_group_label>sodium nitrite</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cystic Fibrosis and at least two sputum cultures demonstrating Pseudomonas in the last
             12 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  use of supplemental oxygen, FEV1 &lt; 40% predicted, inability to discontinue inhaled
             antibiotics for 8 weeks,

          -  hospitalization within 4 weeks prior to enrollment,

          -  change in maintenance CF therapies within 2 weeks of enrollment,

          -  severe anemia, significant chronic liver disease, severe pulmonary hypertension, prior
             organ transplantation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph Pilewski, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joseph M Pilewski, MD</last_name>
    <phone>412-692-5872</phone>
    <email>pilewskijm@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Hartigan, MPH, RN</last_name>
    <phone>412-692-7060</phone>
    <email>elizabeth.hartigan@chp.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elizabeth Hartigan, MPH, RN</last_name>
      <phone>412-692-7060</phone>
      <email>elizabeth.hartigan@chp.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <phone>412-692-7042</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph M Pilewski, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Comprehensive Lung Center - Falk Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph M Pilewski, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Major TA, Panmanee W, Mortensen JE, Gray LD, Hoglen N, Hassett DJ. Sodium nitrite-mediated killing of the major cystic fibrosis pathogens Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Staphylococcus aureus, and Burkholderia cepacia under anaerobic planktonic and biofilm conditions. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2010 Nov;54(11):4671-7. doi: 10.1128/AAC.00379-10. Epub 2010 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>20696868</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zemke AC, Shiva S, Burns JL, Moskowitz SM, Pilewski JM, Gladwin MT, Bomberger JM. Nitrite modulates bacterial antibiotic susceptibility and biofilm formation in association with airway epithelial cells. Free Radic Biol Med. 2014 Dec;77:307-16. doi: 10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2014.08.011. Epub 2014 Sep 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25229185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joseph Pilewski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine and Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Infective Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

