<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02690987</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15/LO/1041</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MR/M007022/1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02690987</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gut Hormones in Obesity, Nicotine and Alcohol Dependence</brief_title>
  <acronym>GHADD</acronym>
  <official_title>Do Appetitive Gut Hormones Reduce Addictive and Eating Behaviours in Obesity, and Nicotine and Alcohol Dependence?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The &quot;Gut Hormones in Addiction&quot; study is a proof-of-concept experimental medicine human study
      to answer the following questions:

        1. Does the administration of the hormone desacyl ghrelin reduce core behavioural
           components of addiction in dependent individuals who have recently stopped smoking
           tobacco or drinking alcohol, or overweight/obese subjects?

        2. Does the administration of the drug Exenatide reduce core behavioural components of
           addiction in dependent individuals who have recently stopped smoking tobacco or drinking
           alcohol, or overweight/obese subjects?

        3. Does the administration of desacyl ghrelin or Exenatide reduce reward responses to
           high-calorie foods and appetite in dependent individuals who have recently stopped
           smoking tobacco or drinking alcohol, or overweight/obese subjects?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obesity, smoking and alcohol dependence are major health burdens to society. Relapse after
      alcohol and smoking abstinence is common despite the use of combined behavioural support and
      current limited available medications. In obesity, nonsurgical interventions have also been
      disappointing in achieving longterm weight loss. Therefore, there is a pressing need to
      develop novel drug treatments for addiction derived from knowledge of brain mechanisms
      related to relapse and reward responses to food and drugs.

      There is evidence in animals that some gut hormones, produced in the stomach and intestine,
      influence the consumption of food and desire for food, but also alcohol, nicotine and other
      drugs of abuse. Examples of such gut hormones are glucagon-like peptide1 (GLP1) and ghrelin.

      The influence of these hormones is exerted through brain systems involved in the core
      behavioural components of addiction: reward sensitivity, stress, impulsivity and
      compulsivity. These components are often also seen in obesity and food-related disorders such
      as binge eating disorder. It is unknown whether these gut hormones directly influence the
      core behavioural components of addiction in humans, particularly during abstinence.

      The investigators will examine the acute effects of Exenatide (mimics GLP1) and desacyl
      ghrelin (counteracts active acyl ghrelin), which are infused through a vein, on brain reward
      systems, craving for food, cigarettes and alcohol, and addictive and eating behaviours.

      The investigators will recruit adults with nicotine or alcohol dependence who have recently
      stopped smoking or drinking, and overweight/obese adults. The investigators will use
      functional magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain scans and computer-based test over 3
      separate study days to study different aspects of eating and addictive behaviours.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional MRI measure of brain activation during cigarette, alcohol and food picture evaluation task</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>BOLD signal in brain reward systems to cigarette, alcohol and food pictures vs. object pictures</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional MRI measure of brain activation during anticipation of winning monetary reward (monetary incentive delay task)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>BOLD signal in striatum to anticipation of winning vs. not winning money</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional MRI measure of brain activation during negative emotional reactivity task</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>BOLD signal in amygdala during viewing of evocative vs. neutral pictures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional MRI measure of brain activity in salience resting state network</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Network integrity of BOLD signal in salience resting state network</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional MRI measure of brain activity in limbic resting state network</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Network integrity of BOLD signal in limbic resting state network</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional MRI measure of brain activity in default mode resting state network</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Network integrity of BOLD signal in default mode resting state network</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hunger visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Appetite measure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol Urge Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Alcohol craving measure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Questionnaire of Smoking Urges</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cigarette craving measure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Food craving visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Progressive ratio task breakpoint</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of motivation to obtain sweet palatable food</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of unsuccessful stop trials</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Motor response inhibition measure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Energy intake at test meal in kilocalories</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Energy intake of sugar at test meal as percentage of total</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Energy intake of fat at test meal as percentage of total</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Ratio of speed of approach to avoidance for food vs. object pictures</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Ratio of speed of approach to avoidance for alcohol vs. object pictures</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Ratio of speed of approach to avoidance for cigarette vs. object pictures</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Food picture appeal rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol picture appeal rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cigarette picture appeal rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma glucose concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum insulin concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum cortisol concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum growth hormone concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma GLP1 concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma peptide YY concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma exenatide concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma desacyl ghrelin concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma acyl ghrelin concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Nausea visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fullness visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sweet taste intensity visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fat taste intensity visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fat taste just right visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sweet taste just right visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sweet taste liking visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fat taste liking visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Fat taste pleasant visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sweet taste pleasant visual analogue scale rating</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Paired associates learning task number of trials required to locate patterns correctly</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Episodic memory measure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Paired associates learning task memory score</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Episodic memory measure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Paired associates learning task number of stages completed</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Episodic memory measure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cambridge gambling task risk taking measure</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Neuropsychological test</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cambridge gambling task quality of decision taking measure</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Neuropsychological test</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Smoking relapse rate at 6 months after completion of the study in ex-smokers</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Smoking relapse rate at 12 months after completion of the study in ex-smokers</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol relapse rate at 6 months after completion of the study in ex-drinkers</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol relapse rate at 12 months after completion of the study in ex-drinkers</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <condition>Alcoholism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Overweight/obese subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Overweight/obese volunteers with BMI 28.0-50.0 kg/m2, otherwise healthy. This group will receive interventions with saline as placebo, Exenatide and desacyl ghrelin infusions at separate visits in a within subject randomised crossover design.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ex-smokers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Abstinent tobacco dependent individuals who score at least moderately on tobacco dependence as measured retrospectively using the Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence (FTND), and who have been in stable tobacco abstinence for at least 6 weeks.
This group will receive interventions with saline as placebo, Exenatide and desacyl ghrelin infusions at separate visits in a within subject randomised crossover design.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ex-alcohol dependent subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Abstinent alcohol dependent individuals who score at least moderately alcohol dependent as measured retrospectively using the Severity of Alcohol Dependence Questionnaire (SADQ), and who have been abstinent for at least 6 weeks.
This group will receive interventions with saline as placebo, Exenatide and desacyl ghrelin infusions at separate visits in a within subject randomised crossover design.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exenatide</intervention_name>
    <description>Exenatide is a commercially available GLP-1 receptor agonist. It is a synthetic form of exendin-4, a protein extracted from the saliva of a Gila monster lizard, which exhibits 53% sequence identity to human GLP-1.
The planned intravenous Exenatide infusion dose is expected to be 0.06 pmol/kg/min aiming for maintenance plasma concentrations of ~130-190 pg/mL.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Overweight/obese subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ex-smokers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ex-alcohol dependent subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Byetta</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Desacyl ghrelin</intervention_name>
    <description>Ghrelin is a 28 amino acid stomach-derived peptide hormone, with the desacyl ghrelin (DAG) form inactive at the GHSR1a receptor. GMP-grade DAG is obtained from Clinalfa (Bachem AG, Bubendorf, Switzerland).
The planned intravenous DAG infusion dose is expected to be 4.0 mcg/kg/hour aiming for maintenance plasma concentrations of ~13-19 ng/mL.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Overweight/obese subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ex-smokers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ex-alcohol dependent subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Unacylated ghrelin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo visit will involve an intravenous infusion of normal saline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Overweight/obese subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ex-smokers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ex-alcohol dependent subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female volunteers between the ages of 18 and 60 years.

          2. Healthy as determined by a responsible physician, based on a medical evaluation
             including medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests, cardiac monitoring
             and a psychiatric evaluation. Any volunteer with a clinical abnormality or laboratory
             parameters outside the reference range for the population being studied may be
             included, only if the investigators concur that the finding is unlikely to jeopardize
             either volunteer safety or study integrity.

          3. The subject is capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance
             with the requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

          4. The subject is able to read, comprehend and record information written in English.

          5. For non-dependent groups:

             i) Overweight/obese volunteers with BMI 28.0-50.0 kg/m2.

          6. For addiction groups:

        Subjects meeting DSM-V criteria for previous nicotine or alcohol dependence, but who are in
        early stable abstinence (&gt;6 weeks). Minor lapses within this time period will be allowed
        but not relapses into dependence.

        ii) Abstinent alcohol dependent individuals who score at least moderately alcohol dependent
        as measured retrospectively using the Severity of Alcohol Dependence Questionnaire (SADQ),
        and who have been abstinent for &gt;6 weeks.

        iii) Abstinent tobacco dependent individuals who score at least moderately on tobacco
        dependence as measured retrospectively using the Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence
        (FTND), and who have been in stable tobacco abstinence for &gt;6 weeks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Potential volunteers will NOT be eligible for inclusion in this study if any of the
        following criteria apply:

          1. Previous history of recreational use or abuse of other substances of addiction will be
             permissible, but there should be no use of any illegal drugs (except cannabis) in the
             month prior to the Screening Visit or during the course of the study, except where
             specified for individual groups below.

          2. For individual groups:

             i) Overweight/obese group: history of or current alcohol abuse or dependence; nicotine
             use other than &quot;never smoked&quot;, i.e. &gt;100 cigarettes lifetime use; history of
             dependence, abuse or heavy recreational use of cocaine, cannabis, opiates or other
             substance of abuse; history of problem gambling. Any previous or current psychiatric
             diagnosis listed in DSM-V Axis I, which in the opinion of the clinical team will
             compromise conduct and interpretability of the study.

             ii) Abstinent tobacco dependent group: history of or current alcohol abuse or
             dependence; current dependence for cocaine, cannabis, opiates or other substance of
             abuse, or problem gambling (previous history will be allowed); taking varenicline,
             bupropion or other prescription medications for smoking cessation. Any previous or
             current psychiatric diagnosis listed in DSM-V Axis I, which in the opinion of the
             clinical team will compromise conduct and interpretability of the study.

             iii) Abstinent alcohol dependent group: current dependence for cocaine, cannabis,
             opiates or other substance of abuse, or problem gambling (previous history will be
             allowed); taking prescription medication for alcohol or smoking cessation or
             withdrawal; smoking is allowed past or present including dependence; current nicotine
             replacement therapy is allowed.

          3. Currently suffering from DSM-V depressive disorder or on anti-depressant medication,
             though a history of depression or anxiety will be allowed. A current or past history
             of enduring severe mental illness (e.g., schizophrenia, bipolar affective disorder)
             will not be allowed.

             For all groups:

          4. Cannabis use up to five times in the month prior to the Screening Visit will be
             allowed, but no use within one week of experimental assessments; no use of any other
             illegal drugs in the month prior to the Screening Visit or during the course of the
             study.

          5. Intoxication at any of the visits, as manifested by difficulty in walking, slurring of
             speech, difficulty concentrating or drowsiness (or by the subject volunteering this
             information directly to the research team).

          6. Positive drug/alcohol screens on testing at the screening visit, other than that
             explicable by other causes (e.g. recent use of opiate containing analgesic etc), at
             the discretion of the research team.

          7. Carbon monoxide levels of =/&gt;10ppm in the overweight/obese and abstinent smoker groups
             at screening visit.

          8. Use of current regular prescriptions (including smoking or alcohol cessation medicines
             such as Disulfiram, Acamprosate, Naltrexone, Bupropion; weight loss medication
             including Orlistat, Metformin, GLP-1 agonists, Bupropion, Naltrexone), or
             over-the-counter medications that in the opinion of the Investigators may affect
             subject safety or outcome measures.

          9. Pulse rate &lt;40 or &gt;100 beats per minute OR systolic blood pressure &gt;160 and &lt;100 and a
             diastolic blood pressure &gt;95 and &lt;50 in the semi-supine position.

         10. Claustrophobia or feels that they will be unable to lay still on their back in the MRI
             scanner for a period of ~80 minutes.

         11. Presence of a cardiac pacemaker or other electronic device or ferromagnetic metal
             foreign bodies as assessed by a standard pre-MRI questionnaire and radiographer.

         12. History or presence of a neurological diagnosis (not limited to but including, for
             example, stroke, epilepsy, space occupying lesions, multiple sclerosis, Parkinson's
             disease, vascular dementia, transient ischemic attack, that may influence the outcome
             or analysis of the scan results). A history of alcohol-related or alcohol-withdrawal
             seizures will be allowed for volunteers in the abstinent alcoholic group.

         13. Significant current or past medical or psychiatric history that, in the opinion of the
             investigators, contraindicates their participation.

         14. Clinically significant head injury (e.g. requiring hospitalisation or surgical
             intervention) that in the opinion of the investigators may affect subject safety or
             outcome measures.

         15. Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures outlined in the protocol.

         16. Any of the following liver function tests (LFT) abnormalities at screening: Alkaline
             Phosphatase, AST, ALT or gammaGT &gt; 4 x upper limit of normal (ULN), INR &gt; 1.5, Albumin
             &lt;25 g/L, raised bilirubin (other than just isolated i.e. without other liver function
             tests abnormalities).

         17. History of decompensated alcoholic liver disease - i.e. history of variceal bleeding,
             ascites, jaundice, encephalopathy.

         18. History of pancreatitis from any cause.

         19. History of type 1 or type 2 diabetes mellitus.

         20. ECG abnormality, which in the opinion of the study physician, is clinically
             significant and represents a safety risk.

         21. The volunteer has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first experimental visit in the
             current study: 90 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of
             the investigational product (whichever is longer).

         22. Exposure to more than 3 new investigational medicinal products within 12 months prior
             to the scan.

         23. History of sensitivity to any of the peptides, or components thereof, or a history of
             drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigators, contraindicates their
             participation.

         24. Diagnosis of endocrine disorder, including uncontrolled hypothyroidism (stable treated
             hypothyroidism with currently normal thyroid function tests is allowed), history of
             hyperthyroidism or Cushing's syndrome, which, in the opinion of the investigators, may
             affect subject safety or outcome measures.

         25. History of ischaemic heart disease, heart failure, cardiac arrhythmia or peripheral
             vascular or cerebrovascular disease.

         26. History or presence of significant respiratory, gastrointestinal, hepatic, oncological
             or renal disease or other condition that in the opinion of the Investigators may
             affect subject safety or outcome measures.

         27. Previous bariatric surgery for obesity including Roux-en-Y gastric bypass, gastric
             banding, sleeve gastrectomy.

         28. Current pregnancy or breast-feeding in female volunteers.

         29. Vegetarian, vegan, gluten or lactose-intolerant.

         30. Volunteers who have donated, or intend to donate, blood within three months before the
             screening visit or following study visit completion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tony Goldstone, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Nutt, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yong Yong Ling, MD</last_name>
    <phone>020 7594 8586</phone>
    <email>ghadd@imperial.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Liam Nestor, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>020 7594 6648</phone>
    <email>ghadd@imperial.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Neuropsychopharmacology, Division of Brain Sciences, Imperial College London, Hammersmith Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>W12 0NN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yong Yong Ling, MD</last_name>
      <phone>020 7594 8586</phone>
      <email>ghadd@imperial.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Liam Nestor, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>020 7594 6648</phone>
      <email>ghadd@imperial.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ghadd.co.uk</url>
    <description>GHADD study website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dickson SL, Egecioglu E, Landgren S, Skibicka KP, Engel JA, Jerlhag E. The role of the central ghrelin system in reward from food and chemical drugs. Mol Cell Endocrinol. 2011 Jun 20;340(1):80-7. doi: 10.1016/j.mce.2011.02.017. Epub 2011 Feb 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21354264</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Egecioglu E, Engel JA, Jerlhag E. The glucagon-like peptide 1 analogue Exendin-4 attenuates the nicotine-induced locomotor stimulation, accumbal dopamine release, conditioned place preference as well as the expression of locomotor sensitization in mice. PLoS One. 2013 Oct 18;8(10):e77284. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0077284. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>24204788</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldstone AP, Prechtl CG, Scholtz S, Miras AD, Chhina N, Durighel G, Deliran SS, Beckmann C, Ghatei MA, Ashby DR, Waldman AD, Gaylinn BD, Thorner MO, Frost GS, Bloom SR, Bell JD. Ghrelin mimics fasting to enhance human hedonic, orbitofrontal cortex, and hippocampal responses to food. Am J Clin Nutr. 2014 Jun;99(6):1319-30. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.113.075291. Epub 2014 Apr 23.</citation>
    <PMID>24760977</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heatherton TF, Kozlowski LT, Frecker RC, Fagerström KO. The Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence: a revision of the Fagerström Tolerance Questionnaire. Br J Addict. 1991 Sep;86(9):1119-27.</citation>
    <PMID>1932883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saunders JB, Aasland OG, Babor TF, de la Fuente JR, Grant M. Development of the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT): WHO Collaborative Project on Early Detection of Persons with Harmful Alcohol Consumption--II. Addiction. 1993 Jun;88(6):791-804.</citation>
    <PMID>8329970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shirazi RH, Dickson SL, Skibicka KP. Gut peptide GLP-1 and its analogue, Exendin-4, decrease alcohol intake and reward. PLoS One. 2013 Apr 16;8(4):e61965. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0061965. Print 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>23613987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tong J, Davis HW, Summer S, Benoit SC, Haque A, Bidlingmaier M, Tschöp MH, D'Alessio D. Acute administration of unacylated ghrelin has no effect on Basal or stimulated insulin secretion in healthy humans. Diabetes. 2014 Jul;63(7):2309-19. doi: 10.2337/db13-1598. Epub 2014 Feb 18.</citation>
    <PMID>24550190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Bloemendaal L, IJzerman RG, Ten Kulve JS, Barkhof F, Konrad RJ, Drent ML, Veltman DJ, Diamant M. GLP-1 receptor activation modulates appetite- and reward-related brain areas in humans. Diabetes. 2014 Dec;63(12):4186-96. doi: 10.2337/db14-0849. Epub 2014 Jul 28.</citation>
    <PMID>25071023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scholtz S, Miras AD, Chhina N, Prechtl CG, Sleeth ML, Daud NM, Ismail NA, Durighel G, Ahmed AR, Olbers T, Vincent RP, Alaghband-Zadeh J, Ghatei MA, Waldman AD, Frost GS, Bell JD, le Roux CW, Goldstone AP. Obese patients after gastric bypass surgery have lower brain-hedonic responses to food than after gastric banding. Gut. 2014 Jun;63(6):891-902. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2013-305008. Epub 2013 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23964100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 11, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 24, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>tobacco</keyword>
  <keyword>GLP1</keyword>
  <keyword>ghrelin</keyword>
  <keyword>alcohol</keyword>
  <keyword>appetite</keyword>
  <keyword>reward</keyword>
  <keyword>addiction</keyword>
  <keyword>hormone</keyword>
  <keyword>cigarette</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Exenatide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nicotine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

