<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02247856</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Valdecir_COPD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02247856</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>COPD AND ASSESSMENT OF RADIOLABELED AEROSOL DURING NONINVASIVE VENTILATION</brief_title>
  <official_title>IN VIVO ASSESSMENT OF RADIOLABELED AEROSOL DURING NONINVASIVE VENTILATION IN STABLE COPD: A RANDOMIZED CROSSOVER CLINICAL TRIAL</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Daniella Cunha Brandao</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universidade Federal de Pernambuco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Federal de Pernambuco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Beneficial effects from noninvasive ventilation (NIV) in acute COPD are
      well-established, but couple to nebulization is still challenging. Aim: To compare
      radioaerosol pulmonary deposition and radioaerosol mass balance in the different compartments
      (pulmonary and extrapulmonary) using vibrating mesh nebulizer (VMN) and jet nebulizer (JN)
      coupled to NIV.Methods: It was a crossover study involving 9 stable moderate to severe COPD
      randomly allocated for both phases of the study: Phase 1(NIV+MN,n=9) and phase 2(NIV+JN,n=9).
      Bronchodilators were delivered during NIV using a facemask (pressures of 12 cmH2O and 5 cmH2O
      - inspiratory and expiratory, respectively). Radioactivity counts were performed using a
      gamma camera and regions of interest(ROIs) were delimited. We determine aerosol mass balance
      from the lungs, upper airways, stomach, nebulizer, circuit, inspiratory and expiratory
      filters, and mask as a percentage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>radioaerosol deposition index into the lungs</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Immediately after inhalation, participants sat in a chair with the back positioned in front to the gamma camera (STARCAM 3200 GE, California, USA) to obtain radioactivity counts from the posterior thorax during a period of 300 seconds on a matrix of 256 X 256. After, participants were positioned sitting in front to the gama camera to obtain images from face. Then, the same procedure was performed to analysis deposition in the nebulizer, circuits, inspiratory filter, expiratory filter and face mask. Counts representing stomach were obtained from posterior thorax and corrections for decay of technetium were used to during extrapulmonary measurements</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>radioaerosol mass balance that reached pulmonary and extrapulmonary compartments.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 months</time_frame>
    <description>The analysis of deposition in pulmonary and extrapulmonary compartments was expressed as a percentage from the count in each compartment to the total radioaerosol mass generated by nebulizers. The inhaled radioaerosol was considered the sum of deposition into the upper airways, lungs and stomach.
Regions of interest were delimited based on a previous protocol and RDI was expressed as absolute values and was calculated according to the counts generated from each regions of interest.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">9</enrollment>
  <condition>COPD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Noninvasive ventilation+ jet nebulizer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Noninvasive ventilation+ Vibrating Mesh Nebulizer (VMN)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Noninvasive ventilation</intervention_name>
    <description>Bilevel positive pressure (BiPAP Synchrony, Respironics®, Murrysville, Pennsylvania, USA) was applied through face mask (Comfort Full 2, Respironics®, Murrysville, Pennsylvania, USA) attached with straps and pressure adjusted were 12 cmH2O of inspiratory pressure and 5 cmH2O of expiratory pressure after a period of adaptation before beginning the procedure to avoid ventilator-patient asynchrony</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Jet Nebulizer</intervention_name>
    <description>Both nebulizers were charged with 2.5 mg of salbutamol and 0.25 mg of ipratropium bromide and 3 mL of saline solution was added to complete 3 Ml. JN (Mist yMax, Air Life, Yorba Linda, USA) was positioned in the circuit using a &quot;T&quot; piece, particle size generation in a 5 µm range (according to the manufacturer information) and flow oxygen tritated at 8 L/min</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vibrating Mesh Nebulizer (VMN)</intervention_name>
    <description>Both nebulizers were charged with 2.5 mg of salbutamol and 0.25 mg of ipratropium bromide and 3 mL of saline solution was added to complete 3 Ml. VMN (Aeroneb Solo, Galway, Ireland) was positioned in the mask using an elbow (Elbow Kit, Respironics®, Murrysville, Pennsylvania, USA), particle size generation in a 1 µm and connected to electrical energy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion criteria were considered as follows: moderate to severe stable COPD (50% ≤ FEV1 &lt;
        80% from predicted values or 30% ≤ FEV1 &lt; 50% from predicted values)(4); none exacerbation
        in the last six months; age between 18 - 60 years; both sexes; no smoking history; able to
        understand verbal commands, and consent to participate in this protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Presence of dyspnea; cardiopulmonary diseases (chronic obstructive pulmonary disease,
        pneumonia, cardiac failure, myocardial infarction, pneumothorax); hyperthermia; hemodynamic
        instability (heart rate &gt; 150 bpm and systolic blood pressure &lt; 90 mmHg); arrhythmia
        absence; pregnancy; and contraindications for use of NIV (29).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Valdecir G Filho, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universidade Federal de Pernambuco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital das Clínicas de Pernambuco</name>
      <address>
        <city>Recife</city>
        <state>Pernambuco</state>
        <zip>50670-901</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.pubmed.com</url>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brandao DC, Lima VM, Filho VG, Silva TS, Campos TF, Dean E, de Andrade AD. Reversal of bronchial obstruction with bi-level positive airway pressure and nebulization in patients with acute asthma. J Asthma. 2009 May;46(4):356-61. doi: 10.1080/02770900902718829.</citation>
    <PMID>19484669</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Galindo-Filho VC, Brandão DC, Ferreira Rde C, Menezes MJ, Almeida-Filho P, Parreira VF, Silva TN, Rodrigues-Machado Mda G, Dean E, Dornelas de Andrade A. Noninvasive ventilation coupled with nebulization during asthma crises: a randomized controlled trial. Respir Care. 2013 Feb;58(2):241-9. doi: 10.4187/respcare.01371.</citation>
    <PMID>22781558</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Soroksky A, Stav D, Shpirer I. A pilot prospective, randomized, placebo-controlled trial of bilevel positive airway pressure in acute asthmatic attack. Chest. 2003 Apr;123(4):1018-25.</citation>
    <PMID>12684289</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 25, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 23, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 23, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 25, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Federal de Pernambuco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniella Cunha Brandao</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>nebulizers,</keyword>
  <keyword>noninvasive ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>COPD</keyword>
  <keyword>scintigraphy,</keyword>
  <keyword>aerosol</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

