<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02247843</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Lenti/βAS3-FB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02247843</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stem Cell Gene Therapy for Sickle Cell Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Research Study of Autologous Bone Marrow Transplantation for Sickle Cell Disease (SCD) Using Bone Marrow CD34+ Cells Modified With the Lenti/βAS3-FB Lentiviral Vector</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Donald B. Kohn, M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>California Institute for Regenerative Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase I clinical trial will assess the safety and initial evidence for efficacy of an
      autologous transplant of lentiviral vector modified bone marrow for adults with severe sickle
      cell disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sickle cell disease (SCD) affects ~90,000 people in the U.S. who suffer significant
      neurological, lung, and kidney damage, as well as severe chronic pain episodes that adversely
      impact on quality of life. While current medical therapies for SCD can reduce short-term
      morbidity, the inevitable progressive deterioration in organ function results in a
      significant decrease in quality of health with early mortality. Allogeneic hematopoietic stem
      cell transplant (HSCT) can benefit patients with SCD, by providing a source for life-long
      production of normal red blood cells. However, allogeneic HSCT is limited by the availability
      of well-matched donors and immunological complications, especially for the more than 80% of
      patients who lack an HLA-identical sibling donor. Autologous HSCT using a patient's own bone
      marrow stem cells that have been corrected by transfer of a modified human beta-globin gene
      that inhibits polymerization of the HbS (stem cell gene therapy) may provide a better
      therapeutic alternative, as it would avoid the immunologic complications and donor
      limitations of allogeneic HSCT.

      Up to 6 subjects with SCD lacking matched sibling donors and meeting eligibility criteria for
      disease severity and adequacy of organ function will be enrolled. Following informed consent,
      enrolled subjects will be screened to confirm full eligibility for participation. Eligible
      subjects will undergo bone marrow harvest (with a portion cryopreserved as &quot;back-up&quot;) with
      the remaining portion of marrow used to prepare the gene-modified Final Cellular Product:
      autologous bone marrow CD34+ cells transduced ex vivo by the Lenti/βAS3-FB lentiviral vector
      to express an anti-sickling (βAS3) gene. The subject will receive marrow cytoreduction with
      busulfan prior to infusion of the gene-modified cells. The follow-up period will include an
      initial 2 years of active end-point evaluations, where the subjects will be seen at intervals
      of no more than 3 months, followed by offer for enrollment into a long-term follow-up study
      during years 3-15.

      The primary objectives of the Phase I study are to assess safety and feasibility, with
      secondary objectives to assess efficacy (engraftment, βAS3-globin gene expression, and
      effects on RBC function and clinical hematologic and disease parameters).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical toxicity: Absence of grade 3-4 SAEs
Absence of replication-competent lentivirus (RCL):
Absence of monoclonal expansion or leukoproliferative disorder from vector insertional effects: To monitor for monoclonal expansion or leukoproliferative complications, LAM-PCR will be performed.
Event-free survival. Event-free survival will be determined for each subject over the 24 months after gene therapy. An event is defined as death or performance of an allogeneic HSCT.
Absence of humoral immune response to novel epitopes of βAS3-globin protein</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>βAS3-FB vector transduced BM CD34+ cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a single arm study without randomization. All subjects will receive the intervention of BetaAS3 lentiviral vector-modified autologous bone marrow stem cell transplant.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>βAS3-FB vector transduced BM CD34+ cells</intervention_name>
    <description>BM CD34+ from SCD patients are transduced ex-vivo with the Lenti/βAS3-FB lentiviral vector. The transduced cells are then infused into the patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>βAS3-FB vector transduced BM CD34+ cells</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lenti/βAS3-FB</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥18 by time of enrollment

          -  Diagnosis of SCD documented by phenotype (Hb electrophoresis) or genetic analysis
             (S/S, S/β-thalassemia-zero)

          -  Must not have medically eligible and available HLA-identical sibling donor or 10/10
             allele-matched unrelated donor

          -  Inadequate clinical response to hydroxyurea (HU), defined as any one of the following
             outcomes, while on HU for at least 3 months:

               -  2 or more acute sickle pain crises requiring hospitalization

               -  no rise in Hb &gt;1.5 gm/dl from pre-HU baseline or requires transfusion to maintain
                  Hb &gt; 6.0 gm/dL

               -  Has an episode of acute chest syndrome despite adequate supportive care measures.

               -  Or medical decision for other therapy (e.g. chronic transfusion program), or
                  subject refusal to take HU.

          -  The patient must be off HU for at least 90 days (+/- 5 days) before enrolling in the
             trial.

          -  Must have one or more of the following clinical complications demonstrating disease
             severity:

               -  Clinically-significant neurologic event: stroke or any central nervous system
                  deficit lasting &gt;24 hours.

               -  Abnormal head CT or brain MRI demonstrating previous stroke

               -  Administration of regular RBC transfusions for equal or longer than 1 year to
                  prevent vaso-occlusive crises or other sickle cell disease complications or to
                  maintain Hb &gt;6.

               -  Pulmonary arterial hypertension with tricuspid regurgitant jet velocity &gt; 2.5
                  m/sec.

               -  At least one episode of acute chest syndrome that required hospitalization,
                  intubation, and mechanical ventilation support within the 2 years prior to
                  enrollment

               -  At least 2 acute sickle pain crises requiring hospitalization within the 2 years
                  prior to enrollment

               -  Osteonecrosis requiring joint replacement

               -  History of acute dactylitis during childhood

               -  Recurrent priapism (2 or more episodes)

          -  Karnofsky performance score ≥60%

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has a medically eligible and available HLA-identical sibling donor or 10/10
             allele-matched unrelated donor (after at least 3 months search)

          -  Cardiac evaluation: left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 40% or LV shortening
             fraction &lt; 26% by cardiac echocardiogram or by MUGA scan,

          -  Poorly-controlled hypertension as determined by history of recorded BP in previous
             year with systolic &gt;135 or diastolic &gt;95 mmHg.

          -  Pulmonary evaluation: baseline oxygen saturation of &lt;85% or DLCO&lt; 40% (corrected for
             Hb).

          -  Renal evaluation: serum creatinine &gt;1.5x upper limit of normal for age or GFR&lt;60
             mL/min/1.73 m2

          -  Hepatic evaluation: serum conjugated (direct) bilirubin &gt; 2x upper limit of normal for
             age as per local laboratory or ALT and AST &gt; 5 times upper limit of normal as per
             local laboratory

          -  Hematologic evaluation: Leukopenia (WBC&lt; 3x103/uL) or neutropenia (ANC &lt; 1.0x103/uL)
             or thrombocytopenia (platelet count &lt; 100x103/uL)

          -  PT/INR or PTT &gt;1.5x upper limit of normal or other clinically significant bleeding
             disorder

          -  Serum ferritin &gt;1,000 ng/ml. (Potential subjects with serum ferritin &gt;1,000 will be
             referred back to their physician for more specific evaluation {e.g. MRI or liver
             biopsy}, and consideration of iron chelation therapy, if indicated. If successful and
             serum ferritin comes below 1,000 ng/ml, subjects may be reconsidered for enrollment).

          -  Seropositivity for HIV (Human Immunodeficiency Virus), HCV (Hepatitis C Virus), HTLV-1
             (Human T-Lymphotropic Virus), or active Hepatitis B Virus, or active infection by CMV
             or parvovirus B19, based on positive blood PCR

          -  Psychiatric evaluation: psychiatric disorder or neurologic disease that would impair
             the informed consent process or cooperation with the clinical trial performance

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Cancer or other malignant disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary Sehl, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary Schiller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gary Schiller, MD</last_name>
    <phone>310-206-5755</phone>
    <email>gschiller@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Donald Kohn, MD</last_name>
    <phone>310-794-1964</phone>
    <email>dkohn1@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary E. Sehl, MD</last_name>
      <phone>310-206-8477</phone>
      <phone_ext>21169</phone_ext>
      <email>msehl@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gary Schiller, MD</last_name>
      <phone>310-206-5755</phone>
      <email>gschiller@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gary Schiller, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald B Kohn, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Theodore B Moore, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah Larson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gay M Crooks, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Satiro DeOliveira, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lonnie Zeltzer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Gjertson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Romero Z, Urbinati F, Geiger S, Cooper AR, Wherley J, Kaufman ML, Hollis RP, de Assin RR, Senadheera S, Sahagian A, Jin X, Gellis A, Wang X, Gjertson D, Deoliveira S, Kempert P, Shupien S, Abdel-Azim H, Walters MC, Meiselman HJ, Wenby RB, Gruber T, Marder V, Coates TD, Kohn DB. β-globin gene transfer to human bone marrow for sickle cell disease. J Clin Invest. 2013 Jul 1. pii: 67930. doi: 10.1172/JCI67930. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>23863630</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 20, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 25, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Donald B. Kohn, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sickle Cell Disease (SCD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Lentiviral Vector</keyword>
  <keyword>Beta Globin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

