<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02941497</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UTK IRB-14-09366 B-XP</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-67001-21851</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>WBS number R011770127</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02941497</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Get Fruved: Obesity Prevention for Older Adolescents</brief_title>
  <official_title>&quot;Get Fruved:&quot; A Peer-led, Train-the-trainer Social Marketing Intervention to Increase Fruit and Vegetable Intake and Prevent Childhood Obesity.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Agriculture (USDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>West Virginia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>South Dakota State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Auburn University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Syracuse University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Maine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kansas State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This program is a non-diet approach to obesity prevention for older adolescents which does
      not promote following a special diet to manage weight; instead, it promotes healthy behavior
      associated with obesity prevention. This approach is especially important with youth and
      older adolescent populations so as to avoid impairment in emotional well-being associated
      with body dissatisfaction. Healthy weight status will be achieved by improving dietary intake
      patterns, increasing physical activity, and improving stress management.

      Fall of year 01 was devoted to the recruitment of student partners (intense intervention
      group) and the development of partnerships. In the spring of year 01, recruited students were
      enrolled in two newly developed undergraduate courses across four intervention state
      partners, became collegiate 4-H members, planned a social marketing campaign, and/or learned
      to be peer mentors or student researchers. In year 02, first year college students were
      recruited, peer mentors were matched with a group of first year students, and the developed
      social marketing campaign was pilot tested on four college campuses (diffuse intervention) by
      the collegiate 4-H teams. In year 02, a toolkit with 24 weeks of intervention activities was
      also refined. In year 03, the collegiate 4-H team (intense intervention group) will use the
      refined toolkit to test and implement the intervention on college campuses. In year 03, the
      assessment process for high school 4-H students (intense intervention group) will be pilot
      tested and college students will work with the high school students on adapting the toolkit
      for use in the implementation of the social marketing campaign in high school settings in
      year 04 (diffuse intervention). In year 04, the college tool kit will be disseminated to
      additional college campuses. In year 05, the program will be disseminated to additional high
      schools.

      The nine month interactive, social marketing environmental intervention will aid older
      adolescents in effectively managing weight through increasing healthfulness of diet,
      increased physical activity, and improved stress management behavior as compared to a control
      group. On all measures it is anticipated that participants in the intensive intervention
      group will have greater improvements than those in the diffuse intervention group and both
      intensive and diffuse intervention groups will have improvements over those in the control
      groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of the research is to develop a novel strategy to promote healthy behaviors
      associated with obesity prevention in older adolescent populations. A community based
      participatory research (CBPR) approach is used with partnerships among older adolescents,
      university researchers and faculty, and Extension partners. The objective is to test the
      effectiveness of a peer-led, train-the-trainer intervention. The intervention is an
      interactive, non-traditional social marketing, online media, and environmental change
      approach seeking to promote healthy behavior with communities of college and high school
      students. Specific health behaviors targeted include increasing intakes of fruits and
      vegetables, decreasing foods high in saturated fats and added sugars, managing stress, and
      increasing physical activity. This project uniquely 1) increases participant engagement
      through creative interactions, participant-created content, and incorporation of
      age-appropriate technology; 2) incorporates social environments and peer-led strategies; and
      3) simultaneously addresses changes in environments to support participant-driven behavior
      change efforts.

      This project is a Pretest-Posttest, Control Group Trial using a nested cohort design with
      three conditions (intense intervention, diffuse intervention, and control), four control
      universities and four intervention universities in years 01- 03, one high school as control
      and one as intervention at each of the four intervention university towns in years 03-04, and
      disseminated to four additional university and high school pairs in years 04-05.

      A CBPR, peer-led approach is used in that upper level college students mentor freshmen 4-H
      college students through the development of the intervention. The CBPR, peer-led approach
      continues when the now sophomore 4-H college students implement the intervention with
      incoming college freshmen in the following year. The train-the-trainer approach is utilized
      when the now junior level 4-H college students mentor 4-H high school students in the
      modification of the intervention for high schools. The approach continues when 4-H high
      school students implement the intervention with incoming freshmen in high schools.

      In the fall of year 01, 283 freshman students were recruited from general/survey nutrition
      courses at the four intervention universities to participate in a special undergraduate
      spring course (the intense intervention group). 94 freshman students were also recruited from
      general/survey nutrition courses at the four control universities. During the fall,
      researchers at the intervention schools worked with nutrition (graduate and undergraduate)
      students to identify and develop partnerships with student organizations for the development
      of a social marketing health promotion campaign. Researchers and student partners also worked
      with local high schools (including student organizations, school food service, Parent Teacher
      Associations, school wellness committees, and administration) and school boards to formalize
      research agreements and relationships.

      In the spring of year 01, as a part of the newly developed undergraduate course, the freshman
      students (the intense intervention group) from each intervention university joined their
      collegiate 4-H program. The courses were offered as independent studies or as a newly
      developed course through the respective University's PI. The course covered principals of
      social marketing for health behavior change. University researchers and Extension faculty
      collaborated and taught in-person classes with their respective collegiate 4-H students.
      Collegiate 4-H students were co-taught (by all four University's research and Extension
      faculty) and had the opportunity to interact with the other collegiate 4-H students from all
      four intervention universities through web-based technologies. Throughout the course, the
      collegiate 4-H students developed and planned a social marketing campaign. Following a
      peer-led approach, the 4-H students partnered with and were mentored by upper-level nutrition
      students and student organizations (student partners) in the development and planning of the
      campaign.

      In year 02, the now sophomore collegiate 4-H students in the intense intervention group
      (receiving hourly compensation) worked with student partners to implement the developed
      nine-month social marketing campaign. The campaign centered around five costumed characters
      (Spinach, Carrot, Banana, Grapes, and Tomato). Characters interacted with students on campus
      in freshmen residence halls, dining halls/cafeterias and highly trafficked public areas on
      campus. Photos and videos of interactions were put on the website (www.fruved.com), Facebook,
      twitter, YouTube, Snap Chat, and Instagram. Online educational modules (focused on healthy
      diet patterns, physical activity, and stress management) will also become available on the
      website. Student participants from the general freshman population were asked to set weekly
      healthy goals related to diet, physical activity, and stress management throughout the
      campaign and receive email and/or text messages with goal-specific written and video health
      promotion messages. Extension faculty and staff partnered with the collegiate 4-H student
      teams throughout the intervention process to educate and give advice on the content of health
      promotion messages. Throughout the campaign, collegiate 4-H students worked with researchers
      to assess the healthiness of their campus environments using a previously developed Healthy
      Campus Audit and advocated for changes to the physical and food environment.

      In year 02, a random sample of 1,153 freshmen (the diffuse intervention group), determined by
      screening to be at increased health risk were recruited from the eight universities (four
      intervention and four control). The collegiate 4-H students (the intense intervention group)
      and the same students from the control schools recruited in year 01 were reassessed.

      In year 03, the collegiate 4-H team (intense intervention group) will use the refined toolkit
      to test and implement the intervention on college campuses. The sustainability of observed
      changes at the individual and environmental college level will be assessed by conducting
      follow-up assessments with the students in the intervention (the diffuse intervention group)
      and control sites at colleges in year 03. The collegiate 4-H students (the intensive
      intervention group) leading the project at the high school level and the same students from
      the control schools recruited in year 01 will be reassessed at the beginning of fall year 03,
      and end of spring year 03. Also in year 03, the assessment process for high school 4-H
      students (intense intervention group) will be piloted tested and college students will work
      with the high school students on adapting the toolkit for use in the implementation of the
      social marketing campaign in high school settings (diffuse intervention).

      In year 04, two high schools in each of the four intervention University states will be
      recruited to participate in the research process and will be randomized to control and
      intervention. High schools in each state will be matched by size and community composition
      and geographically separated to prevent potential exposure to the campaign. Following the
      train-the-trainer model, teams of now junior collegiate 4-H students (the intense
      intervention group) will mentor teams of high school 4-H students (the intense intervention
      group) at each of the intervention sites in the development and implementation of the Fruved
      campaign in the high school environment. In the fall, collegiate students will work with the
      high school students (the intense intervention group) to modify the campaign to meet the age
      and cultural needs of a high school audience and plan the specific campaign components. The
      high school 4-H teams will partner with their school's food service, Parent Teacher
      Association (PTA), school Wellness committee, and school administration throughout the
      campaign development, implementation, and evaluation. The campaign will be conducted in the
      intervention high schools over the remaining nine-month school year.

      In year 04, a random sample of 331 freshman high school students (the diffuse intervention
      group) will be recruited from the intervention high schools and a random sample of 331
      freshman high school students (the control group) from the control high schools in each of
      the four intervention University town areas. Assessments will take place in early fall and
      late spring. The 4-H high school students (intensive intervention group) recruited to
      participate in the design and implementation phases of the project will also be assessed in
      early fall/late spring in year 04.

      Also in year 04, to continue to assess the sustainability of observed changes at the
      individual and environmental high school level, participants will be assessed by conducting
      follow-up assessments with the students in the intensive intervention group and control sites
      in high schools. The collegiate 4-H students (the intensive intervention group) that lead the
      project at the high school level and the same students from the control schools recruited in
      year 01 will be reassessed at the beginning of fall year 04 and end of spring year 04.

      In year 04-05, materials will be developed allowing the project to be further disseminated to
      other college and high school environments. Four additional college and high school pairs
      will be recruited to participate in the dissemination phase. In year 04 the college students
      will receive training materials, study manual, costumes, cameras, and a small implementation
      budget but will not receive support for incentives or student 4-H compensation. The campaign
      will be developed and implemented over one school year. A modified project assessment will be
      required to be completed by the collegiate student 4H groups. In year 05 the collegiate 4-H
      students will work with high school 4-H students to develop and implement the project in high
      schools. The high school 4-H student group will complete the modified project assessments.

      The nine month interactive, social marketing environmental intervention will aid older
      adolescents in effectively preventing obesity through increasing healthfulness of diet,
      increased physical activity, and improved stress management behavior as compared to a control
      group. On all measures it is anticipated that participants in the intensive intervention
      group will have greater improvements than those in the diffuse intervention group and both
      intensive and diffuse intervention groups will have improvements over those in the control
      groups. Students participating in the intervention will more effectively manage their weight
      than those in the non-intervention control condition; those participating in the intervention
      will improve intermediary outcomes related to diet, physical activity, and improved stress
      management to a greater extent than those in the control condition; and environments at
      intervention sites will show health behavior-supportive changes as compared to control sites.

      Since there are more than two time intervals in the design, General Linear Modeling will be
      used to analyze for changes in physical assessments, specifically a mixed-model Analysis of
      variance and covariance (ANCOVA) if the group-specific slopes are homogeneous. A wide range
      of analyses will be employed to analyze the influence of the intervention on secondary
      outcomes, including multivariate analyses of variance (MANOVA), ANOVAs, and logistic
      regression. Significant ANOVAs will be followed up with tests of simple and main effects as
      appropriate. The intervention group-by-occasions interaction test will assess the impact of
      the intervention in the treatment group relative to the control group across time on the
      secondary outcome measures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in body weight from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Following an overnight fast and voiding, weight is measured in light clothing without shoes and with pockets emptied. Weight is measured in duplicate (average used unless &gt; 0.1 kg difference requiring re-measurement until 2 values within range are achieved) to the nearest 0.1 kilograms using a calibrated electronic scale by trained assessors. Height without shoes is measured to the nearest 0.1 centimeter using a portable stadiometer. Height and weight are used to calculate BMI.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in amount of physical activity from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>The International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ) is used to measure self-reported physical activity. Results are calculated as Metabolic Equivalent (MET) minutes/week and can be used to estimate energy expenditure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dietary quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in dietary quality from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>The Automated Self-Administered Recall System (ASA24) is a web-based tool that allows participants to complete 24-hour recalls online. The Researcher Web site is used to incorporate the recall process in assessments and analyze data. Subjects complete the initial 24-hour recall at the time of the in-person physical assessment. They then receive email prompts asking them to completed two follow-up 24 hour recalls within the same week for a total of two recalls on nonconsecutive weekdays and one weekend day.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fruit and vegetable intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in fruit and vegetable intake from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Cups of fruits and vegetables/day is assessed using the NCI Fruit and Vegetable Screener (FVS). The FVS is a 19-item instrument that includes assessment of portion size.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in body composition from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>All circumference measurements are done using a Gulick tape measure. The waist is measured at the level of the iliac crests. The hips are measured at the maximum extension of the buttocks, and used to calculate body adiposity index (9) and hip to waist ratio. The neck is measured at the level of the Adams apple which can be palpated to identify location.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating competence</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in eating competence from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Eating competence is measured using ecSatter Inventory (ecSI). The ecSI consists of 16 items that measure eating attitudes, food acceptance, internal regulation, and contextual skills such as meal planning. Those who have higher eating competence scores are more likely to be satisfied with weight, have lower BMI, and consume more fruits and vegetables than those with lower eating competence scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in quality of life from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life is measured using two self-reported questionnaires the 12-Item General Health Questionnaire and the Brief Multidimensional Student Life Satisfaction Survey (BMSLSS). The 12-Item General Health Questionnaire is a measure of current mental health and psychological stress and has been used in different settings, cultures, and with young adults. The BMSLSS is a self-reported assessment of satisfaction with family, friends, school, self and environment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in stress from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Perceived stress is measured Cohen's Perceived Stress Scale (PSS). The PSS is a 14 item instrument designed to measure the degree to which situations in one's life are appraised as stressful.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavior changeability</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in perceptions and willingness to change from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>The Behavioral Environmental Changeability Survey (BECS) was developed and is used to assess perceptions of the importance and willingness to change weight related behavior. The BECS consists of eight scales (Nutrition Changeability; Nutrition Behavior; Environmental Changeability; Program Importance and Changeability; Exercise Behavior; Sleep Behavior and Importance; Weight Loss; and Alcohol Intake).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in sleep from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Quality and quantity of sleep are assessed using the Pittsburg Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). The survey has 19 self-reported items related to sleep over the past month. The items generate seven component scores (sleep quality, sleep latency, duration, efficiency, disturbances, use of sleeping medication and daytime dysfunction) which are summed for a global PSQI score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Campus healthy food access</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in campus food choice from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in overall consumption of all foods on campus are evaluated by reviewing the ordering records (with control for total student population) and sales data for all vending and dining services.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Environmental change</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in the campus environment from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in the environment are assessed using the Healthy Campus Audit and the CEPS. The HCA assesses physical activity, food, and policy aspects of the environment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recreational facility usage</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in recreational facility usage from baseline to six months and one year follow up</time_frame>
    <description>The use of the recreational facilities are assessed through reviewing entrance records (with control for total student population).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5800</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intensive intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intensive intervention group participates in development and implementation of the social marketing and health promotion campaign and peer-led campus activities and is assessed for their health-related behaviors. This was Wave 1 in colleges in Yr 01-02 and is being repeated as Wave 2 in colleges in Yr 03. This will also be repeated in high schools in Yr 04.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diffuse intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The diffuse intervention group receives the social marketing and health promotion campaign and participates in the peer-led campus activities and is assessed for their health related behaviors, but is not involved in the design and delivery of the intervention materials and activities. This was Wave 1 in colleges in Yr 01-02 and is being repeated as Wave 2 in colleges in Yr 03. This will also be repeated in high schools in Yr 04.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Social marketing and health promotion campaign</intervention_name>
    <description>Students in the intensive intervention group developed a nine-month social marketing health campaign. The campaign included five costumed characters who interacted with students on campus in residence halls, dining halls, and other highly-trafficked public areas on campus. Photos and videos of interactions were put on social media. Student participants from the general population (the diffuse intervention group) were asked to set weekly healthy goals related to diet, physical activity, and stress management throughout the campaign and received email and text messages with goal-specific written and video health-promotion messages. Faculty partnered with the students throughout the intervention process to educate and give advice on the content of health promotion messages.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intensive intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Diffuse intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Get Fruved</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Students in the intensive intervention group must be registered for a general/survey
             nutrition or wellness course

          -  Students in the diffuse intervention group randomly selected from those who screen in
             because they are at increased health risk (increased BMI and waist circumference, low
             intakes of fruits and vegetables, high levels of stress, and low levels of physical
             activity)

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  There are no exclusionary criteria for students in the intensive intervention group

          -  Students who are not at-risk for health issues are excluded from the diffuse
             intervention group
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah Colby, PhD, RD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Tennessee</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sarah Colby, PhD, RD</last_name>
    <phone>865-974-6248</phone>
    <email>scolby1@utk.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Anne Mathews, PhD, RDN</last_name>
    <phone>352-294-3719</phone>
    <email>anne.mathews@ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anne Mathews, PhD, RDN</last_name>
      <phone>352-294-3719</phone>
      <email>anne.mathews@ufl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anne Mathews, PhD, RDN</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kansas State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manhattan</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66506</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tandalayo Kidd, PhD, RD</last_name>
      <phone>785-532-0154</phone>
      <email>martan@k-state.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tandalayo Kidd, PhD, RD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orono</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>04469</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Adrienne White, PhD, RD</last_name>
      <phone>207-581-3134</phone>
      <email>awhite@maine.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adrienne White, PhD, RD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Syracuse University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Syracuse</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>13244</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tanya Horacek, PhD, RD</last_name>
      <phone>315-443-9323</phone>
      <email>thoracek@syr.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tanya Horacek, PhD, RD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Dakota State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brookings</city>
        <state>South Dakota</state>
        <zip>57007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kendra Kattelmann, PhD, RDN</last_name>
      <phone>605-688-4045</phone>
      <email>Kendra.kattelmann@sdstate.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kendra Kattelmann, PhD, RDN</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Tennessee</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37996</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Colby, PhD, RD</last_name>
      <phone>865-974-6248</phone>
      <email>scolby1@utk.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kerri Martin, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>865-312-4725</phone>
      <email>kmarti50@utk.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah Colby, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Virginia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morgantown</city>
        <state>West Virginia</state>
        <zip>26506</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa Olfert, DrPH, RDN</last_name>
      <phone>304-293-1918</phone>
      <email>Melissa.Olfert@mail.wvu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Melissa Olfert, DrPH, RDN</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://fruved.com/</url>
    <description>Click here for more information about &quot;Get Fruved&quot;: A Peer-Led, Train-the-Trainer Social Marketing Intervention to Increase Fruit and Vegetable Intake and Prevent Childhood Obesity A USDA grant-funded project</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Byrd-Bredbenner C, Johnson M, Quick VM, Walsh J, Greene GW, Hoerr S, Colby SM, Kattelmann KK, Phillips BW, Kidd T, Horacek TM. Sweet and salty. An assessment of the snacks and beverages sold in vending machines on US post-secondary institution campuses. Appetite. 2012 Jun;58(3):1143-51. doi: 10.1016/j.appet.2012.02.055. Epub 2012 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22414787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Do M, Kattelmann K, Boeckner L, Greene G, White A, Hoerr S, Horacek T, Lohse B, Phillips B, Nitzke S. Low-income young adults report increased variety in fruit and vegetable intake after a stage-tailored intervention. Nutr Res. 2008 Aug;28(8):517-22. doi: 10.1016/j.nutres.2008.05.013.</citation>
    <PMID>19083454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gordon R, McDermott L, Stead M, Angus K. The effectiveness of social marketing interventions for health improvement: what's the evidence? Public Health. 2006 Dec;120(12):1133-9. Epub 2006 Nov 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17095026</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gracia-Marco L, Vicente-Rodríguez G, Borys JM, Le Bodo Y, Pettigrew S, Moreno LA. Contribution of social marketing strategies to community-based obesity prevention programmes in children. Int J Obes (Lond). 2011 Apr;35(4):472-9. doi: 10.1038/ijo.2010.221. Epub 2010 Oct 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20975724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greene GW, Schembre SM, White AA, Hoerr SL, Lohse B, Shoff S, Horacek T, Riebe D, Patterson J, Phillips BW, Kattelmann KK, Blissmer B. Identifying clusters of college students at elevated health risk based on eating and exercise behaviors and psychosocial determinants of body weight. J Am Diet Assoc. 2011 Mar;111(3):394-400. doi: 10.1016/j.jada.2010.11.011.</citation>
    <PMID>21338738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horacek TM, Erdman MB, Byrd-Bredbenner C, Carey G, Colby SM, Greene GW, Guo W, Kattelmann KK, Olfert M, Walsh J, White AB. Assessment of the dining environment on and near the campuses of fifteen post-secondary institutions. Public Health Nutr. 2013 Jul;16(7):1186-96. doi: 10.1017/S1368980012004454. Epub 2012 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>23174458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horacek TM, White AA, Greene GW, Reznar MM, Quick VM, Morrell JS, Colby SM, Kattelmann KK, Herrick MS, Shelnutt KP, Mathews A, Phillips BW, Byrd-Bredbenner C. Sneakers and spokes: an assessment of the walkability and bikeability of U.S. postsecondary institutions. J Environ Health. 2012 Mar;74(7):8-15; quiz 42.</citation>
    <PMID>22428317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Toole TP, Aaron KF, Chin MH, Horowitz C, Tyson F. Community-based participatory research: opportunities, challenges, and the need for a common language. J Gen Intern Med. 2003 Jul;18(7):592-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12848844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schultz JT, Moodie M, Mavoa H, Utter J, Snowdon W, McCabe MP, Millar L, Kremer P, Swinburn BA. Experiences and challenges in implementing complex community-based research project: the Pacific Obesity Prevention in Communities project. Obes Rev. 2011 Nov;12 Suppl 2:12-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1467-789X.2011.00911.x.</citation>
    <PMID>22008555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Szymona K, Quick V, Olfert M, et al. The University Environment: A Comprehensive Assessment of Health-Related Advertisements. Health Ed. 2012;112(6):497-512.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 20, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 21, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 20, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 20, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 21, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sarah Colby</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stress, Psychological</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Fruit</keyword>
  <keyword>Vegetables</keyword>
  <keyword>Social Marketing</keyword>
  <keyword>Peer Influence</keyword>
  <keyword>Community-Based Participatory Research</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan at this time.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

