<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02947581</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>61449</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02947581</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sub Arachnoid Neurocysticercosis Treatment Outcome (SANTO)</brief_title>
  <acronym>SANTO</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Trial of Combined Albendazole Plus Praziquantel for Subarachnoid Cysticercosis of the Sylvian Fissure or the Basal Cisterns</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Taenia solium neurocysticercosis (NCC) is a parasitic infection causing much neurological
      disease in most of the world. When parasites locate in the cavities around the brain
      (subarachnoid NCC, SANCC), it becomes an aggressive, progressive and frequently lethal
      presentation. Current treatment regimens for SANCC have quite limited efficacy. The
      investigators propose to compare the current standard of care (a single antiparasitic drug,
      albendazole) with a combined regimen using two antiparasitic drugs simultaneously by adding
      praziquantel. The trial will enrol 164 patients in four centers, two in Peru, one in Ecuador,
      and one in Brasil.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled study in patients with subarachnoid
      cysticercosis of the basal cisterns or the Sylvian fissure, comparing in two parallel arms
      the efficacy of the standard of care anti-parasitic regime (30 days of ABZ at 15 mg/k/d, up
      to 1200 mg/k/d) with a combined regime using similar doses of ABZ and adding PZQ at 50 mg/k/d
      for the initial 15 days of anti-parasitic treatment. The study and interim analysis plan are
      designed to allow direct, concrete efficacy comparison in this deadly type of NCC while
      minimizing the risks of disease progression in the standard of care arm.

      In short, this is a parallel group study with a dichotomous primary outcome variable. The
      main analysis will compare the proportions of patients obtaining the primary outcome at 6
      months, using a Chi-square test in a bivariate analysis. A similar analysis will be used for
      the proportions of patients with a good clinical outcome, and the proportions of patients in
      whom lesion resolution sustains when assessed at month 12. A Student T test analysis will be
      used to compare for reduction in parasite volume and non-parametric Mann-Whitney test will be
      alternatively applied for non-normally distributed data. A non-parametric Spearman's Rho test
      will be used to assess the correlation between the proportions of cyst mass reduction with
      the decrease in antigen levels in each study group. A Chi-square test in a bivariate analysis
      will evaluate the association between negative antigen levels at 6 months versus the complete
      disappearance of cyst mass.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiological efficacy at three months (3-month improvement).</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 90 +/- 15 days</time_frame>
    <description>Thirty percent or greater decrease in the combined volume of all parasitic masses, evaluated by contrast-enhanced MRI 3 months after therapy onset, and recorded both as a dichotomous outcome and as a continuous quantification.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiological efficacy at six months (marked improvement or &quot;radiological cure&quot;) (evaluated only in patients with improvement at month 3).</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 180 +/- 15 days</time_frame>
    <description>Total disappearance or greater than 50% decrease in the combined volume of subarachnoid parasites, evaluated by contrast-enhanced MRI 6 months after therapy onset, and recorded both as a dichotomous outcome and as a continuous quantification. three.months after treatment onset (comparative between treatment arms).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect persistence at 12 months (no relapse) (evaluated only in patients with marked improvement at month 6) Effect persistence at 12 months (no relapse) (evaluated only in patients with marked improvement at month 6)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 365 +/- 15 days</time_frame>
    <description>No reappearance or re-growth of the parasitic lesions on contrast enhanced MRI at 12 months after therapy onset, recorded as a dichotomous outcome. hypertension, or progressive neurologic deficits (in cognitive functions, motor function, gait, or other defined neurological signs) in a patient off steroid therapy, as assessed by a study neurologist 12 months post treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically asymptomatic patient</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>No evidence of uncontrolled seizures, chronic severe headaches, intracranial hypertension, or progressive neurologic deficits (in cognitive functions, motor function, gait, or other defined neurological signs) in a patient off steroid therapy, as assessed by a study neurologist at 3, 6, and 12 months post treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Decrease in serum levels</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>will be measured at 3 months, and expressed as a proportion of the baseline level. This variable will be compared between arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">164</enrollment>
  <condition>Neurocysticercosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interventions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Albendazole and praziquantel. Albendazole: 15 mg/k/d up to 800 mg/d (days 1 to 20), followed by 15 mg/k/d up to 1200 mg/d (day 21 to 30) and prazicuantel (50 mg/k/d days 1 to 15).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison regime</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Albendazole and praziquantel placebo. Albendazole: 15 mg/k/d (days 1 to 30) and prazicuantel placebo in similar doses 50 mg/k/d (days 1 to 15).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Albendazole and praziquantel</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention - PZQ (50 mg/k/d, up to 3600 mg/d, for 15 days), as an add-on to ABZ treatment (15 mg/k/d, up to 800 mg/d for days 1-20, up to 1200 mg/d for days 21-30). In order to maintain the double blind nature of the trial, ABZ placebo will be administered to individuals over 53 kg of weight until completing the equivalent doses in the comparison group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventions</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ABZ+PZQ</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Albendazole and praziquantel placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>PZQ placebo in similar doses, given during the initial 15 days of ABZ treatment at standard doses (15 mg/k/d up to 1200 mg/d for 30 days)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Comparison regime</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ABZ+PZQ PCB</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  - Male or female adult individuals (18 to 65 y.o.) with a diagnosis of basal
             subarachnoid cysticercosis (including locations in the Sylvian fissure or lower
             interhemispheric spaces) by neuroimaging and confirmed by serology.

          -  Baseline laboratory results along acceptable ranges (specifically defined in the study
             protocol).

          -  Willingness to accomplish the two-week minimum hospitalization required.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous therapy with ABZ or PZQ in the preceding 3 years (except for patients who
             received single-dose ABZ for intestinal parasites, or patients who received
             antiparasitic treatment between one and three years before enrollment but demonstrated
             lesion persistence or progression during the past 12 months).

          -  A type of NCC which can expose the patient to increased risk during the study,
             specifically: a) intraventricular cysts; b) cysts in brainstem; c) concomitant
             intraparenchymal lesions greater than 3 cm of diameter in addition to their SANCC
             lesions; d) more than 20 intraparenchymal cysts in addition to their SANCC lesions; or
             d) untreated ocular cysticercosis. Patients with a lateral ventricle cyst, less than 2
             cm in diameter, without hydrocephalus or intracranial hypertension, can be included.
             The presence of concomitant intraparenchymal cysts of less than 3 cm in diameter will
             not exclude the patient unless there are more than 20 of them.

          -  Active pulmonary tuberculosis evidenced by positive chest X-ray and positive sputum
             smears, or symptoms compatible with tuberculosis (fever+sweats or fever+cough) not
             otherwise explained.

          -  Individuals with positive markers for active hepatitis.

          -  Systemic disease that may affect therapy or short-term prognosis, including but not
             limited to chronic renal failure, hepatic insufficiency, cardiac failure, and
             steroid-dependent immune diseases.

          -  Patients in unstable condition or with symptomatic intracranial hypertension (ICH).
             Definition of symptomatic ICH for this study is the presence of headaches, nausea, and
             vomiting, with papilledema at fundoscopic examination. Patients in this category can
             be considered for entrance into the study only after resolution of ICH by
             ventricular-peritoneal shunting or neuroendoscopic procedures involving CSF flow
             derivation. These procedures would be done as part of their standard medical care and
             are not part of the trial intervention.

          -  Pregnancy during anti-parasitic treatment. If a patient becomes pregnant after
             treatment, she will continue in the study but will have radiological exams delayed
             until after delivery.

          -  History of hypersensitivity to ABZ or PZQ

          -  Chronic or drug abuse as defined in the study protocol.

          -  Unwilling or unable to undergo MRI exams (like patients with ferromagnetic implants)

          -  Inability or unwillingness of subject or legal representative to give written informed
             consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hector H. Garcia Lescano, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hector H. Garcia Lescano, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>(511) 328-7360</phone>
    <email>hgarcia@jhsph.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cysticercosis Unit, Instituto Nacional de Ciencias Neurologicas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lima</city>
        <zip>Lima 1</zip>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Isidro Gonzales, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+511 3288589</phone>
      <email>isidrogonzalesq@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Peru</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 24, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>subarachnoid neurocysticercosis</keyword>
  <keyword>albendazole</keyword>
  <keyword>praziquantel</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neurocysticercosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cysticercosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Taeniasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Albendazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Praziquantel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Anonymized patient data will be shared upon request and review by the project leaders.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

