<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02947516</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20162017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02947516</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of EUS-Guided Liver Biopsy With Percutaneous Liver Biopsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Pain Scores Between Endoscopic Ultrasound (EUS)-Guided Liver Biopsy and Percutaneous Liver Biopsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There are several ways to perform liver biopsies, including the percutaneous route
      (historical gold standard) and via endoscopic ultrasound (EUS) guidance. The primary aim of
      this study is to prospectively compare patients undergoing EUS-guided liver biopsies to
      patients undergoing percutaneous biopsy. The investigators hypothesize that (1) patients who
      are randomized to undergo EUS-guided liver biopsy will rate themselves as having less pain in
      the 48 hours following the procedure, and (2) will have comparable histologic yield to a 2:1
      matched cohort of patients undergoing percutaneous liver biopsies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Currently, liver biopsy is the gold standard for determining the index of liver fibrosis in a
      patient with chronic liver disease, and whether the patient has progressed to cirrhosis.
      These biopsies are predominantly performed percutaneously. However, there are several
      complications related to liver biopsy, the most common of which are pain and bleeding.

      There has been significant movement over the past several years to assess the utility of
      alternative techniques and approaches for the evaluation of liver disease. Endoscopic
      ultrasound (EUS) is a well-established technique for diagnostic and therapeutic evaluation of
      gastrointestinal and pancreaticobiliary disorders. EUS-guided liver biopsy (EUS-LB) has shown
      to be technically simple, safe, and provides adequate diagnostic yield for evaluation of
      liver disease in both children and adults. There are several advantages to EUS-LB. First, it
      would theoretically be less painful than the percutaneous approach, as it does not require
      skin puncture and also offers the comfort of sedation and analgesia. It also eliminates the
      need for breath hold. Furthermore, it is an image-guided approach which allows visualization
      and avoidance of blood vessels even 1 mm in size. Additionally, it provides an access area to
      a much wider segment of liver parenchyma as the entire left lobe, and the majority of the
      right lobe can be evaluated for possible needle puncture sites from the stomach and duodenal
      bulb, respectively. In addition to obtaining tissue, EUS-LB also offers the benefit of
      evaluating the biliary tree, gallbladder, pancreas, lymph nodes, and vascular anatomy for a
      more comprehensive evaluation in the same setting. Finally, in patients ultimately found to
      have biopsy-proven cirrhosis, it simultaneously provides the necessary variceal screening
      which would otherwise require an additional procedure.

      The aim of this study is to prospectively perform EUS-guided liver biopsies in patients who
      are otherwise candidates for percutaneous biopsy. We hypothesize that (1) patients who are
      randomized to undergo EUS-guided liver biopsy will rate themselves as having less pain in the
      48 hours following the procedure and (2) will have comparable histologic yield to a 2:1
      matched cohort of patients undergoing percutaneous transjugular liver biopsies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Pain Scores on the Universal Pain Assessment Tool (UPAT)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Medication Requirements</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Use of any analgesics/narcotics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Histologic Yield</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Number of portal triads on histology</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Percutaneous liver biopsy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be referred for liver biopsy by their hepatologist/gastroenterologist. The intervention is that these participants will undergo a percutaneous liver biopsy per standard protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EUS-guided liver biopsy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be referred for liver biopsy by their hepatologist/gastroenterologist. The intervention is that these participants will undergo an endoscopic ultrasound procedure per standard protocol. The liver will be identified, and Color Doppler imaging prior to needle puncture will confirm lack of significant vascular structures within the needle path. Liver biopsies using up to 1-2 passes from the left hepatic lobe using a transgastric approach and up to 1-2 passes from the right hepatic lobe using a transduodenal bulb approach will be performed. The participant will be observed in the recovery unit for up to 60 minutes after the EUS-LB, and discharged if no pain or signs of complication.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endoscopic ultrasound-guided liver biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will undergo endoscopic ultrasound per standard technique, with liver biopsy performed at that time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EUS-guided liver biopsy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Percutaneous liver biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will undergo percutaneous liver biopsy per standard protocol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Percutaneous liver biopsy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 years and older

          -  Eligibility for receiving conscious sedation or monitored anesthesia care

          -  Abnormal liver function tests with comprehensive previous evaluation (including
             serologic testing and cross-sectional imaging) leading to an appropriate decision to
             proceed with liver biopsy and/or portal pressure measurements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Suspected or known malignant liver disease

          -  Severe thrombocytopenia (platelets &lt;50,000/microL)

          -  Severe coagulopathy (international normalized ratio [INR] &gt; 1.7 or other known
             coagulopathy)

          -  Use of antiplatelet agents within 7 days of the procedure

          -  Inability to provide informed consent

          -  Pregnancy or suspected pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marvin Ryou, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marvin Ryou, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-732-6389</phone>
    <email>mryou@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Allison R Schulman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-732-6389</phone>
    <email>arschulman@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bedossa P, Dargère D, Paradis V. Sampling variability of liver fibrosis in chronic hepatitis C. Hepatology. 2003 Dec;38(6):1449-57.</citation>
    <PMID>14647056</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Eisenberg E, Konopniki M, Veitsman E, Kramskay R, Gaitini D, Baruch Y. Prevalence and characteristics of pain induced by percutaneous liver biopsy. Anesth Analg. 2003 May;96(5):1392-6, table of contents.</citation>
    <PMID>12707140</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Caldwell SH. Controlling pain in liver biopsy, or &quot;we will probably need to repeat the biopsy in a year or two to assess the response&quot;. Am J Gastroenterol. 2001 May;96(5):1327-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11374664</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Piccinino F, Sagnelli E, Pasquale G, Giusti G. Complications following percutaneous liver biopsy. A multicentre retrospective study on 68,276 biopsies. J Hepatol. 1986;2(2):165-73.</citation>
    <PMID>3958472</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Huang JF, Hsieh MY, Dai CY, Hou NJ, Lee LP, Lin ZY, Chen SC, Wang LY, Hsieh MY, Chang WY, Yu ML, Chuang WL. The incidence and risks of liver biopsy in non-cirrhotic patients: An evaluation of 3806 biopsies. Gut. 2007 May;56(5):736-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17440193</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Perrault J, McGill DB, Ott BJ, Taylor WF. Liver biopsy: complications in 1000 inpatients and outpatients. Gastroenterology. 1978 Jan;74(1):103-6.</citation>
    <PMID>618417</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Firpi RJ, Soldevila-Pico C, Abdelmalek MF, Morelli G, Judah J, Nelson DR. Short recovery time after percutaneous liver biopsy: should we change our current practices? Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2005 Sep;3(9):926-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16234032</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stone MA, Mayberry JF. An audit of ultrasound guided liver biopsies: a need for evidence-based practice. Hepatogastroenterology. 1996 Mar-Apr;43(8):432-4.</citation>
    <PMID>8714240</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hollerbach S, Willert J, Topalidis T, Reiser M, Schmiegel W. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration biopsy of liver lesions: histological and cytological assessment. Endoscopy. 2003 Sep;35(9):743-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12929021</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fuccio L, Larghi A. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine needle aspiration: How to obtain a core biopsy? Endosc Ultrasound. 2014 Apr;3(2):71-81. doi: 10.4103/2303-9027.123011. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24955336</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stavropoulos SN, Im GY, Jlayer Z, Harris MD, Pitea TC, Turi GK, Malet PF, Friedel DM, Grendell JH. High yield of same-session EUS-guided liver biopsy by 19-gauge FNA needle in patients undergoing EUS to exclude biliary obstruction. Gastrointest Endosc. 2012 Feb;75(2):310-8. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2011.09.043.</citation>
    <PMID>22248599</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Iglesias-Garcia J, Poley JW, Larghi A, Giovannini M, Petrone MC, Abdulkader I, Monges G, Costamagna G, Arcidiacono P, Biermann K, Rindi G, Bories E, Dogloni C, Bruno M, Dominguez-Muñoz JE. Feasibility and yield of a new EUS histology needle: results from a multicenter, pooled, cohort study. Gastrointest Endosc. 2011 Jun;73(6):1189-96. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2011.01.053. Epub 2011 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21420083</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Johal AS, Khara HS, Maksimak MG, Diehl DL. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided liver biopsy in pediatric patients. Endosc Ultrasound. 2014 Jul;3(3):191-4. doi: 10.4103/2303-9027.138794.</citation>
    <PMID>25184126</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 26, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 26, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 26, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marvin Ryou</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Endoscopic Ultrasound-Guided Fine Needle Aspiration</keyword>
  <keyword>liver</keyword>
  <keyword>biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Extracts</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

