<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02948647</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HS-11-00446</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02948647</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Healthy Eating Through Reduction Of Excess Sugar</brief_title>
  <acronym>HEROES</acronym>
  <official_title>Diets Based on PNPLA3 Genotype for Reducing Liver Fat in Hispanics With Pediatric Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This dietary intervention aims at developing a more personalized and targeted treatment for
      NAFLD in Hispanic children and adolescents who are GG for the PNPLA3 variant. The
      investigators previous publications have shown that this particular demographic has a greater
      than 2-fold higher liver fat compared to GC and CC individuals. They have also demonstrated a
      significant gene*dietary sugar interaction with a significant association between liver fat
      and dietary sugar intake in GG subjects with no such association in GC or CC individuals.
      These studies suggests that different dietary strategies may have differential effects on
      reducing liver fat, depending on PNPLA3 genotype. To confirm this, the investigators will
      complete a clinical trial in 120 overweight and obese Hispanic children (12 - 18 years) with
      clinically verified NAFLD who will be randomized to one of two 12-week interventions:

      Group 1 (standard of care control group): Dietary intervention focused on healthy eating
      (n=60; 30GG + 30GC/CC)

      Group 2 (standard of care + sugar reduction): Dietary intervention based on healthy eating
      and sugar reduction focused on reduction of sugary beverages and added sugar towards a goal
      of 10% of daily calories (n=60; 30GG + 30GC/CC)

      The following outcomes will be measured before and after intervention: Total liver fat
      fraction, and visceral and subcutaneous abdominal adipose tissue volume by magnetic resonance
      imaging (MRI); liver fibrosis by magnetic resonance elastography (MRE); total body fat by
      DEXA; liver enzymes, fasting insulin, glucose, lipids, free fatty acids and inflammatory
      markers, gut microbiome, and insulin and glucose response to an oral glucose challenge. The
      investigators hypothesize that liver fat fraction, liver fibrosis, and metabolic outcomes,
      such as fasting and 2h-glucose and insulin, and inflammatory biomarkers, will show
      significantly greater improvements with sugar reduction relative to control. In addition, the
      investigators also hypothesize a treatment*genotype interaction whereby the reduction in
      liver fat will be significantly greater in GG relative to CC/CG subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total liver fat fraction by Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver fibrosis by Magnetic Resonance Enterography (MRE)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total body fat by dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver enzymes by fasting blood analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting glucose by fasting blood analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Insulin and glucose response to an oral glucose challenge</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipids by fasting blood analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory markers by fasting blood analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>NAFLD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Will receive standard of care, which is general dietary advice</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Will receive standard of care as well as sugar-reduction education</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of care plus sugar-reduction education</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a 12-week intervention where subjects will be educated on how to monitor their added sugar consumption. They will be asked to eliminate consumption of sweetened beverages for the 12-week period and will be receiving a weekly delivery of water bottles to their homes to displace the sweetened beverages in their home environment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  NAFLD: Children with clinically diagnosed NAFLD through the pediatric
             gastroenterology/liver disease clinics at LA-County+USC Medical Center, CHLA, or other
             pediatric GI clinic will be eligible for the study. NAFLD will be defined by:

               1. Fatty liver indicated by clinical assessment through qualitative ultrasound
                  ultrasound measures will be used for diagnosis purposes only and upon entry to
                  the study, liver fat and fibrosis will be evaluated through MR imaging and MR
                  elastography, as described below;

               2. Negative evaluation for viral hepatitis, autoimmune liver disease,
                  alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency, Wilson's disease, and drug or toxin exposure; and

               3. Elevated AST and ALT (defined by 1.5 times upper limit of normal).

          -  Ethnicity: This study is limited to Hispanics because of their higher risk of NAFLD,
             higher frequency (~50%) of the at-risk PNPLA3 allele (G), and because no prior studies
             have targeted improvement in liver fat and NAFLD in this high-risk population. As with
             all of our ongoing studies, Hispanic ethnicity will be based on self-identity for the
             participants as well as their parents and grandparents.

          -  Gender: Males and females will be eligible for this study.

          -  Age: Children 12 to 18 years of age will be eligible. In our experience, children
             younger than around 12 years of age and greater than 18 years would require different
             intervention/counseling strategies. Therefore, we can develop a more consistent
             &quot;age-neutral&quot; approach if we limit the age range to 12-18 years. In addition, based on
             our ongoing experience, this age range incorporates the general window of late
             pubertal development and we will limit recruitment to subjects who are Tanner stage 3
             or greater to exclude the potential confounding effects of early pubertal transition.
             Puberty will be determined by a self-assessment of pubertal maturation, and included
             as a co-variate.

          -  Weight status: Subjects will be eligible if they are overweight or obese, defined by a
             BMI &gt; 85th percentile for age and gender.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diabetes: Presence of type 1 or 2 diabetes, as defined by fasting plasma glucose &gt; 126
             mg/dl, or positive for diabetes related antibodies including ICA512 and GAD.
             Participants testing positive for diabetes will be referred for treatment. Subjects
             with pre-diabetes will be eligible for the study

          -  Pregnancy: Women who self-report as pregnant or obtain a positive pregnancy test
             result during Visit 1 will be excluded. Furthermore, should a woman become pregnant
             during the course of the intervention, she will be withdrawn from the study at that
             time and asked to no longer participate. This is in order to protect the mother and
             child from radiation involved with the DEXA scan and potential complications
             associated with a low-sugar diet.

          -  Medication: Taking any medications known to influence liver function, insulin action
             or lipid levels

          -  Self-prescribed dietary supplements: Taking any non-prescription supplements that
             could potentially affect liver function and liver fat (eg vitamin E or fish oils)

          -  Other metabolic diseases: Diagnosis of other syndromes or diseases that may influence
             insulin action and secretion (e.g., maturity-onset diabetes of the young, lipoatrophic
             diabetes, cystic fibrosis), or body composition and fat distribution (e.g. Cushing
             syndrome, Down syndrome, lipodystrophy)

          -  Other medical condition: Previously diagnosed with any major illness since birth (e.g.
             severe intrauterine growth retardation, chronic birth asphyxia, cancer)

          -  Familial hyperlipidemia: Patients with a family history of hyperlipidemia will be
             excluded, due to the particular genetic background of this disease, which may bias our
             results. Familial hyperlipidemia will be defined as LDL/cholesterol &gt; 160 mg/dL and/or
             triglycerides &gt; 200 mg/dL in both the participant AND at least one family member
             (first degree: parents or siblings).

          -  Smoking or drinking: Self-reported current smoking participants (more than 1 cigarette
             in the past week) will be excluded due to the potential effect of smoking on weight
             control and inflammatory status. Consumption of alcohol on a regular basis (40g/day
             alcohol per day determined by questionnaire) will also be excluded due to its
             important role in liver disease. Use of recreational drugs will also be an exclusion
             criteria, due to the potent effect of cannabinoids receptors on weight status and food
             intake.

          -  Participation in a weight-loss or exercise program: participants who have participated
             to a weight-loss or exercise program in the past three months will be excluded due to
             its potential effect on weight status.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael I Goran, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>323-442-3027</phone>
    <email>goran@usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michelle Munevar, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>323-442-4102</phone>
    <email>michelle.munevar@med.usc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diabetes &amp; Obesity Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033-9073</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christina Ayala, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>323-442-2500</phone>
      <email>trujillc@usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael I Goran, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 25, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 27, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael I. Goran</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

