<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02946268</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00072762</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02946268</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimal Volume, Rate, and Interval of Bolus Nerve Catheters for Shoulder Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Up-down Sequential Allocation Study to Determine the Optimal Volume, Rate, and Interval of Bolus of Ropivacaine 0.2% in Interscalene Continuous Nerve Catheters for Shoulder Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the ideal delivery of local anesthetics for pain
      control when using continuous interscalene peripheral nerve catheters for shoulder surgery.

      The study will be conducted in three stages. In the first stage the ideal bolus volume of
      ropivacaine will be determined. In the second stage the optimal rate of delivery of the bolus
      (infusion rate) will be determined. Finally, once both the ideal volume and infusion rate has
      been determined, the optimal interval between boluses of local anesthetic will be determined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the ideal delivery of local anesthetics for
      postoperative analgesia when using continuous interscalene peripheral nerve catheters for
      shoulder surgery. New technology has emerged with electronic pumps that permit intermittent
      mandatory boluses of local anesthetic to be delivered in addition to continuous infusions.
      The pump would automatically deliver a bolus at a given interval, but would otherwise be idle
      for a period of time. This technology could improve the efficacy of local anesthetics, and
      thereby improve postoperative analgesia.

      Continuous peripheral nerve catheters have been shown to improve pain control in several
      orthopedic surgical procedures when compared to opioids. However, it is not uncommon for
      patients to experience breakthrough pain in spite of a functional peripheral nerve block.
      Many times, this breakthrough pain can be managed with a bolus of local anesthetic
      administered by an anesthesia provider. Until recently, the vast majority of peripheral nerve
      catheter infusion pumps have only had the capability of providing a constant rate of local
      anesthetic administration. Newer technology allows for infusion pumps to deliver intermittent
      mandatory boluses of local anesthetic. This technique of local anesthetic administration has
      previously been evaluated with popliteal nerve blocks, but to our knowledge has never been
      evaluated for use with interscalene nerve catheters.

      Currently, data would support the idea that a bolus of local anesthetic can improve analgesia
      with decreased side effects compared to a continuous infusion. However, there is little data
      evaluating the optimal volume of bolus, the optimal speed of delivery, or the optimal
      interval between local anesthetic boluses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 21, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Optimal Volume of Ropivacaine 0.2% bolus via interscalene catheter</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Up-down sequential allocation alteration of volume to determine optimal volume of bolus</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Optimal Rate of Ropivacaine 0.2% administration bolus via interscalene cathter</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Up-down sequential allocation alteration of rate to determine optimal rate of bolus</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Optimal Interval of Ropivacaine 0.2% administration of bolus via interscalene catheter</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Up-down sequential allocation alteration of interval to determine optimal interval of bolus</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">99</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Volume of bolus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ropivacaine 0.2% volume increased or decreased by 1ml based on previous patient experience. If pain greater than or equal to 5/10 in the previous patient, the current patient will receive an increase in volume of bolus by 1ml. If pain is less than 5/10 in the previous patient the current patient will receive a decrease in volume by 1ml.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rate of delivery of bolus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ropivacaine 0.2% rate increased or decreased by 50ml/hr based on previous patient experience. If pain greater than or equal to 5/10 in the previous patient at 30 minutes, the current patient will receive an increase in rate of bolus by 50ml/hr. If the pain is less than 5/10 the rate will be decreased by 50ml/hr.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interval between bolus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ropivacaine 0.2% interval increased or decreased by 1 hour based on previous patient experience. If the previous patient received pain score of 2/10 at 2 hours then the current patient will have an interval of three hours. If the pain is greater than 2/10, the interval will be shortened by 1 hour.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ropivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>Change in administration of ropivacaine. Rate, Volume and Interval of bolus altered.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Volume of bolus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Rate of delivery of bolus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Interval between bolus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Naropin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female, ≥18 years of age

          -  Patients scheduled to undergo unilateral shoulder surgery at Duke University Medical
             Center, including arthroscopic rotator cuff repair, acromioplasty, hemiarthroplasty,
             and total shoulder replacement.

          -  American Society of Anesthesiology (ASA) Physical Class 1-3.

          -  BMI ≤40 kg/m2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a contraindication to placement of interscalene nerve block. This
             includes abnormal clotting, skin infection involving the neck, the presence of
             neurological disorders or cervical spine disease, contralateral phrenic nerve
             dysfunction, or moderate-severe COPD (FEV1&lt;80% of normal values and/or FEV1/FVC &lt;
             0.70)

          -  Patients with chronic pain (pain existing for longer than 6 months), or taking chronic
             opioids (greater than 60 morphine equivalents per day) at time of surgery

          -  Contraindications to or known drug interactions with local anesthetics

          -  Patients who will be discharged home directly from PACU

          -  Planned administration of another investigational product or procedure during the
             subject's participation in this study.

          -  Patients who do not have the capacity to give legally effective consent

          -  Suspected, or known addiction to or abuse of illicit drug(s), prescription
             medicine(s), or alcohol within the past 2 years.

          -  Uncontrolled anxiety, schizophrenia, or other psychiatric disorder that, in the
             opinion of the Investigator, may interfere with study assessments or compliance.

          -  Current or historical evidence of any clinically significant disease or condition
             that, in the opinion of the Investigator, may increase the risk of surgery or
             complicate the subject's postoperative course.

          -  Pregnant women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joshua R Dooley, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joshua R Dooley, MD</last_name>
    <phone>919-681-3551</phone>
    <email>joshua.dooley@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke Ambulatory Surgery Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steve Melton, MD</last_name>
      <phone>919-668-2047</phone>
      <email>steve.melton@duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 21, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ropivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

