<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02947178</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>500025</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02947178</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hip Arthroscopy Pain Control Randomized Control Trial (RCT)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Liposomal Bupivacaine Versus Bupivacaine With Fascia Iliaca Blockade for Perioperative Pain Management During Hip Arthroscopy: A Double-Blinded Prospective Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Femoroacetabular impingement is a pathologic process within the hip joint that results from a
      mechanical discord between the femoral head and neck and the acetabulum that results in
      chronic hip pain, hip labral tears and early progression of osteoarthritis of the hip.1, 2
      Historically an open surgical hip dislocation was performed to treat patients with this
      condition, however with recent advances in arthroscopy, patients more commonly now undergo
      arthroscopic hip surgery. From a pain management standpoint, previous attempts to provide
      peri-operative analgesia included intraarticular or portal analgesic injections. More
      recently, regional anesthesia techniques are being employed to provide more reliable and
      longer lasting post-operative pain control.3, 4 Currently, there are several local
      anesthetics available for regional anesthesia. However, they only provide an average of 12-18
      hours of post-operative pain control following a single injection.5 Bupivacaine is a local
      anesthetic that has been used for many years by multiple routes to control post-operative
      pain. A new formulation of the medication prolongs the release of the active ingredient after
      a single injection and has been shown to result in up to 72 hours of post-operative
      analgesia.6, 7 To the investigator's knowledge, there has not been any studies in the
      literature comparing a historical control local anesthetic to this new formulation of
      liposomal bupivacaine via a fascial iliaca regional soft tissue infiltration blockade to
      provide post operative pain control following hip arthroscopy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a double-blinded prospective randomized control trial. Patients will be
      randomized in a 1:1 ratio to either the liposomal bupivacaine group versus bupivacaine alone.
      Randomization assignment will be determined using a computer program based on random number
      generation, with an equal number of treatments in blocks of 2, 4, and 6 patients. The order
      of the blocks will be randomized as well. Treatment assignments will be concealed in
      sequentially numbered opaque sealed envelopes (SNOSE). The anesthesia provider administering
      the medication will not be an investigator of this study and will be allowed to know what
      medication that is administered to ensure safety with regards to any potential medication
      interactions the study medication may have with any other medication or anesthesia provided
      during the operation. This study will be double blinded by having the associate investigator
      (anesthesia resident/fellow) that will be conducting the post-operative pain score, Defense
      and Veterans Pain Rating Scale (DVPRS) evaluations, un-aware of which medication each patient
      received during the fascial iliac regional soft tissue infiltration blockade. The anesthesia
      resident/fellow will remain blinded to which medication the patient received by not having
      access to the patients electronic medical record, did not participate in the procedure, and
      will not have access to the database created by the orthopaedics residents where this
      information will be entered. The treating surgeons will also be blinded to which medication
      was administered by not being present during the randomization process and will only be made
      aware of which medication the patient received after the final two-week postoperative pain
      assessment and oral pain medication pill count, after which patient study participation will
      be concluded. The success of blinding will be evaluated by asking the patient, anesthesia
      resident/fellow and treating surgeon to guess their treatment assignment the day of surgery,
      during the pain score collection process and at the final two-week routine follow up
      appointment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate Post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>To compare post-operative pain scores between the two treatments groups. To advance this objective, DVPRS (Defense and Veterans Pain Rating Scale) scores will be collected and analyzed at discharge and on post-operative days one, two, and three. The investigator's hypothesize that the addition of liposomal bupivacaine will result in a 2-point improvement in DVPRS scores during the post-operative period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid Use</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate Post-operative</time_frame>
    <description>To compare overall post-operative opioid use between the two treatment groups. Opioid usage will be quantified using a patient-reported medication diary and a pill count. The investigator's hypothesize that the addition of liposomal bupivacaine will result in a decrease in total opioid use during the post-operative time period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Hip Pain Chronic</condition>
  <condition>Anesthesia</condition>
  <condition>Bupivacaine</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivicaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bupivicaine fascial iliaca regional soft tissue infiltration blockade</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivacaine plus liposomal bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bupivacaine plus liposomal bupivacaine fascial iliaca regional soft tissue infiltration blockade</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fascial iliac regional soft tissue infiltration blockade</intervention_name>
    <description>Fascial iliac regional soft tissue infiltration blockade: Pain relief procedure (offered to all patients undergoing hip arthroscopy)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivicaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivacaine plus liposomal bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pain Score Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>Utilizing: Defense and Veterans Pain Rating Scale (DVPRS)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivicaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivacaine plus liposomal bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pill Count</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient reported as needed (prn) pain medication usage</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivicaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivacaine plus liposomal bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupivacaine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivicaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivacaine plus liposomal bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liposomal Bupivacaine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivacaine plus liposomal bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient is scheduled to undergo hip arthroscopy

          2. Patient is between 18-50 years of age

          3. DEERS eligibility

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who are on a medication pre-operatively that would prohibit them from
             receiving one of the study medications

          2. Patient is unable to speak/read the English language (Currently, the DVPRS has only
             been scientifically validated in the English language and translating to languages
             other than English would compromise the validity of the pain scale)

          3. Patient has a history of previous hip arthroscopy surgery

          4. The patient is pregnant - ruled out with routine urine pregnancy test the morning of
             surgery in the anesthesia pre-operative unit.

          5. The patient carries a pre-existing diagnosis of a pain disorder. (Example:
             Fibromyalgia)

          6. The patient has a previous history of narcotic pain medication abuse.

          7. The patient has an allergy to one of the study medications
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Kent, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20889</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data will be combined together for data analysis.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

