<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02948036</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PSC-1011-16</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R43MH111325</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02948036</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Closed-loop Assessment and Treatment Platform for Mood Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Closed-loop Assessment and Treatment Platform for Mood Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Posit Science Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Posit Science Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aim 1: Finalize development of the closed-loop strategy in the Moodify application.

      Specific Aim 2: Evaluate the acceptability and feasibility of the Moodify application with
      the target population to prepare for a large-scale efficacy trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aim 1: Investigators have recently constructed a beta version of the Moodify
      application, comprised of the multi-modal assessment modules, several treatment modules and
      an initial version of the closed-loop algorithm to control treatment delivery. Utilizing the
      extensive experience in developing mobile assessment and treatment tools at Posit Science
      Corporation, the investigators will employ an iterative development process incorporating
      feedback from users (focus groups of patients with mood disorders), clinicians and scientists
      (project consultants) to achieve the following development goals: (1) Finalize Moodify's
      closed-loop algorithm to incorporate all assessment modules and expand the existing triage
      approach; (2) Expand cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) functions within the app; and (3)
      Expand in-app bi-directional communication feature between the clinician and user. At the
      completion of Specific Aim 1, the investigators will have a mobile app suitable for
      evaluation in a feasibility trial (Specific Aim 2).

      Specific Aim 2: The investigators will conduct a single arm, open label feasibility field
      trial with 25 participants that meet criteria for Major Depressive Disorder (MDD).
      Participants will be asked to engage with the experimental cognitive treatment and spend up
      to six weeks engaged in 15 hours of cognitive training as an adjunct to their standard
      clinical treatment. The experimental cognitive treatment will be deployed as dictated by the
      closed loop predictive algorithm, with all patient data continuously accessible for remote
      monitoring by the attending clinicians and Posit Science Corporation (PSC) clinician and
      Principal Investigator, Dr. Thomas Van Vleet. Participants will be re-evaluated every two
      weeks during treatment use, and again at the expected time of completion of training, at 6
      weeks, to evaluate changes in cognitive function. Participants will then stop using their
      assigned program for 6 weeks, and return for a follow-up assessment to evaluate the endurance
      of changes in cognitive function in the absence of further program use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change scores for mood and depressive symptoms using Hamilton Rating Scale of Depression (HRDS-17)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 6 weeks and at 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change scores for depressive symptoms using Beck Depression Scale (BDI-II)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 6 weeks and at 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change scores for depressive symptoms using Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 6 weeks and at 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change scores for depressive symptoms using Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology (QIDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 6 weeks and at 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change scores for mood and anxiety symptoms using Mood and Anxiety Symptom Questionnaire (MASQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 6 weeks and at 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change scores for anxiety symptoms using Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD-7)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 6 weeks and at 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change scores for functional health and well being using the 12-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-12)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 6 weeks and at 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change scores for quality of life using the Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire (Q-LES-Q)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 6 weeks and at 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moodify</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plasticity-based adaptive cognitive treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>This study employs a mobile-device delivered treatment program. Participants will be asked to use the assigned treatment program for approximately 30 minutes per session, up to seven sessions per week, over 6 weeks (30 total sessions)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Moodify</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Moodify</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Participant meets Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM)-5
             diagnostic criteria for Major Depressive Disorder (MDD; confirmed by Structured
             Clinical Interview for DSM-5 (SCID))

          2. Participants must be 18 to 60 years of age

          3. Participant with a score ≥ 17 on Baseline Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HRSD,
             17 item)

          4. Participants taking antidepressants or engaged in psychotherapy will not be excluded;
             instead, their antidepressant treatment will be evaluated and entered as covariates in
             all statistical analyses

          5. Participant must be a fluent English speaker from the age of 12

          6. Participant must have adequate sensorimotor capacity to perform the program, including
             visual capacity adequate to read from a computer screen at a normal viewing distance,
             auditory capacity adequate to understand normal speech, and motor capacity adequate to
             control a computer mouse, in the judgment of the consenting clinician

          7. Participant has access to wireless Internet connectivity

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participants with serious, unstable and/or untreated conditions that may affect
             cognition, including substance abuse/dependence disorders, cardiovascular, endocrine,
             neurologic diseases, brain injury, recent hospitalization, ongoing chemotherapy or
             other cancer treatment

          2. Participants with history or current DSM-5 diagnosis of organic mental disorder,
             schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, delusion disorder, psychotic disorder not
             otherwise specific, bipolar disorder, substance abuse (&lt;1 year), and/or mood congruent
             or mood incongruent psychotic features or disorders

          3. Participant with a history or current diagnosis of dementia and/or a scores within an
             abnormal range on the Mini Mental State Examination, based on age and education, at
             the time of screening

          4. Participant with a history of seizure disorder

          5. Participants that self-report, or have clinical or laboratory evidence of
             hypothyroidism

          6. Participant with a lifetime history of Electroconvulsive Therapy (ECT) or Vagus Nerve
             Stimulation (VNS)

          7. Participant with active suicidal ideation or behaviors

          8. Participants who shows signs of intoxication due to current substance abuse (including
             alcohol and/or illegal drugs) during any in person visit

          9. Participant with problems performing assessments or comprehending or following spoken
             instructions, or those with behaviors during screening or baseline visits that, in the
             judgment of the screening clinician, are likely to present significant problems for
             the clinicians performing assessments or those supporting participants in the
             in-residence setting

         10. Participant is enrolled in a concurrent clinical trial involving an investigational
             pharmaceutical, nutraceutical, medical device, or behavioral treatment that could
             affect the outcome of this study. However, participation in standard treatments (e.g.,
             occupational therapy) or use of prescribed medications (e.g., anti-depressants) is
             allowable.

         11. Participant is using computer-based cognitive training programs or has used it within
             a month of the consent date
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sawsan Dabit</last_name>
    <phone>415-230-3741</phone>
    <email>sawsan.dabit@positscience.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dana Frostig</last_name>
    <phone>415-233-7119</phone>
    <email>dana.frostig@positscience.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Posit Science Corporation</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sawsan Dabit, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>415-230-3741</phone>
      <email>sawsan.dabit@positscience.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Thomas Van Vleet, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mor Nahum, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 14, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 26, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mood Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

