<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02946606</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GX-H9-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02946606</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Clinical Study in AGHD to Assess Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of GX-H9</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Active-controlled, Multiple-dose, Open-label Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Efficacy of the Long-acting Antibody-fused Recombinant Human Growth Hormone (GX-H9) in Adult Growth Hormone Deficiency (AGHD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Genexine, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Genexine, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, active-controlled, open-label, sequential dose group, Phase 1b/2 study
      designed to assess the safety, tolerability, efficacy, pharmacokinetics, and pharmacodynamics
      of weekly and every other week doses of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The subjects who are adequately eligible to attend this clinical trial via screening will be
      sequentially assigned starting with Group 1. Each group will be comprised of subjects who
      will receive both GX-H9 and Genotropin, and subjects will be randomly assigned to either
      GX-H9 and Genotropin in the ratio of 4:1. The treatment will proceed as the proposed group
      order (Group 1, Group 2, Group 3), and safety and insulin-like growth factor (IGF-1) will be
      reviewed six weeks after each treatment by the safety monitoring committees before proceeding
      to the next group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 30, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 30, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Open Label</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1) levels in relation to time and dose strength</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD: Area under the curve, AUC0-t</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD: Area under the curve, AUC0-inf</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD: Area under the curve, AUC0-tau</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD: Maximum serum concentration, Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD: The time taken to reach the maximum concentration, Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK profile of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD: Half-life, t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamic (PD) profile of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD: Maximum serum concentration of IGF-1, Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PD profile of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD: Area under curve of IGF-1, AUC0-t</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PD profile of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD: Maximum serum concentration of IGFBP-3, Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PD profile of GX-H9 in the treatment of AGHD: Area under curve of IGFBP-3, AUC0-t</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Data in Physical examination, Vital signs, Electrocardiography, Clinical Laboratory Test Results Related to Investigational Product</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity Test After subcutaneous injection of GX-H9</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The changes of glucose metabolism indices</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Data in hormonal status of thyroid, estradiol(female), testosterone(male), and cortisol levels</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The lipid parameters as actual values and percent change from baseline (CFB)at week 12: total cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline at 12weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The lipid parameters as actual values and percent change from baseline (CFB) at week 12: High-density lipoprotein cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline at 12weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The lipid parameters as actual values and percent change from baseline (CFB) at week 12: low-density lipoprotein cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline at 12weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The lipid parameters as actual values and percent change from baseline (CFB) at week 12: Triglycerides</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline at 12weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The lipid parameters as actual values and percent change from baseline (CFB) at week 12: lipoprotein[a]</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline at 12weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The waist circumference as actual values and CFB at week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline at 12weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The hip circumference as actual values and CFB at week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline at 12weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The waist-to-hip ratio as actual values and CFB at week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline at 12weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The BMI as actual values and CFB at week 12</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline at 12weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Growth Hormone Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1: GX-H9 + Genotropin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GX-H9 (weekly dose), Genotropin (daily)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: GX-H9 + Genotropin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GX-H9 (weekly dose), Genotropin (daily)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3: GX-H9 + Genotropin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GX-H9 (weekly dose), Genotropin (daily)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GX-H9</intervention_name>
    <description>Human growth hormone</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1: GX-H9 + Genotropin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: GX-H9 + Genotropin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3: GX-H9 + Genotropin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Genotropin</intervention_name>
    <description>Human growth hormone</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1: GX-H9 + Genotropin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: GX-H9 + Genotropin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3: GX-H9 + Genotropin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Each subject must meet all of the following criteria to be enrolled in this study:

          1. Is a male or female aged ≥20 and 65 years with AGHD, either adult onset GHD due to
             hypothalamic pituitary disease or childhood onset GHD that is either idiopathic or due
             to hypothalamic pituitary disease or due to genetic causes.

          2. Has documented confirmation (medical history) of GH deficiency during adulthood by 1
             or more growth hormone (GH) stimulation tests, as follows:

               -  Insulin tolerance test (peak hGH≤3.0 ng/mL)

               -  Arginine + growth-hormone-releasing hormone (peak hGH≤4.0 ng/mL)

          3. Has been treated with stable hormonal replacement therapies for deficiencies of other
             hypothalamo pituitary axes and must have been on an optimized and stable treatment
             regimen for at least 3 months before screening (free thyroxine [T4] level within
             normal range at screening). Temporary adjustment of glucocorticoid replacement
             therapy, as appropriate, is acceptable.

          4. Has a screening IGF-1 level of at least 1 standard deviation (SD) score (IGF-1 SD
             score &lt;1) below the mean IGF-1 level standardized for age and gender according to the
             central laboratory reference values.

          5. Has a BMI of ≥18.0 and 35.0 kg/m2 (both male and female subjects).

          6. Has a confirmed negative test result for anti-recombinant human growth hormone
             (anti-rhGH) antibodies at screening.

          7. Must agree to use appropriate contraceptive methods (ie, condoms, cervical cap in
             conjunction with spermicide, sterilization, and intra uterine device) during the study
             and for 6 months after the last dose of study drug.

          8. Female subjects must have a negative serum pregnancy test result at screening.

          9. Must be willing and able to provide written informed consent before performing any
             study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        A subject meeting any of the following criteria will be excluded from the study:

          1. Has evidence of growth of pituitary adenoma or other intracranial tumor within the
             last 12 months which has to be confirmed by computed tomography or magnetic resonance
             imaging scan (with contrast) within 3 months before screening. (Subjects with inactive
             remnant intracranial tumors are eligible).

          2. Is currently receiving antitumor therapy and has a history of malignancy other than i)
             cranial tumor or leukemia causing GHD, or ii) fully treated basal cell carcinoma or
             evidence of active malignancy.

          3. Has any clinically significant electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormality at screening.

          4. Has evidence of intracranial hypertension at screening.

          5. Has uncontrolled diabetes mellitus with diet and exercise, as determined based on
             glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) levels ≥7.0% at screening.

          6. Has impaired liver function defined as elevation of alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or
             aspartate aminotransferase (AST) greater than 2.0 × upper limit of normal (ULN).

          7. Has impaired kidney function defined as increased serum creatinine levels greater than
             1.5 × ULN.

          8. Has had active acromegaly within 18 months before screening.

          9. Has active carpal tunnel syndrome.

         10. Has Prader-Willi syndrome.

         11. Has had active Cushing syndrome within 12 months before screening.

         12. Has any other major medical conditions, including eg, clinically manifested
             hypertension, tuberculosis, major surgery within the 3 months before screening, or
             significantly abnormal laboratory test results (eg, disturbed calcium homeostasis); or
             any other conditions (eg, acute infections) that may influence drug absorption,
             metabolism, or excretion, or that may interfere with any study variables in the
             judgment of the investigator.

         13. Has been treated with systemic corticosteroids other than replacement therapy within 3
             months before screening.

         14. Is a female subject of childbearing potential who is pregnant, breastfeeding, or
             intends to become pregnant.

         15. Has been treated with anabolic steroids other than gonadal steroid replacement therapy
             within 2 months before screening. Oral estrogen replacement and hormonal
             contraceptives are not allowed in female subjects. For replacement purposes,
             transdermal estrogens are permitted in female subjects.

         16. Has a history of noncompliance with medications, uncooperativeness, or alcohol/drug
             abuse.

         17. Has a positive result from serology examination for hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis
             C virus (HCV), or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

         18. Has a known or suspected hypersensitivity to rhGH.

         19. Has donated blood or had any major blood loss greater than 500 mL within 90 days
             before screening.

         20. Has a history of any medical or psychiatric condition that in the opinion of the
             investigator would pose a risk for participation in this study or interfere with the
             compliance needed for this study.

         21. Has received an investigational drug or product or has participated in a drug study
             within 60 days before screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eun Jig Lee, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yonsei University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Severance Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endocrine System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dwarfism, Pituitary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

