<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02945358</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HE581287</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02945358</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of OHIR Score to Predict a Prolonged Intensive Care Unit Stay</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of OHIR Score to Predict a Prolonged Intensive Care Unit Stay for Adult Patients Undergoing Cardiac Surgery With Cardiopulmonary Bypass</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Khon Kaen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Khon Kaen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A prolonged stay in intensive care unit (ICU) after cardiac surgery with cardiopulmonary
      bypass increases not only cost of patient care but also morbidity and mortality of patients.
      The ability to predict which patient has the tendency to have a prolonged ICU stay would help
      in patient and resource management of the hospital. There are many predictive models aiming
      at identifying patient at risk of prolonged ICU stay after cardiac surgery with
      cardiopulmonary bypass but almost all involve the preoperative assessment for proper resource
      management with one model, Open-Heart Intraoperative Risk (OHIR) Scoring concerning
      intraoperative manipulatable risk factors to improve anesthetic care and patient outcome. The
      OHIR model comprises 6 risk factors, 5 of which can be managed intraoperatively, with total
      score of 7 and a score of ≥ 3 indicating a likely prolonged ICU stay. The objective of this
      study was to re-validate the performance of OHIR score in the recent context.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a retrospective, observational, analytical study. The study protocol was
      approved by the Human Research Ethics Committee, Khon Kaen University (HE581287).

      The investigators will review all eligible medical records at Srinagarind Hospital and Queen
      Sirikit Heart Center of the Northeast, Khon Kaen University during January 2013 and December
      2014. The extracted data consist of patient's clinical data and all risk factors in the OHIR
      score. The investigators will apply the OHIR scoring to the data to assess its performance.
      The investigators will use the same criteria for a prolonged ICU stay as in the previous
      study, i.e. a stay longer that the median.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intensive care stay</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 week</time_frame>
    <description>number of hours admitted in ICU</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>ICU Stay</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prolonged ICU stay</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group 1: adult cardiac surgery with cardiopulmonary pump with prolonged ICU stay Group 2: adult cardiac surgery with cardiopulmonary pump with non-prolonged ICU stay</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>adult cardiac surgery with cardiopulmonary pump</intervention_name>
    <description>Open-heart surgery both coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) and valve surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prolonged ICU stay</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult patients undergoing open-heart surgery both CABG and valve surgery with
        cardiopulmonary pump
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients aged 18-75 undergoing cardiac surgery, both CABG and valvular surgery, with
             the use of cardiopulmonary bypass.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients having emergency surgery; receiving special devices such as intra-aortic
             balloon pump or extracorporeal membrane oxygenation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sirirat Tribuddharat, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, Khon Kaen University, Khon Kaen, Thailand</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Sirikit Heart Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Khon Kaen</city>
        <zip>40002</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Srinagarind Hospital, Faculty of Medicine, Khon Kaen University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Khon Kaen</city>
        <zip>40002</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Williams TA, Ho KM, Dobb GJ, Finn JC, Knuiman M, Webb SA; Royal Perth Hospital ICU Data Linkage Group. Effect of length of stay in intensive care unit on hospital and long-term mortality of critically ill adult patients. Br J Anaesth. 2010 Apr;104(4):459-64. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeq025. Epub 2010 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>20185517</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hein OV, Birnbaum J, Wernecke K, England M, Konertz W, Spies C. Prolonged intensive care unit stay in cardiac surgery: risk factors and long-term-survival. Ann Thorac Surg. 2006 Mar;81(3):880-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16488688</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nakasuji M, Matsushita M, Asada A. Risk factors for prolonged ICU stay in patients following coronary artery bypass grafting with a long duration of cardiopulmonary bypass. J Anesth. 2005;19(2):118-23.</citation>
    <PMID>15875128</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gruenberg DA, Shelton W, Rose SL, Rutter AE, Socaris S, McGee G. Factors influencing length of stay in the intensive care unit. Am J Crit Care. 2006 Sep;15(5):502-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16926372</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Almashrafi A, Alsabti H, Mukaddirov M, Balan B, Aylin P. Factors associated with prolonged length of stay following cardiac surgery in a major referral hospital in Oman: a retrospective observational study. BMJ Open. 2016 Jun 8;6(6):e010764. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2015-010764.</citation>
    <PMID>27279475</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Almashrafi A, Elmontsri M, Aylin P. Systematic review of factors influencing length of stay in ICU after adult cardiac surgery. BMC Health Serv Res. 2016 Jul 29;16:318. doi: 10.1186/s12913-016-1591-3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27473872</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tribuddharat S, Sathitkarnmanee T, Ngamsangsirisup K, Charuluxananan S, Hurst CP, Silarat S, Lertmemongkolchai G. Development of an open-heart intraoperative risk scoring model for predicting a prolonged intensive care unit stay. Biomed Res Int. 2014;2014:158051. doi: 10.1155/2014/158051. Epub 2014 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24818129</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 24, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 26, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Khon Kaen University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Thepakorn Sathitkarnmanee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

