<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01488253</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KSBMT2011-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01488253</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sirolimus/Tacrolimus Combination After HLA Matched Related Peripheral Blood Stem Cell Transplants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multicenter Trials to Evaluate the Efficacy and Toxicity of Sirolimus/Tacrolimus Combination as a GVHD Prophylaxis After HLA Matched Related PBSCT</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Korean Society of Blood and Marrow Transplantation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Asan Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chonbuk National University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chonnam National University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chung-Ang University Hosptial, Chung-Ang University College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Daegu Catholic University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ewha Womans University Mokdong Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gachon University Gil Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Inha University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Inje University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Keimyung University Dongsan Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Korea University Anam Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pusan National University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Samsung Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Severance Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Seoul St. Mary's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Seoul National University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Soonchunhyang University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Korean Society of Blood and Marrow Transplantation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study Design: To evaluate the efficacy of the combination of sirolimus and tacrolimus as a
      graft-versus-host disease prophylaxis, the investigators are going to perform a phase II,
      multicenter clinical trial after human leukocyte antigen (HLA)-matched, related peripheral
      blood stem cell transplants (PBSCT) in patients with hematologic malignancies. Total 116
      patients will be accrued.

      Objective: The primary objective is to evaluate the rates of 100 day Grade II-IV acute GVHD.
      Secondary objectives include the time to neutrophil and platelet engraftment, the incidence
      of grade III-IV acute GVHD, non-relapse mortality during 100 days after transplant, mucositis
      severity, all infectious complications including cytomegalovirus (CMV) reactivation, vascular
      complications (venoocclusive disease of liver; VOD, thrombotic microangiopathy; TMA),
      disease-free survival, and overall survival at 1 year after transplant.

      Eligibility Criteria: Eligible patients are between 20 and 60 years of age, have acute
      leukemia, myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS), chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML), and adequate
      organ function. For available sibling donor, a serologic (or higher resolution) 6/6 Class I
      HLA-A and B and molecular Class II DRB1 must be matched.

      Treatment Description: Conditioning regimens will vary by center and donor will donate
      peripheral blood stem cells according to local institutional practices. Peripheral blood stem
      cells will not be manipulated or T-depleted prior to infusion. Tacrolimus will be
      administered at 0.05 mg/kg/day intravenously by continuous infusion beginning on day -1 with
      a target serum concentration of 5 to 10 ng/mL. Sirolimus will be administered as a 6 mg oral
      loading dose on day -1, followed by a 3 mg/day single dose, with a target serum concentration
      of 3 to 12 ng/mL. Levels will be monitored weekly during hospitalization and then as
      clinically indicated. Intravenous tacrolimus will be converted to an oral equivalent dose
      prior to discharge and both immunosuppressives will be tapered beginning at day +100 after
      transplantation and eliminated by day +180 when clinically feasible.

      Accrual Period: The estimated accrual period is three years. Patients will be followed for
      100 days post transplantation for evaluation of the primary endpoint, with additional
      follow-up to two years after transplantation for evaluation of secondary endpoints.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Graft-versus-host disease (GVHD) remains a major cause of morbidity and mortality
      after allogeneic HSCT. The combination of a calcineurin inhibitor and methotrexate has been
      the standard GVHD prophylactic regimen for the past 20 years. However, the incidence of acute
      GVHD remains high, with reported cumulative incidence of grade II-IV up to 60%. Serious acute
      GVHD or chronic GVHD has detrimental consequences in patients including death, disability,
      infections, or prolonged hospitalization.

      Sirolimus is the first available inhibitor of the mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR). And
      sirolimus binds uniquely to FK-binding protein (FKBP12) and forms a complex with mTOR. This
      complex inhibits several biochemical pathways, resulting in a reduction in DNA transcription,
      DNA translation, protein synthesis, and cell cycling, ultimately leading to T-cell
      immunosuppression. Sirolimus has been used alone and in combination with calcineurin
      inhibitors for prevention of allograft rejection after solid organ transplantation. In the
      field of hematopoietic stem cell transplantation, the combination of sirolimus and tacrolimus
      has also resulted in a low incidence of acute GVHD and reduced transplant-related toxicity.

      In addition, the investigators demonstrated previously that the combination of tacrolimus and
      sirolimus is effective as a GVHD prophylaxis and well tolerated in cases of high risk
      transplantation using mismatched related or unrelated donor.

      As discussed above, sirolimus has emerged as one of the most promising immunosuppressive
      agents in allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. However, the benefit of GVHD
      prophylaxis regimens including sirolimus has not been confirmed consistently and there is
      controversy that the incorporation of sirolimus into GVHD prophylaxis results in improved
      survival.

      Efficacy measures: Patients will be followed for 100 days post transplantation for evaluation
      of the primary endpoint (the incidence and severity of acute GVHD) and clinical data will be
      collected at 100 day after HSCT using case report form. And patients will be recommended
      additional follow-up to one year after HSCT for evaluation of secondary endpoints or
      parameters including clinical outcomes (disease-free survival and overall at 1 year after
      transplant). The investigators will perform the interim analyses at the time when 31 patients
      are enrolled during phase 1.

      Acute GVHD will be graded according to the consensus grading scale (appendix-1). The broad
      category of acute GVHD includes:

        1. Classic acute GVHD (maculopapular rash, nausea, vomiting, anorexia, profuse diarrhea,
           illus, or cholestatic hepatitis) occurring within 100 days after transplantation
           (without diagnostic or distinctive signs of chronic GVHD)

        2. Persistent, recurrent, or late acute GVHD: Features of classic acute GVHD without
           diagnostic or distinctive manifestations of chronic GVHD occurring beyond 100 days of
           transplantation (often seen after withdrawal of immune suppression).

      Safety: All the safety analyses will be based on safety population. The assessment of safety
      will be based mainly on the frequency of adverse events and on the number of laboratory
      values that fall outside of predetermined ranges. Adverse events will be summarized by
      presenting the number and percentage of patients having any adverse event as well as by
      severity to study treatment. In addition the summary of grade 3 and 4 will be presented.

      During administration of drugs as a GVHD prophylaxis, toxicities related to drugs will be
      graded according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE v3.0). Patients
      will also be assessed regularly by physical examination and laboratory tests including CBC,
      biochemistry including liver function test and chest X-ray.

      Statistical Methods: Descriptive statistical analysis will be performed to assess patient
      baseline characteristics, engraftment, acute GVHD, and non-relapse mortality. Overall
      survival and relapse-free survival will be calculated using the Kaplan-Meier method and
      estimated using a competing risk of 100-day mortality for cumulative incidence rate of grades
      II-IV acute GVHD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    We could not receive the support from the national medical insurance owing to the changed
    policy of the government for clincal trials.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The rate of grade II-IV acute graft-versus host disease</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days after allogeneic HSCT</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be followed for 100 days post transplantation for evaluation of the primary endpoint (the incidence and severity of acute GVHD) and clinical data will be collected at 100 day after HSCT using case report form. Acute GVHD will be graded according to the consensus grading scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The time to neutrophil and platelet engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>within 6 weeks after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>The time of engraftment is defined as the first of three consecutive days on which the absolute neutrophil counts exceed 0.5 X 10(9)/L and platelet count to 20 X 10(9)/L, respectively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of grade III-IV acute GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>During 100 days after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Acute GVHD will be graded according to the consensus grading scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-relapse mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>During 100 days after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>All deaths without relapse or progression of underlying disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mucositis severity</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>It will be graded according to the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE v3.0).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All infectious complications including CMV reactivation</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence and type of infectious complications</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vascular complications</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of venoocclusive disease of liver and syndrome of thrombotic microangiopathy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical outcome at 1 year after transplant</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Disease-free survival and overall survival at 1 year after transplant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Leukemia in Remission</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia, Myeloid, Chronic-Phase</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia, Myeloid, Accelerated-Phase</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>acute GVHD prevention by sirolimus based regimen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigators will evaluated the primary endpoint and secondary endpoints comparing with historical control, that is used tacrolimus/methotrexate as a GVHD prophylaxis after HLA-matched, related PBSCT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sirolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Sirolimus will be administered as a 6-mg oral loading dose beginning on day -1, followed by 3 mg per day orally in a single morning dose with a target trough level of 5-12 ng/mL. Trough levels will be measured once a week. Sirolimus will be gradually tapered beginning at day +100, and eliminated by day +180, unless the patient required continued treatment for GVHD or experienced toxicity related to drugs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>acute GVHD prevention by sirolimus based regimen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rapamune (sirolimus, rapamycin)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Tacrolimus will be administered beginning on day -1 at 0.05 mg/kg intravenously by continuous infusion every 24 hours, with a target serum level of 5 to 10 ng/mL. Tacrolimus dosing is converted to oral capsules prior to discharge. Trough levels will be measured once a week. Tacrolimus will be gradually tapered beginning at day +100, and eliminated by day +180, unless the patient required continued treatment for GVHD or experienced toxicity related to drugs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>acute GVHD prevention by sirolimus based regimen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Prograf (tacrolimus)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to provide written informed consent prior to participating to the study

          -  Patients with acute leukemia in remission, MDS, and CML in chronic &amp; accelerated phase

          -  Patients with HLA identical donor, a serologic (or higher resolution) 6/6 Class I
             HLA-A and B and molecular Class II DRB1 must be matched.

          -  Patients with an ECOG performance status score &lt; 2

          -  Adequate end organ functions as defined by: Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 × ULN, AST and ALT &lt;
             2.5 × ULN, Creatinine &lt; 1.5 × ULN.

          -  Female patients of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test
             within 7 days before initiation of study drug.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute promyelocytic leukemia (M3)

          -  Patients with another primary malignancy other than hematologic disease

          -  Patients with a severe or uncontrolled medical condition (i.e. uncontrolled diabetes,
             chronic renal disease)

          -  Patients who are ① pregnancy, ② breast feeding, ③ of childbearing potential without a
             negative pregnancy test prior to baseline and ④ male or female of childbearing
             potential unwilling to use barrier contraceptive precautious throughout the trial
             (post menopausal women must be amenorrheic for at least 12 months to be considered of
             non-childbearing potential)

          -  Patients with an ECOG performance status score ≥ 2

          -  Patients with known positivity for HIV; baseline testing for HIV is not required
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Seong Kyu Park, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinical Trials Committee of The Korean Society of Blood and Marrow Transplantation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Soonchunhyang University Bucheon Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucheon</city>
        <state>Gyeonggi</state>
        <zip>420-767</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 6, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 8, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 31, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 31, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Korean Society of Blood and Marrow Transplantation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Seong Kyu Park, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Clinical Trials Committee</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Graft vs Host disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Sirolimus</keyword>
  <keyword>Tacrolimus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Chronic-Phase</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Accelerated Phase</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

