<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01484678</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201700056-N</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01AR056973</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>176-2010</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01484678</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Magnetic Resonance Imaging and Biomarkers for Muscular Dystrophy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Magnetic Resonance Imaging and Biomarkers for Muscular Dystrophy; The Relationship Between Genomic Variants And MRI/MRS Markers In DMD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shriners Hospitals for Children</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to determine the potential of magnetic resonance
      imaging to monitor disease progression and to serve as an objective outcome measure for
      clinical trials in Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD). The investigators also hope to learn
      more about the changes that occur in muscles of the lower leg and arm in boys with DMD.

      The investigators will compare the muscles of ambulatory or non-ambulatory boys with DMD with
      muscles of healthy children of the same age and monitor disease progression in boys with DMD
      over a 5-10 year period. The amount of muscle damage and fat that the investigators measure
      will also be related to performance in daily activities, such as walking and the loss of
      muscle strength. In a small group of subjects the investigators will also assess the effect
      of corticosteroid drugs on the muscle measurements.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overall objective of this proposal is to validate the potential of noninvasive magnetic
      resonance imaging (MRI) and spectroscopy (MRS) to monitor disease progression and to serve as
      an outcome measure for clinical trials in Duchenne muscular dystrophy (DMD). DMD is one of
      the most devastating genetically linked neuromuscular diseases and is characterized by the
      absence of dystrophin, resulting in progressive muscle weakness, loss of walking ability and
      premature death. Despite the poor prognosis for patients with muscular dystrophy, therapeutic
      interventions have been lacking, and outcome measures for clinical trials have been limited
      to measures of muscle function, serum biomarkers of muscle breakdown and invasive muscle
      biopsies. Additional quantitative outcome measures that are noninvasive and sensitive to
      changes in muscle structure and composition are needed to facilitate the rapid translation of
      promising new interventions from preclinical studies to clinical trials. As such, this
      proposal targets the development and validation of magnetic resonance as a noninvasive
      biomarker of disease progression in muscular dystrophy. Using a multi-site research design
      this study will examine the intramuscular lipid content, muscle damage/inflammation and
      contractile area in the lower extremity and/or upper extremity muscles of 200 ambulatory or
      non-ambulatory boys with DMD and 100 healthy age matched boys using a combination of MRI and
      MRS technologies. In order to assess the sensitivity of each MR measure to disease
      progression, all boys with DMD will be reevaluated in yearly or 6 month intervals. In
      addition, the investigators will correlate changes in MR measures with standard measures of
      disease progression, such as loss in muscle strength and functional ability. Using MRI/MRS
      the investigators will also examine the effect of initiating corticosteroid treatment on
      skeletal muscle characteristics and composition. Finally, the investigators will deposit
      immortalized fibroblasts from carefully characterized DMD boys participating in this study in
      established tissue repositories.

      The investigators anticipate that the MR techniques developed and validated in this proposal
      will be suitable for clinical trials in a wide range of muscular dystrophies and other
      neuromuscular diseases. In addition, MR characterization may serve as a powerful tool to
      further advance our understanding of the pathogenesis of muscular dystrophy and help guide
      the design of future trials.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in intramuscular lipid up to 5-10 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline up to 5-10 years</time_frame>
    <description>MR measures of intramuscular lipid will be measured in yearly intervals for a period up to 5-10 years.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in muscle T2 up to 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>In a subgroup of subjects the effect of corticosteroids on muscle T2 will be measured at 3 and 6 months. Muscle T2 is a noninvasive marker of muscle damage/inflammation and will be measured using MR. This substudy requires its own Primary and Secondary Outcome measures.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in muscle T2 up to 5-10 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline up to 5-10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Muscle T2 will be measured in the lower extremity and/or upper extremity muscles using MR at yearly intervals up to 5-10 years.
We will report the change for each year interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in muscle contractile area up to 5-10 years</measure>
    <time_frame>change in baseline up to 5-10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Muscle contractile area will be measured in the lower extremity and/or upper extremity muscles using MR at yearly intervals up to 5 years. We will report the change for each year interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in muscle T2 at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in baseline up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>In a subgroup of subjects the effect of corticosteroids on muscle T2 will be measured at 3 and 6 months. Muscle T2 is a noninvasive marker of muscle damage/inflammation and will be measured using MR. This substudy requires its own Primary and Secondary Outcome measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Age Matched Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Age matched non-affected (non-DMD) boys</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Boys with DMD</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will include ambulatory and non-ambulatory boys with Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy ranging form 5-18 years old.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood and Skin Samples Collected
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects will be recruited from across the country as well as locally. The investigators
        have established a website (www.imagingDMD.org) and advertise the study nationally through
        list serves.The study will also be advertised at the website of non-profit DMD
        organizations. General information will be emailed to faculty and colleagues around the
        country. Fliers and brochures will be distributed in participating local clinics, MDA
        clinics, schools, and local pediatric clinics, and in strategic locations in associated
        hospitals. Age-matched healthy boys will be recruited from the families of the local DMD
        population as well as the university community. Parents of eligible subjects will be asked
        to contact the site clinical coordinator, who will complete a telephone screening interview
        to assess eligibility.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria for boys with DMD:

          1. Ambulatory and non-ambulatory males (ages 5-18) previously diagnosed with DMD based
             on:

               -  clinical features with onset of symptoms before age five

               -  elevated serum creatine kinase level or

               -  absence of dystrophin expression, as determined by immunostain or western blot
                  (&lt;2%) and/or DNA confirmation of a dystrophin mutation.

          2. Subjects will not be excluded based on corticosteroid treatment

        Inclusion Criteria for age matched controls:

        1. Ambulatory males (ages 5-18) without disease or injury to the lower extremities

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Males with a contraindication to an MR examination

          2. Males with unstable medical problems

          3. Males who are not able to cooperate during testing

          4. Males with a secondary condition that may impact muscle metabolism, muscle function or
             functional ability (i.e. cerebral palsy, endocrine disorders, mitochondrial disease)

          5. Healthy boys who participate in competitive sports specific training in excess of 8
             hours per week. Participation in multiple recreational sports activities is not an
             exclusion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gihan Tennekoon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Rooney, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregan Health and Science University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>H. Lee Sweeney, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Krista Vandenborne, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Krista Vandenborne, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>352-273-6100</phone>
    <email>kvandenb@phhp.ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Claudia Senesac, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>352-273-6453</phone>
    <email>csenesac@phhp.ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32610</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Krista Vandenborne, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>352-273-6100</phone>
      <email>kvandenb@phhp.ufl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Claudia Senesac, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>352-273-6453</phone>
      <email>csenesac@phhp.ufl.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Krista Vandenborne, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health and Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William Rooney, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>503-418-1532</phone>
      <email>rooneyw@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Laura McMahon</last_name>
      <phone>503-418-1540</phone>
      <email>mcmahola@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bill Rooney, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gihan Tennekoon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>215-590-1710</phone>
      <email>tennekoon@email.chop.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michele Toms</last_name>
      <phone>215-590-7727</phone>
      <email>toms@email.chop.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gihan Tennekoon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.imagingdmd.org</url>
    <description>Study Website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akima H, Lott D, Senesac C, Deol J, Germain S, Arpan I, Bendixen R, Lee Sweeney H, Walter G, Vandenborne K. Relationships of thigh muscle contractile and non-contractile tissue with function, strength, and age in boys with Duchenne muscular dystrophy. Neuromuscul Disord. 2012 Jan;22(1):16-25. doi: 10.1016/j.nmd.2011.06.750. Epub 2011 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>21807516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Forbes SC, Walter GA, Rooney WD, Wang DJ, DeVos S, Pollaro J, Triplett W, Lott DJ, Willcocks RJ, Senesac C, Daniels MJ, Byrne BJ, Russman B, Finkel RS, Meyer JS, Sweeney HL, Vandenborne K. Skeletal muscles of ambulant children with Duchenne muscular dystrophy: validation of multicenter study of evaluation with MR imaging and MR spectroscopy. Radiology. 2013 Oct;269(1):198-207. doi: 10.1148/radiol.13121948. Epub 2013 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23696684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Triplett WT, Baligand C, Forbes SC, Willcocks RJ, Lott DJ, DeVos S, Pollaro J, Rooney WD, Sweeney HL, Bönnemann CG, Wang DJ, Vandenborne K, Walter GA. Chemical shift-based MRI to measure fat fractions in dystrophic skeletal muscle. Magn Reson Med. 2014 Jul;72(1):8-19. doi: 10.1002/mrm.24917. Epub 2013 Sep 4.</citation>
    <PMID>24006208</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Willcocks RJ, Arpan IA, Forbes SC, Lott DJ, Senesac CR, Senesac E, Deol J, Triplett WT, Baligand C, Daniels MJ, Sweeney HL, Walter GA, Vandenborne K. Longitudinal measurements of MRI-T2 in boys with Duchenne muscular dystrophy: effects of age and disease progression. Neuromuscul Disord. 2014 May;24(5):393-401. doi: 10.1016/j.nmd.2013.12.012. Epub 2014 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24491484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arpan I, Willcocks RJ, Forbes SC, Finkel RS, Lott DJ, Rooney WD, Triplett WT, Senesac CR, Daniels MJ, Byrne BJ, Finanger EL, Russman BS, Wang DJ, Tennekoon GI, Walter GA, Sweeney HL, Vandenborne K. Examination of effects of corticosteroids on skeletal muscles of boys with DMD using MRI and MRS. Neurology. 2014 Sep 9;83(11):974-80. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000000775. Epub 2014 Aug 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25098537</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arpan I, Forbes SC, Lott DJ, Senesac CR, Daniels MJ, Triplett WT, Deol JK, Sweeney HL, Walter GA, Vandenborne K. T₂ mapping provides multiple approaches for the characterization of muscle involvement in neuromuscular diseases: a cross-sectional study of lower leg muscles in 5-15-year-old boys with Duchenne muscular dystrophy. NMR Biomed. 2013 Mar;26(3):320-8. doi: 10.1002/nbm.2851. Epub 2012 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>23044995</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Forbes SC, Willcocks RJ, Triplett WT, Rooney WD, Lott DJ, Wang DJ, Pollaro J, Senesac CR, Daniels MJ, Finkel RS, Russman BS, Byrne BJ, Finanger EL, Tennekoon GI, Walter GA, Sweeney HL, Vandenborne K. Magnetic resonance imaging and spectroscopy assessment of lower extremity skeletal muscles in boys with Duchenne muscular dystrophy: a multicenter cross sectional study. PLoS One. 2014 Sep 9;9(9):e106435. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0106435. eCollection 2014. Erratum in: PLoS One. 2014;9(10):e111822.</citation>
    <PMID>25203313</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bendixen RM, Lott DJ, Senesac C, Mathur S, Vandenborne K. Participation in daily life activities and its relationship to strength and functional measures in boys with Duchenne muscular dystrophy. Disabil Rehabil. 2014;36(22):1918-23. doi: 10.3109/09638288.2014.883444. Epub 2014 Feb 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24499260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Senesac CR, Lott DJ, Forbes SC, Mathur S, Arpan I, Senesac ES, Walter GA, Vandenborne K. Longitudinal Evaluation of Muscle Composition Using Magnetic Resonance in 4 Boys With Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy: Case Series. Phys Ther. 2015 Jul;95(7):978-88. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20140234. Epub 2015 Jan 15.</citation>
    <PMID>25592189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 10, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 30, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 2, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophy, Duchenne</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

