<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01480531</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00030060</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01480531</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pre and or Post Operative Blood Pressure Control With Clevidipine (Cleviprexm Medicines Company) in Aortic Aneurysm / Dissection</brief_title>
  <acronym>Clevidipine</acronym>
  <official_title>Pre and or Post Operative Blood Pressure Control With Clevidipine (Cleviprexm Medicines Company) in Aortic Aneurysm / Dissection.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Medicines Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      2. Purpose of the Study -

        1. To determine the feasibility of Clevidipine use for rapidly achieving and maintaining
           individually specified patient BP target ranges in the pre and postoperative periods of
           aortic aneurysm and dissection management.

        2. To determine the safety of Clevidipine use in the pre and postoperative periods of
           aneurysm and dissection management

        3. Background &amp; Significance - Surgical treatments for persons with aortic root/arch
           dissection or aneurysm have significantly improved survival. However, critical in
           management of these patients is precise control of blood pressure (BP). With increasing
           BP, both acute and chronic, the risk of fatal and nonfatal vascular complications is
           imminent. Similarly, with excessive lowering of arterial pressures, cerebral, spinal
           cord, cardiac, and renal ischemic hypoperfusion is also noteworthy. Typically, the
           target systolic blood pressure range for these patients is 100-120 mmHg.

           Several different classes of vasoactive agents are in current use to acutely manage BP
           but none possess the optimal profile of an ideal vasodilator. Notable limitations
           include inadequate potency, slow onset and offset of action, multiple receptor function,
           safety concerns and, importantly, restricted/ineffective titration, which results in
           clinically significant hemodynamic and cardiovascular perturbations.

           Recently, the ultra short-acting intravenous dihydropyridine calcium-channel blocker
           clevidipine (Cleviprex, The Medicines Company) was approved for management of BP in
           critical care settings.

           Clevidipine's pharmacology lends itself to acute management of BP in a broad critical
           care setting in both surgical and nonsurgical patients. In the current study, the
           investigators propose to further characterize the hemodynamic effect of CLV in the pre
           and post-operative management of BP in patients with aortic aneurysm/dissection.

        4. Design &amp; Procedures Eligible patients will be approached to participate in the study by
           the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) attending and/or by a cardiothoracic
           surgical/anesthesiology fellow or a cardiac research nurse. All aspects of clinical
           management and monitoring will be according to standard practice that includes:

             -  ECG

             -  Oxymetry

             -  Temperature

             -  Invasive arterial blood pressure

             -  Recording of routine laboratory results

             -  Imaging studies including CT/MRI (A)/ Echocardiography

             -  Pulmonary artery catheter (postoperative patients)

             -  Mechanical ventilation (postoperative patients)

             -  According to established protocol for acute intravenous management of arterial
                blood pressure in these patients, an upper and lower threshold of systolic blood
                pressure will be prescribed by the attending physician (the range being (100 mmHg
                -120 mm Hg SBP).

      Hemodynamic data will be collected continuously via a bedside laptop as well as pertinent
      clinical data and information about efficacy and safety will be recorded.

      • Subjective evaluation of efficacy of CLV (questionnaire format to be completed by the
      critical care team)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    We elected to stop this study due to our inability to recruit suitable subjects.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The use of Clevidipine to maintain clinically acceptable blood pressure.</measure>
    <time_frame>Begining 24 hours prior to surgery thru 24 hours after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the feasibility of Clevidipine use for rapidly achieving and maintaining individually specified patient BP target ranges (75 to 135 mm Hg) in the pre and postoperative periods of aortic aneurysm and dissection management.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of hypotension</measure>
    <time_frame>Begining 24 hours prior to surgery thru 24 hours after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the safety of Clevidipine use in the pre and postoperative periods of aneurysm and dissection management to prevent hypotension as defined by a systolic blood pressure of less than 75 mm Hg.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Aorta Aneurysm</condition>
  <condition>Dissection of Aorta</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clevidipine</intervention_name>
    <description>Clevidipine administration begins in the ER or ICU
Clevidipine is again administered post op when blood pressure control is required.
Clevidipine will be administered by an infusion pump via either a central line or a peripheral IV as follows:
Clevidipine will be initiated at an infusion rate of 0.4 μg•kg-1•min-1 and will be titrated as tolerated in doubling increments every 90 s up to 3.2 μg•kg-1•min-1.
Infusion rates above 3.2 μg•kg-1•min-1 will be guided by the patient's response and permitted in serial increments of 1.5 μg•kg-1•min-1.
Infusion rates between 4.4 and 8.0 μg•kg-1•min-1 will be administered for no longer than 2 h.
As blood pressure approaches goal, increase dose by less than double and lengthen time between does adjustments to every 5-10 minutes (a 1-2 mg/hr increase will generally result in a 2-4 mm Hg reduction in SBP)</description>
    <other_name>Cleviprex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult patients (age 18-80 years)

          2. Able to provide written consent

          3. Type I and Type II (Type A) aortic dissection or unstable chronic aortic aneurysm

          4. Patients expected to be admitted to ICU following aortic surgery for either dissection
             or aneurysm requiring acute management of elevated systolic blood pressure (consent
             obtained preoperatively)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Unstable emergent dissections

          2. Evidence of end-organ dysfunction (ischemia of spinal cord, bowel, myocardium or
             renal)

          3. Active bleeding

          4. Allergies to soybeans, soy products, eggs, or egg products; defective lipid metabolism
             such as pathologic hyperlipemia, lipoid nephrosis, or acute pancreatitis

          5. Women who are pregnant

          6. Female subjects of child bearing potential must have a blood serum pregnancy test
             performed prior to participating in this study and the results must be negative.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Manuel Fontes, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ericsson H, Fakt C, Höglund L, Jolin-Mellgård A, Nordlander M, Sunzel M, Regårdh CG. Pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of clevidipine in healthy volunteers after intravenous infusion. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 1999 Mar;55(1):61-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10206087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ericsson H, Fakt C, Jolin-Mellgård A, Nordlander M, Sohtell L, Sunzel M, Regårdh CG. Clinical and pharmacokinetic results with a new ultrashort-acting calcium antagonist, clevidipine, following gradually increasing intravenous doses to healthy volunteers. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 1999 May;47(5):531-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10336577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bailey JM, Lu W, Levy JH, Ramsay JG, Shore-Lesserson L, Prielipp RC, Brister NW, Roach GW, Jolin-Mellgard A, Nordlander M. Clevidipine in adult cardiac surgical patients: a dose-finding study. Anesthesiology. 2002 May;96(5):1086-94.</citation>
    <PMID>11981147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pollack CV, Varon J, Garrison NA, Ebrahimi R, Dunbar L, Peacock WF 4th. Clevidipine, an intravenous dihydropyridine calcium channel blocker, is safe and effective for the treatment of patients with acute severe hypertension. Ann Emerg Med. 2009 Mar;53(3):329-38. doi: 10.1016/j.annemergmed.2008.04.025. Epub 2008 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>18534716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aronson S, Dyke CM, Stierer KA, Levy JH, Cheung AT, Lumb PD, Kereiakes DJ, Newman MF. The ECLIPSE trials: comparative studies of clevidipine to nitroglycerin, sodium nitroprusside, and nicardipine for acute hypertension treatment in cardiac surgery patients. Anesth Analg. 2008 Oct;107(4):1110-21. doi: 10.1213/ane.0b013e31818240db.</citation>
    <PMID>18806012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aronson S, Boisvert D, Lapp W. Isolated systolic hypertension is associated with adverse outcomes from coronary artery bypass grafting surgery. Anesth Analg. 2002 May;94(5):1079-84, table of contents.</citation>
    <PMID>11973166</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reich DL, Bennett-Guerrero E, Bodian CA, Hossain S, Winfree W, Krol M. Intraoperative tachycardia and hypertension are independently associated with adverse outcome in noncardiac surgery of long duration. Anesth Analg. 2002 Aug;95(2):273-7, table of contents.</citation>
    <PMID>12145033</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weiss SJ, Longnecker DE. Perioperative hypertension: an overview. Coron Artery Dis. 1993 May;4(5):401-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8261215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Charlson ME, MacKenzie CR, Gold JP, Ales KL, Topkins M, Shires GT. Intraoperative blood pressure. What patterns identify patients at risk for postoperative complications? Ann Surg. 1990 Nov;212(5):567-80.</citation>
    <PMID>2241312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chobanian AV, Bakris GL, Black HR, Cushman WC, Green LA, Izzo JL Jr, Jones DW, Materson BJ, Oparil S, Wright JT Jr, Roccella EJ; Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure. National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute; National High Blood Pressure Education Program Coordinating Committee. Seventh report of the Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure. Hypertension. 2003 Dec;42(6):1206-52. Epub 2003 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>14656957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vuylsteke A, Feneck RO, Jolin-Mellgård A, Latimer RD, Levy JH, Lynch C 3rd, Nordlander ML, Nyström P, Ricksten SE. Perioperative blood pressure control: a prospective survey of patient management in cardiac surgery. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2000 Jun;14(3):269-73.</citation>
    <PMID>10890479</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Viljoen JF, Estafanous FG, Tarazi RC. Acute hypertension immediately after coronary artery surgery. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 1976 Apr;71(4):548-50.</citation>
    <PMID>817089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheung AT, Cruz-Shiavone GE, Meng QC, Pochettino A, Augoustides JA, Bavaria JE, Ochroch EA. Cardiopulmonary bypass, hemolysis, and nitroprusside-induced cyanide production. Anesth Analg. 2007 Jul;105(1):29-33.</citation>
    <PMID>17578949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aronson S, Fontes ML, Miao Y, Mangano DT; Investigators of the Multicenter Study of Perioperative Ischemia Research Group; Ischemia Research and Education Foundation. Risk index for perioperative renal dysfunction/failure: critical dependence on pulse pressure hypertension. Circulation. 2007 Feb 13;115(6):733-42. Epub 2007 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>17283267</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 14, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 23, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 29, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 11, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>aorta</keyword>
  <keyword>aneurysm</keyword>
  <keyword>dissection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Aneurysm</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Clevidipine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

