<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01481090</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NUHS H1007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01481090</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Electro-acupuncture and Assisted Reproductive Technology</brief_title>
  <official_title>Electro-acupuncture and Assisted Reproductive Technology: Impact of EA on Endometrium During Medicated Frozen Embryo Transfer Uterine Preparation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University of Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University of Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      One of the most widely used procedures in reproductive medicine technologies is In Vitro
      Fertilization (IVF). During the IVF procedure, there are sometimes unused embryos that are
      frozen to be used at later times. If these embryos are thawed and transferred back to the
      mother, proper development of the uterine lining plays an important role in outcome of
      pregnancy. Electro-acupuncture (EA), a technique where electrical current is applied to the
      needle to stimulate an acupoint, has been shown to increase uterine blood flow, increasing
      the likelihood of developing a more ideal endometrial lining. This randomized study aims to
      evaluate the impact of EA on endometrium undergoing medicated frozen embryo transfer cycle
      preparation. The treatment group will receive four acupuncture treatments during the
      medicated uterine preparation. Endometrial thickness will be compared to a group that does
      not receive acupuncture.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All the subjects in the study will be randomized and their participation is completely
      voluntary. Patients recruited to join the study will not receive any monetary compensation
      for participation.

      This research will include 100 female subjects, ages 21-45, undergoing medicated frozen
      embryo transfer (mFET). The subjects will be randomized into treatment and the non-treatment
      groups. The non-treatment group will undergo the medicated uterine preparation for FET
      according to the fertility clinic's protocol.

      Subjects in the treatment group will receive four electro-acupuncture (EA) treatments in
      addition to the mFET protocol, starting after the 1st Ultrasound measurement which
      constitutes as a baseline, until the start of the progesterone administration. Endometrial
      thickness will be measured using ultrasound and estrogen (E2) levels will be measured by
      blood samples as a standard measure to assess the time of P4 (progesterone) supplementation.
      This step will be done by the participant's fertility clinic according to the clinic's
      protocol.

      Acupuncture points of LI-4, LV-3, SP-6, Zi Gong, CV-3, CV-4, ST-36 will be needled.
      Electro-stimulation will be applied to acupoints SP-6, Zi-Gong, CV-3 and CV-4 at low
      frequency. The needle retention with electro-stimulation will last for 25 minutes. After the
      25 minutes, the needles and the electro-stimulation will be removed and the patients will be
      dismissed.

      Ultrasound results measuring endometrium will be obtained from the subject's fertility
      clinic. US and bloodwork will be performed at baseline, and before the progesterone
      administration according to the fertility clinic. This US measurement and bloodwork results
      will be used for statistical analysis to compare endometrial lining of the two groups. The
      final discussion will be presented according to the findings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    IRB violations
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in endometrium thickness during hormone treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, day 8 and day 15 of hormone treatment</time_frame>
    <description>As part of the preparation for embryo transfer, patients undergo ultrasound during hormone treatment to assess endometrium thickness. Research participants will agree to release ultrasound results to the research personnel to determine whether acupuncture treatments affect endometrium thickness compared to no acupuncture treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Electro-Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group will receive 4 acupuncture treatments over 14 days during hormone treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group will not receive acupuncture.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acupuncture, Electro-Acupuncture</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive 4 Electro-acupuncture stimulation applied to acupoints SP-6, Zi-Gong, CV-3 and CV-4acupuncture treatments during hormone treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Electro-Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women undergoing medicated frozen embryo transfer uterine preparation

          -  Ages between 21-45 years old

          -  Must be fluent in English

          -  Must be willing to receive four electro-acupuncture treatments

          -  Must be willing to provide access to medical records from the fertility clinic

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Males

          -  Subjects involved with fresh IVF cycle

          -  Subjects with pace maker

          -  Subjects with history of seizure disorders

          -  All others who do not meet the inclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hui Y Cai, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National University of Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tiffani Kim Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60654</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National University of Health Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lombard</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60148</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 22, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 23, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 29, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>acupuncture</keyword>
  <keyword>frozen embryos</keyword>
  <keyword>endometrium</keyword>
  <keyword>TCM</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

