<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01481246</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ΑΝΘΡΩ/ΚΟΙΝΩ/0308(ΒΕ)/07</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ΑΝΘΡΩ/ΚΟΙΝΩ/0308(ΒΕ)/07</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>SKEPSH</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01481246</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurocognitive Study for the Aging</brief_title>
  <acronym>NEUROAGE</acronym>
  <official_title>The Neurocognitive Study for the Aging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cyprus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cyprus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Neurocognitive Study for the Aging (NEUROAGE) was initially funded by the Cyprus Research
      Promotion Foundation and has received subsequent funding by the European Union Regional
      Development Fund. The project focuses on the understanding of the effects of age on
      neurocognitive abilities such as attention, memory, language, categorization, and executive
      functioning. In addition, specific arms of the project investigate the effects of a
      theory-driven hierarchical training program, the Categorization Program, to improve cognitive
      abilities in adults with Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI). Over 800 adults ages 40 and older
      have been recruited in the NEUROAGE project thus far. The grant was awarded to the University
      of Cyprus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Given the fact that older adults are expected to live longer while maintaining their social
      and professional activities, the development of effective cognitive retraining methodologies
      designed to maximize independence has been of interest. In addition to changes caused by the
      normal aging process, older adults over 65 are at a high risk for developing dementia. About
      8-12% of the older adult population will demonstrate a pre-dementia syndrome referred to as
      Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) which is considered a prodrome to dementia. Consequently, it
      is important to identify variables that contribute to the development of MCI as well as
      neurocognitive therapy approaches to help patients improve their level of functioning.

      Categorization is one of the most fundamental cognitive processes. The ability to divide the
      world into discrete categories is a rudimentary process beginning early in life and continues
      to be developed and refined across the lifespan. This underlying process is crucial to a
      variety of neurocognitive abilities including attention and memory and can influence
      vocational and educational reintegration. Normal aging results in categorization deficits
      which in turn can interfere with the individual's ability to attend, remember, and organize
      information. This difficulty could hamper activities of daily living, social participation,
      and independence. This project implements an innovative treatment program based on current
      theoretical models of human cognition designed to improve neurocognitive abilities.

      e of the objectives of the project is to provide evidence on the effectiveness of a
      systematic and hierarchical neurocognitive therapy method, the Categorization Program (CP) in
      adults with MCI and in normal older adults. It is hypothesized that the CP will be an
      effective treatment approach to improve categorization abilities in both groups of subjects.

      The following activities have been taking place:

        1. Initially, a population-based sample of 500 older adults was tested using a battery of
           neuropsychological measures. Normal older adults are reassessed every two years.
           Currently, more than 800 healthy adults have been recruited in this project.

        2. Second, normal OA and adults with MCI have been randomly assigned into either the
           treated or untreated groups. The treated groups receive the CP training in order to test
           its effectiveness.

        3. Third, the long term effects of cognitive retraining up to 1 year post treatment will be
           assessed.

        4. Finally, the project examines the relationship between the categorization tasks,
           neuropsychological performance, functional outcome measures, and subject characteristics
           including health indices, education, and biomarkers. Theoretical constructs such as
           Cognitive Reserve have been explored as part of this project.

      The long-term objective of this research program is to determine variables that influence
      cognitive decline in older adults and develop effective neurocognitive therapy techniques.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychological Tests</measure>
    <time_frame>on going</time_frame>
    <description>a variety of cognitive tests as well as psychosocial measures are used in this project</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <condition>Memory Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Decline</condition>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Aging/Cognitive Decline</arm_group_label>
    <description>Health adults as well as adults with MCI and early stage AD are being recruited in the study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Categorization training</intervention_name>
    <description>Behavioral intervention consisting of cognitive training exercises to improve categorization performance</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Aging/Cognitive Decline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      APOE phenotyping
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Normal older adults and adults with cognitive decline are recruited in this study
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  healthy with no prior neurological history

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  prior neurological history or significant psychiatric history
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fofi Constantinidou, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cyprus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fofi Constantinidou, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>35722892078</phone>
    <email>fofic@ucy.ac.cy</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cyprus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nicosia</city>
        <zip>1678</zip>
        <country>Cyprus</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fofi Constantinidou, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>35722894437</phone>
      <email>fofic@ucy.ac.cy</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fofi Constantinidou, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Cyprus</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cancyprus.org</url>
    <description>Center for Applied Neuroscience</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 25, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 28, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 29, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Cyprus</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fofi Constantinidou</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>neurorehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>cognition</keyword>
  <keyword>aging</keyword>
  <keyword>MCI</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive decline</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

