<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01489384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRC-06-2011</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>JSS-01-2013</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01489384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cimzia Treatment in Rheumatoid Arthritis: Randomizing to Stop Versus Continue Disease-modifying Anti-rheumatic Drug(s)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Canadian Randomized Controlled Trial of DMARD Withdrawal in RA Patients Achieving Therapeutic Response With Cimzia + DMARD Combination Treatment.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pope Research Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pope Research Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the safety and efficacy of Cimzia given as an
      add-on to your current therapy with disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drug(s)
      (DMARDs)including MTX or given as monotherapy (alone) over an 18 month period.

      Approximately 125 patients with moderate to severe Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA) who are being
      prescribed Cimzia will be enrolled into the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rheumatoid arthritis is a chronic systemic inflammatory disease that is associated with
      significant morbidity and mortality. The disease is characterized by inflammation of synovial
      joints that can result in pain, swelling and joint damage with secondary deformity and
      progressive disability and impairment of patient's health related quality of life. It is
      estimated that about 1% of the population worldwide has RA.

      Treatment for RA includes use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs),
      cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) selective inhibitors, corticosteroids and DMARDs. The effectiveness
      and toxicities associated with use of DMARDs differs based on the individual agent; DMARDs
      are often partially effective. For those in whom DMARDs have not fully treated RA, TNF
      inhibitors are often prescribed.

      TNFα plays an important role in RA. Activities ascribed to TNFα in RA include recruitment and
      activation of polymorphonuclear leukocytes (PMNs), cellular proliferation, increased
      prostaglandin and matrix-degrading protease activity, and bone and cartilage resorption.

      CIMZIA (certolizumab pegol) in combination with methotrexate (MTX) is indicated for:

      • reducing signs and symptoms, inducing major clinical response, and reducing the progression
      of joint damage as assessed by X-ray, in adult patients with moderately to severely active
      rheumatoid arthritis (RA).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 27, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of patients achieving DAS28&lt;3.2 or maintaining a change in DAS from baseline of ≥ 1.2 at 18 months.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between-group differences with respect to the proportion of subjects achieving DAS28&lt;3.2 will be assessed for statistical significance with the Chi-square test. Multiple-logistic regression model with terms for treatment group and potential confounders will be used to produce adjusted estimates of the relative rate of achieving therapeutic effectiveness. Time to achieving DAS28&lt;3.2 will be assessed with Kaplan Meier survival analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in DAS28 score in each group at 18 months</measure>
    <time_frame>At 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Between-group differences will be assessed for statistical significance with One Way ANOVA. General Linear Models will be used to adjust the between-group differences for potential confounders identified during the assessment of the baseline and demographic characteristics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">125</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3 months: Discontinue vs continue DMARDS</arm_group_label>
    <description>At 3 months those patients who achieved a change in DAS28 of 1.2 or greater will be randomized to discontinue versus continue DMARDs and will be followed for an additional 15 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>6 months: discontinue vs continue DMARDs</arm_group_label>
    <description>(Protocol amendment 4.0)At 6 months, those patients still on Cimzia and DMARD therapy who were not randomized at month 3 AND achieve a change in DAS28&gt; 1.2 will be randomized to discontinue versus continue DMARDs and will be followed for an additional 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>6 months: D/C vs Cont'd DMARDs if change in DAS28</arm_group_label>
    <description>(Protocol amendment 4.0)At 6 months, if the change in DAS28 is at least 0.6 and there is a decision to continue Cimzia, then the patients will be randomized to discontinue versus continue DMARDs with Cimzia and will be followed for an additional 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3 or 6 months: stop CIMZIA and treat as per SOC</arm_group_label>
    <description>(Protocol amendment 4.0)If a change in DAS28 of &lt;0.6 occurs at 6 months (at 3 months for protocol amendment 6.1)in patients not randomized at month 3 then the patient will stop Cimzia and treatment will be standard of care. However, patient will still be followed until the end of study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who had not had an adequate response to a DMARD therapy will have Cimzia added to
        their existing DMARD therapy at baseline and will be followed.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient must be ≥ 18 years of age.

          2. Patient must be able to understand the information provided to them and to give
             written Informed Consent.

          3. Patient must fulfill the old or new criteria for RA (see Appendix 1) or have a
             clinical diagnosis of RA.

          4. Patient must be receiving (for 3 months before baseline) one of the following:
             methotrexate (≥ 12.5 mg) or another DMARD (leflunomide 10 to 20 mg/day, sulfasalazine
             &gt;1000 mg/day, IM myochrysine for at least 20 weeks at 25 mg per month or more,
             azathioprine&gt; 75mg/day), or combination DMARDs such as methotrexate with any other
             DMARD, or other combinations.

          5. If patient is on prednisone they must be on a stable dose (≤ 10 mg/day) for 1 month
             prior to baseline.

          6. Patient with active RA (≥ 3 SJC, on 28 joint count) who needs anti-TNF therapy as
             determined by the investigator and ability to obtain coverage for anti-TNF (Cimzia).

          7. Patient must not have previously been exposed to Cimzia, however, previous anti-TNF
             exposure is allowed.

          8. Patient with past anti-TNF exposure will be included if 1st anti-TNF was stopped due
             to secondary loss of efficacy, side effect or discontinuation for other reasons.

          9. Patient must use Cimzia as per the dosing guidelines in the approved product
             monograph.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Female patient who is breast-feeding or pregnant or does plan to become pregnant over
             the next year

          2. Failure to use acceptable form of contraception in a pre-menopausal woman

          3. Patient with concurrent serious liver disease

          4. Patient with concurrent serious renal disease

          5. Patient with significant hematological impairments

          6. Patient with a history of cancer within the last 2 years, other than a successfully
             treated skin basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma and/or localized carcinoma in situ
             of the cervix

          7. Patient with a history of malignant lymphoma of leukemia

          8. Patient with a history of neurologic symptoms suggestive of central nervous system
             (CNS) demyelinating disease (e.g. Multiple Sclerosis)

          9. Patient with a history of untreated active tuberculosis

         10. Patient with positive PPD (&gt;5 mm) who have not had prophylaxis

         11. Patient with a known positive HIV test

         12. Patient with a persistent or severe infection(s) requiring hospitalization or
             treatment with iv antibiotics within 30 days or oral antibiotics within 7 days prior
             to baseline.

         13. Patient with significant congestive heart failure

         14. Patient with clinically significant concurrent medical of psychiatric disorders that
             in the physician's judgment may influence the study outcomes.

         15. Patient with any condition that would prevent participation or completion in this
             study including language limitation or possibility that the patient will not be
             available for the complete study period

         16. Patient with severe noncompliance

         17. Patient receiving an experimental product within the last 6 weeks prior to first dose
             of Cimzia.

         18. Other joint disease or joint pain condition where the patient or physician cannot
             distinguish RA assessments from the other joint disease

         19. Concomitant SLE

         20. Chest x-ray shows evidence of TB.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janet Pope, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Pope Research Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rhumatologie Moncton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moncton</city>
        <state>New Brunswick</state>
        <zip>E1G 2K5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eric N. Grant Professional Corp.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quispamsis</city>
        <state>New Brunswick</state>
        <zip>E2E 4J8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Bowmanville</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L1C 1P6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dr.'s Nalin and Vandana Ahluwalia Medicine Professional Corp.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brampton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L6T 3J1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brockville Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brockville</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K6V 5J9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Arthritis Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L7L 0B7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Health Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guelph</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N1H 5H8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St-Joseph Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 4V2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>N.R. Medical Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Markham</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L6E 0H7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arthur Karasik Medicine Professional Corporation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M9C 5N2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut de Rhumatologie de Montréal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2L 1S6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>G.R.M.O. (Groupe de recherche en maladies oseuses) Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quebec</city>
        <zip>G1V 3M7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre de Rhumatologie St-Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quebec</city>
        <zip>G1W 4R4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 7, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 8, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 9, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rheumatoid arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>DAS28</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antirheumatic Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Certolizumab Pegol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

