<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01482637</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>#0902</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DA025687</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01482637</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development of Coercion Assessment Scale</brief_title>
  <acronym>CAS</acronym>
  <official_title>Improving Ethics in Research: Development of the Coercion Assessment Scale</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Treatment Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Treatment Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, the investigators seek to further develop the CAS as a comprehensive,
      reliable, and valid instrument for measuring coercion to participate in research among adult
      substance abusing offender populations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      First, the investigators wish to widen the scope of the CAS so that it can reliably and
      validly measure perceived coercion. The content domain will be expanded to included pressures
      experienced by a range of individuals involved in the criminal justice system. Second, the
      investigators will finalize the CAS by ensuring that the instrument is appropriate for use
      with substance abusing offenders. A final goal of the study examines the psychometric
      properties of the instrument. This evaluation will include an examination of test-retest
      reliability, internal consistency and factor structure, and convergent and discriminant
      validity.

      This study will be carried out in three distinct phases to satisfy the goals detailed above.
      The purpose of Phase 1 is to add to the already existing content of the CAS. In this phase,
      focus groups will be conducted with clients (i.e., substance abusing offenders) and
      professionals (i.e., treatment and criminal justice staff and stakeholders) in several
      different criminal justice. The goal of these groups will be to identify additional sources
      of coercion that substance abusing offenders may experience related to participation in
      research. The purpose of Phase 2 is to finalize and ensure the appropriateness of the
      instrument. In this phase, the investigators will conduct a protocol analysis with 30 drug
      court clients. The interviewer will read each item aloud to participants, and participants
      will provide their response. After completing each item, they will be interviewed about how
      they arrived at their decision. The purpose of Phase 3 is to evaluate the psychometric
      properties of the CAS. A total of 200 substance abusing offenders participating in an ongoing
      NIDA-funded study (i.e., the &quot;host study&quot;) will receive TRI's manualized written informed
      consent procedure as part of their participation in the host study. Following consent,
      research staff will administer study assessments to all consented participants. Additionally,
      a random sample of 50 clients will be selected to complete a retest interview, scheduled
      three to five days following the initial interview to assess the extent to which responses
      vary between the two administrations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Expand Scope of CAS Measure</measure>
    <time_frame>Months 9-30</time_frame>
    <description>To expand the scope of the CAS so that it can reliably and validly measure perceived coercion to enter research studies in a wide-range of substance abusing offender populations. The content domain will be expanded to include pressures experienced by individuals who have been arrested but not adjudicated (i.e., drug court clients), offenders who have been adjudicated but are not currently incarcerated (i.e., parolees/probationers) and offenders who are currently incarcerated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ensuring CAS Use with Substance Abusing Offenders</measure>
    <time_frame>Months 9-30</time_frame>
    <description>To finalize the development of the CAS by ensuring that the instrument is appropriate for use with substance abusing offenders. Items on the instrument will be evaluated to ensure that they are correctly worded and that their intended meaning is accurately conveyed to participants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate Psychometric Properties of CAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Months 9-30</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the psychometric properties of the CAS to ensure that it is a reliable and valid measure of perceived coercion to participate in research. The psychometric evaluation will include an examination of test-retest reliability, internal consistency and factor structure, and convergent and discriminant validity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">228</enrollment>
  <condition>Coercion to Participate in Research</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CAS</arm_group_label>
    <description>There are no separate groups. All subjects are being asked to complete the CAS measure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CAS</intervention_name>
    <description>All clients will be asked to complete the CAS instrument.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CAS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        For Phase 3, a total of 228 clients were drawn from the host study recruiting from a
        misdemeanor drug court in New Castle County, Delaware and from Miriam Prison in Rhode
        Island. The sample is representative of the combined demographic characteristics of our
        host studies with the study participants being 75% male, 75% Caucasian, and 22%
        African-American in the Wilmington and Rhode Island sites. Our sample of adolescents is
        representative of the host study with 78% African-American, 8% Caucasian and 13% &quot;Other.&quot;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Virtually any defendant admitted to either the misdemeanor drug court of the New
             Castle County Court of Common Pleas, the 17th Judicial District Drug Court in Union
             and Snyder Counties, or any research participant in the NITE Study at Miriam Hospital
             will be eligible to participate.

          -  The legal criteria for entry into drug court require defendant to (1) be 18 years of
             age or older; (2)be a resident of or commit their offense in either New Castle County,
             Delaware or Union and Snyder Counties, respectively; (3) be charged with a misdemeanor
             drug offense including possession or consumption of cannabis, possession of drug
             paraphernalia, possession of hypodermic syringes, or driving under the influence
             (DUI); and (4) not have a history of a violent offense involving serious injury to a
             victim or use of a deadly weapon. Individuals with medical or psychiatric conditions
             will be eligible to participate in the study so long a they are capable of giving
             competent, informed consent to research participation.

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Dugosh, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Treatment Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Treatment Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 28, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 29, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 30, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 10, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 10, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

