<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01135394</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HP-00043497</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DK074828</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01135394</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacogenomics of Thiazolidinediones</brief_title>
  <acronym>PPAR</acronym>
  <official_title>Pharmacogenomics of Thiazolidinediones</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Maryland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Maryland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine predictors of response to pioglitazone, an
      anti-diabetic medication. The investigators know from randomized clinical trials that some
      30% of patients do not respond to this type of medication. There is presently no way to
      identify this group of patients leading to unnecessary drug exposure and medication costs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In phase I, subjects who are eligible based on height and weight and general health
      information will sign informed consent. In phase II, subjects will be screened to ensure that
      they fit the inclusion/exclusion criteria, including an oral glucose tolerance test. Other
      blood tests will be performed to check complete blood count, lipids, liver functions and
      electrolytes.

      Qualifying volunteers will enter phase III, which will consist of outpatient radioimaging and
      body composition, metabolic testing (intravenous glucose tolerance test), and tissue
      biopsies. Blood will also be drawn for genetic testing and for microarray studies of
      leukocytes. Written medication information and instructions for pioglitazone, discharge
      instructions and satisfaction surveys following the tissue biopsy procedures will be given to
      subjects during the study. During phase IV, subjects will begin pioglitazone therapy. Every 4
      weeks throughout the drug intervention, glycemic control, lipoprotein profile, and weight
      will be monitored. After 12 weeks of pioglitazone therapy, the X-ray and MR measurements of
      body composition, the biopsies and the metabolic tests performed during phase III will be
      repeated (phase V), and blood will be drawn for microarray studies of leukocytes.

      Thereafter, subjects will have the option to be enrolled in a 10 week, behavioral weight loss
      program (phase VI). Following the 10-week weight loss program, a few outcome measurements
      will be repeated (phase VII).

      Throughout the study, Women of Child Bearing Potential (WCBP) will have HCG urine pregnancy
      tests. Pregnancy tests will only be performed on Women of childbearing potential, meaning
      women who are pre-menopausal and who have not had surgical sterilization. Women who have not
      had a hysterectomy or tubal ligation at least six months prior to signing informed consent or
      have been postmenopausal for at least one year, will be instructed to practice one of the
      following methods of birth control throughout the study: oral, transdermal, or implantable
      hormonal contraceptives, intrauterine device, diaphragm plus spermicide, condom plus
      spermicide, or abstinence. Pioglitazone may reduce the effectiveness of some hormonal types
      of contraceptives. Women using hormonal methods of birth control will be advised to use a
      barrier method as well. Female subjects are informed to notify the investigators immediately
      if they think they might have become pregnant during the study.

      Participants who are eligible have 10 visits over an approximate 15-week period. Participants
      can choose to participate in an optional weight management program for an additional 10 weeks
      after treatment and before their final visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize the variability in response to thiazolidinediones (TZDs) at the physiological, cellular and molecular levels.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The outcome will be measured for each subject at the end of their participation (12 to 24 weeks). However, analysis of these outcomes will occur at the completion of all subject participation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Define genes whose regulation correlates to TZD response.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The outcome will be measured for each subject at the end of their participation (12 to 24 weeks). However, analysis of these outcomes will occur at the completion of all subject participation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify the SNPs and haplotypes in candidate genes that influence TZD response.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The outcome will be measured for each subject at the end of their participation (12 to 24 weeks). However, analysis of these outcomes will occur at the completion of all subject participation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">134</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pioglitazone (Actos)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will have metabolism studies to consist of outpatient X-ray and MR measurements of bone density and body composition, metabolic testing (intravenous glucose tolerance test), and muscle and adipose tissue biopsies. Blood will also be drawn for genetic testing and for microarray studies of leukocytes. Upon completion of the above studies, the participant will begin pioglitazone therapy. Every 4 weeks throughout the drug intervention, glycemic control, lipoprotein profile, and weight will be monitored. After 12 weeks of pioglitazone therapy, the X-ray and MR measurements of body composition, the biopsies, microarray studies for leukocytes and the metabolic tests will be repeated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pioglitazone</intervention_name>
    <description>30 mg tablet once daily for 4 weeks, then increased to 45 mg once daily for an additional 8 weeks. Total dosage period is 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pioglitazone (Actos)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Actos</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 35-64

          -  BMI: ≥ 25 and ≤ 40

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy as determined by urine pregnancy test Breast-feeding, or planning to become
             pregnant during the study

          -  Physical dimensions exceeding the limits of any equipment used

          -  Stage III or greater congestive heart failure

          -  Symptomatic peripheral vascular disease

          -  Stroke

          -  Severe hypertension (&gt;170/100 mmHg)

          -  Anemia (Hgb and Hct &lt; normal reference range)

          -  Receiving treatment for thyroid, pituitary, kidney or liver disease (except controlled
             thyroid hormone replacement)

          -  History of diabetes (as told by doctor, or taking diabetic medications Fasting glucose
             value diagnostic for diabetes 2-h oral glucose tolerance test diagnostic for diabetes

          -  Rheumatoid arthritis

          -  History of wrist, hip or leg fracture after the age of 45

          -  History of kidney stones

          -  Medications that the investigator judges will make interpretation of the results
             difficult or increase the risk of participation (e.g. anticoagulants)

          -  Any disease or condition that the investigator judges will affect bone metabolism or
             make interpretation of the results difficult or increase the risk of participation
             (e.g. anemia, cardiac decompensation, intolerance to pioglitazone, lidocaine, or other
             agents used)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dawei Gong, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 1, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 1, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 2, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Maryland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Da-Wei Gong</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pioglitazone</keyword>
  <keyword>Type 2 diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin sensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Thiazolidinediones</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacogenetics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pioglitazone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>2,4-thiazolidinedione</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

