<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01131663</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0063-09-ZIV</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01131663</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Design and Development of an Infant's Oriented Face Mask</brief_title>
  <official_title>Design and Development of an Infant's Oriented Face Mask</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ziv Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ziv Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Face masks are used for many respiratory care applications such as anaesthesia,
      resuscitation, and aerosol therapy. None of the currently available face mask for infants and
      young children are specifically designed and developed for infants. The aim of this study is
      to design, develop and test the first infant's oriented face mask.

      To achieve this ultimate goal we will first define appropriate sizes of infants' faces that
      would be used as templates for the design and development of optimally fitted model masks. In
      the next stage we will use these masks and incorporate the infants' own soother (pacifier)
      into a new SootherMask (SM). In the last part of the study we will compare acceptance levels
      between Soothermask (SM) and a conventional commodity masks without a pacifier.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Not all face masks are &quot;born equal&quot; and care must be taken in mask design, particularly for
      the early pediatric age group. Unfortunately, facemasks provided for infants and young
      children have been merely smaller versions of those used for adults with little consideration
      given to their special needs

      We believe that a major advance in answering the needs of infants rely in making the mask
      more friendly user by making sucking on the infant's soother an integral part of the newly
      developed mask. This is based on the following premises:

        1. Sucking is a vital feeding and soothing activity of infants. Incorporating sucking into
           the act of aerosol delivery greatly reduces the fear engendered and inconvenience of
           putting an obtrusive mask on the infant's face.

        2. Linking the mask to the sucking action ensures a tight seal between the mask and the
           face. Every time the baby sucks on the pacifier or the bottle nipple, the mask is
           pressed onto the face by atmospheric pressure thus ensuring a good mask to face seal.
           This then also ensures that the aerosol that has been sprayed into the holding chamber
           will be drawn into the baby's lungs through the nose with each inspiration.

        3. The material of the mask's rim is relatively wide, soft, corrugated and is thus highly
           flexible. This makes the mask easily compressible without overdue force on the infant's
           face. Thus, the act of sucking attracts the mask to the child's face, assists in
           achieving a good seal and compresses it thus substantially reducing the dead space
           volume of the mask.

      The ultimate goal of the present study is to answer these specific needs of infants and to
      develop an appropriate infant's oriented face mask. In order to achieve this goal the study
      will have three specific objectives.

      Objective #1 Define morphometric data of infants' faces Objective #2 Design and develop an
      optimally adapted face mask SootherMask (SM) based on the morphometric results Objective #3
      Compare the acceptance levels between Soothermask (SM) and a conventional commonly used masks
      without a pacifier.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptance levels of new infant face mask</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Infants will be offered two sets of simulated treatment options at random order:
Placebo treatment by nebulizer (half the group) or by Valved Holding Chamber (VHC) (the other half) through the SM followed by placebo treatment by nebulizer (half the group) or by VHC (the other half) through the conventional mask.
Treatments will be done sequentially at random order while the procedure is being captured and recorded on video. The video clips will be analyzed later off site and will be coded according to the scale in the scoring form to compare between acceptance levels of the two face masks.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Infant</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        hospitals,primary care clinic, community sample
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Non cooperation with procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>4 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Israel Amirav, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ziv Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Israel Amirav, MD</last_name>
    <phone>97246828712</phone>
    <email>amirav@012.net.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ziv Medical center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Safed</city>
        <zip>13100</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Israel Amirav, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric Department, Ziv Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Safed</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Israel Amirav, MD</last_name>
      <phone>9726828712</phone>
      <email>amirav@012.net.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Israel Amirav, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 27, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 27, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Israel Amirav</name_title>
    <organization>Ziv Medical Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Infants, aerosol, acceptance, face mask, drug delivery</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

