<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01134068</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ADJUST</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01134068</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Age-adjusted D-dimer Cut-off Levels to Rule Out Pulmonary Embolism</brief_title>
  <acronym>ADJUST</acronym>
  <official_title>Age-adjusted D-dimer Cut-off Levels to Rule Out Pulmonary Embolism: a Prospective Outcome Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Marc Righini</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Brest</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Angers</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Geneva</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Suspected pulmonary embolism (PE) is a frequent clinical problem and remains a diagnostic
      challenge. The diagnostic approach of PE relies on sequential diagnostic tests, such as
      plasma D-dimer measurement, multi-slice computed tomography (MSCT) and pulmonary angiography.
      In addition, the diagnostic workup is usually stratified according to the clinical
      probability of pulmonary embolism. Clinical probability has a fair predictive accuracy either
      evaluated implicitly or by clinical prediction rules1 and is useful for identifying patients
      with a low prevalence of pulmonary embolism who can be usually fully investigated by non
      invasive tests.The D-dimer test has been extensively evaluated in the exclusion of pulmonary
      embolism, particularly in outpatients. ELISA D-dimer and second-generation latex
      agglutination (immuno-turbidimetric tests) have a remarkably high sensitivity and have been
      proved safe first-line tests in association with clinical probability to rule out pulmonary
      embolism in outcome studies. The clinical usefulness of D-dimer is defined by the proportion
      of patients in whom pulmonary embolism may be ruled out by a normal result and it is
      determined by the specificity. However, ELISA and second-generation latex agglutination
      (immuno-turbidimetric tests) tests have a quite limited overall specificity of around 35% to
      40%. Therefore, many investigators tried to increase the D-dimer thresholds in particular in
      elderly patients to increase the rate of patients in whom the diagnosis could be excluded by
      this easy and inexpensive test. Several studies have shown that D-dimer levels increase with
      age and which turns in a decreased specificity of the D-dimer test at the usual threshold in
      the elderly, and thus to a less useful test to exclude PE in older patients. Indeed, ELISA
      D-dimer is able to rule out PE in 60% of patients aged less than 40 years, but in only 5% of
      patients above the age of 80.8 In this study, raising the cut-off value to various points
      between 600 ng/ml and 1000 ng/ml increased specificity, but this came at the cost of safety
      with more false negative test results. In this analysis, however, no stratification was made
      for clinical probability and the sample was small.

      Recently, the investigators retrospectively assessed the value of a progressive cut-off
      adjusted to age in a wide sample of 1712 patients. This &quot;new&quot; cut-off was defined for D-Dimer
      test positivity in each patient by multiplying patient's age by 10. All patients with a
      D-Dimer level below 500mg/ml, and all patients above 50 years whose D-Dimer levels were
      inferior to their age multiplied by 10 were considered as having a negative D-Dimer test. The
      exact derivation and validation of this &quot;new&quot; D-dimer cut-off is described hereafter. Using
      the conventional cutoff, the VIDAS® D-Dimer test was negative (below 500 mg/ml) in 512/1712
      patients (29.9%) and none had PE during initial workup or the three-month follow-up period.

      Using the cutoff adjusted to age (cutoff for D-Dimer test positivity equals age multiplied by
      ten, in mg/ml), the figure was as follows. D-Dimer levels were below the adjusted cutoff in
      615/1712 patients (35.9%, number needed to test 2.8). This represented a statistically
      significant 20.1% increase in the number of patients in whom the D-Dimer test was considered
      as negative, p=0.0002. Of these 615 patients, 5 had PE during initial workup (0.8%, 95
      percent confidence interval 0.4 to 1.9%).

      These data suggest that adopting this progressive cut-off in patients above 50 years, could
      increase of about 20% the number of patients in whom PE could be excluded without further
      testing, with an acceptable safety profile as the three-month thromboembolic rate remained
      very low.

      Therefore, the investigators plan a prospective outcome study in which this progressive or
      &quot;new&quot; cut-off (age X 10 ng/ml) in patients above 50 years will be used. In this multicentre
      study, clinical probability will be assessed by the simplified revised Geneva revised score
      (Table 1) and an ELISA D-dimer test will be performed [Vidas D-Dimer Exclusion® test
      (Biomérieux, Marcy l'Etoile, Paris, France)]. Patients with a non high clinical probability
      with the simplified revised Geneva score and a normal &quot;new&quot; D-dimer cut-off with the Vidas
      D-dimer Exclusion®, (Biomerieux, Marcy l'Etoile, France) will be considered as not having PE,
      and will be followed for three-months to assess possible VTE recurrences. The main outcome
      will be the rate of thromboembolic events during a formal 3-month follow-up in patients not
      anticoagulated on the basis of this strategy. Patients with positive D-dimers will be
      investigated with MSCT as currently admitted.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The main outcome is the rate of thromboembolic events during a formal 3-month follow-up in patients not anticoagulated on the basis of a PE ruled out by the association mentioned here above.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prospective validation of the simplified revised Geneva score.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3306</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Embolism</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Evaluation of a modified DD cut-off to rule out PE</intervention_name>
    <description>Evaluation of a modified DD cut-off to rule out PE</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        All outpatients admitted to the emergency ward for suspected pulmonary embolism defined as
        acute onset of new or worsening shortness of breath or chest pain without another obvious
        etiology will be included in the study, provided they correspond to the following
        diagnostic and exclusion criteria and they have signed an informed consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  PE suspicion raised more than 24 hours after admission to the hospital

          -  Absence of informed consent

          -  Incapacity to deliver informed consent

          -  Life expectancy less than 3 months

          -  Geographic inaccessibility for follow-up

          -  Pregnancy.

          -  Patients anticoagulated for a disease other than venous thromboembolism (for instance,
             atrial fibrillation)

          -  Patients allergic to contrast medium

          -  Impaired renal function (creatine clearance less than 30 ml/min as calculated by the
             Cockroft formula).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc Righini, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Geneva University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Grégoire Le Gal, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Brest</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Renée Douma, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Amsterdam University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pierre-Marie Roy, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Angers University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Angers University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Angers</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grégoire Le Gal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brest</city>
        <zip>02</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Amsterdam University hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Geneva University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Geneva</city>
        <zip>1205</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 28, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 31, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 27, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 27, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital, Geneva</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marc Righini</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>D-dimer</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary embolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostic strategy</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety of ruling PE with and age-adjusted DD cut-off</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Embolism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Embolism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrin fragment D</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

