<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01135056</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AHCC06</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01135056</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Compare Selective Internal Radiation Therapy (SIRT) Versus Sorafenib in Locally Advanced Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC)</brief_title>
  <acronym>SIRveNIB</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase III Multi-Centre Open-Label Randomized Controlled Trial of Selective Internal Radiation Therapy (SIRT) Versus Sorafenib in Locally Advanced Hepatocellular Carcinoma (SIRveNIB)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Singapore General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Centre, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Medical Research Council (NMRC), Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Singapore Clinical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sirtex Medical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Singapore General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to assess the efficacy of SIRT as compared with
      Sorafenib in patients with locally advanced liver cancer in terms of overall survival (OS).

      The Study null hypothesis is, there is no difference in overall survival between patients
      receiving SIRT and those receiving Sorafenib therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the 5th most common cancer worldwide but unfortunately
      between 70 - 80% of all HCC are in the Asia-Pacific because of the prevalence of chronic
      viral hepatitis in the region. The increase in the prevalence of chronic hepatitis C in the
      Western world however predicts that HCC will similarly be an important cause of death there
      in the next 20 years.

      Only 15-20% of HCC are today potentially curable by surgery at the time of diagnosis. Another
      10-15% of patients may benefit from potentially curative locally ablative therapy such as
      radio-frequency ablation. Prognosis in the majority of patients has been dismal as
      conventional systemic therapies have been largely inefficacious. The first successfully
      trialed systemic targeted therapy, sorafenib (2007) prolonged survival by a modest average of
      3 months in patients with good underlying liver function.

      While the liver is radio-sensitive, external beam radiation causes significant
      radio-toxicity. To overcome this, selective internal radiation therapy (SIRT) was developed
      to deliver a radiation source directly to liver cancer via the arterial route. Sir-sphere is
      radioactive yttrium on a 90 micro-meter diameter resin carrier and is an established therapy
      in colorectal metastasis. Sir-sphere has been reported to cause significantly tumour
      regression in HCC.

      This study will evaluate the efficacy of SIRT using SIR-Spheres yttrium-90 microspheres
      compared to sorafenib in the treatment of patients with locally advanced primary HCC.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall Survival is defined as the time from the date of randomisation to the date of death due to any cause. All patients will be followed up until death to compare the overall survival between the two treatments. 2 years is an estimated time frame.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival in the liver</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-free survival in the liver is defined as the time interval between randomisation and the date of tumour progression in the liver or death, whichever is earlier. Tumour progression in the liver will be determined from serial CT scans. Diagnosis of tumour progression of disease should be made using the RECIST guideline version 1.1. 2 years is an estimated time frame.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival overall</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-free survival overall is defined as the time interval between randomisation and the date of tumour progression at any site in the body or death, whichever is earlier. Tumour progression at any site in the body will be measured by any definitive imaging technique including CT scan, MRI study or other nuclear medicine scan. The Investigator should clearly indicate the site of tumour progression (hepatic or extra-hepatic) at the time of recurrence.
2 years is an estimated time frame.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumour Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Tumour response and progression will be evaluated in this study using the new response evaluation criteria in solid tumours: Revised RECIST guideline (version 1.1) [European Journal of Cancer (45): 228 - 247, 2009] (http://ctep.cancer.gov/protocolDevelopment/docs/recist_guideline.pdf).
2 years is an estimated time frame</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity and Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicity will be assessed using the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria (NCI-CTC) version 4.02. Patients for both treatment arms will be followed-up for safety and toxicity from the time of study entry (randomisation day) until 30 days post study conclusion or until commencement of the next alternative therapy, which ever is earlier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life (QoL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life (QoL) will be measured by using the EQ-5D questionnaire over the study period. QoL for patients will be measured until their first disease progression up to 2 years (estimated) which ever is earlier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver resection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be assessed for suitability for liver resection every 12 weekly until their study conclusion up to 2 years which ever is earlier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver Transplantation Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be assessed for suitability for liver transplantation every 12 weekly until their study conclusion up to 2 years which ever is earlier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Disease Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time to Disease Progression (TTP) is defined as a measure of time after a disease is diagnosed (or treated) until the disease starts to get worse. Disease Progression will be measured by RECIST guideline version 1.1. TTP will be measured every 12 weekly up to 2 years (estimated).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sorafenib, Multikinase Inhibitor, Tablet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sorafenib tosylate:
Sorafenib is a multikinase inhibitor that decreases tumor cell proliferation.
Sorafenib was shown to inhibit multiple intracellular (c-CRAF, BRAF and mutant BRAF) and cell surface kinases (KIT, FLT- 3, RET, VEGFR-1, VEGFR- 2, VEGFR- 3, and PDGFR- ß). Several of these kinases are thought to be involved in tumor cell signaling, angiogenesis and apoptosis. Sorafenib inhibited tumor growth of the human hepatocellular carcinoma and renal cell carcinoma, and several other human tumor xenografts in immunocompromised mice. A reduction in tumor angiogenesis and increases in tumor apoptosis was seen in models of human hepatocellular and renal cell carcinoma. Additionally a reduction in tumor cell signaling was seen in a model of human hepatocellular carcinoma.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SIR-Spheres, Microspheres, Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>SIR-Spheres:
SIR-Spheres consist of biocompatible resin microspheres containing yttrium-90, with a size between 20 and 60 microns in diameter. Yttrium-90 is a high-energy pure beta-emitting isotope with no primary gamma emission. The half life of yttrium-90 is 64.1 hours. In clinical use which requires the isotope to decay to infinity, 94% of the radiation is delivered in 11 days leaving only background radiation with no therapeutic value.
SIR-Spheres is implanted into hepatic tumours by delivery via either the common hepatic artery or the right or left hepatic artery using a catheter or implanted port . Once SIR-Spheres is implanted into the liver, it is not metabolised or excreted and it stays permanently in the liver.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SIR-Spheres</intervention_name>
    <description>One time treatment. Dose administered based on tumour volume. Each vial is 3.0GBq.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SIR-Spheres, Microspheres, Device</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Yttrium-90 Microspheres</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sorafenib tosylate</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral Tablet, 400mg B.i.d, until progression or unacceptable toxicity develops</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sorafenib, Multikinase Inhibitor, Tablet</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nexavar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Disease must be locally advanced as defined by BCLC (B) intermediate stage or BCLC (C)
             advanced stage without extra-hepatic disease (only with branch portal vein
             thrombosis).

          -  Willing, able and mentally competent to provide written informed consent prior to any
             testing undertaken for this study protocol, including screening tests and evaluations
             that are not considered to be part of the subject's routine care.

          -  Aged 18 years/older (either gender).

          -  Unequivocal diagnosis of HCC.

          -  HCC not amenable to surgical resection or immediate liver transplantation, or cannot
             be optimally treated with local ablative techniques such as RFA, consistent with the
             practice of the clinical trial centre.

          -  Measurable disease, defined as at least one lesion that can be accurately measured in
             at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded) as ≥ 10 mm with spiral CT
             scan or MRI.

          -  ECOG performance status 0-1.

          -  Child-Pugh A-B (up to 7 points)

          -  Adequate haematological, renal and hepatic function as follows:

          -  Leukocytes ≥ 2,500/μL

          -  Platelets ≥ 80,000/μL

          -  Haemoglobin &gt; 9.5g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin &lt; 2.0mg/dL

          -  INR ≤ 2.0

          -  ALP ≤ 5 x institutional ULN

          -  AST and ALT ≤ 5 x institutional ULN

          -  Albumin ≥ 2.5g/dL

          -  Creatinine ≤ 2.0mg/dL

          -  Life expectancy of at least 3 months without any active treatment.

          -  Suitable for protocol treatment as determined by clinical assessment undertaken by the
             Investigator.

          -  Female patients must be either postmenopausal or, if premenopausal, must have a
             negative pregnancy test and agree to use 2 forms of contraception if sexually active
             during their study participation.

          -  Male patients must be surgically sterile, or if sexually active and having a
             pre-menopausal female partner then must be using an acceptable form of contraception.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have had more than 2 administrations of hepatic artery directed therapy.

          -  Subjects who have had hepatic artery directed therapy done &lt; 4 weeks prior to study
             entry.

          -  Have had systemic chemotherapy for HCC except for prior adjuvant or neoadjuvant
             therapy given more than 6 months from enrolment.

          -  have had prior treatment with Sorafenib or VEGF inhibitors.

          -  Prior hepatic radiation therapy for HCC or other malignancy.

          -  Currently receiving any other investigational agents for the treatment of their
             cancer.

          -  Has intractable clinical ascites (in spite of optimal diuretic treatment) or any other
             clinical signs of liver failure, on physical examination.

          -  Complete main portal vein thrombosis.

          -  Any metastatic disease (local-regional lymph nodes measuring less than 2 cm in
             greatest diameter or lung nodules measuring less than 1 cm are not contraindications
             as per Investigator discretion).

          -  Any other concurrent malignancy, except for adequately treated basal cell or squamous
             cell skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer, or other cancer for which the patient has
             been disease-free for at least 5 years.

          -  Presence of clinical signs of CNS metastases due to their poor prognosis and because
             progressive neurologic dysfunction would confound the evaluation of neurologic and
             other adverse events.

          -  Uncontrolled inter-current illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection (except viral hepatitis), symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable
             angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that
             would limit compliance with study requirements.

          -  Any of the following contraindications to angiography and selective visceral
             catheterization:

          -  Bleeding diathesis, not correctable by the standard forms of therapy.

          -  Severe peripheral vascular disease that would preclude arterial catheterization.

          -  Portal hypertension with hepato-fugal flow as documented on baseline spiral CT scan.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to SIR-Spheres or Sorafenib.

          -  Inability or unwillingness to understand or sign a written informed consent document.

          -  Female subjects who are pregnant or currently breastfeeding.

          -  Female subjects, unless postmenopausal or surgically sterile, unwillingness to
             practice effective contraception, as per Investigator discretion during the study. The
             rhythm method is not to be used as the sole method of contraception.

          -  Male subjects, unwillingness to practice effective contraception (per Investigator
             discretion) while taking part in this study, because the effect of the SIR-Spheres
             treatment on sperm or upon the development of an unborn child are unknown.

          -  Current enrolment in any other investigational therapeutic drug or device study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pierce KH Chow, MBBS, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Centre, Singapore</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Brunei Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerudong</city>
        <state>Brunei</state>
        <zip>3122</zip>
        <country>Brunei Darussalam</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Mary Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <state>Hong Kong</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Udayana, Rumah Sakit Sanglah, Indonesia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denpasar</city>
        <state>Bali</state>
        <zip>80114</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cipto Mangunkusumo Hospital ,University of Indonesia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jakarta</city>
        <zip>16424</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Severance Hospital, Yonsei University College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>120-752</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Korea University Anam Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>136-705</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul St. Mary's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>137- 040</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asan Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>138-736</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul National University Bundang Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>463-707</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarawak General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuching</city>
        <state>Sarawak</state>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Malaya Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuala Lumpur</city>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penang Adventist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Penang</city>
        <zip>10350</zip>
        <country>Malaysia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Center of Mongolia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulaanbaatar</city>
        <zip>210648</zip>
        <country>Mongolia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yangon GI &amp; Liver Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yangon</city>
        <zip>11141</zip>
        <country>Myanmar</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Auckland City Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grafton</city>
        <state>Auckland</state>
        <zip>1023</zip>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Makati Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manila</city>
        <state>Makati City</state>
        <zip>1229</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Medical City</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pasig City</city>
        <state>Manila</state>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Luke's Medical Center, Philippines</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quezon City</city>
        <state>Manila</state>
        <zip>1102</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Davao Doctors Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Davao</city>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>119075</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Singapore General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>168608</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Center Singapore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169610</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Khoo Teck Puat Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>768828</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Taiwan University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei City</city>
        <state>Taipei</state>
        <zip>100</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Taipei Veterans General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei City</city>
        <state>Taipei</state>
        <zip>112</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taoyuan</city>
        <state>Taoyuan Hsien</state>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaohsiung Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kaohsiung</city>
        <zip>833</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>China Medical University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taichung</city>
        <zip>404</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chulabhorn Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10210</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brunei Darussalam</country>
    <country>China</country>
    <country>Indonesia</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Malaysia</country>
    <country>Mongolia</country>
    <country>Myanmar</country>
    <country>New Zealand</country>
    <country>Philippines</country>
    <country>Singapore</country>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
    <country>Vietnam</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.scri.edu.sg/crn/asia-pacific-hepatocellular-carcinoma-ahcc-trials-group/about-ahcc/</url>
    <description>AHCC Trials Group</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.sirvenib.com/</url>
    <description>AHCC06 Study Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 24, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 30, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 2, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized</keyword>
  <keyword>Open-label</keyword>
  <keyword>Multi-Centre</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase III</keyword>
  <keyword>Sorafenib</keyword>
  <keyword>SIR-Spheres</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niacinamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

