<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02052102</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Breast-26159</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02052102</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to See Whether Breath-Hold Techniques During RT Are Effective in Helping to Improve Sparing of the Heart</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Cohort Study Assessing Cardiac Function With MRI in Left-Sided Breast Cancer Patients Treated With Deep Inspiration Breath Hold (DIBH) Technique to Improve Cardiac Sparing During Adjuvant Radiotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AHS Cancer Control Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cross Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AHS Cancer Control Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study hopes to determine whether patients with left-sided breast cancer are at an
      increased risk of cardiac changes due to radiation to the breast +/- Anthracycline-based
      chemotherapy +/- Herceptin and whether a deep inspiration breath hold (DIBH) technique during
      radiotherapy treatments would further reduce dosimetric dose to the heart as compared to the
      conventional free breathing (FB) technique thus reducing cardiac toxicity as measured by
      cardiac MRI using left ventricular end-diastolic volume (LVEDV) as a metric. Bio fluid
      samples will also be collected to investigate specific biomarkers of breast cancer: BNP,
      PIIINP and CITP
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with left-sided breast cancer who receive adjuvant breast or chest wall radiation
      have increased risk of treatment related cardiovascular morbidity. The risk of cardiac
      morbidity and mortality is increased when a patient receives radiation following adjuvant
      chemotherapy and Herceptin. The dose-volume histogram (DVH) parameters associated with
      increased cardiac toxicity include volume of heart irradiated, total radiation dose received
      by the left ventricle (LV), V25 and mean cardiac dose. Even though modern RT treatments like
      3DCRT and IMRT can reduce the mean dose to the heart, the maximum dose to the left side of
      the heart/LV may not be reduced if the target is close to the heart. The hypothesis is that
      DIBH RT can safely and effectively reduce the heart dose, especially the dose to the LV, that
      could lead to reduction in the incidence of radiation induced cardiovascular morbidity and
      mortality.

      Radiotherapy has detrimental effects on cardiac function due to remodeling of the cardiac
      tissue that receive radiation. We believe that the radiation related acute effects on heart
      tissue can be detected with cardiac functional MRI. The study will quantify the acute RT
      related effects. To our knowledge, cardiac MRI has not been explored as a non invasive
      technique to quantify RT +/- chemotherapy related effects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiation related acute and long term functional changes in patients treated with deep-inspiration breath hold compared to free-breathing technique</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using MRI-based cardiac functional imaging to measure radiation-related acute and long term cardiac functional changes in patients treated with deep-inspiration breath-hold (DIBH) compared to free breathing (FB) treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiation dosimetric comparison</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Radiation dosimetry is the accurate calculation and measurement of radiation doses received by tissue resulting from the exposure to radiation. A radiation dosimetric comparison will be performed between the deep inspiration breath hold (DIBH) technique treatment plan and the free breathing (FB) technique treatment plan to explore sparing of cardiac sub-structures from radiation, if any</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">63</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Adverse Effect of Radiation Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No prior therapy, DIBH irradiation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort 1 - No prior anthracycline-based chemotherapy or herceptin, deep inspiration breath hold breast radiation therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No prior therapy, FB technique</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort II - no prior Anthracycline based chemotherapy or Herceptin and (ii) to receive FB RT (not able to hold breath for at least 20 seconds or does not have a minimum of 1.0 cm of heart on at least 3 slices (3mm slices) on the FB scan)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prior therapy, DIBH irradiation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cohort III - Prior Anthracycline-based chemotherapy or Herceptin, and (ii) eligible to receive DIBH RT. (Patient has a minimum of 1.0 cm of heart on at least 3 slices (3mm slices) on the FB scan)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>No prior therapy, DIBH irradiation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No prior therapy, FB technique</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Prior therapy, DIBH irradiation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female patients with pathologically confirmed left sided breast cancer eligible for
             adjuvant breast/chest wall plus or minus regional nodal radiotherapy

          -  Women patients with age group between 18 and 70 years old

          -  Karnofsky performance score ≥ 70

          -  Ability to hold breath for at least 20 sec (for DIBH cohorts only)

          -  Life expectancy &gt;10 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  For patients with prior Anthracycline based chemotherapy or Herceptin, if there is &lt;
             1.0 cm of heart on at least 3 slices ( 3 mm slices) on the FB scan, the patient will
             be considered a screen failure.

          -  Previously irradiated or recurrent breast/chest wall tumours or previous malignancy
             other than non-melanoma skin cancer unless disease free for a minimum of 5 years prior
             to study entry

          -  Patients that require a shell for breast immobilization

          -  Patients requiring a boost

          -  Stage IV disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kurian Joseph, MB, FFRRCSI, FRCR, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cross Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kurian Joseph, MB, FFRRCSI, FRCR, FRCPC</last_name>
    <phone>780-432-8755</phone>
    <email>kurian.joseph@albertahealthservices.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cross Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 1Z2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 24, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Deep inspiration breath hold</keyword>
  <keyword>radiation therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac toxicity</keyword>
  <keyword>Left-sided breast cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Unilateral Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

