<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02054806</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3475-028</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-004507-39</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>142515</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02054806</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Pembrolizumab (MK-3475) in Participants With Advanced Solid Tumors (MK-3475-028/KEYNOTE-28)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase IB Study of Pembrolizumab (MK-3475) in Subjects With Select Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will assess the efficacy and safety of pembrolizumab (MK-3475) administered to
      participants with incurable advanced biomarker-positive solid tumors that have not responded
      to current therapy or for which current therapy is not appropriate.

      The study hypothesis is that administration of pembrolizumab to participants with some types
      of solid tumors will result in a clinically meaningful response rate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 17, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 28, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 28, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Best Overall Response Using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST Version 1.1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response (DOR) in Participants Who Achieve Partial Response (PR) or Better</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">477</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive pembrolizumab 10 mg/kg, intravenously (IV), on Day 1 of every 2-week dosing cycle for up to 24 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>IV infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MK-3475</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically documented locally-advanced and/or metastatic solid
             malignancy that is incurable, and has failed prior standard therapy or for which
             standard therapy is not appropriate

          -  Have biomarker-positive solid tumor

          -  Have measurable disease based on Response Criteria in Solid Tumors Version 1.1 (RECIST
             1.1)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Adequate organ function

          -  Female participants of childbearing potential must be willing to use an adequate
             method of contraception for the course of the study through 120 days after the last
             dose of study medication

          -  Male participants of childbearing potential must agree to use an adequate method of
             contraception starting with the first dose of study medication through 120 days after
             the last dose of study medication

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Is currently participating and receiving study therapy or has participated in a study
             of an investigational agent and received study therapy or used an investigational
             device within 4 weeks of the first dose of treatment

          -  Diagnosis of immunodeficiency or receiving systemic steroid therapy or any other form
             of immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of trial treatment

          -  Prior anti-cancer therapy with a monoclonal antibody (mAb) within 4 weeks prior to
             study Day 1 or not recovered from adverse events due to mAbs administered more than 4
             weeks earlier

          -  Prior chemotherapy, targeted small molecule therapy, or radiation therapy within 2
             weeks (12 weeks for measurable sites of central nervous system [CNS] disease) prior to
             study Day 1 or not recovered from adverse events due to a previously administered
             agent

          -  Known additional malignancy that is progressing or requires active treatment excepting
             basal cell carcinoma of the skin, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin that has
             undergone potentially curative therapy, or in situ cervical cancer

          -  Known active CNS metastases and/or carcinomatous meningitis

          -  Has an active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in past 2 years
             (i.e. with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive
             drugs). Replacement therapy (e.g., thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid
             replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, etc.) is not considered a
             form of systemic treatment

          -  Has evidence of interstitial lung disease or a history of (non-infectious) pneumonitis
             that required steroids or has current pneumonitis

          -  Active infection requiring systemic therapy

          -  Known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with cooperation
             with the requirements of the trial

          -  Pregnant, breastfeeding, or expecting to conceive or father children within the
             projected duration of the trial, starting with the pre-screening or screening visit
             through 120 days after the last dose of trial treatment

          -  Has previously participated in any other pembrolizumab (MK-3475) trial, or received
             prior therapy with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, and anti-PD-L2 (including ipilimumab or
             any other antibody or drug specifically targeting T-cell co-stimulation or checkpoint
             pathways)

          -  Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          -  Known active Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C

          -  Has received a live vaccine within 30 days of planned start of study medication.
             Examples of live vaccines include, but are not limited to, the following: measles,
             mumps, rubella, varicella/zoster (chicken pox), yellow fever, rabies, Bacillus
             Calmette-Guérin (BCG), and typhoid vaccine. Seasonal influenza vaccines for injection
             are generally killed virus vaccines and are allowed; however, intranasal influenza
             vaccines (e.g. FluMist®) are live attenuated vaccines and are not allowed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Alley EW, Lopez J, Santoro A, Morosky A, Saraf S, Piperdi B, van Brummelen E. Clinical safety and activity of pembrolizumab in patients with malignant pleural mesothelioma (KEYNOTE-028): preliminary results from a non-randomised, open-label, phase 1b trial. Lancet Oncol. 2017 May;18(5):623-630. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(17)30169-9. Epub 2017 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>28291584</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ott PA, Piha-Paul SA, Munster P, Pishvaian MJ, van Brummelen EMJ, Cohen RB, Gomez-Roca C, Ejadi S, Stein M, Chan E, Simonelli M, Morosky A, Saraf S, Emancipator K, Koshiji M, Bennouna J. Safety and antitumor activity of the anti-PD-1 antibody pembrolizumab in patients with recurrent carcinoma of the anal canal. Ann Oncol. 2017 May 1;28(5):1036-1041. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdx029.</citation>
    <PMID>28453692</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hsu C, Lee SH, Ejadi S, Even C, Cohen RB, Le Tourneau C, Mehnert JM, Algazi A, van Brummelen EMJ, Saraf S, Thanigaimani P, Cheng JD, Hansen AR. Safety and Antitumor Activity of Pembrolizumab in Patients With Programmed Death-Ligand 1-Positive Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma: Results of the KEYNOTE-028 Study. J Clin Oncol. 2017 Dec 20;35(36):4050-4056. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2017.73.3675. Epub 2017 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>28837405</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ott PA, Elez E, Hiret S, Kim DW, Morosky A, Saraf S, Piperdi B, Mehnert JM. Pembrolizumab in Patients With Extensive-Stage Small-Cell Lung Cancer: Results From the Phase Ib KEYNOTE-028 Study. J Clin Oncol. 2017 Dec 1;35(34):3823-3829. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2017.72.5069. Epub 2017 Aug 16.</citation>
    <PMID>28813164</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Doi T, Piha-Paul SA, Jalal SI, Saraf S, Lunceford J, Koshiji M, Bennouna J. Safety and Antitumor Activity of the Anti-Programmed Death-1 Antibody Pembrolizumab in Patients With Advanced Esophageal Carcinoma. J Clin Oncol. 2018 Jan 1;36(1):61-67. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2017.74.9846. Epub 2017 Nov 8.</citation>
    <PMID>29116900</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Frenel JS, Le Tourneau C, O'Neil B, Ott PA, Piha-Paul SA, Gomez-Roca C, van Brummelen EMJ, Rugo HS, Thomas S, Saraf S, Rangwala R, Varga A. Safety and Efficacy of Pembrolizumab in Advanced, Programmed Death Ligand 1-Positive Cervical Cancer: Results From the Phase Ib KEYNOTE-028 Trial. J Clin Oncol. 2017 Dec 20;35(36):4035-4041. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2017.74.5471. Epub 2017 Nov 2.</citation>
    <PMID>29095678</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>O'Neil BH, Wallmark JM, Lorente D, Elez E, Raimbourg J, Gomez-Roca C, Ejadi S, Piha-Paul SA, Stein MN, Abdul Razak AR, Dotti K, Santoro A, Cohen RB, Gould M, Saraf S, Stein K, Han SW. Safety and antitumor activity of the anti-PD-1 antibody pembrolizumab in patients with advanced colorectal carcinoma. PLoS One. 2017 Dec 28;12(12):e0189848. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0189848. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>29284010</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 3, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PD1</keyword>
  <keyword>PD-1</keyword>
  <keyword>PDL1</keyword>
  <keyword>PD-L1</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

