<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02056002</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R-IHS-1306-02505</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PCORI</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02056002</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Peer-Driven Intervention for Sleep Apnea</brief_title>
  <acronym>PCORI</acronym>
  <official_title>Peer-Driven Intervention as an Alternate Model of Care Delivery and Coordination for Sleep Apnea</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Arizona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arizona</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fragmentation of care can lead to poor treatment adherence in patients with chronic medical
      conditions which can, in turn, lead to adverse health consequences, poor quality of life, and
      patient dissatisfaction. Poor treatment adherence may be due to lack of sufficient patient
      education, time delays in delivery of care, lack of adequate healthcare coordination, or
      difficulty accessing various healthcare providers across a front desk which serves as a
      &quot;healthcare bottle-neck&quot;. Better efficiency in healthcare delivery, with greater connectivity
      through knowledgeable and trained peer volunteers and inexpensive cell-phones integrated by a
      smart telephone exchange may alleviate some of the care and communication burden faced by the
      healthcare system. Specifically, such community health education volunteers (&quot;peer-buddies&quot;)
      who are experienced in managing their disease condition may be able to impart knowledge and
      confidence to a recently diagnosed patient in a much more personalized manner than that of a
      group therapy session. An additional important advantage is the peer-buddy's ability to
      relate to the patient in a manner consistent with their social, ethnic, and cultural believes
      without language barriers or differences that may stem from socioeconomic strata. We will use
      sleep apnea as an example condition to test the effect of a peer-buddy helper (combined with
      the universal availability of personal cell phones) on the problem of poor care coordination
      and treatment adherence to the &quot;CPAP&quot; treatment for sleep apnea. Sleep apnea is a very common
      condition that affects 7-12% of the US population, and if left untreated, can lead to poor
      health and even death through its effects on high blood pressure, heart disease, stroke, and
      motor vehicle accidents. Fortunately, CPAP therapy can lead to a 3-fold reduction in such
      consequences, but patient adherence to such CPAP treatment is generally poor. We have
      recently completed a small study that demonstrated improved usage of CPAP treatment by
      patients receiving help from a peer-buddy with excellent results. We propose to further
      enhance the &quot;peer-buddy&quot; community-volunteer concept in our proposed research by combining
      this with cell-phone technology and a telephone exchange that improves access to healthcare
      providers, technicians, and home care companies. We hope to show that active community
      participation by experienced &quot;lay individuals&quot; assisted by the universal availability of
      cheap cell-phones can improve the reach and effectiveness of our healthcare system in
      improving the health and well-being of our patients. If successful, such an innovative and
      community-based approach can be applied to other chronic medical conditions.

      Hypothesis #1: We hypothesize that patients in the peer-driven intervention with interactive
      voice response (PDI-IVR) group will experience a greater patient satisfaction (measured by
      Likert scale64,70 and PACIC71,72) and perception of care coordination (measured by CPCQ72,73)
      than patients in the usual care (control) group.

      Hypothesis #2: We hypothesize that patients in the PDI-IVR group will experience a greater
      CPAP adherence (measured by device download), patient activation (PAM), and self-efficacy
      (SEMSA) than patients in the usual care (control) group.

      Hypothesis #3: We hypothesize that patients in the PDI-IVR group will experience greater
      improvements in HR-QOL (measured by FOSQ) vigilance (psychomotor vigilance testing) and blood
      pressure than patients in the usual care (control) group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      COMPARATORS:

        1. Intervention group: In order to address the proposed aims, we will recruit recently
           diagnosed patients with obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) who have not been initiated on
           CPAP therapy and randomly assign them to the PDI-IVR system to promote adherence to CPAP
           therapy (intervention group) or be provided with educational brochures regarding OSA and
           CPAP therapy (usual care [control] group). In the PDI-IVR intervention group, trained
           and experienced peers (peer-buddy) with sleep apnea will be paired with the newly
           diagnosed patients over a 6-month period. As in our preliminary study, the peer-buddy
           will be matched with the subjects with regards to age, gender, race, ethnicity,
           socioeconomic, and educational backgrounds. During this time the trained peers will
           share experiences on coping strategies with CPAP device and equipment (promote self
           efficacy), share their positive experiences (motivational effects and outcome
           expectancies), share their knowledge of perceived vulnerabilities due to untreated sleep
           apnea (promote risk perception), share methods for improving efficacy of CPAP equipment
           and interface (patient education) and prepare their subjects for upcoming physician or
           respiratory therapist appointments (patient activation). The interaction will occur
           during supervised &quot;in-person&quot; sessions (two sessions at day 1 and day 7) and also
           telephone-based conversations through the IVR system (once a week for one month followed
           by telephone calls on a fortnightly basis). Additionally, they will help the patient
           navigate the delivery system and effect better care coordination through the IVR system
           at patient-initiated request.

        2. Usual care description: All participants will receive usual care following initiation of
           CPAP therapy. Usual care of the newly diagnosed patient with OSA consists of attending a
           CPAP initiation and education class which is conducted either at the patient's home or
           in the offices of a home care (DME) company by a dedicated respiratory therapist.
           Patients are educated about the basics of the care and operation of the device, mask and
           related equipment. Following this CPAP initiation and education class, they receive
           instructions to either mail-in the CPAP adherence monitoring card (&quot;Smart card&quot;) by mail
           to the therapist about 4 weeks following the initial visit. The adherence information is
           evaluated and posted in electronic medical records. Patients with OSA will be seen in
           the sleep clinic at 1 and 3 months following initiation of CPAP therapy and will have
           the option to call any of their care providers. In order to balance the number of
           contacts and educational sessions between the two comparison groups, educational
           brochures (from the AASM) and videos on DVD (from Industry stakeholders) will be mailed
           to participants. We did not incorporate an attention-control arm requiring in-person
           contacts as the comparator because the overarching goal of this proposal is to make this
           study relevant to the real-world conditions of a well measured usual care arm to make
           the study findings generalizable and better inform patients' decision-making. Such
           external validity was felt to be of greater value than comparing two conditions that
           currently do not exist in current practice.

      Peer-buddy system: Selection and Training of Peer-buddies: Fifty peer-buddies will be
      recruited from the four sleep clinics who are adherent to CPAP therapy. Peer buddies will be
      consented and compensated for their role in the research study ($350 for 6 month
      participation per subject). Each buddy may be paired with up to 12 subjects over the length
      of the study.

      Training: PI and research staff will educate the peer buddy and provide them with guidelines
      for their interactions with the research participants. They will be instructed to share their
      experiences and not to provide medical advice. The sharing of coping strategies will fall
      under the following categories:

      (i) Promote self efficacy: Strategies to deal with CPAP device and equipment (such as
      pressure ramp feature, humidifier settings, mask and strap application; and cleaning of
      device and related equipment). (ii) Promote outcome expectancies: Share their positive
      experiences with regards to effects of CPAP on energy level or vigilance, sense of
      well-being, hypertension control and other medical benefits that they possibly derived from
      CPAP therapy. (iii) Risk perception: Share their knowledge of perceived vulnerabilities due
      to untreated sleep apnea. Share methods for improving efficacy of CPAP equipment and
      interface (patient education). (iv) Patient activation: Share experiences of how to prepare
      for upcoming physician or respiratory therapist appointments, such as what questions to ask
      the healthcare provider, what to take with them (e.g., CPAP adherence card or malfunctioning
      device, humidifier, or mask, and what to expect at a given provider visit. At the end of the
      training, a mock interaction between the peer-buddy and PI (playing the role of the patient
      with OSA) will be undertaken before &quot;certifying&quot; or &quot;graduating&quot; the peer-buddy as competent.

      Potential for inter-personal conflicts and management plan: The peer-buddy and research
      participant will be informed that they can withdraw from participation if there is a
      potential conflict or difficult situation (they feel threatened, face verbal abuse from
      subject, individual is too demanding, frequent calls or late night calls). The peer-buddy and
      subject starting CPAP will provide the research coordinator with an availability sheet as to
      when they are available to take phone calls and/or appear in person. Each peer-buddy will be
      paired up with one research participant, and may choose to take on up to 3 patients at a time
      and take on a new assignment at the end of the 6-month participation period. Peer-buddy and
      participant will be matched by age, gender, race, ethnicity, and socioeconomic status. The
      peer-buddies will be instructed not to offer medical advice. If a medical need or problem
      were to arise, the peer-buddies will be instructed to provide the research participant with
      the phone number to call the PI (via call operator) who will assess their medical needs and
      situation.

      Fidelity assessments: Twenty percent of the telephonic communications between the peer-buddy
      and patient will be randomly recorded by IVR system for fidelity assessments by the
      behavioral therapist (Haynes, Co-investigator). Similarly, 20% of in-person visits will be
      assessed by the behavioral therapist. Such fidelity assessments will be used to increase
      fidelity (efficacy) during study.

      In-person interactions: In-person interaction will occur on 2 occasions (30-minutes each)
      within the first 10 days of CPAP initiation. The research coordinator will be present during
      this interaction but will not be facilitating or running the interaction. A clean CPAP device
      and related supplies for the patient will need to be present during these interactions for
      demonstration purposes.

      Telephonic IVR interactions: Once a week for the first month followed by 4 phone
      conversations over the subsequent 2 month period (8 scheduled telephonic interactions) and as
      needed in the subsequent 3 months. There will be no more than 10 such &quot;as-needed&quot; phone calls
      in the latter 3-months between participant and peer-buddy. Therefore, over the 6-months,
      there will not be in excess of 18 phone calls per subject assigned to peer-buddy. Each phone
      conversation will last a maximum of 30 minutes. The PDI-IVR system will be programmed to
      recognize the peer-buddy's phones (cell or home) and be programmed to link this with the
      patient's phones (cell or home) and thereby protect the privacy of both participants. The
      dyad of the peer-buddy and participant will introduce themselves on a first name basis and
      will not be required to provide other personal information. However, the study does not
      preclude them from sharing such information or developing long-lasting friendships. For each
      dyad, the research coordinator may monitor a few calls (with the participants' knowledge and
      random IVR-based recording) in order to monitor the content and level of participation
      between the dyad; however, the coordinators will not direct the participation in any way.
      Peer-buddies will share their experiences that would promote self-efficacy, outcome
      expectations, risk perception and patient activation. During in-person interactions, greater
      emphasis on promotion of self-efficacy will be placed, considering the physicality of the
      medical device (CPAP) therapy, masks, hoses, humidifiers, and filters. During phone
      interactions, greater emphasis on promotion of outcome expectancies, risk perception, and
      patient activation will be undertaken. The research coordinators may provide feedback to the
      peer-buddy regarding their performance and remind them to cover topics that were not covered
      in order to ensure fidelity. Either the patient or the peer-buddy (on behalf of the patient)
      can initiate calls to other members of the inter-disciplinary team, including obtaining CPAP
      adherence data through the IVR that was derived from the industry server (figure 2). Call
      backs from any of the providers (physician, RT, RN, DME representative, or sleep tech) will
      be connected back to the initiator of the call (Patient or peer-buddy). IVR-initiated queries
      regarding CPAP device - for adherence, leak, and efficacy [residual obstructive events] data
      - will be faxed to the sleep physician's office (or designee [RN or RT]) by the IVR with a
      note for patient call back. Content of interactions will pertain to OSA and CPAP therapy and
      related supplies (mask, hose, filters and humidifier). Content will include aspects
      pertaining to mask fitting, using ramp function on CPAP unit, using the CPAP humidification
      system, etc. Conversations regarding erectile dysfunction or a similar sensitive matter will
      be discouraged. Both peer-buddy and subject would have provided voluntary consent for sharing
      their experiences with CPAP therapy and sleep apnea. A checklist of content areas will be
      provided to the peer-buddy to ensure that such topical areas were discussed by the
      peer-subject pair. We will refrain from writing a script for the peer-buddy as we believe
      that would detract from the sense of bond or trust within the dyad.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient rating of sleep-specific services (Usual Care, Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will rate their global satisfaction of how satisfied they are with the care received from their sleep physician and sleep center on a 5-point scale: very satisfied, satisfied, neutral, dissatisfied, very dissatisfied</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Assessment of Care for Chronic Conditions (PACIC) ( Usual Care, Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Derived from AHRQ care coordination measures atlas, measures care that is patient-centered, includes collaborative goal setting; problem-solving and follow-up support within the past 6 months and consists of five sub scales addressing the patient activation, delivery system design, goal setting, problem solving, and follow-up/coordination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Client perception of care coordination (CPCQ) (Usual Care, Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>A measure of coordination of health care from the AHRQ care coordination measures atlas that is useful for assessment and program evaluation of individual and provider units as well as research into patient experience and measurement of patient-focused care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Consumer Assessment of Health Plans Survey (CAHPS v4.0) item (Usual Care, Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Health plan member's satisfaction with care on 0 to 10 scale (0 is the &quot;worst &quot; and 10 is the &quot;best health plan possible&quot;)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CPAP Adherence downloads (Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 30, Day 90, Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>All CPAP devices have internal adherence monitoring which can be downloaded using a computer cable, smart card, SD chip or wireless transmission. The objective, adherence information as 'mask-on' time for 6 months, number of nights used, cumulative hours used, average hours of CPAP use per night, and average number of hours per day of CPAP use will be derived. The proportion of days in which CPAP use was at least 4 hr (Medicare criterion) will also be utilized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Activation Measure (PAM) (Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 90, Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Activation Measure (PAM) is a 22-item measure that assesses patient knowledge, skill, and confidence for self-management</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-efficacy measure for sleep apnea (SEMSA) ( Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 90, Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>SEMSA is a tool with strong psychometric properties and has the potential for identifying patient perceptions that may indicate those most likely to not adhere to treatment. There are 3 domains that contribute to global score: (a) Measure of perceived risk is rated on a 4-point scale ranging from very low to very high. (b) Outcome expectancies are surveyed by a 4-point scale seeking responses (ranging from not at all true to very true) to statements of potential general outcomes if CPAP is or was not used. (c) Self-efficacy, or the volition to use CPAP therapy, is evaluated by asking the respondent to rate on a 4-point scale the level of validity (ranging from 'not at all true' to 'very true') of statements regarding their confidence in using CPAP.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Outcomes of Sleep Questionnaire (FOSQ) ( Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 90, Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>A condition-specific functional status measure designed to evaluate the impact of disorders of excessive sleepiness on activities of daily living. Lower global scores are associated with greater dysfunction. FOSQ has good to excellent test-retest reproducibility, internal consistency, with discriminate validity between those seeking medical attention for sleep disorders compared to normal subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychomotor vigilance task (PVT) (Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 90, Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>PVT is a &quot;video game&quot; measure of an individual's (vigilance) readiness to detect and respond to certain specified small changes in a labile environment, conceptualized pragmatically within a visio-reactive framework. Essentially, a stop clock is set at zero and begins to suddenly and spontaneously run at various time points in multiple (5) trials. As soon as the subject notices the clock start to run, they click a button that registers their reaction time. The average reaction time to such multiple runs is calculated as a inverse function of the subjects' reaction time. A practice session is afforded before the real test is administered. This takes 5 minutes time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic and diastolic blood pressure (Peer buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 90, Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>measured by experienced staff following international guidelines.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Epworth sleepiness questionnaire ( Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 90, Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>A measure of sleepiness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Driving Questionnaire (Usual Care, Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire regarding driving habits for patients with sleep apnea. If a motor vehicle accident was reported will need to provide documentation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Mass Index (BMI) (Usual Care, Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>A measure of body fat based on height and weight.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Ratings Survey (Usual Care, Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction survey of care delivery compared between intervention and usual care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Re-admission (Usual Care, Peer Buddy System)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 90, Day 180</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor hospital re-admission in both intervention and usual care arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">362</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard CPAP educational training
Educational Brochures
Educational DVD videos mailed to participant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peer-Buddy System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two 30-minute in person sessions with Peer Buddy
Standard CPAP training
Eight phone conversations with Peer Buddy over 3 months
Subsequent 3 months use of phone system to contact Peer Buddy as needed
One Month Visit:
-Home visit to collect CPAP information
Three Month Visit:
Questionnaires
Psycho Motor Vigilance Test (PVT) &quot;Video Game&quot;
Collect CPAP information
Measure weight
Measure blood pressure
Six Month Visit:
Questionnaires
PVT (Video game)
Collect CPAP information
Measure Weight
Measure Blood Pressure
Evaluate the program and Peer Buddy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>- Standard CPAP educational training</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peer-Buddy System</intervention_name>
    <description>Two 30-minute in person sessions with Peer Buddy
Standard CPAP educational training
Eight phone conversations with Peer Buddy over 3 months
Subsequent 3 months use of phone system to contact Peer Buddy as needed
One Month Visit:
- Home visit to collect CPAP information
Three Month Visit:
Questionnaires
Psycho Motor Vigilance Test (PVT) &quot;Video Game&quot;
Collect CPAP information
Measure weight
Measure blood pressure
Six Month Visit:
Questionnaires
PVT (Video game)
Collect CPAP information
Measure Weight
Measure Blood Pressure
Evaluate the program and Peer Buddy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peer-Buddy System</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Peer-Driven Intervention</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>- Educational Brochures</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>- Educational DVD videos mailed to participant</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria for Subject:

          -  Obstructive Sleep Apnea

          -  18-85 years of age

          -  Availability of cell or other reliable phone line

        Inclusion Criteria for Peer Buddy:

          -  Adherent to CPAP therapy ( greater than 4 hours per night of CPAP use)

          -  Willing to meet with subject on 2 occasions in-person

          -  Has a cell or other reliable telephone line and able to converse with subject on 8
             occasions over the first 3 months and be available subsequently for a 3 month period
             on an as-needed basis

          -  Willing to undergo 2 training and orientation sessions with the Principal Investigator
             and research staff followed by a mock patient interaction session.

        Exclusion Criteria for Subject:

          -  Central sleep apnea

          -  Participation in another intervention-based research study

          -  Patient's primary care provider refuses patient participation for medical instability

        Exclusion Criteria for Peer Buddy:

          -  Central sleep apnea

          -  Participation in another intervention-based research study

          -  Patient's primary care provider refuses patient participation for medical instability

          -  Patients suffering from major depression or other major psychiatric illness

          -  Shift-worker or frequent out of town traveler

          -  Unwilling to participate in orientation and training session or unable to &quot;graduate&quot;
             from the mock patient interaction session with study staff
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sairam Parthasarathy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arizona</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arizona Center for Sleep Disorders</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tucson</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85724</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parthasarathy S, Wendel C, Haynes PL, Atwood C, Kuna S. A pilot study of CPAP adherence promotion by peer buddies with sleep apnea. J Clin Sleep Med. 2013 Jun 15;9(6):543-50. doi: 10.5664/jcsm.2744.</citation>
    <PMID>23772186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 3, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 5, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Peer-driven intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Interactive voice response system</keyword>
  <keyword>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure therapy and adherence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>July 6, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>August 3, 2017</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

