<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02057081</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D1106-R</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1I01RX001106</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02057081</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multifamily Group to Reduce Marital Conflict and Disability in Veterans With mTBI</brief_title>
  <acronym>MFG-mTBI</acronym>
  <official_title>Multifamily Group to Reduce Marital Conflict and Disability in Veterans With mTBI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project addresses the rehabilitation and mental health needs of married combat Veterans
      post-deployed from Iraq or Afghanistan with a mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI) by providing
      psychoeducation, communication and problem solving skills in a multifamily group (MFG)
      setting. In this group, Veterans and spouses/cohabiting partners learn customized therapeutic
      strategies to help compensate for mTBI deficits and promote Veteran community integration,
      interpersonal and emotion regulation skills, and marital satisfaction. The effectiveness of
      the skills-based MFG will be compared to that of a health education group which offers a
      supportive environment and basic education without skills training through a randomized
      clinical trial. As there is currently no family-based intervention for Operation Enduring
      Freedom/Operation Iraqi Freedom (OEF/OIF) Veterans with mTBI offered within the VA spectrum
      of services, this intervention fills a crucial gap in healthcare for our newest Veterans.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI), an injury or concussion associated with brief loss of
      consciousness or altered mental state, has affected as many as 35% of soldiers wounded during
      recent military actions in Iraq and Afghanistan. Up to 30% of those injured report persistent
      somatic, emotional and cognitive post-concussive symptoms (PCS) which may adversely impact
      family life and community re-integration. Marital conflict and intimate partner violence,
      reported by 54% of OEF/OIF couples, and co-occurring mental health problems may exacerbate
      cognitive dysfunction and delay rehabilitation. A key contributor to marital conflict is a
      lack of knowledge about the Veteran's condition and the skills needed to help him compensate
      for common deficits in memory and planning which create challenges in household management.
      Despite a growing evidence base for couples treatment for PTSD, there is no established
      family-based treatment for OEF/OIF Veterans with mTBI, creating a critical research and
      services gap. The proposed research aims to fill this gap by evaluating a novel form of
      multi-family group treatment designed to improve community integration (CI) among
      married/cohabiting OEF/OIF Veterans with mTBI and/or significant posttraumatic stress (PTS)
      or combat-related stress (CS) by training spouse/partners to aid with rehabilitation and
      employing disability-adapted communication and problem-solving skills to reduce marital
      conflict and improve marital satisfaction.

      Veterans (N=150) with a positive Defense and Veterans Brain Injury Center (DVBIC) screen for
      mTBI sustained during the OEF/OIF era, confirmed by the VA Identification Clinical Interview
      and a Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) score 19 or if they either meet diagnostic
      criteria for PTSD or have trauma- or CS of at least moderate severity, as defined by either
      a) PTSD Checklist (PCL) score &gt;34 or b) Customer Effort Score (CES) score of &gt;23, will be
      randomized to receive either: 1) Multifamily Group for TBI for Couples (MFG-mTBI-C), a
      psychoeducational, rehabilitation and skills-building intervention consisting of a 2-session
      multifamily educational workshop providing information about TBI and 12 bi-monthly
      multifamily group meetings providing skills training in problem-solving and communication
      related to cognitive/emotional deficits; or 2) 14 bi-monthly multifamily group sessions
      delivering health education without skills training. Both treatments will be preceded by 2-3
      individual couples sessions. Participants will be assessed pre- and post-treatment and 6
      months post-treatment. Data will be analyzed using an intent-to-treat analysis with paired
      comparisons between treatment groups on primary (Veteran CI, caregiver burden) and secondary
      (anger management, use of social supports) outcome variables using mixed effects regression
      models. It is hypothesized that: 1) Veterans treated with MFG-mTBI-C will show improved CI,
      anger management and use of social support, and spouse/partners will show reduced burden
      compared with those treated in the health education group; 2) that improvement in CI will be
      mediated by improvement in marital satisfaction and Veteran anger management and social
      support; 3) that Veterans with more intact cognitive functioning at baseline will show
      greater improvement in CI, anger management, social support and marital satisfaction. If
      efficacious, MFG-mTBI-C has the potential to assist Veterans with mTBI and their partners
      throughout the VA Health Care System.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 9, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in The Computer Adaptive Test version of the Community Reintegration of Injured Service Members (CRIS-CAT)</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-treatment in study month 5, post-treatment in study month 38 after 12 bimonthly sessions, and 6-months post-treatment in study month 44</time_frame>
    <description>The CRIS assesses community reintegration through the assessment of participation in life roles. Items on the CRIS cover 9 aspects of participation: 1) Learning and Applying Knowledge, 2) General Tasks and Demands, 3) Communication, 4) Mobility, 5) Self-care, 6) Domestic Life, 7) Interpersonal Relationships, 8) Major Life Areas, and 9) Community, Social, and Civic Life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Burden Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-treatment in study month 5, post-treatment in study month 38 after 12 bimonthly sessions, and 6-months post-treatment in study month 44</time_frame>
    <description>A 24-item scale that will evaluate caregiver burden in four areas: physical, social, emotional and time dependence burden.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <condition>Posttraumatic Stress Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intensive 12-session psychoeducational rehabilitation and skills-building intervention for couples.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Didactic 14-session educational group intervention for families.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epigenetic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Optional blood draw at Bronx site only to investigate epigenetic biomarkers of treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multifamily Group for mTBI for Couples</intervention_name>
    <description>MFG-mTBI-C uses a structured problem-solving and skills training approach to provide Veterans and partners with tools and information to improve coping and help couples reconnect through positive behavioral exchanges.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MFG-mTBI-C</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group Health Education (GHE)</intervention_name>
    <description>GHE is a 14-session, highly structured educational intervention providing general information on health problems that are common among the general OEF/OIF cohort including sleep and sleep problems, physical activity and exercise, and alcohol and drug use, as well as guidelines for improving health behavior in these areas.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GHE</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Eligible Veterans must have a diagnosis of mTBI in accordance with the VA/DoD Clinical
        Practice Guideline for Management of Concussion/Mild Traumatic Brain Injury: injury or
        concussion associated with at least one of the following: brief (&lt; 30 minutes) loss of
        consciousness or altered state of consciousness or post-traumatic amnesia for &lt; 24 hours
        following the injury, or they either meet diagnostic criteria for PTSD based on the MINI or
        have trauma- or CS of at least moderate severity, as defined by either: a) PCL score &gt;34;
        or b) CES score of &gt;23.

          -  The TBI must be either blast-related or attributable to another discrete event (e.g.,
             fall, fight, injury) sustained during deployment in the OEF/OIF era.

          -  Post-concussive symptoms (e.g., sleep or memory problems, headache) must not be
             attributable to a subsequent injury or other pre-existing or concurrent neurologic
             disorder:

          -  Eligible Veterans must also have a consenting, qualifying spouse/cohabiting partner
             and a Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) (Nasreddine,2005) score 19.

          -  The 30-item MoCA screens for impairment in specific areas of cognitive functioning
             deemed necessary for participation in a 90-minute, structured group including
             attention and concentration, executive functions, language and conceptual thinking.

          -  We have specified a MoCA cut-off at the lower end of the range for mild cognitive
             dysfunction (19), in order to exclude Veterans with severe memory and/or other
             cognitive deficits, while admitting those with more mild deficits, as these represent
             our target population, i.e. Veterans with a history of mTBI.

        Inclusion criteria-partners: Legally married to or co-residing with Veteran for at least 6
        months, with no plans for divorce or separation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Exclusion criteria for Veterans and partners are:

          -  a lifetime diagnosis of a major psychiatric disorder (schizophrenia, schizoaffective
             or bipolar disorder with psychotic features) or active psychosis based on the
             Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV-TR (SCID-L) (First et al., 2007).

          -  alcohol or drug abuse or dependence with past 6 months defined by a Short Michigan
             Alcoholism Screening Test (SMAST) (Selzer, 1975) 3, based on the recommended cut-off
             for TBI survivors (Gentilello et al.,1995) or a Drug Abuse Screening Test-10 (DAST-10)
             (Skinner, 1982) 3.

          -  &quot;severe&quot; inter-partner violence as defined by the revised 20-item Conflict Tactics
             Scale Short Form (CTS2S) (Straus &amp; Douglas, 2004).

          -  a suicide attempt within the past 6 months (aborted and interrupted attempts) as
             assessed by the Columbia Suicide Severity Rating scale (C-SSRS).

          -  medical condition or life event (e.g., ongoing or pending legal action in another
             state) that would compromise participation.

          -  participation of either the caregiver or Veteran in another psychosocial intervention
             trial or couples' treatment six months prior to or during study or follow-up.
             Participation in individual psychotherapy and pharmacotherapy are permitted: use of
             and starting/stopping these services will be tracked. Participants will be screened
             for inclusion/exclusion as described above immediately after giving consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy Lynne Drapalski, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baltimore VA Medical Center VA Maryland Health Care System, Baltimore, MD</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baltimore VA Medical Center VA Maryland Health Care System, Baltimore, MD</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>James J. Peters VA Medical Center, Bronx, NY</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10468</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Manhattan Campus of the VA NY Harbor Healthcare System, New York, NY</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 22, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 6, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stress Disorders, Post-traumatic</keyword>
  <keyword>Mild Traumatic Brain Injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Veterans Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Veterans</keyword>
  <keyword>Spouses</keyword>
  <keyword>Couples</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychotherapy, Group</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Couples Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Family Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <keyword>posttraumatic stress disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Concussion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

