<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02059850</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2720.00</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-02464</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2720.00</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>K23CA175167</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02059850</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NY-ESO-1 Specific T Cells After Cyclophosphamide in Treating Patients With Advanced Synovial Sarcoma or Myxoid/Round Cell Liposarcoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Determine the Feasibility of Treating Synovial Sarcoma and Myxoid/Round Cell Liposarcoma Using Autologous NY-ESO-1 Specific CD8+ T Cells With Cyclophosphamide Pre-conditioning But Without the Use of IL-2</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best way to give NY-ESO-1 specific T cells
      after cyclophosphamide in treating patients with advanced synovial sarcoma or myxoid/round
      cell liposarcoma. Placing a gene that has been created in the laboratory into white blood
      cells may make the body build an immune response to kill tumor cells. Drugs used in
      chemotherapy, such as cyclophosphamide, work in different ways to stop the growth of cancer
      cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. Giving NY-ESO-1
      specific T cells with cyclophosphamide may kill more tumor cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To confirm the safety and efficacy of cancer-testis antigen (NY-ESO-1) specific T cells
      (autologous NY-ESO-1-specific cluster of differentiation [CD]8-positive T lymphocytes) in
      patients with advanced synovial sarcoma and myxoid/round cell liposarcoma following
      conditioning with high dose cyclophosphamide.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To confirm the persistence of NY-ESO-1 tetramer positive cells in the peripheral blood at
      10 weeks after T cell infusion for synovial sarcoma and myxoid/round cell liposarcoma
      patients receiving NY-ESO-1 specific T cells following cyclophosphamide conditioning but not
      post-infusion interleukin (IL)-2.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive cyclophosphamide intravenously (IV) on days -3 and -2 and NY-ESO-1 specific
      T cells IV over 60 minutes on day 0. Patients may receive additional infusions at the
      discretion of the Principal Investigator (PI).

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for up to 12 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of grade III or greater toxicity graded according to National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The type and grade of toxicities noted during therapy will be summarized for each dose level. All adverse events noted by the investigator will be tabulated according to the affected body system. Descriptive statistics will be used to summarize changes from baseline in clinical laboratory parameters.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistence of tetramer positive T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The standard deviation and variance will be determined.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistence of tetramer positive T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>At 10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The standard deviation and variance will be determined.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Synovial Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Myxoid/Round Cell Liposarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Adult Soft Tissue Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Adult Soft Tissue Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Adult Soft Tissue Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cyclophosphamide, NY-ESO-1 specific T cells)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive cyclophosphamide IV on days -3 and -2 and NY-ESO-1 specific T cells IV over 60 minutes on day 0. Patients may receive additional infusions at the discretion of the PI.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autologous NY-ESO-1-specific CD8-positive T Lymphocytes</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cyclophosphamide, NY-ESO-1 specific T cells)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cyclophosphamide, NY-ESO-1 specific T cells)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (cyclophosphamide, NY-ESO-1 specific T cells)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        INCLUSION CRITERIA FOR SCREENING:

          -  Medical history including histopathological documentation of sarcoma

          -  Informed consent and Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA)
             signing

        CRITERIA FOR LEUKAPHERESIS:

          -  NY-ESO-1 expression in tumor by immunohistochemistry (IHC) is not required prior to
             screening consent; however, patients must have NY-ESO-1 expression to proceed with the
             leukapheresis; additionally patients must also meet the following criteria to proceed
             with leukapheresis (any exceptions to this will require prior approval by the
             Apheresis director and Principal Investigator):

          -  Physical exam and Karnofsky performance status

          -  Laboratory evaluation:

          -  Complete blood count (CBC), differential and platelet count

          -  Basic metabolic and hepatic function panels

          -  Puget Sound Blood Center Recipient Donor Battery Panel

          -  Pregnancy test for females of child-bearing potential

          -  Pulse &gt; 45 and &lt; 120

          -  Weight &gt;= 45 kg

          -  Temperature =&lt; 38 Celsius (C) (=&lt; 100.4 Fahrenheit [F])

          -  White blood cell (WBC) &gt;= 2,000

          -  Hematocrit (HCT) &gt;= 30%

          -  Platelets &gt;= 75,000

          -  Research blood including 40 mL of blood in a heparinized tube for peripheral blood
             mononuclear cell (PBMC) collection and 10 mL of blood for serum collection (generally
             in a red top tube) within 30 days of leukapheresis collection

        INCLUSION CRITERIA FOR TREATMENT:

          -  A diagnosis of synovial sarcoma or myxoid/round cell liposarcoma

          -  Patients must have &quot;advanced disease&quot;; usually, this will mean metastatic disease;
             this may also be multiply recurrent disease or locally advanced disease; locally
             advanced disease is defined for this study as disease where a mutilating surgery is
             required and the patient is more likely than not to die of their disease despite an
             aggressive operation; patients with metastatic disease that has been resected or
             radiated are allowed to participate; Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors
             (RECIST) evaluable disease is not necessary for participation

          -  NY-ESO-1 positive by IHC (for this study, even a small level of positivity is
             acceptable); for patients with &lt; 5% NY-ESO-1 by IHC positivity, the level of staining
             should be discussed with the patient and they should be informed that this will likely
             effect the efficacy of the therapy; this conversation must be documented in the
             patient's medical chart

          -  Human leukocyte antigen (HLA)-A0201 or HLA-A2402

          -  Zubrod performance status of '0-1'

          -  All patients must have an electrocardiogram (ECG) within 2 weeks of starting
             conditioning

          -  All patients must have a stress test within 6 months of starting treatment showing no
             evidence of cardiac ischemia

          -  All patients must have an echo or multi gated acquisition scan (MUGA) scan showing
             ejection fraction (EF) &gt; 50% and normal troponin and creatine kinase (CK) myoglobin
             binding (MB) (echo may be done at the time of stress test as a stress echo); within 6
             months of starting treatment; however if the patient has received cardiotoxic
             chemotherapy such as Adriamycin, they must have had an echo or MUGA scan since
             completing this treatment

          -  If there is a patient with an NY-ESO-1 expressing soft tissue sarcoma who would be
             otherwise eligible for the trial, which is either not synovial sarcoma (SS) or
             myxoid/round cell liposarcoma (MRCL) or there is controversy about the diagnosis,
             eligibility will be decided by the PI

          -  Patients must have NY-ESO-1 specific cells already produced or in production; these
             cells may be either in the process of their final expansion (for fresh infusion) or
             expanded and frozen at the time of enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients for whom we are unable to generate NY-ESO-1 specific cells

          -  Pregnant women, nursing women, and men and women of reproductive ability who are
             unwilling to use effective contraception or abstinence; women of childbearing
             potential must have a negative pregnancy test within two weeks prior to study entry

          -  Serum creatinine &gt; 1.6 mg/dL or glomerular filtration rate &lt; 50

          -  Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) &gt; 150 IU or &gt; 3 x upper limit of normal

          -  Bilirubin &gt; 1.6 mg/dL

          -  Prothrombin time &gt; 1.5 x control

          -  Active symptomatic congestive heart failure

          -  Clinically significant hypotension (systolic blood pressure [SBP] &lt; 80 mm HG or
             symptomatic)

          -  Newly diagnosed cardiac arrhythmia; patients with an arrhythmia that has been stable
             for at least 6 months will be allowed to participate

          -  Known untreated central nervous system (CNS) metastasis; patients with CNS metastasis
             will be allowed on study once treated

          -  Patients with active systemic infections requiring antibiotics or chronic
             maintenance/suppressive therapy; once the infection in question has resolved and
             patient is off antimicrobial treatment, patients may participate

          -  Systemic anticancer treatments (including chemotherapy and biologics) less than 3
             weeks prior to T cell therapy; locally directed therapy (e.g. radiation) 2 weeks prior
             to cell infusion

          -  Known clinically significant autoimmune disorders requiring systemic immunosuppression
             for control

          -  Patients who are known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive are not
             eligible for this study

          -  Current treatment with steroids

          -  Known infection with hepatitis B virus (HBV) and hepatitis C virus (HCV); (if a
             patient was not tested at the time of their leukapheresis, they must be tested prior
             to receiving T cell infusion; if testing was done for leukapheresis, this is adequate
             and does not need to be repeated)

          -  Patients with a known history of proven myocarditis, pericarditis, and/ or
             endocarditis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Seth Pollack</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 11, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 1, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 1, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma, Synovial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

