<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02058706</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-083</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00212</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1311012529</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-083</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA022453</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02058706</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LHRH Analogue Therapy With Enzalutamide or Bicalutamide in Treating Patients With Metastatic Hormone Sensitive Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Phase II Screening Trial of Enzalutamide/MDV-3100 and LHRH Analogue vs Combined Androgen Deprivation (LHRH Analogue + Bicalutamide) in Metastatic Hormone Sensitive Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase II trial studies if enzalutamide added to standard luteinizing
      hormone-releasing hormone (LHRH) analogue therapy will improve effects against prostate
      cancer compared to the standard therapy of LHRH analogue and bicalutamide. Hormone therapies
      stop the body from producing or block the effect of male sex hormones (testosterone).
      Enzalutamide blocks the effect of male sex hormones which are responsible for the growth of
      prostate cancer. Hormonal therapies that lower the level of testosterone are among the most
      effective treatments for prostate cancer that have spread to other areas of the body
      (metastasized). It is not yet known whether LHRH analogue therapy with bicalutamide is more
      effective than LHRH analogue therapy with enzalutamide in treating prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To compare the rates of achieving prostate-specific antigen (PSA) remission at month 7
      with LHRH analogue therapy and enzalutamide (Arm A) with that achieved with LHRH analogue and
      bicalutamide (Arm B) in metastatic hormone sensitive prostate cancer.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To compare the primary endpoint by race. II. To compare the rates of each of 2 types of
      response by treatment arm: measurable disease response; and PSA response.

      III. To compare each of 7 time-to-event endpoints by treatment arm: duration of overall
      response (RD); duration of stable disease (SDD); time to treatment failure (TTF);
      time-to-progression (TTP); TTP in patients with bone metastases; progression-free survival
      (PFS); and overall survival (OS).

      IV. To compare the rates of each type of toxicity by treatment arm. V. To compare the
      incidence rate of skeletal related events (SRE), and the time until SRE, separately by
      treatment arm.

      VI. To compare the rates of circulating tumor cell (CTC) response by treatment arm.

      VIII. To explore the molecular mechanisms within the androgen receptor pathway by determining
      the levels of chemokine (C-X-C motif) receptor 4 (CXCR4) and transmembrane protease, serine 2
      (TMPRSS2)-v-ets avian erythroblastosis virus E26 oncogene homolog (ERG) expression, androgen
      metabolism enzymes; androgen receptor variants, and length of cytosine-adenine-guanine (CAG)
      repeats within the androgen receptor gene, and to associate them with the primary endpoint.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

      ARM A: Patients receive enzalutamide orally (PO) once daily (QD) and undergo orchiectomy or
      receive LHRH analogue therapy (leuprolide acetate, goserelin acetate, or any other Food and
      Drug Administration [FDA] approved preparation). Treatment continues in the absence of
      disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM B: Patients receive bicalutamide PO QD and undergo orchiectomy or receive LHRH analogue
      therapy as in Arm A. Treatment continues in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Achievement of PSA remission assessed using the Prostate Cancer Clinical Trials Working Group (PCWG2) criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 7</time_frame>
    <description>The binary endpoint (yes/no) will be summarized with its point estimate (an occurrence rate), and 2-sided Wilson type 95% confidence interval (CI). PSA response rates will be compared by treatment arm in a stratified logistic regression model.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Achievement of measurable disease assessed using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized with point estimates (occurrence rates), and 2-sided Wilson type 95% CIs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Achievement of PSA response assessed using PCWG2 criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized with point estimates (occurrence rates), and 2-sided Wilson type 95% CIs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of RD</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time measurement criteria are met for complete response/partial response (whichever is first recorded) until the first date that recurrent or progressive disease is objectively documented, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated with standard Kaplan-Meier (K-M) methodology. Point and CI estimates of the median and various time point-specific rates will be derived from the K-M life table. The censored K-M distributions will be compared with the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of SDD</measure>
    <time_frame>From the start of the treatment until the criteria for progression are met, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated with standard K-M methodology. Point and CI estimates of the median and various time point-specific rates will be derived from the K-M life table. The censored K-M distributions will be compared with the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TTF</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration to date of progressive disease or date patient is taken off study for any reason, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated with standard K-M methodology. Point and CI estimates of the median and various time point-specific rates will be derived from the K-M life table. The censored K-M distributions will be compared with the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TTP</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration to date of progressive disease defined as either progression of measurable disease by RECIST criteria, progression of bone metastases, or occurrence of new SRE, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated with standard K-M methodology. Point and CI estimates of the median and various time point-specific rates will be derived from the K-M life table. The censored K-M distributions will be compared with the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TTP in patients with bone metastases</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration to date of progressive disease defined as either the appearance of a minimum of 2 new lesions on bone scan which are related to metastatic disease or the occurrence of a new SRE, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated with standard K-M methodology. Point and CI estimates of the median and various time point-specific rates will be derived from the K-M life table. The censored K-M distributions will be compared with the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>From registration to PSA progression defined by PCWG II criteria or measurable disease by RECIST 1.1, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated with standard K-M methodology. Point and CI estimates of the median and various time point-specific rates will be derived from the K-M life table. The censored K-M distributions will be compared with the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OS</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration to death or last follow up, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated with standard K-M methodology. Point and CI estimates of the median and various time point-specific rates will be derived from the K-M life table. The censored K-M distributions will be compared with the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence rate of toxicity, graded per the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The occurrence rate of each specific type of toxicity observed will be summarized with point estimates (occurrence rates), and 2-sided Wilson type 95% CIs. The grade and each type of toxicity (an ordinal variable) will be summarized with 1-way frequency distributions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence rate of SRE</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized with point estimates (occurrence rates), and 2-sided Wilson type 95% CIs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distribution of time until SRE</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated with standard K-M methodology. Point and CI estimates of the median and various time point-specific rates will be derived from the K-M life table. The censored K-M distributions will be compared with the log-rank test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence rate of CTC response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to month 1</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized with point estimates (occurrence rates), and 2-sided Wilson type 95% CIs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Expression levels of the selected biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to month 1</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized with descriptive statistics including the point estimate of the mean, its associated 95% CI (or 90% CI, depending on N), median, interquartile range (IQR), standard deviation, minimum, and maximum. The association of correlative markers with achievement of PSA remission at month 7 will be explored using exact logistic regression models.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Length of CAG repeats</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to month 1</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized with descriptive statistics including the point estimate of the mean, its associated 95% CI (or 90% CI, depending on N), median, IQR, standard deviation, minimum, and maximum. The association of correlative markers with achievement of PSA remission at month 7 will be explored using exact logistic regression models.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">92</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma of the Prostate</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (enzalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive enzalutamide orally PO QD and undergo orchiectomy or receive LHRH analogue therapy (leuprolide acetate, goserelin acetate, or any other FDA approved preparation). Treatment continues in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (bicalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive bicalutamide PO QD and undergo orchiectomy or receive LHRH analogue therapy as in Arm A. Treatment continues in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>enzalutamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (enzalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MDV3100</other_name>
    <other_name>selective androgen receptor modulator MDV3100</other_name>
    <other_name>XTANDI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bicalutamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (bicalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Casodex</other_name>
    <other_name>CDX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>orchiectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo orchiectomy or receive LHRH analogue therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (enzalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (bicalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>leuprolide acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo orchiectomy or receive LHRH analogue therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (enzalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (bicalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Enantone</other_name>
    <other_name>LEUP</other_name>
    <other_name>Lupron</other_name>
    <other_name>Lupron Depot</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>goserelin acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo orchiectomy or receive LHRH analogue therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (enzalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (bicalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ICI-118630</other_name>
    <other_name>ZDX</other_name>
    <other_name>Zoladex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (enzalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (bicalutamide and LHRH analogue therapy)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed prostate adenocarcinoma with metastasis either starting or
             recently started on LHRH analogue therapy. [Late induction permitted within 3 months
             of starting LHRH analogue therapy or antiandrogen]

          -  All patients who have not initiated hormone therapy (Early induction patients) must
             have elevated PSA ≥ 4 ng/ml within 28 days prior to registration. For late induction
             registrations, PSA must be ≥ 4 ng/ml prior to start of androgen deprivation therapy;
             either antiandrogen or LHRH analogue or GNRH antagonist .If patients are on
             antiandrogen, this will need to be discontinued for at least 7 days prior to
             registration.

          -  Patients with a history of prior neoadjuvant or adjuvant hormone therapy are eligible
             provided they have received twenty four or less months of hormone treatment (single or
             combination treatment, excluding orchiectomy). Both therapies (neoadjuvant/adjuvant
             hormone therapy) must have been discontinued at least 6 months prior to registration.
             This is intended to exclude patients who might have been rendered indirectly androgen
             insensitive.

          -  There must be no plans to receive concomitant chemotherapy, biological response
             modifiers, radiation therapy or hormonal therapy. Concomitant radiation therapy is
             allowed for the palliation of severe pain/neuropathic compression. Prior or
             concomitant use of megestrol acetate for the treatment of hot flashes is allowed.

          -  Patients must have a performance status of 0 - 2 by Zubrod Criteria.

          -  Patients must have recovered from any major infections and/or surgical procedures
             and,in the opinion of the investigator, not have significant active medical illness
             precluding protocol treatment or survival.

          -  No prior malignancy is allowed except for adequately treated basal cell (or squamous
             cell) skin cancer, superficial or in situ cancer of the bladder. For an invasive
             cancer the patients should be disease free for at least 3 years prior to enrollment on
             study.

          -  For all patients a bone scan must be performed within 60 days prior to registration
             for tumor assessment. CT scans (abdomen and pelvis) and chest x-ray are optional, but
             must be repeated if used for disease assessment. For late induction registrations,
             tumor assessment imaging showing metastatic disease must be available prior to start
             of androgen deprivation therapy.

          -  Age 18 or older and willing and able to provide informed consent.

          -  Willingness to swallow pills and no medical condition that would interfere with this.

          -  Male patient and his female partner who is of childbearing potential must use 2
             acceptable methods of birth control (one of which must include a condom as a barrier
             method of contraception) starting at screening and continuing throughout the study
             period and for 3 months after final study drug administration. Patients are also
             required to use a condom if having sex with a pregnant woman.

          -  Patient should agree to a tumor tissue biopsy prior to protocol enrollment. Post
             therapy biopsy is optional.

          -  Patients who are being treated with a GNRH antagonist should be willing to switch to a
             LHRH analogue after registration.

          -  Patients must have one of the following a) Low volume disease (defined as no visceral
             metastases and &lt; 4 bone metastases) or b) are not candidates for docetaxel based
             chemotherapy or 3) refused docetaxel chemotherapy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of seizure or any condition that may predispose to seizure (e.g., prior
             cortical stroke, significant brain trauma) at any time in the past. Also, history of
             loss of consciousness or transient ischemic attack within 12 months of Day 1 visit;

          -  Known or suspected brain metastasis or active leptomeningeal disease;

          -  Severe concurrent disease, infection, or co-morbidity that, in the judgment of the
             Investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for enrollment;

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1,000/μL, or platelet count &lt; 50,000/μL, or hemoglobin&lt;8
             g/dL) at the Screening visit.

          -  Total bilirubin, alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt;
             2.5 times the upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine &gt; 177 μmol/L (2 mg/dL)

          -  Clinically significant cardiovascular disease including: Myocardial infarction within
             6 months; Uncontrolled angina within 3 months; Congestive heart failure New York Heart
             Association (NYHA) class 3 or 4, or patients with history of congestive heart failure
             (NYHA) class 3 or 4 in the past, unless screening echocardiogram or multi-gated
             acquistion scan performed within 3 months results in a left ventricular ejection
             fraction that is greater or equal to 45%; History of clinically significant
             ventricular arrhythmias (e.g., ventricular tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation,
             torsades de pointes); History of Mobitz II second degree or third degree heart block
             without a permanent pacemaker in place; Hypotension as indicated by systolic blood
             pressure &lt; 86 millimeters of mercury (mmHg) at the Screening visit; Bradycardia as
             indicated by a heart rate of &lt; 50 beats per minute on the Screening ECG; Uncontrolled
             hypertension as indicated by systolic blood pressure &gt; 170 mmHg or diastolic blood
             pressure &gt; 105 mmHg

          -  Gastrointestinal disorder affecting absorption (e.g., gastrectomy, active peptic ulcer
             disease within last 3 months);

          -  Treatment with concurrent 5-α reductase inhibitors (finasteride, dutasteride),
             estrogens, and/or cyproterone

          -  Treatment with systemic biologic therapy for prostate cancer (other than approved bone
             targeted agents and GnRH-analogue therapy) or other agents with anti-tumor activity
             within 4 weeks of enrollment (Day 1 visit);

          -  History of prostate cancer progression on ketoconazole;

          -  Prior use, or participation in a clinical trial, of an investigational agent that
             blocks androgen synthesis (e.g., abiraterone acetate, TAK-700, TAK-683, TAK-448) or
             agents that block the androgen receptor (e.g.,ARN-509)

          -  Previous enzalutamide therapy;

          -  Use of an investigational agent within 2 weeks of enrollment (Day 1 visit);

          -  Use of herbal products that may have hormonal anti-prostate cancer activity and/or are
             known to decrease PSA levels (e.g., saw palmetto) or systemic corticosteroids greater
             than the equivalent of replacement steroids or &gt; equivalent of 10 mg of prednisone
             perday within 4 weeks of enrollment (Day 1 visit);

          -  Any condition or reason that, in the opinion of the Investigator, interferes with the
             ability of the patient to participate in the trial, which places the patient at undue
             risk, or complicates the interpretation of safety data.

          -  Prior chemotherapy for metastatic disease.

          -  &gt;30 days of antiandrogen therapy monotherapy without androgen deprivation therapy.

          -  Life expectancy of 6 months or less.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ulka Vaishampayan</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Henry Ford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 6, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 10, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Barbara Ann Karmanos Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ulka Vaishampayan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Androgens</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leuprolide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Goserelin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bicalutamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

