<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02054416</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PVB012013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02054416</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>External Compression Therapy for Secondary Prevention of Lower-Limb Loss and Cardiovascular Mortality</brief_title>
  <acronym>ArtAssist</acronym>
  <official_title>External Compression Therapy for Secondary Prevention of Lower-Limb Loss and Cardiovascular Mortality in Underserved Philadelphia Patient Population: A Randomized Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Temple University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Temple University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this clinical research study the investigators will test the efficacy of an innovative,
      non-invasive methodology to reduce mortality and lower limb loss among high-risk
      medically-underserved patients with cardiovascular disease in North Philadelphia.

      Patients with cardiovascular disease and recent lower limb amputation will be treated with an
      intermittent compression device on the remaining lower limb to prevent dual amputation.

      The study hypothesis is that the study intervention will protect against further lower
      limb-loss/death and reduce cardiovascular mortality in these patients (one year effect
      against limb-loss/death).

      This study may result in better secondary prevention strategies for disadvantaged urban
      populations as well as the general population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate whether a non-invasive intervention for 3 months
      with an intermittent compression device (ArtAssist®) in a high risk patient group reduces the
      risk of subsequent one-year limb-loss and/or death (e.g. one-year amputation-free survival
      and overall survival.) Survival after an amputation is markedly decreased due to generalized
      cardiovascular disease. The thirty-day mortality after amputation ranges from 6% to 16%
      depending on renal function. Two-year mortality after amputation is up to 40%.For dialysis
      patients, two year mortality was 58%.13 The five-year mortality after amputation in non-renal
      patients is 65%, while in dialysis patients five-year mortality is 83%. Patients who have
      undergone a major lower extremity amputation related to vascular disease are also at
      increased risk for losing their remaining lower extremity. The loss of the second lower
      extremity has a more profound impact on patients' ability to ambulate or function
      independently than the first amputation. Despite intensive initial rehabilitation, the use of
      prosthetics in bilateral amputees decreases rapidly over time. Contra-lateral amputations
      occur in up to 33%, after a mean of eight months. According to another study, 17% of diabetic
      initial amputees become bilateral amputees after a median time of less than one year for men
      and less than two years for women. According to a 2013 study, the majority of the subsequent
      contra-lateral amputations occur in the first year after the index amputation.

      We hope to prove that that there is a role for IPC in vascular patients at high-risk for
      mortality and limb-loss with relatively low-cost compression therapy. We hope to learn more
      about which underserved patient categories are most likely to benefit from this and when to
      start the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Amputation free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Limb Ischemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Art Assist Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The ArtAssist© (model AA1000) device is made by ACI Medical located in San Marcos, CA (http://acimedical.com/) and is cleared per FDA under K942530.The study intervention will consist of one hour of IPC with the ArtAssist© device to the remaining leg, three times a day for a three month period. We will obtain the usage data from the device when the subject returns the device (the device has an internal device that stores the usage data) to evaluate subject compliance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham devices look identical to the actual ArtAssist© devices, but provide low-pressure and differ only in number-coded tubing. The study &quot;sham intervention&quot; will consist of one hour of IPC with the sham ArtAssist© device to the remaining leg, three times a day for a three month period. We will obtain the usage data from the device when the subject returns the device (the sham device has an internal device that stores the usage data) to evaluate subject compliance.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ArtAssist© Device</intervention_name>
    <description>The study intervention will consist of one hour of IPC with the ArtAssist© device to the remaining leg, three times a day for a three month period. We will obtain the usage data from the device when the subject returns the device (the device has an internal device that stores the usage data) to evaluate subject compliance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Art Assist Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Device</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>The ArtAssist© (model AA1000)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and Female ages ≥ 21years old

          -  Able and willing to provide informed consent

          -  Status post amputation of lower limb

          -  IPC treatment can be initiated within 30 days post lower limb amputation

          -  Ankle-brachial index in the remaining extremity of less than 0.80, or toe- brachial
             index less than 0 .60 (obtained within last 6 months)

          -  Patients must be able to sit and able to perform the compression therapy independently

          -  Intact renal function or if patient has chronic kidney disease a pre study Creatinine
             will be obtained. If the patient has acute renal failure or is a dialysis patient
             he/she is eligible, but will be separately randomized and analyzed because Creatinine
             is linked to survival.

               -  Subjects status post healed minor (toe/metatarsal) amputations on treatment leg
                  will be included.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have no demonstrable peripheral artery disease by ankle-pressure and/or
             toe-pressure in the remaining limb (initial amputations were mostly precipitated by
             diabetic neuropathy, deformity, infection, or acute embolization. Amputations
             resulting from the late effects of trauma, burns, frostbite, etc. are also excluded.

          -  Patients who are not able to consent due to their mental status, or who are not
             willing or able to perform the compression therapy in a sitting position

          -  Contracted nursing-home patients with index amputations resulting from largely
             pressure-related tissue-loss decubitus

          -  Patients with infected gangrene or osteomyelitis present in the contra-lateral
             extremity (which would need to be compressed) at the time of the index amputation

          -  Patients with active dry gangrene on the leg that is to be compressed

          -  Patients with congestive heart failure

          -  Patients in which a deep venous thrombosis or pulmonary embolism is suspected

          -  Patients who have undergone arterial compression therapy within 1 year prior to study

          -  Bilateral amputation of lower extremity

          -  Patients with an expected life-span less than 3 months

          -  Patients who require intensive care are not eligible, until they can be transferred to
             a regular nursing floor

          -  Patients in whom the remaining limb is non-functional, for example due to previous
             stroke
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul van Bemmelen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul van Bemmelen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>215-707-3622</phone>
    <email>Paul.vanBemmelen@tuhs.temple.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Arrikka Mullins, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>215-707-7143</phone>
    <email>Arrikka.Mullins@Tuhs.temple.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Temple University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19140</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul van Bemmelen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>215-707-3622</phone>
      <email>paul.vanBemmelen@tuhs.temple.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <phone>215-707-7143</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 31, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 4, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 4, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non-traumatic lower limb amputation</keyword>
  <keyword>AKA</keyword>
  <keyword>BKA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

