<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02058979</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17266</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02058979</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetics of Bolus Versus Continuous Cefazolin Infusion in Patients Undergoing Major Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetics of Bolus Versus Continuous Cefazolin Infusion in Patients Undergoing Major Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Virginia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The University of Queensland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Virginia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Abstract The administration of an antibiotic preoperatively is an important intervention that
      helps to reduce the risk of post-operative health-care associated infections (HCAI). These
      include urinary tract, surgical site and blood stream infection. Based on the current
      Surgical Infection Prevention Project, (SCIP) recommendations, the choice of the antibiotic
      is based on the nature and site of the surgery and the presence of a β-lactam allergy (Table
      1).

      Currently, the antibiotic treatment for preventing surgical infections is administered as a
      single bolus an hour before surgery, and every four hours after the initial dose. This
      presents a concentration profile that has a high concentration after the bolus, but decays as
      the kidneys remove the antibiotics. In this present study, investigators would like to
      compare this traditional method of delivery to a constant infusion model that would sustain a
      constant level of antibiotics that is defined by the difference between the rate of infusion
      and rate of clearance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The current incidence of post-operative surgical infections varies between 6% for patients
      undergoing non-cardiac surgery to greater than 30% in high-risk surgery. 1 The administration
      of an antibiotic preoperatively is an important intervention that helps to reduce the risk of
      post-operative health-care associated infections (HCAI). These include urinary tract,
      surgical site and blood stream infection. Based on the current Surgical Infection Prevention
      Project, (SCIP) recommendations, the choice of the antibiotic is based on the nature and site
      of the surgery and the presence of a β-lactam allergy (Table 2). The antibiotic of choice for
      perioperative prophylaxis remains first and second generation cephalosporin. These drugs have
      a broad range of antimicrobial activity against common skin pathogens and have an excellent
      safety profile.

      Based on current recommendations, the cephalosporin is administered 1 hour prior to
      incision.1 Timing is critical, as both early and late administration of the antibiotic is
      associated with an increase risk of HCAI. Additional doses of the cephalosporin are
      administered at pre-set intervals based on the duration of the surgery in an attempt to
      maintain antibiotic concentrations at a desired level.

      Antibiotics can be classified into two broad classes, based on their bacterial killing
      characteristics. Antibiotics with concentration-dependent killing characteristics require a
      high ratio between the peak concentration and the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of
      the pathogen, during the dosing interval. Therefore large infrequent doses of these
      antibiotics will result in optimal antibacterial activity.

      In contrast β-lactam antibiotics, like cephalosporins, demonstrate time-dependent
      pharmacokinetics. This means that effective microbiological activity only occurs if the
      unbound (or free) plasma concentration of the drug is above the MIC for a specified time
      period. In infection models, bacteriostatic and bacteriocidical activity occurs when
      antibiotic concentrations are maintained above the MIC for 35-40% and 60-70% of the dosing
      interval respectively. However, in surgical prophylaxis, it is preferred that antibiotic
      concentrations are maintained above the MIC of the likely pathogen/s for the entire duration
      of the procedure. Therefore more frequent dosing or use of extended or continuous infusion of
      these drugs will better maintain the pharmacokinetic goals. Recent studies have shown that
      plasma levels of β-lactam antibiotics fall below the MIC 1-2 hours after the initial bolus
      dose in both normal and obese patients.2, 3 Even with appropriate re-dosing of the β-lactam
      antibiotic, there are times when the plasma concentration of the drug is below the MIC. The
      combination of sub-MIC plasma drug level and high bacteremic load can potentially increase
      the risk of developing a post-operative HCAI. It follows that to effectively prevent
      microbiological activity in the perioperative period the β-lactam antibiotic must remain
      above the MIC during the entire operative period. This is of particular importance in
      patients undergoing major abdominal surgery where the risk of perioperative surgical site
      infection (including superficial, deep and organ specific infection) is 13.1%. The aim of
      this study is to compare the pharmacokinetics of bolus and continuous cefazolin infusion
      during major abdominal surgery.

      Hypothesis to be Tested Hypothesis A continuous infusion of cefazolin maintains the unbound
      plasma concentration above Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) for the duration of the
      operative procedure better than the traditional bolus administration at every four hours.

      Specific Aims

      1. Compare the pharmacokinetics of a bolus versus continuous cefazolin (Ansef) infusion in
      major surgery

      A. Preliminary studies

      There are 2 studies in the abdominal surgery population. The study by Troconiz et al studies
      the pharmacokinetics of a bolus dose of cefoxitin.3 The study by Suffoleta studied a
      postoperative continuous infusion in the postoperative colorectal group.4

      B. Experimental design and methods (including data analysis)

      Informed consent for the study will be obtained in the PETC (Pre-anesthesia Clinic) prior to
      surgery.

      Induction and maintenance of anesthesia will be at the discretion of the attending
      anesthesiologist. Intraoperative analgesia will be provided at the discretion of the
      attending anesthesiologist and may include intravenous narcotics and/or intrathecal morphine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Concentration of Antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Day</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma concentration of antibiotics during surgery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Plasma Concentration of Antibiotics</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BOLUS INFUSION</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bolus infusion of antibiotics</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CONTINUOUS INFUSION</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Continuous infusion of antibiotics by way of infusion pump</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BOLUS INFUSION (Ancef)</intervention_name>
    <description>Bolus Infusion of antibiotics</description>
    <arm_group_label>BOLUS INFUSION</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ANCEF Bolus Infusion of antibiotics</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CONTINUOUS INFUSION (Ancef)</intervention_name>
    <description>Continuous Infusion of ANCEF with infusion pump</description>
    <arm_group_label>CONTINUOUS INFUSION</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Continuous Infusion of ANCEF with infusion pump</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Elective abdominal and orthopedic surgery

          -  A patent arterial line

          -  A patent IV line

          -  Must be able to read and speak English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects unable to give informed consent.

          -  Allergy to cefazolin

          -  Cognitively Impared

          -  Prisoners

          -  Pregnant females (self reported)

          -  History of coagulopathy

          -  Subjects presenting for emergency abdominal surgery

          -  Creatinine clearance &lt; 30 ml/min

          -  Received cefazolin within 72 hours prior to surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>BHIKEN NAIK, M.B.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Virginia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22910-0710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suffoletta TJ, Jennings HR, Oh JJ, Stephens D, Poe KL. Continuous versus intermittent infusion of prophylactic cefoxitin after colorectal surgery: a pilot study. Pharmacotherapy. 2008 Sep;28(9):1133-9. doi: 10.1592/phco.28.9.1133.</citation>
    <PMID>18752384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toma O, Suntrup P, Stefanescu A, London A, Mutch M, Kharasch E. Pharmacokinetics and tissue penetration of cefoxitin in obesity: implications for risk of surgical site infection. Anesth Analg. 2011 Oct;113(4):730-7. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e31821fff74. Epub 2011 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21642605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Isla A, Trocóniz IF, de Tejada IL, Vázquez S, Canut A, López JM, Solinís MÁ, Rodríguez Gascón A. Population pharmacokinetics of prophylactic cefoxitin in patients undergoing colorectal surgery. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 2012 May;68(5):735-45. doi: 10.1007/s00228-011-1206-1. Epub 2012 Jan 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22246211</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bratzler DW, Hunt DR. The surgical infection prevention and surgical care improvement projects: national initiatives to improve outcomes for patients having surgery. Clin Infect Dis. 2006 Aug 1;43(3):322-30. Epub 2006 Jun 16.</citation>
    <PMID>16804848</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 10, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 11, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 26, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Virginia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bhiken I. Naik, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Anesthesiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cefazolin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibiotics, Antitubercular</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

