<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03052777</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HREBA.CC-16-0775</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03052777</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Telephone Counselling to Improve Exercise Participation in Hematologic Cancer Survivors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Quality of Life in Hematologic Cancer Survivors by Closing the Exercise Intention—Behavior Gap: a Phase II Randomized Controlled Trial of a Theory-based, Telephone-delivered Exercise Counselling Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the impact of a 12-week theory-based exercise telephone counselling
      program (versus a self-directed exercise group) on closing the exercise intention-behavior
      gap in a sample of hematologic cancer survivors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Problem: Regular exercise participation improves quality of life and physical function for
      cancer survivors. Unfortunately, the most effective way of promoting exercise to cancer
      survivors has yet to be determined, and as a result, many survivors are inactive.
      Theory-based efforts have typically focused on promoting intentions to exercise, though we
      are now discovering that only about half of those who intend to exercise actually follow
      through on their intentions. This is known as the exercise intention-behavior gap. It also
      appears that survivors are more likely to follow-through on their intention to exercise when
      they report employing key behavioral and motivational strategies (i.e., creating detailed
      exercise plans, feeling capable and obligated to exercise, perceiving it to be beneficial and
      fun, and avoiding the temptation to participate in alternative activities) which may be
      promoted via telephone counselling.

      Objective: To determine whether a theory-based telephone counselling intervention focused on
      closing the exercise intention-behavior gap is feasible and can improve exercise levels,
      motivation, quality of life, and fatigue in hematologic cancer survivors.

      Methods: A two-armed randomized controlled trial will compare the efficacy of telephone
      counselling versus a control condition (self-directed with Canada's Physical Activity Guide).
      All participants will be asked to increase their exercise by at least 60 minutes per week.
      Hematologic cancer survivors who previously participated in an exercise survey study and
      indicated interest in participating in future exercise related research (N=407) will be
      contacted to participate in the current trial. Eligible participants will be randomized in a
      1:1 ratio to either the telephone counseling group or a self-directed exercise group.
      Participants in the intervention arm will receive 12 weekly telephone counseling sessions
      aimed at helping survivors follow-through on their exercise intention. A sample of
      approximately N=66 hematologic cancer survivors will be recruited for this 12-week trial.
      Data will be collected via online surveys assessing changes in exercise levels, motivation,
      quality of life, and fatigue. Feasibility will be determined by eligibility percentage,
      recruitment percentage, adherence rate, assessment completion rate, adverse events, and
      ratings of program acceptability.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 21, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Exercise Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and within 7 days of completing the 12-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Exercise levels assessed using the Godin Leisure-Time Exercise Questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Exercise Motivation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and within 7 days of completing the 12-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Exercise motivation assessed via validated questionnaires that align with the Multi-Process Action Control Framework</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and within 7 days of completing the 12-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life assessed using the Short Form-36 (SF-36) questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and within 7 days of completing the 12-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Fatigue assessed using the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy: Fatigue (FACT-F) questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</condition>
  <condition>Behavior, Health</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone Counselling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be asked to increase their exercise by at least 60 minutes per week and will receive a copy of Canada's Physical Activity Guideline plus 12 weekly telephone counseling sessions aimed at helping survivors follow-through on their exercise intention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be asked to increase their exercise by at least 60 minutes per week and will be self-directed, only receiving a copy of Canada's Physical Activity Guideline as standard of care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telephone counselling</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is a 12 week telephone counselling exercise program where participants will receive weekly telephone counselling that targets key theoretical behavior change constructs. Participants will also receive a copy of Canada's Physical Activity Guideline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone Counselling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The inclusion criteria for this study will be survivors who have had a histologically
             confirmed hematologic cancer, and who are between 18-80 years of age, living in
             Alberta, can speak and comprehend English, and willing to participate in a 12-week
             exercise telephone counseling intervention.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Survivors reporting greater or equal to 150 minutes of moderate-to-vigorous exercise
             will be excluded because they will already be meeting the public health guidelines for
             exercise. Survivors planning to be away for more than 2 weeks during the intervention,
             or with major exercise contraindications will also be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alberta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>t6g 2h9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 31, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alberta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kerry Courneya</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

