<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03050944</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>57</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03050944</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Association of the Mediterranean Diet With Fertility Outcomes</brief_title>
  <acronym>MedDietIVF</acronym>
  <official_title>Association of the Mediterranean Diet With Fertility Outcomes: a Study Among Couples Undergoing in Vitro Fertilization Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Harokopio University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Embryogenesis Assisted Conception Unit</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Harokopio University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Infertility affects one of every six couples and one out of ten couples may seek fertility
      treatment such as ovulation induction and assisted reproductive technologies. With respect to
      diet, several dietary factors, i.e. micro-, macro-nutrients and individual food groups, have
      been associated with the risk of subfertility; however, more information is needed on the
      role of dietary factors in reproductive functions. However, evidence concerning the
      association between dietary patterns, such as the Mediterranean diet (MD) pattern, and
      fertility is scarce. The aim of this study is to investigate the relationship between
      preconception dietary patterns, especially the MD pattern, and in vitro fertilization (IVF)
      outcomes, as well as adiponectin and follistatin concentrations in the plasma and follicular
      fluid of women undergoing IVF treatment. Blood and follicular fluid adiponectin and
      follistatin concentrations will be measured on each day of the ovarian stimulation protocol.
      Main IVF treatment outcomes are fertilization rate, oocyte and embryo quality, implantation,
      clinical pregnancy and live birth rates.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Infertility affects one of every six couples and one out of ten couples may seek fertility
      treatment such as ovulation induction and assisted reproductive technologies. There are
      multiple causes of infertility, including ovulatory disorders, endometriosis and sperm
      factors, or even psychological problems, among others. Modifiable lifestyle factors, such as
      diet, smoking and physical activity, may also affect fertility. With respect to diet, several
      dietary factors, i.e. micro-, macro-nutrients and individual food groups, have been
      associated with the risk of subfertility; however, more information is needed on the role of
      dietary factors in reproductive functions. A more comprehensive approach to investigate the
      associations between dietary factors and health outcomes is to assess the impact of the
      overall diet rather than separate foods or nutrients. However, evidence concerning the
      association between dietary patterns, such as the Mediterranean diet (MD) pattern, and
      fertility is scarce. The benefits of the MD on health have been well-publicized; it is
      associated with a significant reduction of overall mortality, cardiovascular disease and
      cancer. Adherence to the MD also seems to reduce the risk of weight gain and diabetes,
      conditions that raise insulin resistance and may thus lead to ovulatory infertility.
      Recently, adherence to MD was also associated with an increase in circulating adiponectin
      levels, a hormone produced by the adipose tissue that acts to reduce insulin resistance.
      Interestingly, adiponectin has been shown to exert actions in the female reproductive system,
      including the hypothalamic-pituitary ovarian axis and endometrium, and thus, it can be
      hypothesized that MD may exert a beneficial effect on reproductive functions through a
      raising effect on adiponectin levels. The aim of this study is to investigate the
      relationship between preconception dietary patterns, especially the MD pattern, and in vitro
      fertilization (IVF) outcomes, as well as adiponectin and follistatin concentrations in the
      plasma and follicular fluid of women undergoing IVF treatment.

      Two-hundred subfertile couples undergoing IVF treatment at a Fertility Clinic in Athens
      (www.embryogenesis.gr/) will be invited to participate. Participants will fill out the
      following questionnaires: a general questionnaire to record the baseline characteristics of
      the subjects (age, educational level, annual income, medical history, body mass index,
      smoking, etc), a semi-quantitative 77-item food frequency questionnaire to assess habitual
      dietary intakes, and a 40-item state-trait anxiety inventory instrument to measure anxiety
      symptoms. Dietary patterns will be evaluated using principal component analysis and factor
      analysis. Adherence to the MD will be assessed with a MD-score that incorporates the inherent
      characteristics of this traditional diet, that is, high intake of plant foods and olive oil,
      low intake of meat and dairy products, and moderate intake of alcohol. Blood and follicular
      fluid adiponectin and follistatin concentrations will be measured on each day of the ovarian
      stimulation protocol. Main IVF treatment outcomes are fertilization rate, embryo quality,
      implantation, clinical pregnancy and live birth.

      Associations between dietary patterns, adiponectin and follistatin concentrations and the IVF
      treatment outcomes will be tested using linear and logistic regression analyses, adjusting
      for potential confounders (e.g. age, smoking, anxiety symptoms, etc). The findings of the
      study could contribute in the development of guidelines to prevent infertility or to
      nutritional management associated to infertility treatments to improve reproductive
      performance. Furthermore, the elucidation of the role of adiponectin and follistatin in
      female reproductive functions and its association with dietary variables and the IVF outcomes
      could lead to the use of adiponectin or follistatin as therapeutic targets in novel treatment
      strategies of infertility disorders.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Live Birth</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Birth of a neonate on or after 24 weeks gestation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hormonal profile</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline serum E2, anti-mullerian hormone, inhibin b, luteinizing hormone, follicle stimulating hormone concentrations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oocyte number.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total Number of oocytes produced.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oocyte quality.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The morphological feature of each oocyte wil be evaluated with the aid of inverted microscope. The criteria employed for the morphological evaluation of oocytes are: a. normal oocytes showed clear cytoplasm with homogenous fine granularity; b. granular oocytes, dark with granularity either homogenous in whole cytoplasm or concentrated in the central portion of oocyte; c. cytoplasmic inclusions comprised vacuoles presumed to be of endocytotic origin; d. anomalies of zona pellucida e. fragmented polar body of different sizes; f. non-spherical shape of oocyte; and g. wide perivitelline space.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Embryo number.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total Number of embryos produced.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Embryo quality.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Embryo morphology will be assessed as follows: 44 h ± 1 h after intracytoplasmatic sperm injection, for day two evaluation and 68h ± 1 h after intracytoplasmatic sperm injection, for day 3 evaluation. Embryo morphology will be carried out using an inverted microscope</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Semen volume.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month.</time_frame>
    <description>Ejaculate volumes will be estimated by specimen weight, assuming a semen density of 1.0 g/ml.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Semen concentration.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month.</time_frame>
    <description>Sperm concentration will be evaluated by hemocytometer Motility will be assessed in accordance with the World Health Organization 2010 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Semen morphology.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month.</time_frame>
    <description>Regarding semen morphology, the World Health Organization criteria as described in 2010 state that a sample is normal if 4% (or 5th centile) or more of the observed sperm have normal morphology.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Semen Motility.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month.</time_frame>
    <description>Motility will be assessed in accordance with the World Health Organization 2010 criteria and classified as progressive motile (A + B), total motile (A + B + C), or immotile (D).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fertilization rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fertilization rate will be determined on day 1 after the IVF/intracytoplasmatic sperm injection procedure, and is going to calculated as the number of fertilized oocytes divided by the total number of oocytes retrieved</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Adiponectin</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Serum adiponectin levels will be measured by ELISA method on day 1 of the ovarian stimulation protocol, on day 3, on day 5, on day 7, on day 9 and the day of oocyte retrieval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Follicular Fluid Adiponectin</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Follicular fluid adiponectin levels from the dominant oocyte will be measured by ELISA method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Follicular Fluid Follistatin,</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Follicular fluid follistatin levels from the dominant oocyte will be measured by ELISA method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Elevation in b-human chorionic gonadotropin with the confirmation of an intrauterine pregnancy by ultrasound, first performed at 6 weeks of gestation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cases</arm_group_label>
    <description>Lifestyle behaviour and dietary habits assessment in couples achieving pregnancy after in vitro fertilization process.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Lifestyle behaviour and dietary habits assessment in couples failed to achieve pregnancy after in vitro fertilization process.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lifestyle behaviour and dietary habits assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Lifestyle behaviour and dietary habits assessment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cases</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood, follicular fluid
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subfertile couples undergoing IVF treatment at a Fertility Clinic in Athens
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of subfertility (male or female origin)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women's age &lt;41.

          -  Previous IVF attempt or pregnancy.

          -  Female obesity (BMI&gt;30 kgr/m2).

          -  Endometriosis

          -  Oocyte donation.

          -  Adherence to a hypocaloric diet for weight loss or changes in dietary habits during
             the last six months.

          -  Presence of female diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular disease, hypertension, neoplasm,
             hypothyroidism or psychiatric disorders.

          -  Previous ovarian surgery.

          -  Natural cycle IVF.

          -  Couples whose male partner shows an abnormality of the male genital tractus :
             Varicocele, undescended testis, testicular volume &lt; 12ml
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nikolaos Yiannakouris, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Associate Professor of Physiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harokopio University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>Attiki</state>
        <zip>10676</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karayiannis D, Kontogianni MD, Mendorou C, Douka L, Mastrominas M, Yiannakouris N. Association between adherence to the Mediterranean diet and semen quality parameters in male partners of couples attempting fertility. Hum Reprod. 2017 Jan;32(1):215-222. Epub 2016 Nov 14.</citation>
    <PMID>27994040</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 3, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 8, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Harokopio University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nikos Yiannakouris</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assοciate Professor of Physiology, Harokopio University</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fertility</keyword>
  <keyword>Infertility</keyword>
  <keyword>Dietary Patterns</keyword>
  <keyword>Mediterranean diet</keyword>
  <keyword>Adiponectin</keyword>
  <keyword>Follistatin</keyword>
  <keyword>Assisted Reproduction</keyword>
  <keyword>In Vitro Fertilization</keyword>
  <keyword>Semen quality</keyword>
  <keyword>Diet</keyword>
  <keyword>IVF</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

