<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03058965</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>[18F]MNI-958</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03058965</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 0 Evaluation of [18F]MNI-958 as a Potential PET Radioligand for Imaging Tau Protein in the Brain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 0 Evaluation of [18F]MNI-958 as a Potential PET Radioligand for Imaging Tau Protein in the Brain of Patients With Probable Alzheimer's Disease or Progressive Supranuclear Palsy Compared With Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Molecular NeuroImaging</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Molecular NeuroImaging</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall goal of this imaging trial is to evaluate [18F]MNI-958, a tau targeted PET
      radioligand, in individuals with Alzheimer's disease (AD), Progressive Supranuclear Palsy
      (PSP), and healthy volunteers (HV).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tracer uptake will be evaluated in regions of interest for analysis of regional [18F]MNI-958 binding/uptake and expressed in SUV by using established methods for normalization for 3 AD, 3 PSP, and 3 HV subjects.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics will be applied to describe the tau deposition by region as measured by [18F]MNI-958.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">9</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <condition>Progressive Supranuclear Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>[18F]MNI-958</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To evaluate [18F]MNI-958, a tau targeted PET radioligand.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[18F]MNI-958</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will undergo PET imaging using [18F]MNI-958, a PET radioligand for imaging tau.</description>
    <arm_group_label>[18F]MNI-958</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[18F]Florbetapir</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects with Alzheimer's disease will receive a [18F]florbetapir scan to compare distribution of tau in the brain compared to that of [18F]MNI-958.</description>
    <arm_group_label>[18F]MNI-958</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DaTscan</intervention_name>
    <description>DaTscan SPECT imaging will be completed in those PSP subjects who have not previously had DATScan imaging as part of the screening procedures.</description>
    <arm_group_label>[18F]MNI-958</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion:

          -  Written informed consent must be obtained before any assessment is performed.

          -  Female subjects must be documented by medical records or physician's note to be either
             surgically sterile (by means of hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, or tubal
             ligation) or post-menopausal for at least 1 year or, if they are of child-bearing
             potential, must commit to use a barrier contraception method for the duration of the
             study.

          -  Male subjects and their partners of childbearing potential must commit to the use of
             two methods of contraception, one of which is a barrier method for male subjects for
             the study duration.

          -  Male subjects must not donate sperm for the study duration.

          -  Willing and able to cooperate with study procedures

        Inclusion Criteria for Healthy Volunteer Subjects:

          -  Males and females aged ≥50 years. Healthy with no clinically relevant finding on
             physical examination at screening and upon reporting for the [18F]MNI-958 imaging
             visit.

          -  No cognitive impairment from neuropsychological battery as judged by the investigator

          -  Have screening [18F]florbetapir PET imaging demonstrating no significant amyloid
             binding based on qualitative analysis (visual read).

          -  No family history of Alzheimer's disease or neurological disease associated with
             dementia

          -  Have a CDR score=0

        Inclusion Criteria for subjects with a diagnosis of probable Alzheimer's disease (AD):

          -  Males and females aged 50 to 90 years.

          -  Have probable Alzheimer's disease, based on the NINCDS/ADRDA and DSM-IV criteria.

          -  Have a CDR score of 0.5 or greater at screening.

          -  Have an MMSE score ≤ 28.

          -  Have screening or prior (in the last 12 months) [18F]florbetapir PET imaging
             demonstrating amyloid binding based on qualitative (visual read)

          -  A brain MRI that supports a diagnosis of AD, with no evidence of focal disease to
             account for dementia or MRI exclusion criteria.

          -  Medications taken for symptomatic treatment of AD must be maintained on a stable
             dosage regimen for at least 30 days before the screening visit.

          -  Signed and dated written informed consent obtained from the subject and the subject's
             legally authorized representative or caregiver (if applicable).

          -  The subject has an appropriate caregiver capable of accompanying subject, if
             necessary.

        Inclusion Criteria for subjects with a diagnosis of probable Progressive Suprnuclear Palsy
        (PSP)

          -  Males and females aged 50 to 90 years.

          -  Has a clinical diagnosis of PSP based on the NINDS and Society for PSP criteria
             (Litvan, et al 1996).

          -  Have screening or prior DaTscan SPECT imaging demonstrating evidence of dopamine
             transporter deficit based on visual read.

          -  A brain MRI that supports a diagnosis of PSP, with no other evidence of significant
             neurologic pathology

          -  Medications taken for symptomatic treatment of PSP must be maintained on a stable
             dosage regimen for at least 30 days before screening visit.

          -  Signed and dated written informed consent obtained from the subject and the subject's
             legally authorized representative or caregiver (if applicable).

          -  The subject has an appropriate caregiver capable of accompanying subject, if
             necessary.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current or prior history of any alcohol or drug abuse.

          -  Laboratory tests with clinically significant abnormalities and/or clinically
             significant unstable medical illness.

          -  Subject has received an investigational drug or device within 30 days of screening

          -  Prior participation in other research protocols or clinical care in the last year in
             addition to the radiation exposure expected from participation in this clinical study,
             such that radiation exposure exceeds the effective dose of 50 mSv, which would be
             above the acceptable annual limit established by the US Federal Guidelines

          -  Pregnancy, lactating or breastfeeding.

          -  Evidence of clinically significant gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, hepatic, renal,
             hematological, neoplastic, endocrine, alternative neurological, immunodeficiency,
             pulmonary, or other disorder or disease.

          -  Unsuitable veins for repeated venipuncture.

          -  MRI exclusion criteria include: evidence of cerebrovascular disease (more than two
             lacunar infarcts, any territorial infarct &gt;1cm3, or deep white matter abnormality
             corresponding to an overall Fazekas scale of 3 with at least one confluent
             hyperintense lesion on the FLAIR sequence that is ≥20 mm in any dimension), infectious
             disease, space-occupying lesions, normal pressure hydrocephalus or any other
             abnormalities associated with CNS disease.

          -  Implants such as implanted cardiac pacemakers or defibrillators, insulin pumps,
             cochlear implants, metallic ocular foreign body, implanted neural stimulators, CNS
             aneurysm clips and other medical implants that have not been certified for MRI, or
             history of claustrophobia in MRI.

        Exclusion Criteria for Subjects with Probable AD:

          -  Has received treatment that targeted amyloid-β or tau within the last 3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria for Subjects with Probable PSP:

          -  Ongoing treatment with methylphenidate, bupropion, modafinil, metoclopramide, alpha
             methyldopa, reserpine, or amphetamine derivative.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Madonia, PA-C</last_name>
    <phone>203-401-4300</phone>
    <email>jmadonia@mnimaging.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David Russell, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>203-401-4300</phone>
    <email>drussell@mnimaging.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Molecular NeuroImaging, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Madonia, PA-C</last_name>
      <phone>203-401-4300</phone>
      <email>jmadonia@mnimaging.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://mnimaging.com/</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>AD</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <keyword>PSP</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Supranuclear Palsy, Progressive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

