<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03052439</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00122970</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03052439</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diet Reintroduction Study in Irritable Bowel Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Charting a Course to a Less Restrictive Diet for IBS</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) is the most common gastrointestinal disease, affecting 12% of
      the US population and up to 20% of the population worldwide. This is a condition that is
      diagnosed based on specific symptoms of altered bowel habits and abdominal pain, as well as
      the exclusion of select other GI diseases. IBS not only causes constipation, diarrhea,
      abdominal cramping, and bloating, it also significantly affects quality of life, overall
      functioning, and work productivity.

      The cause of IBS is likely multifactorial, which makes it a difficult disease to treat.
      However, patients often associate their IBS symptoms with eating a meal. Up to 90% of IBS
      patients restrict their diet to prevent or improve their symptoms, and patients are
      increasingly interested in more holistic approaches to disease management. At present, the
      most persuasive evidence that dietary changes can treat IBS supports a diet low in
      fermentable carbohydrates (the low FODMAP (fermentable oligo, di, and monosaccharides and
      polyols) diet). This diet, which is low in certain carbohydrates, has been shown to improve
      IBS symptoms (particularly abdominal pain and bloating), but can be difficult to follow and
      quite restrictive. In addition, this diet is not meant to be used as a maintenance diet;
      patients undergo an elimination phase followed by a reintroduction phase of specific
      carbohydrate groups as they monitor their symptoms. From the results of our proposed study,
      the study team hopes to arrive at a modified, less -restrictive version of the low FODMAP
      diet that is equally effective, and also create a standard protocol that patients can use
      during this reintroduction phase.

      Patients with IBS will be recruited into a 13-week trial that would help determine the
      optimal way in which high FODMAP foods should be introduced. After consent, patients would
      start on a low FODMAP diet for 14 days, and if their symptoms improve, they would be invited
      to continue in the study. For 7 days prior to the reintroduction of individual FODMAPs,
      patients will ingest 1daily servings of a low FODMAP nutrition drink to validate the low
      FODMAP content of this dietary supplement. If patients do not experience a flare of symptoms
      with the supplement, they enter the reintroduction period. During this period, subjects would
      introduce different groups of FODMAPs in a blinded fashion while remaining on an otherwise
      low FODMAP diet while monitoring their IBS symptoms. At the end of the study period, subjects
      would be informed of the FODMAPs to which they were sensitive and would meet with a
      dietitian. At the completion of the study, the investigators would compile the data and
      determine which FODMAPs were mostly likely to exacerbate IBS symptoms, thus providing the
      construct for a modified low FODMAP diet, or &quot;low FODMAP-Light.&quot; It is hoped that this
      modified, less restrictive version of the low FODMAP diet would be equally effective for the
      majority of IBS patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Research Plan Design: Blinded FODMAP reintroduction study Duration of study: 1 year

      Patient population:

      Eligible IBS patients

      Visit 1 (-2 weeks): After providing written informed consent, baseline and descriptive data
      will be obtained including age, sex, race, pertinent medical history, prior IBS treatments,
      vital signs, weight, use of concurrent medications and supplements, duration of symptoms, and
      baseline symptoms. The investigators will also collect blood, stool and urine for a series of
      separately funded translational studies assessing immune activation, permeability, and
      microbiome.

      After this visit, patients will enter a two-week screening period during which severity of
      symptoms will be assessed. Eligible patients will rate their average daily abdominal
      pain/discomfort as a 4 or higher on an 11 point numerical rating scale (NRS) (0-no pain,
      10-intolerable pain) and IBS subtype of constipation-predominant, diarrhea- predominant, or
      mixed bowel habits (by Rome IV criteria19). Patients with an indeterminate subtype will be
      excluded. Patients will record symptoms (Table 1) daily using a web-based survey instrument.
      Experience from previous diet trials suggests that approximately 50% of participants will not
      fulfill these inclusion criteria after the screening period, and will be termed screen
      failures.

      Visit 2 (weeks 0-2): IBS patients who fulfill the entry criteria will be invited to
      participate in the remainder of the trial. Instruction from an experienced research dietitian
      pertaining to the low FODMAP diet will be administered to all participants in an open-label
      fashion for 2 weeks. Patients are to continue to record symptoms daily. Our previous work has
      demonstrated that abdominal pain and bloating are the most responsive symptoms to the low
      FODMAP diet. As such, the primary measure for this study will be improvement in abdominal
      pain with improvement in bloating as a key secondary endpoint. If a subject experiences a
      ≥30% reduction in abdominal pain during the 2-week low FODMAP intervention compared to
      baseline, they will be invited to participate in the blinded, FODMAP reintroduction phase
      (below). If this ≥30% reduction is not obtained, this period of open-label low FODMAP diet
      will be extended an additional 2 weeks to ascertain if their symptoms improve to qualify for
      continuation.

      Standard dietary compliance measures used in the counseling environment are to include
      prospectively recorded 3-day food diaries before and after the open label period. Body weight
      over the course of the study will also be followed. Food diaries will be analyzed for
      compliance via the Nutrition Data System for Research (NDSR) computer program, measuring
      fructose, lactose, sucrose, pectins, sorbitol, and added sugars. Blood, stool and urine
      samples will be collected for translational studies (separately funded).

      Week 2: If a ≥30% reduction in abdominal pain is obtained from the low FODMAP diet, subjects
      will be eligible to continue in the study during which they will remain on a full FODMAP
      elimination diet. For 7 days (week 2-3) prior to the reintroduction of individual FODMAPs,
      subjects will ingest 1 daily servings of a low FODMAP nutrition drink (Pronourish, 170
      calories each, Nestlé S.A., Vevey, Switzerland) to validate the low FODMAP content of this
      dietary supplement. Daily symptoms will be measured as above. If a participant does not
      experience a flare of symptoms with the supplement, they will continue onto the
      reintroduction phase. If the participant does experience a flare in symptoms, they will
      discontinue the product for 1 week before continuing in to the next phase (reintroduction
      phase) of the study. The supplement will be supplied with an unbranded label. Adverse events
      will be monitored during weeks 2-3 and significant adverse events (discontinuation of the
      supplement, worsening of GI symptoms back to baseline) will be recorded.

      Visit 3 (weeks 3-13): FODMAP reintroduction (lactose, fructose, fructans, polyols, galactans)
      will be achieved by providing subjects with similar appearing and similar tasting snacks
      which will contain specific types of supplemental FODMAPs prepared by research dieticians at
      MCRU. The study team will ask the participants to continue on their low FODMAP diet during
      this reintroduction phase, with the addition of 1-2 supplemental low FODMAP drinks per day
      for convenience. The re-introduction of FODMAP containing foods will be conducted in a
      double-blind fashion where both subjects and investigators will be unaware of the type of
      FODMAP being reintroduced. The study dietitians will remain un-blinded to the subjects'
      FODMAP treatment since they will be responsible for preparing and providing the FODMAP
      containing supplement to the subjects. For the first 7 days of the re-introduction phase,
      subjects will receive a FODMAP containing food item; this treatment will be followed by a
      7-day wash out period during which subjects will receive a similar food or supplement that
      does not contain the targeted FODMAP. The daily dose of fermentable carbohydrate contained in
      the study food or supplement will be administered in 2 doses (moderate for the first 3 days
      and higher amount for the later 4 days of the 7 day reintroduction period), with the content
      similar to that found in the typical American diet (internal data from healthy study
      subjects, published data18,20). To determine optimal dosing, the study team will conduct a
      careful systematic review and interviews with experienced dieticians and GIs to determine the
      optimal dose to each FODMAP with which to challenge. The order in which each specific FODMAP
      is tested will be randomized to minimize the chances of an order effect. Throughout the study
      period, symptom data will continue to be recorded on a daily basis (Table 1). If a subject is
      unable to tolerate any portion of the reintroduction phase, they will discontinue
      reintroduction of that specific FODMAP and revert again to a low FODMAP diet for washout.

      Visit 4: Final study visit (13 weeks). Subjects will be unblinded as to which FODMAP
      components exacerbated symptoms, if any. This information will be disseminated to study
      participants by our dietitians immediately after their completion of the study period. The
      primary investigators remain blinded to this information through analysis of data. A
      three-day food diary will be obtained to ensure ongoing compliance with the low FODMAP diet.
      Serum samples for immune activation, stool for microbiome analysis, urine for metabolome
      analysis will be collected at Visit 2 and 3 and analyzed with funding from alternate sources.
      Body weight will again be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 5, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Food items will be blindly reintroduced, and symptoms will be measured.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants blinded to randomization of order of reintroduction; Investigators blinded to order of reintroduction</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Abdominal Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Daily score (0-10) for abdominal pain will be recorded. This will be averaged and compared to the baseline and run-in periods</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bloating</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Daily score (0-10) for bloating will be recorded. This will be averaged and compared to the baseline and run-in periods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stool Consistency</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Daily stool consistency score will be recorded. This will be averaged and compared to the baseline and run-in periods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stool Frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Daily number of stools will be recorded. This will be averaged and compared to the baseline and run-in periods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stool urgency</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Daily score (0-10) for stool urgency will be recorded. This will be averaged and compared to the baseline and run-in periods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Daily score (0-10) for fatigue will be recorded. This will be averaged and compared to the baseline and run-in periods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Daily score (0-10) for sleep quality will be recorded. This will be averaged and compared to the baseline and run-in periods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Order 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects would introduce 5 different groups of FODMAPs in a blinded fashion (random order, 1 week on, one week off) while remaining on an otherwise low FODMAP diet while monitoring their IBS symptoms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Order 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects would introduce 5 different groups of FODMAPs in a blinded fashion (random order, 1 week on, one week off) while remaining on an otherwise low FODMAP diet while monitoring their IBS symptoms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Order 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects would introduce 5 different groups of FODMAPs in a blinded fashion (random order, 1 week on, one week off) while remaining on an otherwise low FODMAP diet while monitoring their IBS symptoms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Order 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects would introduce 5 different groups of FODMAPs in a blinded fashion (random order, 1 week on, one week off) while remaining on an otherwise low FODMAP diet while monitoring their IBS symptoms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Order 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects would introduce 5 different groups of FODMAPs in a blinded fashion (random order, 1 week on, one week off) while remaining on an otherwise low FODMAP diet while monitoring their IBS symptoms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FODMAP</intervention_name>
    <description>After 2 weeks on a low FODMAP diet, subject will undergo a reintroduction period. 5 different FODMAPs will be reintroduced (1 week at a time, followed by 1 week washout) in a blinded, randomized fashion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Order 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Order 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Order 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Order 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Order 5</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patient population:

        Eligible non-constipated IBS (NC-IBS) patients will be invited to participate in a study
        that will provide double blinded, individual FODMAP challenges to patients who have
        responded to full dietary FODMAP restriction.

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males or females, at least 18 years of age, able to provide informed consent

          -  Meet Rome IV criteria for IBS-C (constipation-predominant), IBS-D
             (diarrhea-predominant), IBS-M (mixed bowel habits) as assessed by a gastroenterologist

          -  Willingness to maintain a stable dosage of IBS medications during the pretreatment
             baseline period, including tricyclic antidepressants; &quot;rescue&quot; medications permitted
             (ie loperamide)

          -  For IBS-D patients only, documentation of normal colonoscopy or flexible sigmoidoscopy
             with colon biopsies within five years

          -  Documentation of normal TSH, CBC, CRP, electrolyte panel

          -  Negative evaluation for celiac disease either with normal TTG IgA, EMA, and/or
             duodenal biopsy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  IBS-U subtype (undetermined)

          -  Comorbid medical problems that may affect gastrointestinal transit or motility
             (inflammatory bowel disease, extra-intestinal disease known to affect the
             gastrointestinal system (scleroderma, unstable thyroid disease, uncontrolled diabetes
             mellitus, etc.), severe renal or hepatic disease

          -  Previous treatment with a low FODMAP diet or active participation in another form of
             dietary therapy

          -  Previous surgery to the GI tract except appendectomy or cholecystectomy if performed
             more than six months prior to enrollment.

          -  Medications not permitted include probiotics, antibiotics, laxatives, and narcotics
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shanti Eswaran, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shanti Eswaran, MD</last_name>
    <phone>7343308617</phone>
    <email>seswaran@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lina Nahlawi</last_name>
    <phone>7349362761</phone>
    <email>lnahlawi@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109-0362</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shanti Eswaran, MD</last_name>
      <phone>734-936-6400</phone>
      <email>seswaran@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Shanti Eswaran</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plan to share IPD</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

