<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03056469</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>REG-72-2016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03056469</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient-Reported Outcomes Integrated in the Follow-up of Patients With Hematological Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Patient-Reported Outcomes Integrated in the Follow-up of Patients With Hematological Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Zealand University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Zealand University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study investigates if integration of patient-reported outcomes in the follow-up of
      patients with newly diagnosed, not curable, chronic hematological cancer changes the number
      and kind of supportive care interventions. Furthermore, this study investigates if the
      patients feel that they are more involved in a positive way when patient-reported outcomes
      are integrated in the follow-up of their cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multimethod study. It has a quantitative and a qualitative part. The
      patient-reported outcome questionnaire European Organization for Research and Treatment of
      Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Core 30 (EORTC QLQ C-30) and the patient-reported
      outcome and patient-reported experience questionnaire The Outcomes and Experiences
      Questionnaire (OEQ) are completed by the included patients within one week before a
      patient-physician consultation at the outpatient clinic at one single department of
      hematology. Baseline is different for different patient groups; 1) for participants receiving
      a primary treatment baseline is defined as the first patient-physician consultation after the
      primary treatment ended, 2) for patients continuously receiving medical treatment baseline is
      defined as the first patient-physician consultation after starting medical treatment, and 3)
      for patients followed using a watch and wait strategy baseline is defined as the first
      patient-physician consultation after deciding the watch and wait strategy. Each patient
      completes the questionnaires for 2 years. The questionnaires can be completed online or on
      paper depending on the patients choice. Answers from both questionnaires are eligible to all
      health care professionals in the outpatient clinic in an internet-based tool. A summary of
      scores from the EORTC QLQ C-30, and the answers and the score from the OEQ, are written in
      the medical record.

      This study investigates, if use of the patient-reported outcome (PRO) questionnaires are
      useful in the assessment of the patients needs and health care providers decision making
      regarding supportive care interventions. It investigates, if completion of PRO questionnaires
      changes the number and kind of supportive care interventions.

      Observations of patient-physician consultations and individual interviews with patients are
      used to capture the impact of the questionnaires on the consultations and patients evaluation
      of the use of the questionnaires.

      This study also investigates, if patients completion of PRO questionnaires and health care
      professionals use of the questionnaires in clinical decision making changes the number of
      contacts between patients and a department of hematology and the number of paraclinical
      interventions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>In one randomization arm the participants submit patient-reported outcomes, and the care providers have access to the patient-reported outcomes. In another randomization arm the participants submit patient-reported outcomes, but the care providers do not have access to the patient-reported outcomes. In the last randomization arm the participants are randomized to standard follow-up, do not complete PRO questionnaires and are thus controls.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Supportive care interventions</measure>
    <time_frame>Three and a half year</time_frame>
    <description>Number and kind of supportive care interventions are registered. Supportive care actions are defined as: a) a plan for rehabilitation, b) an intervention by a physiotherapist, occupational therapist, dietician, or social worker, c) consultation with a psychologist or talk with a priest, d) an intervention done by a general practitioner because of the hematological cancer after contact between the hematological department and the general practitioner, e) use of offers like group talks etc offered by the Danish Cancer Society, or f) other supportive care interventions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients satisfaction with the interventions done by a department of hematology</measure>
    <time_frame>Three and a half year</time_frame>
    <description>Patients satisfaction with the interventions done by a department of hematology are measured using a patient-reported experience questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of the use of PRO questionnaires on the consultation and patient satisfaction with and evaluation of the use of patient-reported outcomes in the outpatient clinic</measure>
    <time_frame>Three and a half year</time_frame>
    <description>The impact of the use of PRO questionnaires on the consultation and patients satisfaction with and evaluation of the use of patient-reported outcomes in the outpatient clinic are investigated by observation of conversations between doctors and patients in the outpatient clinic, and furthermore investigated by individual interviews</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Contacts to the outpatient clinic at department of hematology</measure>
    <time_frame>Three and a half year</time_frame>
    <description>All contacts between the patients and the department of hematology are registered. Are there more/less/equal number and kind of contacts to the outpatient clinic at department of hematology when using patient-reported outcomes compared to when not using patient-reported outcomes?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Paraclinical interventions</measure>
    <time_frame>Three and a half year</time_frame>
    <description>All paraclinical actions ordered by the department of hematology are registered. Are more/less/equal number and kind of paraclinical interventions done when using patient-reported outcomes compared to when not using patient-reported outcomes?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">225</enrollment>
  <condition>Hematological Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Care providers do have access to PROs</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants complete patient-reported outcome (PRO) questionnaires. Care providers do have access to the PROs and use them in clinical decision making.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Care providers do not have access to PROs</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants complete patient-reported outcome (PRO) questionnaires. Care providers do not have access to the PROs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard follow-up. The participants do not complete PRO questionnaires.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Completion of patient-reported outcome (PRO) questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient-reported outcome (PRO) questionnaires are completed at home within one week before a patient-physician consultation at the outpatient clinic. The questionnaires are submitted online or on paper depending on the participants choice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Care providers do have access to PROs</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Care providers do not have access to PROs</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients newly diagnosed with not curable, chronic hematological cancer

          -  ≥18 years old

          -  oral and written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  participation in another intervention study

          -  psychological or physiological conditions that may prevent compliance/adherence to the
             study

          -  patients do not wish to be included in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hans Hasselbalch, professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Hematology, Zealand University Hospital, Vestermarksvej 9, 4000 Roskilde, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nana Brochmann, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+4522833458</phone>
    <phone_ext>+4522833458</phone_ext>
    <email>nmor@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hans Hasselbalch, professor</last_name>
    <phone>+4526223678</phone>
    <phone_ext>+4526223678</phone_ext>
    <email>hans.hasselbalch@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Hematology, Zealand University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roskilde</city>
        <state>Zealand</state>
        <zip>4000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nana Brochmann, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+4522833458</phone>
      <phone_ext>+4522833458</phone_ext>
      <email>nmor@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Hans Hasselbalch, professor</last_name>
      <phone>+4526223678</phone>
      <phone_ext>+4526223678</phone_ext>
      <email>hans.hasselbalch@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 25, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>patient-reported outcomes</keyword>
  <keyword>supportive care</keyword>
  <keyword>clinical practice</keyword>
  <keyword>hematological cancer</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

