<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03050580</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UW12-557</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03050580</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Evaluation of the &quot;Treatment Group Model for Abused Women&quot; in Shelters in Hong Kong</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Evaluation of the &quot;Treatment Group Model for Abused Women&quot; in Shelters in Hong Kong</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is cluster randomized control trial, that aims to evaluate the effectiveness of the
      treatment group model for abused women in enhancing their self-esteem and reducing the level
      of depression, in three shelters for abused women of Po Leung Kuk (a social service
      organization in Hong Kong). It is hypothesized that subjects in the Treatment Group would
      report significant improvement in self-esteem, social support, quality of life; reduction in
      the level of depression, symptoms of Posttraumatic Stress Disorder at 3 months after service
      delivery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is cluster randomized control trial, that aims to evaluate the effectiveness of the
      treatment group model for abused women in enhancing their self-esteem and reducing the level
      of depression, in three shelters for abused women of Po Leung Kuk (a social service
      organization in Hong Kong). 50-60 abused women are recruited as treatment group from two
      randomized shelters of Po Leung Kuk (Shelters A and B), where subjects receive self-esteem
      enhancement group intervention for abused women. Another 50-60 abused women are recruited as
      the control group from a randomized shelter of Po Leung Kuk (Shelter C), where subject
      receive standard shelter services for abused women. It is hypothesized that subjects in the
      Treatment Group would report significant improvement in self-esteem, social support, quality
      of life; reduction in the level of depression, symptoms of Posttraumatic Stress Disorder at 3
      months after service delivery, are compared to those in the control group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 30, 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of self-esteem from baseline to 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Confidence in one's own worth or abilities; self-respect; feeling of powerlessness.
Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale (Rosenberg, 1965) will be used to measure the self-esteem of the participants. This is a 10-item Likert-type scale on a 4-point scale ranging from strongly agree to strongly disagree. The scores for the 10 items are then summed; the higher the score, the higher the participant's self-esteem.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Basic demographics data questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Basic demographics data: Age, ethnicity, marital status, living arrangements with spouse/partner, education level, occupation, immigration status (if applicable), information on support network (family and friend), action plan (e.g., filing divorce, application of Injunctions)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social support</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-perceived social support from others
The Interpersonal Support Evaluation List-12 (ISEL-12) (Cohen et al., 1985), will be used to measure social support. It has has good psychometric properties and good internal consistency (Cronbach α = 0.88), was used to measure the perceived social support of abused women. The 12-item questionnaire measures 3 sub-scales consisting of appraisal, belonging and tangible support, each of which has 4 items. Each item scores from 0 (definitely false) to 3 (definitely true) giving a total score ranging from 0 to 36. The higher the score, the more the women perceive that they received social support.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of depression</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report symptoms corresponding to criteria for diagnosing depressive disorders
The Beck Depression Inventory version II (BDI-II) will be used to measure level of depression. It is a self-report instrument for the assessment of symptoms corresponding to criteria for diagnosing depressive disorders (Beck, Steer, &amp; Brown, 1996). It consists of 21 groups of statements and requires the respondent to choose one statement in each group that best describes her during the previous two weeks. The BDI-II has been translated into Chinese and has demonstrated satisfactory validity and reliability (α ranged from .86 to .87) (Leung, 2001).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-traumatic Stress Disorder symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report symptoms corresponding to criteria for diagnosing Post-traumatic Stress Disorder symptoms
The Chinese Version of the Impact of Event Scale-Revised (IES-R) (Chen et al., 2005 Wu and Chan, 2003) will be used to assess the PTSD symptoms of participants. This is a 22-items self-report instrument to assess PTSD symptoms after a specific traumatic stressor. There are three subscales, including intrusive, avoidance, and hyperarousal symptoms, corresponding to the three dimensions of the DSM-IV criteria for PTSD (American Psychiatric Association, 1994). Each participant will be asked to indicate the frequency of their distress for each of the 22 items on four point scale (0=not at all, 1=seldom, 3=sometime, 4=often).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Health-related quality of life
The SF-12 - Short Form Health Survey (SF-12) will be used to assess health-related quality of life (Ware, Snow &amp; Kosinski, 1993). It consists of 36 items with one measuring health transition and the remaining 35 grouped under eight scales: physical functioning (PF), role limitation due to physical health problems (role-physical; RP), bodily pain (BP), general health (GH), vitality (VT), social functioning (SF), role limitation due to emotional health problems (role-emotional; RE) and mental health (MH).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spousal violence</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Spousal violence includes any form of physical, psychological and sexual abuse between experienced by the abused women.
The Chinese version of the Abuse Assessment Screen (C-AAS) will be used to assess participants for IPV. The C-AAS addresses physical, psychological and sexual abuse. The main difference between the original AAS for women (McFarlane, Parker, Soeken &amp; Bullock, 1992) and the C-AAS is that the C-AAS addresses emotional and physical abuse separately in both lifetime and the preceding 3 months while the English AAS measures psychological and physical abuse simultaneously for the lifetime period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">122</enrollment>
  <condition>Abused Women</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Self-esteem enhancement group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The self-esteem enhancement group service for abused women will receive a six-session program for recognizing strengths and resources through group activities and sharing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The shelter standard care for abused women includes residential accommodations, emotional support, legal, housing and financial advice and referral service.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>self-esteem enhancement group</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in the treatment group will join a six-session treatment for recognizing their strengths and resources through group activities and sharing. Each session is 1.5-2 hours long, and all sessions are designed for 4-8 abused women. The activities are designed and led with an aim to improve their self-esteem, general health, as well as to reduce the level of depression. This service is provided by registered social workers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Self-esteem enhancement group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>experimental/treatment group</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard care for abused women</intervention_name>
    <description>The shelter standard care and services will be provided to the abused women in one randomized shelter. Besides, standard care in shelters includes residential accommodations, emotional support, legal, housing and financial advice and referrals will be given to survivors who reported being abused.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>control group</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Abused women of family violence aged 18 or older

          -  Receiving services from shelters of Po Leung Kuk

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to communicate (possible reasons: dialects used by targets but not
             understandable by interviewers; mentally challenged)

          -  Unable to give consent to participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anna Choi, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>annachoi@socwork.hku.hk</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 1, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 10, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Anna W.M. Choi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Abused women</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment group</keyword>
  <keyword>family violence</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

