<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03059940</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-0626</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01-CA 2027078-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03059940</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Smoking Cessation Intervention During Low Dose CT (LDCT) Screening for Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimizing Effectiveness of Smoking Cessation Intervention During Low Dose CT Screening for Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to offer lung cancer screenings to smokers who
      want to change their smoking behaviors. All eligible participants will receive smoking
      cessation counseling and may be offered at least one form of smoking cessation drug.
      Different forms of counseling (the delivery of counseling and access to counseling) will be
      compared.

      This is an investigational study. Participants on this study will not be prescribed smoking
      drugs directly by the study staff. However, participants in this study may or may not receive
      smoking cessation drugs, depending on what the provider thinks is in the participants best
      interest. All smoking cessation drugs being used are FDA approved and commercially available.
      It is investigational to compare the different forms of counseling participants receive.

      Up to 1260 participants will be enrolled in this study. All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Groups:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will have a CT scan of your
      chest to look for signs of lung cancer. You will receive the results 0-4 days after the scan.
      If there are any abnormal areas, you will be referred to your regular doctor for follow-up.
      No matter what the results are, you will be advised to quit smoking. If you have previously
      had a low dose CT scan for lung cancer screening in the last 30 days, you may still be
      eligible to participate in this study. You will be asked to provide documentation of the CT
      scan results.

      You will receive a referral for counseling to help you reduce/quit smoking. You may also
      discuss medications you can take to reduce smoking.

      As part of your counseling treatment, you may be prescribed an FDA-approved and commercially
      available anti-smoking drug. This may be either nicotine replacement therapy (such as a
      patch, gum, or lozenge) or an oral drug (such as varenicline or buproprion). The provider
      will tell you when and how much of your anti-smoking drug you should take each time, based on
      a discussion between you and your provider. Receiving anti-smoking medication will be done
      through your counseling treatment and not as part of your participation in this study.

      You will have at least 5, but no more than 8, smoking cessation counseling sessions over the
      next 12 weeks. Each session will last between 30 - 60 minutes, in which you will set a quit
      date, prepare for your quit date, and discuss coping skills for dealing with smoking
      &quot;triggers&quot; after your quit date. You will also discuss challenges you may have with quitting.

      Study Visits:

      You will have 3 additional study visits, at around 6 weeks, 12 weeks, and 6 months after the
      screening visit, as well as 1 follow-up phone call. At all study visits:

        -  You will complete questionnaires about several topics, including depression, suicide,
           and your smoking behavior. These questionnaires should take about 30-45 minutes in total
           to complete.

        -  Your CO level will be measured.

        -  Urine and/or saliva may be collected (at 12 weeks and 6 months only) for a routine test
           to check your cotinine and nicotine. Cotinine is a chemical released in your body when
           it breaks down nicotine and will show whether and how much you have recently smoked.

      Follow-Up:

      About 5 months after you start receiving counseling sessions, you will be called by a member
      of the study staff and asked about your recent smoking behaviors and habits. This call should
      last about 5-10 minutes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 16, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Smoking Abstinence Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Statistical power will focus on primary objective. Primary analyses use intention-to-treat (ITT) principles, with missing observations imputed as smoking.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1260</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline (QL) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Questionnaires completed at baseline and at 6 weeks, 12 weeks, and 6 months after the CT scan. CO level measured at baseline and at 6 weeks, 12 weeks, and 6 months after the CT scan.
Participants have a CT scan of chest to look for signs of lung cancer. Participants watch a short video about lung cancer, CT scans, and smoking cessation. Brief cessation counseling given by LDCT provider. Participants given shared decision making and discussion about screening with the LDCT provider.
Participants referred to the Quitline for counseling and NRT (nicotine patch). Participants have 5 smoking cessation counseling sessions over the next 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline-Rx (QL-Rx) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Questionnaires completed at baseline and at 6 weeks, 12 weeks, and 6 months after the CT scan. CO level measured at baseline and at 6 weeks, 12 weeks, and 6 months after the CT scan.
Participants have a CT scan of chest to look for signs of lung cancer. Participants watch a short video about lung cancer, CT scans, and smoking cessation. Brief cessation counseling given by LDCT provider.
LDCT provider and patient discuss options for pharmacotherapy.
Participants referred to the Quitline for counseling. Participants have 5 smoking cessation counseling sessions over the next 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Integrated Care (IC) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Questionnaires completed at baseline and at 6 weeks, 12 weeks, and 6 months after the CT scan. CO level measured at baseline and at 6 weeks, 12 weeks, and 6 months after the CT scan.
Participants have a CT scan of chest to look for signs of lung cancer. Participants watch a short video about lung cancer, CT scans, and smoking cessation. Brief cessation counseling given by LDCT provider.
Participant referred to Tobacco Treatment Program (TTP). TTP provides 4-8 counseling sessions and pharmacotherapy over a 10-12 week period,</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>Questionnaires completed at baseline and at 6 weeks, 12 weeks, and 6 months after the CT scan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline (QL) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline-Rx (QL-Rx) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Integrated Care (IC) Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surveys</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low Dose Computed Tomography Scan</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants have a CT scan of chest to look for signs of lung cancer.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline (QL) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline-Rx (QL-Rx) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Integrated Care (IC) Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LDCT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Shared Decision Making + Video</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants given shared decision making and discussion about screening with the LDCT provider. Participants watch a short video about lung cancer, CT scans, and smoking cessation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline (QL) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline-Rx (QL-Rx) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Integrated Care (IC) Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cessation Counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>Brief cessation counseling given by LDCT provider.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline (QL) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline-Rx (QL-Rx) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Integrated Care (IC) Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quitline</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants referred to the Quitline for counseling. Participants have 5 smoking cessation counseling sessions over the next 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline (QL) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline-Rx (QL-Rx) Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacotherapy Discussion</intervention_name>
    <description>Participant informed of the risk, benefits and relative efficacy of cessation medications and to assess their medication preferences, expectations and medical suitability for either option. At the conclusion of this conversation the patient is provided with an initial supply of the medication jointly decided between provider and patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline-Rx (QL-Rx) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Integrated Care (IC) Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nicotine Patch</intervention_name>
    <description>Nicotine patch dispensed. Dosing at physician's discretion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline (QL) Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti-Smoking Drug</intervention_name>
    <description>Varenicline or Buproprion prescribed by study doctor with directions of when and how much of anti-smoking drug that should be taken each time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline-Rx (QL-Rx) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Integrated Care (IC) Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tobacco Treatment Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Participant referred to Tobacco Treatment Program (TTP). TTP provides 4-8 counseling sessions and pharmacotherapy over a 10-12 week period,</description>
    <arm_group_label>Integrated Care (IC) Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TTP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carbon Monoxide (CO) Level Test</intervention_name>
    <description>Participant asked to blow air through a CO-measuring device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline (QL) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Quitline-Rx (QL-Rx) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Integrated Care (IC) Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age: 50 or older

          2. Reports being a daily or non-daily smoker (any self-reported smoking in the past 30
             days) and is interested in treatment that might change smoking behavior.

          3. Meets guidelines for lung cancer screening, as determined by radiology team

          4. Able to follow verbal and written instructions in English and complete all aspects of
             the study.

          5. Provide informed consent and agree to all assessments and study procedures.

          6. Have an address and telephone number where he/she may be reached.

          7. Be the only participant in his/her household on active treatment in Protocol 2016-0626
             at the time.

          8. Following good clinical practice guidelines, be medically suitable for one or more
             pharmacotherapies for smoking cessation including NRT, bupropion or varenicline, at
             provider discretion.

          9. Willing and able to undergo low dose CT scan, as determined by radiology team,or has
             had a lung cancer screen within 30 days of enrollment into this protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current enrollment or plans to enroll in another smoking cessation program in the next
             9 months.

          2. Unwilling to refrain from other nicotine substitutes (i.e., OTC or prescription
             medication for smoking cessation) or smoking cessation treatments in the next 9
             months.

          3. Current use of certain medications: (1) Smoking cessation meds (last 7 days), i.e.,
             Wellbutrin, Bupropion, Zyban, NRT, Chantix.

          4. A positive urine pregnancy test during the screening period. Women who are one year
             post-menopausal, or who have had a tubal ligation or a partial or full hysterectomy
             will not be subject to a urine pregnancy test.

          5. Pregnant, breast-feeding or of childbearing potential and is not protected by a
             medically acceptable, effective method of birth control while enrolled in the study.
             Medically acceptable contraceptives include: (1) approved hormonal contraceptives
             (such as birth control pills, patches, implants or injections), (2) barrier methods
             (such as a condom or diaphragm) used with a spermicide, or (3) an intrauterine device
             (IUD). Contraceptive measures sold for emergency use after unprotected sex are not
             acceptable methods for routine use.

          6. Exclusive use of tobacco products other than cigarettes, such as (but not limited to)
             cigars, chew, snuff, pipe or e-cigs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Cinciripini, PHD, MS, BS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul Cinciripini, PHD, MS, BS</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-0919</phone>
    <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Research Operations</last_name>
      <email>CR_Study_Registration@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Smoking Cessation</keyword>
  <keyword>Low Dose computed tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>LDCT</keyword>
  <keyword>Quitline</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>Surveys</keyword>
  <keyword>Counseling</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking cessation drugs</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-Smoking Drug</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine replacement therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>NRT</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine Patch</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nicotine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carbon Monoxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

