<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03056235</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ELAPR-P1D</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03056235</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Efficacy of ELAPR002f and ELAPR002g in Females and Males With Atrophic Acne Scars</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Within-subject, Placebo-controlled, Single-blind Study to Evaluate the Efficacy of ELAPR002f and ELAPR002g in Females and Males With Atrophic Acne Scars</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Elastagen Pty Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Elastagen Pty Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is designed to evaluate the efficacy of two formulations of a cross-linked
      tropoelastin matrix given the product codes ELAPR002f and ELAPR002g (collectively referred to
      as ELAPR or ELAPR002) for the treatment of rolling atrophic acne scars when administered as
      intradermal implants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study consists of a pre-screen visit followed by seven study visits. There will be a
      pre-screen visit where up to 30 potential study subjects will have 2D and 3D photographs
      taken of the candidate treatment fields to enable the Sponsor and Trial Centre staff to set
      practical guidelines for subject recruitment based on example atrophic acne scar images and
      published acne scar assessment scales. Subjects participating in the pre-screen period may be
      invited to participate in the full study if they are considered to be able to meet the
      eligibility criteria.

      There will be a screening visit to confirm eligibility and to assess baseline parameters
      (D-28 to D-1). In addition, the proposed treatment fields on each side of the face will be
      selected at screening and recorded with 2D &amp; 3D photographs and their location marked in
      detail on acetate sheets.

      For enrolled subjects there will be three intradermal (i.d.) treatment sessions of ELAPR002f
      or ELAPR002g and placebo, given at one-monthly intervals (approximately D0, D28 and D56). The
      treatment at D0 will be administered so as to reduce the appearance of the atrophic rolling
      acne scars in the treatment field relative to the surrounding skin. The treatments at D28 and
      D56 will be given to optimise the treatment outcome and to minimise the appearance of the
      atrophic rolling acne scars in the treatment field.

      In addition to the facial acne scars, a minimum of 5 subjects in each treatment group will
      also receive treatment on two moderate to severe, distensible, rolling acne scars present
      approximately 5-10cm apart on the back or torso.

      There will be an assessment visit 14 and 84 days after the first treatment session (D14 and
      D84) to review any adverse events and assess the implant sites.

      ELAPR002f or ELAPR002g will be administered alone vs. placebo. Subjects will be followed for
      a total of 24 weeks (to D168) following the first treatment, with efficacy and safety
      assessments undertaken at each study visit. At the final follow-up visit (D168) a biopsy
      sample will be taken from of each of the treated atrophic acne scars on the back or torso
      (active and placebo treated) from those subjects who received treatment to scars on the back
      or torso.

      Each study subject will act as their own control with active and placebo treatments given
      single-blind to treatment fields on contralateral sides of the face. Prior to administration
      the selected treatment fields will be identified and marked with a washable marker using the
      2D and 3D images and acetate sheets created at the screening visit to ensure consistency of
      anatomic sites for treatment (and biopsy for those subjects receiving treatment to the back
      or torso).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of the dimensions of acne scars pre and post treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The volume of acne scar depressions within the treatment field will be measured using 3D camera analysis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of product integration into dermal tissue using histological analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects who receive treatments to acne scars on the torso will undergo biopsy and the tissue analysed using histology techniques. The level of product persisting in the dermis will be assessed as a score out of 5 and dermal and epidermal thickness measured pre and post treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrophic Acne Scar</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ELAPR002f</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ELAPR002f is a tropoelastin gel cross-linked with derivatised hyaluronic acid</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ELAPR002g</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ELAPR002g is a tropoelastin gel cross-linked with derivatised hyaluronic acid</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Saline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ELAPR002f</intervention_name>
    <description>30mg/ml Tropoelastin cross-linked with derivatised hyaluronic acid</description>
    <arm_group_label>ELAPR002f</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ELAPR002g</intervention_name>
    <description>40mg/ml Tropoelastin cross-linked with derivatised hyaluronic acid</description>
    <arm_group_label>ELAPR002g</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>Saline control</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saline control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female/male subjects with matched treatment fields of approximately 2cm x 2cm on each
             side of the face on the temples or cheek bones that each contain a minimum of two
             rolling atrophic acne scars that are distensible when stretched between one's fingers
             and that are classified as moderate to severe on the scales detailed at Appendix 2.

          -  Acne scars in areas of otherwise normal healthy skin.

          -  Age: 18 - 55 years.

          -  Capable of providing voluntary informed consent.

          -  Good general health.

          -  Female subjects who are sexually active will be of non-child bearing potential (i.e.,
             surgically sterilized or postmenopausal), abstain from sexual intercourse, or use a
             reliable method of contraception (e.g. hormonal contraceptive, condom, IUD) for at
             least 30 days prior to dosing and during the duration of the study.

          -  Fitzpatrick skin types I, II, III, IV or V.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No active ongoing acne lesions on the face (or back and torso for the subjects who
             will also receive treatment in these areas).

          -  Subjects who present with predominantly ice pick or box scars.

          -  Current or previous treatment of atrophic acne scars with fillers, lasers, or deep
             chemical peels which reach the dermis, or any other medical or surgical treatment
             which in the investigators opinion could reasonably be deemed to impact on the results
             of the current clinical study.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to tropoelastin, hyaluronic acid or any other component of
             ELAPR002f or ELAPR002g.

          -  Female subjects with a positive pregnancy test, women refusing to agree to adequate
             contraception and pregnancy tests during the study, or women who are planning to
             become pregnant during the period of the trial.

          -  Participation in a clinical trial of a pharmacological agent within 1 month prior to
             screening.

          -  Clinically significant haematology or biochemistry findings at screening.

          -  Positive test for hepatitis B, hepatitis C or HIV at screening.

          -  Bleeding diathesis, anticoagulant drugs, thrombocytopenia or clinically significant
             prolonged APTT or PT.

          -  Chronic use of aspirin, other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs or other
             anti-platelet agents.

          -  History of keloid formation.

          -  History of granulomatous or connective tissue disease.

          -  Systemic corticosteroids within last 12 weeks.

          -  Currently using topical retinoids, or have used topical retinoids in the past 8 weeks.

          -  Diabetes or other metabolic disorders that may interfere with the subject's response
             to treatment in the opinion of the investigator.

          -  Any serious medical condition which in the opinion of the investigator would have a
             strong possibility of requiring systemic corticosteroid medication.

          -  Females who are pregnant or lactating.

          -  Previous administration of tropoelastin.

          -  A history of anaphylaxis or allergic reactions including any known hypersensitivity to
             lidocaine.

          -  Use of any investigational product on the intended implant site in the previous 12
             months.

          -  Fitzpatrick skin types VI.

          -  Any other factor that in the opinion of the Investigator would make the subject unsafe
             or unsuitable for the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hammersmith Medicines Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Greater London</state>
        <zip>NW10 7EW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atrophic acne scar</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyaluronic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

