<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03059407</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00081186</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03059407</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Therapy Dog Presence on Pediatric Echocardiogram</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Animal Assisted Therapy on Quality, Completeness, and Patient and Parental Satisfaction in Children Undergoing Clinical Echocardiography</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Young children with known or suspected heart disease frequently have difficulty cooperating
      with a clinically ordered echocardiogram. Current distraction techniques vary in efficacy.
      There have been no studies examining the use of animal assisted therapy to improve
      echocardiogram quality and completeness, as well as the patient/parent experience.

      Hypotheses:

        1. The presence and interaction of therapy dogs with young children undergoing
           echocardiography in a clinical setting will result in more complete and higher quality
           echocardiograms compared to standard distraction techniques.

        2. Parents will report higher visit satisfaction scores and greater exam comfort for their
           children for echocardiograms performed with the aid of canine assisted therapy compared
           to use of standard distraction techniques.

      Study Activities and Population Group:

      Pilot Phase: Introduction of trained therapy dogs (approved by the Pets at Duke Therapy
      Program) for 10 echocardiograms to observe canine-patient interactions and determine best
      practices for inclusion of dog/handler team into the echocardiogram protocol.

      Study Phase: 150 subjects ages will be selected from all children ages 1 to 5 years
      presenting for clinically ordered echocardiograms during the study time period. Subjects will
      be assigned into one of three groups: 1) Canine assisted therapy only; 2) Canine assisted
      therapy plus standard distraction techniques; and 3) Standard distraction techniques only.
      Echocardiography reviewers will be blinded to subject study group and will assign quality and
      completeness score based on validated criteria. Parental satisfaction will be assessed using
      validated survey tools.

      Data analysis and risk/safety issues:

      All subjects will be assigned a random subject ID, with the only link to PHI stored in a Duke
      Redcap database. Statistical testing will be performed with the assistance of Tracy Spears
      (biostatistician in DCRI) who has assisted with development of testing tools. There are no
      physical risks associated with the echocardiogram portion of the study, and very minimal
      risks with the therapy dog portion of the study. Please see &quot;Pets at Duke&quot; policy included in
      study documents. There is a potential loss of confidentiality, although the only link between
      subject ID and PHI will be stored in a Duke Recap database.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design and Procedures:

      160 study subjects will be selected from all children 1 to 5 years of age presenting to the
      Duke University Pediatric Echocardiography Laboratory for a clinically ordered echocardiogram
      during the study period.

      Duke University Hospital has an established program for pet therapy that includes bedside
      visits from trained and certified therapy dogs. At present, these dog-handler teams are
      certified as therapy dogs, and then fulfill additional certification requirements in order to
      be allowed into patient rooms. As this program and certification requirements are already
      established, this project would be able to liaison with the Pets at Duke program to provide
      suitable dog-handler teams for the study. Therapy dog certification requires passage of the
      AKC Good Citizen Test as well as instruction and certification through a recognized therapy
      dog program (including North Carolina Pet Partners, and Carolina Canines for Service).
      Currently, dogs (of any breed) that are certified as therapy dogs undergo evaluation by a
      team at Duke University and, if appropriate, are able to perform lobby visits (Level 2 dogs)
      or bed/patient room visits (Level 3 dogs). Only Level 3 dogs would be included in this study.

      Data Collection:

        -  Subject demographics (age, ethnicity, gender, birth order, home ZIP code, city/rural
           designation)

        -  Presence and type of heart disease and interventions, if any

        -  Presence of a dog (breed to be specified) or other pet at home, exposure to other
           animals

        -  History of any traumatic canine experience (fears, bites)

        -  Presence of parental anxiety with dogs

        -  Completeness of echocardiogram based on existing protocol QA document

        -  Quality of echocardiogram (poor, average, good, excellent)

        -  Time required to perform echocardiogram

        -  Assessment of echocardiogram complexity (low, medium, high)

        -  Patient and parental/guardian comfort and satisfaction with echocardiogram experience

        -  Handler assessment of dog comfort throughout echocardiogram

        -  Handler assessment of quality of dog-subject interaction

      Echocardiography Data Echocardiography completeness, quality, time and complexity will be
      assessed by either co-PI, who will be blinded to the subject group or presence of a dog
      during the echocardiogram.

        -  Echo completeness will be assessed using a numerical version of the existing protocol
           document used for QA

        -  Quality of the echocardiogram will be assessed using a qualitative scale derived from
           published pediatric echocardiography studies

        -  Time required to perform echocardiogram will be measured from time stamp on first image
           to time stamp on last image, automatically displayed for each echo.

      Video Recording of Therapy Dog Interaction with Subject A video recording of the therapy dog
      interaction with the subject will be performed. This video review is part of a separate Duke
      University study investigating how therapy dogs behave around young children (Duke IACUC
      Protocol A112-14-05) and will not be analyzed as part of this study. It is likely that an
      image of the subject will be captured on the video, but none of the subject's protected
      health information or subject ID number will be included with the video. No video recordings
      will be released beyond the therapy dog analysis.

      Timeline:

      The study will be broken into 4 distinct phases:

        1. Initial Phase (3 months): Medical team training and inclusion of study metrics into
           daily routine of the Duke University Hospital Pediatric Echocardiography Laboratory.

        2. Pilot phase (3 months):

             1. 10 non-randomized subjects will be recruited and matched with dog-handler teams

             2. Through observation of dog-handler-child behavior and suggested interventions, a
                list of techniques will be developed for use in the main study. This will be an
                extension of knowledge gained from patient visits performed by therapy dogs in
                other settings within Duke Hospital.

           i. Suggested interventions may include, but are not limited to: having the dog lie next
           to the child on the bed, having the child practice resting their hand on the dog,
           demonstrating probe placement on the dog prior to placement on the child c. The
           behaviors rated as most helpful by sonographers and dog handlers will be selected as a
           list of techniques from which to select for consistent use during the main study.

        3. Study phase (12 months)

             1. Subjects will be approached for participation and randomized into study group as
                outlined above

             2. Study data will be collected as outlined above

        4. Data analysis and manuscript submission (12 months)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 25, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Subjects will be assigned into one of three groups: 1) Canine assisted therapy only; 2) Canine assisted therapy plus standard distraction techniques; and 3) Standard distraction techniques only.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of echocardiogram</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Echocardiography completeness, quality, time and complexity will be assessed by co-PI, who will be blinded to the subject group or presence of a dog during the echocardiogram.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be measured by parent questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Dog Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dog therapy only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Canine assisted therapy only during echocardiogram</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dog plus standard distraction tech</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Canine assisted therapy plus standard distraction techniques during echocardiogram</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard distraction technique only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard distraction techniques only during echocardiogram.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dog therapy only</intervention_name>
    <description>Canine assisted therapy only during echocardiogram</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dog therapy only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dog plus standard distraction tech</intervention_name>
    <description>Canine assisted therapy plus standard distraction techniques during echo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dog plus standard distraction tech</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard distraction techniques only</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard distraction techniques (such as watching a movie) only during echocardiogram</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard distraction technique only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Study subjects will be selected from all children 1 to 5 years of age presenting to
             the Duke University Pediatric Echocardiography Laboratory (Duke Peds Echo Lab) for a
             clinically ordered echocardiogram during the study time period

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  parental or child refusal to participate;

          -  known allergy to dogs;

          -  fear of dogs;

          -  concern for overly aggressive child behavior towards the dog;

          -  or concern for immune system function/infectious risk that could be worsened by animal
             exposure.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Piers Barker</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mingfen Xu, MSN</last_name>
    <phone>919-668-6352</phone>
    <email>mingfen.xu@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Piers Barker, MD</last_name>
    <phone>919-681-5166</phone>
    <email>piers.barker@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mingfen Xu, MSN</last_name>
      <phone>919-668-6352</phone>
      <email>mingfen.xu@duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Piers Barker, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

