<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03059004</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1U01AR071658-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03059004</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparing Different Types of Physical Therapy for Treating People With a Meniscal Tear and Osteoarthritis</brief_title>
  <acronym>TeMPO</acronym>
  <official_title>Treatment of Meniscal Problems in Osteoarthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>State University of New York at Buffalo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Cleveland Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Melbourne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Knee osteoarthritis is a disabling problem affecting over 15 million adults in the United
      States. Many people who have knee arthritis also experience painful meniscal tears. There are
      a number of different treatments that can be used to manage meniscal tears in the presence of
      knee arthritis. Treatments include surgically removing the damaged part of the meniscus;
      strengthening exercises to improve pain and function; manual therapy including massage and
      mobilization; acupuncture; and others. The combination of surgery and exercise therapy was
      long thought to be the best treatment. However, recent studies have shown that surgery
      followed by physical therapy is no more effective than physical therapy by itself.

      While physical therapy alone has been shown to result in similar pain relief as arthroscopic
      surgery, researchers have not yet done studies to determine what type of physical therapy is
      best for people with knee arthritis and meniscal tears. In the &quot;TeMPO&quot; Trial, we will be
      comparing 4 different, non-operative physical therapy regimens in order to gain a better
      understanding of how physical therapy works and what regimen will best reduce pain and
      improve function in persons with meniscal tear and osteoarthritis. The four arms in this
      randomized trial will contain different combinations of therapeutic treatments including
      in-clinic therapist-supervised exercise, in-clinic topical therapies, and exercises to be
      completed at home. Subjects in three of the arms will also receive motivational SMS (text)
      messages intended to improve adherence to the home exercise regimen.

      TeMPO is designed as a randomized controlled trial. Participants will be assigned randomly to
      one of the four arms. All arms include therapies that have been previously shown to work in
      clinical settings. One arm also contains some placebo treatments. The placebo treatments will
      help us to understand what aspects of physical therapy actually make people feel better.

      Our hypothesis is that subjects in the arm that includes in-clinic physical therapy and a
      home exercise regimen will experience more pain relief than subjects in each of the other
      arms. Also, we expect that subjects in the arm that receives the home exercise regimen and
      SMS messages will experience more pain relief than subjects in the arm that receives home
      exercise without the SMS messages.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Knee osteoarthritis is a disabling problem affecting over 15 million adults in the United
      States. Many people who have knee arthritis also experience painful meniscal tears. There are
      a number of different treatments that can be used to address meniscal tears in the presence
      of knee arthritis. These include surgically removing the damaged part of the meniscus;
      strengthening exercises; manual therapy including massage and mobilization; and others. The
      combination of surgery and exercise therapy was long thought to be the best treatment.
      However, recent studies have shown that surgery followed by physical therapy leads to similar
      levels of pain relief as physical therapy alone.

      While physical therapy appears to be useful in knee osteoarthritis and meniscal tear,
      research is needed to determine what type of physical therapy is best for people with these
      conditions. The &quot;TeMPO&quot; Trial will compare 4 different non-operative regimens in order to
      gain a better understanding of how physical therapy works and to determine which regimen will
      best reduce participants' pain and improve their function. The four arms in this trial will
      contain different combinations of therapeutic treatments including in-clinic supervised
      exercise therapy, in-clinic topical therapies, and exercises to be completed at home. Some of
      the arms will also receive text messages designed to improve adherence to assigned exercises.
      All arms include therapies that have been previously shown to work in clinical settings. One
      arm also contains some placebo treatments. The placebo treatments will help identify the
      aspects of physical therapy that make people feel better.

      The four arms in the TeMPO study are as follows:

        1. Home Exercise Program

        2. Home Exercise Program + Motivational SMS messages

        3. Home Exercise Program + Motivational SMS messages + In-Clinic topical therapy

        4. Home Exercise Program + Motivational SMS messages + In-Clinic Exercise Therapy
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 6, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Four arm parallel randomized controlled trial.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Outcomes assessors will not be appraised of treatment arm.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between arms in change in the KOOS Pain score over three months (Arm 4 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 2; Arm 2 vs. Arm 1. Arm 4 vs. Arm 3)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in function</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between arms in change in the KOOS ADL score over three months (Arm 4 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 2; Arm 2 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 3)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between arms in change in quality of life measured with the EQ-5D scale over three months (Arm 4 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 2; Arm 2 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 3)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Binary treatment failure indicator</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between arms in treatment failure defined as either not reaching improvement of &gt;=8 points on KOOS Pain or receiving injection or undergoing index knee surgery within three months (Arm 4 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 2; Arm 2 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 3)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forty meter fast-paced walk</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between arms in change in 40 m fast-paced walk (seconds) over three months (Arm 4 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 2; Arm 2 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 3)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>30-second sit to stand</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between arms in number of repetitions (of sit to stand) over 30 seconds</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Strength of quadriceps, hamstrings, gluteus medius</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between arms in strength (pounds-cm) between arms, measured at three sites (quadriceps, hamstrings, gluteus medius)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Single Leg Balance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between arms in number of seconds participant can stand on single leg without moving hands off hips, stepping or stumbling, abducting or flexing hip beyond 30 deg, lifting heel or forefoot off ground.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Durability of pain relief</measure>
    <time_frame>3-12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between arms in proportion of subjects who maintain through 12 months the benefit (in KOOS Pain) achieved at 3 months. (Arm 4 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 2; Arm 2 vs. Arm 1; Arm 4 vs. Arm 3 )</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">860</enrollment>
  <condition>Meniscal Degeneration</condition>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1. Home Exercise Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Home Exercise group receives the TeMPO Home Exercise Program (including a set of weights, a DVD showing how to complete the TeMPO exercises, and a pamphlet outlining instructions on how to complete the exercises and how often should they be done).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2. Home Exercise Program + SMS Messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm receive the TeMPO Home Exercise Program and motivational SMS messages to encourage them to adhere to the TeMPO Home Exercise regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3. In-Clinic Topical Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm receive the TeMPO Home Exercise Program, motivational SMS messages to encourage them to adhere to the TeMPO Home Exercise Program, and 14 in-clinic sessions with a trained physical therapist. The therapist will apply topical therapies: ultrasound, gel, and manual therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4. In-Clinic Exercise Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm will receive the TeMPO Home Exercise Program, SMS motivational messages to encourage them to adhere to the TeMPO Home Exercise Program and 14 in-clinic sessions with a trained physical therapist. The therapist will supervise the participant in a rigorous set of strengthening and stretching exercises.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TeMPO Home Exercise Program</intervention_name>
    <description>This exercise program includes quadriceps, gluteus medius, gluteus maximus, and core exercises. The program includes a DVD and multi-page instruction pamphlet.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1. Home Exercise Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2. Home Exercise Program + SMS Messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3. In-Clinic Topical Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4. In-Clinic Exercise Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Motivational SMS Messages</intervention_name>
    <description>The motivational SMS messages will be sent three times per week encouraging participants to complete their exercises.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2. Home Exercise Program + SMS Messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3. In-Clinic Topical Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>4. In-Clinic Exercise Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>In-Clinic Topical Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be assigned to a physical therapist and will attend 14 in-clinic topical therapy sessions. Sessions will include application of ultrasound, gel, and manual therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>3. In-Clinic Topical Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>In-Clinic Exercise Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be assigned to a physical therapist and will attend 14 in-clinic exercise and manual therapy sessions. Sessions will include the same exercises from the Home Exercise Program but the in-clinic therapy setting will allow for more personalization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>4. In-Clinic Exercise Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Knee pain of at least 21 days duration if traumatic; no minimum duration if
             non-traumatic

          -  Age 45 -85 years

          -  Physician diagnosis of meniscal tear

          -  Evidence on MRI of meniscal tear

          -  Evidence of osteoarthritic changes on imaging: Cartilage damage on MRI, osteophyte or
             joint space narrowing on X-ray

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  KL-Grade 4

          -  Inflammatory arthritis

          -  Prior APM or TKR on index knee; or any surgery on index knee in prior 6 mo

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Contraindication to MRI

          -  Daily use of strong opioids

          -  Intra-articular therapy in last 4 weeks

          -  Non-English speaking

          -  History of dementia

          -  Currently resides in a nursing home

          -  Current claimant of worker's compensation for this condition
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chuck Washabaugh, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute for Arthritis, Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS, NIH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jeffrey N Katz, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>6177325338</phone>
    <email>jnkatz@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Faith Selzer, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>6175258301</phone>
    <email>fselzer@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Faith Selzer, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>617-525-8617</phone>
      <email>fselzer@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>James K Sullivan, BA</last_name>
      <phone>617 732 4313</phone>
      <email>jsullivan76@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey N Katz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University at Buffalo Medical Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa Kluczynski, MS</last_name>
      <phone>716-829-2561</phone>
      <email>mk67@buffalo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leslie Bisson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Leddy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jen Turczyk</last_name>
      <phone>216-444-2924</phone>
      <email>turczyk@ccf.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Morgan Jones, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kurt Spindler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elaine Husni, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15237</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jill Tarr, LCSW, ACSW</last_name>
      <phone>412-432-3721</phone>
      <email>tarrja@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jay Irrgang, PhD, PT</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aaron Mares, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ale Gil, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 16, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jeffrey Neil Katz, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Physician, Brigham and Women's Hospital Professor of Medicine, Harvard Medical School</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>physical therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>TEMPO</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

