<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03054103</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00031444</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03054103</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sedation Methods During Cataract Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comparison of Midazolam vs. Midazolam/Ketamine for Conscious Sedation in Patients Undergoing Phacoemulsification Under Topical Anesthesia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Phacoemulsification is the most common surgical procedure performed in the United
      States and European Union and sedation is commonly used during phacoemulsification to help
      alleviate patient anxiety and prevent the patient from interfering with the procedure. The
      investigators have administered ketamine in addition to midazolam in this regard. To study
      the effectiveness of this technique, The investigators proposed a study to determine if
      adding low-dose ketamine to midazolam has any beneficial (or negative) effects on operating
      conditions, patient satisfaction, and recovery during and after unilateral
      phacoemulsification procedures performed using topical anesthesia and intravenous (IV)
      conscious sedation.

      Methods: In a free-standing Outpatient Surgery Center, the investigators conducted a
      randomized, double-masked, 3-arm, prospective comparison of IV midazolam only vs. midazolam
      with ketamine 5 mg IV vs. midazolam with ketamine 10 mg IV. The investigators then measured a
      single surgeon's assessment of surgical conditions, self-reported patient satisfaction,
      postoperative pain score, and duration of postoperative stay. The investigators also analyzed
      the dose of midazolam required to meet subjective anxiolysis in each group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phacoemulsification is the most common surgical procedure performed in the United States and
      European Union. In addition, the number of diagnoses of cataracts is expected to double from
      25,000,000 in 2010 to 50,000,000 in 2050 while the incidence of phacoemulsification is also
      increasing. Therefore, any attempt to optimize outcome and efficiency is significant.

      Sedation is commonly used during phacoemulsification to help alleviate patient anxiety and
      prevent the patient from interfering with the procedure. However, a great deal of variation
      exists in anesthetic management of these cases. Investigators have published use of a number
      of agents for sedation in the literature. These include midazolam, clonidine, propofol,
      fentanyl, dexmedetomidine, remifentanil, and oral diazepam. Intravenous (IV) clonidine has a
      half-life of 9-13 h and increased risk of postoperative hypotension. Propofol causes
      disinhibition and it has to be titrated during surgery to prevent oversedation. Opioids carry
      an increased risk of respiratory depression, prolonged sedation, as well as delirium in the
      elderly. Finally, oral medications do not allow for quick dose adjustments during surgery.

      Intravenous midazolam is commonly used for sedation during phacoemulsification and other
      minor procedures. It has properties as an anxiolytic, muscle relaxant, and it is effective at
      reducing intraocular pressure. However, anxious patients administered benzodiazepines may
      require higher doses during cataract surgery which can lead to oversedation or disinhibition
      with subsequent patient movement. These responses can reduce the patient's ability to follow
      simple commands which can affect surgical outcome. Additionally, patients who receive too
      much sedation may fall asleep and wake up startled, similarly compromising the outcome of the
      surgery.

      In the search for additional medications that can improve surgical conditions and patient
      comfort during phacoemulsification, the investigators explored the use of a medication that
      can improve analgesia and reduce patient movement during procedures, namely ketamine.
      Ketamine is an NMDA antagonist with both sedative and analgesic properties and has minimal
      effects on respiration. Ketamine has been used to premedicate and sedate patients undergoing
      day care procedures without adverse effects, and patients, typically, remain cooperative
      albeit being sedated. These properties along with its relatively short elimination half-life
      of 2 h (compared with 3-4 h for midazolam) make ketamine an attractive agent for sedation
      during monitored anesthesia care (MAC) for cataract surgery.

      The purpose of this study was to determine if adding low-dose ketamine to midazolam has any
      beneficial (or negative) effects on operating conditions, patient satisfaction, and recovery
      during and after unilateral phacoemulsification procedures performed using topical anesthesia
      and IV conscious sedation.

      The investigators measured the surgeon's assessment of the participant's cooperation during
      surgery according to a predetermined Likert scale. The investigators also recorded the
      following outcome measures regarding each participant's surgery: 1) total dose of midazolam,
      2) average time spent in the procedural room, 3) postoperative length of stay (LOS), and 4)
      average postoperative pain score. The subjects received a survey inquiring about the
      subjects' comfort and sedation level during surgery. Finally, the investigators recorded the
      following demographic data for all participants: gender, age, psychiatric diagnoses, and use
      of CNS, psychiatric, or opioid medications.

      Statistical Analysis The investigators used Fisher's exact test for examining data expressed
      as percentages, and Students t-test for yes/no data, and repeated measures ANOVA for 3 group
      analysis (LOS, surgical duration). The investigators judged significance at a P-value of
      0.05. The investigators utilized a generalized estimated equations (GEE) to fit a logistic
      model to assess differences in the responses of patients based on amount of ketamine
      received. The GEE approach can fit models to correlated outcomes, as in the case where
      subjects had more than one procedure performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 3, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 11, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 5, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized, controlled, double-masked, three-armed clinical comparison</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Surgical conditions and patient response not aware of medication given.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Eye Mobility During Surgery (See Link to Study Protocol for Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative, end of operation reported</time_frame>
    <description>Scale of mobility of eye during surgery rate 0 (no movement) to 3 (movement enough to stop surgery).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of Comfort (See Link to Study Protocol for Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>Obtained on the first day after surgery during the subject's routine postoperative check in the Ophthalmology Clinic.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of comfort (0-3; 0=very comfortable to 3=extremely uncomfortable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PACU Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>This will occur one time only, in a range of 20 to 30 minutes after the surgery is completed.</time_frame>
    <description>This is obtained from the records as time spent in the PACU (Recovery Room) after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nausea</measure>
    <time_frame>This will occur from time of entry into PACU to time of departure after their surgery. (One time only, in a range of 20 to 30 minutes after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported incidence of nausea. This will be assessed by asking the subjects once (just prior to discharge from the PACU) whether they experienced any nausea while they were in the PACU (Recovery Room) and will be a measurement of the count of participants that experienced nausea during this period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Phacoemulsification</condition>
  <condition>Cataract</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Midazolam alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug: Midazolam titrated 0.5-2.0 mg + normal saline placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Midazolam + Ketamine 5 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug: Midazolam titrated 0.5-2.0 mg + Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Midazolam + Ketamine 10 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug: Midazolam titrated 0.5-2.0 mg + Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Midazolam + Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Midazolam + Ketamine 5 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ketalar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Midazolam + Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML</intervention_name>
    <description>10 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Midazolam + Ketamine 10 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ketalar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Midazolam + Normal saline</intervention_name>
    <description>Preoperative control: Normal saline placebo given preoperatively. Then protocol followed for titration of midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Midazolam alone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients met inclusion criteria if they were between 18- and 80-years-old and
             undergoing elective cataract surgery performed by a single ophthalmologist (KW).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients younger than 18, older than 80, those with a serum creatinine &gt;3 mg/dl,
             advanced liver disease (liver enzymes twice the normal range or higher), and those
             with an allergy to any of the study medications were excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy N Harwood, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 10, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>November 7, 2017</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2018</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ketamine</keyword>
  <keyword>midazolam</keyword>
  <keyword>sedation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Midazolam</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_type>Study Protocol</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.dropbox.com/s/6048n2j5u8ycko5/DeId_PhacoData.pdf?dl=0</doc_url>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Midazolam Alone</title>
          <description>Drug: Titrated midazolam + normal saline placebo
Normal saline: Preoperative control: Normal saline placebo given preoperatively. Then protocol followed for titration of midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Midazolam + Ketamine 5 mg</title>
          <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML: 5 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P3">
          <title>Midazolam + Ketamine 10 mg</title>
          <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML: 10 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="41"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="29"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="35"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="41"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="29"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="35"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P3" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Midazolam Alone</title>
          <description>Drug: Titrated midazolam + normal saline placebo
Normal saline: Preoperative control: Normal saline placebo given preoperatively. Then protocol followed for titration of midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Midazolam + Ketamine 5 mg</title>
          <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML: 5 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Ketamine 10 mg</title>
          <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML: 10 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B4">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="41"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="29"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="35"/>
            <count group_id="B4" value="105"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="25"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="31"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="80"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="70.4" spread="8.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="69.1" spread="8.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="65.6" spread="9.8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="68" spread="9.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="53"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="22"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="16"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="52"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="41"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="29"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="35"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B4" value="105"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Eye Mobility During Surgery (See Link to Study Protocol for Scale)</title>
        <description>Scale of mobility of eye during surgery rate 0 (no movement) to 3 (movement enough to stop surgery).</description>
        <time_frame>Intraoperative, end of operation reported</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Midazolam Alone</title>
            <description>Drug: Titrated midazolam + normal saline placebo
Normal saline: Preoperative control: Normal saline placebo given preoperatively. Then protocol followed for titration of midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Midazolam + Ketamine 5 mg</title>
            <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML: 5 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Ketamine 10 mg</title>
            <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML: 10 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Eye Mobility During Surgery (See Link to Study Protocol for Scale)</title>
          <description>Scale of mobility of eye during surgery rate 0 (no movement) to 3 (movement enough to stop surgery).</description>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="41"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="35"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1.39" spread="0.63"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.41" spread="0.63"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="1.31" spread="0.63"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Measure of Comfort (See Link to Study Protocol for Scale)</title>
        <description>Measure of comfort (0-3; 0=very comfortable to 3=extremely uncomfortable</description>
        <time_frame>Obtained on the first day after surgery during the subject's routine postoperative check in the Ophthalmology Clinic.</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Midazolam Alone</title>
            <description>Drug: Titrated midazolam + normal saline placebo
Normal saline: Preoperative control: Normal saline placebo given preoperatively. Then protocol followed for titration of midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Midazolam + Ketamine 5 mg</title>
            <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML: 5 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Ketamine 10 mg</title>
            <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML: 10 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Measure of Comfort (See Link to Study Protocol for Scale)</title>
          <description>Measure of comfort (0-3; 0=very comfortable to 3=extremely uncomfortable</description>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="41"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="35"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1.29" spread="0.62"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.18" spread="0.60"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="1.17" spread="0.59"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>PACU Length of Stay</title>
        <description>This is obtained from the records as time spent in the PACU (Recovery Room) after surgery.</description>
        <time_frame>This will occur one time only, in a range of 20 to 30 minutes after the surgery is completed.</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Midazolam Alone</title>
            <description>Drug: Titrated midazolam + normal saline placebo
Normal saline: Preoperative control: Normal saline placebo given preoperatively. Then protocol followed for titration of midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Midazolam + Ketamine 5 mg</title>
            <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML: 5 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Ketamine 10 mg</title>
            <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML: 10 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>PACU Length of Stay</title>
          <description>This is obtained from the records as time spent in the PACU (Recovery Room) after surgery.</description>
          <units>Minutes</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="41"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="35"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="19.2" spread="7.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="19.0" spread="6.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="20.1" spread="10.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Nausea</title>
        <description>Self-reported incidence of nausea. This will be assessed by asking the subjects once (just prior to discharge from the PACU) whether they experienced any nausea while they were in the PACU (Recovery Room) and will be a measurement of the count of participants that experienced nausea during this period</description>
        <time_frame>This will occur from time of entry into PACU to time of departure after their surgery. (One time only, in a range of 20 to 30 minutes after surgery.</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Midazolam Alone</title>
            <description>Drug: Titrated midazolam + normal saline placebo
Normal saline: Preoperative control: Normal saline placebo given preoperatively. Then protocol followed for titration of midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Midazolam + Ketamine 5 mg</title>
            <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML: 5 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O3">
            <title>Ketamine 10 mg</title>
            <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML: 10 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Nausea</title>
          <description>Self-reported incidence of nausea. This will be assessed by asking the subjects once (just prior to discharge from the PACU) whether they experienced any nausea while they were in the PACU (Recovery Room) and will be a measurement of the count of participants that experienced nausea during this period</description>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="41"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="29"/>
                <count group_id="O3" value="35"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Midazolam Alone</title>
          <description>Drug: Titrated midazolam + normal saline placebo
Normal saline: Preoperative control: Normal saline placebo given preoperatively. Then protocol followed for titration of midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Midazolam + Ketamine 5 mg</title>
          <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 0.5 ML: 5 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E3">
          <title>Ketamine 10 mg</title>
          <description>Drug: Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML
Ketamine 10 MG/ML: 1 ML: 10 mg ketamine IV given just prior to onset of case. Then titrated midazolam up to 2 mg IV at beginning and during case.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="41"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="35"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="41"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="29"/>
                <counts group_id="E3" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="35"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Study may be a bit underpowered for the small differences between groups in measured outcomes.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Timothy Harwood</name_or_title>
      <organization>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</organization>
      <phone>3367164498</phone>
      <email>tharwood@wakehealth.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

