<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03052907</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCCC-PS01112</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03052907</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Breast Screening &amp; Patient Navigation (BSPAN2): Evaluating a De-Centralized Regional Delivery System for Rural Underserved</brief_title>
  <official_title>Breast Screening &amp; Patient Navigation (BSPAN2): Evaluating a De-Centralized Regional Delivery System for Rural Underserved</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will expand BSPan's reach and sustainability by systematizing how to enable
      counties to assume responsibility for one or two of the components while Moncrief/uTSW
      continues to provide centralized financial review and reimbursement as the Texas BCCS
      contractor. The investigators will prospectively identify which counties have the necessary
      program capacity, then test whether implementation of BSPan tailored to a county's capacity
      and local needs can lead to equivalent program success in an additional 12 rural counties.
      Findings will be used to develop a model by which BSPan benefits can be brought to rural
      communities across the country.

      The investigators will use a readiness assessment criteria (RaC) to gauge county capacity and
      readiness for BSPan program implementation. The goal of our evaluation is to demonstrate
      whether a regional decentralized delivery (hub-and-spoke) model can be sustained and increase
      program reach to underserved rural women. The RaC tool serves two purposes: 1) to determine
      county capacity and 2) harness program data to facilitate communication during operations
      between a central BSPan hub and each county partner (spokes).

      Our evaluation will analyze county training and implementation of BSPan program components,
      and comprehensive screening processes of the hub and spoke model. The investigators will use
      county site visits and selected interviews of participants and staff to gain insight into
      factors at the participant and county levels that facilitate adoption and implementation of
      comprehensive screening processes, in conjunction with key quantitative metrics and process
      outcomes.

      The investigators will apply the Glasgow Re-aiM model to guide our evaluation of BSPan
      program component implementation in each county. Re-aiM specifies dimensions at the
      participant and organizational levels. Dimensions are defined as the intervention's: 1) Reach
      into the target population, 2) effectiveness in modifying risk, 3) adoption by target
      settings, 4) consistent implementation, and 5) Maintenance of its effects among participants
      and target settings. our mixed-methods approach will enable focus at both the individual and
      organizational levels and has been successfully used to assess other similar screening and
      health promotion programs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific aims are to:

        1. Identify readiness assessment criteria (RAC) essential in determining a rural county's
           capacity to support comprehensive mammography and appropriate follow-up services.
           Through a mixed-method analysis, using qualitative and quantitative techniques, we will
           define essential factors in leadership, infrastructure and local resources across the
           five counties of the initial BSPAN network.

        2. Using the RAC (defined in Aim 1), we will determine which of the five BSPAN1 counties
           have capacity to manage and sustain the Outreach &amp; Health Promotion and Delivery &amp;
           Navigation components of the program (High Capacity), and which have the capacity to
           manage and sustain only the Outreach &amp; Health Promotion component (Medium Capacity). We
           will monitor the performance of two High Capacity and one Medium Capacity counties to
           increase program responsibility, adjust BSPAN support as needed, and calibrate the
           sensitivity of our RAC tool.

        3. Expand BSPAN to 12 new rural and underserved counties according to RAC score and
           evaluate each county's ability to implement program components and increase
           comprehensive mammography and appropriate follow-up. Using the RAC (defined in Aim 1),
           we will characterize the capacity in each of the 12 new counties to implement components
           of the BSPAN program (High, Medium, and Low Capacity). We will monitor process measures
           and outcomes in each county at regular intervals. Results of BSPAN2 will demonstrate a
           sustainable hub-and-spoke model of service delivery that capitalizes on local community
           strengths to care for their own residents. This expansion will enable 12 new county
           partners to increase screening access, improve time to diagnostic resolution, and
           facilitate timely referral to local treatment services, while maintaining services
           levels in the original five counties. BSPAN2 will also produce an assessment tool and
           internet-based patient tracking application that can be used to disseminate a
           hub-and-spoke model for delivery of mammography services to rural communities across the
           country.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survey items measuring delivery of comprehensive mammography services and appropriate follow-up for women in rural and underserved counties.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>We will use NVivo 9.0 (QSR International, Melbourne AUS) to collate and analyze data from site visits notes, semi-structured interviews, and document analysis. NVivo, a well-respected qualitative data analysis software program, makes the analysis process transparent so that investigators can track their evolving analysis. Led by Drs. Lee and Inrig, the evaluation team and their staff will organize these codes into a codebook that relates data to behavioral and organizational theory. Regular meetings will enable the BSPAN evaluation team to test emergent themes and interpretation against the knowledge base of experts in clinical medicine (e.g. Argenbright), organizational behavior (Inrig, Lee), and screening behavior (Tiro). Cross-analysis of data from all sources will allow us to conduct an integrated analysis across BSPAN components to assess key steps and interface of mammography screening and appropriate follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18540</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer in Situ</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BSPAN Expansion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>We will expand BSPAN's reach and sustainability by systematizing how to enable counties to assume responsibility for one or two of the components while Moncrief/UTSW continues to provide centralized financial review and reimbursement as the Texas BCCS contractor. We will prospectively identify which counties have the necessary program capacity, then test whether implementation of BSPAN tailored to a county's capacity and local needs can lead to equivalent program success in an additional 12 rural counties (BSPAN2 total= 17 counties). Findings will be used to develop a model by which BSPAN benefits can be brought to rural communities across the country.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BSPAN</intervention_name>
    <description>Identify readiness assessment criteria (RAC) essential in determining a rural county's capacity to support comprehensive mammography and appropriate follow-up services.
Using the RAC, we will determine which of the five BSPAN1 counties have capacity to manage and sustain the Outreach &amp; Health Promotion and Delivery &amp; Navigation components of the program (High Capacity), and which have the capacity to manage and sustain only the Outreach &amp; Health Promotion component (Medium Capacity).
Expand BSPAN to 12 new rural and underserved counties according to RAC score and evaluate each county's ability to implement program components and increase comprehensive mammography and appropriate follow-up.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BSPAN Expansion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion criteria for patient participants include:

          -  adult females age 40-64,

          -  able to read, speak and comprehend English or Spanish,

          -  the capacity to comprehend study information, and

          -  ability to communicate with voice (to participate in interviews).

        Inclusion criteria for key county actors include:

          -  involved in facilitation of mammography screening services in the counties served by
             the BSPAN program.

          -  Both women and men will be eligible to participate.

          -  No racial or ethnic group will be excluded from participation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Exclusion criteria for patient participants:

          -  Patients who do not speak Spanish or English or have severely impaired hearing or
             speech or do not give informed consent will be excluded from participation (in
             interviews).

        Exclusion criteria for key county actors:

          -  individuals not involved in the facilitation of mammography screening services in one
             of the counties served by the BSPAN program will be excluded from participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Simon Lee, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma in Situ</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Carcinoma In Situ</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

