<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03057795</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16378</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2017-00222</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>16378</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03057795</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nivolumab and Brentuximab Vedotin After Stem Cell Transplant in Treating Patients With Relapsed or Refractory High-Risk Classical Hodgkin Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Study of Nivolumab and Brentuximab Vedotin Consolidation After Autologous Stem Cell Transplantation in Patients With High-Risk Classical Hodgkin Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>City of Hope Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>City of Hope Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well nivolumab and brentuximab vedotin work after stem cell
      transplant in treating patients with high-risk classical Hodgkin lymphoma that has come back
      or does not respond to treatment. Monoclonal antibodies, such as nivolumab and brentuximab
      vedotin, may interfere with the ability of cancer cells to grow and spread.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Assess the efficacy of nivolumab plus brentuximab vedotin consolidation after autologous
      stem cell transplantation (ASCT) in participants with relapsed/refractory Hodgkin lymphoma
      (HL), as assessed by 18-month progression-free survival (PFS).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Estimate the overall survival (OS), the cumulative incidence of relapse/progression, the
      cumulative incidence of non-relapse mortality (TRM) in participants with relapsed/ refractory
      HL who receive nivolumab plus brentuximab vedotin consolidation after ASCT.

      II. Estimate the overall response rate to nivolumab plus brentuximab vedotin therapy in
      participants with measurable disease after ASCT.

      III. Establish the safety and tolerability of nivolumab plus brentuximab vedotin when used as
      consolidation after ASCT in participants with relapsed/ refractory HL.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Evaluate the Lymphoma Response to Immunomodulatory therapy Criteria (LYRIC) definition of
      indeterminate response to guide the management of patients regarding treatment past
      progressive disease.

      II. Explore the impact of nivolumab plus brentuximab vedotin therapy on immune reconstitution
      after ASCT.

      III. Explore the prognostic impact of and temporal dynamics of minimal residual disease (MRD)
      in the peripheral blood as assessed by the next-generation sequencing-based ClonoSEQ
      platform.

      IV. Explore the prognostic impact of 9p24.1 abnormalities in tumor tissue assessed by
      fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) on outcomes after ASCT and nivolumab plus
      brentuximab vedotin post-ASCT consolidation therapy.

      V. Explore the relationship between immune cells and Hodgkin and Reed/Sternberg (HRS) in
      tumor samples by 6-color quantitative spatial image analysis using the Vectra system, and
      correlate with outcome after ASCT and nivolumab plus brentuximab vedotin post-ASCT
      consolidation therapy.

      VI. Explore whether genetic alterations (e.g. gene expression profiles or genetic mutations)
      in HL tumor samples are associated with outcome after ASCT and nivolumab plus brentuximab
      vedotin post-ASCT consolidation therapy.

      OUTLINE:

      Beginning 30-60 days post-ASCT, patients receive brentuximab vedotin intravenously (IV) over
      30 minutes and nivolumab IV over 60 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up
      to 8 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 30 and 100 days, at 3, 6,
      12, and 18 months from the start of treatment, and then biannually thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>From the first dose of study treatment to the first observation of disease relapse/progression or death from any cause, whichever occurs first, assessed at 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>PFS will be estimated using the product-limit method of Kaplan and Meier along with the Greenwood estimator of standard error. When there is no censoring in PFS prior to 18 months after the first dose of study treatment, the observed 18-month PFS will be compared to the baseline of 65% by one-sided exact test of binomial proportion. In case of censoring in PFS prior to 18 months after the first dose of study treatment, the Kaplan-Meier estimate for 18-month PFS along with the Greenwood standard error estimator will be used for the testing of null hypothesis at 65%.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of non-relapse mortality defined as the time from the first dose of study treatment to non-disease related death</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative incidence of non-relapse mortality as well as its confidence intervals will be estimated using competing risk methodology, treating the other event as a competing risk.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of relapse/progression defined as the time from the first dose of study treatment to disease relapse/progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative incidence of relapse/progression as well as its confidence intervals will be estimated using competing risk methodology, treating the other event as a competing risk.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of toxicities evaluated according to National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Observed toxicities will be summarized by type (organ affected or laboratory determination such as ANC), severity (by NCI CTCAE version 4.03 and nadir or maximum values for lab measures), date of onset, duration, reversibility, and attribution.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OS</measure>
    <time_frame>From the first dose of study treatment to death from any cause, assessed up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>OS will be estimated using the product-limit method of Kaplan and Meier along with the Greenwood estimator of standard error.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall response rate will be estimated by the proportion of patients achieving either complete response or partial response among participants with measurable disease after ASCT, along with the exact binomial confidence interval.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Classical Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation Recipient</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (brentuximab vedotin, nivolumab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Beginning 30-60 days post-ASCT, patients receive brentuximab vedotin IV over 30 minutes and nivolumab IV over 60 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 8 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brentuximab Vedotin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (brentuximab vedotin, nivolumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ADC SGN-35</other_name>
    <other_name>Adcetris</other_name>
    <other_name>Anti-CD30 Antibody-Drug Conjugate SGN-35</other_name>
    <other_name>Anti-CD30 Monoclonal Antibody-MMAE SGN-35</other_name>
    <other_name>Anti-CD30 Monoclonal Antibody-Monomethylauristatin E SGN-35</other_name>
    <other_name>cAC10-vcMMAE</other_name>
    <other_name>SGN-35</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (brentuximab vedotin, nivolumab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (brentuximab vedotin, nivolumab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BMS-936558</other_name>
    <other_name>MDX-1106</other_name>
    <other_name>NIVO</other_name>
    <other_name>ONO-4538</other_name>
    <other_name>Opdivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented informed consent

          -  Agreement to allow the use of archival tissue from pre-ASCT tumor biopsies

               -  If unavailable, exceptions may be granted with study principal investigator (PI)
                  approval

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of classical Hodgkin lymphoma (excluding nodular
             lymphocyte predominant Hodgkin lymphoma) according to the World Health Organization
             (WHO) classification, with hematopathology review at the participating institution

          -  Have high-risk relapsed or refractory Hodgkin lymphoma (HL), defined as:

               -  Primary refractory disease to front-line therapy

               -  Relapse within 1 year of completing front-line therapy

               -  Extranodal involvement at the time of pre-ASCT relapse

               -  B symptoms at pre-ASCT relapse

               -  More than one type of pre-ASCT salvage therapy required

          -  Planning to receive or have received autologous stem cell transplantation (ACST) per
             institutional standards as part of standard of care

               -  Pre-ASCT participants may consent but will not be eligible to begin treatment
                  until after ASCT, and will have to fulfill all inclusion and exclusion criteria
                  before starting protocol therapy

               -  All participants must initiate day 1 of protocol therapy within 30-60 days post
                  stem cell reinfusion; study PI can grant exception for a patient to start as late
                  as 75 days post stem cell reinfusion with a reasonable justification for delay
                  (e.g. recovery from post-ASCT toxicity) and this will not be a protocol
                  deviation, nor require an exception to be filed

          -  Recovery from ASCT toxicity as defined as outpatient status, able to drink, eat
             normally, and do not need intravenous hydration prior to day 1 of therapy

          -  Achieved at least stable disease to salvage treatment determined by positron emission
             tomography (PET)/computed tomography (CT) using 2014 Lugano Classification prior to
             ASCT

          -  Brentuximab vedotin naive OR had at least stable disease by Lugano Classification to
             prior brentuximab vedotin treatment

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1000/mm^3

          -  Platelets &gt;= 50,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 8 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) or 3 x ULN for Gilbert's disease

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 x ULN

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt;= 40 mL/min per 24 hour urine collection or the Cockcroft-Gault
             formula

          -  Forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) and carbon monoxide diffusion capacity
             (DLCO) (adjusted for Hb) &gt;= 50% adjusted

          -  Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) only: Negative urine or serum pregnancy test
             (minimum sensitivity 25 IU/L or equivalent units of human chorionic gonadotropin
             [HCG])

               -  If the urine test is positive or cannot be confirmed as negative, a serum
                  pregnancy test will be required

          -  Woman of childbearing potential (WOCBP): use two effective methods of contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method) or be surgically sterile, or abstain from heterosexual
             activity for the course of the study through 7 months post last dose of nivolumab

               -  WOCBP defined as not being surgically sterilized or have not been free from
                  menses for &gt; 1 year

               -  Male: use two effective methods of contraception (barrier method) or abstain from
                  heterosexual activity with the first dose of study therapy through 7 months post
                  last dose of nivolumab

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Post-ASCT anti-lymphoma or investigational therapy; immediate post-ASCT consolidative
             radiation therapy is allowed as long as it occurs prior to initiation of study
             therapy; baseline imaging and pulmonary function tests (PFTs) must be performed after
             completion of radiation

          -  Previous allogeneic transplant

          -  Total carmustine (BCNU) dose of &gt; 600 mg/m^2 with prior treatments including
             transplant conditioning regimen

          -  Live vaccine within 30 days prior to day 1 of protocol therapy (e.g. measles, mumps,
             rubella, varicella, yellow fever, rabies, Bacillus Calmette-Guerin [BCG], oral polio
             vaccine, and oral typhoid)

          -  Refractory to prior brentuximab vedotin (i.e. progression while on treatment)

          -  Refractory to prior anti-PD-1/PD-L1 agent

          -  History of prior &gt;= grade 3 hypersensitivity to either brentuximab vedotin or
             nivolumab

          -  History of another primary malignancy that has not been in remission for at least 3
             years; exceptions include:

               -  Basal cell carcinoma of the skin or

               -  Squamous cell carcinoma of the skin that has undergone potentially curative
                  therapy or

               -  In situ cervical cancer

          -  Known active central nervous system (CNS) involvement by lymphoma, including
             parenchymal and/or lymphomatous meningitis

          -  History of progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy (PML)

          -  Grade &gt;= 2 peripheral neuropathy at the present time

          -  Prior diagnosis of inherited or acquired immunodeficiency

          -  Condition requiring systemic treatment with either corticosteroids (&gt; 10 mg daily
             prednisone or equivalent) or other immunosuppressive medications within 14 days of
             study drug administration; exceptions are:

               -  Inhaled or topical steroids and

               -  Adrenal replacement doses &gt; 10 mg daily prednisone equivalents in the absence of
                  active autoimmune disease

          -  Uncontrolled illness including ongoing or active infection

          -  History of or active pneumonitis or interstitial lung disease:

               -  For history of pneumonitis to be an exclusion, patient had to have required
                  supplemental oxygen or corticosteroid treatment; radiographic changes alone are
                  not an exclusion

          -  An active, known or suspected autoimmune disease; the following are exceptions:

               -  Vitiligo

               -  Hemolytic anemia associated with the lymphoma (history of or at the present time)

               -  Type I diabetes mellitus

               -  Residual hypothyroidism due to autoimmune condition only requiring hormone
                  replacement

               -  Psoriasis not requiring systemic treatment, or

               -  Conditions not expected to recur in the absence of an external trigger

          -  Active or known history (standard pre-ASCT assessments) of:

               -  Hepatitis B or C infection

               -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

               -  Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS)

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating

          -  History of a cerebral vascular event (stroke or transient ischemic attack), unstable
             angina, myocardial infarction, or cardiac symptoms consistent with New York Heart
             Association Class III-IV within 6 months prior to day 1 of protocol therapy

          -  History or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality that
             might confound the results of the trial, interfere with the subject's participation
             for the full duration of the trial, or is not in the best interest of the subject to
             participate, in the opinion of the treating investigator

          -  Prospective participants who, in the opinion of the investigator, may not be able to
             comply with all study procedures (including compliance issues related to
             feasibility/logistics)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alex Herrera, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>City of Hope Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alex Herrera, MD</last_name>
      <phone>626-256-4673</phone>
      <email>aherrera@coh.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alex Herrera</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Referral Office https://www.mayo.edu/research/forms/cancer-clinical-trials</last_name>
      <phone>855-776-0015</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patrick B. Johnston, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hackensack University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alan P. Skarbnik</last_name>
      <phone>212-996-5900</phone>
      <email>Alan.Skarbnik@hackensackmeridian.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alan P. Skarbnik</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gunjan L. Shah</last_name>
      <email>shahg@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gunjan L. Shah</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yago L. Nieto</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-8750</phone>
      <email>ynieto@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yago L. Nieto</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leona A. Holmberg</last_name>
      <phone>206-288-2035</phone>
      <email>lholmber@fredhutch.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leona A. Holmberg</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

