<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03051139</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU00202855</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23HL118139</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03051139</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Strategy to Improve Implementation of LTVV for Patients w/ ARDS</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Cluster Randomized Controlled Trial of a Multi-component Strategy to Improve Implementation of Low Tidal Volume Ventilation for Patients With Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate whether a multi-component implementation
      strategy/quality improvement intervention comprised of 1) clinical decision support that
      couples a natural language processing (NLP) acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS)
      recognition tool with a clinician alert system, and 2) audit and feedback improves the
      implementation of low tidal volume ventilation (LTVV) for patients with the acute respiratory
      distress syndrome (ARDS). This will be accomplished with a cluster randomized controlled
      trial comparing the implementation strategy to usual care
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Setting:

      This is a multi-ICU, single-center cluster randomized trial that will be conducted among the
      patients and their clinicians on four adult ICU services at Northwestern Memorial Hospital.
      Each ICU service will act as a cluster.

      Each ICU service cares for patients in one or two physical ICU locations:

        -  MICU service (Medical ICU location)

        -  NCC service (Neuroscience/spine ICU location)

        -  ACC service (Cardiothoracic/transplant ICU and neuroscience/spine ICU locations)

        -  SCC service (Cardiothoracic/transplant ICU and surgical ICU locations)

      Overall Study Design:

      The study will consist of a pre-trial period of baseline data collection followed by a
      cluster randomized controlled trial. During the pre-trial period, the investigators will
      retrospectively determine the proportion of patients with ARDS on each ICU service who
      received at least one ventilator setting adherent to LTVV in the previous one year (baseline
      LTVV rate). At the end of the pre-trial period, the investigators will randomize the four
      ICUs services into an intervention group (ICUs A and B) and usual care group (ICUs C and D).
      Based on pre-trial data, the investigators will calculate the difference in baseline LTVV
      rates between ICUs A+B and C+D, which will be used to calculate the sample size necessary for
      the trial period. Following the pre-trial period, ICUs A and B will begin to receive the
      implementation strategy while ICUs C and D will continue with usual care as a comparator
      group. All mechanically ventilated, non-ARDS patients on all four ICU services during the
      pre-trial and trial periods will also be included as a separate concurrent comparator cohort.
      This will allow us to assess for temporal changes in LTVV use for mechanically ventilated
      patients in general, and potential spill-over of LTVV use for non-ARDS patients in ICUs A and
      B.

      Phase I: Pre-trial cohort study

      The study will begin with a pre-trial cohort study. The investigators will conduct a
      retrospective chart review of all mechanically ventilated patients admitted to one of the
      four participating ICUs within the previous one year. All patients who meet the inclusion
      criteria as either ARDS or non-ARDS patients will be included. The main purpose of the
      pre-trial study is to establish a baseline rate of LTVV use in each study ICU, which will be
      used as part of the primary endpoint for the clinical trial described below. All secondary
      endpoints listed in the Appendix will be collected on all patients in the pre-trial study.

      Phase II: Randomization

      At the end of the pre-trial study, the investigators will randomize the four ICU services to
      the intervention and usual care groups. The study statistician will conduct a simple
      randomization approach using computer-generated random numbers to allocate each of the four
      ICUs to the intervention (2 ICUs) and usual care groups (2 ICUs), ensuring that there are two
      intervention and two usual care ICUs. The intervention ICU services will be labeled ICU A and
      ICU B, and the usual care ICU services will be labeled ICU C and ICU D. The allocation of
      each ICU will not be revealed to other study personnel until after the calculation of the
      baseline LTVV rates for each ICU service.

      After randomization, the investigators will calculate the baseline LTVV rate in each ICU (and
      therefore for the intervention and usual care groups). Based on these baseline LTVV rates,
      the investigators will finalize the sample size calculation for the clinical trial.

      Phase III: Cluster randomized controlled trial

      After the randomization process is completed, the person conducting ICU randomization will
      reveal the allocation of ICUs to other study co-investigators. Immediately following this
      unblinding, the cluster randomized controlled trial will begin. The two ICUs randomized to
      receive usual care (ICUs C and D) will not be exposed to an intervention during the trial
      period. The two ICUs randomized to the intervention group (ICUs A and B) will receive the
      intervention for the duration of the trial period.

      Implementation strategy/Intervention (ICUs A and B)

      The multi-component implementation strategy/quality improvement intervention that ICUs A and
      B will receive during the clinical trial will consist of three parts: orientation, audit and
      feedback, and clinical decision support that combines an NLP-driven ARDS diagnostic screening
      tool, EHR-based tasks for clinicians to complete, and a clinician reminder system.

      Implementation strategy component A: Orientation

      The attending and fellow physicians and ICU nurse managers of ICUs A and B will be sent an
      email with information orienting them to the study. Respiratory therapists will not be sent
      the orientation email since they rotate between the different ICUs. The text of the email is
      shown in the Appendix (final wording may be modified).

      Implementation strategy component B: Audit and feedback

      Audit and feedback will be directed to ICU attendings and fellows. At the end of every ICU
      shift/rotation of at least five days, each physician who has cared for at least one ARDS
      patient in ICU A or B during the previous shift/rotation will receive an anonymous email from
      a study co-investigator providing their specific rate of LTVV (number of patients to whom
      they gave LTVV / number of ARDS patients managed).

      Implementation strategy component C: Clinical decision support

      The clinical decision support (CDS) intervention combines 1) an ARDS screening tool using a
      natural language processing (NLP) algorithm, 2) EHR-based tasks for clinicians to complete,
      and 3) a clinician reminder system.

        1. Based on our prior research, the investigators developed a computer application that
           automatically screens the EHR in real-time for initial diagnostic criteria for ARDS. If
           a patient is flagged as meeting these initial criteria, the application will download
           all data necessary to make a diagnosis of ARDS according to the Berlin Definition.

           Part of the CDS intervention includes a natural language processing (NLP) program. The
           NLP program will analyze downloaded data and determine whether the patient has ARDS
           according to the Berlin Definition.

        2. If a patient in ICU A or B is identified as having ARDS, the NLP program will trigger
           the EHR-based tasks for clinicians to complete and the clinician reminder system. The
           NLP will send an alert to at least one member of the study team that a patient has been
           identified as having ARDS.

             1. The study team member will create an order set for low tidal volume ventilation for
                that patient. This order set will not be signed, but will be directed to the
                attending and/or fellow physician to sign. The order set will include information
                on the patient's current tidal volume, target tidal volume for low tidal volume
                ventilation, and an order to initiate low tidal volume ventilation. In addition,
                the co-investigator will also enter a task for the patient's nurse and RT. The task
                will alert the nurse and RT that the patient has ARDS, and that they should discuss
                initiating low tidal volume ventilation with the patient's physicians.

             2. The study team member who receives the NLP alert will also send a text page to the
                pagers of the attending, fellow, and resident physicians currently taking care of a
                newly identified ARDS patient. The page will contain text suggesting that the
                physician consider a diagnosis of ARDS and initiate LTVV.

      For all patients in ICUs A and B identified as having ARDS and reported to the
      co-investigator, who are subsequently not started on LTVV within 24 hours of the clinical
      decision support intervention described above, both the EHR-based tasks and the web pages
      will be repeated every 24 hours.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>LTVV rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the difference between intervention ICUs (ICUs A and B) and usual care ICUs (ICUs C and D) in the change in the LTVV rate between the pre-trial period and the trial period. The statistical analysis of the primary endpoint will be to test the null hypothesis that there is no difference in the change in the LTVV rate between intervention and usual care groups. LTVV is defined as a patient who receives any single tidal volume less than 6.5mL/kg predicted body weight between ARDS onset and the earlier or extubation, death, or ICU discharge. ARDS onset is defined as the time at which the latter of the following two events occurred: PaO2/FIO2 &lt;= 300 and bilateral infiltrates reported on a chest imaging radiology report, which themselves must occur within 24 hours of each other.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in proportions of patients receiving LTVV between intervention and usual care groups during pre-trial period</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in proportions of patients receiving LTVV between intervention and usual care groups during trial period</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LTVV rate in individual ICUs</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in overall LTVV rate between pre-trial and trial periods</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of time receiving LTVV</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time from ARDS onset to LTVV initiation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of ventilator settings adherent to LTVV</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ARDS duration</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of clinicians using LTVV</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plateau pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU and hospital length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU, hospital, 30-, 60-, 90-, 180-day and one year mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Discharge status</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ventilator duration</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention delivered as intended</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subgroup analyses of primary and secondary endpoints based on ARDS severity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subgroup analyses of primary and secondary endpoints based on FiO2</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subgroup analyses of primary and secondary endpoints based on plateau pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">264</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ICU A and ICU B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is the intervention group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ICU C and ICU D</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is the usual care group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multi-component LTVV implementation strategy</intervention_name>
    <description>Multicomponent LTVV implementation strategy consisting of: 1) physician orientation, 2) physician audit and feedback, and 3) clinical decision support comprised of a) an ARDS screening tool using a natural language processing (NLP) algorithm, b) EHR-based tasks for clinicians to complete, and c) a clinician reminder system.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ICU A and ICU B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Clinician Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All critical care attending physicians and critical care fellows who provide patient
             care on one of the participating ICU physician services at Northwestern Memorial
             Hospital (medical ICU [MICU], surgical critical care [SCC], anesthesia/critical care
             [ACC], neurocritical care [NCC]) during the study period

          -  All resident physicians who provide patient care on the participating ICU services
             during the study period

          -  All nurses who provide patient care in the participating ICUs during the study period

          -  All respiratory therapists (RTs) who provide patient care in the participating ICUs
             during the study period

        Patient Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients admitted to a participating ICU service listed above during the study
             period and meeting the following additional criteria:

          -  Age 18 or older

          -  Receiving mechanical ventilation via endotracheal tube or tracheostomy

          -  For primary analysis: meeting Berlin Definition of ARDS (as adjudicated by NLP
             algorithm)(2)

          -  For non-ARDS comparator group: all patients meeting other inclusion criteria and not
             adjudicated as having ARDS

          -  For pre-trial period: all patients age 18 or older and receiving mechanical
             ventilation

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - Patients whose time from ARDS onset to the earlier of extubation, death, or ICU discharge
        is less than 24 hours. ARDS onset is defined as the time at which the latter of the
        following two events occurred: PaO2/FIO2 &lt;= 300 and bilateral infiltrates reported on a
        chest imaging radiology report (these must be within 24 hours of each other).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Curtis H Weiss, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern Univeristy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Curtis H Weiss, MD, MS</last_name>
    <email>curtisweiss@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Katrina Tulas, BS</last_name>
    <email>ktulas@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Curtis H Weiss, MD, MS</last_name>
      <email>curtisweiss@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Katrina Tulas, BS</last_name>
      <email>ktulas@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Curtis H Weiss, MD, MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 28, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 8, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Implementation Science</keyword>
  <keyword>Low Tidal Volume Ventilation (LTVV)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Newborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Lung Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

