<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03057379</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-002040</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03057379</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HPV IIS Reminder/Recall- New York State</brief_title>
  <official_title>State Immunization Information Systems to Improve HPV Vaccination Rates</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overarching goal of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness, cost-effectiveness and
      sustainability of utilizing statewide Immunization Information Systems (IIS) to conduct
      centralized reminder/recall (R/R) to improve Human Papiloma Virus (HPV) vaccination rates
      among adolescents ages 11-17.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overarching goal of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness, cost-effectiveness and
      sustainability of utilizing statewide Immunization Information Systems (IIS) to conduct
      centralized reminder/recall (R/R) to improve HPV vaccination rates among adolescents ages
      11-17. The investigators will extend previous research on effectiveness of centralized R/R to
      a new population--adolescents due for HPV vaccine-- and test the use of centralized R/R as a
      cancer-prevention strategy. Investigators will assess the effect of centralized R/R in two
      states--one with and one without mandated reporting of vaccinations to IISs, and disseminate
      IIS R/R to other states. Investigators will implement, evaluate (using the RE-AIM framework
      31-36), and disseminate a collaborative, IIS-based centralized HPV vaccine R/R model in which
      partnerships of public health systems and primary care practices in two states (NY, CO)
      collaborate to remind parents about HPV vaccination.

      Specific Aims and hypotheses:

      Aim #1: Adapt IIS messages and delivery systems (e.g., algorithms) previously developed for
      centralized R/R for other vaccines to fit HPV vaccine IIS R/R.

      Aim #2: Assess the impact and cost-effectiveness of centralized IIS-based (IIS-C) autodialer
      (phone) R/R in increasing vaccine rates [initial dose (HPV#1) and a complete series (HPV#3)]
      among teens.

      Conduct a pragmatic trial, to assess the impact and cost effectiveness of centralized
      IIS-based (IIS-C) autodialer (phone) R/R in increasing initiation and completion rates for
      the HPV vaccine series in adolescents ages 11-17 years. The investigators will use a
      within-practice design, randomizing patients within randomly selected primary care practices
      to IIS-C R/R (1, 2, or 3 reminders per dose) compared to usual care (0 reminders from this
      study). The investigators will apply the RE-AIM framework to evaluate the reach,
      effectiveness/cost effectiveness, adoption, and implementation of IIS-C R/R.

      Hypothesis 2a: IIS-C R/R will result in higher HPV vaccination rates than usual care.

      Hypothesis 2b: IIS-C R/R will result in higher HPV vaccination rates than usual care in key
      subgroups (males and females, younger and older teens, urban//rural teens).

      Hypothesis 2c: IIS-C R/R will be more cost-effective (cost/vaccine received) than usual care.

      Aim #3: Disseminate IIS-C R/R across NY and CO and pilot in four IISs: (a) Develop an IIS-C
      HPV R/R toolkit, (b) Use a technical advisory group, (c) Initiate IIS-C R/R in four other
      IISs [Yr. 4].

      By the end of the study investigators will have a feasible, sustainable, cost-effective model
      for HPV vaccine reminders that can be used nationally to prevent cervical cancer and other
      HPV-related cancers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 27, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomized to one of four arms to receive 0,1,2,or 3 reminders for overdue HPV vaccine doses.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Initiation of the HPV vaccine series (receipt and documentation of initial dose of vaccine series within immunization registry)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months from initial recall notices for the first dose</time_frame>
    <description>Did the adolescent initiate the HPV vaccine series? The investigators are allowing up to 5 months after the initial recall notice for the adolescent to make an appointment and receive their dose. After that time frame, the investigators will not attribute vaccination to the recall. Receipt will be documented by providers within the state immunization registry via electronic medical record (EMR) direct transfer or manual entry.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Completion of the HPV vaccine series (receipt and documentation of final dose of vaccine series within immunization registry)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months from first reminder received for last dose</time_frame>
    <description>Did those eligible to complete the HPV vaccine series within the time frame of the study do so? The investigators are allowing up to 5 months after the first recall notice of the last dose (could be dose 2 or dose 3, depending on the age at which they received their first dose) for adolescents to complete their vaccination series. After that time frame, the investigators will not attribute vaccination to the recall. Receipt will be documented by providers within the state immunization registry via EMR direct transfer or manual entry.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences between arms - initiation</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>Is 1, 2, or 3 reminders per arm most effective and cost effective for initiation. Only those who need an initial dose at baseline will be eligible for this outcome. We will compare the arms (receipt of zero, 1, 2 or 3 reminders) to see if there are any differences between the arms in terms of receipt of the 1st dose of HPV vaccine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences between arms - completion</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Is 1, 2, or 3 reminders per arm most effective and cost effective for completion. Because the second or third dose of the series is dependent on when the adolescent receives their initial dose, the investigators will be following eligible adolescents for 20 months to allow time for those who did not respond to the recall for the initial dose right away to be able to complete the series within the time frame. However, receipt of the completion dose will only be attributed to the recall if it was received within 5 months of the 1st recall for the completion dose. Receipt will be documented by providers within the state immunization registry via EMR direct transfer or manual entry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45000</enrollment>
  <condition>Reminder Systems</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual source of care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1 R/R per Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sending up to one recall notice per dose of HPV vaccine needed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2 R/R per dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sending up to two recall notice per dose of HPV vaccine needed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3 R/R per dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sending up to three recall notice per dose of HPV vaccine needed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vaccine Reminder Recall</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators will be sending recall notices via phone call to 11-17 year olds who are eligible but lacking HPV vaccine doses recorded in the New York State Immunization Information System (NYSIIS). The investigators will be testing the effectiveness and cost effectiveness of up to 3 notices per dose with usual care (no intervention)</description>
    <arm_group_label>1 R/R per Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2 R/R per dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3 R/R per dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  11 through 17 years of age

          -  patient of a participating practice (practices randomly selected)

          -  is either due for an HPV dose at baseline, or

          -  has initiated but not yet completed the HPV series at baseline

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  has completed the HPV vaccination series
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 15, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Peter G Szilagyi, MD MPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HPV vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunization registry</keyword>
  <keyword>Reminder recall</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

