<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03051802</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-5056</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03051802</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility Study of Navigated Endoscopy for the Placement of High Dose Rate Brachytherapy Applicators in the Esophagus and Lung</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility Study of Navigated Endoscopy for the Placement of High Dose Rate Brachytherapy Applicators in the Esophagus and Lung</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The scope of this clinical trial is to assess the clinical feasibility of this procedure,
      optimize the protocol and perform an initial comparison of the positional accuracy of
      navigated endoscopy and applicator insertion versus the standard of care 2D fluoroscopy
      protocol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      High dose rate brachytherapy is used in a limited number of esophagus and lung patients,
      often in combination with external beam radiation therapy. The procedure uses an applicator
      inserted into the lumen with the applicator connected to an automated &quot;afterloader&quot;, a device
      with a radioactive brachytherapy source attached to a thick guide wire that positions the
      source within the applicator at set positions and times based on a treatment plan.
      Identification of the ideal applicator position is determined by white light endoscopy. With
      the endoscope in the lumen, fluoroscopic imaging can visualize the endoscope position.
      Temporary radio-opaque skin markers are placed on the patient's anterior surface under
      fluoroscopy imaging so that they align with the endoscope tip. The proximal and the distal
      ends of the target volume are marked in this manner by the surgeon stopping the endoscope at
      these positions. The endoscope is removed and the applicator inserted, with the positions of
      the applicator and &quot;dummy&quot; seeds (i.e. non-radioactive seeds used only for positioning
      purposes) aligned under fluoroscopy to match the skin markers. The procedure has 2
      disadvantages: i. There is extra radiation dose to the clinical staff due to the fluoroscopy
      used to identify the source position.

      ii. Visualization is only in 2D, which is inaccurate since it does not account for
      separations in the vertical direction and the angle of projection between the applicator and
      the so patient surface. Furthermore, any movement of the fluoroscopy device during the
      insertion leads to errors in visualization.

      Medical applications of navigated endoscopy continue to grow, especially when used in
      combination with volumetricimaging for image-guided procedures. This feasibility study is
      aimed to use navigation endoscopy technology to overcome the disadvantages of the current
      practice and improve the overall process.

      In the proposed protocol, applicator insertion, tracking and recording of the endoscope and
      applicator positions would enable placement of the applicator using 3D information, with
      greater accuracy and without extra radiation dose to the clinical staff. The tracking
      technology would be used to replace the use of radio-opaque skin markers; rather than placing
      these markers on the patient's skin, the location of the target volume boundaries would be
      noted by the tracker position within the endoscope. Applicator insertion would also be
      tracked, with the applicator positioning based on the location of the applicator relative to
      the previously recorded endoscope positions, including the locations of the distal and
      proximal ends of the target volume.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Slow recruitment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 27, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 24, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 24, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Device Feasibility</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of navigated endoscopy procedures that were successfully completed</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To assess clinical feasibility of inserting intraluminal (esophagus or lung) HDR applicators using navigation technologies for tracking endoscope and applicator insertion.
This study is designed to assess the workflow when using the EM tracking technology and the accuracy of the procedure will be measured by comparison with current standard of care.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positional accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>day 1</time_frame>
    <description>To compare the positional accuracy of the navigation procedure versus the current standard of care using 2D fluoroscopy using analysis of tracking data. All tracking data will be recorded for post-procedure analysis and comparison with the fluoroscopic imaging performed during current standard of care</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Optimize the clinical protocol using this technology</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The procedure will be assessed in detail (based on time and workflow) after three patients. Participants in the review of the procedure will include surgeon, radiation oncologist, brachy-therapists and physicists. Workflow improvements will be implemented at this time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophagus Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Navigated Endoscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Navigated endoscopy used to guide the placement of HDR applicators in the esophagus or lung as a replacement to current standard of practice using fluoroscopic imaging.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Primary or metastatic cancer including endoluminal disease of either the lung or the
             esophagus

          -  Intention to treat using high dose rate brachytherapy as part of standard
             radiotherapy.

          -  Ability to provide written informed consent to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Contraindications to standard radiation therapy including pregnancy, lactation,
             connective tissue disorders, serious co-morbid illness

          -  Concurrent illness or condition that precludes subject from undergoing endoscopy

          -  Patient is unable to tolerate an hour and a half long procedure. Standard of care
             practice is no more than 1 hour. However, with the additional tracking component, the
             procedure could be at most 1.5 hours long.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Margaret Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Endoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>HDR Brachytherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>navigation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

