<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00037908</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B2405R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00037908</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Strength Training on Upper-Limb Function in Post-Stroke Hemiparesis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Strength Training on Upper-Limb Function in Post-Stroke Hemiparesis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Our overall goal is to develop therapeutic interventions to improve upper-limb motor function
      in hemiparetic persons based on an improved understanding of the mechanisms responsible for
      its loss and recovery. We intend to rigorously evaluate the efficacy of these interventions
      with clinical trials, and to study the mechanisms by which these interventions affect motor
      recovery. In this proposal, we will use a controlled, randomized, double blind clinical trial
      to study the effects of shoulder and elbow strength training in subjects in the subacute
      phase of recovery following stroke.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypotheses: The specific hypotheses that we will test in this proposal all refer to persons
      with post-stroke hemiparesis in the subacute phase of recovery (completed all out-patient
      therapy programs, but still less than 6 months post-CVA).

        1. a) Standard functional rehabilitation combined with strength training in the form of
           high-intensity resistance exercise results in greater gains in elbow and shoulder
           strength than standard functional rehabilitation alone.

           b) This increased strength is not accompanied by increased hypertonia. c) This increased
           strength is not accompanied by significant muscular hypertrophy.

        2. Standard functional rehabilitation combined with strength training results in greater
           improvements in motor function than functional rehabilitation alone.

        3. Strength training results in improved control of elbow trajectory tracking movements and
           shoulder-elbow reaching movements.

      Specific Objectives

        1. To perform a controlled, randomized, double-blind clinical trial to test the effects of
           high-intensity resistance exercise at the shoulder and elbow. Two interventions will be
           compared: standard functional rehabilitation (SFR), and standard functional
           rehabilitation combined with high-intensity resistance exercise (strength training)
           (SFR+STR). We will study persons with post-stroke hemiparesis in the subacute phase of
           recovery, i.e. having completed all outpatient therapy programs, but still less than 6
           months post-CVA. Outcome measures will include strength (maximal voluntary isovelocity
           joint torque), hypertonia (onset threshold of the stretch reflex, Modified Ashworth
           Scale), standard clinical assessment of activities of daily living (Barthel Index,
           Functional Independence Measure), and upper extremity motor function (Fugl-Meyer exam,
           Functional Test of the Hemiparetic Upper Extremity).

        2. To study the neuromuscular mechanisms associated with improvements in strength and motor
           control that result from these interventions. Strength changes will be investigated by
           measuring muscle hypertrophy, hyperreflexia, and passive stiffness. Changes in control
           of upper extremity movements will be investigated by measuring motor performance and
           muscle activation patterns in trajectory tracking and reaching tasks.

      Our long term goal is to develop therapeutic interventions to improve upper-limb motor
      function in persons with post-stroke hemiparesis. Improved motor function involves not only
      increased strength at the shoulder and elbow, but also increased strength and dexterity at
      the wrist and hand. The proposed study will establish a foundation by demonstrating the
      positive effects of strength training in persons with hemiparesis. Then, in future studies,
      we can investigate the effects of specific interventions at the hand and wrist and
      investigate physiologic mechanisms subserving change in neuromuscular function following
      strength training.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2003</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebrovascular Accident</condition>
  <condition>Hemiparesis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Strength training</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Post stroke
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Wolff, Ph.D. Special Assistant to the Director</last_name>
    <affiliation>Program Analysis and Review Section (PARS) VA Rehabilitation Research &amp; Development Service</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Danielle M Kerkovitch, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <affiliation>Program Analysis and Review Section (PARS), VA Rehabilitation Research and Development Service</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VAMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2002</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 24, 2002</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 27, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 20, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 20, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 21, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemiparesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Upper limb function</keyword>
  <keyword>Strength training</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paresis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

