<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00030134</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>020116</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>02-N-0116</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00030134</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Data Collection in Women With Fabry Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Collect Normative Data in Female Patients With Fabry Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This protocol will collect information needed to design a clinical study for the symptoms and
      problems of women with Fabry disease, an inherited metabolic disorder. In this disease, an
      enzyme called a-galactosidase A, which normally breaks down fatty substances called
      glycolipids, does not function properly. The resulting accumulation of glycolipids in various
      tissues causes arm and leg pain, skin lesions, and problems with the kidneys, heart, nerves,
      and blood vessels. This protocol does not involve any experimental drug treatments, but
      participants may be offered enrollment in future studies and registries.

      Women 18 years of age and older with Fabry disease who have not had enzyme replacement
      therapy may participate in this study. Pregnant women are eligible, but may be excluded from
      certain procedures, such as magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).

      Participants will have the following tests and procedures over a 3-day period:

        -  Personal and family medical history

        -  Physical, neurological, and eye examinations

        -  Blood and urine tests

        -  Electrocardiogram (ECG) to measure electrical activity of the heart

        -  Echocardiogram (ultrasound) to examine the heart muscles and pumping action

        -  Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) to examine the brain. This test uses a magnetic field
           and radio waves to produce images of the brain. The patient lies in a narrow cylinder
           (the MRI scanner) during the imaging and may talk with staff at any time during the
           procedure.

        -  Magnetic resonance angiogram (MRA) to examine the blood vessels in the head and neck.
           This procedure is similar to MRI.

        -  Genotyping to confirm the diagnosis of Fabry disease. DNA from a blood sample will be
           examined for the gene associated with Fabry disease.

        -  Skin punch biopsy for microscopic examination of tissue. A piece of skin tissue about
           1/8-inch thick is removed with a cookie cutter-like instrument.

      Participants will also complete two questionnaires regarding pain and quality of life. They
      will be asked to stop taking pain medications for 7 days before completing the pain
      questionnaire, but may resume medications before 7 days if the pain is too intense. The
      questionnaire will be completed by telephone interview.

      Patients will also be asked to keep a diary of pain medications taken for 7 days while on the
      study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a study to collect normative data in female patients with Fabry disease. After
      signing informed consent, patients will complete various study evaluations. Serious adverse
      events will be monitored throughout the patients study participation (approximately 7 days).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>February 2003</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>60</enrollment>
  <condition>Fabry Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        The patient must provide written informed consent prior to any study-related procedures
        being performed.

        Patients must be 18 years of age or older.

        Patients must have signs of symptoms consistent with Fabry disease with no prior treatment
        with any enzyme replacement therapy for Fabry Disease.

        Patients of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test (urine beta-hCG) in
        order to complete all study tests.

        If a patient is pregnant, they may still enter the trial but may not participate in MRI or
        MRA procedures.

        Patients who have received an investigational drug within 30 days prior to study enrollment
        or received prior treatment with any enzyme replacement therapy for Fabry disease will be
        excluded.

        Patients who have diabetic nephropathy or other confounding renal disorder will be
        excluded.

        Patients who have a clinically significant organic disease or an unstable condition that,
        in the opinion of the Investigator, would preclude participation in this protocol will be
        excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahlmén J, Hultberg B, Brynger H, Sjöblad S, Svalander C. Clinical and diagnostic considerations in Fabry's disease. Acta Med Scand. 1982;211(4):309-12.</citation>
    <PMID>6808807</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aĭvazian AA, Trofimov IB, Seredniakova NI. [Ultrastructural changes in the skin of patients with Fabry's angiokeratoma]. Arkh Patol. 1985;47(7):60-3. Russian.</citation>
    <PMID>2996471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Altarescu G, Moore DF, Pursley R, Campia U, Goldstein S, Bryant M, Panza JA, Schiffmann R. Enhanced endothelium-dependent vasodilation in Fabry disease. Stroke. 2001 Jul;32(7):1559-62.</citation>
    <PMID>11441201</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2003</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2002</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 2, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Natural History</keyword>
  <keyword>Female Carrier</keyword>
  <keyword>Alpha-Galactosidase</keyword>
  <keyword>Lysosomal Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>X-Linked</keyword>
  <keyword>Fabry</keyword>
  <keyword>Fabry Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fabry Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

