<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00521794</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RDCRN 5301</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5U54RR019482-02</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00521794</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characteristics of Andersen-Tawil Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Andersen-Tawil Syndrome: Genotype-Phenotype Correlation and Longitudinal Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Rochester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Office of Rare Diseases (ORD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rare Diseases Clinical Research Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Research Resources (NCRR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Rochester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Andersen-Tawil Syndrome (ATS) is a rare, genetic disorder that causes episodes of muscle
      weakness, potentially life-threatening changes in heart rhythm, and developmental
      abnormalities. Disease symptoms can vary, the cause of some ATS cases remains unknown, and no
      specific treatment has been identified. The purpose of this multi-site study is to better
      characterize ATS, establish whether symptoms change over time, and determine if symptoms are
      related to a mutation in the KCNJ2 gene.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ATS is an ion channel disorder that causes episodes of muscle weakness and potentially
      life-threatening heart arrhythmias for which no treatment has been identified. The majority
      of ATS cases are caused by a mutation in the KCNJ2 gene; other cases result from unknown
      causes. The KCNJ2 gene mutation alters potassium channels in such a way that it disrupts the
      flow of potassium ions in skeletal and heart muscle. This can lead to the characteristic
      periodic paralysis and irregular heart rhythms. The purpose of this study is to better define
      the genetic basis, clinical features, and disease progression of ATS. The study will also
      establish clinically relevant endpoints for use in future clinical studies.

      This observational study will last 2 years and will involve three study visits. The first
      visit will entail a 1.5- to 3.5-day inpatient stay; the length of stay will depend on whether
      a participant has been taking medications for their symptoms of weakness. Participants will
      be asked to discontinue use of such medications during the inpatient stay. Participants will
      not be asked to stop any medications that they may be taking for heart symptoms. This first
      study visit will include a medical history, a quality of life questionnaire, a physical exam,
      and muscle strength testing. Nerve, muscle, and heart activity will also be measured, and
      blood will be drawn for laboratory tests and optional DNA analysis. The second and third
      study visits will take place 1 and 2 years after the initial study visit and will include the
      same evaluations. During the 8 weeks following each study visit, participants will record in
      a telephone diary any muscle and heart symptoms that they experience. During the 1 week after
      both yearly visits, participants will also undergo an outpatient heart rhythm evaluation. A
      study coordinator will contact participants once a month by phone over the course of the
      study to review symptoms.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Collect prospective standardized data from participants to help better define the clinical phenotype of ATS.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Andersen-Tawil Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Andersen Syndrome</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Individuals with a clinically confirmed diagnosis of Andersen-Tawil Syndrome (ATS) enrolled
        across seven sites in the United States, England, Italy and Canada
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically confirmed diagnosis of ATS as defined by at least two of the following
             three criteria:

               1. Presence of clear-cut episodes of transient muscle weakness with or without a
                  fixed deficit, typically following exertion or prolonged rest OR atypical history
                  with otherwise typical exam findings (absent reflexes with normal sensation
                  during an episode) OR unexplained hypokalemia between episodes OR abnormal
                  long-exercise nerve conduction study

               2. Heart conduction defects: prolonged QTc interval on 12-lead electrocardiogram OR
                  ventricular ectopy, including uniform or multifocal PVCs, polymorphic VT, or
                  bidirectional VT

               3. Presence of two or more of the following physical features: low set ears,
                  hypertelorism, small mandible, clinodactyly, syndactyly, micromelia of hands or
                  feet --OR--

          -  Meets one of the above three criteria and has at least one family member with two of
             the criteria --OR--

          -  Does not meet the above three criteria, but possesses a mutation in the KCNJ2 gene

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Less than 10 years of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emma Ciafaloni, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Rochester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert C. Griggs, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Rochester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kansas Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66160</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>London Health Sciences Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 5A5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Milan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Neurology and National Hospital for Neurology</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tawil R, Ptacek LJ, Pavlakis SG, DeVivo DC, Penn AS, Ozdemir C, Griggs RC. Andersen's syndrome: potassium-sensitive periodic paralysis, ventricular ectopy, and dysmorphic features. Ann Neurol. 1994 Mar;35(3):326-30.</citation>
    <PMID>8080508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sansone V, Griggs RC, Meola G, Ptácek LJ, Barohn R, Iannaccone S, Bryan W, Baker N, Janas SJ, Scott W, Ririe D, Tawil R. Andersen's syndrome: a distinct periodic paralysis. Ann Neurol. 1997 Sep;42(3):305-12.</citation>
    <PMID>9307251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tristani-Firouzi M, Jensen JL, Donaldson MR, Sansone V, Meola G, Hahn A, Bendahhou S, Kwiecinski H, Fidzianska A, Plaster N, Fu YH, Ptacek LJ, Tawil R. Functional and clinical characterization of KCNJ2 mutations associated with LQT7 (Andersen syndrome). J Clin Invest. 2002 Aug;110(3):381-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12163457</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 24, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 24, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 28, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 16, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Rochester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert Griggs, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Neurology, Medicine, Pediatrics, Pathology &amp; Laboratory Medicine, and Center for Human Experimental Therapeutics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Arrhythmia</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscle Weakness</keyword>
  <keyword>Periodic Paralysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Channelopathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Andersen Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

