<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00095485</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>050027</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>05-CC-0027</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00095485</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Move to Clinical Research Center on Physical Activity of Employees</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Move to CRC on Physical Activity of Employees</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the changes that the move from NIH's Building 10 Clinical Center (CC)
      into the Clinical Research Center (CRC) may have on the amount of activity a person engages
      in daily, as registered by a pedometer, which measures horizontal and vertical steps. The
      investigators in this study hope to better understand the impact that the move will have had
      on one group of employees compared with the impact for other groups. Moving to a new work
      location may require physical activity that is different from what employees currently
      experience on the job. In the new location, they may be walking longer or shorter distances;
      they may also be climbing fewer or more stairs. In addition, they may need to walk more
      quickly to accomplish the same tasks. It is important to understand how the move from the CC
      to the CRC influences employees' health, well-being, and overall function. Physical measures,
      such as blood pressure, will be examined. So will how well employees are adjusting to the new
      location-for example, through information about work-related injuries.

      Clinical Center employees who are able to walk, whose move dates allow 10 days in the
      Clinical Center before the move, who wish to participate in the study and are able to wear a
      pedometer, and whose work requirements include a sufficient amount of walking may be eligible
      for the study.

      Participants will undergo the following procedures before the move into the CRC and then 1
      month after the move. Each evaluation will take about 30 minutes:

        -  Brief history about age, medical problems, and current medications.

        -  Measurements of heart rate, blood pressure, height, and weight.

        -  Completing a brief questionnaire about the history of injuries, such as back pain,
           tendonitis, and bursitis.

      In addition, participants will complete a questionnaire about daily life and leisure
      activities, consisting of 94 questions, to take about 20 minutes to complete. There will also
      be a measurement of the distance that participants can walk in 2 minutes.

      A pedometer will be provided to each participant and will remain the property of that person.
      Participants will receive a daily log on which to record the number of steps they have walked
      and the distance as registered by the pedometer. About 5 minutes a day will be needed to
      record such information. The information that participants provide will be coded. They will
      not be personally identified, nor will the information be discussed with other people,
      including supervisors or co-workers.

      Information collected will be analyzed for changes in activity patterns and will be analyzed
      by groups of staff. For example, the investigators may wish to compare the activity of nurses
      before and after the move and then compare that information with information collected from
      food service workers, or personnel serving as messengers or escorts. Participants may find
      the information gathered to be useful to them as individuals. That is, they may learn that
      their activity has increased as a result of the move to the new location. They may have
      benefited by having lost weight or lowered their blood pressure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project attempts to answer three questions about employees in the Magnuson Clinical
      Center. It is designed to study the effects of the move into the CRC on the amount of
      activity an individual performs daily in terms of units measured by a waist mounted pedometer
      (horizontal and vertical steps).

      The hypotheses are:

        1. There will be an increase in amount of activity in CRC compared with CC (horizontal
           distance traveled, up/down activity including stairs and chairs).

        2. There will be an increase in walk velocity after move into CRC. This implies an
           increased level of aerobic capacity.

      There will be an increase in the musculoskeletal symptoms, especially in the lower
      extremities and low back after move to the CRC. This implies there will be overuse of lower
      extremities because of increased activity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date>November 2005</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>150</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Any CC employee who is ambulatory, whose move date allows 10 days in CC prior to move, who
        wishes to participate in the study and whose work requirements include sufficient amount of
        walking so that they are not primarily confined to one office module.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. inability to wear a pedometer; and record pedometer data

          2. musculoskeletal impairments that significantly limit ambulation, e.g. recent
             fractures, tendinitis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 5, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 5, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 8, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Activity Level</keyword>
  <keyword>Musculoskeletal</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

