<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00094406</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>050012</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>05-CC-0012</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00094406</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carbon Monoxide to Prevent Lung Inflammation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Inhaled Carbon Monoxide on Pulmonary Inflammatory Responses Following Endotoxin Instillation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine in healthy volunteers how breathing carbon monoxide (CO) affects lung
      inflammation. Severe lung inflammation sometimes develops in patients with pneumonia or
      patients who develop serious blood stream infections. Studies in the laboratory and in
      animals show that CO can decrease lung inflammation.

      Healthy volunteers between 18 and 40 years of age who do not smoke, are not taking any
      medications, do not have asthma, are not allergic to sulfa- and penicillin-based drugs, and
      are not pregnant may be eligible for this study. Candidates are screened with a medical
      history and physical examination, blood and urine tests, electrocardiogram (EKG), and chest
      x-ray. Subjects are enrolled in either a pilot study or the main study.

      Participants undergo bronchoscopy and bronchoalveolar lavage to study the effects of
      endotoxin (a component of bacteria that causes inflammation similar to that in patients with
      lung infections) on lung function. Before the procedure, a small plastic tube (catheter) is
      placed in a vein to collect blood samples and another is placed in an artery to check blood
      pressure. For the bronchoscopy, the mouth and nasal airways are numbed with lidocaine, and a
      bronchoscope (thin flexible tube) is passed through the nose into the airways of the lung. A
      small amount of salt water is squirted through the bronchoscope into one lung and then salt
      water containing endotoxin is squirted into the other lung.

      Following the bronchoscopy, subjects are treated with either CO or room air (placebo) for 6
      hours. (Subjects in the pilot study receive treatment for only 3 hours). The gas is delivered
      through a cushioned mask placed over the nose and mouth. The amount of exhaled CO is measured
      before, during, and after inhalation of the gas. For this measurement, subjects take a deep
      breath to fill up their lungs and slowly exhale into a mouthpiece connected to a measuring
      device until they feel their lungs are empty.

      After the CO treatment, a second bronchoscopy is done to examine how the lung responded to
      the CO or room air. This is studied in two ways. To sample the air, a large needle is used to
      withdraw air through the bronchoscope over about 3 seconds. Then the areas of the lung that
      were squirted with salt water alone and with endotoxin and salt water and are rinsed (lavage)
      and cells and secretions are collected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) is a major cause of morbidity and mortality. Of
      the many potential predisposing factors, sepsis and pneumonia represent the two main causes
      of ARDS. In spite of an increase in survival in recent years mortality in patients with ARDS
      is still estimated around 30 to 40%. In this context, development of effective preventive
      strategies in patients at high risk of development of ARDS is of paramount importance.
      Unfortunately, the results of studies evaluating prophylactic regimens for ARDS have been
      mostly disappointing.

      The gaseous molecule carbon monoxide (CO) has been traditionally viewed as a toxic metabolic
      and industrial waste. However, recent studies have demonstrated an important physiologic role
      of CO in many biological systems. Specifically, strong anti-inflammatory, anti-oxidant and
      anti-thrombotic effects of CO gas administration and heme oxygenase activation (the enzyme
      that generates endogenous CO gas) have been demonstrated in several animal models.

      Previous studies conducted in our department have demonstrated that bronchoscopic
      instillation of endotoxin (LPS) in healthy volunteers elicits a compartmentalized pulmonary
      inflammatory response, serving as an excellent model to evaluate interventions directed
      towards suppression of lung inflammation at its earliest stages.

      In the current single blinded, randomized, placebo controlled study, we are planning to
      evaluate the effects of inhaled carbon monoxide on local pulmonary inflammatory responses
      following endotoxin administration. Healthy subjects will undergo local endotoxin
      instillation, breathe CO or room air through a mask for 6 hours, and then a repeat
      bronchoscopy with lavage will be done at 6 hours to assess the ability of CO to suppress
      local inflammation in the lung.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 13, 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 11, 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 11, 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bronchoscopy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bronchoalveolar lavage</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endotoxin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carbon Monoxide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        All volunteer subjects, employees and non-employees, must 18 to 40 years of age and must be
        able to provide informed, written consent for participation in this study. We will not
        directly advertise the study to employees to avoid the potential for coercion. Eligibility
        in the study is determined prior to enrollment on the basis of the following inclusion and
        exclusion criteria.

        Normal screening examination including:

          1. medical history and physical examination, nonsmoker, no concurrent medications
             including aspirin or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, no active medical problems

          2. complete blood count with differential and platelet counts

          3. serum chemistries including creatinine, blood urea nitrogen, glucose, liver enzymes
             and function tests, electrolytes, prothrombin time, partial thromboplastin time,
             carboxyhemoglobin measured by venous co-oxymetry.

          4. urinalysis

          5. female subjects must have negative urine pregnancy test within one week of
             participation (this will be repeated immediately prior to beginning the screening
             procedures due to radiation exposure from the chest x-ray)

          6. electrocardiogram

          7. chest radiograph

        Sexually active females not using contraceptive methods will be instructed to abstain from
        sexual activity or use barrier contraception methods from the time of last negative
        pregnancy test to 24 hours after completion of the study.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. active tobacco use

          2. baseline caroxyhemoglobin greater than 2%

          3. pregnancy

          4. lactation

          5. medical history of recent clinically significant asthma allergy to both sulfa- and
             penicillin-based drugs

          6. Allergy to both sulfa- and penicillin-based drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anthony F Suffredini, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hudson LD, Milberg JA, Anardi D, Maunder RJ. Clinical risks for development of the acute respiratory distress syndrome. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 1995 Feb;151(2 Pt 1):293-301.</citation>
    <PMID>7842182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baumann WR, Jung RC, Koss M, Boylen CT, Navarro L, Sharma OP. Incidence and mortality of adult respiratory distress syndrome: a prospective analysis from a large metropolitan hospital. Crit Care Med. 1986 Jan;14(1):1-4.</citation>
    <PMID>3484443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Milberg JA, Davis DR, Steinberg KP, Hudson LD. Improved survival of patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS): 1983-1993. JAMA. 1995 Jan 25;273(4):306-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7815658</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 19, 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 16, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 18, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lung Permeability</keyword>
  <keyword>Endotoxin Tolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>Bronchoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Carbon Monoxide Inhalation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Newborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Lung Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carbon Monoxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

