<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00097175</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>050035</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>05-M-0035</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00097175</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Tryptophan Depletion on Brain Processing of Emotions in Patients With Mood Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Mood and Tryptophan Depletion on the Neural Correlates of Affective Shifting in Mood Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will investigate how the brain process emotions in healthy people and in patients
      who have major depression in order to better understand the causes of depression. It will
      examine what happens in the brain when a person responds to words related to different
      emotions while the brain's ability to manufacture a chemical called serotonin is reduced.
      Serotonin regulates functions such as emotion, anxiety and sleep, and stress hormones such as
      cortisol. In this study, participants' serotonin levels are reduced by depleting tryptophan,
      an amino acid that is the main building block for serotonin.

      Healthy volunteers and patients with major depression that has been in remission for at least
      3 months may be eligible for this study. Candidates must be between 18 and 50 years of age
      and right-handed. They are interviewed about their medical and psychiatric history, current
      emotional state and sleep pattern, and family history of psychiatric disorders. Screening
      also includes psychiatric interviews and rating scales, neuropsychological tests, physical
      examination, electrocardiogram (EKG), and blood, urine, and saliva tests. Women have their
      menstrual phase determined by a blood test and home urine ovulation test kit.

      The study involves two clinic visits in which participants undergo tryptophan depletion and
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). Subjects arrive at the NIH Clinical Center in the morning
      after fasting overnight. They fill out questionnaires have a blood sample drawn, and then
      take 74 capsules that contain a mixture of amino acids found in the diet. At one visit they
      are given capsules that contain a balanced mixture of amino acids one would normally eat in a
      day; at the other visit, some of the capsules contain lactose instead of tryptophan, causing
      tryptophan depletion. At 2 p.m. participants fill out the same questionnaires they completed
      at the beginning of the day and have another blood sample drawn. Then they do a computerized
      test in the MRI scanner. MRI uses a magnet and radio waves to obtain pictures of the brain.
      For the test, subjects lie on a narrow bed that slides into the cylindrical MRI scanner. They
      are asked to press a button in response to words associated with different emotions that
      appear on a screen. Arterial spin labeling - a test that uses magnetism to measure blood flow
      in different areas of the brain-is also done during the procedure. After the scan, subjects
      eat a meal and then return home.

      DNA from the participants' blood samples is also examined to try to better understand the
      genetic causes of depression. Some of the white cells from the samples may also be grown in
      the laboratory so that additional studies can be done later.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Major depressive disorder (MDD) has been associated with abnormally reduced function of
      central serotonergic systems by various types of evidence. One instructive paradigm for
      investigating the relationship between serotonergic function, cognition and depression has
      involved the mood response to tryptophan depletion (TD), achieved by oral loading with all
      essential amino acids excepting the 5-HT precursor, tryptophan. Subjects who are depressed
      show altered behavioral and neural response to affectively valenced stimuli, similar to those
      seen under TD.

      More, specifically, increased response latencies to happy words have been noted in both
      depressed patients and healthy controls following TD using the Affective Go/No go (AGNG)
      test, in which subjects are required either to respond or inhibit a response to a series of
      emotionally valenced words.

      The first round of our study employed fMRI imaging of BOLD response and arterial spin
      labeling to investigate response to affectively valenced words under TD in two groups,
      remitted MDD (rMDD) patients and healthy controls with no family history of depression. We
      have thus far examined the effects of TD depletion in our healthy control group. We found
      that emotional information processing was indeed altered by 5-HT depletion.

      A behavioral bias toward positive stimuli was attenuated following depletion, which was
      accompanied by increased hemodynamic responses during the processing of emotional words in
      several subcortical structures, including the ventral striatum, hippocampal cortex, anterior
      insula, superior temporal gyrus and posterior cingulate. Further, inter-individual
      differences in tryptophan depletion-elicited anxiety correlated positively with caudate bias
      toward negative stimuli. On the basis of these data, we suggest that the bias towards
      positive stimuli might represent a normal suppression of attention to negative stimuli; a
      process which is abrogated in conditions, such as depression, which are characterized by a
      serotonergic dysfunction. In the second round of this study, we are examining whether such
      biases also occur beneath the level of conscious awareness.

      One of the weaknesses of these data is that the patients were consciously aware of the verbal
      stimuli that were presented to them and likely possess learned, individualized associations
      to the verbal stimuli in question. We have developed a conditioning task which obviates this
      problem through the presentation of emotionally-valenced visual stimuli below the threshold
      of conscious awareness.

      Since embarking on the first two phases of this study, a new paradigm has been developed
      which may provide further insight into affective behavioral biases. The Split Reversals task
      is a pavlovian reversal-learning task which allows the assessment of responses to expected
      and unexpected punishment and reward cues. Previous research with this task has demonstrated
      that reduction of serotonin in healthy individuals removes a disproportionate inability to
      predict punishment at baseline. In other words, serotonin reduction removes a positive bias
      on this task. . This is consistent with the observed removal of a positive bias on the AGNG
      following TD. However, on the split reversals task this positive bias is revealed by an
      inability to process negative stimuli at baseline, which is improved, rather than a bias
      towards positive stimuli which is diminished, by TD. As such, the new task provides a
      different direction from which to consider the emotional biases observed in affective
      disorders. We have suggested that the bias on the new task reflects a serotonin-mediated
      suppression of responses to negative stimuli in healthy individuals which, in turn, promote
      resilience to affective disorders. Serotonin reduction via TD hence removes this bias. That
      this task may therefore be sensitive to cognitive biases resulting from resilience
      mechanisms.

      Similarly, fear potentiated startle which has been shown to be sensitive to the symptoms of
      anxiety has been shown to be reduced by the elevation of 5-HT via two week citalopram
      treatment. This is consistent with reduced processing of negative information following 5-HT
      increase (Grillon et al 2009). We predict that reducing 5-HT via TD will have the opposite
      effect and increase the duration of fear potentiated startle processing. This would provide
      an indirect link between reduced 5-HT and anxiety disorders. As such, we include this task in
      a new phase of this protocol.

      In addition these behavioural TD findings, this task has been neuroimaged (fMRI) in healthy
      individuals. As predicted, the striatum was shown to be involved in reward processing, whilst
      the amygdala was shown to be involved in punishment processing. A subproject of this study
      will therefore attempt to extend the prior findings from the split reversals task (and
      reconcile them with the AGNG findings) by examining healthy individuals completing the task
      whilst undergoing both serotonin manipulation (TD) and fMRI. This subproject will be
      initially restricted to healthy individuals and should provide us with further insight into
      the neural substrates involved in serotonergic inhibition of aversive processing highlighted
      by the first phase of this study. This will also provide a basis from which to consider
      potential future study with the same task in MDD subjects undergoing TD.

      There may well be a genetic basis to these phenomena. It is known that the functional variant
      in the promoter region of the serotonin transporter gene (5-HTTLPR) is partly responsible for
      determining how individuals respond to TD. In fact, recently reported that carriers of the
      short 5-HTTLPR allele showed impaired recognition of fearful faces following TD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 10, 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 15, 2014</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Actual">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder, Major</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Healthy Volunteers

        Right-handed subjects (ages 18-50) will be selected who have not met criteria for any major
        psychiatric disorder, have no known first-degree relatives with mood disorders, and have a
        current score on the Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HDRS; 17 item) in the not depressed
        range ( 7). Control subjects will be matched to depressed subjects and their relatives for
        age, gender, and education.

        MDD Samples

        Right-handed subjects (ages 18-50) will be selected with a past history of MDD by DSM-IV
        criteria.

        Healthy Relatives

        Healthy, right-handed, first-degree relatives of patients with MDD will be recruited.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects must not have taken antidepressant drugs for at least 3 months (4 months for
        fluoxetine) prior to the fMRI studies or other medications likely to alter monoamine
        neurochemistry or cerebrovascular and cardiovascular function for at least 3 weeks prior to
        imaging. However, effective medications will not be discontinued for the purposes of this
        study. Subjects will also be excluded if they have:

          1. Psychosis

          2. Medical or neurological illnesses likely to affect physiology or anatomy, i.e.
             hypertension, cardiovascular disorders

          3. A history of drug (including benzodiazepines (BZD)) abuse within 1 year or a lifetime
             history of drug dependence (DSM IV criteria)

          4. A history of alcohol abuse within 1 year or a lifetime history of alcohol dependence
             (DSM IV criteria)

          5. Current pregnancy (as documented by pregnancy testing at screening or at days of the
             challenge studies)

          6. Current breast feeding

          7. Are smokers

          8. Serious suicidal ideation or behavior. In this study, there is a small risk of
             transient depressive symptoms occurring after ingesting the amino acid mixture.
             Therefore, if volunteers manifest evidence of serious suicidal ideation or behavior,
             they will be excluded from participating. Criteria for meeting suicidal ideation
             include but are not limited to: 1) thoughts of suicide within the past 3 months which
             are accompanied by intent to harm oneself, serious consideration of means or plan to
             attempt suicide, evidence of arranging for a suicide attempt (e.g. giving away prized
             possessions or updating a will), or clear desire to commit suicide, 2) severity of
             past suicide events, if applicable or 3) a current plan for harming themselves. All
             assessments will be conducted by an experienced, NIMH credentialed health
             professional, such as a psychiatrist or psychiatric nurse who will use their expert
             knowledge and experiences in determining the authenticity of a participant s
             information and handle the situation accordingly.

          9. General MRI exclusion criteria

        Subjects must exhibit no or only moderate alcohol use. Subjects with current or previous
        regular use (greater than 4 weeks) of BZDs and excessive use of alcohol (greater than 8
        ounces/day for men and greater than 6 ounces/day for women) in the past or present are
        ineligible for participation, as such drug use may confound the results. Smokers (regular
        use within the last 3 months) are ineligible because of the evidence for interactions
        between nicotine and depression, and the possibility of withdrawal symptoms that may affect
        behavioral and neural responses to TD.

        Subjects beyond age 50 are excluded to address the biological heterogeneity encompassed by
        the MDD criteria, since depressives whose age-at-onset is later than 50 have a far greater
        likelihood of having MRI correlates of cerebrovascular disease than age-matched healthy
        controls or age-matched early-onset depressives. Subjects whose first major depressive
        episodes arose temporally after other medical or psychiatric conditions will also be
        excluded, since their functional imaging results generally differ from those reported in
        primary MDD.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christian Grillon, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drevets WC, Price JL, Simpson JR Jr, Todd RD, Reich T, Vannier M, Raichle ME. Subgenual prefrontal cortex abnormalities in mood disorders. Nature. 1997 Apr 24;386(6627):824-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9126739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lesch KP, Bengel D, Heils A, Sabol SZ, Greenberg BD, Petri S, Benjamin J, Müller CR, Hamer DH, Murphy DL. Association of anxiety-related traits with a polymorphism in the serotonin transporter gene regulatory region. Science. 1996 Nov 29;274(5292):1527-31.</citation>
    <PMID>8929413</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreno FA, Rowe DC, Kaiser B, Chase D, Michaels T, Gelernter J, Delgado PL. Association between a serotonin transporter promoter region polymorphism and mood response during tryptophan depletion. Mol Psychiatry. 2002;7(2):213-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11840315</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 15, 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 17, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 18, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Serotonin</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Genotype</keyword>
  <keyword>Negative Affect</keyword>
  <keyword>MDD</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mood Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tryptophan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

