<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00097682</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>050038</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>05-CC-0038</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00097682</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Views of Cancer Patients Regarding Financial Conflicts of Interest</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ethics Study to Understand the Views of Cancer Patients Regarding Financial Conflicts of Interest in Research</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will explore what research patients understand about financial collaborations in
      the research setting and their concerns about these collaborations. Financial partnerships
      are crucial to advancing medical research; however, they are giving rise to increasing
      concerns about financial conflicts of interest and possible impacts on the integrity of
      research and patient safety. This study will examine patients' views about financial ties
      between drug companies and the doctors running research studies, as well as ties between the
      drug companies and the cancer centers where the studies are conducted.

      Patients 18 years of age and older who are enrolled in cancer studies at the National Cancer
      Institute in Bethesda, MD; the Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center in Seattle, WA; the
      Dana-Farber Cancer Institute in Boston, MA; the Columbia Comprehensive University Herbert
      Irving Cancer Center in New York, NY; and the University of Colorado Cancer Center in Denver,
      CO, may be eligible for this study.

      Participants are interviewed about the following:

        -  Patients' awareness and understanding about individual and institutional financial
           conflicts of interest, and how such conflicts, if they exist, are being managed

        -  The impact of a researcher's financial ties on the patient's decision to participate in
           that researcher's study

        -  The impact of the institution's financial ties on the patient's decision to participate
           in research at that institution

        -  Attitudes about policies and practices regarding conflicts of interest in the research
           setting

        -  Attitudes about disclosure of conflicts of interest in the research setting

        -  Patient symptoms and performance

        -  Patient's cancer trial

        -  Patient's cancer history

        -  Patient's trust

        -  Patient demographics (gender, age, race, religion, education, income, health insurance,
           employment).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study seeks to inform deliberation of ethical issues related to financial conflicts of
      interest in clinical research through empirical data obtained from patients participating in
      cancer studies. In particular, this study endeavors to describe and summarize the views of
      patients about both individual and institutional financial conflicts of interest pertaining
      to clinical research. This study will assess awareness of financial conflicts of interest and
      the current safeguards in place to manage financial ties; assess the impact of hypothetical
      financial conflicts of interest on a research subject's decision to participate in a clinical
      study; identify the reasons that financial conflicts of interest either do or do not
      influence patients' research participation; summarize views regarding the presence of
      financial conflicts of interest and what limits should be in place to manage them; identify
      interests about disclosure of these financial conflicts of interest; describe demographic
      characteristics of subjects enrolled in the survey and evaluate the impact of demographic
      information on subjects' views regarding financial conflicts of interest. Participants will
      be recruited from all phases of oncology studies being conducted at 5 sites, the National
      Cancer Institute in Bethesda, MD; the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute in Boston, MA; the Fred
      Hutchinson Cancer Research Center in Seattle, WA; the University of Colorado Cancer Center in
      Denver, CO, and the Columbia University Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center in New
      York, NY. The primary methodology for the study is an in-person administration of a
      questionnaire.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 18, 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 2, 2007</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>300</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects will be included if they:

          1. Have consented to participate in a phase I, I/II, II, or III cancer study and are at
             any point in that study.

          2. Give informed consent.

          3. Understand written and spoken English.

          4. Are over 18 years of age.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80220-3706</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06510-8005</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032-3784</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>28104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelch RP. Maintaining the public trust in clinical research. N Engl J Med. 2002 Jan 24;346(4):285-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11807156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2, 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 24, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Financial Ties</keyword>
  <keyword>Institution</keyword>
  <keyword>Research Doctor</keyword>
  <keyword>Oncology</keyword>
  <keyword>Attitudes</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Survey</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

