<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00094198</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1278</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00094198</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacogenetics and Cardiovascular Events</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess interactions between selected cardiovascular medications and genes in the incidence
      of heart attack, stroke, and atrial fibrillation, an irregular heartbeat.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      This complex study will collect additional genetic data for 3 ongoing case-control
      observational studies of drug-gene interactions in myocardial infarction, stroke, and
      new-onset atrial fibrillation. This study will add single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)
      discovery for 16 of 36 candidate genes involving the renin-angiotensin system, sodium
      transport, adrenergic receptors, and G-proteins, and allow analysis of haplotype data.

      The study was initiated in response to RFA HL-03-001, Ancillary Studies in Pharmacogenetics.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      The primary aim of this study is to assess interactions between selected cardiovascular
      medications and the major candidate-gene variants or haplotypes on the incidence of
      myocardial infarction (MI), stroke and atrial fibrillation (AF). The candidate-gene
      sets-selected on the basis of biology, pharmacology, and information from genome-wide
      scans-include: (1) 10 genes in the renin-angiotensin system; (2) 10 genes involved in renal
      sodium transport; (3) 8 genes encoding alpha and beta adrenergic receptors; (4) 8 other
      genes, including G-proteins, estrogen receptors, and the alpha-1C subunit of the L-type
      calcium channel. The products of these genes represent the sites of action for many
      cardiovascular drugs: angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors, angiotensin receptor
      blockers, all classes of diuretics, alpha blockers, beta-blockers, central alpha agonists,
      calcium antagonists, and estrogens. Both hypothesis-testing and hypothesis-generating
      analyses are planned. For selected single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) studied in vitro or
      in small clinical populations, several specific drug-gene interactions are plausible, and
      these associations will be evaluated in an hypothesis-testing manner.

      The study used data from previously funded case-control studies which are expected to produce
      1053 MI cases, 565 stroke cases and 800 atrial fibrillation cases and 3249 matching controls
      from the enrollees of Group Health Cooperative. These patients will already have had chart
      abstractions, pharmacy database searches, telephone interviews and phlebotomy with specimen
      storage.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Cerebrovascular Accident</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bruce Psaty</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kooperberg C, Ruczinski I. Identifying interacting SNPs using Monte Carlo logic regression. Genet Epidemiol. 2005 Feb;28(2):157-70.</citation>
    <PMID>15532037</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith NL, Heckbert SR, Lemaitre RN, Reiner AP, Lumley T, Weiss NS, Larson EB, Rosendaal FR, Psaty BM. Esterified estrogens and conjugated equine estrogens and the risk of venous thrombosis. JAMA. 2004 Oct 6;292(13):1581-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15467060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Psaty BM, Furberg CD. Contemplating ACTION--long-acting nifedipine in stable angina. Lancet. 2004 Sep 4-10;364(9437):817-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15351169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 15, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 14, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 15, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 21, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

