<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02388386</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PROTEUS-LVAD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02388386</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Monitoring Medication Adherence in Left Ventricular Assist Device Recipients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study of Wireless Observed Therapy With an Ingestible Micro-Sensor Among Patients With Heart Failure and Left Ventricular Assist Devices</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Scripps Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Scripps Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Scripps Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aim to develop a novel and wireless method for monitoring medication
      adherence among heart failure patients with left ventricular assist devices (LVADs). Proteus
      Digital™ has developed an ingestible and bio-absorbable micro-sensor as a strategy to monitor
      medication compliance. The edible sensor has at its core a silicon-based integrated circuit
      measuring 1.0 mm x 0.45 mm and is imbedded on a pill. Once ingested, this circuit is
      activated by gastric acid resulting in an electrochemical redox reaction and an electrical
      charge that is transmitted to a patch worn over the abdomen and wirelessly to a portable
      device such as a smart phone. This strategy of medication adherence differs from conventional
      adherence monitoring including pill counting and patient-recall by precisely tracking
      medication ingestion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objectives are to assess the efficacy and safety of the Proteus Digital™ micro-sensor in
      an exploratory investigation among heart failure patients with LVADs. Medication adherence,
      specifically to anticoagulation is critically important in the post-implant period to
      maintain LVAD function and to decrease thromboembolic complications; however, commonly
      results in significant bleeding resulting in significant morbidity and mortality. In
      addition, the anticipated degree of anticoagulation is unpredictable after LVAD implantation
      due to factors related to changes in hepatic blood flow and endothelial dysfunction.
      Enrolling 10 patients will provide results into the function of micro-sensor and to provide a
      preliminary assessment of sensor-based activity, signal strength and signal duration in LVAD
      recipients. Participants will be enrolled during an in-patient hospitalization to assess the
      efficacy and safety of the device in a monitored setting.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>System Performance - Positive Detection Accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes after ingestion</time_frame>
    <description>Primary outcome measure of system performance will be estimated by the positive detection accuracy, defined as the number of ingestible sensors detected divided by those ingested, and the identification accuracy, defined as the number of ingestible sensors identified with a correct signature divided by those detected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of ingestion to 30 minutes after ingestion</time_frame>
    <description>Specific safety metrics will consist of the following composite outcome:
Safety as measured by vital signs
Cardiac rhythm monitoring review for arrhythmias
LVAD device interrogation for changes in device parameters
Implantable cardioverter defibrillator interrogation for arrhythmia occurrence
Documentation of any symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biofeedback (perceptions of the system will be assessed using a post-study questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay or 3-days which ever is shorter</time_frame>
    <description>At the end of the study, perceptions of the system will be assessed using a post-study questionnaire. Questions will be answered using a Likert scale from 1 (strongly agree) to 10 (strongly disagree). Participants are also required to provide qualitative feedback about their experience using the system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Medication Compliance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PROTEUS-SENSOR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The current study is a prospective interventional design with a single experimental arm. The intervention consists of two components: an edible sensor and a wearable receiver health monitor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PROTEUS-SENSOR</intervention_name>
    <description>An edible sensor system, Proteus Digital™ has been developed for electronically confirming medication adherence, gathering physiologic metrics and communicating these data to patients. The system consists of two major components: an edible sensor and a wearable receiver health monitor. An electrical signal is activated upon ingestion of the Proteus Digital micro-sensor with transmission of this signal to a receiving abdominal patch to quantify medication compliance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PROTEUS-SENSOR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Patients undergoing LVAD implantation for end-stage heart failure or admitted from the
        out-patient setting

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to consistently consume oral intake

          -  Hemodynamic instability defined as hypotension requiring intravenous vasoactive
             medications or arrhythmias requiring intravenous antiarrhythmics or oral
             antiarrhythmics for rhythm stabilization

          -  Gastrointestinal bleeding requiring intravenous gastric acid secretion inhibitors
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sanjeev Bhavnani, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Scripps Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sanjeev Bhavnani, MD</last_name>
    <phone>8585545588</phone>
    <email>bhavnani.sanjeev@scrippshealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Thomas J Heywood, MD</last_name>
    <phone>8585545588</phone>
    <email>Heywood.James@scrippshealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Scripps Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhavnani SP, Narula J, Sengupta PP. Mobile technology and the digitization of healthcare. Eur Heart J. 2016 May 7;37(18):1428-38. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehv770. Epub 2016 Feb 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26873093</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiCarlo LA, Weinstein RL, Morimoto CB, Savage GM, Moon GL, Au-Yeung K, Kim YA. Patient-Centered Home Care Using Digital Medicine and Telemetric Data for Hypertension: Feasibility and Acceptability of Objective Ambulatory Assessment. J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich). 2016 Sep;18(9):901-6. doi: 10.1111/jch.12787. Epub 2016 Feb 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26890041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiCarlo L, Moon G, Intondi A, Duck R, Frank J, Hafazi H, Behzadi Y, Robertson T, Costello B, Savage G, Zdeblick M. A digital health solution for using and managing medications: wirelessly observed therapy. IEEE Pulse. 2012 Sep-Oct;3(5):23-6. doi: 10.1109/MPUL.2012.2205777.</citation>
    <PMID>23014703</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Browne SH, Behzadi Y, Littlewort G. Let Visuals Tell the Story: Medication Adherence in Patients with Type II Diabetes Captured by a Novel Ingestion Sensor Platform. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2015 Dec 31;3(4):e108. doi: 10.2196/mhealth.4292.</citation>
    <PMID>26721413</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 25, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 17, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Telemedicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobile Health</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be made available upon request</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

