<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02386384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-01-FB-0004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02386384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TNFα and MFG-E8: Novel Biomarkers to Predict Implantation Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>TNFα (Tumor Necrosis Factor Alpha) and MFG-E8 (Milk Fat Globule-Epidermal Growth Factor 8): Novel Biomarkers to Predict Implantation Failure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eastern Virginia Medical School</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eastern Virginia Medical School</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Question: Can implantation failure (IF) be predicted prior to in vitro fertilization (IVF)? A
      pilot, non-interventional, clinical study Prospective, controlled, cohort study
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesize that TNFα and MFG-E8 cooperatively maintain the integrity of
      the normal endometrium, and that in patients with IF or with recurrent pregnancy loss (RPL)
      of unexplained origin, excessive TNFα increases the maternal shedding of MFG-E8, disrupting
      the normal protective effect of this protein, resulting in damage of the endometrial
      epithelium and impairing trophoblast invasion. The investigators propose that these molecules
      can be measured in local tissue (endometrium) as well as in serum as a reflection of
      increased inflammation and can therefore be used as markers of implantation and its failure.
      The investigators hypothesis is that TNFα is up-regulated in serum of women with implantation
      defects (IF and RM of unexplained origin) and this causes perturbation of MFG-E8 secretion.
      These results will provide first evidence demonstrating endometrial dysfunctions resulting
      from over-expression of pro-inflammatory molecules. The release of significant quantities of
      these molecules into serum broadens the maternal-fetal interface beyond the uterus and into
      the maternal circulation. The characterization of these molecules is essential to better
      understand, not only their biological effects, but also their potential as prognostic and
      diagnostic biomarkers for detection of IF. More importantly, these molecules could be
      potential therapeutic targets (perhaps intrauterine infusion of MFG-E8 for tissue repair,
      and/or oral administration of TNFα antagonists) to improve implantation outcomes. Two recent
      studies have reported the successful therapeutic use of recombinant human MFG-E8 (rhMFG-E8)
      in animals: one was used to decrease intestinal injury after whole body radiation (Ajakaiye
      et al, 2012), and the other was to mitigate inflammation and tissue injury after hemorrhagic
      stroke (Wang et al, 2012). Also, TNFα inhibitors have been shown to significantly increase
      IVF outcome in infertile patients (Winger et al, 2009 and 2008). In summary, these two
      pivotal studies show promising clinical uses of rhMFG-E8 in tissue repair/remodeling by
      decreasing apoptosis, and provide basis for their use as candidates for further clinical
      development in reproductive health.

      Objectives: Here, the investigators seek to delineate novel diagnostic methods with the
      ultimate long term goal of designing directed therapies to improve embryo implantation
      competence.

        -  The specific aim is to quantify and correlate MFG-E8 and TNFα in serum and in
           endometrial biopsies of women in 3 groups: controls, IF and RM.

        -  The ultimate goal of this study is to provide data leading to a simple and quick test to
           measure soluble serum markers of IF/RM in order to discriminate prospectively between
           these groups of patients.

        -  To translate these findings into the use of modulators of these inflammatory molecules
           to improve pregnancy rates in patients with predicted implantation defects. It is widely
           known that &quot;classic&quot; markers of endometrial receptivity such as those provided by an
           invasive endometrial biopsy (with Hematoxilin-Eosin staining, or immuhistochemistry, or
           even with microarray technology) are not reliable to establish clear-cut diagnosis due
           to cycle-to-cycle variations and overlap of results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>concentration of MFG-E8 and TNFα in serum and in endometrial biopsies controls, IF and RM.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 menstrual cycle</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Infertility</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Pregnancy Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>Normal fertile</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Implantation Failure</arm_group_label>
    <description>Failure to conceive</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Recurrent Pregnancy Loss</arm_group_label>
    <description>2 or more unexplained miscarriages</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        women 21-35 years old attending an infertility clinic in an academic center
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  women 21-35y

          -  with no contraindication to pregnancy

          -  on no hormonal contraception

          -  normal uterine cavity

          -  absence of hydrosalpinges

          -  normal ovarian reserve (FSH&lt;13 mIU/.ml or AMH&gt;1 ng/ml or normal antral follicular
             count&gt;10 total follicles &lt;10 mm in diameter, American Society for Reproductive
             Medicine-ASRM 2012).

          -  Three groups of patients will be enrolled: 10 fertile controls (C1-10: women who are
             participating in the donor egg program as egg donors), 10 with unexplained
             implantation failure (IF1-10: patients who have failed IVF cycles -failure of
             implantation following 2 or more cycles with transfer of embryos of good quality-at
             least 2 cleaving embryos with 6-8 cells, grades 1- 3 (scale 1-highest and 5-poorest
             morphology score), and normal uterus, and 10 with recurrent unexplained first
             trimester miscarriages (RM1-10: 2 consecutive miscarriages under 10 weeks, after
             spontaneous or IVF conceptions).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  contraindication to pregnancy

          -  use of hormonal contraception

          -  abnormal uterine cavity

          -  hydrosalpinges

          -  abnormal karyotype.

          -  women who are pregnant or planning to get pregnant in the cycle in which they are
             participating in this study

          -  women who have had a hysterectomy (previous removal of your uterus)

          -  have a current medical condition, which, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             result in hazards to the subject, should she participate in the study or have a
             current medical condition which would potentially confound the study results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Silvina M Bocca, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eastern Virginia Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu L, Anderson S, Oehninger S, Bocca S. Tumor necrosis factor α up-regulates endometrial milk fat globule-epidermal growth factor 8 protein production via nuclear factor κB activation, resulting in cell migration of epithelial cells. Fertil Steril. 2014 Feb;101(2):552-9. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2013.10.032. Epub 2013 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>24262600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmitz C, Yu L, Bocca S, Anderson S, Cunha-Filho JS, Rhavi BS, Oehninger S. Role for the endometrial epithelial protein MFG-E8 and its receptor integrin αvβ3 in human implantation: results of an in vitro trophoblast attachment study using established human cell lines. Fertil Steril. 2014 Mar;101(3):874-82. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2013.12.015. Epub 2014 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24424369</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sarhan et al, MFG-E8 (milk fat globule EGF factor 8 protein) is a novel endometrial epithelial glycoprotein regulated by human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) and secreted via microparticles. J Cell Signaling and Trafficking 2013</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bocca SM, Anderson S, Amaker B, Swanson RJ, Franchi A, Lattanzio F, Oehninger S. Milk fat globule epidermal growth factor 8 (MFG-E8): a novel protein in the mammalian endometrium with putative roles in implantation and placentation. Placenta. 2012 Oct;33(10):795-802. doi: 10.1016/j.placenta.2012.06.015. Epub 2012 Jul 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22770563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riggs RM, Bocca S, Anderson S, Franchi A, Rhavi BS, Oehninger S. Epithelial cell protein milk fat globule-epidermal growth factor 8 and human chorionic gonadotropin regulate stromal cell apoptosis in the human endometrium. Fertil Steril. 2012 Dec;98(6):1549-56.e3. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2012.07.1127. Epub 2012 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22921913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Franchi A, Bocca S, Anderson S, Riggs R, Oehninger S. Expression of milk fat globule EGF-factor 8 (MFG-E8) mRNA and protein in the human endometrium and its regulation by prolactin. Mol Hum Reprod. 2011 Jun;17(6):360-71. doi: 10.1093/molehr/gaq102. Epub 2010 Dec 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21177637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bocca et al. Milk fat globule epithelial growth factor 8 (MFG-E8) regulates human endometrial endothelial cell adhesion and proliferation. Fertil Steril 2010, P423.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Franchi A, Zaret J, Zhang X, Bocca S, Oehninger S. Expression of immunomodulatory genes, their protein products and specific ligands/receptors during the window of implantation in the human endometrium. Mol Hum Reprod. 2008 Jul;14(7):413-21. doi: 10.1093/molehr/gan029. Epub 2008 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18524812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirkin S, Arslan M, Churikov D, Corica A, Diaz JI, Williams S, Bocca S, Oehninger S. In search of candidate genes critically expressed in the human endometrium during the window of implantation. Hum Reprod. 2005 Aug;20(8):2104-17. Epub 2005 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>15878921</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirkin S, Nikas G, Hsiu JG, Díaz J, Oehninger S. Gene expression profiles and structural/functional features of the peri-implantation endometrium in natural and gonadotropin-stimulated cycles. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2004 Nov;89(11):5742-52.</citation>
    <PMID>15531538</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 6, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 10, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 11, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Eastern Virginia Medical School</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Silvina Bocca</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pregnancy failure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Abortion, Habitual</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

