<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02387294</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FABNovo-H-16</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02387294</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immunogenicity and Tolerability Study of Fluval AB Novo Suspension for Injection for Children and Adolescents</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunogenicity and Tolerability Study of Fluval AB Novo Suspension for Injection (Trivalent, Seasonal Influenza Vaccine, Active Ingredient Content: 6 μg HA/Strain/0.5 ml) for Children and Adolescents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fluart Innovative Vaccine Ltd, Hungary</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fluart Innovative Vaccine Ltd, Hungary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Immunogenicity and Tolerability Study of Fluval AB Novo Suspension for Injection (trivalent,
      seasonal influenza vaccine, active ingredient content: 6 μg HA/strain/0.5 ml) for Children
      and Adolescents.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      STUDY PERIOD:

      Length of enrolment: 2 weeks (estimated) Participation per subject: max. 1 month

      OBJECTIVES:

      Immunogenicity Objectives:

      To assess immunogenicity of a single intramuscular injection of Fluval AB Novo suspension for
      injection (trivalent, seasonal influenza vaccine, active ingredient content: 6 μg HA/0.5 ml
      of seasonal A/H1N1, A/H3N2 and B influenza antigens each), as measured by haemagglutination
      inhibition (HI) test.

      Safety and Tolerability Objectives:

      To evaluate safety and tolerability (incidence of adverse events) of a single intramuscular
      injection of Fluval AB Novo suspension for injection.

      CLINICAL PHASE:

      Phase III

      TYPE:

      Interventional, prevention

      DESIGN:

      Non-controlled, open, multi-centre

      METHODS:

      In this uncontrolled, open, multi-centre immunogenicity and tolerability study subjects will
      be enrolled into two groups according to age:

      Age group 1: children (3-11 years): single intramuscular injection of Fluval AB Novo 0.25 ml
      suspension for injection; Age group 2: adolescents (12-18 years): single intramuscular
      injection of Fluval AB Novo 0.5 ml suspension for injection; Subjects will be observed for 30
      minutes after the injection for any immediate reactions.

      All adolescent subjects aged 12 to 18 years and the legitimate representatives of all
      volunteers will be requested to complete a Diary Card (DC) to record local reactions
      (injection site pain, erythema, swelling, induration, numbness, sensitivity and haematoma)
      and systemic reactions (fever, shivering, headache, malaise, fatigue, sweating, nausea,
      myalgia, arthralgia, dizziness and urticaria) starting on the day of vaccination on Visit 1
      (Day 0) until 7 days following that.

      All adverse events will be collected during the period of Visit 1 (Day 0) to Visit 2 (between
      Day 21 and Day 28); Serum samples for immunogenicity assays will be collected immediately
      before immunization on Visit 1 (Day 0) and on Visit 2 (between Day 21 and Day 28) in all
      subjects. Immunogenicity will be evaluated by HI test.

      INVESTIGATIONAL MEDICINAL PRODUCT:

      Fluval AB Novo suspension for injection (trivalent, seasonal influenza vaccine, active
      ingredient content: 6 μg HA/0.5 ml of seasonal A/H1N1, A/H3N2 and B influenza antigens each)
      with aluminium phosphate gel adjuvant.

      Lot No.: FL-N-05/13

      CONCOMITANT VACCINES:

      No concomitant vaccination is permitted for the duration of the study except for
      post-exposure vaccination in a medical emergency (e.g. tetanus, rabies, hepatitis).

      STUDY POPULATION:

      Considering approximately 17% of drop-out (one participant out of six), in total 120 subjects
      (60 subjects in each age group) will be enrolled in order to achieve at least 100 evaluable
      subjects (50 subjects in each age group).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity of a single intramuscular injection of the study vaccine as measured by HAG test.</measure>
    <time_frame>21-28 days after vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>To assess immunogenicity of a single intramuscular injection of Fluval AB Novo as measured by haemagglutination inhibition (HI) test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of a single intramuscular injection of the study vaccine as measured by occurrence of adverse reactions.</measure>
    <time_frame>21-28 days after vaccination</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Children and adolescents</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention:
Vaccination with Fluval AB Novo.
Dosage:
Children (3-11 years): 0,25 ml (half dose of) a single intramuscular injection of Fluval AB Novo suspension for injection.
Adolescents (12-18 years): 0,5 ml (one dose of) a single intramuscular injection of Fluval AB Novo suspension for injection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ntervention: Vaccination with Fluval AB Novo.</intervention_name>
    <description>vaccination</description>
    <arm_group_label>Children and adolescents</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fluval AB Novo suspension for injection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children aged 3 to 11 years, adolescents aged 12 to 18 years from both sexes;

          -  Are in good health (as determined by vital signs and existing medical condition) or
             are in stable medical condition. Subjects will not be excluded with known adequately
             treated clinically significant organ or systemic diseases (e.g. asthma or diabetes),
             such that, in the opinion of the investigator, the significance of the disease will
             not compromise the subject's participation in the study;

          -  Female volunteers of childbearing potential with a negative result from the urine
             pregnancy test prior to vaccination who agrees to use an acceptable contraception
             method or abstinence throughout the trial and not become pregnant for the duration of
             the study;

          -  Capability of adolescent participants aged 12 to 18 years and the legitimate
             representative of all volunteers to understand and comply with planned study
             procedures;

          -  Adolescent participants aged 12 to 18 years and the legitimate representative of all
             volunteers provide written Informed Consent (IC) prior to initiation of study
             procedures;

          -  Absence of existence of any exclusion criteria.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy, breast feeding or positive urine pregnancy test at baseline prior to
             vaccination. Female subjects who are able to bear children but not willing to use an
             acceptable contraception method for the duration of the study.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to eggs, thiomersal, formaldehyde, gentamycin, ciprofloxacin,
             neomycin, vancomycin or any other component of the vaccine;

          -  History of Guillain-Barré syndrome;

          -  History of neurological symptoms or signs, or anaphylactic shock following
             administration of any vaccine;

          -  Serious disease, such as cancer, autoimmune disease, advanced arteriosclerotic
             disease, complicated diabetes mellitus, acute or progressive hepatic disease, acute or
             progressive renal disease, congestive heart failure;

          -  Immunosuppressive therapy within 36 months prior to vaccination;

          -  Concomitant corticosteroid therapy, including high-dose inhaled corticosteroids;

          -  Receipt of immunostimulants,

          -  Receipt of parenteral immunoglobulin, blood products and/or plasma derivate within 3
             months prior to vaccination;

          -  Suspected or known HIV, HBV or HCV infection;

          -  Acute disease and/or axillary temperature ≥37oC within 3 days prior to vaccination;

          -  Vaccine therapy within 4 weeks prior to vaccination;

          -  Influenza vaccination (any kind) within 6 months prior to vaccination;

          -  Experimental drug therapy within 4 weeks prior to vaccination;

          -  Concomitant participation in another clinical study;

          -  Any condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, may interfere with the
             evaluation of the study;

          -  Past or current psychiatric disease of the volunteer or the legitimate representative
             that upon judgement of the investigator may have effect on the objective
             decision-making of the volunteer;

          -  Alcohol or drug abuse of the participant or the legitimate representative.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 13, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 13, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>immunogenicity</keyword>
  <keyword>reduced dos</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase III</keyword>
  <keyword>tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>safety</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

