<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01750827</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>102487</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01750827</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Assess the Effect of SB 659032 on Platelet Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single Dose Study to Assess the Effect of Non-Bioenhanced, Non-Enteric Coated, Freebase SB-659032 on Platelet Function in Healthy Adult Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This will be an open-label, single dose, single period study. Approximately 14 subjects will
      receive one dose of 250 mg of non-enteric coated SB-659032 following a low-fat breakfast.
      This study will evaluate whether SB-659032 has an effect on platelet function as determined
      by platelet aggregation tests using the agonists ADP and collagen. Blood samples for PK
      analysis and measurement of Lp-PLA2 activity will also be collected
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2004</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2004</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Platelet aggregation</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Percent maximum platelet aggregation following ADP- and collagen-induced aggregation a 24-hour post-dose period. Other pharmacokinetic endpoints of interest are Tmax of SB-659032 and its pharmacologically active metabolite, SB-664601, as well as Cmax of SB-664601 and concentrations of SB-664601 over a 24-hour post-dose</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK of SB-659032 and SB-664601</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax of SB-659032 and concentrations of SB-659032 at collection timepoints over</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamics</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma Lp-PLA2 activity, expressed in terms of percent inhibition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety/tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Spontaneous AE reporting, 12-lead ECGs, vital signs, nursing/physician observation, and clinical laboratory tests</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SB-659032</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose open label</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SB659032</intervention_name>
    <description>single dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>SB-659032</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy males or females who are 18 to 55 years of age, inclusive.

          -  Body weight greater than 50 kg (110 pounds) and body mass index (BMI) between 19 and
             30 where: BMI = weight in kg (height in meters)2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any clinically relevant abnormality identified on the screening medical assessment,
             laboratory examination or ECG

          -  History of asthma, anaphylaxis or anaphalactoid reactions, severe allergic responses

          -  History of smoking within six months of the study and/or has a positive urine cotinine
             at screening

          -  History of alcohol consumption exceeding, on average, 7 drinks/week for women or 14
             drinks/week for men (1 drink = 5 ounces of wine or 12 ounces of beer or 1.5 ounces of
             hard liquor) within 6 months of the first dose of study medication

          -  Positive urine drug or alcohol at screening

          -  Use of aspirin, aspirin-containing products, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents or
             any antiplatelet medication within 14 days prior to the first dose of study medication
             (a list of these drugs will be reviewed with the subject at screening and provided to
             them to take home)

          -  Use of prescription (including hormone replacement therapy) or non-prescription drugs
             and vitamins within 7 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to
             administration of study medication. An exception is acetaminophen which is allowed at
             doses of less than and equal to 2g/day for up to 48 hours prior to dosing

          -  Use of dietary/herbal supplements including (but not limited to) St. John's wort,
             kava, ephedra (ma huang), gingko biloba, DHEA, yohimbe, saw palmetto, ginseng and red
             yeast rice within 14 days prior to treatment with study medication

          -  Treatment with an investigational drug within 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to dosing

          -  Consumption of grapefruit or grapefruit juice within 7 days prior to the first dose of
             study medication

          -  A history of biliary tract disease including a history of liver disease with elevated
             liver function tests of known or unknown etiology

          -  Pregnant or nursing female subjects. For female subjects, a positive serum β-hCG at
             screening or Day -1; or for female subjects of childbearing potential an unwillingness
             to agree to one of the methods of contraception listed in the protocol from screening
             until the completion of follow-up procedures. Hormonal contraceptive methods (e.g.
             oral contraceptive pill, implant) for female subjects are not permitted. At least a
             one week interval between screening and first study drug administration will be
             observed for the pregnancy tests.

          -  For male subjects, an unwillingness to abstain from sexual intercourse with pregnant
             or lactating women or an unwillingness to use a condom and another form of
             contraception (e.g., IUD, birth control pills taken by female partner, diaphragm with
             spermicide) if engaging in sexual intercourse with a woman who could become pregnant
             until discharge from the study Donation of blood in excess of 500 mL within 56 days
             prior to dosing

          -  Full ADP- and/or collagen-induced aggregation (greater than and equal to 40%) at all
             three concentrations of one or both agonists, as assessed on Day -1

          -  No ADP- or collagen-induced aggregation (&lt;40%) at the highest concentration of either
             agonist, as assessed on Day -1
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lenexa</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 6, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 13, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 17, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 13, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 13, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 17, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>platelet function</keyword>
  <keyword>atherosclerosis,</keyword>
  <keyword>SB-659032</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

