<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01750060</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PK2011-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01750060</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetic Characterization of the Active, Separated System With PK Controller (Fentanyl Iontophoretic Transdermal System, 40 Mcg Fentanyl Per Activation).</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetic Characterization of the Active, Separated System With PK Controller (Fentanyl Iontophoretic Transdermal System, 40 Mcg Fentanyl Per Activation).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Incline Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Incline Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      &quot;This study is a single-center, randomized, open-label, 3-period, 5-treatment, 6-sequence
      design. A total of 54 eligible subjects will receive three total treatments; one with
      intravenous (IV) infusion and two with the Study System. Each subject will be randomly
      assigned to receive a treatment sequence consisting of Treatment A (IV fentanyl citrate),
      Study System Treatment B (170 mcAmp), and one of three additional Study System treatments
      (140 mcAmp or 200 mcAmp or 230 mcAmp) &quot;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      &quot;The Study System is a single-use system that consists of two parts: a Drug Unit containing
      10.8 mg fentanyl hydrochloride, and a Controller that supplies the dosing current. The two
      parts are packaged separately and assembled immediately prior to use. The Study System will
      be applied to the upper, outer arm of each subject. Fentanyl will be delivered from the Study
      System via transdermal iontophoresis using a current of 170 mcAmp (Treatment B), 140 mcAmp
      (Treatment C), 200 mcAmp (Treatment D), or 230 mcAmp (Treatment E). Each subject will be
      randomly assigned to a treatment sequence consisting of Treatment A (IV fentanyl citrate),
      Study System Treatment B (170 mcAmp), and one of three additional Study System treatments
      consisting of Treatment C (140 mcAmp), Treatment D (200 mcAmp), or Treatment E (230 mcAmp).
      Each subject will therefore receive a total of three treatments (A and B and either C, D, or
      E).

      The specific treatments are outlined in detail below:

        -  Treatment A: Fentanyl citrate (equivalent to 80 mcg fentanyl) administered over 20
           minutes by IV infusion every hour through 23.33 hours.

        -  Treatment B: Two consecutive 40 mcg fentanyl doses each delivered over 10 minutes by the
           Study System (170 mcAmp) every hour through 23.33 hours.

        -  Treatment C: Two consecutive 35 mcg fentanyl doses, each delivered over 10 minutes by
           the Study System (140 mcAmp) every hour through 23.33 hours.

        -  Treatment D: Two consecutive 50 mcg fentanyl doses, each delivered over 10 minutes by
           the Study System (200 mcAmp) every hour through 23.33 hours.

        -  Treatment E: Two consecutive 54 mcg fentanyl doses, each delivered over 10 minutes by
           the Study System (230 mcAmp) every hour through 23.33 hours.

      Naltrexone (50 mg) will be administered orally (PO) every 12 hours, beginning 14 hours before
      the start of each fentanyl treatment and ending approximately 11 hours after completion of
      each treatment &quot;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure area under the fentanyl concentration-time curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>The two-hour period for hours 23-24 for all treatment groups.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure area under the fentanyl concentration-time curve (AUC), one of the five key pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters for the Active, Separated System with PK Controller in the study population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure maximum fentanyl concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>The two-hour period for hours 23-24 for all treatment groups.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure maximum fentanyl concentration (Cmax), one of the five key pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters for the Active, Separated System with PK Controller in the study population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure time to Cmax (tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>The two-hour period for hours 23-24 for all treatment groups.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure time to Cmax (tmax), one of the five key pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters for the Active, Separated System with PK Controller in the study population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure terminal half-life (t½)</measure>
    <time_frame>The two-hour period for hours 23-24 for all treatment groups.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure terminal half-life (t½), one of the five key pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters for the Active, Separated System with PK Controller in the study population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the amount of fentanyl absorbed</measure>
    <time_frame>The two-hour period for hours 23-24 for all treatment groups.</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the amount of fentanyl absorbed, one of the five key pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters for the Active, Separated System with PK Controller in the study population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl citrate IV infusion &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fentanyl citrate (equivalent to 80 mcg fentanyl)administered over 20 minutes by IV infusion every hour through 23.33 hours. Naltrexone (50 mg) will be administered orally (PO) every 12 hours, beginning 14 hours before the start of fentanyl treatment and ending approximately 11 hours after completion of treatment regimen to antagonize the clinical opioid effects of fentanyl.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl Study System (170 mcAmps) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two consecutive 40 mcg fentanyl doses each delivered over 10 minutes by the Study System (170 mcAmps) every hour through 23.33 hours. Naltrexone (50 mg) will be administered orally (PO) every 12 hours, beginning 14 hours before the start of fentanyl treatment and ending approximately 11 hours after completion of treatment regimen to antagonize the clinical opioid effects of fentanyl.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl, Study System (140 mcAmp) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two consecutive 35 mcg fentanyl doses, each delivered over 10 minutes by the Study System (140 mcAmp) every hour through 23.33 hours. Naltrexone (50 mg) will be administered orally (PO) every 12 hours, beginning 14 hours before the start of fentanyl treatment and ending approximately 11 hours after completion of treatment regimen to antagonize the clinical opioid effects of fentanyl.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl, Study System (200 mcAmp) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two consecutive 50 mcg fentanyl doses, each delivered over 10 minutes by the Study System (200 mcAmp) every hour through 23.33 hours. Naltrexone (50 mg) will be administered orally (PO) every 12 hours, beginning 14 hours before the start of fentanyl treatment and ending approximately 11 hours after completion of treatment regimen to antagonize the clinical opioid effects of fentanyl.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl, Study System (230 mcAmp) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two consecutive 54 mcg fentanyl doses, each delivered over 10 minutes by the Study System (230 mcAmp) every hour through 23.33 hours. Naltrexone (50 mg) will be administered orally (PO) every 12 hours, beginning 14 hours before the start of fentanyl treatment and ending approximately 11 hours after completion of treatment regimen to antagonize the clinical opioid effects of fentanyl.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fentanyl</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl citrate IV infusion &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl Study System (170 mcAmps) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl, Study System (140 mcAmp) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl, Study System (200 mcAmp) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl, Study System (230 mcAmp) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Naltrexone</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl citrate IV infusion &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl Study System (170 mcAmps) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl, Study System (140 mcAmp) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl, Study System (200 mcAmp) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl, Study System (230 mcAmp) &amp; Naltrexone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects must provide written informed consent to participate in the study and
             document their understanding that they are free to withdraw from the study at any
             time.

          2. Subjects must be healthy volunteers with no clinically relevant abnormalities, as
             determined by medical history, physical examination, blood chemistry, complete blood
             count, routine urinalysis (a microscopic urine analysis will be performed at the
             Investigator's discretion if the macroscopic analysis is abnormal), and
             electrocardiogram (ECG). Prior medical history, physical examination, and physical and
             laboratory findings will be reviewed and repeated as deemed appropriate by the
             supervising physician.

          3. Subjects must be male or female volunteers, between ages 18 to 45 years, inclusive.

          4. Subjects must have a Body Mass Index (BMI = weight [kg]/height2 [m2] of 18 to 28
             kg/m2, inclusive.

          5. Subjects must have an average blood pressure from three separate readings in the range
             of 100 to 139 mm Hg systolic (inclusive) and 50 and 89 mm Hg diastolic (inclusive)
             after sitting for 5 minutes before and between readings.

          6. Subjects must have negative urine drug test results (for drugs of abuse) in each urine
             sample collected at the time of fentanyl dosing in each treatment period. Each urine
             sample will be tested for the presence of cannabinoids, amphetamines, barbiturates,
             benzodiazepines, cocaine, and opiates.

          7. Subjects must have a negative alcohol test within the 24 hours before the start of
             fentanyl dosing in each treatment period.

          8. Subjects must provide consent to use a medically acceptable method of contraception
             throughout the entire duration of the study and for one week after the study is
             completed. Medically acceptable methods of contraception that may be used by the
             subject and/or female partner include birth control pills, diaphragm with spermicide,
             intrauterine device (IUD), condom with spermicide, vaginal spermicidal suppository,
             surgical sterilization (6 months post-surgery), post-menopausal (not experienced a
             menstrual period for a minimum of 2 years), and progestin implant or injection (used
             consistently for the 3 months prior to study dosing).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects who are pregnant or plan to become pregnant during the time of their
             participation in this study

          2. Subjects with clinically significant medical problems that, in the opinion of the
             supervising principal investigator, place the subject at undue risk of AEs. These
             conditions can include, but are not limited to, dermatologic, psychiatric,
             respiratory, cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, gastrointestinal, hematological,
             genitourinary, gynecologic, neurologic, or endocrine or other organ abnormality or
             pathology.

          3. Subjects with evidence of orthostatic hypotension (e.g., supine-to-standing blood
             pressure decrease of ≥ 20 mm Hg systolic or ≥ 10 mm Hg diastolic AND ≥ 20 beats per
             minute (bpm) increase in heart rate after standing for 3 minutes) or with any reported
             symptoms of lightheadedness, dizziness, or fainting upon standing.

          4. Subjects with resting heart rate &lt; 50 or &gt; 100 beats per minute.

          5. Subjects with a history of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) or any other
             lung disease (e.g., sleep apnea,asthma) that could cause CO2 retention beyond normal.

          6. Subjects with oxygen saturation &lt; 97% on room air.

          7. Subjects with active systemic skin disease or with active local skin disease, such as
             but not limited to, sunburn, psoriasis, or atopic dermatitis, which would preclude
             application of the Study System to the upper outer arm.

          8. Subjects with a history of significant dermatologic cancers (e.g., melanoma or
             squamous cell carcinoma). Basal cell carcinomas that were superficial and do not
             involve the arms are acceptable.

          9. Subjects with localized skin pigmentation (e.g., tattoos, sunburn, scars, branding,
             etc.) or open sores, body piercing, active skin lesions on the upper arms that could
             interfere with the ability to assess skin site reactions.

         10. Subjects with excessive body hair at the intended application site and who refuse hair
             clipping at the application site

         11. Subjects with a known allergy or hypersensitivity to fentanyl or other opioids,
             naltrexone, naloxone, cetylpyridinium chloride, skin adhesives, tapes, or other
             transdermal systems

         12. Subjects who have reported using:

               -  prescription medication (except for sex-hormone replacement or birth control)
                  within 14 days prior to Day 0 of the first treatment period

               -  over-the-counter (OTC) medication (except for multivitamin supplements or
                  acetaminophen &lt; 2 g/day) within 3 days prior to Day 0 of the first treatment
                  period

               -  alcohol, grapefruit juice, Seville oranges (e.g., marmalade), caffeine, or
                  xanthine-containing products within 48 hours prior to dosing in each fentanyl
                  treatment group

               -  daily doses of herbal medication (e.g., Hypericum perforatum [St. John's Wort],
                  Ephedra, Ginkgo, Ginseng, or garlic supplement) within 14 days before Day 0 of
                  the first treatment period

               -  prescription or OTC topical medications on the arms, including but not limited to
                  corticosteroids and retinoids, within 28 days

         13. Subjects planning to take prescription, OTC, or herbal medications from Day 0 of the
             first treatment period to the last study assessment with the exception of sex-hormone
             replacement, birth control, multivitamins, or acetaminophen (&lt; 2 g/day). NOTE: use of
             topical medications, including antibiotics and corticosteroids, required to treat skin
             irritation resulting from application of the Study System is allowed.

         14. Subjects who have received an investigational drug within the longer of: (a) the past
             28 days, or (b) a period of five times the drug's half-life.

         15. Subjects with a history or presence of drug or alcohol dependence or abuse.

         16. Subjects who smoke &gt; 10 cigarettes, 2 cigars, or 2 tobacco pipes per day within the
             last 6 months, as determined by medical history and/or subject's verbal report.

         17. Subjects who are unable to abstain from smoking during the treatment periods.

         18. Subjects who consume alcohol in quantities &gt; 2 alcohol drinks every day, where 1
             alcohol drink is defined as 12 ounces of beer, 1 ounce of hard liquor, or 4 ounces of
             wine.

         19. Subjects who exhibit one or more signs or symptoms of opioid withdrawal due to the
             naloxone challenge test as determined by the Investigator(s).

         20. Males with hemoglobin &lt; 12.5 g/dL and females with hemoglobin &lt; 11.5 g/dL.

         21. Subjects who have donated blood, experienced a blood loss of &gt; 400 mL within 28 days
             before dosing, or who plan to donate blood during the study.

         22. Subjects who donated plasma within 7 days prior to dosing, or who plan to donate
             plasma during the study.

         23. Subjects who are febrile (temperature &gt; 100.3ºF) at check-in for each treatment
             period.

         24. Subjects who are known to have tested positive for HIV or hepatitis B or hepatitis C.

         25. Employees of the investigator or study center, as well as family members of the
             employees or the investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert I. Cooper, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>PRACS Institute, Ltd.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PRACS Institute, Ltd.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fargo</city>
        <state>North Dakota</state>
        <zip>58104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 10, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 17, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 19, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Naltrexone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

