<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01752751</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LCCC 1224</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1224</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>121731</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01752751</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Predicting Tolerance to Radiation Therapy in Older Adults With Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Predicting Tolerance to Radiation Therapy in Older Adults With Cancer: A Prospective Blinded Study of the Comprehensive Geriatric Assessment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alpha Omega Alpha Honor Medical Society</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A comprehensive geriatric assessment tool developed by Hurria and colleagues has been used in
      non-radiation oncology clinical settings to predict how older adults tolerate cancer
      treatments. The investigators think this same tool (referred to as the CGA) can be used in a
      radiation oncology clinic to predict for poor treatment tolerance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A comprehensive geriatric assessment tool developed by Hurria and colleagues has been used in
      non-radiation oncology clinical settings to predict for toxicity in older patients during
      cancer treatments.1 The investigators hypothesize that the same tool (referred to throughout
      this document as the CGA) can be used in a radiation oncology clinic to predict for poor
      treatment tolerance. The primary objective of this study is to assess the association between
      pre-treatment functional status (as measured by the Independent Activities of Daily Living
      (I-ADL) components of the CGA) and poor tolerance to radiation therapy (as defined in section
      2.3.1). Secondary objectives include exploration of associations between pre-treatment I-ADL
      status on the CGA and the occurrence of any acute grade 3-5 toxicity from radiation therapy,
      or any decrease in Quality of Life (QoL) measures throughout radiation therapy as assessed by
      the EORTC QLQ-C30 questionnaire. The investigators also want to compare the rate of physician
      reported acute toxicities to patient reported acute toxicities in an older cancer patient
      population, assess any association between elevated p16Ink4α expression in peripheral T
      lymphocytes and poor tolerance to or acute grade 3-5 toxicity from radiation therapy, and
      explore any association between other baseline components of the CGA and poor tolerance to or
      acute grade 3-5 toxicity from radiation therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 10, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between pre-treatment loss of at least one independent activity of daily living (I-ADL) and poor tolerance to radiation therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 weeks post-radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the association between pre-treatment loss of at least one independent activity of daily living (I-ADL) on the CGA and poor tolerance to radiation therapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between pre-treatment loss of at least one independent activity of daily living (I-ADL) and the occurrence of any patient-reported toxicity from radiation therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 weeks post-radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the association between pre-treatment loss of at least one I-ADL on the CGA and the occurrence of any patient-reported acute grade 3-5 toxicity from radiation therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between pre-treatment loss of at least one independent activity of daily living and changes in Quality of Life measures</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 weeks post radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the association between pre-treatment loss of at least one I-ADL on the CGA and changes in QoL measures, as evaluated by the EORTC-QLQ-C30 throughout radiation therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of physician and patient-reported acute grade 3-5 toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 weeks post-radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>To compare physician-reported acute grade 3-5 toxicities to patient-reported grade 3-5 acute toxicities in this older adult population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between elevated p16Ink4α gene expression and poor tolerance to and/or physician/patient-reported toxicity from radiation therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 weeks post-radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the association between elevated p16Ink4α expression in peripheral T lymphocytes and poor tolerance to and/or patient reported and physician reported acute grade 3-5 toxicity from radiation therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between baseline components of the Comprehensive Geriatric Assessment and poor tolerance to or occurrence of patient-reported toxicity from radiation treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>4-8 weeks post-radiation therapy</time_frame>
    <description>To explore the association between baseline components of the CGA (other than I-ADL) and poor tolerance to or occurrence of any patient-reported acute grade 3-5 toxicity from radiation treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Pre-treatment Loss of Independent Activities of Daily Living</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cancer Patients Age 65 or above</arm_group_label>
    <description>Cancer patients age 65 years or above with a diagnosis of head and neck cancer or lung cancer with radiotherapy or chemoradiotherapy planned as part of curative standard treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Whole blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients age ≥ 65 years of age, with one of the inclusion diagnoses, and an appointment for
        CT simulation for planning of radiation therapy at UNCH department of radiation oncology
        will be assessed for inclusion for this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥Age 65 years (no upper age limit)

          -  Diagnosis of either head and neck cancer, or lung cancer with either radiotherapy or
             chemoradiotherapy planned as part of standard treatment.

          -  Consented for receipt of External Beam Radiation Therapy (EBRT) at UNC Chapel Hill

          -  Able to read English (required for CGA)

          -  Curative treatment intent as defined by their radiation oncologist Signed,
             IRB-approved written informed consent

          -  Patients enrolled in other CGA studies will not be excluded (see LCCC 0916, 1208)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥Age 65 years (no upper age limit)

          -  Diagnosis of either head and neck cancer, or lung cancer with either radiotherapy or
             chemoradiotherapy planned as part of standard treatment.

          -  Consented for receipt of EBRT at UNC Chapel Hill

          -  Able to read English (required for CGA)

          -  Curative treatment intent as defined by their radiation oncologist Signed,
             IRB-approved written informed consent

          -  Patients enrolled in other CGA studies will not be excluded (see LCCC 0916, 1208)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bhishamjit Chera, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Radiation Oncology UNC Cancer Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Noam VanderWalde, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Radiation Oncology UNC Cancer Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radiation Oncology Clinic - UNC Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>VanderWalde NA, Deal AM, Comitz E, Stravers L, Muss H, Reeve BB, Basch E, Tepper J, Chera B. Geriatric Assessment as a Predictor of Tolerance, Quality of Life, and Outcomes in Older Patients With Head and Neck Cancers and Lung Cancers Receiving Radiation Therapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2017 Jul 15;98(4):850-857. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2016.11.048. Epub 2016 Dec 2.</citation>
    <PMID>28258889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 14, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 19, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neck cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Head cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung cancer</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

