<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01753375</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E12816</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01753375</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Role of Vitamin D in Reducing the Relapse Rate in Patients With Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Role of Vitamin D on the Relapse Rate of Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AlJohara M AlQuaiz, M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>King Saud University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vitamin D3 supplementation reduces the incidence of multiple sclerosis.Although clinical
      cross-sectional studies have demonstrated vitamin D3 as a positive mediator in preventing
      relapses and disease progression, prospective randomized control trials are nevertheless
      necessary to confirm these statements and to determine the most efficacious, safe, and the
      minimum required doses. This hypothesis is going to be tested through a randomized triple
      blinded controlled trial in which after randomization, one group of patients will receive
      vitamin D and second group will receive placebo. Both groups are going to be followed in a
      similar way over a period of one year with follow ups at 4, 8 and 12 months. Vitamin D levels
      is going to be performed at 0,4, 12 month interval. MRI is going to be done at the beginning
      and end of trial.The number of relapses and the physical disability will be calculated
      through the Expanded disability status scale (EDSS).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Objectives:

        -  To estimate the prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in Saudi Multiple Sclerosis(MS)
           patient coming to King Khalid hospital, multiple sclerosis clinic.

        -  To compare the difference in the relapse rate among Multiple Sclerosis patients who are
           taking vitamin D3 (50,000 IU per week) versus those who are not taking Vitamin D3
           supplements.

        -  To assess and compare the improvement in the Expanded Disability Status scale and
           clinical symptoms among those who are taking vitamin D3 versus those who are on placebo

      Study Design: A single centre, triple-blinded, parallel randomized placebo controlled trial.

      Methods: All eligible patients with clinical definite MS will be assigned a
      computer-generated Identification number by the statistician and through randomization
      divided into two groups, one group receiving vitamin D3 (the intervention arm) and other
      getting placebo (the control arm). All patients will continue with their routine
      pre-intervention trial treatment for relapse and remission phases of multiple sclerosis. The
      first treatment group will receive 50,000 IU units of vitamin D3 per week . The control arm
      patients, instead of vitamin D3 will receive a placebo supplement that looks, smells and
      tastes the same as the vitamin D3 for 52 weeks. Compliance with the study treatment will be
      verified by asking the patients about missed doses and by counting used and unused bottles.

      All patients will be asked questions related socio-demographic data, vitamin D related
      dietary products, physical activity questions, exposure to sunlight and variation according
      to season, use of sunscreen, body coverage when in sunlight and any previous treatment for
      Multiple Sclerosis, including any vitamin D supplements. Every follow up visit shall include
      documentation of complete neurologic and medical history and findings. This will be a
      triple-blinded trial. The patient, the treating physician and the statistician will be masked
      to the type of treatment each patient receives.Sealed envelopes containing the vitamin D3 or
      placebo are going to be handed over to the physician with the computer assigned number of the
      patient. At each follow-up visit all patients will be required to bring their envelopes along
      with empty/ filled bottles to assess their compliance with the treatment.

      The treating physician will follow all the patients at set regular intervals: 0 (baseline),
      4, 8, and 12 months to assess the relapses and the EDSS scores and also to check for any
      adverse effects arising because of the vitamin D3 supplements. Patients who are going to miss
      their appointment shall be contacted by the project staff to set another appointment in the
      subsequent week. All patients are going to be emphasized about the importance of these
      clinical visits and their compliance with the treatment. All patients will be evaluated by
      the same treating physician.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse rate in patients with Multiple Sclerosis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in the expanded disability status scores after receiving vitamin D3</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin D3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Administered orally on weekly basis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>To be administered orally on weekly basis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin D3</intervention_name>
    <description>Vitamin D3 given as 50000 IU orally on weekly basis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin D3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo to be given orally on weekly basis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 18-55 years

          -  Confirmed Multiple Sclerosis diagnosis according to McDonald criteria

          -  Stable neurological functioning for at least one month prior to study entry

          -  Expanded Disability Scale score (EDSS) less than &lt;_4.0

          -  Must have had one clinical attack in past two years and at least one new silent T2 or
             gadolinium-enhancing lesion on MRI within the past one year.

          -  Willing to participate for the entire 52-week period

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnant or nursing.

          -  Connective tissue disease (SLE, Sjogren's disease)

          -  Endocrine disease (hyperthyroidism, hyperparathyroidism)

          -  Any medical condition predisposing to hypercalcaemia, nephrolithiasis or renal
             insufficiency
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>AlJohara M AlQuaiz, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>King Saud University- Medical college</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Prof. Abdulkader Daif, M.D</last_name>
    <phone>0966-0504205164</phone>
    <email>adaif@ksu.edu.sa</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Multiple Sclerosis clinic, Department of Neurology, King Khalid Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Riyadh 11321</city>
        <zip>231831</zip>
        <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cantorna MT, Hayes CE, DeLuca HF. 1,25-Dihydroxyvitamin D3 reversibly blocks the progression of relapsing encephalomyelitis, a model of multiple sclerosis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1996 Jul 23;93(15):7861-4.</citation>
    <PMID>8755567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hayes CE. Vitamin D: a natural inhibitor of multiple sclerosis. Proc Nutr Soc. 2000 Nov;59(4):531-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11115787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Munger KL, Zhang SM, O'Reilly E, Hernán MA, Olek MJ, Willett WC, Ascherio A. Vitamin D intake and incidence of multiple sclerosis. Neurology. 2004 Jan 13;62(1):60-5.</citation>
    <PMID>14718698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kimball SM, Ursell MR, O'Connor P, Vieth R. Safety of vitamin D3 in adults with multiple sclerosis. Am J Clin Nutr. 2007 Sep;86(3):645-51.</citation>
    <PMID>17823429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaygannejad V, Janghorbani M, Ashtari F, Dehghan H. Effects of adjunct low-dose vitamin d on relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis progression: preliminary findings of a randomized placebo-controlled trial. Mult Scler Int. 2012;2012:452541. doi: 10.1155/2012/452541. Epub 2012 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22567287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jagannath VA, Fedorowicz Z, Asokan GV, Robak EW, Whamond L. Vitamin D for the management of multiple sclerosis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2010 Dec 8;(12):CD008422. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD008422.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21154396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burton JM, Kimball S, Vieth R, Bar-Or A, Dosch HM, Cheung R, Gagne D, D'Souza C, Ursell M, O'Connor P. A phase I/II dose-escalation trial of vitamin D3 and calcium in multiple sclerosis. Neurology. 2010 Jun 8;74(23):1852-9. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181e1cec2. Epub 2010 Apr 28. Erratum in: Neurology. 2010 Aug 3;75(5):480. Neurology. 2010 Sep 14;75(11):1029. Dosage error in article text.</citation>
    <PMID>20427749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 17, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 20, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 17, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 17, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 20, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>King Saud University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>AlJohara M AlQuaiz, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Executive Director of &quot;Princess Nora Chair for Women Health Research&quot; , Associate Professor and Consultant Family Physician, Department of Family and Community Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapsing rate</keyword>
  <keyword>Expanded disability status scale</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin D3</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholecalciferol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

