<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01754857</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HO11414</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-0072</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01754857</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bendamustine and Rituximab Induction Therapy and Maintenance Rituximab and Lenalidomide in Previously Untreated CLL/SLL</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Bendamustine and Rituximab Induction Chemoimmunotherapy Followed by Maintenance Rituximab and Lenalidomide in Previously Untreated Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) and Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma (SLL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose a treatment strategy where patients are treated with induction
      chemoimmunotherapy consisting of rituximab + bendamustine for 6 cycles, followed by
      initiation of maintenance rituximab and lenalidomide among patients achieving an objective
      response (i.e., at least stable disease with some tumor shrinkage) to induction therapy. The
      goal of maintenance therapy will be to capitalize on the cytoreduction following induction
      chemotherapy with a maintenance regimen that has also shown promising activity in CLL, in
      order to allow for improved PFS in this population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase II single arm, open-label, multicenter study evaluating the efficacy and
      safety of the combination of induction chemoimmunotherapy with bendamustine and rituximab
      followed by maintenance therapy with rituximab and lenalidomide in subjects with CLL or SLL
      who have not received any prior cytotoxic chemotherapy for their disease (i.e., prior
      single-agent rituximab is permitted). The study will be carried out at the University of
      Wisconsin Carbone Cancer Center (UWCCC) and participating community and academic practice
      sites within the Wisconsin Oncology Network (WON). There will be 1-3 sites participating in
      this study.

      The subject participation will include a screening period, treatment period, and a follow-up
      period. The treatment period will extend from the first dose of study drug treatment (day 1,
      cycle 1 of induction chemoimmunotherapy) until any of the following: completion of the entire
      course of induction and maintenance therapy; progressive disease (PD); an unacceptable
      adverse event (AE); the initiation of alternate anti-neoplastic therapy; or a decision by the
      subject or by the investigator to discontinue treatment; or death. The induction
      chemoimmunotherapy regimen consists of bendamustine and rituximab for 6 cycles, followed by
      initiation of maintenance therapy with rituximab and lenalidomide among subjects achieving an
      objective response to induction therapy (i.e., complete or partial response; stable disease
      with objective evidence of tumor shrinkage). Subjects with objective response after 4 cycles
      of bendamustine + rituximab (BR) are eligible to proceed to maintenance therapy if toxicities
      are limiting further BR induction therapy, or if the treating physician determines that
      further BR induction therapy would be associated with excessive risk for additional
      toxicities.

      To minimize toxicity with induction chemotherapy, we have chosen a dose of bendamustine at 90
      mg/m2/day on days 1 &amp; 2 every 28 days for a total of 6 cycles. Rituximab will be administered
      at a dose of 500 mg/m2 IV on day 1 of each cycle of induction chemoimmunotherapy (375 mg/m2
      cycle 1 only); however, patients at high-risk for cytokine release syndrome may receive
      rituximab on day 2 of induction therapy. In select circumstances in subjects at high risk for
      cytokine release syndrome and/or tumor lysis syndrome, rituximab may be administered as late
      as day 5 of cycle 1 (this alternative dosing of rituximab applies to cycle 1 of induction
      therapy only). Lenalidomide and rituximab maintenance will be initiated 6-12 weeks after the
      6th cycle of chemotherapy, and continued for a total of 24 cycles. Maintenance therapy will
      continue for a maximum of 24 cycles or until unacceptable toxicity or progression of disease.

      Maintenance therapy will begin once there has been adequate hematologic recovery (ANC
      ≥1000/µL and platelets ≥50,000/µL) and other criteria as outlined in Section 7.5 have been
      met. Rituximab will be administered at a dose of 375 mg/m2 IV on day 1 of every odd-numbered
      28 day cycle (cycles 1,3,5,7,9,11,13,15,17,19,21,23) for a maximum of 12 doses during the
      maintenance phase. Subjects will receive concurrent lenalidomide 5 mg orally daily on days
      1-28 of cycles 1-24 (28 day cycles). If subjects do not experience adverse effects from
      lenalidomide, dose escalation up to 10 mg orally daily on days 1-28 of each 28 day cycle will
      be allowed at the start of cycle 2 or at the start of any subsequent cycle (see Section 9.2.3
      and 9.2.5 for criteria required to escalate the dose of lenalidomide to 10 mg/day).
      Lenalidomide dose escalation is only allowed at the start of a new cycle to a maximum dose of
      10 mg/day. Subjects entering maintenance with reduced renal function (i.e., creatinine
      clearance ≥40 but &lt;60 mL/min) will start lenalidomide at a dose of 5 mg every other day.
      There is no dose modification of rituximab based on reduced renal function. Among subjects
      without excessive toxicity or evidence of progression, treatment with lenalidomide will
      continue for up to 24 cycles (cycle 1-24) and treatment with rituximab will continue for up
      to 12 doses (administered every odd-numbered cycle during cycles
      1,3,5,7,9,11,13,15,17,19,21,23). If subjects have excessive toxicity from lenalidomide,
      ongoing maintenance therapy with rituximab alone is permitted after lenalidomide is
      discontinued. After completing 24 cycles of maintenance therapy, subjects will then be
      observed for evidence of PD with clinical assessments every 3 months for at least 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective is progression-free survival (PFS). Tumor measurements and disease assessments will be performed at the time of screening, following cycles 3 and 6 of induction chemotherapy, every 4 cycles during the maintenance portion of treatment, and at the end of treatment (EOT). Subjects with clinical evidence of progression prior to a planned disease assessment will be evaluated at the time of clinically suspected progression. Follow-up visits for disease assessment will occur every 3 months after the EOT visit until PD, initiation of alternate anti-neoplastic therapy, decision by the subject to withdraw from the study, or death. The follow-up period will begin after the EOT visit, and all subjects will be followed for at least 2 years after completion of therapy or until death or progression and until the last patient has been followed for at least 1 year following completion of therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine objective response rates (CR + PR). As described in the primary objective, formal disease assessments including imaging will be performed after cycles 3 and 6 of induction chemotherapy and every 4 cycles during the maintenance portion of treatment. Response and progression in cases of SLL will be evaluated using the International Working Group Criteria30 for response in lymphoma. Response and progression in cases of CLL will be evaluated in this study using the Revised IWCLL Criteria31 for response in CLL. Radiological methodologies, techniques and/or physical examination, established at baseline for the assessment and measurement of each identified lesion will be used for all subsequent assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>• To determine toxicities observed with induction chemotherapy and maintenance therapy. Safety evaluations will be based on the incidence, intensity, and type of adverse events (AEs) and clinical laboratory results. Drug doses will be modified as required based on toxicity as assessed using the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), version 4.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Death</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 54 months</time_frame>
    <description>• To determine overall survival. Overall survival will be determined from the date of enrollment until death from any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bendamustine, rituximab, lenalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INDUCTION: Bendamustine 90 mg/m2 IV D1&amp;2 and rituximab IV D1 (up to day 5 of course 1 only) every 28 days for 6 treatment cycles. Patients achieving objective response proceed to maintenance therapy. Patients with objective response after 4 courses are eligible to proceed to maintenance therapy if ongoing induction therapy is likely associated with unacceptable toxicity.
MAINTENANCE: Beginning 6-12 weeks after completion of induction therapy, patients receive rituximab IV on day 1 of every odd-numbered cycle for 24 cycles; lenalidomide 5-10 mg PO daily on days 1-28 of each cycle (28 day cycles). Patients experiencing excessive toxicity from lenalidomide may continue maintenance therapy with rituximab alone.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bendamustine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bendamustine, rituximab, lenalidomide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bendamustine, rituximab, lenalidomide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bendamustine, rituximab, lenalidomide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL)/small lymphocytic lymphoma
             (SLL)

          -  No prior cytotoxic chemotherapy for their disease; prior therapy with single-agent
             rituximab is permitted

          -  Understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent document

          -  In cases of SLL, subjects must have at least one bidimensionally measurable lesion at
             least &gt;= 1.5 cm measured in one dimension

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of =&lt; 2 at study entry

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;= 1500/uL

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 100,000/uL

          -  Subjects with neutrophils &lt; 1500/uL or platelets &lt; 100,000/uL with splenomegaly or
             extensive bone marrow involvement as the etiology for their cytopenias are eligible

          -  Subjects must have adequate renal function with a creatinine clearance of &gt;= 40 mL/min
             as determined by the Cockcroft-Gault calculation

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 2 x upper limit laboratory normal (ULN); subjects with
             non-clinically significant elevations of bilirubin due to Gilbert's disease are not
             required to meet these criteria

          -  Serum transaminases aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic
             transaminase [SGOT]) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate
             transaminase [SGPT]) =&lt; 5 x ULN

          -  Serum alkaline phosphatase =&lt; 5 x ULN

          -  Disease-free of prior malignancies for &gt;= 2 years with the exception of basal or
             squamous cell skin carcinoma, carcinoma &quot;in situ&quot; of the breast or cervix, or
             localized prostate cancer (treated definitively with hormone therapy, radiotherapy, or
             surgery)

          -  Life expectancy of at least 3 months

          -  All study participants must be willing to be registered into the mandatory Revlimid
             REMS program after completion of induction chemoimmunotherapy and prior to maintenance
             therapy, and be willing and able to comply with the requirements of the Revlimid REMS
             program

          -  Subjects must not have a known history of hypersensitivity to mannitol

          -  Prior therapy with rituximab is permitted, even in the setting of rituximab-refractory
             disease

          -  Females of reproductive potential must adhere to the scheduled pregnancy testing as
             required in the Revlimid REMS program

          -  Able to take aspirin (81 or 325 mg) daily as prophylactic anticoagulation (subjects
             intolerant to aspirin may use warfarin or low molecular weight heparin) if clinically
             indicated

          -  Females of childbearing potential (FCBP) must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy
             test with a sensitivity of at least 50 mIU/mL within 10 - 14 days and again within 24
             hours prior to prescribing lenalidomide for cycle 1 (prescriptions must be filled
             within 7 days as required by the Revlimid REMS® program) and must either commit to
             continued abstinence from heterosexual intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of
             birth control, one highly effective method and one additional effective method AT THE
             SAME TIME, at least 28 days before she starts taking lenalidomide; FCBP must also
             agree to ongoing pregnancy testing; men must agree to use a latex condom during sexual
             contact with a FCBP even if they have had a successful vasectomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that
             would prevent the subject from signing the informed consent document or complying with
             the protocol treatment

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding females; lactating females must agree not to breast-feed
             while taking lenalidomide

          -  Any condition, including the presence of laboratory abnormalities, which places the
             subject at unacceptable risk if he/she were to participate in the study or confounds
             the ability to interpret data from the study

          -  Subjects are not eligible if there is a prior history or current evidence of central
             nervous system or leptomeningeal involvement

          -  Known hypersensitivity to thalidomide

          -  Concurrent use of other anti-cancer agents or treatments

          -  Known to be positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or infectious hepatitis
             (type B or C)

          -  Prior malignancy, except for adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell skin
             cancer, in situ cervical or breast cancer, or other cancer from which the subject has
             been disease free for at least 2 years

          -  Severe or life-threatening anaphylaxis or hypersensitivity reaction when previously
             exposed to rituximab or other monoclonal antibody therapy

          -  Chronic hepatitis B or hepatitis C infection

          -  New York Heart Association class 3-4 heart failure

          -  More than one grade 2 or higher transaminase elevation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julie Chang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cancer Connect</last_name>
    <phone>(800) 622-8922</phone>
    <email>cancerconnect@uwcarbone.wisc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie Chang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>608-263-1836</phone>
      <email>jc2@medicine.wisc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Erica Stubbendick</last_name>
      <phone>608-263-2944</phone>
      <email>erica.stubbendick@wisc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 9, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 21, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lymphoid Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Bendamustine</keyword>
  <keyword>Rituximab</keyword>
  <keyword>Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bendamustine Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

