<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02095756</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PICO-2013-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02095756</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination Alexandrite Laser and Topical Therapy vs Topical Therapy Alone for Treatment of Melasma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Split-Face, Double-Blind Clinical Pilot Study of Combination Picosecond Alexandrite Laser and Non-Hydroquinone Topical Therapy Versus Topical Therapy Alone for the Treatment of Facial Melasma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cynosure, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cynosure, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of a combination of
      non-hydroquinone topical therapy and a 755nm Alexandrite compared to topical therapy alone
      for the treatment of facial melasma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Melasma clearance</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 months post last treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the efficacy of a combination of non-hydroquinone topical therapy and a 755-nm alexandrite laser compared to topical therapy alone in the treatment of melasma .</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Melasma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>755nm Alexandrite laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>755nm Alexandrite laser for the treatment of melasma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>755nm Alexandrite Laser and Lytera Skin Brightening System (Non-Hydroquinone Topical Therapy)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>755nm Alexandrite laser</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lytera Skin Brightening System (Non-hydroquinone topical therapy)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>755nm Alexandrite laser</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female Subjects aged 18-74 years of age;

          -  Fitzpatrick Skin Types I-IV;

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test at
             the beginning of the study, and agree to practice appropriate birth-control to prevent
             pregnancy during the study. The type and dose of birth control must have been stable
             for at least 3 months prior to study entry and it is not expected to change during the
             study; acceptable methods of birth control are oral contraceptives, contraceptive
             patches/rings/implants Norplant®, Depo-Provera®, double-barrier methods (e.g. condoms
             and spermicide), abstinence and vasectomies of partner with a documented second
             acceptable method of birth control should the subject become sexually active.

          -  Subjects diagnosed with moderate to severe melasma on both sides of the face

          -  For subjects using medication to treat a concurrent medical condition, type and dose
             must have been stable for at least 3 months prior to study entry and it is not
             expected to change during the study (except any medications specifically outlined in
             the exclusion criteria section)

          -  Subjects able to avoid prolonged sun exposure on the face for the duration of the
             study and willing to use appropriate sun avoidance techniques.

          -  Subjects able to follow study instructions and likely to complete all required visits;

          -  Subjects/Representative able and willing to sign the Informed Consent (which includes
             a photography release) prior to any study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female subjects who are pregnant, nursing or planning a pregnancy during the course of
             the study;

          -  Subjects with a condition or who are in a situation which, in the Investigator's
             opinion, may put the Subject at risk, may confound the study results, or may interfere
             with the Subject's participation in the study, such as: the use of a concomitant
             medication that can interfere with the study or worsen any condition when used during
             the study, the use of medications known to induce photosensitivity;

          -  Subjects under treatment for a dermatologic condition, which may interfere with the
             safe evaluation of the study regimen (e.g. eczema, psoriasis, severe sun-damage,
             dermatitis) and/or have scarring or infection of the area to be treated;

          -  Subjects with a diagnosis of skin cancer (BCE, SCC, Melanoma, etc.) in the areas to be
             treated;

          -  Subject unwilling to avoid any other treatment for melasma during the study (total
             duration of 30 weeks);

          -  Subjects with a wash-out period of less than 14 days for melasma treatments at the
             time of study entry or under current treatment;

          -  Subjects with prior facial resurfacing, deep or chemical peels within 6 months of the
             date of study entry;

          -  Subject unwilling to refrain from any facial cosmetic procedures during the study
             period (e.g., chemical peels, resurfacing, microdermabrasion, etc.);

          -  Subject has initiated treatment with hormones including estrogen, progesterone and/or
             oral contraceptives within 3 months of study entry, or who intend to discontinue
             hormonal therapy during the study;

          -  Subject has participated in a clinical research study within the last 30 days prior to
             enrollment;

          -  Subject is unable to communicate or cooperate with the Investigator due to language
             problems, poor mental development, or other reasons;

          -  Subject is unable to meet the study attendance requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>74 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dermatology Cosmetic Laser Medical Associates of La Jolla, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92121</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 21, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 29, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 29, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 31, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

