<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02091531</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-143</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02091531</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dual mTOR Inhibitor MLN0128 in Advanced Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer (CRPC) Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Study of the Dual mTOR Inhibitor MLN0128 in Patients With Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer (CRPC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase II study which will test the study drug MLN0128 in patients with castration
      resistant prostate cancer who have received chemotherapy in the past. Phase II clinical
      trials test how well an investigational drug works in treating a specific cancer.
      &quot;Investigational&quot; means that the drug is still being studied and that research doctors are
      trying to find out more about it. MLN0128 is not approved by the FDA.

      The purpose of this study is to see what effects (good and bad) the study drug MLN0128 has on
      the patient and the cancer. MLN0128 is a drug that belongs to a class of drugs called &quot;mTOR
      kinase inhibitors&quot;. A protein, called &quot;mTOR&quot; inside the cells in the body, plays a role in
      controlling how cells grow. In some cancer cells, mTOR may be over-active. This over-activity
      may cause some cancer cells to grow out of control. Research has shown that mTOR inhibitors
      can block this overactivity and may help stop or slow down the growth of some types of cancer
      cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>from the start of treatment, as defined by the Prostate Cancer Working Group 2 (PCWG2) guidelines.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PSA response</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Summary tables and waterfall plots describing change in PSA relative to baseline will be reported at 8 weeks (or earlier for those who discontinue therapy), and separately, the maximal change at any time on study will also be reported for each patient using summary tables and waterfall plots.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>radiographic response</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>We propose to study both FDG and optional FDHT PET imaging at baseline, 4 weeks after treatment initiation and at the time of progression (end-of-treatment), and to correlate the changes with treatment response. Response and progression will be evaluated in this study using a combination of the international criteria proposed by the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) Committee and modified for prostate cancer and the guidelines for prostate cancer endpoints developed by the Prostate Cancer Clinical Trials Working Group (PCWG2).21</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">9</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MLN0128</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be treated with the established phase II dose of MLN0128 (4mg po daily continuously; 1 cycle=4 weeks) to assess mechanisms of sensitivity and resistance in men with CRPC who have received either enzalutamide and/or abiraterone.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MLN0128</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MLN0128</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        To be included in this study, patients should have histologically confirmed castration
        resistant metastatic prostate cancer with evidence of disease progression. Patients must
        have been in a castrate state either by orchiectomy or by GnRH analogues. In detail, they
        should meet all of the following criteria

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed prostate cancer with progressive metastatic disease based on
             any of the following: i) a rise in PSA, ii) transaxial imaging, or iii) radionuclide
             bone scan.

               1. PSA - a minimum of 3 consecutive rising levels, with an interval of ≥

                  1 week between each determination. The last determination must have a minimal
                  value of ≥ 2 ng/mL and be determined within two weeks prior to enrollment.

               2. Measurable Disease - patients showing new or progressive soft tissue masses on CT
                  or MRI scans as defined by the PCWG2 criteria21

               3. Radionuclide bone scan - at least two new metastatic lesions.

          -  Detectable metastases by bone scan, CT-scan or MRI.

          -  Ongoing androgen depletion therapy with a Gonadotropin Releasing Hormone (GnRH)
             analogue or inhibitor, or orchiectomy (i.e., surgical or medical castration).

        For patients who have not had an orchiectomy, there must be a plan to maintain effective
        GnRH-analogue therapy for the duration of the trial.

          -  Castrate levels of serum testosterone &lt; 50 ng/dL determined within 4 weeks prior to
             starting treatment.

          -  Patients who are receiving an anti-androgen as part of their first-line hormonal
             therapy must have shown progression of disease off the anti-androgen prior to
             enrollment.

          -  At least 4 weeks must have elapsed from the use of androgen receptor antagonists
             (i.e., flutamide, nilutamide, bicalutamide, enzalutamide ); 5-α reductase inhibitors
             (i.e., finasteride, aminoglutethimide); abiraterone acetate; estrogens; nitrosoureas,
             mitomycin C, isotype therapy, ketoconazole, chemotherapy and other anti-cancer
             pharmacologic therapy prior to beginning protocol therapy.

          -  At least 8 weeks must have elapsed from the use of Strontium-89, Radium-223,
             Samarium-153, or immunotherapy (e.g., Provenge) prior to beginning protocol therapy.

          -  At least 4 weeks must have elapsed from the use of any investigational agent prior to
             beginning protocol therapy.

             a. Note: Prior treatment with PI3K/mTOR pathway inhibitors prohibited.

          -  At least 4 weeks must have elapsed from major surgery.

          -  Toxicities related to prior therapy must either have returned to ≤ Grade 1, baseline
             or deemed irreversible.

          -  Patients with treated, non-progressive epidural disease are eligible.

          -  KPS performance status 70-100% (50-60% is allowed only if due to bone pain)

          -  At least 18 years of age, with a life expectancy at least 3 months.

          -  Patient must be willing to comply with study procedures.

          -  Physical and laboratory test findings

               1. Adequate hepatic function with serum bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times the upper
                  institutional limits of normal (ULN), ALT and AST ≤ 2.5 x ULN. Patients with a
                  history of Gilbert's syndrome may be enrolled if the total bilirubin is &lt; 3 mg/dL
                  with a predominance of indirect bilirubin

               2. Adequate renal function with serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN.

               3. Adequate hematologic function with absolute neutrophil counts ≥ 1,500 cell/mm3
                  and platelets ≥ 100,000 cells/mm3 and hemoglobin value ≥ 9 g/dL (Note: patients
                  whose anemia has been corrected to a hemoglobin value ≥ 9 g/dL with blood
                  transfusions are allowed).

               4. Electrolytes (including potassium, sodium, and serum calcium corrected for
                  albumin or ionized calcium) must be within normal limits.

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) no more than 5 absolute percentage points
             below the institutional standard of normal as measured by echocardiogram (ECHO) or
             multiple gated acquisition scan (MUGA) within 4 weeks prior to first study drug
             administration (ie, if the institutional normal is 50%, subject's LVEF may be as low
             as 45% to be eligible for the study)

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients that meet any of the criteria listed below will not be eligible for study entry:

          -  History of, or current known metastases in the brain or untreated spinal cord
             compression;

          -  History of another malignancy within the previous 2 years except for the following:

               1. Adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, superficial bladder
                  cancer,

               2. Adequately treated Stage I or II cancer currently in complete remission, or any
                  other cancer that has been in complete remission for at least 2 years;

          -  Prior treatment with PI3K/mTOR pathway inhibitors;

        Diabetes mellitus on active treatment, or subjects with either of the following:

          1. Fasting blood glucose (FBG) ≥ 126 mg/dL (7.0 mmol/L), or

          2. HbA1c ≥ 6.5%;

               -  Use of herbal products that may decrease PSA levels (i.e., saw palmetto) or
                  systemic corticosteroid greater than the equivalent of 10 mg of prednisone per
                  day during the 4 weeks prior to screening or plans to initiate treatment with the
                  above during the entire duration of the study;

               -  Any history of unstable angina, myocardial infarction, New York Heart Association
                  (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure, and/or pulmonary hypertension;

               -  Significant active cardiovascular disease including:

        a. Uncontrolled high blood pressure (ie, systolic blood pressure &gt; 180 mmHg, diastolic
        blood pressure &gt; 95 mmHg) b. Grade 3 or higher valvular disease c. Grade 3 or higher atrial
        fibrillation d. Grade 3 or higher bradycardia e. Endocarditis f. Pulmonary embolism g.
        Recent cerebrovascular accident within 6 months prior to enrollment

          -  A requirement for positive inotropic support (excluding digoxin) or serious
             uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia (including atrial flutter/fibrillation) within 1 year
             prior to screening

          -  A pacemaker or implantable cardiac defibrillator

          -  Known history of infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), based on medical
             history (screening labs to rule out HIV infection are not required);

          -  Any other condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would impair the
             patient's ability to comply with study procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dana Rathkopf, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>mTOR Inhibitor MLN0128</keyword>
  <keyword>PSA</keyword>
  <keyword>13-143</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

