<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02095951</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2024.11</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02095951</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preemptive Ethanol Lock Therapy in Pediatric Bloodstream Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>Preemptive Ethanol Lock Therapy in Pediatric Hematology/Oncology Patients With Catheter Associated Bloodstream Infection: Impact on Length of Stay and Catheter Salvage</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Blue Cross Blue Shield of Michigan Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study team will compare hospital length of stay (LOS) and attributable length of stay
      (ALOS, the LOS attributable to CRI), in a randomized, un-blinded prospective trial utilizing
      short-dwell ethanol-lock therapy (ELT) (4 hours to 24 hour dwell times per day, repeated for
      up to 72 hours) placed within 24 hours of admission(Group 1, Preemptive ELT) versus ELT
      placed at the time of first positive blood culture report (Group 2, Rescue ELT (Standard of
      Care ). ELT will be given in both groups, in combination with systemic antibiotics, for the
      treatment of CRI (suspected or proven) of the blood in children with central catheters.
      Participants will be enrolled from patients with hematologic/oncologic disorders and bone
      marrow or hematopoetic stem cell transplants (BMT) admitted for care to Children's Hospital
      of Michigan (CHM), a tertiary care pediatric hospital in Detroit, Michigan. ALOS will be
      defined as the number of hospital days between first symptoms of Catheter-related infection
      (CRI) (or date of admission for those admitted with symptoms) and first negative blood
      culture.

      Study Hypothesis: The main hypothesis is that the short-dwell ethanol-lock therapy, defined
      above, placed within 24 hours of symptoms/admission (Arm 1) versus ELT placement at the time
      of first positive blood culture report (Arm 2), with concomitant systemic antibiotics, for
      the treatment of CRI (suspected or proven) of the blood in children with central catheters in
      the H/O/BMT population will have shorter hospital length of stay (LOS) and attributable LOS
      (ALOS) and therefore lower hospital costs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study team will compare hospital length of stay (LOS) and attributable length of stay
      (ALOS, the LOS attributable to CRI), in a randomized, un-blinded prospective trial utilizing
      short-dwell ethanol-lock therapy (ELT) (4 hours to 24 hour dwell times per day, repeated for
      up to 72 hours) placed within 24 hours of admission(Group 1, Preemptive ELT) versus ELT
      placed at the time of first positive blood culture report (Group 2, Rescue ELT (Standard of
      Care ).

      ELT will be given in both groups, in combination with systemic antibiotics, for the treatment
      of Catheter-related Infection (CRI) (suspected or proven) of the blood in children with
      central catheters. Participants will be enrolled from patients with hematologic/oncologic
      disorders and bone marrow or hematopoetic stem cell transplants admitted for care to
      Children's Hospital of Michigan (CHM), a tertiary care pediatric hospital in Detroit,
      Michigan. ALOS will be defined as the number of hospital days between first symptoms of CRI
      (or date of admission for those admitted with symptoms) and first negative blood culture.

      Aim 1: Compare two different treatment regimens for CRI using ELT (the preemptive ELT vs.
      standard of care) by way of a prospective, randomized, two-arm study.

      Study Hypothesis: The main hypothesis is that the short-dwell ethanol-lock therapy, defined
      above, placed within 24 hours of symptoms/admission (Arm 1) versus ELT placement at the time
      of first positive blood culture report (Arm 2), with concomitant systemic antibiotics, for
      the treatment of CRI (suspected or proven) of the blood in children with central catheters in
      the H/O/BMT population will have shorter hospital length of stay (LOS) and attributable LOS
      (ALOS) and therefore lower hospital costs.

      Aim 2: Compare sterilization rate of the infected intravascular device after ethanol-lock
      therapy (as defined by a negative blood culture obtained from the infected catheter 24 - 72
      hours after ELT) and central catheter salvage rate after CRI using ELT in the two study arms.
      If the central catheter is salvaged for further clinical use, recurrence of infection
      (re-infection) of the central catheter for 28 days from date of first ELT procedure will also
      be assessed.

      Aim 3: Assess tolerability and adverse effects of the ELT (safety).

      Aim 4: Perform sub-group analysis on the BSI episodes meeting National Healthcare Safety
      Network (NHSN) criteria for laboratory confirmed central line associated BSI (CLABSI) into
      the three categories of Criteria 1, 2 or 3 within the pediatric
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay (LOS), Attributable Length of Stay (ALOS) and Hospital costs</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A primary endpoint of this study is length of stay (LOS) per catheter infection episode/admission; ALOS, and Hospital costs of admission based on LOS/ALOS</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Catheter sterilization rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary endpoints include catheter sterilization rates per infection episode/admission</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Catheter salvage rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Catheters salvaged during the study will be analyzed per infection episode/admission</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 2 weeks but up to 1 month post the last ethanol dose administration</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events that are thought to be related to the actual study intervention, namely timing of ethanol lock placement, will be reviewed and reported for each individual infection episode/admission.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Re-infection rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 2 weeks but for up to 1 month total</time_frame>
    <description>Re-infection of a salvaged catheter with same or new organism(s) will be recorded and analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Blood Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-emptive Ethanol Lock Therapy Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive ethanol lock before blood cultures grow germ</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Ethanol Lock Therapy Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive ethanol lock if and only after blood cultures grow germ</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ethanol lock therapy (ELT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be randomized to receive early (preemptive) ELT (after 12 hours from time blood culture drawn, but before blood culture positive, R/O sepsis) with systemic antimicrobials versus standard ELT (placed in catheter when blood culture is positive for growth of a germ) with systemic antimicrobials.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-emptive Ethanol Lock Therapy Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Ethanol Lock Therapy Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>70% Ethanol in water</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All children up to 21 years of age, with central catheters (any type) that develop
             symptoms and are admitted to CHM with an underlying H/O/BMT diagnosis for individual
             episodes of suspected or proven CRI of the blood, including rule out sepsis, will be
             screened for potential participation in this study.

          -  Individual CRI episodes in the same patient will be defined as a distinct central
             catheter associated blood stream infection if separated by greater than 28 days from
             prior ELT procedure and caused by a different organism identified on culture than the
             prior central catheter associated blood stream infection episode.

          -  Participants meeting study enrollment criteria will be offered participation and must
             have parental full informed consent, adolescent assent and young child verbal assent
             prior to enrollment as applicable.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children with documented allergy to ethanol or alcohol will be excluded. Blood
             cultures from patients that are reported positive for pathogen growth within 12 hours
             from the time they are obtained will be excluded from the study.

          -  Any patient at CHM with an infected central catheter and with another indwelling
             foreign body that communicates directly with the bloodstream, of which infection or
             colonization could not be excluded directly, will also be excluded from the study
             (i.e. Left Ventricular Assist Device) as it will not be possible to assess
             sterilization of the central catheter.

          -  Any patient with endocarditis or presumed endovascular infection will also be
             excluded.

          -  Any patient deemed critically ill or unstable, upon admission or during the early
             treatment course, in which case the treating clinician(s) feel that immediate line
             removal is potentially life-saving will be excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric J McGrath, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wayne State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>McGrath EJ, Salloum R, Chen X, Jiang Y, Boldt-MacDonald K, Becker C, Chu R, Ang JY. Short-dwell ethanol lock therapy in children is associated with increased clearance of central line-associated bloodstream infections. Clin Pediatr (Phila). 2011 Oct;50(10):943-51. doi: 10.1177/0009922811409568. Epub 2011 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21622689</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 21, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eric McGrath</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Pediatrics - Clinical</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>November 20, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>December 21, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>January 11, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>February 7, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>May 10, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

