<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01046513</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999906364</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>06-DA-N364</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01046513</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PET Imaging of Nicotinic Acetylcholine Receptors</brief_title>
  <official_title>PET Imaging of Nicotinic Acetylcholine Receptors With 2-[18F]F-A-85380-Injection, Initial Evaluation of Radiotracer in Human Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Central nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) are the primary target for the action of
      nicotine. In addition to being involved in tobacco dependence, they are also involved in a
      variety of brain disorders, including Alzheimer's and Parkinson's diseases. Researchers are
      interested in developing better ways to study the action of nAChRs to improve treatments for
      smoking cessation and other problems affected by these receptors. These new study methods may
      involve different radiotracers, which are drugs that can help show brain activity during
      positron emission tomography (PET) scanning.

      Objectives:

      - To evaluate the feasibility of using a radiotracer, 2-[18F]F-A-85380, in PET scanning of
      the brain.

      Eligibility:

      - Healthy volunteers between 21 and 45 years of age who do not use tobacco.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be asked to avoid consuming alcohol or using a number of
           over-the-counter medications, including antihistamines, cough medicines, and nasal
           decongestants, for 5 days before the study day. Participants provide urine and breath
           samples at the start of the study to be tested for chemicals that may interfere with the
           study.

        -  Participants will visit the clinical center the morning of the day before the scanning
           session to provide blood and urine samples as required. Participants will return and be
           admitted for an overnight stay later that afternoon or evening.

        -  On the day of the study, participants will receive a single dose of the radiotracer
           2-[18F]F-A-85380, and will have a series of PET scans over the next 7 hours and provide
           blood samples during that time. Participants will spend that night at the clinical
           center and leave on the morning after the end of the study.

        -  Participants will return for follow-up visits 2 weeks and 1 month after the end of the
           study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Central nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) mediate a variety of brain
      functions and have been implicated in the pathophysiology of Alzheimer's and Parkinson's
      diseases, other CNS disorders (Tourette's syndrome, epilepsy, etc.), and nicotine dependence.
      These receptors are the primary target for the action of nicotine, which is believed to cause
      tobacco dependence. The availability of a suitable agent that could image nAChRs with PET in
      humans would allow scientists to monitor the nAChRs in vivo for the purpose of determining
      their roles in the pathogenesis of neurodegenerative diseases and nicotine dependence.

      Scientific Goals: The immediate goal of the proposed study is to evaluate the feasibility of
      using a radiotracer, 2-[18F]F-A-85380, developed by scientists in the NIDA Brain Imaging
      Center for external imaging of nAChRs in the human brain.

      Study Population: Healthy adult participants, males and females between 21 and 45 years of
      age, will be recruited for this study. The goal is to complete studies of 7 male and 7 female
      subjects.

      Experimental Design and Method: After being medically cleared and giving informed consent,
      participants will receive a single dose of the radiotracer, 2 [18F]F A 85380-Injection, and
      will undergo a series of PET scans acquired over the next 7 hours after the injection. The
      PET scans will be used to determine the time course of the distribution of the injected
      radioactivity in those organs expected to receive the highest radiation exposure and in the
      brain.

      Benefits to participants and/or society: This protocol will provide no direct benefits to the
      research participants other than routine medical screening and attention from the research
      staff. The knowledge gained in this study may lead to the availability of an agent for
      external monitoring of nAChRs using PET. This agent would be a valuable tool for determining
      the role of nAChRs in the pathogenesis of neuropsychiatric diseases, including nicotine
      dependence and for developing medications for diseases that respond to nicotinic agonists.

      Risks to participants: There is some risk attendant to the PET scans in general, involving
      exposure to radiation, arterial catheterization and venous catheterization. In addition,
      there is risk related to the administration of this radiopharmaceutical, as it will be given
      to humans for the first time in this study. Medical supervision will be provided throughout
      the study. A plan for monitoring potential side effects of this radiotracer is given.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 31, 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date>September 28, 2011</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <condition>Nicotine Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Pharmacokinetics</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Age: Subjects will be male and female volunteers aged 21 to 45 years. All
                  subjects must have a stable point of contact and must agree to return at 2 and 4
                  weeks after the PET study for laboratory screening and follow up evaluations.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Psychiatric disease: DSM-IV criteria will be used (DSM-IV, APA, 1994). No subject with
             a current axis I diagnosis will be allowed. No subject with known claustrophobia will
             be allowed.

          2. History of Drug Abuse: Volunteers reporting current or having a significant history of
             illicit drug abuse (single illicit substance use of more than 10 times in a lifetime
             for any given substance, except marijuana) will be excluded from the study. Volunteers
             reporting current use of nicotine will be excluded because nAChRs are usually elevated
             in smokers, and the purpose of this protocol is to determine the feasibility of
             measuring nAChRs in vivo. Including smokers at this time may provide results that are
             more variable and which may overestimate our ability to measure these receptors in
             nonsmokers. Subjects may use moderate amounts of alcohol and caffeine and smoke an
             occasional marijuana cigarette. Moderate alcohol use will be defined as less than ten
             drinks of liquor (1.5 oz) or the equivalent beer (12 oz) or wine (5 oz) per week.
             Moderate caffeine use will be defined as less than 500 mg of caffeine per day, where
             100 mg is equivalent to 1 serving of coffee (5 oz serving), 2.5 servings (12 oz
             serving) of caffeinated soft drinks, or 2.5 servings of tea (5 oz serving). Occasional
             marijuana use will be defined as less than or equal to two marijuana cigarettes/month.

          3. Current Medication Use: Volunteers may not currently use chronic (daily or for more
             than 10/14 days in the last month) prescription or over the counter medications,
             (including, but not limited to, anti-hypertensive, anti-allergy, pain). Over the
             counter or prescription medications may used on an occasional basis (for treatment of
             self-limited conditions, such as occasional headache, musculoskeletal discomfort,
             allergic symptoms or pain). All medications will be discontinued at least 5 days
             before the experimental session.

          4. CNS disease: History of known structural brain abnormalities (e.g., neoplasm,
             subarachnoid cysts), cerebrovascular disease, infectious disease (e.g., abscess),
             history of head trauma (defined as documented loss of consciousness &gt; 5 min or injury
             requiring hospitalization), history of seizures as an adult, sleep apnea.

          5. Cardiovascular, pulmonary, or systemic disease: Repeated (measured on three separate
             occasions) diastolic blood pressure &gt; 90 mm Hg, or systolic blood pressure &gt; 150 mm
             Hg, known arrhythmia, symptomatic or known coronary artery disease; history of
             endocarditis, cerebral embolism, obstructive pulmonary disease, asthma, active
             tuberculosis, known endocrine disease (derangements in adrenal, thyroid, bone or
             reproductive function) known chronic renal or hepatic dysfunction, known HIV
             seropositive, known current autoimmune disease involving the CNS, type I diabetes
             mellitus, current gastrointestinal disease, gastritis or ulcers.

          6. Special considerations for female subjects. Female participants who are currently
             pregnant or nursing will not be allowed to participate in this study. Female subjects
             will be given a serum pregnancy test (quantitative beta HCG) within 24 hours of each
             PET session.

          7. Miscellaneous exclusionary criteria: Body mass index less than 20 or greater than 29.
             Hematocrit &lt; 39.0 for males or &lt; 35.0 for females.

          8. Radiation exposure: Any subject who has participated in any research studies in which
             he/she received a radiation exposure that would result in combination with the present
             study, in a total effective radiation exposure (from research studies) exceeding 3.0
             rem in a 13-week period or 5.0 rem in a year.

          9. Novocain allergy.

         10. Test of hand cubital artery patency for all subjects.

         11. Women who are pregnant or lactating and children under the age of 21 will be excluded
             to avoid unnecessary exposure to radiation to these populations.

         12. The presence within the body of metallic implants or materials that could be moved by
             the magnet of the MRI scanner: pacemakers, surgical implants, aneurysm clips, dental
             braces, bullet(s) or other metallic materials.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute on Drug Abuse, Biomedical Research Center (BRC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adler LE, Hoffer LJ, Griffith J, Waldo MC, Freedman R. Normalization by nicotine of deficient auditory sensory gating in the relatives of schizophrenics. Biol Psychiatry. 1992 Oct 1;32(7):607-16.</citation>
    <PMID>1450287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bannon AW, Decker MW, Curzon P, Buckley MJ, Kim DJ, Radek RJ, Lynch JK, Wasicak JT, Lin NH, Arnold WH, Holladay MW, Williams M, Arneric SP. ABT-594 [(R)-5-(2-azetidinylmethoxy)-2-chloropyridine]: a novel, orally effective antinociceptive agent acting via neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors: II. In vivo characterization. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1998 May;285(2):787-94.</citation>
    <PMID>9580627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benwell ME, Balfour DJ, Anderson JM. Evidence that tobacco smoking increases the density of (-)-[3H]nicotine binding sites in human brain. J Neurochem. 1988 Apr;50(4):1243-7.</citation>
    <PMID>3346676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 28, 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 12, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Nicotinic Acetylcholine Receptors</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuroimaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Positron Emission Tomography (PET)</keyword>
  <keyword>Alpha4beta2</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine</keyword>
  <keyword>Receptor Upregulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acetylcholine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

