<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01048723</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-15962</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CRAD001CUS107T</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>108182</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01048723</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of RAD001 in Soft Tissue Extremity and/or Retroperitoneal Sarcomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-arm, Open Label Phase II Study of RAD001 in Soft Tissue Extremity and/or Retroperitoneal Sarcomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if the study drug RAD001 can stop or
      slow the growth of resectable soft tissue sarcoma. The patient's physical state, their
      symptoms, changes in the size of the tumor, and laboratory findings obtained while on-study
      will help the research team decide if RAD001 is safe and effective in patients with this
      condition. The study drug, RAD001, is made by Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A single-arm, open label, proof of principle phase II study exploring the efficacy of RAD001
      in resectable soft tissue sarcomas either in the extremities, trunk or retroperitoneum.
      Patients with resectable sarcomas as detailed below were to have a core biopsy for molecular
      markers prior to therapy with RAD001 10mg PO daily x 2 weeks. Within 7-14 days of the end of
      therapy with RAD001, the patients were to be brought to surgery for definitive resection or,
      should they be candidates for neoadjuvant radiation, would have 6 16 gauge core biopsies
      taken percutaneously or using image guidance. Pharmacodynamic markers as detailed in the
      objectives were to be assessed in the laboratory.

      Patients were to be numbered sequentially from 1 to 40, or more if there were patients that
      dropped out due to drug toxicity, with the goal of achieving 40 patients in accrual for
      evaluation of the pre- and post-treatment tumor samples for Pharmacodynamic assays.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Novartis terminated funding
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacodynamics (PD) Markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and post the 2 week treatment</time_frame>
    <description>PD markers of RAD001 on downstream signaling pathways in patients with sarcomas: p70S6K, S6-RP, P-AKT, cleaved PARP and PCNA by Western blot, quantitative multiplex assays and immunohistochemical studies measured pre and post the 2 week treatment of RAD001. Patients were to be separated into two groups, responders and non responders based on PD results and downstream up regulation of the referenced pathways. Mean fractional inhibition of each PD marker for the responding and non-responding groups were to be calculated. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PD Markers (p70S6K, S6-RP, P-AKT, Cleaved PARP and PCNA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post the 2 week treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative in vivo and ex vivo assessments of PD markers (p70S6K, S6-RP, P-AKT, cleaved PARP and PCNA) were to be normalized within the same sample. The extent of inhibition is defined as the fractional inhibition in each patient calculated as [(PreRx normalized PD marker - PostRx normalized PD marker) / PreRx normalized PD marker] x 100. Same definition would apply to each of these markers. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Pathological Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Post the 2 week treatment</time_frame>
    <description>We planned to determine pathological response in terms of tumor necrosis and apoptosis assessed on the resected specimens after 2 weeks of RAD001 therapy. Percent necrosis was to be reported based on the routine H and E staining. In addition to cleaved PARP analysis, TUNEL assays were to be performed judging the amount of apoptosis in the specimens after treatment. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Memory CD8 T Cell Enhanced Production</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre and Post the 2 week treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Memory CD8 T cell enhanced production as determined by fluorescence activated cell sorter (FACS) analysis on blood and tumor core biopsy specimens taken before and after therapy with RAD001. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RAD001 Administration</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>RAD001 was administered orally as once daily dose of 10 mg PO daily x 2 weeks (14 X 10 mg tablets) continuously from study day 1 until the end of therapy (2 weeks later) or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RAD001</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients were instructed to take RAD001 in the morning, at the same time each day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RAD001 Administration</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>everolimus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have a resectable primary or recurrent sarcoma according to diagnostic imaging
             criteria (computed tomography [CT] and/or magnetic resonance imaging [MRI]) that has
             not been previously irradiated.

          -  Primary/recurrent or persistent sarcoma must be amenable to core biopsy for pre RAD001
             pharmacodynamic studies

          -  World Health Organization (WHO) performance status ≤ 2

          -  Adequate bone marrow function shown by: absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x
             10^9/L, Platelets ≥ 100 x 10^9/L, hemoglobin (Hb) &gt;9 g/dL

          -  Adequate liver function shown by: serum bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN);
             alanine transaminase (ALT) and aspartic transaminase (AST) ≤ 2.5x ULN

          -  International Normal Ratio (INR) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT) ≤1.5.
             (Anticoagulation allowed if target INR ≤ 1.5 on a stable dose of warfarin or on a
             stable dose of LMW heparin for &gt; 2 weeks at time of randomization.)

          -  Adequate renal function: serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN

          -  Fasting serum cholesterol ≤300 mg/dL OR ≤7.75 mmol/L AND fasting triglycerides ≤ 2.5 x
             ULN. NOTE: In case one or both of these thresholds are exceeded, patient can only be
             included after initiation of appropriate lipid lowering medication.

          -  Signed informed consent

          -  Patients with resectable soft tissue extremity or retroperitoneal sarcomas amenable to
             pre-treatment core biopsy

          -  Biopsy proven surgically resectable retroperitoneal sarcomas of any histologic grade

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently receiving anticancer therapies or have received anticancer therapies within
             4 weeks of the start of study drug. Note: Primary/recurrent/ persistent sarcoma must
             not have been previously treated with radiation. Primary/recurrent or persistent
             sarcoma must not have been treated within 4 weeks of the start of RAD001 with other
             chemotherapeutic agents

          -  Have had a major surgery or significant traumatic injury within 4 weeks of start of
             study drug, have not recovered from the side effects of any major surgery (defined as
             requiring general anesthesia) or patients that may require major surgery during the
             course of the study

          -  Receiving chronic, systemic treatment with corticosteroids or another
             immunosuppressive agent. Topical or inhaled corticosteroids are allowed.

          -  Should not receive immunization with attenuated live vaccines within 1 week of study
             entry or during study period

          -  Brain or leptomeningeal metastases

          -  Other malignancies within the past 3 years except for adequately treated carcinoma of
             the cervix or basal or squamous cell carcinomas of the skin.

          -  Any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions or other conditions that could
             affect their participation in the study such as: Symptomatic congestive heart failure
             of New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV; unstable angina pectoris,
             symptomatic congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction within 6 months of start
             of study drug, serious uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia or any other clinically
             significant cardiac disease; severely impaired lung function as defined as spirometry
             and diffusing lung capacity oxygenation (DLCO) that is 50% of the normal predicted
             value and/or 02 saturation that is 88% or less at rest on room air; uncontrolled
             diabetes as defined by fasting serum glucose &gt;1.5 x ULN; active (acute or chronic) or
             uncontrolled severe infections; liver disease such as cirrhosis, chronic active
             hepatitis or chronic persistent hepatitis

          -  Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositivity

          -  Impairment of gastrointestinal function or gastrointestinal disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of RAD001

          -  Patients with an active, bleeding diathesis

          -  Females who are pregnant or breast feeding, or adults of reproductive potential who
             are not using effective birth control methods. If barrier contraceptives are being
             used, these must be continued throughout the trial by both sexes. Hormonal
             contraceptives are not acceptable as a sole method of contraception. (Women of
             childbearing potential must have a negative urine or serum pregnancy test within 7
             days prior to administration of RAD001)

          -  Received prior treatment with an mTOR inhibitor (sirolimus, temsirolimus, everolimus).

          -  Known hypersensitivity to RAD001 (everolimus) or other rapamycins (sirolimus,
             temsirolimus) or to its excipients

          -  History of noncompliance to medical regimens

          -  Unwilling or unable to comply with the protocol

          -  Cutaneous sarcomas or sarcomas where neoadjuvant chemotherapy or radiation may be
             indicated in the treatment plan

          -  Sarcomas must be deemed fully resectable by pre-treatment imaging

          -  No evidence of distant disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan S. Zager, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.moffitt.org/research--clinical-trials/clinical-trials</url>
    <description>Moffitt Cancer Center Clinical Trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 14, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>July 13, 2012</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2012</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">August 17, 2012</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 21, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 21, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 16, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Soft Tissue</keyword>
  <keyword>Retroperitoneal</keyword>
  <keyword>resectable</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>40 patients were to be treated with RAD001 in a neoadjuvant pre-resection manner 10mg po daily x 2 weeks with resection of their extremity or retroperitoneal tumors within 2 weeks after the conclusion of therapy. All patients with resectable sarcomas by CT or MRI imaging without evidence of distant metastases would be eligible for the trial.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>The sarcomas must be amenable to percutaneous needle core biopsy prior to initiation of RAD001 therapy.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>RAD001 Administration</title>
          <description>RAD001 was administered orally as once daily dose of 10 mg PO daily x 2 weeks (14 X 10 mg tablets) continuously from study day 1 until the end of therapy (2 weeks later) or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>RAD001 Administration</title>
          <description>RAD001 was administered orally as once daily dose of 10 mg PO daily x 2 weeks (14 X 10 mg tablets) continuously from study day 1 until the end of therapy (2 weeks later) or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="2"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Pharmacodynamics (PD) Markers</title>
        <description>PD markers of RAD001 on downstream signaling pathways in patients with sarcomas: p70S6K, S6-RP, P-AKT, cleaved PARP and PCNA by Western blot, quantitative multiplex assays and immunohistochemical studies measured pre and post the 2 week treatment of RAD001. Patients were to be separated into two groups, responders and non responders based on PD results and downstream up regulation of the referenced pathways. Mean fractional inhibition of each PD marker for the responding and non-responding groups were to be calculated. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
        <time_frame>Pre and post the 2 week treatment</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>RAD001 Administration</title>
            <description>RAD001 was administered orally as once daily dose of 10 mg PO daily x 2 weeks (14 X 10 mg tablets) continuously from study day 1 until the end of therapy (2 weeks later) or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Pharmacodynamics (PD) Markers</title>
          <description>PD markers of RAD001 on downstream signaling pathways in patients with sarcomas: p70S6K, S6-RP, P-AKT, cleaved PARP and PCNA by Western blot, quantitative multiplex assays and immunohistochemical studies measured pre and post the 2 week treatment of RAD001. Patients were to be separated into two groups, responders and non responders based on PD results and downstream up regulation of the referenced pathways. Mean fractional inhibition of each PD marker for the responding and non-responding groups were to be calculated. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>PD Markers (p70S6K, S6-RP, P-AKT, Cleaved PARP and PCNA)</title>
        <description>Quantitative in vivo and ex vivo assessments of PD markers (p70S6K, S6-RP, P-AKT, cleaved PARP and PCNA) were to be normalized within the same sample. The extent of inhibition is defined as the fractional inhibition in each patient calculated as [(PreRx normalized PD marker – PostRx normalized PD marker) / PreRx normalized PD marker] x 100. Same definition would apply to each of these markers. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
        <time_frame>Post the 2 week treatment</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>RAD001 Administration</title>
            <description>RAD001 was administered orally as once daily dose of 10 mg PO daily x 2 weeks (14 X 10 mg tablets) continuously from study day 1 until the end of therapy (2 weeks later) or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>PD Markers (p70S6K, S6-RP, P-AKT, Cleaved PARP and PCNA)</title>
          <description>Quantitative in vivo and ex vivo assessments of PD markers (p70S6K, S6-RP, P-AKT, cleaved PARP and PCNA) were to be normalized within the same sample. The extent of inhibition is defined as the fractional inhibition in each patient calculated as [(PreRx normalized PD marker – PostRx normalized PD marker) / PreRx normalized PD marker] x 100. Same definition would apply to each of these markers. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants With Pathological Response</title>
        <description>We planned to determine pathological response in terms of tumor necrosis and apoptosis assessed on the resected specimens after 2 weeks of RAD001 therapy. Percent necrosis was to be reported based on the routine H and E staining. In addition to cleaved PARP analysis, TUNEL assays were to be performed judging the amount of apoptosis in the specimens after treatment. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
        <time_frame>Post the 2 week treatment</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>RAD001 Administration</title>
            <description>RAD001 was administered orally as once daily dose of 10 mg PO daily x 2 weeks (14 X 10 mg tablets) continuously from study day 1 until the end of therapy (2 weeks later) or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants With Pathological Response</title>
          <description>We planned to determine pathological response in terms of tumor necrosis and apoptosis assessed on the resected specimens after 2 weeks of RAD001 therapy. Percent necrosis was to be reported based on the routine H and E staining. In addition to cleaved PARP analysis, TUNEL assays were to be performed judging the amount of apoptosis in the specimens after treatment. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants With Memory CD8 T Cell Enhanced Production</title>
        <description>Memory CD8 T cell enhanced production as determined by fluorescence activated cell sorter (FACS) analysis on blood and tumor core biopsy specimens taken before and after therapy with RAD001. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
        <time_frame>Pre and Post the 2 week treatment</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>RAD001 Administration</title>
            <description>RAD001 was administered orally as once daily dose of 10 mg PO daily x 2 weeks (14 X 10 mg tablets) continuously from study day 1 until the end of therapy (2 weeks later) or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants With Memory CD8 T Cell Enhanced Production</title>
          <description>Memory CD8 T cell enhanced production as determined by fluorescence activated cell sorter (FACS) analysis on blood and tumor core biopsy specimens taken before and after therapy with RAD001. Our planned analysis was for 40 participants.</description>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>RAD001 Administration</title>
          <description>RAD001 was administered orally as once daily dose of 10 mg PO daily x 2 weeks (14 X 10 mg tablets) continuously from study day 1 until the end of therapy (2 weeks later) or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>CTC V3</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Platelets</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Leukocytes (total WBC)</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neutrophils/granulocytes (ANC/AGC)</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Ear and labyrinth disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Tinnitus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Mucositis/stomatitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="3" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fatigue</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Creatinine</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Glucose, serum-high (hyperglycemia)</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dyspnea (shortness of breath)</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Rash</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>This study was terminated early due to sponsor budget cuts. We could not meet our accrual goal to perform planned analysis of 40 participants.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Jonathan Zager, M.D.</name_or_title>
      <organization>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</organization>
      <phone>813-745-1085</phone>
      <email>jonathan.zager@moffitt.org</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

