<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01047891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TRIAS 2009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01047891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety Study of Sorafenib With Topotecan in Patients With Platinum-resistant Recurrent Ovarian Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRIAS 2009</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo Controlled, Multicenter Phase II Study to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of Sorafenib Added to Standard Treatment With Topotecan in Patients With Platinum-resistant Recurrent Ovarian Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>JSehouli</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It is assumed, that the patients of the standard arm show a median progression-free survival
      time of 4.4 months those of the experimental arm of at least 6.9 months. Assuming a
      recruitment period of 18 months and follow-up for at least 12 months a total sample size of
      174 patients is required (two-sided, α=0.05, 80% power). To account for 5% drop-outs 184
      patients will be randomized.

      A Data Monitoring and Safety Board (DMSB) will be established. This board will evaluate the
      safety profile of the drug combination after 6 patients and after 12 patients have received 1
      cycle of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ovarian cancer continues to be a leading cause of cancer-related deaths in women and is the
      leading cause of deaths attributed to gynecologic malignancies. Because ovarian cancer is
      usually asymptomatic in its early stages, the disease often has spread outside of the pelvic
      region at the time of diagnosis and requires debulking surgery followed by systemic
      chemotherapy. First-line chemotherapy involves platinum-based treatments, including the
      widely adopted regimens of cisplatin/paclitaxel, carboplatin/paclitaxel, and single-agent
      carboplatin. Although these regimens yield relatively satisfactory tumor response rates, the
      majority of patients experience disease recurrence and receive additional treatments. For
      such patients, a number of antitumor agents with novel mechanisms of action (topotecan,
      gemcitabine, pegylated liposomal doxorubicin, docetaxel, etoposide) have been applied, in
      addition to retreatment with platinum, with the goal of re-establishing remission or disease
      control, minimizing disease-related symptoms, improving quality of life, and extending
      patient survival. Of these agents, topotecan (Hycamtin®; GlaxoSmithKline) is one of the
      best-characterized agents in the recurrent setting.

      Topotecan is an S-phase 1-dependent cytotoxic agent that targets the topoisomerase I enzyme
      and exhibits broad activity in solid tumors and is approved for the treatment of recurrent
      ovarian cancer in US and in most western countries.

      Data from preclinical and clinical studies reported in the last 2 years demonstrate the
      importance of several proangiogenic factors in the tumorigenesis and prognosis of ovarian
      cancer, suggesting possible new targets for antiangiogenic therapy. Once-daily oral treatment
      with Sorafenib produces broad spectrum antitumor efficacy in preclinical tumor models
      including also xenograft models of ovarian carcinoma. Preliminary antitumor activity has been
      reported in single ovarian cancer patients in several phase I and phase II studies.

      Most promising strategy in the therapy of advanced and recurrent ovarian cancer seems to be
      the combination of cytotoxic agents and targeted therapies. Furthermore an oral therapy to
      achieve and maintain long term tumor control seems to be very attractive.

      Therefore Sorafenib and Topotecan would make a rational therapeutic strategy for combination
      in recurrent ovarian cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary objective: Determination of the progression-free survival (PFS) of patients treated with topotecan and sorafenib versus topotecan and placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary target value of this study is the comparison of the median progression-free survival time between the two study arms. Progression-free survival time (PFS) of a patient is defined as the time in months from start of the first therapy cycle until PD or death is observed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival (OS) of a patient being defined as the time in months from start of the first therapy cycle to death or the end of study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Response rates, i.e. percentage of patients showing overall response (CR+PR), progression or stable disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of response is the time in months from first assessment of CR or PR until the first date of PD or death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time to progression (TTP) of a patient being defined as the time in months from start of the first therapy cycle until PD is observed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence and type of AE in terms of:
All AE,
Related AE,
SAE,
Related SAE,
NCI-CTC grade 3 and 4 AE,
Related NCI-CTC grade 3 and 4 AE,
AE leading to treatment discontinuation,
Incidence of, and reason for, deaths</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of quality of life over time as defined by EORTC-QLQ C 30 and Ovar 28 questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of Quality of life over time as defined by EORTC-QLQ C 30 and Ovar 28 questionnaire and, in case of participation in the sub-study, FOSI questionnaire, respectively</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">174</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sorafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>Topotecan 1,25 mg/m²/d administered as an i.v. infusion over 30 minutes once daily on days 1-5, every 21 days and Sorafenib 400 mg orally twice daily (total daily dose 800 mg) administered</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nexavar®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with histologically confirmed epithelial ovarian cancer, primary peritoneal
             carcinomatosis or fallopian tube cancer

          2. Patients must have platinum resistant (relapse-free interval &lt; 6 months of a
             platinum-containing primary or secondary therapy) or platinum refractory (progression
             during primary or secondary platinum treatment) disease defined by measurable disease
             according to RECIST or elevated CA-125 level according the GCIG-criteria.

             Definition of relapse: Demonstration of measurable or non-measurable tumour according
             to RECIST criteria by an imaging procedure (where applicable before relapse surgery)
             or increase in the tumour marker CA-125 to twice the upper laboratory value of normal
             for the hospital or histological confirmation of tumour relapse by biopsy or surgery.

          3. No more than 2 prior treatment regimens for recurrent epithelial ovarian cancer.

          4. Elevated CA-125-value before study entry in order to assess the response according the
             GCIG-criteria (see below). Patients without elevated CA-125 may be enrolled if they
             show a measurable or not-measurable disease (according RECIST) evaluated by imaging
             techniques (measurable disease - at least one unidimensionally measurable lesion ≥ 20
             mm by conventional techniques OR ≥ 10 mm by spiral CT scan) or histologically or
             cytologically confirmed relapse

          5. ECOG Performance Status of 0 or 1

          6. ≥ 18 years age

          7. The patient must be recovered from a prior operation. The operation must be performed
             at least 4 weeks prior to start of study drug,

          8. Adequate bone marrow, liver and renal function as assessed by the following laboratory
             requirements to be conducted within 7 days prior to screening

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dl

               -  Leucocyte count ≥ 3.000/micro liter

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) major than 1.500/micro liter

               -  Platelet count ≥ 100.000/micro liter

               -  PT-INR/PTT &lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal [Patients who are being therapeutically
                  anticoagulated with an agent such as coumadin or heparin will be allowed to
                  participate provided that no prior evidence of underlying abnormality in these
                  parameters exists].

               -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1,0 times the upper limit of normal

               -  ALT and AST &lt; 2,5 x upper limit of normal (&lt; 5 x upper limit of normal for
                  patients with liver involvement of their cancer); Alkaline phosphatase &lt; 4 x ULN

               -  Calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 50 ml/min or serum creatinine ≤ 1,2 x upper
                  limit of institutional values (according to Cockcroft and Gault)

          9. Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks

         10. Signed and dated written informed consent before the start of specific protocol
             procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of cardiac disease: congestive heart failure &gt;NYHA class 2; active coronary
             artery disease (CAD) or myocardial infarction within the past 6 months (MI more than 6
             months prior to study entry is allowed); cardiac arrhythmias requiring anti-arrhythmic
             therapy (beta blockers or digoxin are permitted) or uncontrolled arterial hypertension
             with systolic blood pressure &gt;160 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure &gt; 90 mm Hg despite
             optimal treatment

          2. Previous or concurrent cancer that is distinct in primary site or histology from the
             cancer being evaluated in this study EXCEPT cervical carcinoma in situ, treated basal
             cell carcinoma, superficial bladder tumors [Ta, Tis &amp; T1] or any cancer curatively
             treated &gt; 5 years prior to study entry

          3. Prior radiological or clinical evidence of CNS metastases including previously
             treated, resected, or asymptomatic brain lesions or leptomeningeal involvement by head
             CT scan or MRI

          4. Known or suspected hypersensitivity reaction to topotecan or any ingredient of
             topotecan or sorafenib or any ingredient of sorafenib

          5. Active clinically serious infections (&gt; grade 2 NCI-CTC version 3.0)

          6. History of HIV infection or chronic hepatitis B or C

          7. History of organ allograft

          8. Patients with history of colon perforation

          9. Patients with history of colitis or neutropenia colitis

         10. Patients with evidence or history of bleeding diathesis

         11. Serious non healing wound, fracture or ulcer

         12. Patients undergoing renal dialysis

         13. Patients unable to swallow oral medications

         14. Significant disease which, in the investigator's opinion, would exclude the patient
             from the study

         15. Substance abuse, medical, psychological or social conditions that may interfere with
             the patient's participation in the study or evaluation of the study results

         16. Patients with seizure disorder requiring medication (such as steroids or
             anti-epileptics)

         17. Medical or psychological conditions that would not permit the subject to complete the
             study or sign informed consent

         18. Any condition that is unstable or could jeopardize the safety of the patient and their
             compliance in the study

         19. Legal incapacity or limited legal capacity

         20. Participation in another clinical study with experimental therapy within the 30 days
             before start of treatment

         21. Subjects housed in an institution on official or legal orders.

             Excluded therapies and medications, previous and concomitant:

         22. Patients with prior therapy containing topotecan

         23. Patients with prior therapy containing Avastin or other VEGFR TK1

         24. Any other anticancer chemotherapy or immunotherapy or investigational drug therapy
             outside of this trial during the study or within 4 weeks prior to study entry.

         25. Radiotherapy during study or within 4 weeks prior to start of study drug and prior
             radiotherapy of &gt; 25% of the bone marrow (exception: palliative radiotherapy of
             non-target lesions or pain therapy or local bone irradiation)

         26. Autologous bone marrow transplant or stem cell rescue within 4 months of study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jalid Sehouli Sehouli, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Charité Campus Virchow-Klinikum, Berlin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charité Campus Virchow-Klinikum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>13355</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 13, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 17, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 17, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 18, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>JSehouli</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Topotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niacinamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

