<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01044485</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0205-1isni 07 / 001.112</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01044485</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lapatinib in Combination With Docetaxel in Patients With HER-2 Positive Advanced or Metastatic Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>LapDoc</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multicenter Open-label, Phase I/II Dose Escalation Study of Oral Lapatinib in Combination With Docetaxel in Patients With HER-2 Positive Advanced or Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Georges Francois Leclerc</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Georges Francois Leclerc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this phase I/ II study is therefore to assess the safety and efficacy of
      lapatinib in combination with docetaxel in patients with advanced cancer. Only patients in
      first line treatment for metastatic disease should be included in the present study. It is
      proposed to start with a phase I part evaluating the safety of lapatinib 1250 mg with
      docetaxel 75 mg/m² without systematic support of growth factors, starting after the
      completion and data from the 1000 mg lapatinib +75 mg/m² docetaxel dose level in the EORTC
      (Bonnefoi) study.The objective of the phase II part will confirm the safety and evaluate
      efficacy of lapatinib in combination with docetaxel.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Docetaxel is a major drug in the treatment of metastatic breast cancer. In HER2 negative
      tumor, the first line treatment is based on docetaxel containing regimen: docetaxel alone,
      docetaxel + anthracycline or docetaxel + capecitabine. The efficacy of docetaxel in
      combination with trastuzumab has been demonstrated in first line metastatic breast cancer
      overexpressing erbB2 receptor. The response rate (RR) and the time to progression (TTP)
      observed were even higher than those obtained with paclitaxel +trastuzumab. Docetaxel is more
      and more used in first line metastatic setting, becoming the first Taxane used in this
      setting.As trastuzumab may raise safety/tolerability concerns, and as its interest in
      trastuzumab refractory patients may be limited, there is a need to find new drugs to combine
      with docetaxel in breast cancer, and to address the specific interaction/safety profile of
      this combination.The association of lapatinib and docetaxel will be the key combination in
      metastatic breast cancer development for GSK.The conclusion of a phase I trial EGF 10021
      trial conducted in the US which assessed the combination of lapatinib and docetaxel showed
      that the acceptable optimal tolerated regimen (OTR) of docetaxel (75 mg/m²) was obtained in
      combination with lapatinib 1250 mg with systematic growth factor support.Data from an ongoing
      EGF100161 phase I study evaluating the OTR of lapatinib + docetaxel + trastuzumab shows that
      the association of lapatinib 1250 mg with docetaxel 75mg/m² is haematological toxic and has
      recently been amended to evaluate lapatinib 1250 mg with docetaxel 75 mg/m² with systematic
      growth factor support.A phase I/II EORTC study evaluating docetaxel plus lapatinib in
      neoadjuvant breast cancer patients has just started. The phase I part of this study will
      evaluate several lapatinib and docetaxel dose levels before conducting phase II.

      The phase I part will enrol patients (in cohorts of 3 or 6) to determine in a step-wise
      approach, the OTR of lapatinib and docetaxel. Patients should not be entered at a higher dose
      level until all patients in the previous cohort complete the first cycle of treatment, this
      first cycle is used to determine OTR. Dose modification of lapatinib will be based on any
      observed toxicity in the treatment period. The OTR will be defined as the dose level at which
      £ 1 of 6 patients experiences the DLT (dose limiting toxicity).If no DLT is observed in the
      first 3 patients at a particular dose level during the first cycle (3 week treatment period),
      recruitment will start at the next dose levelIf 1/3 patients experiences a DLT at a
      particular dose level, additional 3 patients will be enrolled at that dose level to a total
      of 6 patients if no DLT occurred againIf 1/6 patients experiences a DLT at a particular dose
      level, recruitment will start at the next dose levelIf ³ 2/6 patients experiences the same
      DLT at a particular dose level, the dose level is not considered to be tolerableIf ³ 2/6
      patients experiences two distinct DLT at a particular dose level, additional 3 patients will
      be enrolled at that dose level to a total of 9 patients. If one of the previously described
      DLT occurred again among the new enrolled patients, the dose level is not considered to be
      tolerableA total of 12 patients will be treated at the OTR.The OTR is defined as the dose
      level at which no more than 1 of 6 patients experiences a DLT.The DLT for this study is
      defined during cycle 1 for the dose escalation step as:· any grade 3-4 non hematological
      toxicity as defined by the Common Toxicity Criteria, version 3 (with the exclusion of
      alopecia, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, infusion related that can be rapidly controlled with
      appropriate measures)· an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 0.5x109 /L lasting for &gt; = 7 day·
      febrile neutropenia defined as ANC &lt; 1.0 x109 /L and fever at least 38.5°C· thrombocytopenia
      &lt; 25, 000/µl or thrombocytopenic bleeding requiring transfusion· grade 3 or higher left
      ventricular cardiac dysfunction or a ≥ 20% decrease from baseline in left ventricular
      ejection fraction (LVEF) that is also below the institution's lower limit of normal (LLN),
      and confirmed by a repeat evaluation 1 to 2 weeks following the first evaluation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2008</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the optimal tolerated regimen of lapatinib administered in combination with docetaxel as first-line therapy in patients with metastatic breast cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>during first cycle ( each cycle last 3 weeks)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the dose-limiting toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>each weeks of each cycle and after the end of the study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate anti-tumour activity in terms of response</measure>
    <time_frame>each cycle and at the end of the study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate anti-tumour activity in time to response</measure>
    <time_frame>each cycle and at the end of the study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate anti-tumour activity in terms of response duration</measure>
    <time_frame>each cycle and at the end of the study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate anti-tumour activity, in terms time to progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>each cycle and at the end of the study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate anti-tumour activity, in terms of time to treatment failure (TTF)</measure>
    <time_frame>each cycle and at the end of the study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate anti-tumour activity, in terms of overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of the study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>lapatinib + docetaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>dose level Lapatinib (OD) Docetaxel (q3wks) Systematic Growth factor Minus 0 1250 mg 75 mg/m2 + systematic growth factor support
0, 1250mg 75 mg/m2 No
+1 1500mg 75mg/m2 No
Minus +1* 1500mg 75mg/m2 + systematic growth factor support
+2 1250mg 100mg/m2 No
Minus +2* + systematic growth factor support
+3 1500mg 100mg/m2 No
Minus +3* + systematic growth factor support
Apart within the minus dose levels, G-CSF support should be added only as rescue strategy if severe neutropenia occurred during the first cycle of studied dose.Patients will receive 4 cycles of the association. In case of benefit of the treatment, they should continue the treatment with lapatinib until progression.* patients will be included at level &quot;minus X&quot; only if 2 DLT out of 6 patients based on febrile neutropenia occurred at level &quot;X&quot;</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lapatinib</intervention_name>
    <description>escalation dose from 1250 to 1500 mg in association with docetaxel</description>
    <arm_group_label>lapatinib + docetaxel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>escalation dose from 75 mg/m2 to 100 mg/m2 in association with lapatinib</description>
    <arm_group_label>lapatinib + docetaxel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age over or equal 18 years·

          -  ECOG Performance Status of 0 to 2·

          -  Patients with histological or cytological confirmed breast cancer, HER positive (IHC
             3+, or IHC 2+ and FISH/CISH +, or FISH+ or CISH+ only), not amenable for an
             alternative curative strategy in first line metastatic setting·

          -  Patients who receive hormonotherapy for metastatic disease or who received
             chemotherapy in adjuvant setting if recurrence occur after 6 months are eligible·

          -  Patient must have not received the last injection of trastuzumab within the six weeks·

          -  Subjects must have completed prior radiotherapy treatment at least 4 weeks from
             enrolment and recovered from all treatment-related toxicities· Subjects must have
             tissue available to prospectively determine treatment assignment and to compare tumor
             response with intra-tumor expression levels of relevant biomarkers·

          -  No prior systemic investigational agent within the past 30 days or topical
             investigational drugs within the past 7 days·

          -  Subjects must have a cardiac ejection fraction within the institutional range of
             normal as measured by ECHO (echocardiogram) or MUGA (Multigated Acquisition) scan·

          -  Subjects must have adequate haematological, hepatic, and renal function·

          -  Affiliation to a social insurance program is required

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with elevations of transaminase (ALT and/or AST) greater than 2.5 times the
             upper limit of the normal range (ULN) are NOT eligible for the study·

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to entering the study or patients who have not
             recovered from adverse events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier·

          -  Patients who have had prior treatment with EGFR targeting therapies· All herbal
             (alternative) medicines are excluded·

          -  Patients with known brain metastases·

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to lapatinib.·

          -  Uncontrolled inter-current illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, peripheral neuropathy of grade 2 or greater, or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirements·

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because lapatinib is member of the
             4-anilinoquinazoline class of kinase inhibitors with the potential for teratogenic or
             abortifacient effects·

          -  HIV-positive patients receiving combination anti-retroviral therapy are excluded from
             the study because of possible pharmacokinetic interactions with lapatinib·

          -  Patients with gastro intestinal (GI) tract disease resulting in an inability to take
             oral medication, malabsorption syndrome, a requirement for IV alimentation, prior
             surgical procedures affecting absorption, uncontrolled inflammatory GI disease (e.g.,
             Crohn's, ulcerative colitis)· Current active hepatic or biliary disease (with
             exception of patients with Gilbert's syndrome, asymptomatic gallstones, liver
             metastases or stable chronic liver disease per investigator assessment)· Previous
             allergic reaction to docetaxel and/or polyascorbate· Concomitant requirement for
             medication classified as CYP3A4 inducers or inhibitors·

          -  Active cardiac disease, defined as: history of uncontrolled or symptomatic angina
             pectoris, history of cardiac arrhythmias requiring medications, or clinically
             significant, with the exception of asymptomatic atrial fibrillation requiring
             anticoagulation, myocardial infarction &lt; 6 months from study entry, uncontrolled or
             symptomatic congestive heart failure, ejection fraction below the institutional normal
             limit
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicolas Isambert, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre Georges François Leclerc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Georges François Leclerc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dijon</city>
        <state>Bourgogne</state>
        <zip>21000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 7, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 8, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 24, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 24, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 25, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HER-2 positive advanced or metastatic breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>dose escalation study</keyword>
  <keyword>lapatinib</keyword>
  <keyword>docetaxel</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lapatinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

