<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01642771</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EBC protocol 1.1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01642771</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparative Study on Two Post-operative Adjuvant Chemotherapy Regimens for Treating Triple-negative Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Open, Multi-center Phase III Clinical Study Comparing Efficacy and Safety of Sequential T-FEC and TX-XEC as Post-operative Adjuvant Chemotherapy Options for the Treatment of Triple-negative Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>China Breast Cancer Clinical Study Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>China Breast Cancer Clinical Study Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Recent clinical studies showed that triple-negative breast cancer patients (ER-/PR-/HER2-)
      may benefit more from Capecitabine chemotherapy. However, the optimum post-operative adjuvant
      Capecitabine chemotherapy regimen has not been determined for Chinese population with
      triple-negative breast cancer. Thus it's necessary to conduct a multi-center Phase III
      clinical trial to verify efficacy and safety of Capecitabine in the treatment of
      triple-negative breast cancer. In this study, a prospective, randomized, open, multi-center
      Phase III clinical study was conducted to compare efficacy and safety of sequential Docetaxel
      followed by Fluorouracil/Epirubicin/Cyclophosphamide (FEC) and sequential Docetaxel and
      Capecitabine followed by Capecitabine/Epirubicin/Cyclophosphamide (XEC) as post-operative
      adjuvant chemotherapy in the treatment of triple-negative breast cancer in Chinese
      population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Post-operative adjuvant chemotherapy has been shown to improve overall survival, delay local
      relapse and reduce distant metastasis by multiple large-scale prospective clinical trial. In
      registry clinical trial for Capecitabine conducted by O Shaughnessy, it revealed that a
      combined chemotherapy of Capecitabine and Docetaxel achieved better outcomes compared with
      Docetaxel alone. And the significant effect of Capecitabine was also evidenced by CHAT trial
      in which Trastuzumab/Docetaxel/Capecitabine regimen was proved to perform greater than
      Trastuzumab/Docetaxel regimen. In addition to better outcomes, Capecitabine also showed good
      tolerance and safety profile. In 2009, Finnish Breast Cancer Group published their study
      results from FinXX clinical trial on Lancet Oncology, and in this trial, they compared the
      efficacy between sequential Docetaxel (3 cycles) followed by 3 cycles of
      Fluorouracil/Epirubicin/Cyclophosphamide (FEC) and sequential Docetaxel and Capecitabine (3
      cycles) followed by 3 cycles of Capecitabine/Epirubicin/Cyclophosphamide (XEC) in lymph
      positive or high-risk lymph negative early-stage breast cancer patients. And their results
      showed a better outcome in TX-XEC regimen. 5-year follow-up analysis of this trial revealed
      that combined Capecitabine regimen can bring more significant clinical benefits to
      triple-negative breast cancer patients. Another clinical trial NO1062 released their
      preliminary results on comparison of AC-T and AC-XT regimens and it showed that combined
      Capecitabine regimen can significantly improve overall survival and this effect is more
      obvious in triple--negative breast cancer patients.

      Based on the results of FinXX and NO1062, it's of great value to optimize combined
      Capecitabine regimen and clarify involved questions, such as whether the efficacy of
      Capecitabine is related to its treatment course or not, whether Capecitabine should be
      combined into current standardized chemotherapy or a sequential therapy. Also, there are
      still no clear conclusions on the best post-operative adjuvant chemotherapy for
      triple--negative breast cancer patients. Especially in Chinese population, the efficacy and
      safety of Capecitabine in adjuvant chemotherapy has not been well established. So it's
      necessary to explore reasonable dosage, safety profile and efficacy of combined Capecitabine
      therapy. Based on this purpose, this study is hoped to compare efficacy and safety of
      sequential Docetaxel followed by Fluorouracil/Epirubicin/Cyclophosphamide (FEC) and
      sequential Docetaxel and Capecitabine followed by Capecitabine/Epirubicin/Cyclophosphamide
      (XEC) as post-operative adjuvant chemotherapy in the treatment of triple-negative breast
      cancer in Chinese population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>5-year disease free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>5 year after the completion of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>Including local relapse, distant metastasis, contralateral breast cancer, second primary cancer or death from any cause</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 5 years after the completion of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>Safety will be evaluated based on adverse events observed and the number of participants with adverse events. Blood biological tests shall also be conducted for further examination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FACT-B scale scores as a Measure of living quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 0</time_frame>
    <description>FACT-B scale scores of participants would be assessed to reflect their living quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>5-year relapse free survival, distant disease free survival and overall survival as measures of efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 5 years after the completion of chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>Disease relapse shall be considered as the endpoint of relapse free survival and the period between surgery and disease relapse shall be recorded as a measure of efficacy.
Also disease distant metastasis shall be considered as the endpoint of distant disease free survival and the period between surgery and Disease distant metastasis shall be recorded as a measure of efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FACT-B scale scores as a Measure of living quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 9</time_frame>
    <description>FACT-B scale scores of participants would be assessed to reflect their living quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FACT-B scale scores as a Measure of living quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 18</time_frame>
    <description>FACT-B scale scores of participants would be assessed to reflect their living quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">636</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>5-Fu/epirubicin/CTX following Docetaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Docetaxel for the first 3 cycles of chemotherapy followed by 3 cycles of FEC (Fluorouracil, epirubicin and cyclophosphamide) chemotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel/capecitabine followed by XEC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Docetaxel/ capecitabine (TX) for the first 3 cycles of chemotherapy followed by 3 cycles of capecitabine/epirubicin/cyclophosphamide (XEC) chemotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5-Fu/epirubicin/CTX following Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Cycle 1-3: Docetaxel i.v. 75mg/m2 (One cycle = 21 days); Cycle 4-6: Fluorouracil i.v. 500 mg/m2, Epirubicin i.v. 75 mg/m2, Cyclophosphamide i.v. 500 mg/m2 (One cycle = 21 days)</description>
    <arm_group_label>5-Fu/epirubicin/CTX following Docetaxel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fluorouracil: 5-Fu</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel/capecitabine followed by XEC</intervention_name>
    <description>Cycle 1-3: Docetaxel i.v. 75 mg/m2, Capecitabine, p.o., 1000 mg/m2，b.i.d (take Capecitabine for 2 weeks and withdraw for 1 week) (One cycle = 21 days); Cycle 4-6: Capecitabine, i.v. 1000 mg/m2, b.i.d (take for 2 weeks and withdraw for 1 week),Epirubicin, i.v. 75 mg/m2, Cyclophosphamide, i.v. 500 mg/m2 (One cycle = 21 days)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel/capecitabine followed by XEC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Capecitabine: Xeloda</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female aged 18 - 70 years old;

          -  Histological confirmed with unilateral invasive carcinoma (all pathological types are
             applicable);

          -  Newly diagnosed conditions allowing direct surgery without any absolute
             contraindication for surgery;

          -  No mass or microscopic tumor residue after surgery resection;

          -  Initiate adjuvant chemotherapy within 30 days after surgery;

          -  Axillary lymph node positive (including the sentinel lymph node positive and lymph
             node positive after axillary dissection), for example, axillary lymph node negative
             requires that primary tumor size must be greater than 1cm;

          -  Definite reports on ER/PR/Her2 receptor showing all ER/PR/Her2 negative (specific
             definitions: immunohistochemical detection of ER &lt;10% tumor cells is defined as ER
             negative, PR &lt;10% positive tumor cells is defined as PR-negative, Her2 is 0~1+ or 2+
             but determined negative via FISH or CISH detected (no amplification) is defined as
             Her2 negative);

          -  No relevant clinical or imaging evidence of metastasis showing in the preoperative
             examination (M0);

          -  Without peripheral neuropathy;

          -  ECOG performance score is 0 or 1;

          -  Postoperative recovery was good and an interval of at least one week since the surgery
             is necessary;

          -  White blood cell count&gt; 4 × 10^9/l, neutrophil count&gt; 2 × 10^9/l, platelet count&gt; 100
             × 10^9/l and hemoglobin 9g/dl);

          -  ASAT and ALAT &lt;1.5 folds of the upper limit of normal values, alkaline phosphatase
             &lt;2.5 folds of the upper limit of normal values, total bilirubin &lt;1.5 folds of the
             upper limit of normal values;

          -  Serum creatinine &lt;1.5 folds of the upper limit of normal value;

          -  Women at childbearing age should take contraception measures during treatment;

          -  Cardiac function: echocardiographic examination showed LEVF&gt; 50%;

          -  Informed consent form signed. -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Bilateral breast cancer or carcinoma in situ (DCIS / LCIS);

          -  Metastasis at any location;

          -  Any tumor &gt; T4a (UICC1987) (accompanied by skin involvement, lump adhesion and
             fixation, inflammatory breast cancer);

          -  Any of ER, PR or Her-2 is positive;

          -  Contralateral breast clinically or radiologically suspected to be malignant but not
             confirmed which needs a biopsy;

          -  Previous neoadjuvant therapy, including chemotherapy, radiotherapy and hormone
             therapy;

          -  Previously suffering from malignant tumors (except for basal cell carcinoma and
             cervical carcinoma in situ), including contralateral breast cancer;

          -  Already enrolled into other clinical trials;

          -  Severe systemic disease and/or uncontrollable infection, unable to be enrolled in this
             study

          -  LEVF &lt;50% (echocardiography);

          -  Suffering from severe cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases within six months
             before the randomization (such as: unstable angina, chronic heart failure,
             uncontrollable high blood pressure &gt; 150/90mmHg, myocardial infarction or brain
             vascular accident);

          -  Known allergic to taxane and anthracycline agents;

          -  Women at childbearing age refuse to take contraception measures during the treatment
             and 8 weeks after completion of treatment;

          -  Pregnant and breast-feeding women;

          -  Pregnancy test showed positive results before drug administration after enrolling in
             to the study;

          -  With mental illness and cognitive impairment, unable to understand trial protocol and
             side effects and complete trial protocol and follow-ups (systematic evaluation is
             required before recruiting into this study);

          -  Without personal freedom and independent civil capacity.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhimin Shao, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>China Breast Cancer Clinical Study Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Institute and Hospital, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100021</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pekingn Union Medical College Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100032</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Friendship Hospital, Capital Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100050</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PLA 307 Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100071</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The General Hospital of the People's Liberation Army</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100853</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affi liated Hospital of Chongqing Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chongqing</city>
        <state>Chongqing</state>
        <zip>400016</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South West Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chongqing</city>
        <state>Chongqing</state>
        <zip>400038</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gansu Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lanzhou</city>
        <state>Gansu</state>
        <zip>730050</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510120</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Second Affiliated Hospital of Zhongshan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510120</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Hospital of Shantou Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shantou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>515041</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Affiliated Hospital of Guiyang Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guiyang</city>
        <state>Guizhou</state>
        <zip>550002</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Fourth Clinical Medical College of Hebei Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shijiazhuang</city>
        <state>Hebei</state>
        <zip>050011</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The second affiliated hospital of Harbin Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harbin</city>
        <state>Heilongjiang</state>
        <zip>150001</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The third affiliated hospital of Harbin Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harbin</city>
        <state>Heilongjiang</state>
        <zip>150040</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Henan cancer hospital affiliated to Zhengzhou university</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zhengzhou</city>
        <state>Henan</state>
        <zip>450008</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hubei General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuhan</city>
        <state>Hubei</state>
        <zip>430070</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Xiangya Hospital Central-south University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changsha</city>
        <state>Hunan</state>
        <zip>410008</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jiangsu Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suzhou</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>210000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jiangsu Province Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suzhou</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>210029</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Second Affiliated Hospital of Soochow University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suzhou</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>215004</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Third Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanchang</city>
        <state>Jiangxi</state>
        <zip>330009</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jinlin Cancer Hospital &amp; Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changchun</city>
        <state>Jilin</state>
        <zip>130012</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Hospital of Jilin University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changchun</city>
        <state>Jilin</state>
        <zip>130021</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Hospital of China Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenyang</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <zip>110001</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fudan University Shanghai Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200032</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zhongshan Hospital, Fudan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200032</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Huashan Hospital, Fudan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200040</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shanghai 6th People's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200233</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Changhai Hospital of Shanghai</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200433</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shanxi Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taiyuan</city>
        <state>Shanxi</state>
        <zip>030013</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Second Affiliated Hospital of Medical College of Xi'An Jiaotong University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Xi'an</city>
        <state>Shanxi</state>
        <zip>710004</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tianjin Medical University Cancer Institute and Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tianjin</city>
        <state>Tianjin</state>
        <zip>300060</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Xinjiang Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wulumuqi</city>
        <state>Xinjiang</state>
        <zip>830000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zhejiang First Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hangzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>310003</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Second Affiliated Hospital Zhejiang University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hangzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>310009</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Hospital of Wenzhou Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wenzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>325000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bria E, Nistico C, Cuppone F, Carlini P, Ciccarese M, Milella M, Natoli G, Terzoli E, Cognetti F, Giannarelli D. Benefit of taxanes as adjuvant chemotherapy for early breast cancer: pooled analysis of 15,500 patients. Cancer. 2006 Jun 1;106(11):2337-44.</citation>
    <PMID>16649217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mamounas EP, Bryant J, Lembersky B, Fehrenbacher L, Sedlacek SM, Fisher B, Wickerham DL, Yothers G, Soran A, Wolmark N. Paclitaxel after doxorubicin plus cyclophosphamide as adjuvant chemotherapy for node-positive breast cancer: results from NSABP B-28. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Jun 1;23(16):3686-96. Epub 2005 May 16.</citation>
    <PMID>15897552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roché H, Fumoleau P, Spielmann M, Canon JL, Delozier T, Serin D, Symann M, Kerbrat P, Soulié P, Eichler F, Viens P, Monnier A, Vindevoghel A, Campone M, Goudier MJ, Bonneterre J, Ferrero JM, Martin AL, Genève J, Asselain B. Sequential adjuvant epirubicin-based and docetaxel chemotherapy for node-positive breast cancer patients: the FNCLCC PACS 01 Trial. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Dec 20;24(36):5664-71. Epub 2006 Nov 20.</citation>
    <PMID>17116941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piccart-Gebhart MJ, Procter M, Leyland-Jones B, Goldhirsch A, Untch M, Smith I, Gianni L, Baselga J, Bell R, Jackisch C, Cameron D, Dowsett M, Barrios CH, Steger G, Huang CS, Andersson M, Inbar M, Lichinitser M, Láng I, Nitz U, Iwata H, Thomssen C, Lohrisch C, Suter TM, Rüschoff J, Suto T, Greatorex V, Ward C, Straehle C, McFadden E, Dolci MS, Gelber RD; Herceptin Adjuvant (HERA) Trial Study Team. Trastuzumab after adjuvant chemotherapy in HER2-positive breast cancer. N Engl J Med. 2005 Oct 20;353(16):1659-72.</citation>
    <PMID>16236737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Shaughnessy J, Miles D, Vukelja S, Moiseyenko V, Ayoub JP, Cervantes G, Fumoleau P, Jones S, Lui WY, Mauriac L, Twelves C, Van Hazel G, Verma S, Leonard R. Superior survival with capecitabine plus docetaxel combination therapy in anthracycline-pretreated patients with advanced breast cancer: phase III trial results. J Clin Oncol. 2002 Jun 15;20(12):2812-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12065558</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wardley AM, Pivot X, Morales-Vasquez F, Zetina LM, de Fátima Dias Gaui M, Reyes DO, Jassem J, Barton C, Button P, Hersberger V, Torres AA. Randomized phase II trial of first-line trastuzumab plus docetaxel and capecitabine compared with trastuzumab plus docetaxel in HER2-positive metastatic breast cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2010 Feb 20;28(6):976-83. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2008.21.6531. Epub 2009 Dec 28.</citation>
    <PMID>20038734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Joensuu H, Kellokumpu-Lehtinen PL, Huovinen R, Jukkola-Vuorinen A, Tanner M, Asola R, Kokko R, Ahlgren J, Auvinen P, Hemminki A, Paija O, Helle L, Nuortio L, Villman K, Nilsson G, Lahtela SL, Lehtiö K, Pajunen M, Poikonen P, Nyandoto P, Kataja V, Bono P, Leinonen M, Lindman H; FinXX Study Investigators. Adjuvant capecitabine in combination with docetaxel and cyclophosphamide plus epirubicin for breast cancer: an open-label, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Oncol. 2009 Dec;10(12):1145-51. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(09)70307-9. Epub 2009 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19906561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 4, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 15, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 17, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>China Breast Cancer Clinical Study Group</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhimin Shao, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Triple-negative Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-operative adjuvant Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Docetaxel</keyword>
  <keyword>Capecitabine</keyword>
  <keyword>Epirubicin</keyword>
  <keyword>Cyclophosphamide</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluorouracil</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triple Negative Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Capecitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epirubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

