<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01646502</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H12-00862</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01646502</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Chronic Wound Biofilms</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Chronic Wound Staphylococcus Aureus Biofilms With Staphylococcus Epidermidis Esp Protein to Promote Healing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic wounds cause significant morbidity and cost our healthcare system millions of dollars
      each year.Their healing is slowed by biofilms, communities of bacteria surrounded by a
      protective layer that stops the immune system and antibiotics from getting close enough to
      kill them. The investigators will develop a new strategy to destroy biofilms using a protein
      made from bacteria that live on our skin.The Staphylococcus epidermidis Esp protein will be
      used to destroy Staphylococcus aureus biofilms, the most common bacterium in chronic wounds.
      The investigators hypothesize that the use of the Esp protein will breakdown S. aureus
      biofilms, decrease bacterial colonization of chronic wounds and improve healing times.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic wounds lead to significant patient morbidity and mortality, and its treatment is
      associated with a global economic burden of $13-$15 billion annually. In Canada, the average
      cost of three months of community care for a chronic wound is $ 27,600.00. One of the major
      complications associated with chronic wounds is colonization with a Staphylococcus aureus (S.
      aureus) biofilm. These bacterial biofilms delay re-epithelialization and prevent wound
      healing. Standard treatment of chronic wound biofilms includes aggressive debridement as well
      as the addition of anti-biofilm agents such as antimicrobials. Since antimicrobial resistance
      is becoming a serious problem, finding alternatives is essential.

      Staphylococcus epidermidis (S. epidermidis) JK16 cells, their culture supernatants and a
      serine protease (Esp) in the culture supernatants have been shown to inhibit the formation of
      and destroy preexisting S. aureus biofilms. The investigators hypothesize that the use of S.
      epidermidis JK16, culture supernatants or purified Esp protein in the standard wound care
      protocol will breakdown S. aureus biofilms, decrease bacterial colonization of chronic wounds
      and improve healing times. The investigators will employ a two-way cross over study where
      participants will receive standard wound care or S. epidermidis JK16 Esp supplemented
      treatment for the first 6 weeks followed by cross over for a further 6 weeks. These patients
      will be recruited from the Wound Healing Clinic at Vancouver General Hospital. Standard wound
      care will be provided in accordance with established protocols based on &quot;Best Clinical
      Practice Guidelines for Venous Leg Ulcers&quot; from the Canadian Association of Wound Care. For
      the S. epidermidis JK16 Esp supplemented treatment arm, the investigators will produce
      purified Esp and impregnate wound dressings with this protein. After 6 weeks, participants
      will be crossed over to the corresponding treatment arm.

      Our primary outcome measure will be healing rate as calculated for each 6 week standard or
      experimental treatment periods. The investigators will employ standardized photography and
      wound image analysis software to calculate the healing rate. Other outcome measures will
      include visual detection and qualitative assessment of biofilms as determined by trained
      nurses and/or physicians. Finally, bacterial type and quantity will be determined by wound
      biopsy. Outcome measures for standard treatment arms will be compared with results from S.
      epidermidis JK16 Esp supplemented treatment arms. Objectives of this pilot study include:

        1. To assess the feasibility of conducting a more definitive trial to examine the efficacy
           of S. epidermidis Esp protein from strain JK16 in healing chronic wounds

        2. To perform a pilot study using a cross-over design with the purified S. epidermidis Esp
           protein from strain JK16 in comparison to standard therapy

        3. To demonstrate that the intervention is acceptable to participants

        4. To demonstrate the safety of the intervention

        5. To explore the biologic activity of S. epidermidis Esp protein from strain JK16 on wound
           biofilms and healing times
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Project was discontinued. Ran into difficulties with purification at the protein production
    stage
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>rate of wound healing</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The rate of wound healing (% change in wound surface area) over each 6-week treatment period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A qualitative assessment of the healing process.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>A physician or nurse will record a visual assessment of the chronic wound in order to obtain a qualitative wound score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Bacterial type and quantity.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This will be determined by wound biopsy performed at baseline and at weeks 6 and 12.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Wound</condition>
  <condition>Venous Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Biofilms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Esp-supplemented standard wound care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>500 pmol Esp protein will be added to the standard wound care protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard wound care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The standard treatment protocol established at the Vancouver Wound Healing Clinic is based on the &quot;Best Clinical Practice Guidelines for Venous Leg Ulcers&quot; from the Canadian Association of Wound Care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Esp protein</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Esp-supplemented standard wound care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard wound care</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Standard wound care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Have a leg ulcer with the ankle brachial pressure index (ABPI) equal or greater than
             0.6;

          2. Have a wound that is 15 cm or less in diameter;

          3. Are 19 years or older;

          4. Have no known contraindication to the treatment products

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Have a leg ulcer caused by pressure, diabetes, ischemia, inflammatory disorder,
             hematologic disorder or malignancy

          2. Have applied an antiseptic to the wound in the one week prior to recruitment

          3. Have received systemic or topical antibiotic therapy within 48 hours prior to
             recruitment

          4. Are being treated with systemic steroids (prednisone)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Kunimoto, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wound Healing Clinic,Vancouver General Hospital - Gordon and Leslie Diamond Health Care Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 1M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 18, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 20, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 3, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 3, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 7, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic wound</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>biofilms</keyword>
  <keyword>venous insufficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Esp</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

