<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01642901</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11F.612</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01642901</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zoledronic Acid in Acute Spinal Cord Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>Zoledronic Acid to Prevent Bone Loss After Acute Spinal Cord Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Department of Health and Human Services</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Maintenance of bone mass following spinal cord injury (SCI) is essential to fracture
      prevention and the associated morbidity of bed rest and further secondary complications.
      Intravenous (IV) zoledronic acid (ZA) is an FDA-approved drug that has been shown to be more
      effective than other agents in reducing bone mass resorption and leg fractures in
      post-menopausal women, but has not been studied in patients with acute SCI. This will be a
      randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of IV ZA to prevent bone loss early after
      SCI. Up to 48 subjects will be randomized to receive a one-time dose of 5 mg of IV ZA versus
      placebo within 21 days of an SCI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Maintenance of bone mass following spinal cord injury (SCI) is essential to fracture
      prevention and the associated morbidity of bed rest and further secondary complications.
      Intravenous (IV) zoledronic acid (ZA) has been shown to be more effective than other agents
      in reducing bone mass resorption and fracture of the legs in post-menopausal women, but has
      not been studied in acute spinal cord injury. Two previous studies of ZA in persons with
      subacute SCI, while promising, were inconclusive. As stated in the long range plan of the
      National Institute on Disability and Rehabilitation Research (NIDRR), one goal in the area of
      health and function is to &quot;focus on the onset of new conditions…exacerbation of existing
      conditions, or the development of coexisting conditions.&quot; This study is intended to
      demonstrate reduction in loss of bone mass at the hip and knee regions in acute SCI in a
      rigorous study of sufficient size to determine effectiveness of our intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in bone mineral density</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Change in bone mineral density (BMD) assessed by dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA) at baseline, 4 months, and 12 months post-injury.
This will compare BMD at the hip, distal femur and proximal tibia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarkers of bone formation and resorption</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month, 4 month, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Collection of blood biomarkers of bone formation and resorption at selected time intervals within the first 12 months post-injury.
This will observe the timing of metabolic indexes of bone formation and resorption, and of pro-osteoclastogenic factors promoting bone resorption.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety and tolerability of zoledronic acid</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the safety and tolerability of zoledronic acid in the acute spinal cord injury population. This will be done by examination reportable adverse events including fevers, flu-like symptoms, GI upset as measures of safety and report of patient's willingness to have participate in physical therapy in the first week after receiving medication as a measure of tolerability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Zoledronic Acid 5 mg IV infusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single infusion of 5 mg intravenous zoledronic acid given within 21 days of acute traumatic spinal cord injury.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>normal saline 0.9%</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Infusion of normal saline of equivalent volume to reconstituted zoledronic acid, given only once and run over 2 hours, to occur within 21 days of acute traumatic spinal cord injury.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zoledronic acid</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg zoledronic acid infused intravenously over two hours (2.5mg per hour), given only once, within 21 days of acute traumatic spinal cord injury.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zoledronic Acid 5 mg IV infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Reclast</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>normal saline 0.9%</intervention_name>
    <description>Infusion of equivalent volume of 0.9% normal saline to that of the reconstituted zoledronic acid, given only once over two hours, occurring within 21 days of acute traumatic spinal cord injury</description>
    <arm_group_label>normal saline 0.9%</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>normal saline</other_name>
    <other_name>0.9% saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages 18-65, male or female

          -  Traumatic SCI with Neurological level C4-T10, AIS (ASIA Impairment Scale) A,

          -  Serum calcium level &gt;7.0 mg/dL) at time of study drug administration

          -  Screening baseline serum 25OH (25-hydroxy) vitamin D of at least 13 ng/ml

          -  No medical contraindication to supplemental vitamin D for participants whose levels
             are &gt;13 ng/ml but sub-therapeutic (&lt;32ng/ml)

          -  No medical contraindication to supplemental calcium

          -  Weight under 300 pounds, which is the maximum permitted on the DXA scanner

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Ventilator-dependent individuals

          -  Chronic steroid use (defined as &gt;6 months)

          -  Rheumatoid disease with use of prior disease modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (DMARDs)
             affecting bone density

          -  History of osteoporosis or of treatment for osteopenia or osteoporosis with
             bisphosphonates, or selective reuptake estrogen modifying agents

          -  Current use of medications* including bisphosphonates to treat osteoporosis (*note
             that prior calcium or vitamin D use is not an exclusion criteria)

          -  History of more than one lower extremity osteoporosis-related fracture

          -  Chronic renal insufficiency, creatinine clearance &lt; 35 ml/min, during screening

          -  End stage liver or kidney disease

          -  Medical conditions resulting in hypogonadal states that affect bone density

          -  Uncontrolled thyroid disease/thyrotoxicosis

          -  Hereditary or acquired metabolic bone disorder

          -  History of use of unfractionated heparin for &gt;1 year

          -  History of selected antiseizure medications, specifically phenobarbital, phenytoin,
             carbamazepine, sodium valproate &gt;1 year

          -  Acute or chronic bilateral lower extremity fractures involving tibia or femur, with
             placement of surgical hardware in any areas of above locations

          -  Severe hypotension requiring use of intravenous blood pressure agents such as
             dopamine, norepinephrine or phenylephrine. Exception may allow for patients on
             pressors who arm experiencing hypotension as they acclimate to upright posture.

          -  Inability to provide informed consent and understand the consent process

          -  Facial fractures requiring oral surgery

          -  Dental surgery or oral maxillofacial surgery within 2 weeks of anticipated study drug
             administration

          -  Pregnancy present on admission

          -  Vitamin D deficiency on admission testing (serum 25-OH D reported as &lt; 13 ng/mL )

          -  Patients with an established reaction to, or history of, anaphylactic shock to aspirin
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christina V Oleson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Thomas Jefferson University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University and Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 6, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 17, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>spinal cord injury</keyword>
  <keyword>bone mineral density</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Zoledronic acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diphosphonates</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

