<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01640262</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-1-2011-066</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01640262</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Modern MRI in the Diagnosis of Prostate Cancer in a Danish Setup</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Modern MRI in the Diagnosis of Prostate Cancer in a Danish Setup</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Copenhagen University Hospital at Herlev</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Copenhagen University Hospital at Herlev</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Clinical staging of prostate cancer in Denmark is determined solely by digital rectal
      examination and sometimes by TRUS, even though the investigators know these examinations are
      inaccurate and have limitations. Since the majority of men diagnosed with prostate cancer
      will die with their disease and not of their disease, and the different treatment-options may
      imply greater side effects, it is important to improve the diagnostic localization and
      staging of the tumour for optimal clinical management and therapy selection.

      The development of modern multiparametric-high-field-magnetic-imaging (mMRI) offers new
      possibilities and approaches in detection, localization and staging of prostate cancer due to
      its high resolution and soft-tissue contrast. mMRI can provide information about the
      morphological, metabolic and cellular changes and characterize tissue- and tumour-
      vascularity and correlate it with tumour aggressiveness. This helps to locate and stage a
      possible tumour and to guide targeted-biopsies towards disease-suspicious areas.
      Internationally published data support the rapidly growing use of multiparametric MRI, as
      being the most sensitive and specific imaging tool for prostate cancer patients.

      While mMRI internationally is a well recognized and accepted method for detection,
      localization and staging of prostate cancer, the use of mMRI in the diagnosis of PCa in
      Denmark has never been applied. Therefore, this project is carried out in order to evaluate
      the use of modern mMRI in the diagnosis of prostate cancer in a Danish setup.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prostate cancer (PCa) is now the most frequently diagnosed male malignant disease in Denmark
      with more than 4000 new cases each year. PCa is the second leading cause of cancer related
      mortality in the western world. During their lifetime, one in six men will be clinically
      diagnosed with Prostate cancer and approximately one out of thirty will die of the disease.
      We know from autopsies that more than half of the male-population above the age of 60 is
      found to have histological cancer-changes. Therefore, the majority of men with histological
      proven cancer-changes will never develop a clinical disease that would affect their morbidity
      and mortality.

      An elevated PSA (blood sample) and/or an abnormal rectal examination are indications of PCa.
      The diagnosis is made by trans-rectal-ultrasound guided biopsies (TRUS-biopsies) followed by
      histological examination. Each biopsy-session includes 10 to 12 biopsy-cores taken from
      standard locations throughout the prostate. Since over 40 % of the cancers are isoechoic on
      ultrasound and cannot be seen, there is a high risk that the tumour is either missed or that
      the most aggressive part of the tumour is not biopsied.

      If you find a prostate cancer, it is important to know if the cancer is localized within the
      prostate or if it grows outside of the capsule. This is called staging and is essential in
      determine the best treatment-strategy and the patient's prognosis. In Denmark, staging is
      determined by digital rectal examination and sometimes by TRUS, even though we know these
      examinations are inaccurate and have limitations. It is important to improve the diagnostic
      localization and staging of the tumour for optimal clinical management and therapy selection.

      The development of modern multiparametric-high-field-magnetic-imaging (mMRI) offers new
      possibilities and approaches in detection, localization and staging of prostate cancer due to
      its high resolution and soft-tissue contrast. mMRI can provide information about the
      morphological, metabolic and cellular changes and characterize tissue- and tumour-
      vascularity and correlate it with tumour aggressiveness. This helps to locate and stage a
      possible tumour and to guide targeted-biopsies towards disease-suspicious areas.
      Internationally published data support the rapidly growing use of multiparametric MRI, as
      being the most sensitive and specific imaging tool for prostate cancer patients.

      The primary objective of this project is to investigate whether the use of modern MRI in
      Denmark can:

        -  Improve the diagnosis of Danish men suspected of prostate cancer and

        -  Improve the diagnosis and treatment planning of Danish men with biopsy-proven prostate
           cancer.

      The secondary goal is to gain experience in the use of modern MRI in Denmark to evaluate
      prostatic tumors. This study forms the basis for investigating whether modern MRI should be
      used as an adjunct diagnostic tool for selected patients in the diagnosis of prostate cancer.

      The project contains three separate studies evaluating the adjunct diagnostic value of mMRI
      to the conventional standard diagnostic evaluation and treatment.

      The three studies:

        -  Study 1 is offered to patients with newly diagnosed localized non-metastatic prostate
           cancer and is comparing mMRI to TRUS and DRE in clinical classification of the cancer.

        -  Study 2 is offered to patients with newly diagnosed localized non-metastatic prostate
           cancer who underwent Brachytherapy and is comparing mMRI to CT-scan performed 4 weeks
           after surgery in the evaluation of postoperative dosimetry (treatment effect).

        -  Study 3 is offered to patients scheduled for re-biopsy due to continuing suspicion of
           prostate cancer after standard TRUS-guided biopsies with negative findings to see if
           multiparametric MRI can detect prostate cancer invisible on transrectal ultrasound; in
           order to improve detection rate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the diagnosis and treatment planning based on MRI examination</measure>
    <time_frame>The participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital diagnostic investagation, an expected average of 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Study 1: Change in clinical T-stage (TNM-classification) at baseline compared to the patological T-stage after curative treatment approx. 4 weeks later.
Study 2: Change in prostatic volumen expressed in milliliter(ml) on CT and MRI 4 weeks after brachytherapy-operation compared to the prostatic volumen on TRUS at baseline.
Study 3: Change detectionrate of prostatecancer using MRI-targeted biopsies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To gain experience in the use of modern multiparametric MRI in Denmark to evaluate prostatic tumors.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>This study forms the basis for investigating whether modern MRI should be used as an adjunct diagnostic tool for selected patients in the diagnosis of prostate cancer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">170</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostatic Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>localized prostate cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>Danish men with localized prostate cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multiparametric magnetic resonance imaging (mMRI)</intervention_name>
    <description>A mMRI is performed before treatment of the patient and is compared to the standard diagnostic tools for evaluating the clinical stage and diagnose of prostate cancer</description>
    <arm_group_label>localized prostate cancer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        -  Study 1 is offered to 140 patients with newly diagnosed localized prostate cancer and
             is comparing mMRI to TRUS and DRE in the assessment of the clinical stage of prostate
             cancer.

          -  Study 2 is offered to 55 patients with newly diagnosed localized prostate cancer who
             have undergone Brachytherapy and is comparing MRI to CT scan performed 4 weeks after
             surgery in the evaluation of postoperative dosimetry (treatment effect).

          -  Study 3 is offered to 55 patients scheduled for re-biopsy due to continuing suspicion
             of prostate cancer after standard TRUS-guided biopsies with negative findings.
             Standardised TRUS-guided re-biopsies as well as TRUS biopsies of any MRI-suspicious
             lesion are performed in the same session and marked separately. The MRI-targeted
             biopsies are compared to the standard TRUS-guided re-biopsies to see if
             multiparametric MRI can detect prostate cancer invisible on transrectal ultrasound; in
             order to improve detection rate.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria Study 1:

          -  Patients with newly diagnosed localized (T1-2) or locally advanced (T3)prostate cancer

        Exclusion Criteria Study 1:

          -  Metastatic prostate cancer

          -  Prostate cancer treatment

          -  Known allergic reaction to Gadolinium-based MRI contrast agent

          -  Prostate biopsy during the last 21 days

          -  Impaired renal function with GFR &lt; 30 ml / min

          -  pacemaker

          -  Magnetic metal residues in the body

          -  Claustrophobia

          -  Psychiatric disorders

          -  Age under 18 years

        Inclusion Criteria Study 2:

        - Patients with localized prostate cancer who underwent brachytherapy 4 weeks prior to MRI.

        Exclusion Criteria Study 2:

          -  Metastatic prostate cancer

          -  Prostate cancer treatment other than Brachytherapy

          -  Known allergic reaction to Gadolinium-based MRI contrast agent

          -  Prostate biopsy during the last 21 days

          -  Impaired renal function with GFR &lt; 30 ml / min

          -  pacemaker

          -  Magnetic metal residues in the body

          -  Claustrophobia

          -  Psychiatric disorders

          -  Age under 18 years

        Inclusion Criteria Study 3:

          -  Patients scheduled for re-biopsy due to continuing suspicion of prostate cancer after
             standard TRUS-guided biopsies with negative findings.

        Exclusion Criteria Study 3:

          -  Histological positive prostate biopsies and known prostate cancer

          -  Metastatic prostate cancer

          -  Known allergic reaction to Gadolinium-based MRI contrast agent

          -  Prostate biopsy during the last 21 days

          -  Impaired renal function with GFR &lt; 30 ml / min

          -  pacemaker

          -  Magnetic metal residues in the body

          -  Claustrophobia

          -  Psychiatric disorders

          -  Age under 18 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lars P. Boesen, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Urology and Radiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Urology, Herlev University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Herlev</city>
        <zip>2730</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prostate biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Neoplasm Staging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

