<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01644526</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CVM-HVS-Phase I</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01644526</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Study To Evaluate The CreatiVasc Hemoaccess Valve System In Patients Requiring Arteriovenous Graft Placement</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study To Evaluate The CreatiVasc Hemoaccess Valve System In Patients Requiring Arteriovenous Graft Placement</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Diaxamed LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Diaxamed LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The ability to selectively control blood flow through an arteriovenous (AV) graft only when
      it is needed for dialysis may reduce the current repetitive complications such as thrombosis,
      venous hypertension post-dialysis bleeding, and blood steal from the extremities. The
      Hemoaccess Valve System (HVS) allows an AV graft to be turned on to blood flow when it is
      needed for dialysis then when dialysis is concluded, the device shuts off arterial blood flow
      and residual blood in the graft is flushed back into the body, using the dialysis blood
      lines. Once the graft is cleared of blood, the venous valve is then closed. Heparinized
      sterile saline reside in the graft between dialysis sessions. By having only saline in the
      graft and restoring normal blood flow to the artery and vein, it is believed that this will
      dramatically reduce the current complications associated with now having blood diverted
      through the graft 24/7.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Hemoaccess Valve System (HVS) is a subcutaneous valve device that is implanted when a new
      AV graft is placed. A saline pump delivers fluid to the arterial balloon valve and closes
      that end of the graft off to blood flow. Using the dialysis blood lines, saline flushes
      residual blood from the graft back into the body. Then the venous balloon valve closes and
      heparinized saline resides in the graft between dialysis sessions.

      When the patient returns for dialysis, the dialysis technician deflates the valves and allows
      blood to flow to the graft for dialysis. (The saline inside the graft simply enters the blood
      stream.)

      By only having saline inside the AV graft between dialysis sessions, there is no
      post-dialysis bleeding where the dialysis needles were cannulated, and because blood flow is
      restored to its normal course in the vein and artery, the traditional turbulent blood flow
      through the graft is eliminated, reducing the traditional complications caused when arterial
      blood is diverted through the graft then into the vein.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    An enhanced device has been developed
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 31, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Device Feasibility</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Unassisted patency rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determine if the ability to limit blood flow to an AV graft only when it is needed for dialysis will increase unassisted patency rate of the test arm by a minimum of 50%. The New England Journal of Medicine study, &quot;Effect of Dipyridamole plus Aspirin on Hemodialysis Graft Patency&quot; (NEJM 360;21, 5/21/09) indicated a 1 year unassisted patency rate of 23% (77% required intervention). Our objective is to determine if the intervention rate can be reduced to 38-39% during the study, a 50% reduction in the expected intervention rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Eliminate Post-Dialysis Needle Site Bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Outcome measure: Reduce post-dialysis needle site bleeding by 95%.
Currently most dialysis patients experience mild to severe post-dialysis bleeding when the large (15 gauge) dialysis needles are removed from their AV graft. The HVS device shuts off blood flow to the graft after dialysis therefore no post-dialysis bleeding should be experienced.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>End Stage Renal Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hemoaccess Valve System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Valve system for use with AV graft</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hemoaccess Valve System</intervention_name>
    <description>Device that allows blood to selectively flow into an arteriovenous graft to provide vascular access for dialysis then turn off the flow of blood to the graft in between dialysis sessions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hemoaccess Valve System</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be a candidate for a new arteriovenous graft

          -  Be either currently on dialysis or ready to begin dialysis as soon as the access
             device (AV graft with Hemoaccess Valve System) is ready for use.

          -  Be prepared to receive dialysis at dialysis centers in proximity of study centers

          -  Have an outflow vein of greater than or equal to 3mm in diameter to which the graft
             can be successfully anastomosed.

          -  Be able to communicate with study personnel.

          -  Be considered by the physician to be readily available for subsequent visits.

          -  Be willing to comply with all aspects of the treatment and evaluation as directed over
             the duration of the study.

          -  Allow representatives of the Sponsor, the designated Clinical Research Organization,
             the Institutional Review Board and the FDA to review his/her relevant medical records
             that pertain to this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  An identification of a central venous stenosis on the ipsilateral side is documented
             or otherwise identified

          -  An identification of an arterial venous stenosis on the ipsilateral side is documented
             or otherwise identified

          -  A hypercoagulable state is documented or otherwise identified and/or previous AV
             access failures have occurred without an identifiable cause.

          -  Has a life expectancy of less than one year.

          -  An immunodeficiency syndrome

          -  An organ transplant is expected within 6 months of enrollment

          -  3 or more previous new AV graft or fistula placements have occurred.

          -  Body habitus (e.g., extremely small or obese arms( precludes HVS device implantation
             or access.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Scribner</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>CEO</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Robert Scribner</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenville</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29615</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 3, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 19, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>dialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>vascular access</keyword>
  <keyword>arteriovenous grafts</keyword>
  <keyword>valve system</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

