<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02190565</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014/815-31/4</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02190565</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy Study of a Food Supplement for Pregnant and Lactating Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Supplementation With WellnessPack Mama During Pregnancy and Lactation - a Randomized Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oriflame Cosmetics AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oriflame Cosmetics AB</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether a food supplement consisting of vitamins,
      minerals and fish oil taken during and after pregnancy can decrease the need for additional
      iron supplementation due to anemia during pregnancy, and optimize levels of nutritional
      markers such as vitamin D and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA, an omega 3 fatty acid) in maternal
      blood and breast milk, compared to placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      200 healthy, pregnant women will be randomized to receive either active or placebo at their
      first visit to the pre-natal centres. They will be monitored at regular intervals, blood
      samples will be taken and they will be asked about compliance and any adverse reactions.

      Approx 8 weeks after delivery, the women will come to the pre-natal centres for a check-up.
      During this visit, a blood sample will be drawn and a breast milk sample will be collected.

      The blood samples will be analysed for haemoglobin, serum ferritin, vitamin D and DHA. The
      breast milk samples will be analysed for vitamin D and DHA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Business decision - strategy changes and budget limitations
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 7, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 7, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 7, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of anaemia in active and placebo groups</measure>
    <time_frame>pregnancy week 28-30</time_frame>
    <description>Blood will be analysed for haemoglobin and ferritin values. We will compare how many women in each group (active vs placebo) are ordinated iron supplementation due to anaemia by mid-pregnancy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of nutritional biomarkers in maternal blood and breast milk</measure>
    <time_frame>6-10 weeks after delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Levels of nutritional biomarkers such as DHA and vitamin D in maternal blood and breast milk will be measured in active and placebo groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Anaemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo consisting of two sham multivitamin and mineral tablets and two capsules of oil</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Food supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Food supplement consisting of fish oil (omega 3 fatty acids DHA and EPA) and multivitamin and mineral tablets with extra iron and folic acid</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Food supplement</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomized double-blind, placebo-controlled</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Food supplement</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>WellnessPack mama</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy pregnant women aged 18-40 years with a body mass index (BMI) above 18.5 and
             below 35 kg/m2 who visit pre-natal clinics (midwife centres) to register.

          -  Nulliparous and multiparous women.

          -  The women must be able to understand verbal and written information in Swedish to give
             an informed consent to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women below the age of 18 or above 40 years old.

          -  Women with a BMI below 18.5 or above 35 kg/m2.

          -  Women with any form of anaemia as diagnosed at the first visit to the prenatal clinic.

          -  Women expecting two or more babies.

          -  Women who have undergone bariatric surgery.

          -  Women on medication with pharmaceuticals that could affect the result of the study,
             e.g., vitamin K antagonists.

          -  Women who are allergic to any of the components of WellnessPack mama, e.g., fish.

          -  Women who suffer from drug or alcohol abuse.

          -  Women who suffer from known severe eating disorders.

          -  Women who suffer from chronic diseases that could affect gastrointestinal absorption
             and metabolism.

          -  Women who want to continue or start using similar food supplements in addition to
             WellnessPack mama/placebo, unless recommended by a physician or midwife, will be
             excluded from the study.

          -  Upon miscarriage or transfer to prenatal care specialist, the subject is excluded from
             the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Angelica Lindén Hirschberg, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Woman and Child Health, Division of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Karolinska Institutet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>SE-171 76</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.fsai.ie/uploadedFiles/Reg440_2011.pdf</url>
    <description>Commission regulation (EU) No 440/2011 of 6 May 2011 on the authorisation and refusal of authorisation of certain health claims made on foods and referring to children's development and health.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fsai.ie/uploadedFiles/Reg432_2012.pdf</url>
    <description>Commission regulation (EU) No 432/2012 of 16 May 2012 establishing a list of permitted health claims made on foods, other than those referring to the reduction of disease risk and to children's development and health.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://whqlibdoc.who.int/publications/2008/9789241596657_eng.pdf</url>
    <description>World Health Organization. Worldwide prevalence of anaemia 1993-2005: WHO Global Database on Anaemia.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/nutrition/publications/micronutrients/9241546123/en/</url>
    <description>World Health Organization, Food and Agricultural Organization of the United Nations. Vitamin and mineral requirements in human nutrition, 2nd edition. 2004.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhutta ZA, Das JK, Rizvi A, Gaffey MF, Walker N, Horton S, Webb P, Lartey A, Black RE; Lancet Nutrition Interventions Review Group, the Maternal and Child Nutrition Study Group. Evidence-based interventions for improvement of maternal and child nutrition: what can be done and at what cost? Lancet. 2013 Aug 3;382(9890):452-477. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60996-4. Epub 2013 Jun 6. Review. Erratum in: Lancet. 2013 Aug 3;382(9890):396.</citation>
    <PMID>23746776</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kawai K, Spiegelman D, Shankar AH, Fawzi WW. Maternal multiple micronutrient supplementation and pregnancy outcomes in developing countries: meta-analysis and meta-regression. Bull World Health Organ. 2011 Jun 1;89(6):402-411B. doi: 10.2471/BLT.10.083758. Epub 2011 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21673856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 9, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 11, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pregnancy, lactation, food supplement, anaemia</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

