<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02196376</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140671</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02196376</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Antibodies and Inflammatory Markers in Postural Tachycardia Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Antibodies and Inflammatory Markers in Postural Tachycardia Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this pilot study, the investigators will test the hypothesis that patients with postural
      tachycardia syndrome will have an elevated percentage of functional antibodies to adrenergic
      receptors compared with control subjects without POTS. The investigators further hypothesize
      that the percentage of POTS patients with antibodies will be higher in those patients with a
      viral infection at the onset of their illness than in those patients with other or undefined
      illness onsets.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome is poorly understood. Many of these patients have
      elevated levels of plasma norepinephrine, particularly when upright One subgroup of patients
      has a primary hyperadrenergic state. The majority of patients have a marked deficit in plasma
      blood volume compared to healthy control subjects. The investigators have previously reported
      that some patients suffer paradoxically from a partial dysautonomia affecting the lower
      limbs. Most patients seem to suffer from either a primary or secondary increase in central
      sympathetic nervous system drive. Recent data have shown that patients with postural
      orthostatic tachycardia syndrome have a lower cardiac stroke volume than their healthy
      counterparts and this low stroke volume may drive their orthostatic tachycardia.

      The investigators plan to do the following:

      The physical examination will include (at minimum):

        -  Height

        -  Weight

        -  Orthostatic vital signs (heart rate and blood pressure) Supine and Standing for up to 10
           minutes

        -  Beighton Criteria for Joint Hypermobility Syndrome (Ehlers-Danlos III)

        -  Dependent acrocyanosis (during stand test)

      Continuous Heart Rate and Blood Pressure Recording A subset of subjects will be given the
      opportunity to also have continuous recordings of heart rate and blood pressure for 5-10
      minutes while lying down quietly. They will be instrumented with EKG patches on their body
      and a finger blood pressure cuff, and these data will be digitally sampled and acquired on a
      dedicated laptop computer for later offline analysis.

      There will be an optional rider on the consent form to allow the patient to consent to this
      portion of the study.

      Blood work

      Blood will be drawn for future assay and analysis of the following tests:

        -  Antibodies regulating cardiovascular function

           o The clinical significance of these antibodies is unknown. The investigators will share
           the results of the antibody panel with the subject, but with the caveat that no clinical
           interpretation or comment on significance can be made.

        -  Inflammatory markers

      The total amount of blood drawn for this project will be less than 15 ml.

      Questionnaires

        -  RAND-36

        -  Health Thermometer

        -  Chandler Fatigue Scale

        -  Daily diary of Fatigue Symptoms - Fibromyalgia

        -  Pain Detect Questionnaire

        -  Orthostatic Grading Scale

        -  COMPASS-31

        -  Structured History (including some of the elements from section 6.1)

      These questionnaires will be completed directly online (web-based interface) using a
      personalized link that will be provided to the subjects after they give their informed
      consent. These will be created in a REDCap-Survey environment, with the data collected and
      stored on a password-protected, HIPAA-compliant, secure computer server.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ab titer in POTS patients compared to control subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>One time only, at first visit</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure will be the proportion of subjects with alpha-1 Ab titer. The primary comparison will be the proportion of Ab titers between POTS patients compared to control subjects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>comparison of the number of POTS patients with viral based Ab versus non-viral based Ab</measure>
    <time_frame>One time only - at first study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at study visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>comparison of the number of POTS patients with and without Ehlers Danlos syndrome III</measure>
    <time_frame>One time only - at first study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Ehlers Danlos Syndrome will be assessed during the physical exam. The hypermobility assessment (Beighton Score) will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>comparison of the number of POTS patients with a history of autoimmune disorders versus no history of auto-immune disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>One time only - at first study visit</time_frame>
    <description>History of auto-immune disorders will be collected during the history and physical performed by the physician.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>comparison of the number of POTS patients with fatigue versus no history of fatigue based on severity of impact on normal daily activities.</measure>
    <time_frame>One time only - at first study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Fatigue will be assessed using the RAND-36 Health Thermometer Chalder Scale of Fatigue, and Daily Diary of Fatigue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>comparison of pain in POTS patients versus non-POTS patients</measure>
    <time_frame>One time only - at first study visit</time_frame>
    <description>Pain will be assessed using Fibromyalgia Pain Detect Questionnaire, Orthostatic Grading Scale and COMPASS-31.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">212</enrollment>
  <condition>Postural Orthostatic Tachycardia Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>orthostatic tachycardia syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <description>participants with postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>participants not diagnosed with postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>History</intervention_name>
    <description>the physician / PI will conduct a history that may include: demographics Framingham risk factors metabolic diseases inflammatory diseases autoimmune disorders review of medications date of last menstrual period (females) family history of autonomic disorders Onset of postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome</description>
    <arm_group_label>orthostatic tachycardia syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>control subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical</intervention_name>
    <description>the physical exam will include: height weight orthostatic vitals (heart rate and blood pressure), supine and standing for up to 10 minutes.
Beighton Criteria for Join Hypermobility Syndrome Dependent acrocyanosis</description>
    <arm_group_label>orthostatic tachycardia syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>control subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>blood draw</intervention_name>
    <description>blood will be drawn for: antibodies regulating cardiovascular function inflammatory markers
no more than 15 ml (1 TBSP) will be drawn.</description>
    <arm_group_label>orthostatic tachycardia syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>control subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>The questionnaires will be completed directly online (web-based interface) using a personalized link that will be provided to the subjects after they give their informed consent. These will be created in a REDCap-Survey environment, with the data collected and stored on a password-protected, HIPAA-compliant, secure computer server.
The following questionnaires will be conducted:
RAND-36 Health Thermometer Chalder Fatigue Scale Daily diary of Fatigue Symptoms - Fibromyalgia Pain Detect Questionnaire Orthostatic Grading Scale COMPASS-31</description>
    <arm_group_label>orthostatic tachycardia syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>control subjects</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood will be drawn for future assay and analysis of the following tests:

      Antibodies regulating cardiovascular function

      The clinical significance of these antibodies is unknown. We will share the results of the
      antibody panel with the subject, but with the caveat that no clinical interpretation or
      comment on significance can be made.

      Inflammatory markers
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Chronic orthostatic intolerance, sometimes known as the postural tachycardia syndrome
        (POTS), is the most common disorder among patients seen at several centers specializing in
        diseases of the autonomic nervous system.

        excessive increase in heart rate [&gt;30 min-1] on standing associated with orthostatic
        symptoms [including palpitation, chest pain syndrome, dyspnea on standing, mental clouding
        and difficulties with concentration], in the absence of orthostatic hypotension.
        Orthostatic tachycardia can produce substantial disability among otherwise healthy people.
        Patients typically feel tired and run down. Many also report a myriad of symptoms that are
        hard to categorize, often involving fatigue. We and others have reported that patients had
        a diminished quality of life.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Postural Tachycardia Syndrome

          -  Previously diagnosed with POTS

          -  Control Subjects

          -  Not diagnosed with POTS

          -  Age between 13-80 years

          -  Male and female subjects are eligible.

          -  Able and willing to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to give, or withdrawal of, informed consent

          -  Other factors which in the investigator's opinion would prevent the subject from
             completing the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Satish Raj, MD, MSCI</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 15, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 22, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Vanderbilt University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Satish R. Raj</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Adjunct Associate Professor of Medicine and Pharmacology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Postural orthostatic syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>orthostatic intolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>autonomic dysfunction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postural Orthostatic Tachycardia Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

