<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02195284</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200330</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02195284</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Study Device Attributes by Investigating Errors Made in Use, Ease of Use and Preference Among Different Inhalers in Subjects With Asthma</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Study of Inhaler Device Attributes Investigating Critical and Overall Errors, and Ease of Use and Preference Between a Number of Inhaler Devices (ELLIPTA, DISKUS/ACCUHALER, TURBUHALER, and MDI) in Adult Subjects With Asthma (Study 200330)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to assess the proportion of asthma subjects making critical and
      non-critical errors made in using ELLIPTA® inhaler compared with other commercially available
      inhaler devices such as the TURBUHALER®, MDI (metered-dose inhaler), and DISKUS/ACCUHALER®.
      This study will also assess the ease of use and preference between the ELLIPTA inhaler and
      the other commercially available inhaler devices. This is a randomized, open-label, placebo,
      crossover, multicentre study with a single visit. The study will comprise three sub-studies.
      Subjects will receive inactive treatment (placebo) via the ELLIPTA inhaler and one of the
      other inhaler devices depending on the sub-study they are allocated to. Only subjects who are
      naïve to the ELLIPTA inhaler and to one of the other inhalers that will be used in this study
      will be included. The study will be conducted in the Netherlands and the UK, and comprises
      one visit only. A sufficient number of subjects (at least 190) with asthma will be screened
      and 180 will be randomized to one of the three sub-studies. Eligible subjects will be
      allocated to one of the sub-studies in the following order depending on their experience of
      using the other inhaler (i.e., depending on which other inhaler they are naïve to).

      ELLIPTA, DISKUS, and ACCUHALER are registered trademarks of the GSK group of companies.
      TURBUHALER is a registered trademark of AstraZeneca.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a non-interventional study and not an observational study and therefore some fields
      are not applicable for the CT.gov observational study design. It would be preferential to
      have the field populated as &quot;not applicable&quot; for sampling method, time perspective, and
      observational study model as they don't apply to this study design.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects making at least one critical error after reading the patient information leaflet</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>In each sub-study, subjects will be asked to read the patient instruction leaflet of the first device and then asked to demonstrate inhaler use. Any errors (critical or non-critical) made by the subject while using the first inhaler will be recorded by the health care professional (HCP). The same procedures will be followed for the second inhaler. A critical error is defined as an error that is most likely to result in no or only minimal medication being inhaled</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects making at least one critical error after the first instruction from HCP</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>In each sub-study, if the subject makes any error while demonstrating the use of the first inhaler after reading the patient instruction leaflet, the HCP will demonstrate the correct use of the inhaler to the subject. The subject will then be asked to demonstrate inhaler use again. Any errors will be recorded by the HCP. The same procedures will be followed for the second inhaler. A critical error is defined as an error that is most likely to result in no or only minimal medication being inhaled</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects making at least one overall error after reading the patient information leaflet</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>In each sub-study, subjects will be asked to read the patient instruction leaflet of the first device and then asked to demonstrate inhaler use. Any errors (critical or non-critical) made by the subject while using the first inhaler will be recorded by the HCP. The same procedures will be followed for the second inhaler. An overall error includes a critical and non-critical error</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects making at least one overall error after the first instruction on use by the HCP</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>In each sub-study, if the subject makes any error while demonstrating the use of the first inhaler after reading the patient instruction leaflet, the HCP will demonstrate the correct use of the inhaler to the subject. The subject will then be asked to demonstrate inhaler use again. Any errors (critical or non-critical) will be recorded by the HCP. The same procedures will be followed for the second inhaler. An overall error includes a critical and non-critical error</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of instructions (maximum three times) from the HCP which are needed to demonstrate adequate inhalation technique</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>In each sub-study, if the subject makes any error while demonstrating the use of the first inhaler after reading the patient instruction leaflet, the HCP will demonstrate the correct usage of the inhaler to the subject. The subject will then be asked to demonstrate inhaler use again. Any errors will be recorded by the HCP. The same procedures will be repeated if the subject continues to make errors in the use of the inhaler. In total, the HCP will demonstrate the use of the inhaler up to three times. Same procedures will be followed for second inhaler.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects who prefer the ELLIPTA device compared to the other devices as assessed by the 'preference' questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>After completing the demonstration procedures of the inhalers, the HCP will ask the subject a number of questions from preference questionnaire after completing the ease of use questionnaire. Preference questionnaire will consist of eight questions with each question having one response to chose from 3 options of preference (Other inhaler device, ELLIPTA inhaler device, No preference)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of subjects who found the ELLIPTA device 'easy to use' compared with the other devices' as assessed by the 'ease of use' questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>After completing the demonstration procedures of the inhalers, the HCP will ask the subject a number of questions from ease of use questionnaire. Ease of use questionnaire will consist of six questions each for ELLIPTA inhaler and the other inhaler under study. Each question will have one response to chose from 5 options of ease of use (Very easy, easy, neutral, difficult and very difficult)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">162</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-study 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be randomized to either use ELLIPTA inhaler first and then DISKUS/ACCUHALER inhaler or use DISKUS/ACCUHALER inhaler first and then ELLIPTA inhaler</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-study 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be randomized to either use ELLIPTA inhaler first and then MDI (metered-dose inhaler) or use MDI first and then ELLIPTA inahler</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-study 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be randomized to either use ELLIPTA inhaler first and then TURBUHALER inhaler or use TURBUHALER inhaler first and then ELLIPTA inhaler</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ELLIPTA</intervention_name>
    <description>Dry powder inhaler (placebo) with two blister strips. One placebo strip containing lactose monohydrate and a second placebo strip containing lactose monohydrate blended with magnesium stearate</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-study 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-study 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-study 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DISKUS/ACCUHALER</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo inhaler with one blister strip containing lactose monohydrate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-study 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MDI</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo inhaler containing propellant (1,1,1, 2-Tetrafluoroethane)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-study 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TURBUHALER</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo inhaler containing lactose monohydrate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-study 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed consent: Subject must give their signed and dated written informed consent to
             participate; Subject understands and is willing, able, and likely to comply with study
             procedures and restrictions; Subject must be able to read, comprehend, and record
             information in Dutch and/or English

          -  Age: &gt;=18 years of age

          -  Gender: Male or female subjects.

          -  Asthma Diagnosis: A diagnosis of asthma as defined by the National Institutes of
             Health. Comorbidities (rheumatoid arthritis or other locomotor problems, visual
             impairment, and depression or anxiety) will be documented as relevant to inhaler use.

          -  Asthma treatment: All subjects should be currently receiving treatment for asthma.

          -  Must be naive to using ELLIPTA inhaler and at least one other inhaler device.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD): Subjects with a current diagnosis of
             COPD only.

          -  Contraindications: A history of allergy or hypersensitivity to lactose/milk protein or
             magnesium stearate or to any other excipient.

          -  Subjects who are currently participating in another randomised pharmacological
             interventional trial.

          -  Inability to Read: In the opinion of the investigator, any subject who is unable to
             read and/or would not be able to complete a questionnaire and understand verbal
             instructions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Enschede</city>
        <zip>7513 ER</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zutphen</city>
        <zip>7207 AE</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portsmouth</city>
        <zip>PO6 3LY</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Southampton</city>
        <zip>SO16 6YD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 17, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 17, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 21, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 19, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 19, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 23, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Inhaler preference</keyword>
  <keyword>Overall inhaler error</keyword>
  <keyword>DISKUS/ACCUHALER</keyword>
  <keyword>MDI</keyword>
  <keyword>TURBUHALER</keyword>
  <keyword>ELLIPTA</keyword>
  <keyword>Ease of use</keyword>
  <keyword>Critical inhaler error</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>January 30, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>March 17, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>May 5, 2017</submitted>
    <submission_canceled>Unknown</submission_canceled>
    <submitted>August 14, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>February 16, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>February 22, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

