<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01372332</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>086/2011BO2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01372332</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Homonymous Visual Loss and Its Impact on Visual Exploration, Activities of Daily Living (ADL) and Quality of Life (QoL)</brief_title>
  <acronym>Hemi-Drive</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessment of Homonymous Visual Loss and Its Impact on Visual Exploration, Activities of Daily Living (ADL) and Quality of Life (QoL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Tuebingen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Tuebingen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this explorative study, targeting subjects with homonymous visual field loss,
      is threefold:

      (i) to identify the perimetric / psychophysical method, that is most closely correlated with
      an individually assessed quality of life (QoL) score, using a validated questionnaire
      (NEI-VFQ 25) (ii) to determine, whether gaze-related (exploratory eye movements) or visual
      field-related (eyes steadily fixating) parameters are better for the characterization of the
      visual capacities that are necessary for activities of daily living (ADL), as represented by
      (iia) a standardized visual search task (&quot;supermarket special offer search task&quot;) (iib) by an
      on-road car driving pilot study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of the perimetric / psychophysical method, that is most closely correlated with an individually assessed quality of life (QoL) score</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life (QoL) is better correlated with the modified ESTERMAN score of the binocular semi-automated kinetic perimetry of the 90° visual field than with the number of affected test locations (local sensitivity &lt; 10 dB) according to the binocular integrated visual field (IVF)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exploration whether gaze-related or visual field-related parameters are better for the characterization of the visual capacities that are necessary for activities of daily living (ADL)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Activities of daily living (&quot;supermarket special offer search task&quot;), are better correlated with the modified ESTERMAN score, based on the intact binocular gaze field than with the modified ESTERMAN score, based on the binocular semi-automated kinetic perimetry of the 90° visual field (90° SKP)
Activities of daily living (driving performance) are better correlated with (the ESTERMAN score, based on) the intact binocular gaze field than with the UFOV risk score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Homonymous Hemianopia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>Age-related (+ 5 years of age) and gender-matched normal subjects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with homonymous hemianopia</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with homonymous visual field defects</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        30 patients with homonymous visual field defects and 30 age-related (+ 5 years of age) and
        gender-matched normal subjects. All subjects are free to stop participation of the tests at
        any time without any consequences on the future treatment of the patient. The circumstances
        of any discontinuation will be documented.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Patients with homonymous visual field defects Primary inclusion criterion: (Stable)
        homonymous visual field defects, as obtained by binocular semi-automated kinetic perimetry
        (SKP), using the III4e stimulus, within on onset of at least six months ago, due to a
        vascular or a traumatic lesion.

        Further inclusion criteria: (i) general: physical, intellectual and linguistic abilities,
        necessary to understand the test requirements: no mobility limitations / hemiparesis,
        Minimental Status Examination Test score above 24, adequate knowledge of the German
        language, willingness to comply with the protocol, &gt; 18 years, informed consent.

        (ii) Ophthalmological: spherical ametropia max. ± 8 dpt, cylindrical ametropia max. ± 3
        dpt, best corrected distant visual acuity &gt; 6/12 (= 0.5), isocoria, pupil diameter &gt; 3 mm,
        intraocular pressure ≤ 21 mmHg, normal anterior segments, no clinically relevant media
        opacities, normal appearance of the optic disc (cup to disc ratio = CDR ≤ 0.5, intraocular
        difference of CDR &lt; 0.3).

        - Normal subjects (i) General inclusion criteria: Physical, intellectual and linguistic
        abilities needed to understand the test requirements: no mobility limimtaions /
        hemiparesis, Minimental Status Examination Test score above 24, adequate knowledge of the
        German language, willingness to comply with the protocol, &gt; 18 years, informed consent.

        (ii) Ophthalmological inclusion criteria: maximum allowed spherical ametropia at distance
        is ± 6.00 diopters and the maximum cylindrical ametropia is ± 2 diopters. The best
        corrected distance visual acuities are equal to, or better than 20/20 and 1.0,
        respectively, for those aged up to 60 years; better than 20/25 and 0.8 for those aged
        between 60 and 70 years; and better than, or equal to, 20/33 and 0.6 for those aged more
        than 70 years. All participants manifest equal pupil size, pupil diameter &gt; 3 mm, no
        relative afferent pupillary defect, intraocular pressure ≤ 21 mmHg, normal anterior
        segments, no clinically relevant media opacities, normal appearance of the optic disc (cup
        to disc ratio = CDR ≤ 0.5, intraocular difference of CDR &lt; 0.3) and normal central and
        peripheral fundus findings on direct and indirect undilated ophthalmoscopic examination.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - Patients with homonymous visual field defects: (i) General exclusion criteria: Pregnancy,
        nursing, asthma, HIV+ or AIDS, history of epilepsy or significant psychiatric disease,
        history of drug and alcohol abuse, Minimental Status Examination Test score below 24,
        medications known to affect visual field sensitivity.

        (ii) Ophthalmological exclusion criteria: diabetic retinopathy, infections (e.g. keratitis,
        conjunctivitis, uveitis), severe dry eyes, miotic drug, amblyopia, squint, nystagmus,
        albinism, any ocular pathology, in either eye, that may interfere with the ability to
        obtain visual fields, disc imaging or accurate IOP readings, keratoconus, intraocular
        surgery (except for uncomplicated cataract surgery) performed &lt; 3 month prior to screening,
        protanopia, deuteranopia, history or presence of macular disease and / or macular edema,
        ocular trauma.

        - Normal subjects: (i) General exclusion criteria: pregnancy, nursing, mental or
        neurological diseases, Minimental Status Examination Test score below 24, history of
        coronary heart disease, stroke, diabetes mellitus, migraine, vasospasm/ Raynaud`s disease,
        drugs indicating severe systemic diseases (e.g. anti-diabetic or anti-hypertensive
        medication for subjects under 70 years of age), drugs or medications influencing reaction
        time, history of drug and alcohol abuse, suspected lack of compliance. Subjects over 70
        years of age will not be excluded for use of anti-hypertensive medication.

        (ii) Ophthalmological exclusion criteria: Amblyopia, strabismus, ocular motility disorders,
        retinal pathology, glaucoma, suspicion of glaucoma, ocular hypertension or any other sign
        of other optic neuropathy, macular degeneration, protanopia, deuteranopia, eye surgery
        (except for uncomplicated cataract surgery), any type of refractive surgery, history or
        signs of neuro-ophthalmological diseases, acute infections, diabetic retinopathy, use of
        miotic drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ulrich Schiefer, Prof. Dr.med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre for Ophthalmology Institute for Ophthalmic Research University of Tübingen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Ophthalmology Institute for Ophthalmic Research University of Tübingen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tübingen</city>
        <state>Baden-Württemberg</state>
        <zip>D-72076</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kasneci E, Sippel K, Aehling K, Heister M, Rosenstiel W, Schiefer U, Papageorgiou E. Driving with binocular visual field loss? A study on a supervised on-road parcours with simultaneous eye and head tracking. PLoS One. 2014 Feb 11;9(2):e87470. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0087470. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24523869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kübler T, Kasneci E, Rosenstiel W, Schiefer U, Nagel K, Papageorgiou E. Stress-indicators and exploratory gaze for the analysis of hazard perception in patients with visual field loss. Science Direct, Transportation Research Part F 24: 231-43, 2014</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 10, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 10, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 13, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 27, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 27, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital Tuebingen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ulrich Schiefer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>homonymous hemianopia</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life (QoL)</keyword>
  <keyword>visual exploration</keyword>
  <keyword>on-road car driving</keyword>
  <keyword>driving simulator</keyword>
  <keyword>useful field of view (UFOV)</keyword>
  <keyword>modified field of view (MAFOV)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemianopsia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

