<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01376336</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>QA308</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01376336</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Safe Water Storage Among People Living With HIV</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial of Safe Water Storage Among People Living With HIV</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Zambia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Environmental health-related pathogens include faecal-oral, diarrhoeagenic microbes that may
      be transmitted via drinking water and are related to sanitation and hygiene. Previous
      research has suggested that safeguarding household drinking water against recontamination may
      be a critical intervention that can reduce risks of diarrheal diseases and may be especially
      important for people living with HIV/AIDS (PLWHA) and other vulnerable populations (Clasen et
      al. 2007). The investigators propose here a randomised, controlled trial of a household safe
      storage container for drinking water in a well defined, HIV-impacted population in peri-urban
      Lusaka, Zambia. After a baseline data collection period (9 months) half of all households
      (150 households) will be given a safe water storage container specifically designed to
      prevent recontamination of water in household use. All households will be followed for an
      additional 9 months. Results of this study will help determine whether this promising water
      quality intervention can reduce diarrhoea and related outcomes in this and similar vulnerable
      populations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aim #1: To assess environmental health-related risk and outcomes in a low income
      peri-urban area of Zambia with a high percentage of people living with HIV/AIDS (PLWHA)
      (longitudinal observational cohort study and baseline) (Year 1). We will assemble a rich
      dataset on environmental health-related risk factors in a well defined population, with a
      focus on household drinking water quality and other water, sanitation, and hygiene (WSH)
      exposures.

      Specific Aim #2: To quantify the WSH-related disease burden among PLWHA, compared with those
      without HIV/AIDS (individual and household level stratification) (conclusion of baseline).
      After nine months of data collection, we will perform an initial analysis to determine
      WSH-related risk by HIV status.

      Specific Aim #3: To assess the impact of a water quality intervention on the longitudinal
      prevalence of Highly Credible Gastrointestinal Illness (HCGI) among PLWHA (randomized
      controlled trial, year 2). We will conduct a randomised, controlled trial of a safe water
      storage intervention. We will assess the health impacts of this intervention, with particular
      focus on the high-risk groups of PLWHA and children under 5 years of age.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported diarrheal disease</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported diarrheal disease information will be collected from each study participant monthly. These data will be collected monthly with 24 hour, 48 hour, and 7-day recall. Data will be assessed at 18 months (change from baseline).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight-for-age z-score</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Weight-for-age z-scores will be taken for all children who are aged less than 48 months (&quot;under 5s&quot;) at the start of the trial and monthly during the trial. These data are useful in tracking short-term wasting, associated with diarrheal disease events. Data will be assessed at 18 months (change from baseline).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>E. coli and total coliforms in household drinking water</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Microbiological indicators of fecal contamination of drinking water at the household level. Samples will be taken from all households monthly. Data will be assessed at 18 months (change from baseline).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary antibody response</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will collect salivary samples from all consenting individuals (an additional consent form is required) to gather information on IgG and IgA response to specific diarrheal pathogens using a multiplex assay. This measure provides useful information on both outcomes of interest (diarrheal disease) and exposure to diarrheagenic pathogens. Samples will be taken at three time points: the beginning, midpoint, and end of the trial. Data will be assessed at 18 months (change from baseline).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1600</enrollment>
  <condition>Diarrhea</condition>
  <condition>Waterborne Disease</condition>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Safe storage device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will be assigned a safe water storage device.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm of the trial will receive nothing until the end of the trial.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Safe storage device</intervention_name>
    <description>This device is a specially designed water storage container that is intended to reduce the likelihood of re-contamination of household stored drinking water.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Safe storage device</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Resident of Misisi compound, Lusaka

          -  Willing to participate in the study

          -  Is able to give informed consent and does so

          -  Household has one or more children who are aged 48 months or less at the start of the
             trial

          -  The household stores drinking water in the home

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not a resident of Misisi compound, Lusaka

          -  Unwilling to participate in the study

          -  Unable to give informed consent or chooses not to participate

          -  Household does not have one or more children aged 48 months or less at the start of
             the trial

          -  The household does not store drinking water in the home
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joe Brown, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joe Brown, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+1 919 360 8752</phone>
    <email>joe.brown@lshtm.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Paul Kelly, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 20 7882 2643</phone>
    <email>m.p.kelly@qmul.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tropical Gastroenterology and Nutrition Group (TROPGAN), University of Zambia School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lusaka</city>
        <country>Zambia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul Kelly, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michelo Simuyandi, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Zambia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 14, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 17, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 20, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 17, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 17, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 20, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Joe Brown/Lecturer</name_title>
    <organization>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>environmental health</keyword>
  <keyword>diarrhea</keyword>
  <keyword>water</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Waterborne Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

