<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01378208</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VEK-H-3-2011-023</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01378208</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>How Often Should We Eat</brief_title>
  <official_title>VEK-H-3-2011-023. Fasting and Meal Frequency Project</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Inge Holm</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Danish Food Administration recommends eating three main meals and three small meals a day
      in order to maintain a healthy lifestyle. However, there is little research to support this
      concept- moreover, many studies shows that fasting can have a positive impact on our health.

      HYPOTHESIS AND PURPOSE The investigators hypothesize, that the number of meals per day in
      order to maintain a healthy lifestyle will not differ in normal weight subjects.

      The investigators will include 1) healthy, normal weight subjects. The investigators will
      study the effects of two daily meals.

      More specifically, the investigators want to better understand how the body reacts to
      long-term, intermittent fasting (14 h /day for 4 weeks). The investigators will assess
      cognitive function, dietary intake, appetite regulation, fitness, glucose and insulin
      responses, as well as fat and muscle composition of the body before, during, and after the
      study.

      Our long-term goals are to compare the effects of intermittent fasting with acute fasting.
      All of this is in an effort to establish how our eating habits ultimately affect our health
      and to, perhaps, contribute to new recommendations for healthy eating in normal weight
      population.

      BACKGROUND Obesity and diabetes are increasing health threats facing the Western world today,
      despite abundant research efforts and campaigns to prevent such outcomes. Throughout the
      years, as the incidence of both obesity and diabetes in the general population has increased,
      so too has the typical number of daily meals. A once common three meals per day has now
      increased to six meals per day, in many instances. Recent animal research has shown that
      intermittent fasting (one or two meals per day) over a long period of time can improve
      cardiovascular health and prevent chronic diseases. Biochemically, fasting leads to an
      activation of metabolic mechanisms designed to preserve carbohydrates and increase the
      dependence on energy produced by the metabolism of fat. There is little scientific evidence
      regarding the number of meals per day that proves to be the healthiest, and those studies
      that do exist have opposing conclusions. Several theories do exist regarding the number of
      meals per day that affect us in the most favorable way, but these are just theories. Our
      study is the first to assess, in both a systematic and controlled setting, how long-term,
      intermittent fasting affects the human body.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>oral glucose tolerance test and cognitive function</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>OGTT with stable isotopes. To see the effect of plasma glucose mmol/L and plasma insulin pmol/L 1 month after intervention (2 months from beginning of the study).
Before, during, and after the intervention the subjects will complete cognitive tests for e.g. concentration, mood and appetite.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Continuous glucose monitoring (CGM), body composition, and physical activity.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>During the control period and the intervention the CGM system will measure the continuous glucose concentration (each 5 min), and thereby any change will be measured. Before, during, and after the intervention the subjects body composition will be determined by weight, hip, waist, and with DXA and MRI scans. Furthermore, physical activity will be assessed by Actiheart and VO2 max tests.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Intermittent Fasting</condition>
  <condition>Meal Frequency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal weight</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Body Mass Index between 18-25 kg/m2 Age between 18-35 years male</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intermittent fasting - the effect on glucose metabolism, body composition and cognitive function</intervention_name>
    <description>Each of the 10 subjects must through a period of monitoring (four weeks) before the study period (four weeks). Before, during, and after both the monitoring period and the study period, the subjects will undergo tests at Rigshospitalet.
DAY 1: Inclusion and exclusion of subjects DAY 1 to DAY 28: Monitoring period (usual lifestyle)
28 days of dietary monitoring
28 days measurement by pedometer DAY 1, DAY 28 &amp; DAY 56: Test 1
Oral glucose tolerance test with stable isotopes
Fat and muscle biopsies DAY 2, DAY 29 &amp; DAY 57: Test 2
DXA scanning
Resting Metabolic Rate Measurement
VO2max test on bicycle
Cognitive testing
MRI of the brain and abdomen DAY 9, DAY 19, DAY 38 &amp; DAY 48: Test 3
Actiheart for 3 days
72-hour blood glucose monitoring with CGMS System DAY 29 to DAY 57: INTERVENTION
Fasting from 7am - 9pm
28 days of dietary monitoring
28 days measurement by pedometer</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normal weight</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Physically active, defined as at least 8,000 steps per day

          -  Regular meal frequency, i.e. energy intake=energy utilized, and eating between 3-6
             meals per day

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Daily medications

          -  Acute illness within the past two weeks (infection, fever, or surgery)

          -  Chronic disease, including cancer, heart, liver, kidney, and respiratory diseases, as
             well as metabolic diseases, such as diabetes

          -  Alcohol abuse or more than 14/21 units (women/men) consumed per week

          -  Smoking, including occasional smoking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bente K Pedersen, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre of Inflammation and Metabolism, Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen OE</city>
        <state>Copenhagen</state>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 15, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 19, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 19, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Inge Holm</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>CIM Administrator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intermittent fasting</keyword>
  <keyword>Meal frequency</keyword>
  <keyword>body composition</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive function</keyword>
  <keyword>glucose metabolism</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

