<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01378572</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SDMC060911</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01378572</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Electrophysiologic and Morphologic Assessment of the Substrate to Guide Implantation of Defibrillators in Dilated Cardiomyopathy</brief_title>
  <acronym>EMOSIDD</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Texas Cardiac Arrhythmia Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cardiac Arrhythmia Research Center, Centro Cardiologico Monzino, Milan, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Policlinico Casilino ASL RMB, Rome, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dell'Angelo Hospital, Mestre-Venice, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Catholic University of the Sacred Heart</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      With the present study the investigators intend to identify the morphologic and
      electrophysiologic substrate markers of increased arrhythmic risk in patients with dilated
      cardiomyopathy undergoing implantation of a defibrillator for the primary prevention of
      sudden cardiac death. Moreover, the investigators also aim to identify if there is any
      electrophysiological substrate modification at the time of the first arrhythmic event in
      these patients. To this aim, the investigators will prospectively correlate electroanatomic
      mapping and cardiac magnetic resonance findings with arrhythmic events, in order to identify
      substrate markers of increased arrhythmic risk in patients with dilated cardiomyopathy, who
      are therefore more likely to benefit from a defibrillator implantation. Furthermore,
      electroanatomic mapping will be repeated at the time of the first arrhythmic event and
      compared with that at baseline, in order to evaluate any electrophysiological substrate
      changes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A correct identification of patients at high risk of sudden cardiac death is crucial for a
      rational clinical management, since the demonstrated effectiveness of implantable
      cardioverter-defibrillators on the reduction of sudden cardiac death. Basing on the results
      of multiple clinical trials, left ventricular systolic function, measured as ejection
      fraction, is currently the only recommended tool to identify patients at higher risk of
      sudden death that would benefit from a prophylactic defibrillator. However, the systematic
      implementation of current recommendations results in a substantial number of inappropriate
      defibrillator implantations, while failing to prevent the majority of sudden deaths occurring
      in the general population. Unfortunately, at present time we have no other way to identify
      patients at higher risk of sudden cardiac death, since other proposed risk markers have not
      been consistently demonstrated of incremental value. Recent data suggest that several
      substrate markers, either assessed morphologically with magnetic resonance imaging, or
      electrophysiologically with invasive mapping procedures, may be helpful to identify subgroup
      of patients at higher arrhythmic risk. However, previous studies have been largely conducted
      on few patients, most were retrospective or with short follow-up.

      We will submit patients with dilated cardiomyopathy undergoing implant of an implantable
      cardioverter defibrillator to a morphologic and electrophysiologic substrate evaluation
      including cardiac magnetic resonance with gadolinium contrast-enhancement study, and
      electroanatomic mapping with bipolar electrogram voltage and morphological analysis. The
      electroanatomic mapping and cardiac magnetic resonance will be repeated at the time of the
      first arrhythmic event.

      We expect to define the role of anatomical and electrophysiological substrate abnormalities
      in determining malignant ventricular arrhythmias in patients with dilated cardiomyopathy,
      thus allowing a better risk stratification and prevention of sudden death.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2009</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arrhythmic Event</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>ICD shock on rapid sustained ventricular tachycardia or ventricular fibrillation or effective antitachycardia pacing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Arrhythmogenic Substrate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the arrhythmogenic substrate in patients who will experience an arrhythmic event compared to a matched control group who will remain free from arrhythmic event.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart failure events</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Hospitalization for heart failure events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>All-cause mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Dilated Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <condition>Primary Prevention of Sudden Cardiac Death</condition>
  <condition>Implantable Cardioverter Defibrillator</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with dilated cardiomyopathy (NYHA II-III heart failure, left ventricular ejection
        fraction &lt;=35%) undergoing prophylactic ICD implantation.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females ≥18 year-old with full capacity.

          2. A New York Heart Association (NYHA) class II or III chronic, stable congestive heart
             failure (CHF).

          3. A left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) of no more than 35 percent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt;18 years or diminished capacity.

          2. Patients with LVEF ≥ 35% or asymptomatic left ventricular dysfunction.

          3. Patients with NYHA class IV CHF.

          4. Patients with history of ventricular arrhythmias causing pre-syncope or syncope,
             cardiac arrest or a spontaneous episode of sustained ventricular tachycardia (VT) (≥30
             seconds at rates of &gt;100 bpm), unless these occurred within 48 hours of a myocardial
             infarction.

          5. Females who are pregnant or have childbearing potential and are not using reliable
             methods of contraception.

          6. Patients with history of restrictive, infiltrative, or hypertrophic cardiomyopathy;
             arrhythmogenic cardiomyopathy; constrictive pericarditis; congenital heart disease;
             surgically correctable valvular disease; and/or inoperable obstructive valvular
             disease.

          7. Patients with reversible nonischemic cardiomyopathy such as acute viral myocarditis,
             alcohol-induced cardiomyopathy, peripartum cardiomyopathy, Takotsubo cardiomyopathy.

          8. Patients with mechanical or biologic prosthetic cardiac valves.

          9. Patients with history of a major psychiatric disorder, active alcohol/drug abuse, or
             noncompliance.

         10. Coronary artery bypass graft surgery or percutaneous coronary intervention (balloon
             and/or stent angioplasty) within the past 90 days prior to enrollment.

         11. Myocardial infarction within the past 90 days prior to enrollment.

         12. Angiographic evidence of coronary disease sufficient to be a candidate for coronary
             revascularization and likely to undergo coronary artery bypass graft surgery and/or
             percutaneous coronary intervention and likely to undergo such a procedure in the
             foreseeable future.

         13. Presence of any disease, other than the patient's cardiac disease, associated with a
             reduced likelihood of survival for the duration of the study, including but not
             limited to cancer, uremia (blood urea nitrogen &gt;70 mg/dl or creatinine &gt;3.0 mg/dl),
             respiratory failure, hepatic failure, etc.

         14. Contraindication to cardiac magnetic resonance evaluation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pasquale Santangeli, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5127014689</phone>
    <email>pasquale.santangeli@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Cardiac Arrhythmia Institute, St. David's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Cardiologico Monzino</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <zip>20138</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Antonio Dello Russo, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 02 58002738</phone>
      <email>antonio.dellorusso@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Policlinico &quot;A. Gemelli&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>00168</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gemma Pelargonio, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+390630154187</phone>
      <email>pelargonio@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 21, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 21, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Andrea Natale</name_title>
    <organization>Texas Cardiac Arrhythmia Institute, St David's Medical Center, Austin, TX, USA</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ICD</keyword>
  <keyword>sudden cardiac death</keyword>
  <keyword>mapping</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Death</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathy, Dilated</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Death, Sudden, Cardiac</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

