<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01379027</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01MH087505</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01379027</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MoodHelper: Internet Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT) for Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Internet CBT for Depression: Comparing Pure, Guided, and Stepped Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaiser Permanente</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evidence-based treatments (EBTs) for mental health conditions are often not available to
      persons needing them in the community. Our aim is to test a novel Internet intervention that
      has the promise of eventually improving the Reach and Implementation of mental health EBTs,
      speeding the translation of research successes into improved community care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Evidence-based treatments (EBTs) for depression are often not available to persons needing
      them; this is particularly true of psychotherapies. Even when available, EBTs are often
      poorly delivered at less-than-optimal quality. High direct and indirect costs also limit the
      availability of EBTs. Together these barriers contribute to suboptimal treatment of
      depression in the community. In a preliminary step toward addressing these quality
      shortcomings, the investigators propose to conduct a blended efficacy- effectiveness
      randomized controlled trial (RCT) of high fidelity, Internet-delivered cognitive behavioral
      therapy (CBT) for depression, extending our previous research to maximize treatment
      availability and quality as well as to reduce costs. Over a 36-month recruitment period, the
      investigators will enroll 1,800 adults seeking care for depression from 3 rural healthcare
      clinics, 3 safety net federally qualified healthcare centers (FQHCs), and 2 non-profit HMOs.
      Participants will be randomized to: (a) a treatment as usual (TAU) control condition,
      typically antidepressants and/or psychosocial services; (b) TAU plus Pure self-help Internet
      CBT for depression, consisting of access to the Internet site without any contact with
      therapists; (c) TAU plus Guided self-help Internet CBT, consisting of access to the Internet
      site plus brief, periodic telephone contacts with therapists; or (d) a Stepped-Care Internet
      CBT condition, starting with TAU + Pure self-help CBT and progressing to Guided self-help CBT
      if adequate progress is not observed early on. Participants will be followed for one year.
      The primary hypothesis for which the study is powered is that Guided self-help CBT will
      result in greater depression symptom improvement than Pure self-help CBT. The investigators
      also expect secondary analyses to reveal this pattern of results: Guided CBT &gt; Pure CBT &gt;
      TAU. The investigators will conduct cost-effectiveness analyses (CEA), as the investigators
      project substantial differences in the direct costs of each study arm. The investigators will
      also examine TAU healthcare utilization (medications, visits, etc) from electronic medical
      records (EMR), billing systems, and participant report. The investigators hypothesize that
      cost per depression free days (DFDs) and quality- adjusted life years (QALYs) will be lowest
      for Pure CBT, relative to Guided and Stepped-Care CBT and TAU. The investigators also
      hypothesize that cost per unit of improvement in QALYs and DFDs will be better for
      Stepped-Care compared to Guided CBT. Additional aims include exploratory examination of
      secondary outcomes, and predictors and moderators of outcomes among the interventions. The
      investigators also will collect quantitative and qualitative data on patient, provider, and
      organizational factors that may impede or facilitate implementation of these interventions,
      to help prepare for future dissemination efforts. Finally, in this reapplication the
      investigators have added a non-research Reach Estimation Phase to better estimate acceptance
      and retention rates under conditions that closely match real-world dissemination
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary hypothesis for which the study is powered is that Guided self-help CBT will result in greater depression symptom improvement than Pure self-help CBT.</measure>
    <time_frame>assessment measure is administered at baseline and each follow-up, at 5, 10, 15, 25, and 50 weeks after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>We'll enroll 1,800 adults with depression from 3 rural healthcare clinics, 3 safety net federally qualified healthcare centers and 2 non-profit HMO. Participants will be randomized to: TAU only (b) TAU plus Pure self-help Internet CBT for depression (G-CBT), (c) TAU plus G-CBT, plus brief, periodic therapist telephone contacts; or (d) a Stepped-Care Internet CBT condition, starting with TAU + Pure self-help CBT and progressing to Guided self-help CBT if adequate progress is not observed early on. Participants will be followed for one year.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>secondary analyses will examine healthcare utilization for any signs of shifts in amount or mix of TAU services by study condition.</measure>
    <time_frame>assessment measure is administered at baseline and each follow-up, at 5, 10, 15, 25, and 50 weeks after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>We will conduct cost-effectiveness analyses, examine TAU healthcare utilization from EMR, participant report and collect quantitative and qualitative data on patient, provider, and organizational factors that may impede or facilitate implementation of these interventions and we have added a non-research Reach Estimation Phase to better estimate acceptance and retention rates under conditions that closely match real-world dissemination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1816</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>a treatment as usual (TAU) control condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive recruitment information, go on the study website to enroll and complete assessments over the study web site but will not receive the study intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pure self-help Internet CBT for depression</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive TAU plus access to the study website for the self-help Internet CBT for depression, consisting of access to the Internet site without any contact with therapist</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Guided self-help Internet CBT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive TAU plus Guided self-help Internet CBT, consisting of access to the Internet site plus brief, periodic telephone contacts with therapists</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stepped-Care Internet CBT condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This consists of a Stepped-Care Internet CBT condition, starting with TAU + Pure self-help CBT and progressing to Guided self-help CBT if adequate progress is not observed early on</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pure self-help Internet CBT for depression</intervention_name>
    <description>Internet, CBT, Depression</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pure self-help Internet CBT for depression</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Guided self-help Internet CBT</intervention_name>
    <description>CBT, Depression, Website intervention, coaching</description>
    <arm_group_label>Guided self-help Internet CBT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stepped-Care Internet CBT condition</intervention_name>
    <description>Depression CBT, Internet intervention</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stepped-Care Internet CBT condition</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must have a score ≥ 10 on the self-report Patient Health Questionnaire
             (PHQ-8), indicative of clinically significant, moderate depression.

          -  Participants must identify their primary healthcare provider in one of the 8
             performance sites, and give permission to contact him or her for the purpose of
             periodic progress reports as well as a referral contact in case any emergent crises
             are detected.

          -  Participant must be 18 years of age have access to a computer with internet and a
             working email address.

          -  Participants must also indicate they are planning to continue receiving services from
             one of the performance site clinics/organizations for at least the next 6 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Greg N Clarke, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Permanente Center for Health Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97227</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 10, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 22, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 23, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Website intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>CBT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

