<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01174810</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09/0391</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2009-018137-37</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01174810</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exendin-4 as a Treatment for Parkinson's Disease - Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label, Single Site, 12 Month, Phase II, Randomised Controlled Trial Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of Exendin-4 (Exenatide) in the Treatment of Patients With Moderate Severity Parkinson's Disease.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College, London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College, London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Exenatide is a licensed, safe and effective treatment for patients with Diabetes mellitus.
      Laboratory work has shown strong, reproducible evidence that this drug has beneficial
      &quot;disease modifying&quot; effects when given to animals with a range of experimental models of
      Parkinson's disease (PD). This project aims to make an initial evaluation of possible
      benefits of Exenatide among patients with moderate symptoms of PD. The drug will be given as
      a twice daily 10microgram injection under the skin in a similar way to one of the
      conventional &quot;symptomatic&quot; treatments for PD (Apomorphine).

      Forty patients with moderate symptoms of PD will be recruited and randomised to receive
      Exenatide injections twice daily, or to act as controls in this open label trial. Detailed
      assessments will be made of all patients at baseline and periodically for a total of 14
      months. The primary outcome measure will be the change between baseline and follow up, in the
      severity of a validated PD assessment scale (the UPDRS part 3 motor score) after an overnight
      period free of conventional PD medication. Secondary measures will include adverse event
      reports, self completed questionnaires, and blood test results. Aside from these assessments,
      all patients will continue their regular PD medications throughout the trial with adjustments
      made only according to clinical need.

      In a subgroup of patients (n=10), brain scans that assess the severity of PD, will be
      performed at both baseline and follow up to help understand possible mechanisms of action of
      Exenatide.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline to 12 months &amp; 14 months between patients on active Exenatide treatment and PD controls in respect of their UPDRS-off-medication motor subscore.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse event profile among patients treated with Exenatide compared with matched PD controls. Change from baseline to 12 months/ 14 months between patients on active treatment and PD controls in respect of list given below</measure>
    <description>the UPDRS on medication motor subscore
the UPDRS ADL subscore
dyskinesia rating scale
timed motor tests
the Mattis Dementia rating scale
the Montgomery &amp; Asberg Depression rating scale
the PDQ39
the EQ-5D
the NMS Quest
the SCOPA Sleep scale
the SCOPA AUT scale
the Smell Identification test
DAT (SPECT) scan appearances.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exenatide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exenatide</intervention_name>
    <description>Exenatide, 5 micrograms twice a day for 1 month and 10 micrograms twice a day for 11 months. Total duration of treatment 12 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exenatide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Byetta</other_name>
    <other_name>Exendin-4</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of Idiopathic Parkinson's disease of moderate severity- equivalent to Hoehn/
             Yahr stage 2 to 2.5 (Bilateral symptoms but still physically independent).

        Male or female. Female patients to be post menopausal (defined as 12 months of spontaneous
        amenorrhoea or 6 months spontaneous amenorrhoea with FSH levels greater than 40mIU/ml),
        surgically sterilised (post hysterectomy and/or oophorectomy). Male patients with female
        partners that have child bearing potential must use adequate contraception (condoms
        +/-spermicidal gel/foam) throughout the duration of the trial period.

          -  Age 45-70 years

          -  Disease onset after age 40 years

          -  Disease duration &gt; 5 years

          -  On L-dopa treatment. Patient must be on oral L-dopa treatment - with or without
             dopamine agonist including Apomorphine, MAO-B inhibitor, COMT inhibitor, Amantadine,
             Beta blocker, anticholinergic treatment History of wearing off phenomena- duration of
             action of single dose of L-dopa &lt; 6 hours Stable PD medication for preceding 3 months-
             i.e. no change in medication type or dose.

          -  UPDRS motor off medication score &gt;15

          -  L-dopa responsiveness. Defined as &gt;33% improvement in UPDRS motor off medication score
             following L-dopa challenge

          -  Able to give informed consent

          -  Able to comply with trial protocol and willing to attend necessary clinic visits off
             medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis or suspicion of other cause for parkinsonism including Vascular
             parkinsonism, post traumatic parkinsonism, drug or toxin induced parkinsonism, or
             other neurodegenerative condition including Multiple System Atrophy, Progressive
             Supranuclear Palsy, Huntington's disease, Wilson's disease, Pantothenate kinase
             Neurodegeneration (PKAN), Alzheimer's disease, Creutzfeld Jacob disease.

          -  Known abnormality on CT or MRI brain imaging considered to be causing symptoms or
             signs of neurological dysfunction, or considered likely to compromise compliance with
             trial protocol.

        Concurrent dementia defined by a score lower than 120 on the Mattis Dementia Rating Scale.

          -  Concurrent severe depression defined by a score greater than 16 on the MADRS Exposure
             to neuroleptic drugs within 6 months prior to baseline assessment Prior intracerebral
             surgical intervention for Parkinson's disease including Deep Brain stimulation,
             lesional surgery, growth factor administration, gene therapy or cell transplant

          -  Already actively participating in a trial of a device, drug or surgical treatment for
             Parkinson's disease, or trial participation within previous 30 days.

          -  Type 1 Diabetes mellitus

          -  Type 2 Diabetes mellitus on insulin treatment

          -  End stage renal disease or severely impaired renal function with creatinine clearance
             &lt;30ml/min

          -  History of severe cardiac disease (Angina, Myocardial infarction or cardiac surgery in
             preceding 2 years)

          -  History of pancreatitis

          -  History of alcoholism

          -  Severe gastrointestinal disease including gastroparesis

          -  Ongoing treatment with sulphonylurea

          -  Females that are pregnant or breast feeding or of child bearing potential.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Hospital for Neurology and Neurosurgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1E 3BG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 2, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 3, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 4, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr Thomas Foltynie</name_title>
    <organization>UCL</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>PD</keyword>
  <keyword>Moderate Parkinson's Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Exenatide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

