<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01170325</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100157</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-M-0157</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01170325</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Divalproex Sodium in Children With ASD and Epileptiform EEG</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study of Divalproex Sodium in Children With Autism Spectrum Disorder and Epileptiform EEG</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Electroencephalography (EEG) records electric patterns produced by the brain, and can
           detect conditions such as epilepsy or other l abnormalities that may affect brain
           function. In EEG studies, electric patterns that resemble epileptic seizures are known
           as epileptiform pattern. These patterns are associated with an increased risk of
           seizures, even in people who have not been diagnosed with epilepsy. Epileptiform
           patterns also appear on the EEGs of some children who have autism spectrum disorders but
           do not have epilepsy. It is unclear if these discharges are related in any way to the
           symptoms of autism (behavior, language or intellectual abilities).

        -  Divalproex sodium (Depakote) is a drug that has been used for many years to treat
           epilepsy and other brain disorders in children and adults. Researchers are interested
           determining whether treatment with divalproex sodium can reduce epileptiform patterns in
           children with autism spectrum disorders, and in doing so study whether this treatment
           can improve behavior, language or cognition in children with autism spectrum disorders.

      Objectives:

      - To study the effectiveness of using divalproex sodium to reduce epileptiform EEG discharges
      in children with autism spectrum disorders.

      Eligibility:

      - Children between 3 and 10 years of age who have an autism spectrum disorder and show
      frequent epileptiform discharges on an overnight EEG.

      Design:

        -  This study will last for a total of 9 months, with 6 months of treatment with either
           divalproex sodium or a placebo followed by 3 months of treatment with divalproex sodium
           only.

        -  Potential participants will be screened with a physical examination and medical history,
           blood samples, and psychological tests, and will spend the night in the NIH Clinical
           Center to have an overnight EEG. Children with frequent epileptiform abnormalities on
           the EEG will continue with the study; all others will be considered ineligible.

        -  Eligible participants will receive either divalproex sodium or a placebo to be taken
           twice daily for 24 weeks. Neither the investigators nor the participants will know which
           they are taking.

        -  Participants will have regular visits (every 2-4 weeks) to monitor for adverse effects
           and to test for possible behavioral improvement, and will also have overnight EEG
           testing at 12 and 24 weeks.

        -  At the end of the 24-week study period, participants will have the option to have an
           additional 12 weeks of treatment with divalproex sodium.

        -  A final evaluation (including EEG) will be conducted at the end of the final treatment
           period.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective

      The objective of this study is to investigate the efficacy of divalproex sodium in reduction
      of epileptiform EEG discharges in children with Autism Spectrum Disorders (ASD). ASDs are
      neurodevelopmental disorders that result in abnormalities of social and language development
      and are associated with rigid and repetitive behaviors. ASD prevalence may be as common as 1
      in 110 and as many as 1/3 of these individuals have seizures. Abnormal electroencephalograms
      (EEGs) (without seizure activity) are even more prevalent (Spence &amp; Schneider, 2009). In an
      ongoing study at the NIMH, approximately 50% of children without epilepsy had epileptiform
      discharges present on overnight EEG. The relationship between this abnormal activity and
      autism symptoms has not yet been studied; however, data from other epilepsy syndromes suggest
      that these epileptiform discharges contribute to behavioral and cognitive deficits. It is
      also unknown whether or not reduction of the epileptiform discharges will result in improved
      behavior and more rapid intellectual and social development in children with ASD. This pilot
      study is designed to address that question.

      Study Population

      100 children with ASDs including Autistic Disorder, Asperger's or PDD-NOS ages 3-10 will be
      screened to find up to 40 children with frequent epileptiform discharges noted on overnight
      EEG. Allowing for up to 20% drop out, we expect at least 32 to complete the study.

      Design

      The proposed investigation is a 9 month long trial with a 6 month double-blind placebo
      controlled trial of divalproex sodium (Depakote) and a 3 month open label extension phase.
      Prior to study entry, potential subjects will be evaluated with the standard PDN
      diagnostic/behavioral assessment (06-M-0065). Children meeting eligibility criteria will
      undergo an overnight EEG and those with frequent epileptiform discharges will be randomly
      assigned to receive divalproex sodium or placebo. Study drugs will be administered in a
      blinded fashion for 24 weeks with overnight EEG at 12 and 24 weeks. Biweekly then monthly
      visits with laboratory studies will monitor for behavioral improvement and for potential
      adverse effects. A 3 month open label extension phase follows.

      Outcome Measures

      The primary outcome measure will be EEG changes; tolerability and changes in behavioral
      symptoms will be exploratory secondary outcome assessments. It is hypothesized that
      divalproex will be superior to placebo in reducing epileptiform discharges on the EEG. In
      addition, exploratory analyses will investigate whether children who demonstrate improvements
      and even normalization of the EEG pattern will have more associated behavioral improvements
      than those for whom the EEG does not improve.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 30, 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 28, 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 28, 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>epileptiform EEG discharges</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in behavior</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism</condition>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Divalproex Sodium</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Comparator</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Have a diagnosis of Autistic Disorder, Asperger's syndrome, or Pervasive
                  Developmental Disorder - Not Otherwise Specified (PDD-NOS).

               2. Are aged 3 to 10 years.

               3. Weigh at least 12.5 kg.

               4. Only children with frequent epileptiform EEG activity on the overnight EEG at NIH
                  will be randomized to start study drug. Frequent discharges are defined as
                  spikes, spike wave, and sharp waves occurring at greater than 5 events per hour.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. A diagnosis of epilepsy (past or present) excluding febrile seizures.

          2. The presence of a severe epileptiform EEG on the sleep EEG at NIH referred to as
             electrical status epilepticus in sleep (ESES).

          3. Previous treatment with divalproex sodium

               1. of greater than 6 months duration

               2. within the last 12 months

               3. that was associated with significant side effects leading to termination of
                  treatment.

          4. Recent (less than two months prior to study entry) initiation of a behavioral therapy
             program or new psychotropic medication, or the plan to change or start a new therapy.

          5. Presence of medical condition, such as carnitine deficiency, urea cycle disorder or
             other metabolic disorder that would be a contraindication to divalproex sodium usage.

          6. Renal, hepatic, pancreatic, or hematologic dysfunction as evidenced by increase above
             upper limits of normal for BUN/creatinine, or values twice the upper limit of normal
             for serum transaminases (ALT/SGPT, AST/SGOT), values twice the upper limit of normal
             for serum lipase and amylase, platelets &lt; 80,000 /mcL, WBC&lt; 3.0 10(3)/mcL.

          7. Pregnancy

          8. Concomitant use of medication contraindicated with divalproex sodium including
             topiramate, lamotragine, and drugs that inhibit cytochrome p450 enzymes.

          9. Behavioral management issues (e.g. self-injury, aggressiveness) that are severe enough
             to be of safety concerns (to subject and/or staff).

         10. Absence of primary care physician.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aarts JH, Binnie CD, Smit AM, Wilkins AJ. Selective cognitive impairment during focal and generalized epileptiform EEG activity. Brain. 1984 Mar;107 ( Pt 1):293-308.</citation>
    <PMID>6421454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Artama M, Isojärvi JI, Auvinen A. Antiepileptic drug use and birth rate in patients with epilepsy--a population-based cohort study in Finland. Hum Reprod. 2006 Sep;21(9):2290-5. Epub 2006 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>16751648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Binnie CD. Cognitive impairment during epileptiform discharges: is it ever justifiable to treat the EEG? Lancet Neurol. 2003 Dec;2(12):725-30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14636777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 28, 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 24, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 27, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Sarah J. Spence, M.D./National Institute of Mental Health</name_title>
    <organization>National Institutes of Health</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Valproic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Divalproex</keyword>
  <keyword>Autism</keyword>
  <keyword>EEG</keyword>
  <keyword>Electroencephalogram (EEG)</keyword>
  <keyword>Depakote</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Valproic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

