<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01172184</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NSC99-2314-B-075B-007</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>VGHKS99-CT7-06</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01172184</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Left Atrial Distensibility to Predict Left Ventricular Filling Pressure and Prognosis in Patients With Severe Mitral Regurgitation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Left Atrial Distensibility to Predict Left Ventricular Filling Pressure and Prognosis in Patients With Severe Mitral Regurgitation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaohsiung Veterans General Hospital.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Science Council, Taiwan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaohsiung Veterans General Hospital.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A large left atrial (LA) volume, which represents chronic diastolic dysfunction, is
      associated with a poor outcome, regardless of systolic function. Thus, the LA volume provides
      a long-term view of whether the patient has diastolic dysfunction, regardless of the loading
      conditions present at the examination, such as hemoglobin A1c in diabetes mellitus. To date,
      the relation between the LA volume and left ventricular (LV) filling pressure has not been
      confirmed directly by simultaneous echocardiographic catheterization. The present study,
      therefore, assessed the correlation between the LA volume and LV filling pressure in patients
      with severe mitral regurgitation (MR). Because the LA pressure increases to maintain adequate
      LV diastolic filling, increased atrial wall tension tends to dilate the chamber and stretch
      the atrial myocardium. Therefore, the lower the ability of the left atrium to stretch, the
      greater the pressure in the left atrium. The study is designed to assess 1) the relationship
      between LV filling pressure and LA distensibility, and 2) the power of left atrial
      distensibility to predict the prognosis, including operation mortality, the rate of
      post-operation atrial fibrillation, and late heart failure event in patients with severe
      mitral regurgitation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction LA volume provides the significantly prognostic information in the general
      population and patients with heart disease, including acute myocardial infarction, left
      ventricular dysfunction, mitral regurgitation, cardiomyopathy and atrial fibrillation. Large
      LA volume, which represents chronic diastolic dysfunction, is associated with poor outcome,
      regardless of systolic function. Thereby, LA volume provides a long-term view of whether or
      not the patient has the disease of diastolic dysfunction, regardless of whatever loading
      conditions are present at the time of the examination, as the hemoglobin A1C in diabetes
      mellitus. Until now, the relation between LA volume and LV filling pressure confirmed
      directly by simultaneous echocardiography-catheterization is sparse. This study therefore
      assessed the correlation between LA volume and LV filling pressure in patients with severe
      mitral regurgitation (MR). As LA pressure rises to maintain adequate LV diastolic filling,
      increased atrial wall tension tends to dilate the chamber and stretch the atrial myocardium.
      Therefore, the smaller LA stretchability, the more pressure LA faces. The study is designed
      to assess 1) the relationship between LV filling pressure and LA distensibility, and 2) the
      power of left atrial distensibility to predict the prognosis, including operation mortality,
      the rate of post-operation atrial fibrillation, and late heart failure event in patients with
      severe mitral regurgitation.

      Methods Study population: Between August 2010 and July 2012, this study will enroll 100
      severe MR patients who will receive cardiac catheterization for pre-operation evaluation.
      Exclusion criteria are the following: 1) presence of mitral stenosis, 2) more than mild
      severity of aortic valvular problem, 3) any abnormality of atrial septum (e.g., atrial septal
      defect or aneurysm), and 4) rhythm other than sinus rhythm. MR are categorized by mapping jet
      expansion in the LA in 4- and 2-chamber views at end systole from three separate cardiac
      cycles. MR is considered severe when regurgitant jet area occupies more than 40% of the LA
      area. The grade of MR is increased by one degree (moderate to severe) in cases of eccentric
      MR jet based on evidence of reduced color-flow jet areas due to loss of momentum in jets
      adjacent to chamber walls. Significant coronary lesion is defined as diameter stenosis &gt; 70%
      in at least one major coronary artery. The control group consisted of 50 other comorbid
      disease-, age- and gender-matched patients with negative results of coronary angiography,
      despite positive result of screen test for coronary artery disease (treadmill, Thallium scan,
      stress echocardiography, or 64-slides CT angiography), and they are selected after confirming
      no evidence of valvular heart disease by echocardiography. All patients and controls will
      give written informed consent to participate in the study, and the study is approved by the
      institutional review board.

      Cardiac catheterization: Coronary angiography will be performed to evaluate hemodynamic
      condition and to test for coronary artery disease. The LV filling pressure is continuously
      recorded (50 mm/s) by a 6-F pigtail catheter placed at the apex of the left ventricle and is
      taken from 3 to 5 end-respiratory cycles if patients can tolerate breath holding. The LV
      filling pressure value is calculated as the mean of at least 3 consecutive cardiac cycles. An
      LV filling pressure &gt; 15 mmHg is considered elevated.

      Conventional echocardiographic and myocardial tissue Doppler measurement: Echocardiography
      will be performed immediately after LV filling pressure measurements. LV ejection fraction is
      calculated using Simpson's method for biplane images. Mitral inflow is assessed by
      pulsed-wave Doppler echocardiography form the apical 4-chamber view. From the mitral inflow
      profile, the E-wave velocity, A-wave velocity, and E-deceleration time are measured.
      Pulsed-wave tissue Doppler imaging (TDI) is performed using spectral pulsed Doppler signal
      filters, by adjusting the Nyquist limit to 15 - 20 cm/s and using the minimum optimal gain.
      In the apical 4-chamber view, a 3-mm, a pulsed-wave Doppler sample volume is placed at the
      level of the mitral annulus over the septal border. Pulsed-wave TDI results are characterized
      by a myocardial systolic wave (S') and 2 diastolic waves: early (E') and atrial contraction
      (A'). The pulsed-wave TDI tracing is recorded over 5 cardiac cycles at a sweep speed of 100
      mm/s and is used for offline calculations.

      Measurements of LA volume: All LA volume measurements will be calculated from apical 4- and
      2-chamber views using the biplane area-length method (15). The LA volumes are measured at 3
      points: 1) immediately before the mitral valve opening (maximal LV volume or Volmax); 2) at
      onset of the P-wave on electrocardiography (pre-atrial contraction volume or Volp); and 3) at
      mitral valve closure (minimal LV volume or Volmin). The LA distensibility was calculated as
      (Volmax - Volmin) / Volmin. The LA ejection fraction is calculated as (Volp - Volmin) / Volp.
      In all patients, LA volumes are indexed to body surface area (BSA).

      Measurement of regurgitation volume: The apical window is used to record the pulsed-wave
      velocities at the LV outflow tract and at the mitral annulus and to measure the diameter of
      the mitral annulus. The time-velocity integral is assessed. The stroke volumes of mitral
      annulus and LV outflow tract are obtained by multiplying the cross-sectional area by the
      respective time-velocity integral. The MR regurgitation volume is calculated as Regurgitation
      volume = (stroke volume of mitral annulus) - (stroke volume of LV outflow tract).

      Follow up: All patients will receive mitral valve replacement later. The prevalence of
      operation mortality and post-OP atrial fibrillation will be assessed. Otherwise, patient will
      receive regular follow-up at our outpatient clinic for at least 1 year and any heart failure
      event necessary for hospitalization will be assessed by telephone interview, chart review or
      personal visit interview if needed. Those events, including operation mortality, post-OP
      atrial fibrillation and post-OP hospitalization for heart failure, will account for patients'
      prognosis.

      Interobserver variability: In the first 50 enrolled cases, Volmax, Volmin, and Volp will be
      measured by 2 independent observers. Interobserver variability is calculated as the
      difference between the values obtained by the 2 observers divided by the mean. Interobserver
      difference and variability of Volmax, Volmin, and Volp will be assessed.

      Statistical analysis: The SPSS software (version 12) will be used for all statistical
      analyses. All continuous variables are presented as means ± standard deviation. Analysis of
      variance and post hoc test (Scheffe F-test) for unpaired data are used to evaluate the
      significance of differences between groups. A p vale of &lt; 0.05 is considered statistically
      significant. Comparison of clinical characteristics is performed by chi-square analysis for
      categorical variables. Bivariate analysis, simple correlation and linear regression are used
      as appropriate. The relation curve between LA distensibility and LV filling pressure are
      estimated using SPSS software. ROC curve analysis is also performed to assess the sensitivity
      and specificity of the cut-off points of echocardiographic parameters when predicting
      elevated LV filling pressure (&gt; 15 mmHg), and the presence of the above-mentioned events. If
      LA distensibility is useful for predicting elevated LV filling pressure and major events,
      Kaplan-Meier curve will be performed to assess the cumulative event-free rate according to
      the cut-off point of LA distensibility estimated by ROC curve. The hazards ratios of clinical
      and echocardiographic parameters, including LA distensibility will be assessed by
      multivariate logistic analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Left Ventricular Filling Pressure More Than 15 mmHg Measured by Left Ventricular Catheterization</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Since left ventricular filling pressure more than 15 mmHg indicated poor ventricular compliance and more cardiovascular event in many prior reports, the current study used it as the threshold. Otherwise, the correlation between left ventricular filling pressure and left atrial distensibility was assessed. ROC curve was used to estimate the best cut-off point of left atrial distensibility for predicting left ventricular filling pressure more than 15 mmHg.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Post-operation Atrial Fibrillation</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>After operation, patients received continuous EKG monitor during the ICU stay. After transfer to ordinary ward, patients received 2 times of EKG record per day and another EKG would be done if patients felt palpitation and irregular heart beats were found by nursing staffs. The event of atrial fibrillation (Af) was defined as irregular irregular heart beats which was lack of p wave and last for more than 30 seconds. The relationship between left atrial distensibility and post-operative Af was analysed. ROC curve was used to assess the best cutoff value of left atrial distensibility.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Heart Failure Requiring Rehospitalization During Follow-up Period</measure>
    <time_frame>1-2 years</time_frame>
    <description>After discharge from index hospitalization of surgical intervention, heart failure with rehospitalization will be assessed. Heart failure with re-hospitalization was documented by at least one of the following: worse exercise tolerance and respiratory distress with NYHA class III or IV symptoms, presence of pulmonary rales, or chest radiography showing pulmonary congestion, which needed an augmented decongestive regimen during an in-hospital stay. The correlation between left atrial distensibility and heart failure was analyzed. ROC curve was used to estimate the best cut-off point.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">111</enrollment>
  <condition>Mitral Valve Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Severe mitral regurgitation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with severe mitral regurgitation are admitted for pre-operation cardiac catheterization and are willing to participate in this study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cardiac catheterization</intervention_name>
    <description>Before surgical intervention for severe mitral regurgitation, cardiac catheterization will be performed and left ventricular filling pressure will be assessed. Simultaneously, echocardiography, including left atrial distensibility, will be performed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Severe mitral regurgitation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with severe mitral regurgitation are admitted for surgical intervention and are
        willing to participate in this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with severe mitral regurgitation are admitted for surgical intervention and
             are willing to participate in this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of mitral stenosis

          -  More than mild severity of aortic valvular problem

          -  Any abnormality of atrial septum (e.g., atrial septal defect or aneurysm)

          -  Rhythm other than sinus rhythm

          -  Inadequate image quality

          -  Lack of informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jong-Khing Huang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Medical Education and Research Kaohsiung Veterans General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaohsiung Veterans General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kaohsiung</city>
        <zip>886</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moller JE, Hillis GS, Oh JK, Seward JB, Reeder GS, Wright RS, Park SW, Bailey KR, Pellikka PA. Left atrial volume: a powerful predictor of survival after acute myocardial infarction. Circulation. 2003 May 6;107(17):2207-12. Epub 2003 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>12695291</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beinart R, Boyko V, Schwammenthal E, Kuperstein R, Sagie A, Hod H, Matetzky S, Behar S, Eldar M, Feinberg MS. Long-term prognostic significance of left atrial volume in acute myocardial infarction. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2004 Jul 21;44(2):327-34.</citation>
    <PMID>15261927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meris A, Amigoni M, Uno H, Thune JJ, Verma A, Køber L, Bourgoun M, McMurray JJ, Velazquez EJ, Maggioni AP, Ghali J, Arnold JM, Zelenkofske S, Pfeffer MA, Solomon SD. Left atrial remodelling in patients with myocardial infarction complicated by heart failure, left ventricular dysfunction, or both: the VALIANT Echo study. Eur Heart J. 2009 Jan;30(1):56-65. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehn499. Epub 2008 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>19001474</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reed D, Abbott RD, Smucker ML, Kaul S. Prediction of outcome after mitral valve replacement in patients with symptomatic chronic mitral regurgitation. The importance of left atrial size. Circulation. 1991 Jul;84(1):23-34.</citation>
    <PMID>2060099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen CG, Thomas JD, Anconina J, Harrigan P, Mueller L, Picard MH, Levine RA, Weyman AE. Impact of impinging wall jet on color Doppler quantification of mitral regurgitation. Circulation. 1991 Aug;84(2):712-20.</citation>
    <PMID>1860216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Agricola E, Galderisi M, Oppizzi M, Melisurgo G, Airoldi F, Margonato A. Doppler tissue imaging: a reliable method for estimation of left ventricular filling pressure in patients with mitral regurgitation. Am Heart J. 2005 Sep;150(3):610-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16169349</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hsiao SH, Huang WC, Lin KL, Chiou KR, Kuo FY, Lin SK, Cheng CC. Left atrial distensibility and left ventricular filling pressure in acute versus chronic severe mitral regurgitation. Am J Cardiol. 2010 Mar 1;105(5):709-15. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2009.10.052.</citation>
    <PMID>20185021</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 28, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 28, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 29, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>March 3, 2011</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2011</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2011</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Jong-Khing Huang, MD, Current Superintendent of Kaohsiung Veterans General Hospital</name_title>
    <organization>Kaohsiung Veterans General Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Left atrial distensibility</keyword>
  <keyword>Left ventricular filling pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>Severe mitral regurgitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Prognosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Post-operation (mitral valve replacement or valvuloplasty) atrial fibrillation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitral Valve Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>The present study enrolled 111 patients with severe mitral regurgitation (MR) who had undergone cardiac catheterization in Kaohsiung veterans general hospital.</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Patients With Either Chronic or Acute Mitral Regurgitation</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="111"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="111"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Patients With Either Chronic or Acute Mitral Regurgitation</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="111"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="61"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="50"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="68" spread="18"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="56"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="55"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Taiwan</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="111"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Left Ventricular Filling Pressure More Than 15 mmHg Measured by Left Ventricular Catheterization</title>
        <description>Since left ventricular filling pressure more than 15 mmHg indicated poor ventricular compliance and more cardiovascular event in many prior reports, the current study used it as the threshold. Otherwise, the correlation between left ventricular filling pressure and left atrial distensibility was assessed. ROC curve was used to estimate the best cut-off point of left atrial distensibility for predicting left ventricular filling pressure more than 15 mmHg.</description>
        <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
        <population>Severe mitral regurgitation affects the accuracy of left ventricular filling pressure estimated by tissue Doppler imaging. Therefore, we conducted this study using left atrial parameters to assess left ventricular filling pressure in patients with severe mitral regurgitation.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Patients With Either Chronic or Acute Mitral Regurgitation</title>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Left Ventricular Filling Pressure More Than 15 mmHg Measured by Left Ventricular Catheterization</title>
          <description>Since left ventricular filling pressure more than 15 mmHg indicated poor ventricular compliance and more cardiovascular event in many prior reports, the current study used it as the threshold. Otherwise, the correlation between left ventricular filling pressure and left atrial distensibility was assessed. ROC curve was used to estimate the best cut-off point of left atrial distensibility for predicting left ventricular filling pressure more than 15 mmHg.</description>
          <population>Severe mitral regurgitation affects the accuracy of left ventricular filling pressure estimated by tissue Doppler imaging. Therefore, we conducted this study using left atrial parameters to assess left ventricular filling pressure in patients with severe mitral regurgitation.</population>
          <units>mmHg</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="111"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="25.5" spread="5.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants With Post-operation Atrial Fibrillation</title>
        <description>After operation, patients received continuous EKG monitor during the ICU stay. After transfer to ordinary ward, patients received 2 times of EKG record per day and another EKG would be done if patients felt palpitation and irregular heart beats were found by nursing staffs. The event of atrial fibrillation (Af) was defined as irregular irregular heart beats which was lack of p wave and last for more than 30 seconds. The relationship between left atrial distensibility and post-operative Af was analysed. ROC curve was used to assess the best cutoff value of left atrial distensibility.</description>
        <time_frame>baseline and 1 year</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Patients With Either Chronic or Acute Mitral Regurgitation</title>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants With Post-operation Atrial Fibrillation</title>
          <description>After operation, patients received continuous EKG monitor during the ICU stay. After transfer to ordinary ward, patients received 2 times of EKG record per day and another EKG would be done if patients felt palpitation and irregular heart beats were found by nursing staffs. The event of atrial fibrillation (Af) was defined as irregular irregular heart beats which was lack of p wave and last for more than 30 seconds. The relationship between left atrial distensibility and post-operative Af was analysed. ROC curve was used to assess the best cutoff value of left atrial distensibility.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="111"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="36"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants With Heart Failure Requiring Rehospitalization During Follow-up Period</title>
        <description>After discharge from index hospitalization of surgical intervention, heart failure with rehospitalization will be assessed. Heart failure with re-hospitalization was documented by at least one of the following: worse exercise tolerance and respiratory distress with NYHA class III or IV symptoms, presence of pulmonary rales, or chest radiography showing pulmonary congestion, which needed an augmented decongestive regimen during an in-hospital stay. The correlation between left atrial distensibility and heart failure was analyzed. ROC curve was used to estimate the best cut-off point.</description>
        <time_frame>1-2 years</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Patients With Either Chronic or Acute Mitral Regurgitation</title>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants With Heart Failure Requiring Rehospitalization During Follow-up Period</title>
          <description>After discharge from index hospitalization of surgical intervention, heart failure with rehospitalization will be assessed. Heart failure with re-hospitalization was documented by at least one of the following: worse exercise tolerance and respiratory distress with NYHA class III or IV symptoms, presence of pulmonary rales, or chest radiography showing pulmonary congestion, which needed an augmented decongestive regimen during an in-hospital stay. The correlation between left atrial distensibility and heart failure was analyzed. ROC curve was used to estimate the best cut-off point.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="111"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>All patients with severe mitral regurgitation received mitral valve replacement during index hospitalization. In-hospital mortality, and post-operative atrial fibrillation were recorded. The mean hospital course was 13 days.</time_frame>
      <desc>After discharge from index hospitalization, patients received regular follow-up for heart failure event requiring rehospitalization for 1 year.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Patients With Either Chronic or Acute Mitral Regurgitation</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="9" subjects_at_risk="111"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Heart failure requiring rehospitalizaion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="9" subjects_at_risk="111"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>2</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="111"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>minor bleeding event</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="111"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>LV filling pressure was obtained using fluid-filled pigtail catheters.Although micromanometer-tipped catheters would have been ideal, the method we used to measure LV filling pressure is standard in the clinical setting and is well validated.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Shih-Hung Hsiao</name_or_title>
      <organization>Kaohsiung veterans general hospital</organization>
      <phone>886-7-3422121 ext 1518</phone>
      <email>irb@vghks.gov.tw</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

