<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01179841</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NA_00006553</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01179841</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intervention for Toddlers at Risk for Autism Spectrum Disorders (ASD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comprehensive Approach to Intervention for Toddlers at Risk for ASD</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hugo W. Moser Research Institute at Kennedy Krieger, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Autism Speaks</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hugo W. Moser Research Institute at Kennedy Krieger, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research is being done to test the effectiveness of an early intervention model for very
      young children at high risk for autism spectrum disorders (ASD) and their families. If
      children show improvement in this intervention, the investigators hope that the availability
      of public services of this type will be increased. Children between 11 months and 21 months
      old with Autism Spectrum Disorders, or with social and communication delays that indicate
      high risk for Autism Spectrum Disorders, and their parents may join the study. Treatment must
      start prior to the second birthday.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Developmental Level</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months into treatment, 6 months into treatment, and 6 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Mullen Scales of Early Learning to assess.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Communication</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after treatment starts</time_frame>
    <description>Using Communication and Symbolic Behavior Scales to assess.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Communication</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months into treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Using Communication and Symbolic Behavior Scales to assess.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Communication</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>Using Communication and Symbolic Behavior Scales to assess.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence and Severity of Autism</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after treatment starts</time_frame>
    <description>Using Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule to assess.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence and Severity of Autism</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months into treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Using Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule to assess.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence and Severity of Autism</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>Using Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule to assess.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">49</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Playgroup and Parent Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One to two-hour individual therapeutic sessions with parent training in the home or clinic, 1x every week over six months;
parent training/enrichment once a week in our clinic for 20 sessions at 1-2 hours;
a playgroup session for 1-2 hours 2x week for 6 months in our clinic and
Community treatment as usual.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parent Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parent enrichment sessions once a week for 20 sessions (for 1-2 hours)
Community treatment as usual.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Playgroup</intervention_name>
    <description>The playgroup will be conducted at our center and focuses on providing an invigorating learning environment in which emerging skills/knowledge are skillfully brought to a higher level of maturity, integrated with existing abilities, and used functionally. Learning with and through peers, provides the opportunity to address abnormal peer relationships for developmental level. Providing an enriched environment with toys, structured learning, and opportunities for ongoing engagement we offer the children experiences that they would not otherwise have. Parent training sessions will focus on strategies aimed at improving child social engagement and communication. Parent education sessions will focus on topics related to autism, learning styles, interventions, and resources.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Playgroup and Parent Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Parent Training</intervention_name>
    <description>The 1-2 hour individual therapeutic sessions with parent training in the home or clinic (1x every week over six months) are based on our own program which is in development. This program focuses on teaching parents how to encourage social and communication skills in their toddlers and also provides comprehensive information about development. Sessions will focus on knowledge of autism, current access to services, general knowledge of strategies used to facilitate child development, advocacy, knowledge of how to access services, and coping strategies.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Playgroup and Parent Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Parent Training</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Enrichment Sessions</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Parent Training</intervention_name>
    <description>In the once-a-week 1 to 2 hour parent training/enrichment, we will ask parents to target specific play and care routines in which they may stimulate their child's development in the ways identified by the therapist. These stimulation times may be provided by the parents, other family members, friends, volunteers or hired assistants. Parents will be encouraged to have their child in direct skill-enhancing engagement for 1-2 hour per day. The therapist will work with the family to identify times during the day that best lend themselves to accomplishing this goal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Playgroup and Parent Training</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Individual Therapeutic Sessions</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children will be ascertained between 11 months and 21 months of age

          -  Must be able to enter the study prior to their second birthday

          -  Must then pass an eligibility assessment to determine whether the child meets criteria
             for ASD and thus qualifies for the study. This assessment will consist of the Baby
             ADOS and the Mullen Scales of Early Learning. Children must meet criteria for ASD or
             autism on the ADOS, score more than one standard deviation below the mean on the
             Receptive or Expressive Language scale of the MSEL, and have a clinical judgment of
             ASD to be eligible for enrollment into treatment.

          -  Parents must agree to participate in the study and commit to having their child
             participate in the intervention to which they are randomized for 6 months

          -  The parent (or other primary caregiver, such as grandparent) in the Parent
             Enrichment/Training condition must agree to attend the training sessions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Fail hearing or vision screening (by pediatrician's office, audiologist, or
             ophthalmologist)

          -  Family's first language being other than English (language measures are normed on
             English speakers, putting non-English speakers at a disadvantage. In addition, the
             treatment is delivered in English. Children from non-English speaking homes may not
             make progress, but for reasons other than the efficacy of the intervention.)

          -  Head injury (because this may cause some of the symptoms, which may not be due to
             autism and therefore we would not be able to assess the effects of the intervention on
             autism)

          -  Identified reason for the autism (e.g., fragile X syndrome, Rett syndrome, Tuberous
             Sclerosis)

          -  Inability of the family to attend the playgroup sessions and parent trainings

          -  Parents whose hearing or vision is not within normal limits after correction (e.g.,
             hearing aid, glasses)

          -  Parents with developmental delays, language or learning impairments, or a psychiatric
             diagnosis IF the impairment would interfere with parent training (PI will assess on a
             case by case basis by talking to the parent)

          -  Foster children

          -  Refusal to allow videotaping of the children's assessments or intervention or to allow
             videotaped footage to be used for teaching purposes.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rebecca Landa, PhD, CCC-SLP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hugo W. Moser Research Institute at Kennedy Krieger, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kennedy Krieger Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keen D, Rodger S, Doussin K, Braithwaite M. A pilot study of the effects of a social-pragmatic intervention on the communication and symbolic play of children with autism. Autism. 2007 Jan;11(1):63-71.</citation>
    <PMID>17175574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Solomon R, Necheles J, Ferch C, Bruckman D. Pilot study of a parent training program for young children with autism: the PLAY Project Home Consultation program. Autism. 2007 May;11(3):205-24.</citation>
    <PMID>17478575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howlin P, Gordon RK, Pasco G, Wade A, Charman T. The effectiveness of Picture Exchange Communication System (PECS) training for teachers of children with autism: a pragmatic, group randomised controlled trial. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2007 May;48(5):473-81.</citation>
    <PMID>17501728</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 21, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hugo W. Moser Research Institute at Kennedy Krieger, Inc.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rebecca Landa</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Autism Spectrum Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>language</keyword>
  <keyword>social</keyword>
  <keyword>toddlers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

