<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01175616</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00041936</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01175616</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Creatine Augmentation in Veterans With SSRI-Resistant Major Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Creatine Augmentation in Female &amp; Male Veterans With Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitor-Resistant Major Depressive Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether creatine will be helpful as an adjunctive
      treatment for treatment-resistant major depressive disorder (MDD) in female and male
      Veterans. We hypothesize that Veterans receiving creatine will show decreased depressive
      symptoms as measured by the Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS). We will also
      use 31-Phosphorus Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy (31-P MRS) brain scans to compare levels of
      neurochemicals related to energy metabolism in the brain, before-and-after treatment with
      creatine, and between healthy controls and MDD participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label clinical trial of the investigational drug creatine for augmentation
      treatment of female and male Veterans, ages 18-55, with Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) who
      have failed to respond to antidepressant treatment with a selective serotonin reuptake
      inhibitor (SSRI) drug. Based on converging preclinical and animal model research, and our
      laboratory's prior clinical trials, we hypothesize that the nutritional supplement creatine
      may provide benefit as an adjunctive treatment to SSRI pharmacotherapy, for Veterans with
      treatment-resistant depression.

      Twenty (n=20) Veterans between the ages of 18-55 years with MDD will be recruited for
      participation in an open-label trial of creatine augmentation. Veterans with depression will
      have unremitted MDD, despite having had an adequate trial of an SSRI antidepressant.
      Participants with MDD will be treated with oral creatine 5 gm daily for 8 weeks and will
      continue taking their SSRI antidepressant. Participants will undergo brain scanning at
      baseline, and the scans will be repeated following 8 of adjunctive creatine.

      The neuroimaging technique utilized is Phosphorus-31 Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy
      (31P-MRS). 31P-MRS is a non-invasive method with no exposure to ionizing radiation. At the
      magnetic field strength utilized (3 Tesla), magnetic resonance imaging is FDA-approved and is
      not associated with irreversible or serious adverse events. Furthermore, 31P-MRS is the only
      in vivo method for in vivo quantification of phosphorus energy metabolism, in living human
      brain.

      In addition to Veterans with MDD, twenty (n=20) healthy control (HC) participants will be
      recruited. HCs will be Veterans between the ages of 18-55, who have no history of psychiatric
      or substance use disorder. No treatment will be administered to HC participants.

      The HCs will undergo a single 31P-MRS scan, which will be used to measure the
      phosphorus-bearing neurometabolites that are involved in brain energy metabolism. The
      research team will use data from 31P-MRS scans to compare levels of high-energy phosphate
      metabolites in MDD participants vs. healthy controls.

      In addition, comparison of pre- and post-treatment 31P-MRS metabolite levels will be
      conducted in the MDD participants, to test the hypothesis that creatine augmentation improves
      brain energy metabolism.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study withdrawn from ClinicalTrials.gov.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>screening; baseline; weeks 1, 2, 4, 5, 8, and 10</time_frame>
    <description>The primary clinical outcome measure will be the change in MADRS; response will be defined as a 50% or greater decrease in MADRS score from baseline and a Clinical Global Impression Scale (CGI) improvement score of 1 or 2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in 3T 31Phosphorus Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy metabolites</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary neuroimaging outcome measures will be changes in 3T 31P-MRS metabolites (PCr and β-NTP) globally and in the anterior cingulate cortex</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Creatine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Open-Label Active Treatment with Creatine 5 grams daily for 8 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Creatine</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral Creatine 5 grams daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Creatine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Creapure</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria for Major Depressive Disorder Participants:

          -  Must be a U.S. military Veteran from 18-55 years of age.

          -  Must meet DSM criteria for Major Depressive Disorder (MDD).

          -  Current depressive episode duration of 4 weeks or longer.

          -  Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) score of 18 or greater.

          -  Adequate trial of an SSRI antidepressant, in terms of dosing and duration.

          -  No change in SSRI dose, for 4 weeks prior to the baseline brain scan.

          -  Partial or non-responder to current SSRI pharmacotherapy.

        Exclusion Criteria for Major Depressive Disorder Participants:

          -  Primary psychotic or schizophrenia-spectrum disorder.

          -  Unstable co-morbid medical, neurologic, or psychiatric illness.

          -  Clinically significant substance use disorder.

          -  Significant risk of suicide, in the clinical judgment of the study physician.

          -  Inability to provide informed consent.

          -  Contraindication to brain scanning (e.g., pacemaker, ferromagnetic implant).

          -  Pre-existing renal disease, with proteinuria at baseline.

          -  History of hypersensitivity to creatine.

          -  Concurrent participation in another FDA-sanctioned clinical trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Perry F Renshaw, MD, PhD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Utah</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.utahbrain.org</url>
    <description>Research Website - University of Utah Brain Instititue</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lyoo IK, Yoon S, Kim TS, Hwang J, Kim JE, Won W, Bae S, Renshaw PF. A randomized, double-blind placebo-controlled trial of oral creatine monohydrate augmentation for enhanced response to a selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor in women with major depressive disorder. Am J Psychiatry. 2012 Sep;169(9):937-945. doi: 10.1176/appi.ajp.2012.12010009.</citation>
    <PMID>22864465</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kondo DG, Sung YH, Hellem TL, Fiedler KK, Shi X, Jeong EK, Renshaw PF. Open-label adjunctive creatine for female adolescents with SSRI-resistant major depressive disorder: a 31-phosphorus magnetic resonance spectroscopy study. J Affect Disord. 2011 Dec;135(1-3):354-61. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2011.07.010. Epub 2011 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>21831448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen PJ, D'Anci KE, Kanarek RB, Renshaw PF. Sex-specific antidepressant effects of dietary creatine with and without sub-acute fluoxetine in rats. Pharmacol Biochem Behav. 2012 Jun;101(4):588-601. doi: 10.1016/j.pbb.2012.03.005. Epub 2012 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22429992</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen PJ. Creatine metabolism and psychiatric disorders: Does creatine supplementation have therapeutic value? Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2012 May;36(5):1442-62. doi: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2012.03.005. Epub 2012 Mar 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22465051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 3, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 4, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 11, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 11, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Utah</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Douglas Kondo, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Adults</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Serotonin Uptake Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The study was closed prior to human subjects receiving investigational treatment.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

