<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01178684</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SEARCH 014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01178684</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epidermal Nerve Fiber Density, Fat and Mitochondrial Parameters in Thai HIV+ Patients on d4T and HIV- Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of Epidermal Nerve Fiber Density, Subcutaneous Fat, and Mitochondrial Parameters in Thai HIV-positive Patients on Long-term Stavudine Treatment and in Thai HIV-negative Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>South East Asia Research Collaboration with Hawaii</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Hawaii</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>South East Asia Research Collaboration with Hawaii</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will provide the range of Epidermal Nerve Fiber Density (ENFD) typically seen in
      Thai individuals. ENFD values from Thai HIV-negative subjects without neuropathy will be used
      as appropriate reference norm for Thai HIV-positive subjects. In particular, comparison of
      ENFD values from Thai HIV-negative subjects with baseline ENFD values in Thai HIV-positive
      subjects prior to highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) will allow examination of the
      effect of HIV per se on ENFD. ENFD from Thai HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T
      (stavudine) with and without neuropathy will also provide reference ENFD values at the
      extremes of the disease process i.e. extent of ENFD decrease in subjects with d4T-induced
      symptomatic neuropathy and in subjects completely free of disease despite d4T treatment for
      comparison with Thai HIV-positive subjects on short-term d4T in SEARCH 003 study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The range of changes in epidermal nerve fiber density (ENFD), subcutaneous fat, and
      mitochondrial function induced by stavudine (d4T)-based therapy is currently not known,
      globally or specifically in the Thai population. This study will evaluate ENFD and
      subcutaneous fat and peripheral blood mitochondrial parameters in 4 groups of subjects. Group
      1 will include Thai HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T treatment with symptomatic
      peripheral neuropathy. Group 2 will include Thai HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T
      treatment without peripheral neuropathy. Group 3 will include HIV-negative subjects without
      peripheral neuropathy.Group 4 will include Thai HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T
      treatment with asymptomatic peripheral neuropathy. Information gained from Thai HIV-positive
      subjects on long-term d4T treatment with and without neuropathy in this study will provide
      range of positive control values for subjects in the SEARCH 003 study and other studies
      looking at the influence of antiretroviral agents on peripheral nerve, fat, and mitochondria.
      Information gained from Thai HIV-negative subjects without neuropathy can be used as negative
      control values for subjects in the SEARCH 003 study and other studies looking at the
      influence of HIV or other diseases/pathogens on peripheral nerve, fat, and mitochondria.

      Hypothesis

        1. HIV-positive patients who have been on long-term d4T treatment with symptomatic
           peripheral neuropathy will have less ENFD, increased lipoatrophy, and altered
           mitochondrial function than those on long-term d4T treatment with asymptomatic
           peripheral neuropathy and those on long-term d4T treatment without peripheral
           neuropathy.

        2. HIV-negative patients without peripheral neuropathy will have more ENFD, no lipoatrophy,
           and better mitochondrial function than HIV-positive patients.

      The SEARCH 003 study will assess the extent of deterioration in ENFD induced by short-term
      (from entry to 24 weeks) d4T use and the degree of improvement following discontinuation of
      d4T (from week 24 to 72). However the range of changes in ENFD and in other mitochondrial
      parameters induced by d4T-based therapy in not known, globally or specifically in the Thai
      population.

      This is a cross-sectional study that will enroll 25 HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T
      treatment with symptomatic peripheral neuropathy, 25 HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T
      treatment without peripheral neuropathy, 50 HIV-negative subjects without peripheral
      neuropathy and 25 HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T treatment with asymptomatic
      peripheral neuropathy for a one-time assessment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Crossover</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of nerves in the skin</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>To compare differences in ENFD between the 4 groups
group 1: HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T with symptomatic peripheral neuropathy
group 2: HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T without peripheral neuropathy
group 3: HIV-negative subjects without peripheral neuropathy
group 4: HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T with asymptomatic peripheral neuropathy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Condition of lipoatrophy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>To compare differences lipoatrophy between the 4 groups
group 1: HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T with symptomatic peripheral neuropathy
group 2: HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T without peripheral neuropathy
group 3: HIV-negative subjects without peripheral neuropathy
group 4: HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T with asymptomatic peripheral neuropathy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mitochondrial parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intracellular concentrations of d4T triphosphate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV DNA in peripheral blood mononuclear cell (PBMC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">113</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1: HIV-pos on d4T with neuropathy</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2: HIV-pos on d4T without neuropathy</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3: HIV-neg without peripheral neuropathy</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4 HIV-pos on d4T with asymtomatic neuropathy</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Plasma PBMC Urine CBC
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Seventy five HIV-positive patients on long-term d4T treatment (25 with symptomatic
        peripheral neuropathy, 25 without peripheral neuropathy and 25 with asymptomatic peripheral
        neuropathy) and 50 HIV-negative subjects without peripheral neuropathy will be recruited
        from the Thai Red Cross AIDS Research Centre and the Queen Savang Vadhana Memorial
        Hospital.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Group 1: HIV-positive subjects on long-term d4T with symptomatic peripheral neuropathy

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented HIV-1 infection

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old

          -  Has Thai national identification card

          -  Subject on d4T treatment with symptoms of neuropathy which developed after start of
             d4T therapy

          -  Evidence of symptomatic persistent symptoms of pain, tingling or numbness of lower
             extremities AND bilateral lower extremity neuropathy on exam at entry.

          -  Subject understands the study and is able to sign informed consent

          -  HIV RNA by PCR &lt; 50 copies/mL

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Treatment with concomitant medications (other than d4T) or having conditions (e.g.
             compressive neuropathy, diabetes, vitamin B12 deficiency, excessive alcohol intake
             meeting substance dependence criteria by DSM-IV, hepatitis C infection) known to cause
             neuropathy

          -  History of allergy to any anesthetic medications

          -  Pregnancy

        Group 2 subjects will meet the same criteria described above for group 1 subjects, but will
        NOT have symptoms OR signs of neuropathy.

        Group 3 subjects will meet the same criteria described above for group 1 subjects, but will
        NOT have symptoms OR signs of neuropathy and will have documented

        Group 4 subjects will meet the same criteria described above for group 1 subject, but will
        have evidence of symptomatic persistent symptoms of pain, tingling or numbness of lower
        extremities.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jintanat Ananworanich, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>South East Asia Research Collaboration with Hawaii</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thai Red Cross AIDS Research Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 9, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 10, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 25, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 25, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 26, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>South East Asia Research Collaboration with Hawaii</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Assoc.Prof.Jintanat Ananworanich, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assoc.Prof. Jintanat Ananworanich, MD,PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ENFD</keyword>
  <keyword>epidermal nerve fiber density</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-infection</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

