<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01178216</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Genentech-Ritux2010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01178216</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Immune Globulin Plus Rituximab for Desensitization in Highly HLA Sensitized Patients Awaiting Deceased Donor Kidney Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Use of Immune Globulin Intravenous (Human), 10% (IVIG), Plus Rituximab as Agents to Reduce Donor Specific Antibodies, Improve Transplant Rates and Outcomes in Highly-HLA Sensitized Patients Awaiting Deceased Donor Kidney Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanley Jordan, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This single center, Phase I/II, exploratory study has been modified to a safety/efficacy
      study providing all patients with IVIG and Rituximab. The trial will examine the safety and
      efficacy of human polyclonal IVIG 10%, when given at [2.0 gm/kgx2], + Rituximab 1gm to reduce
      donor-specific antibodies (DSA) to a level that is permissive for transplantation in 75
      subjects (adults only ages &gt;18 yrs) who are highly-HLA sensitized and are awaiting deceased
      donor kidney transplant. Once transplant offers are entertained, a donor-specific crossmatch
      will be performed. If acceptable crossmatches and DSA levels are seen, the patients will
      proceed to DD transplantation. Patients receiving transplants will receive an additional dose
      of IVIG at transplantation (within 10 days) and will receive additional doses of Rituximab 1g
      at 3M post transplant if DSA levels remain or become positive at 6M if de novo DSA occur.
      Patients who are desensitized and not transplanted at 9M after desensitization will have
      completed the study and can be treated as best judged by their physician.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Organ transplantation offers the only hope for a normal life for patients with end-stage
      renal disease on dialysis. For patients with antibodies to human leukocyte antigens (HLA),
      transplantation is extremely difficult or impossible since pre-formed antibodies will cause
      severe rejection and loss of transplanted organs. Intravenous gamma globulin (IVIG) can
      reduce or eliminate these antibodies in most patients and allow for successful
      transplantation. This breakthrough has allowed patients previously considered not
      transplantable to receive life-saving transplants. However, IVIG alone does not always
      eradicate the anti-HLA antibodies to a degree that will allow transplantation.

      In this study, the investigators propose additional treatment with rituximab, a humanized
      antibody directed at the CD20 antigen that is present on most B-cells. Both IVIG and
      rituximab are approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for numerous
      immunologic disorders and Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma, respectively. However, neither is approved
      by the FDA for desensitization of highly-HLA sensitized transplant patients. A previously
      conducted pilot study demonstrated IVIG + Rituximab can fill an important gap in the current
      therapeutic approach for management of highly sensitized patients and may become the standard
      therapy.

      Update: Study updated after observation that subjects transplanted after desensitization with
      IVIG alone experienced higher rates of antibody rejection and graft loss. The primary
      objective of this revised protocol will be to examine the safety and efficacy of IVIG 2gm/kg
      (maximum 140g) given on day#0 &amp; day #30 plus Rituximab 1gm given on day #15. Transplanted
      patients will receive additional doses of Rituximab 1gm at 3 months post-transplant if donor
      specific antibody (DSA) levels remain or become positive or at 6M if de novo DSA occur. All
      transplanted patients who remain DSA negative, will not receive additional Rituximab. All
      transplanted patients will have a protocol biopsy at transplant and 12 months. All subjects
      will complete 5 visits in the pre-transplant phase of the study. Patients who are
      transplanted will have additional 5 post-transplant visits. The following are
      research-related procedures:

        1. Rituximab infusion.

        2. Kidney allograft biopsies (Intra-op, 12 months post-transplant)

        3. Rituximab level, HACA levels

        4. Immunologic biomarkers (CD19+, CD38+, CD27+)

      Although the investigator commonly uses both treatment regimens at Cedars-Sinai Medical
      Center, only the IVIG treatment is considered to be standard of care for highly
      HLA-sensitized patients. The investigational component of this study is the addition of the
      rituximab. Currently the study has been amended to a safety and efficacy study focusing on
      decreasing HLA antibodies pre-transplant and minimizing DSA post-transplant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 28, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 28, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of transplantation</measure>
    <time_frame>9 month</time_frame>
    <description>This trial is designed to determine if Rituximab + IVIG can improve rates of transplantation for highly-HLA sensitized DD candidates on the UNOS waiting list over a 9M period of time after completion of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal allograft survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Graft survival in study participants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in anti-HLA antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Antibody measurements at multiple time points</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of acute rejection episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of rejection episodes in study participants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of serious infections</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Infection rate in study participants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events, toxicity assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse effects in study participants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">41</enrollment>
  <condition>End Stage Renal Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rituxan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All study patients will receive Rituxan 1g on day 15 from start of desensitization and either 3M or 6M post transplant depending on the presence of DSA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituxan</intervention_name>
    <description>Rituximab (1gm) given on day# 15. Transplanted patients will receive an additional dose of Rituximab at 3M if DSA remains or 6M if denovo DSA present.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rituxan</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rituximab</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. End-stage renal disease.

          2. No known contraindications for therapy with IGIV10%/Rituximab.

          3. Age 18-70 years at the time of screening.

          4. PRA&gt; 30% demonstrated on 3 consecutive samples, UNOS wait time sufficient to allow DD
             offers, history of sensitizing events, positive crossmatch with the intended donor.

          5. Subject/Parent/Guardian must be able to understand and provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Lactating or pregnant females.

          2. Pediatric patients &lt;18 years of age

          3. Women of child-bearing age who are not willing or able to practice FDA-approved forms
             of contraception.

          4. HIV-positive subjects.

          5. Subjects who test positive for HBV infection [positive HBVsAg, HBVcAg, or HBVeAg/DNA]
             or HCV infection [positive Anti-HCV (EIA) and confirmatory HCV RIBA].

          6. Subjects with active TB.

          7. Subjects with selective IgA deficiency, those who have known anti-IgA antibodies, and
             those with a history of anaphylaxis or severe systemic responses to any part of the
             clinical trial material.

          8. Subjects who have received or for whom multiple organ transplants are planned.

          9. Recent recipients of any licensed or investigational live attenuated vaccine(s) within
             two months of the screening visit (including but not limited to any of the following:

               -  Adenovirus [Adenovirus vaccine live oral type 7]

               -  Varicella [Varivax]

               -  Hepatitis A [VAQTA]

               -  Rotavirus [Rotashield]

               -  Yellow fever [Y-F-Vax]

               -  Measles and mumps [Measles and mumps virus vaccine live]

               -  Measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine [M-M-R-II]

               -  Sabin oral polio vaccine

               -  Rabies vaccines [IMOVAX Rabies I.D., RabAvert])

         10. A significantly abnormal general serum screening lab result defined as a WBC &lt; 3.0 X
             103/ml, a Hgb &lt; 8.0 g/dL, a platelet count &lt; 100 X 103/ml, , an SGOT &gt; 5X upper limit
             of normal, and an SGPT &gt;5X upper limit of normal range.

         11. Individuals deemed unable to comply with the protocol.

         12. Subjects with active CMV or EBV infection as defined by CMV-specific serology (IgG or
             IgM) and confirmed by quantitative PCR with or without a compatible illness.

         13. Subjects with a known history of previous myocardial infarction within one year of
             screening.

         14. Subjects with a history of clinically significant thrombotic episodes, and subjects
             with active peripheral vascular disease.

         15. Use of investigational agents within 4 weeks of participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stanley Jordan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cedars-sinai.edu/Patients/Quality-Measures/Clinical-Areas/Transplantation/Kidney-Transplantation.aspx</url>
    <description>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center Kidney Transplant Website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jordan SC, Peng A, Vo AA. Therapeutic strategies in management of the highly HLA-sensitized and ABO-incompatible transplant recipients. Contrib Nephrol. 2009;162:13-26. doi: 10.1159/000170864. Epub 2008 Oct 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19001810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vo AA, Lukovsky M, Toyoda M, Wang J, Reinsmoen NL, Lai CH, Peng A, Villicana R, Jordan SC. Rituximab and intravenous immune globulin for desensitization during renal transplantation. N Engl J Med. 2008 Jul 17;359(3):242-51. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0707894.</citation>
    <PMID>18635429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 9, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 9, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 10, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stanley Jordan, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Director, Medical Director, Renal Transplantation &amp; Transplant Immunotherpay</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kidney transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>highly sensitized</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>gamma-Globulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins, Intravenous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rho(D) Immune Globulin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

