<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01170650</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8109-002</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>EC-FV-06</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01170650</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study for Women With Platinum Resistant Ovarian Cancer Evaluating EC145 in Combination With Doxil® (PROCEED)</brief_title>
  <acronym>PROCEED</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Double-Blind Phase 3 Trial Comparing EC145 and Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (PLD/Doxil®/Caelyx®) in Combination Versus PLD in Participants With Platinum-Resistant Ovarian Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Endocyte</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Endocyte</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare progression-free survival (PFS) (based upon
      investigator assessment using RECIST v1.1) in participants with platinum-resistant ovarian
      cancer who receive combination therapy with EC145 and pegylated liposomal doxorubicin
      (EC145+PLD) with that in participants who receive PLD and placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 3 clinical trial to evaluate the efficacy and safety of the combination of
      EC145 and pegylated liposomal doxorubicin (PLD; available in the United States as Doxil® and
      outside the United States as Caelyx®) compared to PLD and placebo. Enrollment of 640 patients
      including approximately 500 that are folate receptor positive is planned.

      EC145 is a drug that is specifically designed to enter cancer cells via the folate vitamin
      receptor (FR) that is not generally found on normal cells. Experimental evidence shows that
      this target receptor is expressed on virtually all ovarian cancers. Early clinical evidence
      in a small number of Phase I participants, in a subset of participants in a completed
      single-arm Phase II study, and interim data from an ongoing randomized Phase 2 study
      (PRECEDENT) suggests that EC145 may have antitumor effect in women with platinum-resistant
      ovarian cancer and that EC145 alone and in combination with PLD is generally well-tolerated.
      This evidence suggests that EC145 may be useful as chemotherapy against platinum-resistant
      ovarian cancer.

      All participants will undergo imaging with the FR-targeting investigational diagnostic agent
      EC20 during the screening period to assess binding of the imaging agent EC20 to tumors. This
      non-invasive procedure will provide additional information on the utility of using EC20
      imaging to identify subjects with the FR molecular &quot;target&quot; prior to treatment with EC145
      therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    DSMB decision
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival based on investigator assessment using RECIST v1.1.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 26 months</time_frame>
    <description>Progression is assessed at 6 week intervals through Week 24 and at 8 week intervals thereafter.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare overall survival of participants between treatment arms.</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 20 months after last patient randomized</time_frame>
    <description>OS analysis will occur when 384 deaths have occurred.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Adverse Events, Serious Adverse Events, and Deaths.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 26 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events (as a measure of safety and tolerability) will be assessed at each study visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">640</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>EC145 + Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (PLD)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo + Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (PLD)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EC145</intervention_name>
    <description>IV bolus on days 1,3,5 and 15,17,19 of a 4-week cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (PLD/Doxil®/Caelyx®)</intervention_name>
    <description>50 mg/m2 (calculated on the basis of ideal body weight) every 4 weeks. Dose reductions permitted for toxicity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Doxil</other_name>
    <other_name>Caelyx</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>IV bolus on days 1,3,5 and 15,17,19 of a 4-week cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EC20</intervention_name>
    <description>During the screening period participants will receive a single intravenous administration of EC20 prior to SPECT imaging</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must sign an approved informed consent form (ICF).

          -  Participants must be ≥ 18 years of age.

          -  Participants must have pathology-confirmed epithelial ovarian, fallopian tube, or
             primary peritoneal carcinoma.

          -  Participants must have primary or secondary platinum-resistant ovarian cancer.

          -  Participants must have at least a single (RECIST v1.1-defined) measurable lesion.

          -  For the purpose of obtaining a RECIST v1.1 baseline scan, participants must have a
             radiological evaluation conducted no more than 28 days prior to beginning study
             therapy (PLD). NOTE: For participants with a history of CNS metastasis, baseline
             radiological imaging must include an evaluation of the head.

          -  Participants must have had prior debulking surgery.

          -  Participants must have received prior platinum-based chemotherapy for management of
             primary disease but must not have received more than 2 prior systemic cytotoxic
             regimens.

          -  Participants are allowed to have received, but are not required to have received, one
             additional non-cytotoxic antitumor agent (eg, biologic or cytostatic) for the
             management of ovarian cancer.

          -  Participants must have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status
             of 0 to 1.

          -  Participants must have recovered (to baseline/stabilization) from prior cytotoxic
             therapy-associated acute toxicities.

          -  Participants must have adequate organ function including:

               1. Bone Marrow Reserve:

                    1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5x10^9/L prior to treatment.
                       Participants on maintenance doses of granulocyte colony stimulating factor
                       (G-CSF) are eligible.

                    2. Platelets ≥ 100x10^9/L

                    3. Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL

                    4. Use of supportive care measures (eg, use of white blood cell [WBC] growth
                       factors, antiemetics, epoetin) should follow the ASCO guidelines as listed
                       at www.asco.org. Participants should receive full supportive care, including
                       transfusion of blood as mandated by clinical need; however, transfusions
                       administered for the sole purpose of meeting the study inclusion criteria
                       between the time informed consent is signed and first dose of
                       EC145/placebo/PLD is administered are not allowed.

               2. Hepatic: Total bilirubin level &lt; 1.5 x ULN and ALT, AST, GGT, and alkaline
                  phosphatase levels &lt; 2.5 x ULN.

               3. Renal: Serum creatinine level ≤ 1.5 x ULN or for participants with serum
                  creatinine levels above 1.5 x ULN, creatinine clearance ≥ 50 mL/min/1.73m^2

               4. Cardiac: Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) equal to or greater than the
                  institutional lower limit of normal.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients refractory to primary platinum therapy where &quot;refactory&quot; is defined as
             disease progression within 6 months of first dose of initial platinum-based therapy.

          -  Diagnosis of &quot;tumor of low-malignant potential&quot;.

          -  Prior exposure to PLD or anthracycline therapy.

          -  Prior exposure to FR-targeted therapy (eg, EC145, EC0225, EC0489, farletuzumab).

          -  Prior therapy with vinorelbine (Navelbine®) or vinca-containing compounds.

          -  Prior abdominal or pelvic radiation therapy or radiation therapy to &gt; 10% of the bone
             marrow at any time in the past or prior radiation therapy within the past 3 years to
             the breast/sternum, dermal lesions, head or neck.

          -  Recent (i.e., ≤ 6 weeks) history of abdominal surgery or peritonitis

          -  Serious comorbidities (as determined by the investigator) such as, but not limited to,
             active congestive heart failure or recent myocardial infarction. Patients who require
             antifolate therapy for the management of comorbid conditions (e.g., rheumatoid
             arthritis) will be excluded from the trial.

          -  Pregnant or nursing.

          -  Concurrent malignancy requiring therapy (excluding non-invasive carcinoma or carcinoma
             in situ).

          -  Symptomatic central nervous system (CNS) metastasis.

          -  Other concurrent chemotherapy, immunotherapy, radiotherapy, or any ancillary therapy
             that is considered to be investigational (i.e., used for non-approved indications(s)
             and in the context of a research investigation). Use of low dose corticosteroid
             therapy (e.g., for nausea prophylaxis) is acceptable; however, concomitant tamoxifen
             therapy is not. Supportive care measures are allowed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Binh Nguyen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Endocyte</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.endocyte.com</url>
    <description>Endocyte website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 7, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 27, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 3, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 3, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 4, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>ovarian</keyword>
  <keyword>platinum-resistant</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase III</keyword>
  <keyword>EC145</keyword>
  <keyword>EC20</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposomal doxorubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

