<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02571491</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FSJD-ESCOKETA-2010</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2011-000407-41</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02571491</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of the Efficacy of Ketamine in Pediatric Patients With Idiopathic Scoliosis After Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of the Analgesic Efficacy and Tolerability of the Perioperative Association of the Ketamine With Opiates After Posterior Vertebral Fusion Surgery in Children With Idiopathic Scoliosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundació Sant Joan de Déu</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto de Salud Carlos III</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundació Sant Joan de Déu</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Comparison of the Efficacy of ketamine measuring the total consumption of morphine in
      pediatric patients with idiopathic scoliosis
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A randomized unicenter clinical trial, parallel, double-blind study, placebo-controlled
      group.

      Involve the participation of Pediatric patients, aged between 11 and 18 years, of both
      genders, diagnosed with idiopathic scoliosis and posterior spinal fusion surgery candidates
      included in the Anesthesia Physical Classification System (ASA) 1 or 2 classes.

      Both groups received remifentanil at doses of 0.3 mcg / Kg / min before surgical procedure
      and a bolus of 150 mcg / Kg of morphine hydrochloride, approximately 60 minutes before
      extubation, followed by PCA morphine hydrochloride administration.

      The patients in the experimental group are treated with a combination of ketamine,
      remifentanil hydrochloride and morphine while the control group will be treated with a
      combination of saline, remifentanil and morphine hydrochloride.

      Treatment of patients in the study is initiated during the induction of anesthesia and ends
      at the hospital discharge.

      The total duration of patient participation in the study is 6 months. During treatment the
      patients being admitted are monitored at regular intervals, at week 6, after the 3rd month
      and at 6 months post-intervention to assess the incidence of chronic pain.

      The entire study duration is approximately 24 months. The hypothesis of the study is that the
      combination of subanesthetic doses of ketamine to opioid drugs during the perioperative
      period reduces central sensitization processes, resulting in lower consumption of
      postoperative morphine with fewer adverse effects, postoperative faster recovery and less
      incidence of chronic pain.

      The post-operative analgesia is induced by the use of opioids or other analgesics associated
      with loco-regional techniques. The technique used in the investigators' center is the
      patient-controlled analgesia (PCA) with the administration of intravenous opioids.

      The association of ketamine to opioid treatment could reduce the consumption of these and can
      be useful in surgery. No clinical trials have been conducted in children with scoliosis, who
      underwent posterior lumbar fusion surgical procedure, evaluating the efficacy of
      post-operative association of ketamine to opioid drugs for both intra and post-operative
      periods.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative Consumption of Epidural Morphine at 72h Postoperatively</measure>
    <time_frame>in the first 72 hours postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>For the assessment of the related ketamine analgesic efficacy. Cumulative consumption of epidural morphine administered as loading dose, intraoperatively, of 0,3 mcg/kg/min until the surgery operation and 150mcg/Kg of Morphine hydrochloride 60min before extubation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Pain Scores (Visual Analogue Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>in the first 72 hours after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Pain scores at rest and on cough using a 10cm Visual Analogue Scale(0=no pain, 10=worst possible pain for the analgesic efficacy assessment of the association of Ketamine and opiates</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of significant adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>every 4 hours from the begin until the end of the surgical operation</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the tolerability of the association of ketamine and opiates</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to oral tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months from the end of the surgical operation</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the efficacy of the association of ketamine and opiates, measuring the time needed from the surgery for reaching the oral tolerability</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to First Postoperative Ambulation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months from the end of the surgical operation</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the efficacy of the association of ketamine and opiates, measuring the time needed to being able to walk without assistance within the room or outside the room</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to postoperative recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months from the end of the surgical operation</time_frame>
    <description>Post operation period needed for each patient from the end of the surgery until hospital discharge by counting each patient postoperative hospital night admissions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Pain by sensorial test using the Voy Frey filament</measure>
    <time_frame>in the first 72 hours post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>measure of the area of hyperalgesia of the inflamed skin and the length of the incision after 72 post surgery. The filaments is used to provide a range of forces to the skin of a test subject, in order to find the force at which the subject reacts because the sensation is painful.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Pain Scores (Visual Analogue Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 6 and after 3 and 6 months post surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of pain at week 6 and chronic pain after 3 and 6 months post-surgery using the Visual Analogue Scale pain scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in neuropathic pain using Douleur Neuropathique en 4 Questions (DN4) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 6 and after 3 and 6 months post surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>The (DN4) questionnaire is a screening tool for neuropathic pain consisting of interview questions (DN4-interview) and physical tests. Two questions (I and II) were based on the interview of the patient and two questions (III and IV) were based on a standardized clinical examination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Progressive Infantile Idiopathic Scoliosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine Hydrochloride</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Received a combination of ketamine, remifentanil and morphine hydrochloride established by the following dosage regimen:
KETAMINE HYDROCHLORIDE 0,5mg/Kg Intravenous bolus administered during the anesthetic induction, followed by 2 mcg / Kg / min of intravenous infusion during and after surgery until 72 hours postoperation
during surgery remifentanil 0,3 mcg / kg / min.
at the end of the operation morphine hydrochloride150 mcg / kg, PCA infusion postoperatively.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Received a combination of physiological serum, remifentanil and morphine hydrochloride established by the following dosage regimen:
0,9 % physiological serum 0,5mg/Kg administered by an intravenous (IV) line during the anesthetic induction, followed by 2 mcg / Kg / min of intravenous infusion during and after surgery until 72 hours postoperation
during surgery remifentanil 0.3 mcg / kg / min.
at the end of the operation morphine hydrochloride150 mcg / kg, PCA infusion postoperatively.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>50 mg/ml, IV (in the vein) during surgery operation, followed by IV ketamine hydrocloride perfusion 2mcg/Kg/min before and until 72 hours after operation Number of Cycles: until progression or unacceptable toxicity develops.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine Hydrochloride</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>KETOLAR 50 mg/ml</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>50 mg/ml, IV (in the vein) during surgery operation, followed by IV placebo perfusion 2mcg/Kg/min before and until 72 hours after operation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>0,9 % physiological serum</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Remifentanil</intervention_name>
    <description>at doses of 0.3 mcg / kg / min during and until the end of the surgical operation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine Hydrochloride</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Morphine hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>at the dose of 150 mcg / kg, 60 minutes before the extubation procedure and until 72 hours after operation by intravenous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine Hydrochloride</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients of both genders diagnosed with idiopathic scoliosis aged between 8 and 18
             years old.

          2. Patients of both genders diagnosed with idiopathic scoliosis and candidates for
             vertebral fusion corrective surgery with instrumentation.

          3. Patients with ASA 1 or ASA 2.

          4. Patients and/or parents/tutors consent to participate in the clinical trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with chronic preoperative pain.

          2. Patients with addiction to narcotics.

          3. Patients with a history of allergy, contraindication or intolerance to the drugs used.

          4. Patients unable to understand the patient-controlled analgesia system.

          5. Patients with mental disorders.

          6. Reoperated patients.

          7. Patients requiring elective postoperative ventilation.

          8. Pregnant patients.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marina Perelló Riera, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Sant Joan de Déu Servicio de Anestesiología, Reanimación y Tratamiento del Dolor</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Sant Joan de Déu</name>
      <address>
        <city>Esplugues de Llobregat</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08950</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mao J. Opioid-induced abnormal pain sensitivity: implications in clinical opioid therapy. Pain. 2002 Dec;100(3):213-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12467992</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woolf CJ, Salter MW. Neuronal plasticity: increasing the gain in pain. Science. 2000 Jun 9;288(5472):1765-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10846153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Angst MS, Koppert W, Pahl I, Clark DJ, Schmelz M. Short-term infusion of the mu-opioid agonist remifentanil in humans causes hyperalgesia during withdrawal. Pain. 2003 Nov;106(1-2):49-57.</citation>
    <PMID>14581110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmid RL, Sandler AN, Katz J. Use and efficacy of low-dose ketamine in the management of acute postoperative pain: a review of current techniques and outcomes. Pain. 1999 Aug;82(2):111-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10467917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 8, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 7, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 7, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 8, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Scoliosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Morphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Remifentanil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>December 9, 2015</submitted>
    <returned>January 19, 2016</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

