<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02577120</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015H0116</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>RFA-NR-15-001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02577120</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Wound Healing Endpoint and Recurrence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Wound Healing Endpoint and Recurrence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This prospective pilot study is to enroll patients with clinically-defined infected wounds.
      Patients enrolled in the study will be followed for 16 weeks for wound closure (Phase A), and
      will then begin Phase B. 265 clinically diagnosed infected burn or chronic wound patients
      will be recruited for this study in Phase A. Based on the expectation that 89% of these
      wounds will heal within 16 weeks of enrollment, 234 of these patients will continue with the
      study for Phase B.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This prospective pilot study is to enroll patients with clinically-defined infected wounds.
      Patients enrolled in the study will be followed for 16 weeks for wound closure (Phase A), and
      will then begin Phase B. Wounds will be subjected to Standard of Care (SoC) followed by all
      Comprehensive Wound Center (CWC) wound physicians in the first 16 weeks. Trans - Epidermal
      Water Loss (TEWL) will be measured with a handheld, non-invasive device, the VapoMeter®
      Closed-Chambered device or using DermaLab TEWL probe. Both of these devices are used to read
      the device. They will be placed on the subjects skin and will read the TEWL measurement. When
      the device is placed on the skin, the measurement takes between 7-20 seconds with the
      standard adapter. Study visit 1 will include informed consent being signed, baseline
      information collected, 2 biopsies will be collected unless the wound is not appropriate for
      biopsy or the patient chooses not to receive a biopsy then a swab for culture will be
      collected, wound image, and a quality of life survey will be completed by the subject. The
      patients medical chart will be followed for 16 weeks following visit 1. At 16 weeks (+/- 1
      week) or within 10 days of wound closure whichever comes first, all subjects will return for
      study visit 2. If the target wound(s) is not yet healed at this visit, this visit will be
      part of their Standard of Care visit per the CWC. The patient's study participation will end
      at this visit but wound data will be collected, digital imaging of wound(s) and quality of
      life survey will be completed by the subject. If the target wound is determined by visual
      inspection to be healed at or prior to this visit, this will be a research only visit; the
      patient will continue to Phase B. Phase B is a continuation of study visit 2. Various
      information will be collected on the data collection sheet, digital imaging and TEWL
      measurements will be recorded. The TEWL device will be placed on the skin. There will be 5
      measurements obtained over the closed wound site. A reference (control) TEWL measurement will
      be taken from intact skin at an anatomically matched site on the patient. A high TEWL/
      defective closure is defined as a TEWL value =2 times the value of the patient's control
      measurement. Patients who meet this criterion will be randomized to one of four groups:
      EpiCeram treatment, Ceramiseal treatment, Vaseline treatment or no treatment. Patients
      randomized to a treatment group will be supplied with study product and will be instructed to
      apply twice daily to the closed wound site for the remaining weeks of the study. All High
      TEWL patients will be asked to return for Study Visits 3-6. Distribution of study product as
      applicable. For this study, a low TEWL/ adequate closure is defined as a value less than 2
      times the value of the patient's control measurement. Patients who meet this criterion will
      not be randomized into a treatment group, but will continue to receive standard of care per
      their physician and will be asked to return for study visits 3, 4, and 6. During these last
      visits the following activities will occur: TEWL measurements, digital imaging, sequential
      tape stripping to measure ceramide levels in the skin (up to 20 tape strips obtained). TEWL
      measurements will be obtained prior to tape stripping. The tape strips be completed after the
      TEWL measurements are obtained, wound site evaluation, various labs, medications review,
      distribution of study product (High TEWL only) and review of compliance and a quality of life
      survey is completed by the subject(visit 6 only). There may be some discomfort with the
      tissue biopsy procedure depending on the amount of sensation the subject has at the site of
      the wound and will be numbed by applying local anesthesia as appropriate to area being
      biopsied. The amount of pain that occurs with wound biopsies will vary from person to person,
      but all efforts will be made to minimize pain and is within the boundaries of the existing
      wound to avoid giving the patient a separate new wound. Bleeding is a possible complication,
      but the risk is low for the small biopsies and is reduced by using local anesthetics with
      epinephrine, and silver nitrate sticks are available in each patient room to cauterize biopsy
      sites as needed. Infection is also a potential risk; however, wound tissue biopsies are
      routinely performed as the standard of care in the CWC to diagnose wound infection. The
      biopsy site will be appropriately monitored for infection by the physician managing the wound
      during routine wound clinic visits.Possible risks for the use of the ceramide emulsion
      EpiCeram® are a temporary tingling sensation (10-15 minutes) and an extremely low risk of an
      allergic reaction. If this occurs the application of the cream will be stopped immediately.
      Possible risks for the use of Vaseline Petroleum and Ceramiseal™ are very low should be
      stopped if an allergic reaction occurs.There can be some minor redness and discomfort at the
      site of the tape stripping. The skin remains intact, i.e. the epidermis is not breached after
      the tape stripping procedure making this less than minimal risk. TEWL measurements are
      noninvasive and propose less than minimal risk.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biofilm Infection effects to TEWL at wound sites</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>If a history of wound biofilm infection results in elevated TEWL at wound sites that appear closed, defectively closed wounds featuring high TEWL show higher &quot;recurrence rate&quot; than functionally closed wounds with low TEWL. This will be identified by how many subjects with a high TEWL reading and biofilm infection, have recurrence of their wound versus subjects with a low TEWL reading.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ceramiseal and EpiCeram restore barrier function to wounds in patients</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>If topical application of the Ceramiseal™ or the FDA approved EpiCeram® restores barrier function to defectively closed wounds. These will be compared to a Placebo cream, Vaseline and will be seen after 3 months of application to the wound site.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>5</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">265</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Wound</condition>
  <condition>Burn Wound</condition>
  <condition>Diabetic Foot Ulcers</condition>
  <condition>Pressure Ulcers</condition>
  <condition>Venous Leg Ulcers</condition>
  <condition>Chronic</condition>
  <condition>Wound</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low TEWL</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects will have the TEWL reading completed at the wound site and a control site (anatomically matched site on the patients contralateral side) at the second study visit. If the wound site reading is less than 3 times the value of the control site subjects will be be discontinued from the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High TEWL - No treatment</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects will have the TEWL reading completed at the wound site and a control site (anatomically matched site on the patients contralateral side) at the second study visit. If the wound site reading is less than 3 times the value of the control site subjects</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High TEWL - Epiceram skin barrier function</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects will have the TEWL reading completed at the wound site and a control site (anatomically matched site on the patients contralateral side) at the second study visit. If the wound site reading is less than 3 times the value of the control site subjects</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High TEWL - Ceramiseal</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects will have the TEWL reading completed at the wound site and a control site (anatomically matched site on the patients contralateral side) at the second study visit. If the wound site reading is less than 3 times the value of the control site</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High TEWL - Vaseline Petroleum Jelly</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects will have the TEWL reading completed at the wound site and a control site (anatomically matched site on the patients contralateral side) at the second study visit. If the wound site reading is less than 3 times the value of the control site subjects</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epiceram Skin Barrier Function</intervention_name>
    <description>Epiceram is a non-sterile, viscous, lipid-rich emulsion</description>
    <arm_group_label>High TEWL - Epiceram skin barrier function</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Epiceram</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vaseline Petroleum Jelly</intervention_name>
    <description>A skin protectant used for temporarily protecting minor cuts, scraps, burns, and helps to protect and help relieve chapped or cracked skin and lips.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High TEWL - Vaseline Petroleum Jelly</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Petroleum</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ceramiseal</intervention_name>
    <description>Topical serum designed to fortify delicate skin with essential lipids. The proprietary blend of naturally occurring lipids contained in Ceramiseal are designed to improve the barrier function of your skin's outer layer; thereby restoring critical moisture balance and improving physical appearance and function.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High TEWL - Ceramiseal</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Skin Barrier Function</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Tissue
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        265 clinically diagnosed infected burn or chronic wound patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18

          -  Willing to comply with protocol instructions, including all biopsies, study visits and
             study activities.

          -  One of the following:

               1. Chronic wound of multiple etiologies and open for at least 30 days, including:

                    1. Diabetic foot ulcers, Wagner grade 1-3

                    2. Pressure ulcers, stage 2-3

                    3. Venous leg ulcers, confirmed by venous duplex

                    4. Burn wounds open

                    5. Clinical contraindication to biopsy in the opinion of the wound care
                       physician

               2. Wounds not appropriate for biopsy due to either:

                    1. Almost healed at the time of enrollment (per physician)

                    2. Healed within 10 days prior to enrollment visit

                    3. Other etiology, deemed appropriate for biopsy

          -  Adequate arterial blood flow as evidenced by at least one of the following:

               1. Transcutaneous oxygen measurement (TcOM) &gt; 30 mmHg

               2. Ankle-brachial index ≥0.7

               3. Toe pressure &gt; 30 mmHg

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals who are deemed unable to understand the procedures, risks and benefits of
             the study, (i.e. unable to provide informed consent)

          -  Diabetics with Hemoglobin A1c &gt; 10%

          -  Subjects with marked immunodeficiency (HIV/AIDS, organ transplant patients and cancer
             patients and patients with autoimmune disease on immunosuppressive medications).

          -  Wounds closed or to be closed by flap or graft coverage - including stage 4 pressure
             ulcers and Wagner grade 4 or 5 diabetic foot ulcers

          -  Prisoners

          -  Patients with allergies to petrolatum

          -  Patients who are currently enrolled in another research study which includes
             investigational treatment and/or medication
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gayle M Gordillo, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amy Hoover, LPN</last_name>
    <phone>614-293-0390</phone>
    <email>Amy.Hoover@osumc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OSU Hospital East</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Hoover, LPN</last_name>
      <phone>614-366-2783</phone>
      <email>Amy.Hoover@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Martha Morehouse Medical Plaza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Hoover, LPN</last_name>
      <phone>614-293-0390</phone>
      <email>Amy.Hoover@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Apelqvist J, Larsson J, Agardh CD. Long-term prognosis for diabetic patients with foot ulcers. J Intern Med. 1993 Jun;233(6):485-91.</citation>
    <PMID>8501419</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barwell JR, Taylor M, Deacon J, Ghauri AS, Wakely C, Phillips LK, Whyman MR, Poskitt KR. Surgical correction of isolated superficial venous reflux reduces long-term recurrence rate in chronic venous leg ulcers. Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg. 2000 Oct;20(4):363-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11035968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brooks B, Dean R, Patel S, Wu B, Molyneaux L, Yue DK. TBI or not TBI: that is the question. Is it better to measure toe pressure than ankle pressure in diabetic patients? Diabet Med. 2001 Jul;18(7):528-32.</citation>
    <PMID>11553180</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chamlin SL, Kao J, Frieden IJ, Sheu MY, Fowler AJ, Fluhr JW, Williams ML, Elias PM. Ceramide-dominant barrier repair lipids alleviate childhood atopic dermatitis: changes in barrier function provide a sensitive indicator of disease activity. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2002 Aug;47(2):198-208.</citation>
    <PMID>12140465</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Disa JJ, Carlton JM, Goldberg NH. Efficacy of operative cure in pressure sore patients. Plast Reconstr Surg. 1992 Feb;89(2):272-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1732895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goodman CM, Cohen V, Armenta A, Thornby J, Netscher DT. Evaluation of results and treatment variables for pressure ulcers in 48 veteran spinal cord-injured patients. Ann Plast Surg. 1999 Jun;42(6):665-72.</citation>
    <PMID>10382806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>James GA, Swogger E, Wolcott R, Pulcini Ed, Secor P, Sestrich J, Costerton JW, Stewart PS. Biofilms in chronic wounds. Wound Repair Regen. 2008 Jan-Feb;16(1):37-44. Epub 2007 Dec 13.</citation>
    <PMID>18086294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lavrijsen AP, Higounenc IM, Weerheim A, Oestmann E, Tuinenburg EE, Boddé HE, Ponec M. Validation of an in vivo extraction method for human stratum corneum ceramides. Arch Dermatol Res. 1994;286(8):495-503.</citation>
    <PMID>7864665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lopez D, Vlamakis H, Kolter R. Generation of multiple cell types in Bacillus subtilis. FEMS Microbiol Rev. 2009 Jan;33(1):152-63. doi: 10.1111/j.1574-6976.2008.00148.x. Epub 2008 Nov 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19054118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Park SC, Choi CY, Ha YI, Yang HE. Utility of Toe-brachial Index for Diagnosis of Peripheral Artery Disease. Arch Plast Surg. 2012 May;39(3):227-31. doi: 10.5999/aps.2012.39.3.227. Epub 2012 May 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22783531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pinnagoda J, Tupker RA, Agner T, Serup J. Guidelines for transepidermal water loss (TEWL) measurement. A report from the Standardization Group of the European Society of Contact Dermatitis. Contact Dermatitis. 1990 Mar;22(3):164-78.</citation>
    <PMID>2335090</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Romanos MT, Raspovic A, Perrin BM. The reliability of toe systolic pressure and the toe brachial index in patients with diabetes. J Foot Ankle Res. 2010 Dec 22;3:31. doi: 10.1186/1757-1146-3-31.</citation>
    <PMID>21176166</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roy S, Elgharably H, Sinha M, Ganesh K, Chaney S, Mann E, Miller C, Khanna S, Bergdall VK, Powell HM, Cook CH, Gordillo GM, Wozniak DJ, Sen CK. Mixed-species biofilm compromises wound healing by disrupting epidermal barrier function. J Pathol. 2014 Aug;233(4):331-343. doi: 10.1002/path.4360. Epub 2014 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24771509</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roy S, Patel D, Khanna S, Gordillo GM, Biswas S, Friedman A, Sen CK. Transcriptome-wide analysis of blood vessels laser captured from human skin and chronic wound-edge tissue. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Sep 4;104(36):14472-7. Epub 2007 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>17728400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sen CK, Gordillo GM, Roy S, Kirsner R, Lambert L, Hunt TK, Gottrup F, Gurtner GC, Longaker MT. Human skin wounds: a major and snowballing threat to public health and the economy. Wound Repair Regen. 2009 Nov-Dec;17(6):763-71. doi: 10.1111/j.1524-475X.2009.00543.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19903300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smack DP, Harrington AC, Dunn C, Howard RS, Szkutnik AJ, Krivda SJ, Caldwell JB, James WD. Infection and allergy incidence in ambulatory surgery patients using white petrolatum vs bacitracin ointment. A randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 1996 Sep 25;276(12):972-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8805732</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tetteh HA, Groth SS, Kast T, Whitson BA, Radosevich DM, Klopp AC, D'Cunha J, Maddaus MA, Andrade RS. Primary palmoplantar hyperhidrosis and thoracoscopic sympathectomy: a new objective assessment method. Ann Thorac Surg. 2009 Jan;87(1):267-74; discussion 274-5. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2008.10.028.</citation>
    <PMID>19101310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thiele JJ, Traber MG, Packer L. Depletion of human stratum corneum vitamin E: an early and sensitive in vivo marker of UV induced photo-oxidation. J Invest Dermatol. 1998 May;110(5):756-61.</citation>
    <PMID>9579541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thiele JJ, Traber MG, Polefka TG, Cross CE, Packer L. Ozone-exposure depletes vitamin E and induces lipid peroxidation in murine stratum corneum. J Invest Dermatol. 1997 May;108(5):753-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9129228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>FDA Wound Healing Clinical Focus Group. Guidance for industry: chronic cutaneous ulcer and burn wounds-developing products for treatment. Wound Repair Regen. 2001 Jul-Aug;9(4):258-68.</citation>
    <PMID>11679134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 13, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 16, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gayle Gordillo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Epiceram</keyword>
  <keyword>Ceramiseal</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Recurrence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Foot</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leg Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pressure Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Petrolatum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Decanoic acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

