<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02574611</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KOR-15-026</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02574611</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of High Resolution Colonic Manometry in Studying Motility</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Efficacy of High Resolution Manometry in Studying Colonic Motility and Iontophoretic Administration of Prokinetic Agents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>James J. Peters Veterans Affairs Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>James J. Peters Veterans Affairs Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An injury to the spinal cord (SCI) results in numerous medical complications, including
      gastrointestinal (GI) function. Individuals with SCI may experience severe constipation
      (prolonged stool retention), incontinence (accidents), and overall difficulty in bowel
      evacuation. While various treatments and medications have been established to address this
      complication, there is little knowledge relating to the overall colonic motility. However,
      new technology such as High Resolution Colonic Manometry allows physicians to visualize high
      pressure contractions inside the colon, leading to a greater understanding of typical
      motility, a more accurate diagnosis, and an effective treatment. In this study, the
      investigators propose to use this technology to understand the effects of SCI on colonic
      motility by comparing to normal colonic function observed in able-bodied (AB) individuals. In
      addition, the investigators plan to study the effects of pharmacological treatments, such as
      neostigmine, on promoting peristaltic contractions in the colon as it is delivered across the
      skin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators data suggests that the fundamental consequence of SCI is a slowing of
      intestinal peristaltic activity, most likely as a result of down regulation of
      parasympathetic neural pathways. Furthermore, the investigators have effectively shown that
      measures involved in increase parasympathetic stimulation results in efficient bowel
      evacuation and improved bowel care. Such measures include the administration of neostigmine
      (NEO), which increases peristaltic contractions in the colon, resulting in predictable bowel
      evacuations. Given the cardiopulmonary side-effects of NEO, an ant-cholinergic known as
      Glycopyrrolate (GLY) is usually co-administered with NEO to reverse these side effects.
      However, the investigators knowledge regarding the effects of SCI on colonic motility is
      still primitive, mainly due to pervious technological disadvantages. New High Resolution
      Colonic Manometry systems (Medical Measurement Systems Dover, NH) simultaneously capture high
      amplitude pressure contractions (HAPCs) across the ascending, transverse, descending, and
      recto-sigmoid colon. Such capabilities allow for a much clearer display of pressure events
      compared to previous line tracing manometric systems and the direction of contractions are
      much easier to discern as well. To date, this technology has been an effective tool in
      diagnosing bowel disorders and complications, such as constipation in able-bodied individuals
      (AB). However, such studies have not been conducted in a SCI population. This technology also
      has the potential to capture the effects of NEO+GLY on improving colonic function.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>High Amplitude Contractions</measure>
    <time_frame>1-2days</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor changes in High Amplitude Contractions inside the colon during a typical day for SCI and AB patients. The manometry system will record these changes and allow the investigators to visualize changes during various activities (eating, resting, supine, seated, walking, etc.) The investigators will also measure changes in contractions during administration of prokinetic agents to promote bowel evacuations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Dysfunction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SCI observational</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals with SCI will undergo a one day observation following elective colonoscopy and placement of the colonic catheter. Investigators will be monitoring colonic motility during a &quot;typical&quot; (eating, sleeping, mobility, etc.)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Able-bodied observational</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Able-bodied individuals (non SCI) will undergo a one day observation following elective colonoscopy and placement of the colonic catheter. Investigators will be monitoring colonic motility during a &quot;typical&quot; (eating, sleeping, mobility, etc.)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SCI drug group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals with SCI will undergo a second day observation following elective colonoscopy and placement of the colonic catheter. Investigators will be monitoring colonic motility during the transdermal administration of neostigmine and glycopyrrolate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SCI placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals with SCI will undergo a one day observation following elective colonoscopy and placement of the colonic catheter. Investigators will be monitoring colonic motility during the transdermal administration of normal saline solution (placebo)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neostigmine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SCI drug group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glycopyrrolate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SCI drug group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline (Placebo)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SCI placebo group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High Resolution Colonic Manometry</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SCI observational</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Able-bodied observational</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SCI drug group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SCI placebo group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic SCI &gt;1year

          -  Able-Bodied (non SCI)

          -  Undergoing Elective Colonoscopy

          -  Age 18-75 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous adverse reaction or hypersensitivity to electrical stimulation

          -  Known sensitivity to neostigmine or glycopyrrolate

          -  Persons with SCI who do not require additional bowel care or have &quot;normal bowel
             function&quot;

          -  Known hypersensitivity to neostigmine or glycopyrrolate

          -  History of mechanical obstruction of the intestine or urinary tract

          -  History of Myocardial infarction

          -  Uncontrollable Hypertension Defined by a blood pressure reading of 160/100 mmHg or
             higher

          -  Organ damage (heart &amp; kidney) and/or transient ischemic attack-cerebral vascular
             accident as a result of hypertension

          -  Known past history of coronary artery disease or bradyarrythmia

          -  Active respiratory disease

          -  Known history of asthma during lifetime or recent (within 3 months) respiratory
             infections

          -  Adrenal insufficiency

          -  Diagnosed coagulopathy

          -  Any renal disease or dysfunction

          -  Potential for pregnancy

          -  Lactating/nursing females

          -  Slow-heart beat (HR&lt;45 bpm)

          -  Lack of mental capacity to give consent

          -  Use of any antibiotic in the past 7 days

          -  Use of medications known to affect the respiratory system

          -  Use of medications known to alter airway caliber

          -  Concurrent participation in other clinical trials (within 30 days)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark A Korsten, MD</last_name>
    <phone>718-584-9000</phone>
    <phone_ext>6753</phone_ext>
    <email>mark.korsten@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tradd Cummings, MS</last_name>
    <phone>718-584-9000</phone>
    <phone_ext>3107</phone_ext>
    <email>tradd.cummings@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>James J. Peters VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10468</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brian Lyons</last_name>
      <phone>718-584-9000</phone>
      <phone_ext>3128</phone_ext>
      <email>brian.lyons@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Joshua Hobson</last_name>
      <phone>718-584-9000</phone>
      <phone_ext>3129</phone_ext>
      <email>joshua.hobson@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark A. Korsten, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>William A. Bauman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Miroslav Radulovic, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marinella D. Galea, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ann M. Spungen, EdD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 6, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 14, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 14, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>James J. Peters Veterans Affairs Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Mark Korsten</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief Gastroenterologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neostigmine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glycopyrrolate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

