<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02571517</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FSJD-GLUCOBR-2010</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2011-000337-36</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02571517</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Glucocorticoid Therapy Impact on the Inflammatory Response and Clinical Evolution in Patients With Severe Bronchiolitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of the Administration of Systemic Glucocorticoids on Inflammatory Response and Clinical Evolution of Patients Diagnosed With Moderate- Severe Bronchiolitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundació Sant Joan de Déu</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundació Sant Joan de Déu</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to to demonstrate that a 7-day course of systemic
      glucocorticoids decreases the inflammatory activity of moderate or severe bronchiolitis in
      paediatric patients compared to the standard treatment. To evaluate the morbidity (regarding
      to the clinical course: Intensive Pediatric Unit Care unit (PICU) admission, mechanical
      ventilation, ionotropic support, nosocomial infection, rescue therapy for respiratory
      failure; duration of PICU stay and hospitalization; and exitus) between the treatment and the
      control groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A Prospective, randomised, double blind and placebo controlled study. Patients assigned to
      experimental group (group 1) will receive iv methylprednisolone 2 mg/kg/day (in two divided
      doses) and/or oral prednisolone 2,5 mg/kg/day (in two divided doses) every 12 hours, during 7
      days.

      Patients assigned to control group (group 2) will receive iv/oral glucose 5% solution as
      placebo, at the same dose and time as the experimental group. A total of 50 (initially 39,
      but it was extended to 50 by Protocol Amendment) patients per group are recruited.

      Bronchiolitis is the most common infection of the lower respiratory tract. It is defined as,
      the first episode of bronchospasm, dyspnea, expiratory difficulty, feed refusal, tachypnea
      greater than 50 rpm and radiological evidence of hyperinflation, in less than 24 months.

      It is a very prevalent disease, Respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) infects 70% of children
      under one year and 100% of children under 2 years and generates a major health impact on
      epidemic period (especially from December to February) . It is the most frequent cause of
      hospitalization in children under one year during the winter and up to 10% of those admitted
      will need intensive care, of which up to 60% required intubation and mechanical ventilation.
      The estimated disease in healthy children, mortality ranges from 0.005% to 0.02%, while in
      hospitalized children becomes between 1% and 3%.

      In recent years, there have been numerous studies, mainly in RSV bronchiolitis, to analyze
      the immunological basis of the disease, as discussed complex, in order to perform a
      prophylaxis and treatment of more optimal infection.

      Inflammatory response in bronchiolitis results in activation of cytokines and chemokines that
      generates a viral clearance. However, if the inflammatory response is disproportionate, the
      pathogenesis of the disease can lead to a worse clinical evolution.

      Corticosteroids are drugs having inhibitory effects on specific immune response, mediated
      both T cells and the B cell, and are potent inhibitors of phagocyte function. These drugs are
      effective in the management of multiple forms of secondary inflammatory diseases or immune
      disorders and may also be useful in the management of bronchiolitis.

      The treatment of bronchiolitis is mainly based on supportive therapy: oxygen therapy, proper
      hydration and aspiration of nasal secretions. Many treatments have been tried that have tried
      to lessen the severity of the infection, such as the use of bronchodilators and / or
      corticosteroids, although with controversial results.

      In the literature review conducted in PubMed, the investigators found about 110 related
      bronchiolitis, as MeSH Terms, publications using the words &quot;bronchiolitis&quot; [All Fields] AND
      (&quot;child&quot; [MeSH Terms].

      Only three of these articles shows results of clinical trials, although none in relation to
      the usefulness of steroids in bronchiolitis.

      There is just a case report describing the use of intravenous corticosteroids in infants with
      severe bronchiolitis, in combination with therapies such as extracorporeal oxygenation.

      One of the important aspects that the investigators took in consideration is that rhinovirus
      bronchiolitis is one of the most involved cause in the development of asthma, and just one of
      the etiologies of bronchiolitis who could benefit from treatment with corticosteroids.

      Prednisolone and methylprednisolone are also well known and used drugs, whose side effects
      are often dose and duration dependent.

      The identification and recruitment of patients will take place during the admission in the
      Intensive Pediatric Unit Care unit at the Hospital Sant Joan de Deu.

      Treatment of patients starts on days 0 and 3 of hospitalization. The patient treatment
      duration is 7 days, after that starts the follow-up phase, which duration is one month from
      the date of the baseline visit and until the hospital discharge.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in inflammatory response</measure>
    <time_frame>enrollment to one week treatment</time_frame>
    <description>inflammatory response evaluation of the first week of glucocorticoids treatment as assessed by multiple measurements aggregated to arrive at one reported value, which are: the bronchiolitis clinical severity Scale, pediatric mortality Risk scale (PRISM III), the Chest x-ray test, the nasopharyngeal aspiration and analytical exploration (at day 5-7)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Morbidity episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <description>Morbidity assessment by multiple measurements aggregated to arrive at one reported value which are as follow: necessity of mechanical ventilation, inotropic, presence of nosocomial infection, rescue therapies if respiratory failure occur; days of admission to the Pediatric Intensive Care Unit and hospitalization, in both treatment and control groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Side effects estimate</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Side effects estimate by comparing the experimental group to the control group</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">94</enrollment>
  <condition>Bronchiolitis, Viral</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Glucocorticoids</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>methylprednisolone intravenous administration of 2mg/kg/day (divided in two doses) and/or oral prednisolone 2,5 mg/kg/day (in two divided doses) during 7 days.
Patients younger than 2 year, who required hospitalization, affected by moderate or severe bronchiolitis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>will receive iv/oral glucose 5% solution as placebo of 2mg/kg/day and/or 2,5 mg/kg/day (divided in two doses) during 7 days.
Patients younger than 2 year, who required hospitalization, affected by moderate or severe bronchiolitis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glucocorticoids</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients assigned to experimental group (group 1) will receive iv methylprednisolone 2 mg/kg/day (divided in two doses) doses and/or oral prednisolone 2,5 mg/kg/day (divided in two doses) during 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Glucocorticoids</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SOLU-MODERIN 125 mg</other_name>
    <other_name>METHYLPREDNISOLONE SODIUM SUCCINATE</other_name>
    <other_name>ESTILSONA Gotas</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients assigned to control group (group 2) will receive iv/oral glucose 5% solution as placebo, 2 mg/kg/day (divided in two doses) during 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>glucose 5% solution</other_name>
    <other_name>Plast-Apyr Glucosado 5%</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The study will recruit paediatric patients younger than one year old who require
        hospitalization for moderate-severe bronchiolitis according to the BRONCHIOLITIS SCORE of
        Sant Joan de Deu Hospital (HSJD)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of either gender under one year old with mild bronchiolitis.

          -  Patients with bronchiolitis in which the principal symptom is apnoea.

          -  Patients who have received corticotherapy before admission to hospital.

          -  No consent from parents or tutors.

          -  Patients with previous acquired or innate immunodepression.

          -  Patients enrolled in other clinical trials.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Iolanda Jordán, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCIP H Sant Joan de Déu</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonzel L, Tenenbaum T, Schroten H, Schildgen O, Schweitzer-Krantz S, Adams O. Frequent detection of viral coinfection in children hospitalized with acute respiratory tract infection using a real-time polymerase chain reaction. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2008 Jul;27(7):589-94. doi: 10.1097/INF.0b013e3181694fb9.</citation>
    <PMID>18520973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ogra PL. Respiratory syncytial virus: the virus, the disease and the immune response. Paediatr Respir Rev. 2004;5 Suppl A:S119-26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14980256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris JA, Huskins WC, Langley JM, Siegel JD; Pediatric Special Interest Group of the Society for Healthcare Epidemiology of America. Health care epidemiology perspective on the October 2006 recommendations of the Subcommittee on Diagnosis and Management of Bronchiolitis. Pediatrics. 2007 Oct;120(4):890-2.</citation>
    <PMID>17908774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bueno SM, González PA, Pacheco R, Leiva ED, Cautivo KM, Tobar HE, Mora JE, Prado CE, Zúñiga JP, Jiménez J, Riedel CA, Kalergis AM. Host immunity during RSV pathogenesis. Int Immunopharmacol. 2008 Oct;8(10):1320-9. doi: 10.1016/j.intimp.2008.03.012. Epub 2008 Apr 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18687294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chatham WW, Kimberly RP. Treatment of lupus with corticosteroids. Lupus. 2001;10(3):140-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11315342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jat KR, Chawla D. Surfactant therapy for bronchiolitis in critically ill infants. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Sep 12;(9):CD009194. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD009194.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015;(8):CD009194.</citation>
    <PMID>22972138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 29, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 8, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 7, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 7, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 8, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Respiratory viral infection.</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory syncytial virus bronchiolitis</keyword>
  <keyword>METHYLPREDNISOLONE SODIUM SUCCINATE</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bronchiolitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchiolitis, Viral</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucocorticoids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

