<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02575339</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BTCRC GI13-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02575339</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MLN0128 Compared to Sorafenib in Advanced or Metastatic Hepatocellular Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label Randomized Phase I/II Trial of MLN0128 Compared to Sorafenib in Patients With Advanced or Metastatic Hepatocellular Carcinoma: Big Ten Cancer Research Consortium BTCRC-GI13-002</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bert O'Neil, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Big Ten Cancer Research Consortium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Big Ten Cancer Research Consortium</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, multi-center, randomized phase I/II study of MLN0128 versus standard
      sorafenib. Eligible subjects in the phase I trial will receive MLN0128 in escalating doses.
      Eligible subjects in the phase II trial will be 1:1 randomized to either the MLN0128 arm or
      the sorafenib arm.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OUTLINE: This is a multi-center trial.

      The phase 1 dose escalation trial will evaluate MLN0128 in a standard 3+3 successive cohort
      design to identify the highest planned dose level. Phase II trial subjects will be 1:1
      randomized to receive either MLN0128 (investigational arm) or sorafenib (control arm).

      PHASE I DOSE ESCALATION INVESTIGATIONAL TREATMENT:

      Cohort 1 (dose level +1) will consist of 3-6 evaluable patients who will receive MLN0128 15mg
      on day 1 of the 28-day cycle.

      Cohort 2 (dose level +2) will consist of 3-6 evaluable patients who will receive MLN0128 20mg
      on day 1 of the 28-day cycle.

      Cohort 3 (dose level +3) will consist of 3-6 evaluable patients who will receive MLN0128 30mg
      on day 1 of the 28-day cycle.

      Subjects will be evaluated for dose limiting toxicity (DLT) in the first 28 days of treatment
      (1 cycle). However, decisions to move to next dose escalation cohort will not be made until
      all subjects complete 2 cycles of therapy at a given dose. There will be no further dose
      escalation beyond dose level +3.

      PHASE II INVESTIGATIONAL TREATMENT:

      Randomization will take place following completion of the screening evaluations and
      eligibility assessments. Stratification factors will be employed during randomization to
      minimize between-arm assignment imbalance.

        -  1 Child-Pugh score 5-6

        -  2 Child-Pugh score 7

      Within the strata, subjects will be randomly assigned with equal probability to either the
      investigational arm (Arm A: MLN0128) or the control arm (Arm B: sorafenib).

      Arm A: MLN0128 will be administered orally at the recommended phase II dose (RP2D) once
      weekly.

      Arm B: Sorafenib will be administered at 400mg PO BID daily, with dose adjustment per
      standard of care.

      A new treatment cycle (1 cycle = 28 days) will only be initiated when all of the following
      conditions are met:

        -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 10*9/L

        -  Platelets ≥ 50 x 10*9/L

        -  Non-hematologic treatment related toxicities have improved to grade 1 or resolved per
           Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v4.0 (CTCAE)

      Treatment may continue until progression, unacceptable toxicity, or withdrawal from study.

      Estimated Life Expectancy: ≥ 3 months

      Subjects must have adequate organ function, as specified below, within 7 days before study
      registration:

      Bone marrow reserve consistent with:

        -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 10*9/L

        -  Platelet count ≥ 50 x 10*9/L

        -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL

      Hepatic:

        -  Total bilirubin ≤ 2 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

        -  Transaminases (aspartate aminotransferase (AST), serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
           (SGOT) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT), serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase (SGPT) ≤
           5 x ULN

      Renal:

        -  Creatinine clearance ≥50 mL/min based either on Cockcroft-Gault estimate or based on
           urine collection (12 or 24 hour)

      Metabolic:

        -  Fasting serum glucose (≤ 130 mg/dL) and fasting triglycerides ≤ 300 mg/dL.

        -  Glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) &lt;7.0%
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I: Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of MLN0128</measure>
    <time_frame>From start of treatment Day 1 (D1) until completion of two cycles of treatment (maximum 56 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Dose limiting toxicities (DLT) assessed to establish recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II: Time to Progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 7 months (estimated).</time_frame>
    <description>TTP of subjects on each arm assessed using Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors v1.1 (RECIST) criteria</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I: Characterize Adverse Effects (AE)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of first dose until 30 days after the last treatment, assessed for estimated 7 cycles (est. 196 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicity assessed using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v4.0 (CTCAE) criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I: Overall Survival (OS) Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration until death from any cause, up to a maximum of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>OS of subjects receiving MLN0128</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I: Time to Progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 7 months (estimated).</time_frame>
    <description>TTP of subjects receiving MLN0128 assessed using RECIST v1.1 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I: Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization to tumor progression or death from any cause, up to a maximum of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>PFS of subjects receiving MLN0128 assessed using RECIST v1.1 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I: Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 16 weeks and 24 weeks from D1 of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>ORR of subjects receiving MLN0128 assessed by RECIST v1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase I: Disease Control Rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 16 weeks and 24 weeks from D1 of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>DCR of subjects receiving MLN0128 assessed by RECIST v1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II: Overall Survival (OS) Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration until death from any cause, up to a maximum of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>OS of subjects randomized to both MLN0128 and sorafenib arms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II: Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization to tumor progression or death from any cause, up to a maximum of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>PFS of subjects randomized to both MLN0128 and sorafenib arms, assessed using RECIST v1.1 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II: Characterize Adverse Effects (AE)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of first dose until 30 days after the last treatment, assessed for estimated 7 cycles (est. 196 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicity for subjects randomized to both MLN0128 and sorafenib arms, assessed using CTCAE v4 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II: Radiographic Response Rate (RRR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 16 weeks and 24 weeks from D1 of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>RRR for subjects randomized to both MLN0128 and sorafenib arms, determined utilizing ORR and DCR assessments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">118</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Liver Cancer</condition>
  <condition>HCC</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I MLN0128 Dose Escalation Study</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive MLN0128 orally on days 1, 8, 15 and 22 in successive cohorts.
Cohort 1 MLN0128 15mg each week (QW); Cohort 2 MLN0128 20mg QW; Cohort 3 MLN0128 30mg QW</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II Arm A: MLN0128</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to experimental arm will receive MLN0128 orally at the recommended phase II dose (RP2D) once weekly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II Arm B: Sorafenib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to control arm will receive sorafenib 400mg by mouth (PO) twice a day (BID) daily.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MLN0128</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase I Dose Escalation Study Cohort 1 MLN0128 15mg QW; Cohort 2 MLN0128 20mg QW; Cohort 3 MLN0128 30mg QW</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I MLN0128 Dose Escalation Study</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sapanisertib</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MLN0128 (RP2D)</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase II Arm A:
MLN0128 administered orally at the recommended phase II dose (RP2D) once weekly.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II Arm A: MLN0128</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sapanisertib</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sorafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase II Arm B:
Sorafenib administered at 400mg PO BID daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase II Arm B: Sorafenib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nexavar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female subjects 18 years or older at the time of informed consent.

          -  Voluntary written consent must be signed before performance of any study related
             procedure not part of standard medical care, with the understanding that the subject
             may withdraw consent at any time without prejudice to future medical care.

          -  Females of childbearing potential must agree to practice 2 effective methods of
             contraception, at the same time, from the time of signing the informed consent through
             90 days after the last dose of study drug, or agree to completely abstain from
             heterosexual intercourse.

          -  Females of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 7
             days prior to prior to registration for protocol therapy. NOTE: Female subjects are
             considered of childbearing potential unless they are surgically sterile (they have
             undergone a hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation, or bilateral oophorectomy) or they
             are naturally postmenopausal for at least 12 consecutive months.

          -  Male subjects, even if surgically sterilized (i.e., status post-vasectomy), must agree
             to practice effective barrier contraception during the entire study treatment period
             and through 120 days after the last dose of study drug, or agree to completely abstain
             from heterosexual intercourse.

          -  Subjects must have a diagnosis of measurable advanced or metastatic hepatocellular
             carcinoma (HCC). Advanced HCC is defined as disease not amenable to surgery, ablation,
             transplant, or embolic therapy.

          -  Phase II subjects must be willing to provide a tissue biopsy prior to registration if
             archived HCC tumor tissue is not available for correlative studies.

          -  For the phase I cohort, subjects with one prior systemic treatment are eligible.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0, 1, or 2.

          -  Adequate organ function, as specified below, within 28 days before study registration:

          -  Bone marrow reserve consistent with: absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 10^9/L;
             platelet count ≥ 50 x 10^9/L; hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL;

          -  Hepatic: total bilirubin ≤ 2 x upper limit of normal (ULN), transaminases (aspartate
             aminotransferase/serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase-AST/SGOT and alanine
             aminotransferase/serum glutamic pyruvic transaminase-ALT/SGPT) ≤ 5 x ULN

          -  Renal: creatinine clearance ≥50 mL/min based either on Cockcroft-Gault estimate or
             based on urine collection (12 or 24 hour);

          -  Metabolic: Glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) ≤7.0%, fasting serum glucose (≤ 130 mg/dL)
             and fasting triglycerides ≤ 300 mg/dL.

          -  Ability to swallow oral medications.

          -  Measurable disease according to RECIST v1.1 and obtained by imaging within 28 days
             prior to registration for protocol therapy.

          -  Subjects who have a history of brain metastasis are eligible for the study provided
             all the following criteria are met:

               -  Must have completed their treatment for brain metastasis

               -  Must be asymptomatic

               -  Must not have evidence of disease progression for ≥3 months or hemorrhage after
                  treatment;

               -  Must be off-treatment from dexamethasone for 4 weeks prior to study registration
                  and

               -  Must not have an ongoing requirement for dexamethasone or anti-epileptic drugs.

          -  Prior locoregional liver directed therapy is allowed as long as treatment was at least
             6 weeks prior to study registration, and clear progression is demonstrated by RECIST
             v1.1 criteria. Subject must have recovered from the acute toxic effects (≤ grade 1
             CTCAE v4) of previous anti-cancer treatment prior to study enrollment; the only
             exception is that grade 2 neuropathy is permitted.

          -  Prior radiation therapy is allowed to &lt; 25% of the bone marrow, but is not permitted
             within 28 days prior to study registration.

          -  Estimated life expectancy &gt; 3 months as determined by the treating physician.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects meeting any of the following exclusion criteria are not to be enrolled in the
        study:

          -  Female subjects who are both lactating and breastfeeding

          -  Any serious medical or psychiatric illness that could, in the investigator's opinion,
             potentially interfere with the completion of treatment according to this protocol.

          -  Treatment with any investigational products within 28 days prior to study
             registration.

          -  No prior systemic treatment is allowed, except for subjects in the phase I cohort who
             are permitted one prior systemic treatment.

          -  Failed to recover from the reversible effects of prior anticancer therapies with the
             exception of alopecia and grade 2 neuropathy.

          -  Have initiated treatment with bisphosphonates less than 30 days prior to study
             registration. Concurrent bisphosphonate use is only allowed if the bisphosphonate was
             initiated at least 30 days prior to study registration.

          -  Manifestations of malabsorption due to prior gastrointestinal (GI) surgery, GI
             disease, or for an unknown reason that may alter the absorption of MLN0128.

          -  No condition that could affect the absorption of study drug, including any of the
             following:

               -  Malabsorption syndrome

               -  Disease significantly affecting gastrointestinal function

               -  Bowel obstruction or sub-obstruction

          -  History of any of the following within the last 6 months prior to study registration:

               -  Ischemic myocardial event, including angina requiring therapy and artery
                  revascularization procedures

               -  Ischemic cerebrovascular event, including transient ischemic attack (TIA) and
                  artery revascularization procedures

               -  Requirement for inotropic support (excluding digoxin) or serious (uncontrolled)
                  cardiac arrhythmia (including atrial flutter/fibrillation, ventricular
                  fibrillation or ventricular tachycardia)

               -  Placement of a pacemaker for control of rhythm

               -  New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III or IV heart failure

               -  Pulmonary embolism

          -  Significant active cardiovascular or pulmonary disease at the time of study
             registration, including:

               -  Uncontrolled high blood pressure (i.e., systolic blood pressure &gt;160 mm Hg,
                  diastolic blood pressure &gt; 95 mm Hg)

               -  Pulmonary hypertension

               -  Uncontrolled asthma or O2 saturation &lt; 90% by ABG (Arterial Blood Gas) analysis
                  or pulse oximetry on room air

               -  Significant valvular disease; severe regurgitation or stenosis by imaging
                  independent of symptom control with medical intervention, or history of valve
                  replacement

               -  Medically significant (symptomatic) bradycardia

               -  History of arrhythmia requiring an implantable cardiac defibrillator

               -  Baseline prolongation of the rate-corrected QT interval (QTc) (e.g., repeated
                  demonstration of QTc interval &gt; 480 milliseconds, or history of congenital long
                  QT syndrome, or torsades de pointes)

          -  Initiation of treatment with hematopoietic growth factors, transfusions of blood and
             blood products, or systemic corticosteroids (either IV or oral steroids, excluding
             inhalers) within 1 week prior to study registration (subjects already receiving
             erythropoietin on a chronic basis for ≥ 28 days are eligible).

          -  Other clinically significant co-morbidities, such as uncontrolled pulmonary disease,
             active central nervous system disease, active infection, or any other condition that
             could compromise participation of the subject in the study.

          -  Cirrhosis with Child-Pugh score &gt; 7

          -  Variceal bleeding within 1 month prior to study registration.

          -  Refractory encephalopathy or ascites

          -  Known HIV positivity

          -  Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) positivity without active treatment. A subject
             found to be HBsAg positive should be on antiviral therapy for at least two weeks prior
             to study registration.

          -  Treatment with strong inhibitors and/or inducers of cytochrome P450 (CYP) 3A4, CYP2C19
             or CYP2C19 within 7 days prior to study registration.

          -  Subjects requiring daily or chronic use of a proton pump inhibitor (PPI) and/or having
             taken a PPI within 7 days prior to study registration.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bert O'Neil, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Big Ten Cancer Research Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bert O'Neil, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>317.278.8845</phone>
    <email>bhoneil@iu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michael Nunley</last_name>
    <phone>317.634.5842</phone>
    <phone_ext>17</phone_ext>
    <email>mnunley@bigtencrc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Danielle Keir</last_name>
      <phone>312-695-0514</phone>
      <email>danielle.keir@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Al Benson III, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Illinois Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alana Aziz-Bradley</last_name>
      <phone>312-996-2088</phone>
      <email>aaziz6@uic.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Neeta Venepalli, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Melvin and Bren Simon Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bert O'Neil, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-8845</phone>
      <email>bhoneil@iu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kerry Bridges</last_name>
      <phone>317.274.2552</phone>
      <email>kdbridge@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Noth Carolina at Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27514</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brian Burgess</last_name>
      <phone>919-962-8548</phone>
      <email>brian_burgess@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Autumn McRee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christina Rodriquez</last_name>
      <phone>717-531-5364</phone>
      <email>crodriguez1@hmc.psu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nelson Yee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>UWCCC Cancer Cennect</last_name>
      <phone>800-622-8922</phone>
      <email>cancerconnect@uwcarbone.wisc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dustin Deming, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Romania</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bigtencrc.org</url>
    <description>Big Ten Cancer Research Consortium Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 12, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Big Ten Cancer Research Consortium</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bert O'Neil, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Sponsor-Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MLN0128</keyword>
  <keyword>Sapanisertib</keyword>
  <keyword>TORC1/2 inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>INK128</keyword>
  <keyword>Nexavar</keyword>
  <keyword>Sorafenib</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niacinamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

