<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02164838</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ADVL1315</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02164838</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VEGF Receptor Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor Axitinib in Children With Recurrent or Refractory Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study of the VEGF Receptor Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor Axitinib (INLYTA, IND# TBD) in Children With Recurrent or Refractory Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial will be the first study of axitinib in children and adolescents. The primary
      objective of this Phase 1 trial is to determine a maximum tolerated dose (MTD) or recommended
      Phase 2 dose (RP2D) of axitinib in pediatric patients with refractory solid tumors.
      Additional objectives include measurement of pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic parameters,
      description of the toxicity profile of this agent in children and adolescents, and assessment
      of response within the confines of a Phase 1 trial. A standard rolling 6 design will be used
      for dose escalation. Further development of axitinib will focus on development of a joint
      cooperative group (COG/ECOG) Phase 2 study of axitinib in pediatric, adolescent and young
      adult translocation renal cell carcinoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 19, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 19, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events as assessed by (CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of axitinib based on dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) at which fewer than one-third of patients experience DLT, as assessed by CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic Assessment of Axitinib Concentrations in Plasma Samples</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 8 of Cycle 1</time_frame>
    <description>A descriptive analysis of pharmacokinetic (PK) parameters of axitinib will be performed to define systemic exposure, drug clearance, and other pharmacokinetic parameters.
Blood samples will be collected at the following time points:Day 1, Cycle 1: Pre-dose, and at 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours after the AM dose on Day 1. Day 8, Cycle 1: Pre-dose, and at 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 hours after the AM dose on Day 8.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of disease response to preliminarily define the antitumor activity of axitinib</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will have tumor disease evaluations performed at the end of cycles 1, 3, and 5 and then every 3 cycles. Disease response will be assessed according to RECIST criteria for patients with solid tumors and will be reported descriptively. Analyses will be descriptive and exploratory and hypotheses generating in nature.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarkers of kidney injury during axitinib treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycles 1 and 3</time_frame>
    <description>Proteins in the blood (cystatin C and neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalcin (NGAL)) and urine (kidney injury molecule-1 (KIM-1), neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalin (NGAL), interleukin-18 (IL-18), creatinine and other markers of renal injury) will be measured before treatment and then weekly during Cycle 1 of axitinib treatment and at the end of Cycle 3</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Refractory or Recurrent Solid Tumors, Excluding CNS Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Axitinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Axitinib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Axitinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AG-013736, INLYTA®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Age: Patients must be &gt; than 12 months and &lt; 18 years of age at the time of study
             enrollment.

          -  Body Surface Area: Patients must have a BSA of ≥ 0.53 m2 at the time of study
             enrollment.

          -  Diagnosis: Patients with refractory or recurrent solid tumors (excluding CNS tumors)
             and patients with unresectable translocation positive renal cell carcinoma (tRCC) are
             eligible. Patients must have had histologic verification of malignancy at original
             diagnosis or relapse.

          -  The diagnosis of translocation morphology or TFE renal cell carcinoma is established
             by having characteristic morphology AND either a) strong nuclear TFE3 or TFEb staining
             on immunohistochemistry OR b) cytogenetic studies of the tumor demonstrating a TFE
             translocation OR c) fluorescent in situ hybridization (FISH) demonstrating a TFE
             translocation.

          -  Disease Status: Patients must have either measurable or evaluable disease

          -  Therapeutic Options: Patient's current disease state must be one for which there is no
             known curative therapy or therapy proven to prolong survival with an acceptable
             quality of life.

          -  Performance Level: Karnofsky ≥ 50% for patients &gt; 16 years of age and Lansky ≥ 50 for
             patients ≤ 16 years of age . Patients who are unable to walk because of paralysis, but
             who are up in a wheelchair, will be considered ambulatory for the purpose of assessing
             the performance score.

          -  Prior Therapy

          -  Patients may have received bevacizumab, VEGF-Trap, or other VEGF blocking tyrosine
             kinase inhibitors, but may not have received axitinib.

          -  Patients must have recovered from any VEGF blocking drug-related toxicity (e.g.,
             proteinuria, hypertension).

          -  All patients must have fully recovered from the acute toxic effects of all prior
             anti-cancer chemotherapy.

          -  Myelosuppressive chemotherapy: At least 21 days after the last dose of
             myelosuppressive chemotherapy (42 days if prior nitrosourea).

          -  Hematopoietic growth factors: At least 14 days after the last dose of a long-acting
             growth factor (e.g. Neulasta) or 7 days for short-acting growth factor. For agents
             that have known adverse events occurring beyond 7 days after administration, this
             period must be extended beyond the time during which adverse events are known to
             occur. The duration of this interval must be discussed with the study chair.

          -  Biologic (anti-neoplastic agent): At least 7 days after the last dose of a biologic
             agent. For agents that have known adverse events occurring beyond 7 days after
             administration, this period must be extended beyond the time during which adverse
             events are known to occur. The duration of this interval must be discussed with the
             study chair.

          -  Immunotherapy: At least 42 days after the completion of any type of immunotherapy,
             e.g. tumor vaccines.

          -  Monoclonal antibodies: At least 3 half-lives of the antibody after the last dose of a
             monoclonal antibody.

          -  XRT: At least 14 days after local palliative XRT (small port); At least 150 days must
             have elapsed if prior TBI, craniospinal XRT or if ≥ 50% radiation of pelvis; At least
             42 days must have elapsed if other substantial BM radiation.

          -  Stem Cell Infusion without TBI: No evidence of active graft vs. host disease and at
             least 84 days must have elapsed after transplant or stem cell infusion.

          -  Organ Function Requirements

          -  Adequate Bone Marrow Function Defined As:

               -  Peripheral absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1000/mm3

               -  Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm3 (transfusion independent, defined as not receiving
                  platelet transfusions for at least 7 days prior to enrollment)

        Adequate Renal Function Defined As:

        • Creatinine clearance or radioisotope GFR ≥ 70ml/min/1.73 m2 or

        Adequate Liver Function Defined as:

          -  Bilirubin (sum of conjugated + unconjugated) ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) for
             age

          -  SGPT (ALT) ≤ 110 U/L. For the purpose of this study, the ULN for SGPT is 45 U/L.

          -  SGOT (AST) ≤ 125 U/L. For the purpose of this study, the ULN for SGOT is 50 U/L.

          -  Serum albumin ≥ 2 g/dL.

        Adequate Cardiac Function Defined As:

          -  Shortening fraction of ≥ 27% by echocardiogram, or Ejection fraction of ≥ 50% by gated
             radionuclide study.

          -  Must not have a history of myocardial infarction, severe or unstable angina, or
             peripheral vascular disease.

        Adequate Blood Pressure Control Defined As:

        A blood pressure (BP) ≤ the 95th percentile for age, height, and gender

        Adequate Coagulation Defined As:

          -  No evidence of active bleeding

          -  PT and PTT ≤ 1.2 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  INR ≤1.2

        Adequate Pancreatic Function Defined as:

        • Lipase ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN).

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Pregnancy or Breast-Feeding

          -  Corticosteroids: Patients receiving chronically dosed corticosteroids within 7 days
             prior to enrollment are not eligible for this trial.

          -  Investigational Drugs: Patients who are currently receiving another investigational
             drug are not eligible.

          -  Anti-cancer Agents: Patients who are currently receiving other anti-cancer agents are
             not eligible.

          -  Anti-GVHD agents post-transplant:

        Patients who are receiving cyclosporine, tacrolimus or other agents to prevent
        graft-versus-host disease post bone marrow transplant are not eligible for this trial.

          -  CYP3A4/5 Inhibitors:

        Patients chronically receiving drugs that are known potent CYP3A4/5 inhibitors within 7
        days prior to study enrollment, including but not limited to ketoconazole, itraconazole,
        clarithromycin, atazanavir, indinavir, nefazodone, nelfinavir, ritonavir, saquinavir,
        telithromycin, voriconazole, grapefruit, and grapefruit juice are not eligible

          -  CYP3A4/5 Inducers:

        Patients chronically receiving drugs that are known potent CYP3A4/5 inducers within 7 days
        prior to study enrollment, including but not limited to rifampin, dexamethasone, phenytoin,
        carbamazepine, rifabutin, rifapentine, phenobarbital, and St John's wort are not eligible.

          -  Anti-hypertensives: Patients who are receiving anti-hypertensive medications for
             control of blood pressure at the time of enrollment are not eligible for this trial.

          -  Anti-coagulation: Patients who are currently receiving therapeutic anti-coagulation
             with heparin, low-molecular weight heparin or coumadin are not eligible for this
             trial.

          -  Anti-inflammatory or anti-platelet agents: Patients who are currently receiving
             aspirin, ibuprofen or other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs or anti-platelet
             agents are not eligible.

          -  Patients must be able to swallow tablets whole.

          -  Thyroid Replacement Therapy: Patients who require thyroid replacement therapy are not
             eligible if they have not been receiving a stable replacement dose for at least 28
             days prior to study enrollment. Patients who enter the study on thyroid replacement
             should have their medication adjusted to maintain TSH in the normal range.

        Bleeding and Thrombosis:

        Patients with evidence of active bleeding, intratumoral hemorrhage, or bleeding diathesis
        are not eligible:

          -  History (within 180 days prior to study enrollment) of arterial thromboembolic events,
             including transient ischemic attack (TIA) or cerebrovascular accident (CVA).

          -  History (within 180 days prior to study enrollment) of pulmonary embolism, DVT, or
             other venous thromboembolic event.

          -  History of hemoptysis within 42 days prior to study enrollment.

        Surgery: Patients who have had or are planning to have the following invasive procedures
        are not eligible:

          -  Major surgical procedure, laparoscopic procedure, open biopsy or significant traumatic
             injury within 28 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Subcutaneous port placement or central line placement is not considered major surgery
             but must be placed at least 3 days prior to enrollment for external lines and at least
             7 days prior to enrollment for subcutaneous port.

          -  Core biopsy within 7 days prior to enrollment.

          -  Fine needle aspirate or central line placement within 7 days prior to enrollment.

        CNS disease:

          -  Patients who have a known primary or metastatic CNS tumor at the time of study
             enrollment are not eligible. A prior history of metastatic CNS tumor is allowed as
             long as there is no evidence of CNS disease at study enrollment.

          -  Patients who have a serious or non-healing wound, ulcer, or bone fracture at the time
             of study enrollment are not eligible.

          -  Patients who have a history of abdominal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation, or
             intra-abdominal abscess within 28 days of study enrollment are not eligible.

          -  Infection: Patients who have known HIV or an uncontrolled infection are not eligible.

          -  Patients who have received a prior solid organ transplantation are not eligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Geller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Oncology Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Alabama</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Childrens Hospital of Orange County</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Medical Center-Parnassus</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Healthcare of Atlanta - Egleston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ann and Robert H Lurie Children's Hospital of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Riley Hospital for Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mark O Hatfield-Warren Grant Magnusun Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>C S Mott Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota Cancer Center-Fairview</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health and Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Childrens Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seattle Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98145</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Midwest Children's Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital for Sick Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1X8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 17, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Axitinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

