<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02163304</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PBRC 2013-031</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02163304</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Images Following Beverage Ingestion on Brain Activation</brief_title>
  <acronym>Sweety</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Images Following Beverage Ingestion on Brain Activation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to quantify activation of regions of the brain
      associated with taste, appetite, and reward after viewing high sugar and high fat (HS/HF)
      images compared to control images following ingestion of (1) an artificially sweetened
      solution, (2) a sucrose solution, and (3) a tasteless control solution in normal weight vs.
      obese women. This is a repeated measures study design; hence, data are collected on three
      days corresponding to the three solutions. Body mass index (BMI) is a between subjects
      measure.

        1. After consuming an artificially sweetened solution and a sucrose solution compared to a
           tasteless solution, viewing HS/HF food images vs. control images will result in higher
           activation of taste pathways (frontal operulum and anterior insula (FO/AI)) in the
           brain.

        2. After consumption of a sucrose solution compared to an artificially sweetened solution
           and a tasteless solution, viewing HS/HF food images vs. control images will result in
           higher activation of regions of the brain associate with appetite (hypothalamus).

        3. After consumption of a sucrose solution compared to an artificially sweetened solution
           and a tasteless solution, viewing HS/HF food images vs. control images will result in
           higher activation of regions of the brain associated with reward [amygdala, anterior
           cingulate cortex (ACC), Orbitalfrontal Cortex (OFC), and ventral tegmental area (VTA),
           striatum, insula] in obese but not normal weight women. After consuming an artificially
           sweetened solution compared to a tasteless solution, viewing HS/HF images vs. control
           images will result in no differences in activation of reward pathways of the brain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this pilot study, we will use functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) to determine
      the effects of high calorie visual food cues [i.e. images of foods that are high in both
      sugar and fat (HS/HF), such as ice cream] on activation of taste, appetite, and reward
      pathways in the brain following the separate ingestion of (1) an artificial sweetened
      solution (2) a sucrose solution and (3) a tasteless solution in obese individuals. Obesity
      rates are high among US adults with 33.8% of adults having a BMI of 30 or greater (1). The
      prevailing belief is that homeostatic systems are in place to monitor energy homeostasis.
      Sugar sweetened beverages appear to alter the homeostatic systems so that (1) metabolic
      feedback signals do not function correctly or as intended (2), as little or no dietary
      compensation is seen with energy from beverages (3), or (2) sweet and savory foods (sugar
      sweetened beverages) override the system (i.e. hedonics) (2). Epidemiological data suggest
      Americans are consuming 20-25% of their energy in beverage form which equates to ~430-535
      kcal/day (3, 4). In most studies, sugar sweetened beverage intake has been shown to increase
      weight (5, 6). While limited data are available, a meta-analysis in humans demonstrates that
      the inclusion of aspartame compared to sugar reduces energy intake (7). A prospective study
      found that weight loss maintainers utilize artificial sweeteners more than normal weight
      individuals (8). This suggests artificial sweeteners may be a method to promote weight loss
      in obese individuals. Public policy on sugar sweetened beverages is starting to be
      reexamined, however, it is currently unknown what effect sugar sweetened beverage intake and
      artificial sweetened solutions have on (1) taste, appetite, and reward regions of the brain
      and (2) food cravings and related brain activation, among obese vs. normal weight
      individuals. The aim of this study is to provide important data on why obese individuals
      continue to consume sugar-sweetened beverages despite the associated negative health
      outcomes. We hypothesize that this consumption is due to sugar sweetened beverages, but not
      artificial sweeteners, activating reward pathways of the brain (hedonics).

      Sucrose and artificial sweetners Previously it has been found that there is an altered
      hypothalamic response to glucose ingestion in obese humans (9). In obese humans, brain
      activation seems impaired; i.e., it was lower and delayed compared to lean subjects. This
      study lacked a functional contrast and had higher noise and less accuracy than current fMRI
      blood-oxygen-level-dependent (BOLD) technology and only the hypothalamus was analyzed (9).
      The current study and future studies from this pilot and feasibility work will further
      determine if dietary sugar responses are differentially regulated in obese individuals
      possibility contributing to the over consumption of sugar sweetened beverages in obese
      adults.

      Frank et al. concluded that taste pathways are activated with sucralose and sucrose taste in
      younger normal weight women (10). Only sucrose recruited reward pathways but appetite
      pathways were not documented due to either lack of significance or examination (10). This
      study will confirm beverage ingestion opposed to tasting evokes a similar reward response and
      also examines appetite and reward pathways in obese individuals.

      The effects of caloric vs. non caloric sweetener on taste activation were previously examined
      in normal weight men (11). During the non-caloric solution tasting, 2 caloric tastants were
      also consumed. These caloric tastants could invoke differential cephalic phase responses
      altering the results (12). Consumption of the artificial sweetener or the caloric solution
      increased activation of the insula, middle OFC, lateral OFC and amygdala. With the artificial
      sweetener, there was greater activation of the OFC (11). Next, the effects of sweet taste
      (2.4 mL) in younger male and female diet soda drinkers was examined (13). Water was utilized
      as the rinse and baseline for the comparison between diet and regular soda. In these persons,
      higher right orbitalfrontal cortex brain activation response in non-caloric compared to
      caloric solution was observed (13). These previous studies utilized only normal weight
      participants and taste to examine for the effects of artificial sweeteners on brain response.
      The current study examines obese individuals and solution ingestion to observe differences in
      brain activation. Overall there are differential brain responses to caloric vs. non-caloric
      sweetener in normal weight individuals thus previously authors suggested that more research
      needs to be performed as to the effectiveness of artificial sweeteners at decreasing energy
      intake.

      Obesity Women were shown food picture cues of high energy foods. The high energy foods
      produced significantly greater activation in the brain reward regions in obese compared to
      normal weight control women (14). Differences between groups included ACC, VTA, nucleus
      accumbens (NAc), amygdala, ventral pallidum (Vent Pall), Caudate, and Putamen (14). Postmeal,
      obese individuals, but not normal weight individuals, increase activation of the putamen
      (part of striatum) and amygdala suggesting these regions may play a role in overeating (15)
      which is why these regions are incorporated into the current study hypothesis. These
      cross-sectional studies are important as previously Murdaugh et. al (16) found that obese
      individuals that were not successful at short term weight loss or longer term weight loss
      maintenance had greater activation of reward pathway brain regions. While speculative,
      artificial sweeteners may reduce cravings by not activating reward pathways especially in
      obese persons. This grant will help provide pilot data to further elucidate this important
      question.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fMRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1,2,3</time_frame>
    <description>fMRI will be performed using a General Electric Signa Excite HDxT 3.0T scanner (Milwaukee, WI) approximately 10 minutes post beverage ingestion. The field of view is 24-28 cm. The scanner is equipped with functional components from GE. Supplemental components include a projection system and eye imaging system from Avotec , Inc. An eight channel head coil will be utilized for all fMRI scans, and E-prime® software will be utilized for computerized experiment design, data collection, and analysis. Visual food and control cues will be presented in a mixed event block design with blocks of HS/HF and control images. Food cues consist of full-color pictures displaying foods within a category (HS/HF). One food item will be shown in each picture. Control cues consist of scrambled images that match the food cues in color intensity and frequency. Each block is 30s in length and 6 images are presented anywhere from 3-7seconds. Total task time will be ~30 minutes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 1, 2, 3</time_frame>
    <description>Visual Analog Scales (VAS). Paper VAS will be used to measure subjective ratings of hunger, satiety, fullness, prospective food consumption, and thirst during the present study. When completing the VAS, participants rate the intensity of subjective states or opinions on a line anchored from &quot;not at all&quot; to &quot;extremely.&quot; The line is divided into 100 equal units. These VAS will be anchored from &quot;strongly disagree&quot; to &quot;strongly agree.&quot; The VAS that measure appetite ratings will be completed at pre and post beverage preload and minute 60 (or immediately post scan) and 120 following the fMRI scan(s).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Artificial Sweetner</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Artificial Sweetener</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tasteless Solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 oz tasteless solution</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sucrose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 oz 75 g sucrose beverage</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sucrose</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Sucrose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Artificial Sweetner</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Artificial Sweetner</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tasteless Solution</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Tasteless Solution</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female

          -  20-35 years old (inclusive)

          -  Weigh less than 350 lbs

          -  Weight stable (&gt;±5 kg in the last 6 months).

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 20-25 kg/m2 or 30-35 kg/m2.

          -  Willing to fast for 10 hours prior to examination.

          -  Right handed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis (by self report) of diabetes

          -  Diagnosis (by self report) of neurological condition

          -  Current or past alcohol or drug abuse problem.

          -  Smoking

          -  Have internal metal medical devices including cardiac pacemakers, aortic or cerebral
             aneurysm clips, artificial heart valves, ferromagnetic implants, shrapnel, wire
             sutures, joint replacements, bone or joint pins/rods/screws/clips, metal plates, metal
             fragments in your eye, or non-removable metal jewelry such as rings.

          -  Unable or unwilling to complete the imaging procedures for the duration of the MRI
             scan due to claustrophobia or other reason.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John W Apolzan, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>PBRC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baton Rouge</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70808</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 12, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 13, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 11, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Pennington Biomedical Research Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John Apolzan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Postdoctoral Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

