<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02169661</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HNU 2000</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02169661</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Burger and Beetroot Study - Lipid Oxidation Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>BABS</acronym>
  <official_title>Lipid Oxidation of Ready Meals: Reformulation With Antioxidant Phytochemicals</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aberdeen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aberdeen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Consumption of &quot;ready meals&quot; and other convenience foods are rapidly increasing. However,
      their nutritional value is problematical. For example, many are high in fats which are
      potentially oxidisable resulting in the formation of toxic end products. Consequently the aim
      of this study is to assess whether consumption of &quot;ready meals&quot; rich in certain fats leads to
      a post-prandial increase in lipid oxidation products in plasma and whether this can be
      ameliorated by reformulating the meals with natural extracts rich in phytochemicals with
      potential antioxidant activity in the stomach
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Many of these lipid oxidation products such as malondialdehyde are known to be genotoxic and
      potentially detrimental to health. Consequently the aim of this study is to assess whether
      consumption of &quot;ready meals&quot; rich in certain fats leads to a post-prandial increase in lipid
      oxidation products in plasma and whether this can be ameliorated by reformulating the meals
      with natural extracts rich in phytochemicals with potential antioxidant activity in the
      stomach.

      Diet design requirements:

      The basic &quot;ready meal&quot; is a turkey burger consisting of

        -  50% fat

        -  20% protein

        -  30% carbohydrate.

      However, there are four experimental forms of the burger.

        1. The fat is unsaturated (stripped corn oil)

        2. The fat is saturated (lard)

        3. The fat is unsaturated and the diet also contains a beetroot extract at a concentration
           of 10g/100g.

        4. The fat is saturated and the diet also contains a beetroot extract at a concentration of
           10g/100g.

      Beetroot (http://www.kanegrade.com/powders.htm) has been selected for the burger
      reformulation as it is a Scottish product rich in phytochemicals with potential antioxidant
      efficacy. An additional benefit may a blood pressure lowering effect. Initial taste tests
      indicate acceptable palatability.

      All other components of the burger are formulated to be as similar as possible.

      Fatty acid profiles and the &quot;basic eight&quot; used on food labels will be determined on the
      diets. Susceptibility of the diets to oxidise will be assessed using RANCIMAT.

      Ready Meal Intervention:

      This will be a latin square format whereby each volunteer consumes 4 treatments on separate
      occasions. This is a powerful design to assess whether incorporation of phytochemicals from
      Scottish products improves the health benefits of processed food as each volunteer acts as
      his/her own control. Volunteers will be randomly allocated to four groups

        -  Treatment A High polyunsaturated (PUFA) ready meal (ie. burger)

        -  Treatment B High saturated (SFA) fat ready meal

        -  Treatment C High PUFA ready meal incorporating food extract

        -  Treatment D High SFA ready meal incorporating food extract

      There will be a washout period of at least 7 days between each treatment.

      Volunteers:

      Healthy volunteers aged 21 to 60 years will be recruited and attend HNU having fasted from
      22.00h the previous evening on four test days. On arrival, they will be asked to provide a
      urine sample. The volunteers will then have a cannula inserted by a trained nurse and an
      initial baseline blood sample will be taken (volume 10 ml). The subjects will then be asked
      to consume the assigned breakfast within a 15 minute period. Water will be provided.
      Volunteers will then be requested to provide 10ml blood samples at 1h, 2h, 4h and 6h and 24
      hrs. A 24 hr urine sample also will be obtained, starting the day of the test day. Blood
      pressure will be recorded at each time point.

      Volunteers will not be included if they

        -  Are taking any medicines prescribed by their GP

        -  Have a known allergy to beetroot

        -  Are vegetarian or vegan

        -  Regularly take nutritional supplements

        -  Have given a large blood donation in last three months
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lipid peroxides</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Indices of oxidised lipids in plasma</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Systolic and diastolic blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Oxidative Stress</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Burger and Beetroot Study</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Burger and Beetroot Study</intervention_name>
    <description>50% fat, 10% beetroot extract</description>
    <arm_group_label>Burger and Beetroot Study</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  No diagnosed clinical condition

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Are taking any medicines prescribed by their GP Have a known allergy to beetroot Are vegan
        Regularly take nutritional supplements Have given a large blood donation in last three
        months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Garry G Duthie, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Aberdeen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Human Nutrition Unit, Rowett Institute of Nutrition and Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aberdeen</city>
        <state>Scotland</state>
        <zip>AB21 9SB</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 26, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 23, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 20, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 20, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 23, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oxidative stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipid peroxides</keyword>
  <keyword>Phytochemicals</keyword>
  <keyword>Ready meals</keyword>
  <keyword>Beetroot</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood pressure</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

