<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02161913</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHNF-288318</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02161913</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Two Psycho-educational Family Group Interventions for Persons With SCI and Their Caregivers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Two Psycho-educational Family Group Interventions for Persons With SCI and Their Caregivers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Luke's Rehabilitation Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Washington State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Craig H. Neilsen Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Luke's Rehabilitation Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Each year over 12,000 spinal cord injuries (SCI) occur in the United States. These injuries
      result in incredibly difficult, long-term, life adjustments both for patients and their
      caregivers. Many families continue to struggle with the physical, emotional and social
      impacts of SCI for months and years after the injury. Family education and support improves
      the outcomes of other challenging long-term conditions such as Traumatic Brain Injury, but
      little effort has been made to provide such interventions for persons with SCI and their
      caregivers. The proposed study will address this problem by refining and testing a group
      treatment for SCI called Multi-family Group (MFG) intervention. The groups will include
      people with SCI and their primary caregivers, and will be facilitated by an &quot;educator&quot; who is
      a health care provider who works with people with SCI. By providing education about the
      management of SCI and support in an MFG format, quality of life for persons with SCI is
      predicted to be improved. In turn, it is expected that caregivers will also benefit from the
      information, problem-solving activities, and social support that they receive from the
      educators and other group members. The investigators will recruit 32 individuals with SCI who
      have been discharged from inpatient rehabilitation within the previous three years and their
      primary caregivers. Participants will be randomized to the MFG intervention or to an
      education control condition and tested before and after treatment and 6 months following
      treatment. It is hypothesized that participants receiving MFG-SCI will have better outcomes
      than controls on measures of quality of life, health, and adjustment. The study will also
      test whether participants who are more recently discharged from inpatient rehabilitation will
      experience greater benefit from the MFG intervention or the education control intervention.
      If the outcomes support the hypotheses, the MFG intervention should be made available to
      those with SCI and their caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ability to take action to improve one's health from baseline to end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ability to take action to improve one's health will be assessed with the Patient Activation Measure (PAM) and the 8-item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-8). The PAM will measure the degree of individual's knowledge, confidence, and skill to participate in self-management. A higher degree of patient activation has been associated with better health outcomes for adults with chronic conditions. The SF-8 will assess self-reported general health, physical functioning, role-limitations due to physical health problems, bodily pain, and vitality.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in emotion regulation and interpersonal skills from baseline to end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Emotion regulation and interpersonal skills will be assessed with the Anger Expression Scale (AXS), the Abbreviated Duke Social Support Index (ADSSI), and the Family Crisis Oriented Personal Evaluation Scales (F-COPES). The AXS measures anger management including anger-in (suppression of angry feelings), anger-out (expression of anger towards property or people) and anger control (the frequency of attempts to control expressions of anger). The ADSSI measures both subjective support and social network interactions. The F-COPES assesses family-level coping including use of social/spiritual support, reframing negative events, and mobilizing the family to acquire/accept help.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mental health and health behavior from baseline to end of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mental health and health behavior will be assessed for the presence and severity of depressive symptoms, substance use, and in caregivers, burden of care, as these may influence benefits derived from treatment. The 10-item Center for Epidemiologic Study of Depression (CESD-10) will measure depressive symptoms, and the Addiction Severity Index-Lite (ASI-L) will evaluate alcohol and substance use and related problems. The Caregiver Burden Inventory (CBI) will evaluate caregiver burden in four areas: physical, social, emotional and time dependence burden.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ability to take action to improve one's health from baseline to 6-months post-treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Ability to take action to improve one's health will be assessed with the Patient Activation Measure (PAM) and the 8-item Short-Form Health Survey (SF-8). The PAM will measure the degree of individual's knowledge, confidence, and skill to participate in self-management. A higher degree of patient activation has been associated with better health outcomes for adults with chronic conditions. The SF-8 will assess self-reported general health, physical functioning, role-limitations due to physical health problems, bodily pain, and vitality.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in emotion regulation and interpersonal skills from baseline to 6-months post-treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Emotion regulation and interpersonal skills will be assessed with the Anger Expression Scale (AXS), the Abbreviated Duke Social Support Index (ADSSI), and the Family Crisis Oriented Personal Evaluation Scales (F-COPES). The AXS measures anger management including anger-in (suppression of angry feelings), anger-out (expression of anger towards property or people) and anger control (the frequency of attempts to control expressions of anger). The ADSSI measures both subjective support and social network interactions. The F-COPES assesses family-level coping including use of social/spiritual support, reframing negative events, and mobilizing the family to acquire/accept help.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mental health and health behavior from baseline to 6-months post-treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mental health and health behavior will be assessed for the presence and severity of depressive symptoms, substance use, and in caregivers, burden of care, as these may influence benefits derived from treatment. The 10-item Center for Epidemiologic Study of Depression (CESD-10) will measure depressive symptoms, and the Addiction Severity Index-Lite (ASI-L) will evaluate alcohol and substance use and related problems. The Caregiver Burden Inventory (CBI) will evaluate caregiver burden in four areas: physical, social, emotional and time dependence burden.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SCI Education Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The SCIEC condition is a 16-session, highly structured educational intervention that provides information on how SCI affects the body; methods for maximizing function, coping, and living with SCI; and staying healthy with SCI. It also includes general guidelines for improving health behavior. Each SCIEC session follows the same structure, beginning with a presentation of the objectives for the current session and a brief review of material from the previous session before introducing the session's topic and presenting information on one or two key problem areas. SCIEC utilizes a traditional didactic model with information delivered by an expert SCI educator in a classroom or lecture setting.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multi-family Group Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The MFG Program uses a structured problem-solving and skills training program to provide participants with SCI and their caregivers with tools and information to improve coping and help family members to connect through positive behavioral exchanges. MFG educators are health professionals with experience in management of SCI, such as physical therapists, recreational therapists, occupational therapists, and psychologists. MFG will last for 16 sessions across 9 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multi-Family Group Treatment</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Multi-family Group Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SCI Education Control Group</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SCI Education Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  For Person with SCI: quadriplegia or paraplegia due to an acquired injury with
             complete or incomplete lesion as defined by ASIA

          -  For person with SCI: discharge from inpatient rehabilitation within the previous 3
             years

          -  For Person with SCI: age 18 years or older

          -  For Person with SCI: mobility impairment as the result of the SCI

          -  For Person with SCI: living in the community in a non-group setting after injury

          -  For Person with SCI: planning to remain in the geographic area for at least 12 months

          -  For Person with SCI: competency in English

          -  For Caregiver of Person with SCI: provision of instrumental or emotional support for a
             spouse, relative, partner, or friend with SCI for at least the past 6 months

          -  For Caregiver of Person with SCI: having regular contact with the individual with SCI
             (at least a minimum of 2 hours face-to-face contact per week)

          -  For Caregiver of Person with SCI: living with or near the individual with SCI

          -  For Caregiver of Person with SCI: over the age of 18

          -  For Caregiver of Person with SCI: having a telephone

          -  For Caregiver of Person with SCI: planning to remain in the geographic area for at
             least 12 months

          -  For Caregiver of Person with SCI: competency in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  For Person with SCI or Caregiver: terminal illness with life expectancy of less than
             12 months

          -  For Person with SCI or Caregiver: in active treatment for cancer

          -  For Person with SCI or Caregiver: blind or deaf

          -  For Person with SCI or Caregiver: moderate to severe cognitive impairment (defined at
             screening as a score on the Short Portable Mental Status Questionnaire &gt; 4 errors)

          -  For Person with SCI or Caregiver: severely high level of depression symptoms (defined
             at screening as a score on the CES-D &gt;30)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dennis G. Dyck, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Douglas L. Weeks, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Luke's Rehabilitation Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Douglas L. Weeks, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>509-939-1316</phone>
    <email>WeeksDL@inhs.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Luke's Rehabilitation Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Douglas L. Weeks, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>509-939-1316</phone>
      <email>WeeksDL@inhs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dennis G. Dyck, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Douglas L. Weeks, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 10, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 12, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Luke's Rehabilitation Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Douglas L. Weeks</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

