<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02168660</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UT092010-217</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02168660</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Correction of Vitamin D Levels and Its Effect on Insulin Resistance and Weight Gain in Obese Youth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Normalization of Vitamin D Levels and Its Effect on Glucose Homeostasis in Obese Youth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vitamin D deficiency is extremely common in obese youth. In our obese population followed in
      the Endocrinology clinic at CMC, vitamin D levels were inversely correlated with a measure of
      insulin resistance. We propose to show that correction of vitamin D levels in obese children
      and adolescents improves their insulin sensitivity. Obese youth presenting to the Center for
      Obesity and its Consequences on Health (COACH) clinic will be randomized to receive either
      the most recent Institute of Medicine (IOM) recommendations of minimum D3 dose of 600 IU/day
      (1), or receive higher doses of D3 such that the blood levels of vitamin D will be brought to
      a target level in either the low part or high part of the normal range. The goal is to
      determine if correction of vitamin D deficiency will improve insulin sensitivity in this
      group. Secondary goals include determining whether correction of vitamin D deficiency in
      obese adolescents and children results in less weight gain, and determining the amount of D3
      required to correct vitamin D levels in this population.

      Our specific hypotheses are as follows:

      Hypothesis #1 Obese youth treated with Vitamin D3 who achieve low-normal 25-OHD levels (30-50
      ng/mL) or high-normal 25-OHD levels (60-80 ng/mL) will have improved insulin resistance, as
      measured by HOMA-IR, compared to those individuals with deficient 25-OHD levels (&lt; 30 ng/mL).

      Hypothesis #2 Subjects with a higher BMI will have higher Vitamin D dose requirements than
      current IOM recommendations of 600 IU/day and will take a longer period of time to reach
      target 25-OHD levels.

      Hypothesis #3 Subjects with normal 25-OHD levels will demonstrate less weight gain compared
      to subjects on the control arm.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Concise Summary of Project: The proposed study is a prospective, unblinded dose-ranging trial
      to examine in obese youth 1) the effect of correcting Vitamin D (Vit D) deficiency on insulin
      resistance, 2) the effect of correcting Vit D deficiency on weight gain, and 3) the amount of
      Vit D3 required to achieve Vit D sufficiency in obese adolescents. Subjects will be recruited
      from obese children and adolescents aged 6 to 17 years presenting to the COACH clinic, a
      referral clinic for obese children at Children's Medical Center of Dallas. Approximately 1300
      new patients are seen in the COACH clinic each year. Ethnicity will be self-assigned as
      African-American, Caucasian, Hispanic, or Other. The ethnic makeup of the COACH clinic over
      the last 20 months was as follows: African-American 25%, Caucasian 19.5%, Hispanic 52%, and
      Other 3.5%.

      As per standard practice in the COACH clinic, a height (cm), weight (kg), and blood pressure
      will be obtained, and body mass index (kg/m2) calculated for each patient. Fasting total
      cholesterol, LDL, HDL, triglyceride, 25-OHD, Hemoglobin A1c (A1c), and fasting insulin will
      be obtained, and an Oral Glucose Tolerance Test (OGTT) performed. The baseline estimate of
      insulin sensitivity is calculated from the fasting insulin and glucose values, and reported
      as the HOMA-IR. After Informed Consent has been obtained, participants will be randomized to
      either the Control group (5000 IU/wk), the Low-normal 25-OHD group (target 25-OHD 30-50
      ng/mL), or the High-normal 25-OHD group (target 25-OHD 60-80 ng/mL). A 25-OHD &lt; 25 ng/mL will
      be confirmed. These groups will be matched for age (6-12 years versus 13-17 years) and
      ethnicity (Caucasian versus African-American verus Hispanic). Approximately 60 patients will
      be recruited for each group. Subject participation will continue until Vit D sufficiency has
      been documented for 4 consecutive months, at which point the fasting insulin and glucose
      values will be repeated for calculation of HOMA-IR and assessment of insulin sensitivity, and
      amount of weight gain will be measured.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>log delta HOMA-IR versus delta 25-OHD</measure>
    <time_frame>end of study (4-12 mo)</time_frame>
    <description>Log base 10 of the change in HOMA-IR from initial visit to end of study visit versus the change in serum 25-OH vitamin D levels.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to normalization of Vit D level versus BMI Z score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The time required to reach a normal Vitamin D level (&gt; 30) versus BMI Z score at each vitamin D3 dose; OR vitamin D level at 6 weeks versus BMI Z score at each starting vitamin D3 dose.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>delta BMI Z score versus delta 25-OHD level</measure>
    <time_frame>study end, 4-12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change in BMI Z score from initial to study end versus the change in serum 25-OH D level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Insulin Resistance</condition>
  <condition>Vitamin D Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard vitamin D3 dose as per IOM (Institute of Medicine) recommendations; actual dose will be 5000 IU per week, which is just slightly higher than the IOM recommendation of 600 IU per day. Length of time proposed to be 4 months at 5000 IU D3 per week. End of study measures at 4 months to be HOMA-IR, BMI Z score, 25-OH D level.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low-Normal Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Initial D3 dose will be 30,000 IU per week; at 6 week intervals serum D3 levels will be checked, and dose adjustments made to reach target 25-OHD level of between 30-50 ng/mL (inclusive). Once within target, D3 dose will be continued for 4 months, and end of study measurements done (HOMA-IR, BMI Z score, 25-OHD level).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High-Normal Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Initial D3 dose will be 60,000 IU/week; at 6 week intervals 25-OHD levels will be done, and dose adjustments made to achieve target level of 40-60 ng/mL (inclusive). Once within target range, De3 dose will be continued for 4 months, and end of study measures obtained (HOMA-IR, BMI Z score, 25-OHD level).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin D3</intervention_name>
    <description>Vitamin D3, liquid formulation, 5000 IU/mL.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low-Normal Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High-Normal Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>calcidiol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age 6-17 years

          -  BMI &gt; 95% for age

          -  serum 25-OH D level &lt; or + to 25 ng/mL

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI &lt; 95% for age

          -  serum 25-OH D level &gt; 25 ng/mL

          -  current Vitamin D supplementation &gt; 400 IU/day

          -  anti-convulsant therapy, anti-hypertensive therapy, lipid lowering medication

          -  any medications that affect glucose metabolism (e.g., metformin, insulin)

          -  daily glucocorticoid therapy

          -  diabetes

          -  any disorders of bone or calcium metabolism

          -  hepatic or renal disease

          -  any malabsorptive disorder

          -  baseline serum Calcium &gt; 11 ng/dL (&gt; 2 SD above the mean)

          -  any genetic disorder that predisposes to obesity (e.g., Prader Willi

          -  hypothalamic obesity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michele R Hutchison, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olson ML, Maalouf NM, Oden JD, White PC, Hutchison MR. Vitamin D deficiency in obese children and its relationship to glucose homeostasis. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2012 Jan;97(1):279-85. doi: 10.1210/jc.2011-1507. Epub 2011 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22072738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ross AC, Manson JE, Abrams SA, Aloia JF, Brannon PM, Clinton SK, Durazo-Arvizu RA, Gallagher JC, Gallo RL, Jones G, Kovacs CS, Mayne ST, Rosen CJ, Shapses SA. The 2011 report on dietary reference intakes for calcium and vitamin D from the Institute of Medicine: what clinicians need to know. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2011 Jan;96(1):53-8. doi: 10.1210/jc.2010-2704. Epub 2010 Nov 29.</citation>
    <PMID>21118827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mansbach JM, Ginde AA, Camargo CA Jr. Serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D levels among US children aged 1 to 11 years: do children need more vitamin D? Pediatrics. 2009 Nov;124(5):1404-10. doi: 10.1542/peds.2008-2041. Erratum in: Pediatrics. 2009 Dec;124(6):1709.</citation>
    <PMID>19951983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rajakumar K, Fernstrom JD, Holick MF, Janosky JE, Greenspan SL. Vitamin D status and response to Vitamin D(3) in obese vs. non-obese African American children. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2008 Jan;16(1):90-5. doi: 10.1038/oby.2007.23.</citation>
    <PMID>18223618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bischoff-Ferrari HA, Giovannucci E, Willett WC, Dietrich T, Dawson-Hughes B. Estimation of optimal serum concentrations of 25-hydroxyvitamin D for multiple health outcomes. Am J Clin Nutr. 2006 Jul;84(1):18-28. Review. Erratum in: Am J Clin Nutr. 2006 Nov;84(5):1253. Dosage error in published abstract; MEDLINE/PubMed abstract corrected. Am J Clin Nutr. 2007 Sep;86(3):809. Dosage error in published abstract; MEDLINE/PubMed abstract corrected.</citation>
    <PMID>16825677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagpal J, Pande JN, Bhartia A. A double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled trial of the short-term effect of vitamin D3 supplementation on insulin sensitivity in apparently healthy, middle-aged, centrally obese men. Diabet Med. 2009 Jan;26(1):19-27. doi: 10.1111/j.1464-5491.2008.02636.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19125756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>von Hurst PR, Stonehouse W, Coad J. Vitamin D supplementation reduces insulin resistance in South Asian women living in New Zealand who are insulin resistant and vitamin D deficient - a randomised, placebo-controlled trial. Br J Nutr. 2010 Feb;103(4):549-55. doi: 10.1017/S0007114509992017. Epub 2009 Sep 28.</citation>
    <PMID>19781131</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alemzadeh R, Kichler J, Babar G, Calhoun M. Hypovitaminosis D in obese children and adolescents: relationship with adiposity, insulin sensitivity, ethnicity, and season. Metabolism. 2008 Feb;57(2):183-91. doi: 10.1016/j.metabol.2007.08.023.</citation>
    <PMID>18191047</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maalouf J, Nabulsi M, Vieth R, Kimball S, El-Rassi R, Mahfoud Z, El-Hajj Fuleihan G. Short- and long-term safety of weekly high-dose vitamin D3 supplementation in school children. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2008 Jul;93(7):2693-701. doi: 10.1210/jc.2007-2530. Epub 2008 Apr 29.</citation>
    <PMID>18445674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 17, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 17, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 20, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 17, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 17, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 20, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michele Hutchison</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin D Deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D Deficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholecalciferol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

