<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02164279</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12 356 03</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-A01097-36</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02164279</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validation of Biomarkers of Diabetic Nephropathy in Type I Diabetic Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>peeDIAB2</acronym>
  <official_title>Identification and First Validation of Early Non-invasive Biomarkers of Diabetic Nephropathy in Type I Diabetic Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Toulouse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Laboratory Inserm U858 Team 5 – RF-lab</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Toulouse</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      About 30 to 40% of patients suffering from type I diabetes are at risk of developing a
      diabetic nephropathy (DN) leading more or less rapidly to an end-stage renal disease.
      Nowadays, the microalbuminuria is the most often used clinical parameter for possible onset
      of DN. However, it is a late (because it permits to detect a renal disease already present),
      non-specific and low sensitive biomarker.

      Therefore the main objective of this study is to identify early urinary biomarkers predictive
      of DN in children with type I diabetes, before the appearance of a microalbuminuria.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Once the type I diabetes is diagnosed, the speed of progression to a DN is very variable.
      Thus, the discovery of biomarkers able to distinguish progressor patients from non-progressor
      since the appearance of a microalbuminuria, is crucial in order to take care of progressor
      patients the earlier and to slow down the disease progression.

      The investigators have shown that urine is a biological sample extremely well suited for
      proteome analysis with the aim to identify biomarkers of renal damages. Indeed, they were the
      first to analyze the urinary proteome of infant using capillary electrophoresis-coupled mass
      spectrometry. This technic permits to analyse the entire urinary proteome of a person in one
      hour.

      Several laboratories tried to identify other predictive urinary biomarkers of the development
      of a DN in diabetic patients, but with limited success and nowadays in the clinical practice
      they still use the measure of the microalbuminuria. Contrary to precedent studies, the
      investigators develop an analysis without a priori and starting with early samples (without
      any signs of DN) associating the urinary peptide profile with the DN progression over 9-10
      years.

      This is a nested case-control study in a cohort of 317 patients constituting the urinary
      biological collection. (The urinary samples of a type I diabetic cohort of 317 patients seen
      between 2004 and 2008 have been collected.) These patients will be contacted at the end of
      2012 to obtain a number of participation of 180 patients authorizing the use aposteriori of
      their urinary samples. Among this cohort, the investigators evaluate at 90 the number of
      patients with a DN defined by a dosage of microalbuminuria higher than 100 mg/L.

      The primary endpoint of this study is therefore the identification of urinary biomarkers
      predictive of DN in type I diabetes pediatric patients.

      The secondary endpoints are :

        -  The estimation of sensibility and specificity parameters, and the Area Under the Curve
           (AUC).

        -  The identification of factors associated with the variability of biomarkers expression
           such as the age at the moment of the diagnosis, the time between the diagnosis and the
           urinary collection, the rate of microalbuminuria, and the type of insulin used by the
           patient.

        -  And in the subgroup of patients for whom two urinary samples have been collected, the
           investigators want to study the urinary proteome stability in patients with no DN in
           2013.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify predictive non-invasive urinary biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Inclusion day)</time_frame>
    <description>Urinary samples collection Assessment of the microalbuminuria to diagnose the diabetic nephropathy (DN)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relation of urinary markers with patient characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Inclusion day)</time_frame>
    <description>Patients characteristics : age of the patients at the diabetes diagnosis, their age at the urinary collection, their sex, the time between the diagnosis and the urinary collection, the type of insulin used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus With Diabetic Nephropathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Progressor (ND)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group of patients with an albuminuria &gt; 100mg/L, by Urinary sample collection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Progressor (non-ND)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group of patients without an albuminuria &gt; 100mg/L, by Urinary sample collection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Urinary sample collection</intervention_name>
    <description>urinary sample collection will be done at the inclusion visit for the assessment of the microalbuminuria ( &lt; or &gt; than 100mg/L)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Progressor (ND)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Progressor (non-ND)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with a type I diabetes diagnosed before 15 years-old

          -  Urinary collection done 5 years after the diagnosis

          -  Urinary collection done without any acute intermittent pathology

          -  Urinary collection done without any treatment (other than diabetes treatment)

          -  Glomerular filtration rate ≥ 60 mL/min at the moment of the urinary collection already
             done

          -  Informed consent obtained aposteriori for the analysis of the urinary samples
             collected between 2004 and 2008, and consent obtained for the analysis of urinary
             sample collected in 2013

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients suffering from an autoimmune disease associated with the diabetes (vitiligo,
             Grave's disease, thyroiditis, pernicious anemia or Biermer's disease)

          -  Patient with a renal disease (other than diabetic nephropathy) at the first urinary
             collection (between 2004 and 2008)

          -  Pregnancy, because the urinary proteome and the microalbumin dosage can be modified
             during a pregnancy.

          -  Patient refusal to use urinary samples already collected
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephane DECRAMER, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Toulouse University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Purpan Children Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rangueil Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 12, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 16, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 11, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 11, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 12, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Microalbuminuria</keyword>
  <keyword>diabetic nephropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>type I diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>early predictive urinary biomarkers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Nephropathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

