<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02272595</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PA12-0381</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02272595</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rational Therapeutics Based on Matched Tumor and Normal Tissue</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Select Rational Therapeutics Based on the Analysis of Matched Tumor and Normal Biopsies in Subjects With Advanced Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Commission</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this laboratory research study is to learn if using molecular information
      (matched therapy) or not using molecular information and having the study doctor choose the
      therapy based on your past experience are more effective ways to choose the best cancer
      treatment for you.

      This is an investigational study.

      Up to 200 participants will take part in this study. Up to 50 will be enrolled at MD
      Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If you agree to take part in this study, your tumor tissue and blood samples will be tested
      for molecular profiling. Molecular profiling is the classification of tissue based on the
      expression of certain genes within a tumor compared to normal tissue. This may be used to
      predict how the tumor responds to therapy. Your doctor may use the results of the molecular
      profiling to help decide which treatment might be the most beneficial for the disease.

      Study Procedures:

      Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn and you will have a tumor biopsy and a biopsy of
      normal tissue when you enroll in this study. Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn again
      about 2-3 weeks after you begin treatment. The type of biopsy you have will depend on the
      type of disease you have. The risks of this procedure will be discussed in more detail with
      you.

      If there is not enough tissue with which the study doctor can perform the study tests
      (described below), you may need to have a second biopsy. The study staff will discuss this
      with you if it is needed.

      Treatment Arms:

      A series of tests to find which gene mutations you have, if any, will be performed. Depending
      on the results of your molecular testing, you may be enrolled on 1 of 2 arms.

      If your molecular profile shows that you have a gene mutation that may benefit from study
      drugs that are believed to target your gene mutation, you will be enrolled in Arm A and will
      receive these targeted drugs.

      If your molecular profile shows that you do not have a gene mutation, you will be enrolled in
      Arm B. In Arm B, the doctor will choose a therapy based on other studies rather than gene
      mutation.

      Length of Study:

      This study will last about 2 years. Your participation on this study will be complete after
      the last blood draw and tumor biopsy is collected.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 - 3 weeks after treatment begins</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-free survival (PFS) of the last therapeutic line (PFS1) before entering into study, with the PFS2 under study treatment. A clinical meaningful improvement is defined as demonstrating a PFS ratio (PFS2/PFS1) of being 1.5 or better.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Cancers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A - Treatment Based on Genetic Mutation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participant's molecular profile shows that they have a gene mutation that may benefit from study drugs that are believed to target their gene mutation. Participant assigned to Arm A and will receive these targeted drugs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B - Treatment Based on No Genetic Mutation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participant's molecular profile shows that they do not have a gene mutation. Participant assigned to Arm B in which doctor chooses a therapy based on other studies rather than gene mutation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment Based on Genetic Mutation</intervention_name>
    <description>Participant's molecular profile shows that they have a gene mutation that may benefit from study drugs that are believed to target their gene mutation. Participant assigned to Arm A and will receive these targeted drugs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A - Treatment Based on Genetic Mutation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment Based on No Genetic Mutation</intervention_name>
    <description>Participant's molecular profile shows that they do not have a gene mutation. Participant assigned to Arm B in which doctor chooses a therapy based on other studies rather than gene mutation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B - Treatment Based on No Genetic Mutation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood (about 2 teaspoons) drawn initially and again about 2-3 weeks after chosen treatment
      begins.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Cancer patients from University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center in Houston, Texas,
        Cancer Institute Gustave Roussy in Villejuif, France, Vall D'Hebron University Hospital in
        Barcelona, Spain, and Chaim Sheba Medical Center at Tel Hasomer in Ramat Gan, Israel
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Informed consent

          2. Any histologic type of metastatic cancer, (except for lung and brain at US sites), in
             which histologic normal counterpart can be obtained. See list of cancer types included
             in the trial in Appendix 1.

          3. Progression by RECIST (Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors) or other criteria
             on at least one prior regimen for advanced disease

          4. Ability to undergo a biopsy or surgical procedure to obtain fresh tumor biopsy paired
             with its normal counterpart

          5. Age from 18 years

          6. Life expectancy of at least 3 months

          7. ECOG Performance status of 0 to 1

          8. Measurable or evaluable disease according to RECIST 1.1 criteria

          9. For US sites only: advanced cancer patients that have exhausted all effective therapy
             for their disease and have progressed after previous line of therapy (documented
             disease progression under last treatment received) and conventional methods of
             assigning new therapy would not be expected to increase survival by more than 3
             months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. For US sites only: Any patient that might require a lung or brain biopsy are excluded

          2. Alteration of organ function or hematopoietic function as defined by the following
             criteria:

               1. Serum aspartate transaminase (AST) and serum alanine transaminase (ALT) &gt;2.5 x
                  upper limit of normal (ULN), except for patients with liver metastases, for which
                  AST and ALT &gt; 5.0 ULN is the exclusion criteria.

               2. Bilirubin &gt; 2.0 ULN to allow for Gilberts

               3. Polynuclear neutrophil &lt; 1.5 x 109/L

               4. Platelets &lt; 100 x 10 9/L

               5. Hemoglobin &lt; 90 g/L

               6. Creatinine &gt; 1.5 ULN

             i. Calcemia &gt; 1.5 ULN g. Phosphatemia &gt; 1.5 ULN

          3. Coagulation abnormality prohibiting a biopsy

          4. Symptomatic or progressive brain metastases detected by radio imaging, or meningeal

          5. Patient who received a personalized therapeutic treatment based on molecular anomaly
             during the treatment period immediately prior to the WINTHER directed treatment
             (defining the PFS1). Hormonal therapy may be continued during WINTHER suggested
             therapy. The exclusion of prior matched targeted therapy includes but is not limited
             to all targeted therapeutics that are EMA approved and genomically matched to
             patients. If there are questions about whether or not a prior therapy is a matched
             targeted treatment it will be agreed on by discussion between PIs who are also
             Clinical Management Committee members; the resolution should take place prior to
             starting Winther directed treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Apostolia M. Tsimberidou, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Apostolia M. Tsimberidou, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-4259</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Institute Gustave Roussy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif</city>
        <zip>94805</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chaim Sheba Medical Center at Tel Hasomer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ramat Gan</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vall D'Hebron University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 20, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 21, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 23, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biologic Markers</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular testing</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced cancers</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular information</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular profiling</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic Mutation</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coal Tar</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

