<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02279485</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E2007-A001-048</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02279485</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Demonstrate Bioequivalence Between a 12-mg Dose of an Oral Suspension Formulation of Perampanel and a 12-mg Tablet Formulation of Perampanel Under Fasted and Fed Conditions in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-Label, Crossover Study to Demonstrate Bioequivalence Between a 12-mg Dose of an Oral Suspension Formulation of Perampanel and a 12-mg Tablet Formulation of Perampanel Under Fasted and Fed Conditions in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eisai Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eisai Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label, 2-arm, single-dose, randomized crossover study. The study will enroll
      a total of 100 subjects (2 arms with 50 subjects in each arm). In Arm 1, bioequivalence
      between the oral suspension and tablet formulations of perampanel will be evaluated under
      fasted conditions; in Arm 2, bioequivalence between the oral suspension and tablet
      formulations will be evaluated under fed conditions. In both study arms, subjects will be
      randomized on Study Day 1 for Treatment Period 1 to receive a single 12-mg dose for
      perampanel as either oral suspension or a tablet, and will then receive the alternative
      treatment on Study Day 43 of Treatment Period 2. Drug administration will be separated by a
      washout of at least 6 weeks between the two treatment periods.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of Perampanel: AUC(0-t)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 504 hours postdose in each treatment period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of Perampanel: AUC(0-inf)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 504 hours postdose in each treatment period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of Perampanel: Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 504 hours postdose in each treatment period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of Perampanel: AUC(0-72h)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 504 hours postdose in each treatment period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of Perampanel: tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 504 hours postdose in each treatment period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of Perampanel: tlag</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 504 hours postdose in each treatment period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of Perampanel: Lambda-z</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 504 hours postdose in each treatment period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of Perampanel: t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 504 hours postdose in each treatment period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Subjects</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Perampanel - Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment A: Single oral dose of a 12-mg perampanel tablet under fasted condition.
Treatment B: Single 12 mg dose of perampanel oral suspension under fasted condition.
Subjects will be randomized on Study Day 1 for Treatment Period 1 to Treatment A or Treatment B. On Study Day 43 the subject will then receive the alternate Treatment for Treatment Period 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Perampanel - Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment C: Single oral dose of a 12-mg perampanel tablet co-administered with high fat meal.
Treatment D: Single 12 mg dose of perampanel oral suspension co-administered with high fat meal.
Subjects will be randomized on Study Day 1 for Treatment Period 1 to Treatment C or Treatment D. On Study Day 43 the subject will then receive the alternate Treatment for Treatment Period 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Perampanel</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Perampanel - Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Perampanel - Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Healthy males or females, ages 18 to 55 years, inclusive, at the time of informed
             consent.

          2. Body mass index (BMI) of 18 to 32 kg/m2, inclusive at Screening.

          3. Females must not be lactating or pregnant at Screening or Baseline.

          4. Females of childbearing potential must not have had unprotected sexual intercourse
             within 30 days before study entry and must agree to use a highly effective method of
             contraception (eg, total abstinence, a doublebarrier method [such as condom plus
             diaphragm with spermicide], have a vasectomized partner with confirmed azoospermia, or
             an intrauterine device, contraceptive implant, or oral contraceptive that does not
             contain levogesterol) throughout the entire study period and for 30 days after study
             drug discontinuation. Females using hormonal contraceptives containing levogesterol
             must be on another form of contraception (such as double barrier method.) as well. If
             currently abstinent, the subject must agree to use a doublebarrier method as described
             above if she becomes sexually active during the study period or for 30 days after
             study drug discontinuation. Females who are using hormonal contraceptives must have
             been on a stable dose of the same hormonal contraceptive product for at least 4 weeks
             before dosing and must continue to use the same contraceptive during the study and for
             30 days after study drug discontinuation. All females will be considered to be of
             childbearing potential unless they are postmenopausal (amenorrheic for at least 12
             consecutive months, in the appropriate age group, and without other known or suspected
             cause) or have been sterilized surgically (i.e. bilateral tubal ligation, total
             hysterectomy, or bilateral oophorectomy, all with surgery at least 1 month before
             dosing).

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Clinically significant illness that requires medical treatment within 8 weeks or a
             clinically significant infection that requires medical attention within 4 weeks of
             dosing.

          2. Evidence of disease that may influence the outcome of the study within 4 weeks of
             dosing, eg, psychiatric disorders and disorders of the gastrointestinal tract, liver,
             kidney, respiratory system, endocrine system, hematological system, neurological
             system, cardiovascular system, or subjects who have a congenital abnormality in
             metabolism.

          3. Any history of gastrointestinal surgery that may affect PK profiles of perampanel, eg,
             hepatectomy, nephrotomy, cholecystectomy, digestive organ resection or any
             gastrointestinal procedure for the purpose of weight loss (including Lapband), which
             would slow gastric emptying.

          4. Any clinically abnormal symptom or organ impairment found by medical history at
             Screening, and physical examinations, vital signs, electrocardiogram (ECG) finding, or
             laboratory test results that require medical treatment at Screening or Baseline.

          5. Any laboratory abnormalities considered clinically significant by the investigator.

          6. A prolonged QT/QTc interval (QTc greater than 450 msec) as demonstrated upon repeat
             ECG at Screening or Baseline.

          7. History of prolonged QT/QTc interval.

          8. History of risk factors for torsade de pointes (eg, heart failure, hypokalemia, family
             history of long QT syndrome).

          9. History of ischemic heart disease (eg, acute coronary syndromes, stable angina),
             syncope or cardiac arrhythmias.

         10. Siting heart rate less than 40 or greater than 100 beats/min at Screening or Baseline
             Period 1 and sitting systolic blood pressure greater than 140 mmHg or less than 90
             mmHg or diastolic blood pressure greater than 90 mmHg or less than 60 mmHg at
             Screening or Baseline.

         11. Hemoglobin less than 11.5 g/dLfor females and less than 12.5 g/dL for males at screen
             and Baseline check-in Period 1.

         12. Subjects who experienced a weight loss or gain of greater than 10% between Screening
             and before dosing.

         13. Subjects who received blood products within 4 weeks, donated blood within 8 weeks, or
             donated plasma within 1 week of dosing.

         14. Hypersensitivity to the study drug or any of its excipients.

         15. Known history of food allergies or presently experiencing significant seasonal or
             perennial allergy at Screening.

         16. Known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive at Screening.

         17. Active viral hepatitis (B or C) as demonstrated by positive serology at Screening.

         18. History of use of illegal (or legalized) recreational drugs in the past year.

         19. History of drug or alcohol dependency or abuse within approximately the last 2 years
             or who have a positive urine drug test or breath alcohol test at Screening or
             Baseline.

         20. Engagement in strenuous exercise within 2 weeks before dosing (eg, marathon runners,
             weight lifters).

         21. Currently enrolled in another clinical trial or used any investigational drug or
             device within 30 days preceding informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 15, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 29, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 2, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 2, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy Subjects</keyword>
  <keyword>Bioequivalence</keyword>
  <keyword>Fasted</keyword>
  <keyword>Fed</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

