<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02270918</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14P.366</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02270918</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reversibility of Apixaban Anticoagulation With the Four Factor Prothrombin Complex Concentrate Kcentra</brief_title>
  <acronym>4PAR</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase I Placebo-Controlled, Open-Label, Crossover Study to Assess the Reversibility of Apixaban Anticoagulation With the Four Factor Prothrombin Complex Concentrate Kcentra in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CSL Behring</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Apixaban is an anticoagulant (also known as blood thinner) approved by the Food and Drug
      Administration (FDA) for reducing the risk of stroke and systemic embolism in patients with
      non-valvular atrial fibrillation. It has no reliable method of reversal. Kcentra is an FDA
      approved drug derived from blood that is used as an antidote to treat people with bleeding
      associated with taking the well-known anticoagulant warfarin. This is a Phase I,
      placebo-controlled, single site, open-label, crossover trial to evaluate the reversibility
      apixaban anticoagulation with Kcentra.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Oral anticoagulants are effective in the treatment and prevention of venous and arterial
      thrombotic events. For more than 50 years the only class of anticoagulant available had been
      the vitamin K antagonist (VKA), warfarin, which requires frequent blood work for monitoring.
      Apixaban is a new approved anticoagulant that is used to treat patients who have blood clots
      or are at risk for developing blood clots. Unlike warfarin, the use of apixaban does not
      require frequent blood work for monitoring and is associated with lower bleeding risk. All
      anticoagulation therapies are associated with spontaneous or provoked bleeding risk and
      reversal of their blood thinning effects might be needed. Reversal of anticoagulation may
      also be needed in cases where emergent or urgent surgery is indicated. There is currently no
      available reversal agent for apixaban. Prothrombin complex concentrate (PCC) contain clotting
      factors and can replace factors inhibited by anticoagulants. In a recent study in the
      Netherlands a four factor prothrombin complex concentrate, Cofact (not available in the USA)
      was shown to be able to reverse the anticoagulation effects of another factor Xa inhibitor,
      rivaroxaban. Kcentra is a four factor prothrombin complex concentrate that was FDA approved
      in 2013 and is used as an antidote to treat people with bleeding associated with taking
      warfarin. It contains clotting factors II, VII, IX and X derived from donated blood and could
      be effective in reversing the anticoagulation effects of the factor Xa inhibitor, apixaban.
      No effective reversal agent for apixaban exists. Physicians struggle with bleeding in
      patients who are on apixaban. Indeed, this is not an uncommon problem for patients who suffer
      brain bleeds or trauma. This study could potentially identify Kcentra as reversal agent for
      patients taking apixaban. This study will test the hypothesis that Kcentra has the potential
      to significantly reduce the anticoagulation effect of apixaban as measured by thrombin
      generation assay at 30 minutes post infusion of Kcentra as compared to placebo infusion in
      subjects dosed to steady state with apixaban.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>thrombin generation assay (TGA)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-factor Xa activity</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>prothrombin time (PT)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>activated partial thromboplastin time (PTT)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Thrombosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Apixaban with Kcentra</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral apixaban will be administered to steady state in healthy volunteers followed by a single infusion of prothrombin complex concentrate Kcentra at 25 units/Kg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Apixaban with placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral apixaban will be administered to steady state in healthy volunteers followed by a single infusion of saline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Kcentra</intervention_name>
    <description>IV infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Apixaban with Kcentra</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>4 factor prothrombin complex concentrate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Apixaban</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Apixaban with Kcentra</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Apixaban with placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Apixaban with placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  In order to be eligible for participation in this trial, the subject must:

               1. Be a healthy male or female between ages 18-55 (inclusive) at the screening visit

               2. Have a body mass index (BMI) &gt;19 and &lt;33 (inclusive)

               3. If a female, subject

                    1. Can be of childbearing potential and must demonstrate a urine β-hCG level
                       consistent with the nongravid state at the pretrial (screening) visit and
                       agree to use (and/or have their partner use) an acceptable method of birth
                       control beginning at the pretrial visit throughout the trial (including
                       washout intervals between treatment periods) and until 2 weeks after the
                       last dose of trial drug in the last treatment period.

                    2. Can be of non-childbearing potential which is defined as: a female who is
                       postmenopausal without menses for at least 1 year and an Follicle
                       stimulating hormone value in the postmenopausal range upon pretrial
                       (screening) evaluation and/or a female who is status post hysterectomy,
                       oophorectomy or tubal ligation

                    3. Must be off hormonal oral or transdermal contraceptives for at least 4 weeks
                       prior to initial dose of trial drug

               4. Be a nonsmoker for at least approximately 6 months

               5. Have serum creatinine level &lt; 1.5 mg/dL

               6. Have a prothrombin time (PT) and activated partial thromboplastin time (PTT)
                  level below the upper limit of normal

               7. Have platelet count within normal limits

               8. Be willing to refrain from the use of anticoagulants and antiplatelet medications
                  including aspirin and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) during the
                  entire period of study participation

               9. Be willing to provide written informed consent for the trial

              10. Be willing to comply with trial restrictions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has a history of clinically significant endocrine, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular,
             hematological, hepatic, immunological, renal, respiratory, genitourinary or major
             neurological (including stroke and chronic seizures) abnormalities or diseases

          2. Has history of cancer (excluding treated cutaneous squamous or basal cell carcinoma of
             &gt;3 years previous)

          3. Has history of venous or arterial thromboembolic disease

          4. Has a history of clinically significant bleeding risks including prior serious head
             trauma

          5. Has had major surgery within 6 months prior to screening visit

          6. Is unable to refrain from or anticipates the use of any medication, including
             prescription and non-prescription drugs or herbal remedies for 2 weeks prior to trial
             start date until the post-trial visit

          7. Is unable to refrain from using any drugs or substance known to be inhibitors or
             inducers of cytochrome P450 (CYP) enzymes including grapefruit products for 2 weeks
             prior to dosing and throughout the study, until the post-trial visit

          8. Has a history of illicit drug abuse within six months prior to screening visit

          9. Consumes greater than 3 glasses of alcoholic beverages (1 glass is approximately
             equivalent to: beer [354 mL/12 ounces], wine [118 mL/4 ounces], or distilled spirits
             [29.5 mL/1 ounce]) per day and cannot refrain from alcohol for the duration of the
             trial

         10. Has a history of significant multiple and/or severe allergies (e.g. food, drug), or
             has had an anaphylactic reaction or significant intolerability to prescription or
             non-prescription drugs or food

         11. Has known anaphylactic or severe systemic reactions to any components of study drugs
             (including heparin induced thrombocytopenia) or contraindication to the administration
             of PCC or any other related blood products.

         12. Has moderate or severe hepatic disease or other clinically relevant bleeding risk

         13. Has positive history for hepatitis B surface antigen, hepatitis C or HIV

         14. Has first degree relatives with history of bleeding disorder or hypercoagulable
             disease

         15. Use of any drugs or products which at the discretion of the investigator would
             increase bleeding risk

         16. Is considered inappropriate for participation by the investigator for any reason
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Walter K Kraft, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Thomas Jefferson University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University Hosptial</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cts.12398/full</url>
    <description>Full Text</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nagalla S, Thomson L, Oppong Y, Bachman B, Chervoneva I, Kraft WK. Reversibility of Apixaban Anticoagulation with a Four-Factor Prothrombin Complex Concentrate in Healthy Volunteers. Clin Transl Sci. 2016 Jun;9(3):176-80. doi: 10.1111/cts.12398. Epub 2016 May 12.</citation>
    <PMID>27170068</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 17, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 20, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 21, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Xa inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Prothrombin complex concentrate</keyword>
  <keyword>anticoagulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apixaban</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Protein C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Protein S</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

