<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02279563</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AZFL-NASU-05RB02-CE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02279563</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Comparing the Bioequivalence of Azelastine Hydrochloride and Fluticasone Propionate Nasal Spray (Apotex, Inc.) to That of Dymista™ Nasal Spray (Meda Pharmaceuticals, Inc.) in the Treatment of Seasonal Allergic Rhinitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled,Parallel-group Study Comparing the Bioequivalence of Azelastine Hydrochloride and Fluticasone Propionate Nasal Spray (Apotex, Inc.) to That of Dymista™ Nasal Spray (Meda Pharmaceuticals, Inc. )in the Treatment of Seasonal Allergic Rhinitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Apotex Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Apotex Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is to evaluate the equivalence of generic Azelastine Hydrochloride and Fluticasone
      Propionate Nasal Spray with that of the marketed drug, Dymista™ Nasal Spray, in the treatment
      of seasonal allergic rhinitis, and to evaluate the safety and tolerability of generic
      Azelastine Hydrochloride and Fluticasone Propionate nasal spray compared with Dymista™ nasal
      spray.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Enrolling by invitation</last_known_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment of Seasonal Allergic Rhinitis (Change from baseline in the combined reflective TNSS (combined AM and PM reflective scores of runny nose, nasal congestion, nasal itchiness, and sneezing)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in the combined AM and PM instantaneous scores of runny nose, nasal congestion, nasal itchiness, and sneezing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment of Seasonal Allergic Rhinitis (Change from baseline in the combined AM and PM instantaneous scores of runny nose, nasal congestion, nasal itchiness, and sneezing.)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in the combined AM and PM instantaneous scores of runny nose, nasal congestion, nasal itchiness, and sneezing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">595</enrollment>
  <condition>Seasonal Allergic Rhinitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Azelastine HCl and Fluticasone Propionate Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigational product was administered via nasal inhalation with one spray in each nostril twice daily.
Batch Number KL1981, Expiry Date Mar 2015.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dymista™ Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The reference product was administered via nasal inhalation with one spray in each nostril twice daily.
Batch Number G30349, Expiry Date Mar 2015.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The placebo was administered via nasal inhalation with one spray in each nostril twice daily.
Batch Number KL0781, Expiry Date Mar 2015.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Azelastine HCl and Fluticasone Propionate Nasal Spray, 137 µg/50 µg per spray</intervention_name>
    <description>During the placebo lead-in period, the placebo nasal spray was administered via nasal inhalation with one spray in each nostril twice daily for 7days.
During the randomized treatment period, the investigational products (experimental, active comparator and placebo nasal spray) were administered via nasal inhalation with one spray in each nostril twice daily for 14 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Azelastine HCl and Fluticasone Propionate Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dymista™ Nasal Spray</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dymista™ Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Nasal Spray</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects who met all of the following criteria were eligible for inclusion in the study:

          1. Subjects who provided written informed consent.

          2. Subjects who were able to read and understand English.

          3. Males or females, 18 to 65 years old, inclusive.

          4. If the subject was a female of childbearing potential, she was not pregnant (confirmed
             by negative urine pregnancy test) or lactating. Females of childbearing potential
             agreed to use reliable birth control measures throughout the study, defined as
             abstinence or use of an effective method of birth control (double barrier [female
             subject's partner using condom and female subject using diaphragm, contraceptive
             sponge, spermicide, or intrauterine device], or the use of a hormonal contraceptive
             [oral, patch, or inserted under the skin or injected into the muscle]). Female
             subjects who used oral contraceptives or levonorgestrel implants were required to have
             started the method at least 90 days prior to the screening visit. A female of
             childbearing potential was defined as a female who had experienced menarche, and who
             had not undergone successful surgical sterilization (hysterectomy, bilateral
             oophorectomy or ovariectomy, bilateral tubal ligation or salpingectomy) or was not
             post-menopausal for at least 1 year.

          5. At least a 2-year reliable medical history consistent with SAR, defined as symptoms
             present during the previous two grass and/or pollen seasons.

          6. Positive skin test within 12 months of screening to at least one currently present
             seasonal allergen in the geographical area that had a predictable allergen season (eg,
             birch pollen, ragweed, Mountain Cedar, etc) with a minimum skin test response of 3 mm
             or greater than a negative control, and a positive test to histamine, also defined as
             a response of 3 mm or greater than the negative control.

          7. Was capable of tolerating intranasal application of the study drug.

          8. No clinically significant results from the screening physical examination, nasal
             examination, and medical history.

          9. Was willing and able to comply with the requirements of the protocol and was available
             for the full duration of the study, with no planned travel outside of the pollen area
             for a substantial portion (&gt;48 hours) of the study period.

         10. Was, in the Investigator's judgment (through exposure to allergen), expected to
             require treatment throughout the entire study period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects who met any of the following criteria were excluded from the study:

          1. Signs or symptoms of nasal polyps, deviated septum, or any other condition (including
             nasal piercing within the previous 3 months) which, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, may have resulted in erroneous study data.

          2. Underwent nasal surgery or had nasal trauma within 3 months of Visit 1 (screening).

          3. Had active respiratory conditions that included, but were not limited to, acute or
             exacerbated chronic sinusitis, an abnormal sinus radiograph, an upper or lower
             respiratory tract infection, or rhinitis medicamentosa.

          4. Had PAR that required or was expected to require active PAR treatment during the study
             period.

          5. Had a respiratory tract infection (including otitis media and streptococcus) that
             required antibiotic treatment within 2 weeks of Visit 1 (screening).

          6. Used any of the prohibited medications prior to the start of the single-blind, placebo
             lead-in visit (Visit 2) within the time period specified in the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>October 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 28, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 30, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 30, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 30, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhinitis, Allergic, Seasonal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Azelastine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

