<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02272231</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F131127001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02272231</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pathogenesis of Bacterial Vaginosis in Women Who Have Sex With Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pathogenesis of Bacterial Vaginosis in Women Who Have Sex With Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Mississippi Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center in New Orleans</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of this study are to: (1) use cultivation-independent molecular methods to
      determine the sequence of microbiological events culminating in bacterial vaginosis (BV)
      among sexually active African American women who have sex with women (AAWSW) and (2)
      determine if specific Gardnerella vaginalis oligotypes are associated with the development of
      BV among sexually active AAWSW.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bacterial vaginosis (BV) is the most common cause of vaginal discharge in the U.S. It is
      associated with adverse outcomes including preterm birth, pelvic inflammatory disease, and
      increased risk of acquisition and transmission of sexually transmitted infections (STIs),
      including HIV. Microbiologically, BV is characterized by depletion of lactobacilli that
      comprise the normal vaginal flora and increases in facultative (Gardnerella vaginalis; GV)
      and strict anaerobes.

      Three out of four Amsel criteria are necessary for the clinical diagnosis of BV and include
      (1) homogeneous, thin, grayish-white vaginal discharge, (2) vaginal pH &gt;4.5, (3) positive
      whiff-amine test, and (4) clue cells present on a wet mount of vaginal fluid. BV diagnosis,
      however, is based most rigorously on Nugent scoring of a Gram stain of vaginal secretions.
      Optimal vaginal flora, indicative of a predominance of lactobacilli, is represented by a
      Nugent score of 0-3. Abnormal vaginal flora includes not only what is currently defined as BV
      (Nugent score 7-10) but also what is referred to as intermediate flora (Nugent score 4-6).
      For reasons not well understood, BV is very common among women who have sex with women (WSW),
      perhaps more so than among heterosexual women. Risks for prevalent BV among WSW have included
      higher numbers of lifetime female sexual partners, shared use of vaginally inserted sex toys,
      and oral-anal sex. In addition, WSW in monogamous sexual partnerships have a high concordance
      for the presence or absence of BV. These data support the hypothesis that BV is sexually
      transmitted.

      It is well accepted that BV is caused by a synergistic relationship between a large number of
      microorganisms including GV and other anaerobics (i.e. BV-associated bacteria; BVAB) however
      the trigger which initiates these alterations is debated. It is unknown whether BV results
      from acquisition of GV as the &quot;founder&quot; organism which subsequently leads to the complex
      changes in the vaginal microbiota associated with BV or whether BV is transmitted as a
      polymicrobial consortium. GV, as a facultative anaerobe, may be better able to tolerate the
      high oxidation-reduction (redox) potential of the healthy vaginal microbiome, unlike strict
      anaerobes. Similar to facultative anaerobes involved in the initiation of oral disease, it is
      possible that GV, through its metabolic pathways and ability to form a biofilm (perhaps
      influenced by specific oligotypes), creates a lower redox potential in the vaginal
      microbiome. This alteration would then cause a marked decrease in lactobacilli and an
      increase in other BVAB that are normally present in very low concentrations, leading to the
      BV syndrome. Determining the exact etiology of the agent(s) causing a shift from optimal to
      abnormal vaginal flora and BV is vital for appropriate treatment and prevention of adverse
      outcomes. With increasing use of molecular methods, identification of vaginal microorganisms
      (some uncultivable) to the species level in women with BV has become more feasible. This
      study will seek to further investigate BV pathogenesis. We hypothesize that sexual exposure
      to Gardnerella vaginalis is the inciting event leading to the complex changes in vaginal
      flora associated with BV. If Gardnerella vaginalis is the initial insult, then its appearance
      and establishment in the vaginal microbiome will be seen in women who develop incident BV
      prior to increases in other BV-associated bacteria.

      Only African American women will be enrolled in this protocol as differences in the
      composition of vaginal microbial communities of women with and without BV of different racial
      and ethnic groups have been noted which could confound the results of this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of incident BV</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Based on 3 consecutive days of Nugent score readings of 7-10 (vaginal Gram stain result)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of vaginal symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>vaginal discharge, odor, itch based on participant daily diary information (study questionnaire)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Vaginosis, Bacterial</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Self-collected vaginal swabs from women participating in this study will be stored for future
      research purposes related to the study of the vaginal microbiome.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Sexually active African American women who have sex with women with normal vaginal flora at
        baseline (determined based on 0/4 Amsel criteria and a normal Nugent score of 0-3 with no
        Gardnerella vaginalis morphotypes noted on vaginal Gram stain) will be followed
        prospectively over a 90 day time period for the development of incident BV.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Screening Inclusion Criteria:

          1. African American race

          2. Female Gender

          3. Age 18-45 years

          4. History of sexual activity (oral, vaginal, and/or anal) with a female sexual partner
             during the past 12 months

          5. Current female sexual partner

          6. English speaking

          7. Ability to give written informed consent

        Screening Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Use of antimicrobials (oral and/or vaginal) within the past 14 days

          2. Known HIV

          3. Known pregnancy

          4. Currently on menstrual period

        Enrollment Inclusion Criteria:

          1. No Amsel criteria (i.e. patient currently asymptomatic from vaginal discharge
             standpoint, has normal vaginal pH, negative whiff test, and no clue cells on saline
             microscopy)

          2. Nugent score of 0-3 with no Gardnerella vaginalis morphotypes noted on Gram stain

        Enrollment Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of current vaginal infections (i.e. trichomoniasis or symptomatic vaginal
             yeast infection)

          2. Pregnancy

               -  Reasons for Subsequent Participant Discontinuation after Initial Enrollment**:

        (1) Duplicate Nugent score reading &gt; 3 (2) Concurrent trichomonas diagnosis - as determined
        by nucleic acid amplification testing results
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christina A Muzny, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alabama at Birmingham</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwebke JR, Muzny CA, Josey WE. Role of Gardnerella vaginalis in the pathogenesis of bacterial vaginosis: a conceptual model. J Infect Dis. 2014 Aug 1;210(3):338-43. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jiu089. Epub 2014 Feb 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24511102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muzny CA, Schwebke JR. Gardnerella vaginalis: Still a Prime Suspect in the Pathogenesis of Bacterial Vaginosis. Curr Infect Dis Rep. 2013 Apr;15(2):130-5. doi: 10.1007/s11908-013-0318-4.</citation>
    <PMID>23371405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muzny CA, Sunesara IR, Kumar R, Mena LA, Griswold ME, Martin DH, Lefkowitz EJ, Schwebke JR, Swiatlo E. Characterization of the vaginal microbiota among sexual risk behavior groups of women with bacterial vaginosis. PLoS One. 2013 Nov 13;8(11):e80254. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0080254. eCollection 2013. Erratum in: PLoS One. 2013;8(12). doi:10.1371/annotation/f7674ab1-fbd5-4293-ad2c-d1a795962e8b. Swiatlo, Edwin [added].</citation>
    <PMID>24236175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muzny CA, Sunesara IR, Griswold ME, Kumar R, Lefkowitz EJ, Mena LA, Schwebke JR, Martin DH, Swiatlo E. Association between BVAB1 and high Nugent scores among women with bacterial vaginosis. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2014 Dec;80(4):321-3. doi: 10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2014.09.008. Epub 2014 Sep 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25262105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwebke JR, Muzny CA, Josey WE. Reply to Hickey and Forney. J Infect Dis. 2014 Nov 15;210(10):1683-4. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jiu304. Epub 2014 May 22.</citation>
    <PMID>24855685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muzny CA, Sunesara IR, Austin EL, Mena LA, Schwebke JR. Bacterial vaginosis among African American women who have sex with women. Sex Transm Dis. 2013 Sep;40(9):751-5. doi: 10.1097/OLQ.0000000000000004.</citation>
    <PMID>23949590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muzny CA, Schwebke JR. Editorial commentary: women who have sex with women: a unique population for studying the pathogenesis of bacterial vaginosis. Clin Infect Dis. 2015 Apr 1;60(7):1054-6. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciu1132. Epub 2014 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25516182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muzny CA, Schwebke JR. Biofilms: An Underappreciated Mechanism of Treatment Failure and Recurrence in Vaginal Infections. Clin Infect Dis. 2015 Aug 15;61(4):601-6. doi: 10.1093/cid/civ353. Epub 2015 May 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25935553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muzny CA, Schwebke JR. Accuracy of Self-Report of Sexual Activity among Adolescent Girls: Implications for Interpretation of Vaginal Flora Patterns. MBio. 2015 Jun 23;6(3):e00819. doi: 10.1128/mBio.00819-15.</citation>
    <PMID>26106081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 20, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 20, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 22, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Christina Muzny</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor - Med-Infectious Disease</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>women's health</keyword>
  <keyword>vaginosis, bacterial</keyword>
  <keyword>african americans</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaginal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vaginosis, Bacterial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified data will be shared with statisticians at the University of Mississippi Medical center for statistical analysis.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

