<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00224783</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>D153 P800</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00224783</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00192530</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I Trial Evaluating Safety and Tolerability of CAIV-T in Healthy Japanese Male Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>Placebo-controlled Double-blind Controlled Trial of Single Intranasal Inoculation of CAIV-T Liquid Formulation in Healthy Japanese Male Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MedImmune LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wyeth is now a wholly owned subsidiary of Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MedImmune LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study was to investigate the safety and tolerability of CAIV-T
      liquid formulation in healthy Japanese male adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study was to investigate the safety and tolerability of CAIV-T
      liquid formulation in healthy Japanese male adults by evaluating the incidence of
      influenza-like symptoms, and the type, incidence, and severity of adverse events.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of subjects within each treatment arm who experienced influenza-like symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 6 days post vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Influenza-like symptoms, ie, typical clinical symptoms of influenza infection, including fever (oral temperature &gt; or = 38 degrees C), cough, runny or stuffy nose, sore throat, headache, chills, muscular pain, vomiting, decline in activity, decline in appetite.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of subjects within each treatment arm who experienced adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 28 days of vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events were classified according to the &quot;Glossary of Side Effects of Pharmaceutical Agents, 1996.&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Japanese Male Adults</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CAIV-T</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CAIV-T contains 3 cold-adapted influenza virus strains (A/H1N1, A/H3N2, B) concentrated and refined by centrifugal separation from the chorioallantoic membrane of specific pathogen-free (SPF) eggs, containing SPG (sucrose-phosphate-glutamate), arginine, and acid hydrolyzed pig gelatin as stabilizers. Subjects were inoculated once with about 0.1 mL of investigational vaccine in each nasal cavity (a total of 0.2 mL) using a nebulizer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo contained 0.01 mol/L potassium phosphate buffer containing 0.85% sodium chloride (pH 7.2). Subjects received about 0.1 mL (a total 0.2 mL) of the control drug using a nebulizer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CAIV-T</intervention_name>
    <description>Trivalent cold adapted temperature sensitive attenuated Types A and Type B influenza virus live vaccine (CAIV-T)</description>
    <arm_group_label>CAIV-T</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>0.2 mL, by nebulizer</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>0.2 mL of 0.01 mol/L potassium phosphate buffer containing 0.85% sodium chloride (pH 7.2).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age of 20 years old or over but below 45 years old (at the time of consent)

          -  Persons judged suitable by the principal investigator or investigator from the results
             of prior history, physical examination and clinical findings.

          -  Persons having the ability to understand consent and a written consent obtained prior
             to the start of screening.

          -  Persons being able to participate in the trial for 1 month from the inoculation of the
             trial vaccine to the completion of the trial.

          -  Persons being able to be contacted (by phone, hospital visit or house visit) by the
             trial staff at the time of testing after 28 days from the inoculation of the trial
             vaccine.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Persons judged to be impossible or difficult to contact for requesting hospital visits
             to carry out clinical evaluation and tests during the trial term.

          -  Persons having a prior history of or suspected immunological disease, or those
             receiving administration of systemic corticosteroids or immunosuppressants such as
             cytotoxic drugs (e.g., methotrexate, etc.)

          -  Persons having blood formulations such as immunoglobulin, etc., administered or
             planned during a period from one month before the inoculation of the trial vaccine to
             the completion of the trial.

          -  Persons living with any person with a nonfunctional or suppressed immune system (by
             using immunosuppressants, etc.), in the same household.

          -  Persons with a prior history of hypersensitivity to chicken eggs or chicken egg
             proteins or components of the trial vaccine (such as sucrose, phosphoric acid,
             glutamate, arginine and acid-hydrolyzed pig gelatin).

          -  Persons inoculated with a live virus vaccine within 1 month before screening.

          -  Persons having the planned administration of another trial vaccine or drug during the
             period from one month before screening to the completion of the trial

          -  Person having an influenza treatment drug (such as commercially available drugs or
             trial vaccines: for example, Oseltamivir, Zanamivir, Amantadine, etc.), administered
             within one month before screening. Incidentally, no prophylactic administration of an
             influenza viral drug was permitted.

          -  Persons inoculated with an influenza vaccine within 6 months before screening or
             planned to be inoculated with an influenza vaccine during the term of the present
             trial.

          -  Persons with blood drawn quantity (including blood donation) of 400 mL or more within
             3 months or 200 mL or more within 1 month before screening.

          -  Persons with a history of any febrile disorders (oral cavity temperature ³ 38.0°C) or
             other acute disorders within 36 hours before trial vaccine inoculation.

          -  Persons who had upper respiratory tract disorders themselves or whose family members
             had such disorders within 72 hours before trial vaccine inoculation.

          -  Persons treated with an antibiotic within 72 hours before trial vaccine inoculation.

          -  Persons with an acute asthmatic symptom.

          -  Persons judged to have a pathology preventing the evaluation of the trial effect by
             the principal investigator (or investigator).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Walker, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>MedImmune LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>January 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 20, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 23, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 26, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Christopher Ambrose, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Medimmune, LLC</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Potassium phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

