<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00221442</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>51-345-740</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00221442</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zonegran in the Treatment of Binge Eating Disorder Associated With Obesity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Zonegran in the Treatment of Binge Eating Disorder Associated With Obesity: A Single Center, Double-Blind, Placebo-controlled, Flexible-Dose Study in Outpatients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lindner Center of HOPE</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eisai Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lindner Center of HOPE</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim of this study is to examine the efficacy and safety of zonisamide compared
      with placebo in outpatients with binge eating disorder associated with obesity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Binge eating disorder (BED) is characterized by recurrent, uncontrollable, and distressing
      episodes of excessive food consumption (binge eating) without compensatory weight loss
      behaviors.1,2 Its prevalence in the general population of the United States is conservatively
      estimated to be 1.5% to 2%,1-6 making it more common than anorexia nervosa and bulimia
      nervosa combined. BED is associated with being overweight and obesity.1-7 Approximately 8% to
      30% of those seeking standard weight loss treatments, 1-4 up to 50% of those seeking
      bariatric surgery,8,9 and 70% of those participating in Overeaters Annonymous3 are estimated
      to have BED.

      Zonisamide is a structurally and pharmacologically novel antiepileptic drug - a
      sulfamate-substituted monosaccharide - with proven anticonvulsant efficacy when used
      adjunctively in refractory partial epilepsy.10-12 Mechanisms hypothesized to account for
      zonisamide's antiepileptic properties include antagonism of voltage-gated sodium and T-type
      calcium channels, blockade of potassium-evoked glutamate release, modulation of central
      dopaminergic and serotonergic function, and carbonic anhydrase inhibition.10-16 Several lines
      of evidence suggest that zonisamide might be a useful treatment for BED. First, like the
      anticonvulsant topiramate,17-19 zonisamide has been associated with anorexia and weight loss
      in clinical trials in epilepsy patients10,11,20 and in patients with obesity.20 Topiramate
      has also been shown to reduce binge eating and weight in patients with binge eating disorder
      associated with obesity. 21 Although zonisamide and topiramate have distinct pharmacologic
      profiles, both drugs share several pharmacologic actions. These include sodium channel
      blockade, carbonic anhydrase inhibition, and reduction of glutamate neurotransmission.
      10,11,13,16,17 Regarding the latter property, animal studies have shown that stimulation of
      the lateral hypothalamus by glutamate and glutamate agonists causes an intense, rapid,
      dose-dependent increase in food intake,22 whereas glutamate antagonism of the nucleus tractus
      solitarius reduces food intake.23 Second, unlike topiramate, zonisamide also modulates the
      function of serotonin and dopamine14, 15 --two neurotransmitters involved in the regulation
      of feeding behavior24 and the mechanisms of some medications with efficacy in either binge
      eating (SSRIs, d-fenfluramine) 25-29 or obesity (sibutramine, stimulants).30 Third, a broad
      range of antidepressants have been reported to reduce binge eating in both bulimia nervosa31
      and binge eating disorder25-28,32 and preliminary observations suggest zonisamide may have
      thymoleptic properties.33,34 Fourth, in an open-label trial of zonisamide in 15 patients with
      BED conducted by our group, zonisamide was effective in reducing binge eating frequency,
      severity of illness, and weight (S.L. McElroy, J Clin Psychiatry, under review).35 We
      therefore propose to conduct a double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized, parallel group,
      16-week study of zonisamide in 60 outpatients with binge eating disorder and obesity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>frequency of binge eating episodes</measure>
    <time_frame>per protocol</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Binge Eating Disorder Associated With Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>zonisamide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>zonegran (zonisamide)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>fake pill</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zonegran</intervention_name>
    <description>zonegran (zonisamide)</description>
    <arm_group_label>zonisamide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sugar pill</intervention_name>
    <description>fake pill</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar pill</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients will meet DSM-IV criteria for BED for at least the last 6 months. These criteria
        are as follows:

          -  Recurrent episodes of binge eating. An episode of binge eating is characterized by
             both of the following: (1) eating, in discrete period of time (eg, within any two hour
             period), an amount of food that is definitely larger than most people would eat in a
             similar period of time under similar circumstances and (2) a sense of lack of control
             over eating during the episode (eg, a feeling that one cannot stop eating or control
             what or how much one is eating)

          -  The binge eating episodes are associated with at least three of the following:

               -  Eating much more rapidly than normal

               -  Eating until uncomfortably full

               -  Eating large amounts of food when not feeling physically hungry

               -  Eating alone because of being embarrassed by how much one is eating

               -  Feeling disgusted with oneself, depressed, or feeling very guilty after
                  overeating

          -  Marked distress regarding binge eating.

          -  The binge eating occurs, on average, at least two days a week for six months.

          -  Does not occur exclusively during the course of bulimia nervosa and anorexia nervosa.

          -  Obesity as defined by body mass index &gt; 30 kg/m2.

          -  Men or women, between the ages of 18 and 65. The patient population is expected to be
             predominantly made up of women based on previous research.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have current body mass index &lt; 30kg/m2.

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating and women of childbearing potential who are not
             taking adequate contraceptive measures. If there is a possibility a female subject
             might be pregnant, a pregnancy test will be performed. (All women of childbearing
             potential will have a negative pregnancy test before entering the study.)

          -  Subjects who are displaying clinically significant suicidality or homicidality.

          -  Subjects who are displaying a current clinically unstable depressive disorder (e.g.,
             HAM-D &gt; 21).

          -  A current or recent (within 6 months of the start of study medication) DSM-IV
             diagnosis of substance abuse or dependence.

          -  A lifetime history of a DSM-IV bipolar disorder or dementia.

          -  History of a personality disorder (eg, schizotypal, borderline, or antisocial) which
             might interfere with assessment or compliance with study procedures.

          -  Clinically unstable medical disease, including cardiovascular, hepatic, renal,
             gastrointestinal, pulmonary, metabolic, endocrine or other systemic disease which
             could interfere with diagnosis, assessment, or treatment of binge eating disorder.
             Patients should be biochemically euthyroid prior to entering the study.

          -  History of seizures, including febrile seizures in childhood

          -  History of clinically significant nephrolithiasis.

          -  Subjects requiring treatment with any drug which might interact adversely with or
             obscure the action of the study medication (e.g. stimulants, sympathomimetics,
             antidepressants, carbonic anhydrase inhibitors, anti-obesity drugs).

          -  Subjects who have received psychoactive medication (other than zaleplon [Sonata] or
             zolpidem [Ambien] -- as needed for restlessness/insomnia) within one week prior to
             randomization.

          -  Subjects who have begun and/or are receiving formal psychotherapy (cognitive
             behavioral therapy, interpersonal therapy, or dietary behavioral therapy) for BED or
             weight loss within the past 3 months.

          -  Subjects previously enrolled in this study or have previously been treated with
             zonisamide.

          -  Subjects who have received an experimental drug or used an experimental device within
             30 days.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan L McElroy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cincinnati Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45267-0559</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>McElroy SL, Kotwal R, Guerdjikova AI, Welge JA, Nelson EB, Lake KA, D'Alessio DA, Keck PE, Hudson JI. Zonisamide in the treatment of binge eating disorder with obesity: a randomized controlled trial. J Clin Psychiatry. 2006 Dec;67(12):1897-906. Erratum in: J Clin Psychiatry. 2007 Jan;68(1):172.</citation>
    <PMID>17194267</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 22, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Susan L .McElroy, MD / Professor</name_title>
    <organization>Lindner Center of HOPE</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Binge eating disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood draw</keyword>
  <keyword>E.Coli enterprotoxin</keyword>
  <keyword>Eating disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Electrocardiogram</keyword>
  <keyword>Females</keyword>
  <keyword>Males</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical exam</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychiatric evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaire</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Feeding and Eating Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Binge-Eating Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bulimia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Zonisamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

