<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00221182</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BRI CAD 04-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00221182</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stem Cell Study for Patients With Heart Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I / II Clinical Trial Regarding Vascular Regeneration Therapy by Transplantation of Autologous Peripheral Blood Endothelial Progenitor Cells (CD34+ Cells) in No-Option Patients With Chronic Myocardial Ischemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Foundation for Biomedical Research and Innovation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institute of Biomedical Research and Innovation, Kobe, Hyogo, Japan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kobe City General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Okayama University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Foundation for Biomedical Research and Innovation</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if stem cell therapy with your own cells
      (autologous cells) delivered with a catheter to regions of the heart with poor blood flow
      will be safe and if it will relieve your chest pain, increase the blood flow, and/or improve
      the cardiac contractility (function) by regenerating blood vessels in your heart.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic myocardial ischemia (MI) is a progressive disease, which arises as a result of
      atherosclerosis in coronary arteries. Prognosis of chronic MI is poor, and no effective
      treatments have been established in patients who are not eligible for the traditional
      revascularization therapies such as angioplasty and bypass procedures due to the
      inappropriate anatomy of the coronary arteries or frequent reocclusion following
      revascularization. Therefore, it is necessary to establish novel revascularization treatment
      to improve prognosis of the no-option patients. We will study the safety and clinical
      efficiency of vascular regeneration by means of transplantation of autologous peripheral
      blood endothelial progenitor cells (CD34 positive cells) in patients with severe chronic
      coronary artery disease (CAD) who are not eligible for traditional revascularization
      treatments. The primary endpoint is the severity of myocardial ischemia identified by
      sestamibi SPECT stress myocardial scintigraphy and the evaluation of adverse effect rates,
      while the secondary endpoints are evaluation of CCSAS and NYHA classification, regional
      myocardial blood flow as revealed by PET scan, and various left ventricular function indices.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    slow recruitment of the study subjects
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>September 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy: Severity of myocardial perfusion abnormality by sestamibi SPECT stress myocardial scintigraphy</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Severe adverse events within 4 weeks after cell therapy</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CCSAS (Canada Cardiovascular Society Anginal Score)</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NYHA (New York Heart Association) classification</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise tolerance by treadmill</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular function by cardiac MRI</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Chest Pain</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <condition>Angina</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autologous peripheral blood CD34 positive cell therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        -Chronic severe CAD patients fulfilling all the following criteria are considered suitable
        for inclusion in the study.

          1. At least 6 months since last episode of myocardial infarction or at least 3 months
             since initial anginal episode.

          2. Patients fulfilling either of the following criteria based on the extent of CAD by
             coronary angiography and LVEF by echocardiography.

               -  Patients with single vessel CAD and LVEF &lt; 50%

               -  Patients with multivessel CAD

          3. Reversible myocardial ischemia as revealed by sestamibi SPECT stress myocardial
             scintigraphy.

          4. Patients for whom angioplasty and bypass are not indicated because of anatomical or
             procedural reasons or frequent reocclusion/restenosis following traditional
             revascularization.

          5. Age is between 20 and 80 (at time of consent).

          6. Exercise tolerance time (ETT) duration ≥ 3 minutes and &lt; 13 minutes on a modified
             Bruce protocol on 2 consecutive tests (&gt; 24 hours but &lt; 2 weeks apart), with the
             difference between the 2 exercise times within 25% of their mean (Patients should not
             be informed of exercise restrictions required for entry into the study).

          7. Patients who can give informed consent themselves in writing.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any one of the following exclusion criteria is sufficient to disqualify a patient from
             the study.

               1. Sustained ventricular tachycardia in a 24-hour ECG.

               2. Chronic atrial fibrillation.

               3. Less than 6 months since last episode of cerebral infarction.

               4. Less than 6 months since last coronary angioplasty or less than 3 months since
                  last bypass surgery.

               5. Patients with unstable angina, with a treatment rating of 3 in the Braunwald
                  system (refer to 5.4.), but a severity of III and a clinical rating of B or C.

               6. Presence of left ventricular thrombus by echocardiography

               7. Patients with a malignant tumor*.

               8. Patients with diabetic proliferating retinopathy** (new Fukuda classification BI
                  to BV).

               9. Patients with chronic rheumatoid arthritis.

              10. Patients with a history of severe allergic reactions or side effects to G-CSF
                  preparations or apheresis.

              11. Patients with hematological disease (leukemia, myeloproliferative disease, or
                  myelodysplastic syndromes).

              12. Patients currently suffering from or having a history of interstitial
                  pneumonitis.

              13. Patients for whom cranial MRA reveals cerebral aneurysm.

              14. Patients for whom abdominal CT or ultrasonography reveals splenomegaly.

              15. Patients with cirrhosis of the liver.

              16. Patients who cannot discontinue Warfarin.

              17. Leukocytes less than 4,000/µL or exceeding 10,000/µL.

              18. Platelets less than 100,000/µL.

              19. Hemoglobin less than 10 g/dL.

              20. AST (GOT) exceeding 100 IU/L or ALT (GPT) exceeding 100 IU/L.

              21. Patients for whom it is impossible to perform both cardiac MRI and left
                  ventriculography (LVG) (see 9.2.4 for cardiac MRI details and 9.2.9 for LVG
                  details).

              22. Patients with gate disturbance for reasons other than CAD (such as critical limb
                  ischemia, sciatic neuralgia, or vasculitis), making exercise tolerance evaluation
                  on a treadmill with stress ECG difficult.

              23. Pregnant or nursing patients, those who may be pregnant, or those who plan on
                  becoming pregnant before the end of the study period.

              24. Any other reason that the Clinical Supervisors or Clinical Researchers may have
                  for considering a case unsuitable for the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Takayuki Asahara, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Foundation for Biomedical Research and Innovation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kobe Institute of Biomedical Research and Innovation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kobe</city>
        <state>Hyogo-Pref.</state>
        <zip>650-0047</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kobe City General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kobe</city>
        <state>Hyogo</state>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Okayama University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Okayama</city>
        <zip>700-8530</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asahara T, Kawamoto A. Endothelial progenitor cells for postnatal vasculogenesis. Am J Physiol Cell Physiol. 2004 Sep;287(3):C572-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15308462</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kawamoto A, Tkebuchava T, Yamaguchi J, Nishimura H, Yoon YS, Milliken C, Uchida S, Masuo O, Iwaguro H, Ma H, Hanley A, Silver M, Kearney M, Losordo DW, Isner JM, Asahara T. Intramyocardial transplantation of autologous endothelial progenitor cells for therapeutic neovascularization of myocardial ischemia. Circulation. 2003 Jan 28;107(3):461-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12551872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kawamoto A, Gwon HC, Iwaguro H, Yamaguchi JI, Uchida S, Masuda H, Silver M, Ma H, Kearney M, Isner JM, Asahara T. Therapeutic potential of ex vivo expanded endothelial progenitor cells for myocardial ischemia. Circulation. 2001 Feb 6;103(5):634-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11156872</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asahara T, Murohara T, Sullivan A, Silver M, van der Zee R, Li T, Witzenbichler B, Schatteman G, Isner JM. Isolation of putative progenitor endothelial cells for angiogenesis. Science. 1997 Feb 14;275(5302):964-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9020076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takahashi T, Kalka C, Masuda H, Chen D, Silver M, Kearney M, Magner M, Isner JM, Asahara T. Ischemia- and cytokine-induced mobilization of bone marrow-derived endothelial progenitor cells for neovascularization. Nat Med. 1999 Apr;5(4):434-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10202935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalka C, Masuda H, Takahashi T, Kalka-Moll WM, Silver M, Kearney M, Li T, Isner JM, Asahara T. Transplantation of ex vivo expanded endothelial progenitor cells for therapeutic neovascularization. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2000 Mar 28;97(7):3422-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10725398</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 22, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Angina</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular diseases</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chest Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

