<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00229983</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NIDA-R01DA014553</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00229983</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00592787</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Medical Office Intervention for Adolescent Drug Use</brief_title>
  <official_title>Medical Office Intervention for Adolescent Drug Use</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Children’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to assess the efficacy of a new intervention based on motivational
      enhancement therapy among adolescents with a history of substance use.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In many parts of the U.S. adolescent substance abuse treatment is scarce. Several studies
      have shown that brief interventions increase the likelihood of patients' completion of
      referrals to alcohol counseling or treatment. Other studies have shown a direct effect of
      brief interventions on patients' alcohol consumption. Although brief interventions have been
      widely recommended for adolescents, fewer studies have been conducted in this age group. If
      the current study confirms the effectiveness of the Motivational Enhancement Therapy
      approach, this will add another outpatient treatment option for adolescent patients with drug
      problems.

      The specific aims of the project are to:

        1. Test the effect of the brief intervention on drug use. We hypothesize that, among 12-18
           year old medical patients who use drugs, the experimental intervention (two 60-minute
           motivational interviewing sessions) administered by a trained clinician will be at least
           25% more effective than &quot;standard care&quot; (assessment/referral only) in decreasing drug
           use as measured by a 90-day Timeline Followback (6) (TLFB) calendar.

        2. Test the effect of the brief intervention in increasing engagement in substance abuse
           treatment. We hypothesize that, among 12-18 year old patients who are referred to drug
           counseling or other treatments, the experimental intervention administered by a trained
           clinician will result in at least 25% more patients entering treatment compared to
           standard care, as measured by the numbers of patients who complete referrals to
           treatment providers.

        3. Test the effect of the intervention on other substance-related outcomes. We hypothesize
           that the intervention will result in similar reductions in alcohol use, as measured by
           the TLFB, and in driving/riding while impaired (DRWI) risks as measured by the score of
           a 4-item self-reported scale. Other outcomes of interest include readiness to change,
           school performance, and experience of other harmful consequences of substance use and
           associated risk behaviors.

        4. Identify factors that moderate and/or mediate the effect of the experimental
           intervention on our outcomes of interest (drug use, engagement in treatment), and
           estimate their effect sizes. Identifying moderating variables will help us to identify
           subgroups of optimal responders to the brief intervention. Based on our previous
           experience, we theorize that girls may respond more strongly to the intervention than
           boys, and that those who participate in other treatments (outpatient counseling) and/or
           a laboratory drug testing program will also have greater response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantity and days of substance use</measure>
    <time_frame>Past 90 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DWI or RWID</measure>
    <time_frame>Past 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Driving while intoxicated or riding with an intoxicated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of completed substance use treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Past 90 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Substance related risk behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Past 90 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">170</enrollment>
  <condition>Substance-Related Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational Enhancement Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adolescents who are randomized to the experimental intervention will attend three 60-minute counseling sessions, delivered 2-4 weeks apart. The intervention will include a structured, developmentally appropriate, approach to identification of drug- and alcohol-related risks and problems, and establishment of goals for behavioral change.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Standard Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adolescents who are randomized to Enhanced Standard Care will receive the usual care at the outpatient adolescent substance abuse program. This will include an evaluation by pediatric and mental health staff and could include treatment in a group therapy program, urine drug testing, buprenorphine replacement therapy (for those dependent on opioids), and psychopharmacology evaluation and management.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Motivational Enhancement Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Three 60 minute counseling sessions using a structured, developmentally appropriate approach to identification of drug- and alcohol- related risks and problems, and establishment of goals for behavioral change.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational Enhancement Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MET</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  12-21 years old

          -  Use of alcohol, marijuana or other drugs 6 times in last 3 months

          -  CRAFFT score of 1 or greater

          -  Have completed evaluation at Adolescent Substance Abuse Program at Children's Hospital
             Boston

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Can not read or understand English at a 6th grade reading level

          -  Needs immediate hospitalization
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John R Knight, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Boston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215-5737</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ceasar-boston.org</url>
    <description>This is the web site of the Center for Adolescent Substance Abuse Research, the research center conducting the study &quot;Medical Office Intervention for Adolescent Drug Use.&quot;</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knight JR, Shrier LA, Bravender TD, Farrell M, Vander Bilt J, Shaffer HJ. A new brief screen for adolescent substance abuse. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 1999 Jun;153(6):591-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10357299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knight JR, Sherritt L, Shrier LA, Harris SK, Chang G. Validity of the CRAFFT substance abuse screening test among adolescent clinic patients. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2002 Jun;156(6):607-14.</citation>
    <PMID>12038895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 29, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 29, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 30, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John R Knight, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Pediatrics, Harvard Medical School; Senior Associate in Medicine; Associate in Psychiatry, Director, Center for Adolescent Substance Abuse Research, Boston Children's Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Substance use disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Substance abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug abuse</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

