<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00229554</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIR 04-042</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00229554</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Survey of ColoRectal Cancer Education and Environment Needs</brief_title>
  <acronym>SCREEN</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessing and Addressing Patient Colorectal Cancer Screening Barriers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite strong evidence for the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of a variety of
      colorectal cancer (CRC) screening methods for reducing CRC mortality, current CRC screening
      rates fall far below the levels needed to significantly impact CRC mortality. Unfortunately,
      however, the existing literature on patient CRC screening behavior does not yet provide a
      sufficient evidence base for making sound recommendations regarding how to most effectively
      improve upon these rates in the VA. This study will inform future CRC screening promotion
      efforts and make important scientific contributions to existing literature by: (a)
      delineating the relative contribution of patient cognitive, environmental and background
      factors to CRC screening behavior using a multi-level, theory driven analysis approach on a
      nationally representative sample, and (b) identifying the determinants of variation in CRC
      screening behavior across vulnerable population subgroups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background / Rationale:

      Despite strong evidence for the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of a variety of
      colorectal cancer (CRC) screening methods for reducing CRC mortality, current CRC screening
      rates fall far below the levels needed to significantly impact CRC mortality. Unfortunately,
      however, the existing literature on patient CRC screening behavior does not yet provide a
      sufficient evidence base for making sound recommendations regarding how to most effectively
      improve upon these rates in the VA. This study will inform future CRC screening promotion
      efforts and make important scientific contributions to existing literature by: (a)
      delineating the relative contribution of patient cognitive, environmental and background
      factors to CRC screening behavior using a multi-level, theory driven analysis approach on a
      nationally representative sample, and (b) identifying the determinants of variation in CRC
      screening behavior across vulnerable population subgroups.

      Objective(s):

      The overall goal of this study was to address significant gaps in the existing evidence base
      in order to inform the development of effective patient-directed interventions to increase
      CRC screening among veterans age 50 and older. This was accomplished by using data collected
      from a mailed patient survey and theory-based analysis approaches to uncover key barriers to
      screening adherence and to identify fruitful intervention approaches for modifying them. The
      specific primary objectives of this study were to: (1) Estimate the relative effect of
      patient cognitive (knowledge, attitudes, and self-efficacy), environmental (social network
      and medical care characteristics), and background (demographics, health status, prior
      screening experiences) factors on CRC screening behavior; (2) Identify factors that
      contribute to any disparities in CRC screening behavior by race/ethnicity or other patient
      characteristics; (3) Identify from these analyses: (a) priority population subgroups to
      target in future interventions (i.e., those at the greatest risk of failing to be screened),
      and (b) priority factors to target in future interventions (i.e., those that are not only
      strongly associated with CRC screening but also prevalent in the target population and
      amenable to intervention, as well as those that are most likely to ameliorate race and other
      disparities). Secondary objectives included: (1) assessing patient values and preferences
      regarding the various CRC screening modality options, (2) estimating stage of readiness to
      adopt CRC screening in the study population, and (3) validating measures of CRC knowledge and
      self-reported screening behavior.

      Methods:

      This is an observational study based on a nationally representative, cross-sectional mailed
      survey of 3,744 male and female veterans age 50-75 who have had one or more primary care
      visits at a VA Medical facility in the past two years. The survey sample was drawn using a
      two stage procedure where we first randomly select 24 VA facilities stratified by size and
      racial mix and then select a simple random sample of 156 eligible veterans from each sampled
      facility. Prior to the national survey, a pilot survey was conducted with the purpose of
      refining both the study instruments and the study protocol. The sample consisted of 900
      randomly selected veterans from the Minneapolis VA Medical Center meeting the same sampling
      eligibility criteria used for the national mailed survey. The mailed patient questionnaire,
      made up primarily of previously validated measures, included measures of self-reported CRC
      screening behavior; patient demographic, health, social network and medical care
      characteristics; CRC screening knowledge, attitudes, social norms and self-efficacy; and
      attitudes toward medical care. Additional measures of organizational-level CRC screening
      practices from a recently completed VA facility survey were linked to the patient survey.The
      primary outcome is whether the patient is currently compliant with CRC screening guidelines
      (i.e., received either a fecal occult blood test in the past year, a sigmoidoscopy or double
      contrast barium enema in the past five years, or a colonoscopy in the past ten years). The
      primary analyses tested (using logistic regression and a multi-level, structural equation
      modeling approach) specific hypotheses about the association between this measure and patient
      background, cognitive and environmental factors and their interactions. Additional analyses
      conducted include a multinomial logistic regression to assess patient screening mode
      preferences and their determinants, and logistic and multinomial logistics regression
      analyses with interactions to determine whether and why any observed patterns in CRC
      screening behavior vary by race.

      Status:

      Completed
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>colorectal cancer screening compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>self-report or medical records documentation of either a fecal occult blood test (FOBT) in the past 15 months, a sigmoidoscopy or double contrast barium enema in the past 5.5 years, or a colonoscopy in the past 11 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4644</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Mass Screening</condition>
  <condition>Patient Compliance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Male and female veterans age 50-75 who have had one or more primary care visits at a VA Medical facility in the past two years.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Primary care patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Study subjects must be a male or female veteran who has had one or more primary care visits
        at a VHA medical center in the past 2 years and is between the age of 50 and 75.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Study subjects cannot be a VHA employee, deceased, have a colorectal cancer diagnosis, be
        enrolled in VA adult day care or nursing home, or have dementia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melissa R. Partin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Minneapolis VA Health Care System, Minneapolis, MN</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Minneapolis VA Health Care System, Minneapolis, MN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55417</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Partin MR, Grill J, Noorbaloochi S, Powell AA, Burgess DJ, Vernon SW, Halek K, Griffin JM, van Ryn M, Fisher DA. Validation of self-reported colorectal cancer screening behavior from a mixed-mode survey of veterans. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2008 Apr;17(4):768-76. doi: 10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-07-0759. Epub 2008 Apr 1.</citation>
    <PMID>18381474</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Burgess DJ, Powell AA, Griffin JM, Partin MR. Race and the validity of self-reported cancer screening behaviors: development of a conceptual model. Prev Med. 2009 Feb;48(2):99-107. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2008.11.014. Epub 2008 Dec 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19118570</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Partin MR, Burgess DJ, Halek K, Grill J, Vernon SW, Fisher DA, Griffin JM, Murdoch M. Randomized trial showed requesting medical records with a survey produced a more representative sample than requesting separately. J Clin Epidemiol. 2008 Oct;61(10):1028-35. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2007.11.015. Epub 2008 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>18550333</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Friedemann-Sánchez G, Griffin JM, Partin MR. Gender differences in colorectal cancer screening barriers and information needs. Health Expect. 2007 Jun;10(2):148-60.</citation>
    <PMID>17524008</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Burgess DJ, van Ryn M, Grill J, Noorbaloochi S, Griffin JM, Ricards J, Vernon SW, Fisher DA, Partin MR. Presence and correlates of racial disparities in adherence to colorectal cancer screening guidelines. J Gen Intern Med. 2011 Mar;26(3):251-8. doi: 10.1007/s11606-010-1575-7. Epub 2010 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>21088920</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kodl MM, Powell AA, Noorbaloochi S, Grill JP, Bangerter AK, Partin MR. Mental health, frequency of healthcare visits, and colorectal cancer screening. Med Care. 2010 Oct;48(10):934-9. doi: 10.1097/MLR.0b013e3181e57901.</citation>
    <PMID>20706162</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Partin MR, Noorbaloochi S, Grill J, Burgess DJ, van Ryn M, Fisher DA, Griffin JM, Powell AA, Halek K, Bangerter A, Vernon SW. The interrelationships between and contributions of background, cognitive, and environmental factors to colorectal cancer screening adherence. Cancer Causes Control. 2010 Sep;21(9):1357-68. doi: 10.1007/s10552-010-9563-0. Epub 2010 Apr 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20419343</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Burgess DJ, Grill J, Noorbaloochi S, Griffin JM, Ricards J, van Ryn M, Partin MR. The effect of perceived racial discrimination on bodily pain among older African American men. Pain Med. 2009 Nov;10(8):1341-52. doi: 10.1111/j.1526-4637.2009.00742.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20021596</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Powell AA, Burgess DJ, Vernon SW, Griffin JM, Grill JP, Noorbaloochi S, Partin MR. Colorectal cancer screening mode preferences among US veterans. Prev Med. 2009 Nov;49(5):442-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2009.09.002. Epub 2009 Sep 8.</citation>
    <PMID>19747502</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Griffin JM, Burgess D, Vernon SW, Friedemann-Sanchez G, Powell A, van Ryn M, Halek K, Noorbaloochi S, Grill J, Bloomfield H, Partin M. Are gender differences in colorectal cancer screening rates due to differences in self-reporting? Prev Med. 2009 Nov;49(5):436-41. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2009.09.013. Epub 2009 Sep 16.</citation>
    <PMID>19765609</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 27, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 27, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 29, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 7, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>health surveys</keyword>
  <keyword>questionnaires</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

