<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00221364</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-02630</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00221364</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trachoma Elimination Follow-up</brief_title>
  <acronym>TEF</acronym>
  <official_title>Trachoma Elimination With Repeated Mass Azithromycin Treatments</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The WHO has initiated a program to eliminate blinding trachoma by the year 2020, in large
      part by mass oral azithromycin distributions. It is not clear how frequently or for how long
      these treatments are necessary. Here we assess the frequency and duration of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      40 villages in the Gurage Zone of Ethiopia were randomly assigned to biannual treatment,
      annual treatment, and a single treatment. Each treatment consisted of a single dose of oral
      azithromycin to the entire population over the age of 1 year (when the study was started,
      azithromycin had not yet been approved for ages below 1 year). We assess the prevalence the
      ocular chlamydia that causes trachoma in the peak prevalence age of 1-5 years at baseline,
      and 2, 6, 12, 18, and 24 months post treatment. An extension of the study monitors infection
      at 30 and 36 months post treatment. Untreated villages from the same area are enrolled in a
      step-wedge design to assess the presence of a secular trend. A random sample of those not
      within the 1-5 year old age group are examined to assess the prevalence of infection in the
      entire community.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2005</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The prevalence of ocular chlamydia infection in a village as determined by PCR</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical active trachoma, as determined by the WHO simplified grading system, by village</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20000</enrollment>
  <condition>Trachoma</condition>
  <condition>Chlamydia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mass treatment with oral azithromycin to an entire village</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Age 1 to 5 years old in a village in the Gurage zone with endemic trachoma

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Refusal of village chief (for village inclusion), or refusal of parent or guardian (for
        individual inclusion)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas M Lietman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Proctor Foundation, UCSF</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ORBIS-Ethiopia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Addis Ababa</city>
        <country>Ethiopia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Ethiopia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melese M, Chidambaram JD, Alemayehu W, Lee DC, Yi EH, Cevallos V, Zhou Z, Donnellan C, Saidel M, Whitcher JP, Gaynor BD, Lietman TM. Feasibility of eliminating ocular Chlamydia trachomatis with repeat mass antibiotic treatments. JAMA. 2004 Aug 11;292(6):721-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15304470</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chidambaram JD, Melese M, Alemayehu W, Yi E, Prabriputaloong T, Lee DC, Cevallos V, Zhou Z, Whitcher JP, Gaynor BD, Lietman TM. Mass antibiotic treatment and community protection in trachoma control programs. Clin Infect Dis. 2004 Nov 1;39(9):e95-7. Epub 2004 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>15494901</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ray KJ, Porco TC, Hong KC, Lee DC, Alemayehu W, Melese M, Lakew T, Yi E, House J, Chidambaram JD, Whitcher JP, Gaynor BD, Lietman TM. A rationale for continuing mass antibiotic distributions for trachoma. BMC Infect Dis. 2007 Aug 7;7:91.</citation>
    <PMID>17683646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee S, Alemayehu W, Melese M, Lakew T, Lee D, Yi E, Cevallos V, Donnellan C, Zhou Z, Chidambaram JD, Gaynor BD, Whitcher JP, Lietman TM. Chlamydia on children and flies after mass antibiotic treatment for trachoma. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2007 Jan;76(1):129-31.</citation>
    <PMID>17255240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chidambaram JD, Alemayehu W, Melese M, Lakew T, Yi E, House J, Cevallos V, Zhou Z, Maxey K, Lee DC, Shapiro BL, Srinivasan M, Porco T, Whitcher JP, Gaynor BD, Lietman TM. Effect of a single mass antibiotic distribution on the prevalence of infectious trachoma. JAMA. 2006 Mar 8;295(10):1142-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16522834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haug S, Lakew T, Habtemariam G, Alemayehu W, Cevallos V, Zhou Z, House J, Ray K, Porco T, Rutar T, Keenan J, Lietman TM, Gaynor BD. The decline of pneumococcal resistance after cessation of mass antibiotic distributions for trachoma. Clin Infect Dis. 2010 Sep 1;51(5):571-4. doi: 10.1086/655697.</citation>
    <PMID>20649409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah NA, House J, Lakew T, Alemayehu W, Halfpenny C, Hong KC, Keenan JD, Porco TC, Whitcher JP, Lietman TM, Gaynor BD. Travel and implications for the elimination of trachoma in ethiopia. Ophthalmic Epidemiol. 2010 Mar;17(2):113-7. doi: 10.3109/09286581003624921.</citation>
    <PMID>20302432</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keenan JD, Lakew T, Alemayehu W, Melese M, Porco TC, Yi E, House JI, Zhou Z, Ray KJ, Acharya NR, Whitcher JP, Gaynor BD, Lietman TM. Clinical activity and polymerase chain reaction evidence of chlamydial infection after repeated mass antibiotic treatments for trachoma. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2010 Mar;82(3):482-7. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.2010.09-0315.</citation>
    <PMID>20207878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Biebesheimer JB, House J, Hong KC, Lakew T, Alemayehu W, Zhou Z, Moncada J, Rogér A, Keenan J, Gaynor BD, Schachter J, Lietman TM. Complete local elimination of infectious trachoma from severely affected communities after six biannual mass azithromycin distributions. Ophthalmology. 2009 Nov;116(11):2047-50. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2009.04.041. Epub 2009 Sep 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19744717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lakew T, Alemayehu W, Melese M, Yi E, House JI, Hong KC, Zhou Z, Ray KJ, Porco TC, Gaynor BD, Lietman TM, Keenan JD. Importance of coverage and endemicity on the return of infectious trachoma after a single mass antibiotic distribution. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2009 Aug 25;3(8):e507. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0000507.</citation>
    <PMID>19707573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lakew T, House J, Hong KC, Yi E, Alemayehu W, Melese M, Zhou Z, Ray K, Chin S, Romero E, Keenan J, Whitcher JP, Gaynor BD, Lietman TM. Reduction and return of infectious trachoma in severely affected communities in Ethiopia. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2009;3(2):e376. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0000376. Epub 2009 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19190781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong KC, Schachter J, Moncada J, Zhou Z, House J, Lietman TM. Lack of macrolide resistance in Chlamydia trachomatis after mass azithromycin distributions for trachoma. Emerg Infect Dis. 2009 Jul;15(7):1088-90. doi: 10.3201/eid1507.081563.</citation>
    <PMID>19624926</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang JL, Hong KC, Schachter J, Moncada J, Lekew T, House JI, Zhou Z, Neuwelt MD, Rutar T, Halfpenny C, Shah N, Whitcher JP, Lietman TM. Detection of Chlamydia trachomatis ocular infection in trachoma-endemic communities by rRNA amplification. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2009 Jan;50(1):90-4. doi: 10.1167/iovs.08-2247. Epub 2008 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>18689701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melese M, Alemayehu W, Lakew T, Yi E, House J, Chidambaram JD, Zhou Z, Cevallos V, Ray K, Hong KC, Porco TC, Phan I, Zaidi A, Gaynor BD, Whitcher JP, Lietman TM. Comparison of annual and biannual mass antibiotic administration for elimination of infectious trachoma. JAMA. 2008 Feb 20;299(7):778-84. doi: 10.1001/jama.299.7.778.</citation>
    <PMID>18285589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gill DA, Lakew T, Alemayehu W, Melese M, Zhou Z, House JI, Hong KC, Ray KJ, Gandhi N, Whitcher JP, Gaynor BD, Lietman TM. Complete elimination is a difficult goal for trachoma programs in severely affected communities. Clin Infect Dis. 2008 Feb 15;46(4):564-6. doi: 10.1086/526777.</citation>
    <PMID>18194094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keenan JD, Lakew T, Alemayehu W, Melese M, House JI, Acharya NR, Porco TC, Gaynor BD, Lietman TM. Slow resolution of clinically active trachoma following successful mass antibiotic treatments. Arch Ophthalmol. 2011 Apr;129(4):512-3. doi: 10.1001/archophthalmol.2011.46.</citation>
    <PMID>21482879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 16, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 22, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Trachoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Chlamydia</keyword>
  <keyword>Azithromycin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chlamydia Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trachoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

