<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00225108</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2002191-01H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00225108</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The STOP CLOT Pilot Study: Study of Low Molecular Weight Heparin in High Risk Cesarean Section</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Cesarean Section Thromboprophylaxis Pilot Study:A Randomized Open-Label Controlled Pilot Study of Prophylactic Low Molecular Weight Heparin in High Risk Postpartum Women Following Cesarean Section</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>LEO Pharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Venous thromboembolism (VTE) remains the most common cause of maternal death in the developed
      world. VTE includes two conditions, deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism (PE).
      DVT refers to a blood clot that has formed in a deep vein, often in the legs and/or pelvis
      and PE refers to the passage of these clots into the lungs (which can be fatal). VTE is up to
      10 times more common in pregnant women than non-pregnant women of comparable age. More than a
      third of pregnancy related VTE occur during the 6 weeks after delivery. When compared with
      vaginal delivery, cesarean delivery further increases the risk of pregnancy associated VTE by
      three-fold.

      A medication called low molecular weight heparin is sometimes prescribed during pregnancy and
      after delivery to prevent VTE. However, clinical practice varies because there hasn't been
      adequate research to determine that this medication is safe and effective at preventing VTE
      during this time. The potential benefits of the medication must also be weighed against its
      cost and possible side effects.

      The researchers are conducting a study that will assess the effectiveness and safety of low
      molecular weight heparin in women who are at moderate to high risk of VTE after a cesarean
      section. They will monitor these women to determine if those who received the medication have
      fewer blood clots. Participants will also be monitored closely for any side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: Venous thromboembolism (VTE) remains the most common cause of maternal mortality
      in the developed world. VTE is up to 10 times more common in pregnant women than non-pregnant
      women of comparable age. More than a third of pregnancy related VTE occur during the brief
      postpartum period (6 weeks). When compared with vaginal delivery, cesarean delivery further
      increases the risk of pregnancy associated VTE by three-fold. Pregnancy associated VTE is
      unique in that isolated iliac vein thrombosis is more likely and long term morbidity
      (post-phlebitic syndrome) is common.

      There is an absence of randomized controlled trials (RCTs) of thromboprophylaxis after
      C-section to guide practice. Many national societies have guidelines on thromboprophylaxis
      however these are not evidence based and compliance with these guidelines is poor.
      Thromboprophylaxis may be associated with adverse effects (bleeding, heparin induced
      thrombocytopenia, skin reactions), inconvenience and cost. It is critical that the efficacy
      and safety of thromboprophylaxis following cesarean delivery be assessed in well designed and
      conducted randomized trials.

      OBJECTIVES: We are conducting a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled pilot study. The
      pilot study seeks to answer the question: Is a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled
      multicentre trial of low molecular weight heparin thromboprophylaxis feasible in moderate to
      high risk women post cesarean section with DVT detected by pelvic vein (MRV) or leg vein (leg
      compression ultrasound) imaging? Our ultimate goal is to determine:

        1. Is LMWH effective in preventing postpartum DVT following cesarean section in women at
           moderate to high risk of VTE?

        2. Is LMWH safe in preventing postpartum DVT following cesarean section in women at
           moderate to high risk of VTE?

        3. Is LMWH cost effective in preventing postpartum DVT following cesarean section in women
           at moderate to high risk of VTE?

      STUDY DESIGN: We propose a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled pilot study of
      prophylactic LMWH in women at moderate to high risk for VTE following cesarean section.
      Eligible, consenting and randomized participants will receive once-daily injections of study
      drug (4,500 IU tinzaparin sodium (Innohep®;) or placebo) within 6 to 24 hours postpartum and
      continue until 3 to 7 days postpartum. On the day of hospital discharge, bilateral leg
      imaging with compression leg ultrasounds and pelvic vein imaging with MRV will be completed.
      The primary outcome will be adjudicated DVT documented on ultrasounds or MRV on the day of
      hospital discharge. Secondary outcomes will include symptomatic DVT and PE, death from PE,
      major and minor bleeding, HIT during the six week postpartum period. All outcomes will be
      adjudicated by an independent committee of experts blinded to study drug allocation.

      With a sample size of 134 patients we will have over 80% power to detect a 50% relative risk
      reduction in the primary outcome event rate and a large enough sample to determine the
      feasibility objectives of the pilot study (i.e. obtain a precise estimate of the primary
      outcome event rate [DVT], a precise estimate of the multicentre recruitment rate, feasibility
      and acceptability of blinded study drug and placebo administration, feasibility of obtaining
      local study centre MRV and central interpretation of MRV and a preliminary relative risk
      reduction estimate with study drug compared to placebo to inform final study sample size
      determination).

      RELEVANCE: Maternal mortality is a devastating outcome with far reaching emotional and
      societal implications. Evidence to guide thromboprophylaxis in women at risk for the number 1
      cause of maternal mortality is required.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>September 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>VTE on magnetic resonance venography (MRV) or bilateral leg Doppler ultrasound</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment>30</enrollment>
  <condition>Deep Vein Thrombosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tinzaparin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (must meet inclusion criteria 1, 2 and 3):

          1. At high risk for thromboembolism (any one of the following):

               1. Age &gt; 35 years

               2. Obesity (&gt; 80 kg)

               3. Para &amp;#61619;4

               4. Gross varicose veins

               5. Current infection

               6. Pre-eclampsia

               7. Immobility prior to surgery (&gt; 4 days)

               8. Major current disease: includes heart or lung disease, cancer, inflammatory bowel
                  disease, and nephrotic syndrome.

               9. Emergency cesarean section in labour

              10. Extended major pelvic or abdominal surgery (e.g. cesarean hysterectomy)

              11. Patients with a family history of VTE

              12. History of superficial phlebitis

          2. Delivered by cesarean section (emergency or planned)

          3. Signed, informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria (must not meet any of the following criteria):

          1. Greater than 36 hours since delivery

          2. Need for anticoagulation, including:

               1. Women with a confirmed thrombophilia

               2. Women with paralysis of lower limbs

               3. Women with personal history of VTE

               4. Women with antiphospholipid antibody syndrome (APLA)

               5. Women with mechanical heart valves

          3. Contraindication to heparin therapy, including:

               1. History of heparin induced thrombocytopenia

               2. Platelet count of less than 100,000 x 10^6/L

               3. Hemoglobin &lt;= 90 g/L or a greater than 30 g/L drop in hemoglobin compared to last
                  antepartum result

               4. History of osteoporosis

               5. History of steroid use (one week or more)

               6. Active bleeding

               7. Documented peptic ulcer within 6 weeks

               8. Heparin, bisulfite, or fish allergy

               9. Severe hypertension (systolic blood pressure [SBP] &gt; 200 and/or diastolic blood
                  pressure [DBP] &gt; 120)

              10. Severe hepatic failure (International Normalized Ratio [INR] &gt; 1.8)

              11. Women with serum creatinine &gt; 80 and an abnormal 24 hour creatinine clearance.

          4. Contraindications to magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), including:

               1. Women with electrically, magnetically or mechanically activated implants

               2. Women with claustrophobia

          5. Women &lt; 18 years of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc Rodger, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Ottawa Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ottawa Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H 8L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rodger MA, Avruch LI, Howley HE, Olivier A, Walker MC. Pelvic magnetic resonance venography reveals high rate of pelvic vein thrombosis after cesarean section. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2006 Feb;194(2):436-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16458642</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 21, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 23, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Deep vein thrombosis</keyword>
  <keyword>bleeding</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heparin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heparin, Low-Molecular-Weight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dalteparin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tinzaparin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

