<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01820130</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR-12-047-FR-SC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01820130</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Autonomic neuroModulation for trEatment of Chronic Heart Failure</brief_title>
  <acronym>TAME-HF</acronym>
  <official_title>Trial of Autonomic neuroModulation for trEatment of Chronic Heart Failure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Jude Medical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Jude Medical</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this clinical investigation is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of Spinal
      Cord Stimulation (SCS) in advanced heart failure (HF) patients with Implantable Cardioverter
      Defibrillator (ICD) but not indicated for Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy (CRT).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    end of inclusion period without patient enrolled
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy Marker of Cardiac remodeling via Left Ventricular End Diastolic Volume (LVEDV) of Patient with advanced HF</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of left ventricular end diastolic volume (LVEDV) as measured by cardiac echo between baseline and after 6 months of SCS therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy Marker of patient symptom via NYHA class for patient with advanced HF</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of NYHA class as marker of patient symptom between baseline and after 6 months of SCS therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy Marker of patient symptom via 6 Minutes Hall Walk distance for patient with advanced HF</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of 6 Minutes Hall walk (6MHW) as marker of patient symptom between baseline and after 6 months of SCS therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety composite marker of SCS therapy for patient with HF and ICD device</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Report of cardiovascular event, arrythmias, devices interaction, procedural and post-procedural events analyzed in a global composite way.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Additional efficacy markers of SCS therapy on patient symptom via Quality Of Life questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Endpoint measurements of patient-reported quality of life after 6 months of therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Additional efficacy markers of SCS therapy on patient symptom via Maximal exercise test tolerance</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Additional endpoint measurements include exercise tolerance between baseline and 6 months via cardiopulmonary test, including maximum level of exercise and heart rhythm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Additional efficacy markers of SCS therapy on cardiac function via echocardiography</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Additional endpoint measurements include standard echocardiography markers of LV structure and function including systolic and diastolic performance and cardiac dimensions as a marker of structural reverse remodeling</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Cord Stimulation system therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>St Jude Medical EON mini rechargeable system</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>St Jude Medical EON mini rechargeable system</intervention_name>
    <description>implantation of Eon Mini Neurostimulation System (IPG Model 3788)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Cord Stimulation system therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Eon Mini Neurostimulation System (IPG Model 3788)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients has a Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) less than or equal to 35%

          -  Patient is in New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class III

          -  Patient has a QRS duration &lt;120 ms (non-paced QRS, at the time of device Implant or
             protocol inclusion)

          -  Patient has had an ICD implanted for &gt;90 days

          -  Patient is receiving stable and optimal medical therapy for HF (&gt;90 days) as describe
             by &quot;European Society of Cardiology 2012 recommendation for diagnosis and treatment of
             acute and chronic Heart Failure&quot;, except in case of contraindication or allergy

          -  Patient is able to provide written Informed Consent prior to any investigational
             related procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient currently has an implanted spinal cord stimulator or previously had an
             implanted spinal cord stimulator which is now explanted or has had previous spinal
             surgery that would interfere with implant of percutaneous SCS leads in the upper
             thoracic region

          -  Patient has polyneuropathy

          -  Patient requires short-wave diathermy, microwave diathermy or therapeutic ultrasound
             diathermy

          -  Patient is in NYHA class IV

          -  Patient has received a tissue / organ transplant or is expected to have a tissue /
             organ transplant within the next 180 days

          -  Patient has a cardiac resynchronization therapy (CRT) device, or LV Assist device or
             is expected to receive CRT, or left ventricular assist device (LVAD) within the next
             180 days

          -  Patient has critical valvular heart disease that requires valve repair or replacement

          -  Patient has had a myocardial infarction (MI) or cardiac revascularization procedure
             (percutaneous coronary intervention or coronary artery bypass graft) within 90 days of
             enrollment

          -  Patient is on IV inotropic therapy

          -  Patient has active myocarditis or early postpartum cardiomyopathy

          -  Patient has taken any of the following drugs within 30 days of enrollment: systemic
             corticosteroids, cytostatic and immunosuppressive drug therapy (cyclophosphamide,
             methotrexate, cyclosporine, azathioprine, etc.), DNA depleting or cytotoxic drugs

          -  Patient is pregnant, or of childbearing potential and is not using adequate
             contraceptive methods, or nursing

          -  Patient with a bleeding tendency (INR &gt;1.2 and platelet count &lt;100 x109 per liter)

          -  Patient has a local infection at the ICD implant location or systemic infection

          -  Patient has renal insufficiency (creatinine &gt;3.0 mg/dl)

          -  Patient with risk of allergy to SCS device component materials

          -  Patient having one of the following condition must be considered as non relevant for
             SCS implantation:

               1. / Patient with active stent

               2. / Patient having bare metal stent for less than 6 months

               3. / Patient presented with an acute coronary syndrome within the last 6 months

               4. / Patient with stent on the common

               5. / Patient with a history of stent thrombosis

               6. / Coronary Patient receiving double antiplatelet medication

          -  Patient is participating in another clinical study with an active treatment arm

          -  Patient is less than 18 years old

          -  Patient's life's expectancy is less than 1 year as assessed by investigators
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pierre Bordachar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Bordeaux</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac</city>
        <zip>33604</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 25, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 28, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 26, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 26, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 27, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

