<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01824420</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TCGHUROL008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01824420</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Flexibly adding-on Second Antimuscarinic Agent to the First Antimuscarinics for Refractory Overactive Bladder Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Flexibly adding-on Second Antimuscarinic Agent to the First Antimuscarinics for Refractory Overactive Bladder Syndrome - A Prospective Randomized Controlled Comparative Study With Mono-antimuscarinic Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Buddhist Tzu Chi General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Buddhist Tzu Chi General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate if oxybutynin ER adding on antimuscarinics is more effective than
      mono-antimuscarinic treatment for patients with refractory OAB
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  Introduction:Overactive bladder (OAB) is a symptom syndrome characterized by urgency
           frequency with or without urgency incontinence. Usually no metabolic or anatomical
           disorders can be found in patients with OAB, and the condition may have a great impact
           on quality of life. Antimuscarinics are the first line treatment and yield a success
           rate of more than 70%. Urothelial dysfunction and abnormalities of sensory receptor
           expression or transmitter release in the suburothelial nerves might contribute to OAB
           which is refractory to antimuscarinics. In patients who failed current antimuscarinic
           treatment, intravesical botulinum toxin A (BoNT-A) injection provides an chance of
           improvement. Previous studies reported success rates of BoNT-A injection for OAB ranged
           from 60 to 80%. Intravesical treatment to inhibit abnormal receptor expression or
           transmitter release in the sensory nerve terminals of the suburothelial space can
           provide good therapeutic effects in the treatment of OAB. However, patients might
           develop large postvoid residual (PVR) and subsequent urinary tract infection (UTI) after
           BoNT-A injections, therefore, this treatment is usually left for patients who are
           refractory to antimuscarinic therapy. However, how to define antimuscarinic refractory
           OAB remains controversial. How many different types of antimuscarinics should be
           prescribed before we call the case failure has not been elucidated. The aim of this
           study is to evaluate the effect of flexibly adding-on oxybutynin ER (5mg QD) in patients
           with OAB who were refractory to monotherapy with the first antimuscarinic agent
           (tolterodine 4mg QD).

        -  Methods: A total of 200 patients with refractory OAB will be included in this
           prospective, open label protocol. Inclusion criteria are persistent OAB symptoms
           (frequency urgency with/without urgency urinary incontinence) after behaviour therapy
           and an optimized dose of one antimuscarinic agent (Tolterodine 4mg) for at least 3
           months. Patients with neurogenic diseases, untreated bladder outlet obstruction,
           recurrent UTI, large PVR (&gt;150ml) will be excluded from this study. Patients will be
           randomized to allocate in the treatment group (receiving tolterodine 4mg QD and
           oxybutynin 5mg to 15mg QD) or control group (tolterodine 4mg QD) in 1:1 ratio based on
           the permuted block randomization code. Oxybutynin ER 5mg to 15 mg once daily will be
           flexibly adding-on from baseline to the third month in the treatment group, depending on
           patient's effectiveness and tolerability to adverse events. At the baseline, 1 and 3
           months after oxybutynin ER adding-on, we will assess the International Prostate Symptom
           Score (IPSS), Overactive Bladder Symptom Score (OABSS), Patient Perception of Bladder
           Condition (PPBC), the Urgency Severity Scale (USS) questionnaires, uroflowmetry and PVR.
           The therapeutic effect will be considered as successful if there was a reduction of PPBC
           of 2 from baseline and a reduction of USS of 1 from baseline, or the USS value is 0 at 3
           months. The adverse events and tolerability of this combined therapy will also be
           assessed.

        -  Expected Results: Compared with baseline, total IPSS, IPSS storage subscore, quality of
           life indexes, OABSS, USS and PPBC will be expected to significantly decrease at 1 and 3
           months. PVR might be increased at 3 months after adding-on treatment. The changes of
           IPSS voiding subscore, peak urinary flow rate and voided volume might be increased or
           comparable to the control group during the follow-up. We expect at least one-third of
           patients can have a successful therapeutic effect without significantly increased
           adverse events. However, the other patients might withdraw from the study due to adverse
           events such as severe dry mouth, constipation, large PVR, UTI, severe difficult
           urination or acute urinary retention.

      Adverse events should be cautiously monitored during the treatment course.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, open-label study. The overactive bladder patients maintained their previous antimuscarinic medication and we flexibly added on the second antimuscarinic drug (oxybutynin ER 5 mg QD) or not.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>No masking was designed in this study</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the Perception of Bladder Condition (PPBC) at different time points</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy:
Change from Baseline in the Perception of Bladder Condition (PPBC) at different time points (1 month, 2 months and 3 months). If patients have a PPBC improved by two scales, they are considered as successfully treated, otherwise failed treatment.
Safety:
Systemic adverse events such as difficult urination, dry mouth, dry eye, blurred vision, constipation, dizziness or general weakness</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the Overactive Bladder Symptom Score (OABSS) at different time points</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy:
Change from Baseline in the Overactive Bladder Symptom Score (OABSS) at different time points (1 month, 2 months and 3 months).
Safety:
Systemic adverse events such as difficult urination, dry mouth, dry eye, blurred vision, constipation, dizziness or general weakness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the urinary sensation scale (USS) at different time points</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy:
Change from Baseline in the urinary sensation scale (USS) at different time points (1 month, 2 months and 3 months).
Safety:
Systemic adverse events such as difficult urination, dry mouth, dry eye, blurred vision, constipation, dizziness or general weakness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) at different time points</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy:
Change from Baseline in the International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) at different time points (1 month, 2 months and 3 months).
Safety:
Systemic adverse events such as difficult urination, dry mouth, dry eye, blurred vision, constipation, dizziness or general weakness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the maximum flow rate (Qmax) at different time points</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy:
Change from Baseline in the maximum flow rate (Qmax) at different time points (1 month, 2 months and 3 months).
Safety:
Systemic adverse events such as difficult urination, dry mouth, dry eye, blurred vision, constipation, dizziness or general weakness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the voided volume at different time points</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy:
Change from Baseline in the voided volume at different time points (1 month, 2 months and 3 months).
Safety:
Systemic adverse events such as difficult urination, dry mouth, dry eye, blurred vision, constipation, dizziness or general weakness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the postvoid residual volume (PVR) at different time points</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy:
Change from Baseline in the postvoid residual volume (PVR) at different time points (1 month, 2 months and 3 months).
Safety:
Systemic adverse events such as difficult urination, dry mouth, dry eye, blurred vision, constipation, dizziness or general weakness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the total prostate volume (TPV) at different time points</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy:
Change from Baseline in the total prostate volume (TPV) at different time points (1 month, 2 months and 3 months) are evaluated in men
Safety:
Systemic adverse events such as difficult urination, dry mouth, dry eye, blurred vision, constipation, dizziness or general weakness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the transition zone index (TZI) at different time points</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 2 months and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy:
Change from Baseline in the transition zone index (TZI) at different time points (1 month, 2 months and 3 months) are evaluated in men
Safety:
Systemic adverse events such as difficult urination, dry mouth, dry eye, blurred vision, constipation, dizziness or general weakness</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">129</enrollment>
  <condition>Overactive Bladder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tolterodine (Detrusitol) 4mg QD and Oxybutynin (Ditropan) ER 5mg QD</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tolterodine (Detrusitol) 4mg QD</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Detrusitol 4mg QD and Oxybutynin ER 5mg QD</intervention_name>
    <description>Study group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tolterodine (Detrusitol) 4mg QD</other_name>
    <other_name>Oxybutynin (Ditropan) ER 5mg QD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Detrusitol 4mg QD</intervention_name>
    <description>Control group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tolterodine (Detrusitol) 4mg QD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients aged ≥20 years of male or female gender with OAB refractory to one
             antimuscarinics therapy

          -  Patient or his/her legally acceptable representative has signed the written informed
             consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with untreated bladder outlet obstruction, intrinsic sphincter deficiency,
             pelvic organ prolapse

          -  Patients with history of urethral injury or transurethral surgery for prostate or
             bladder

          -  Patients with severe cardiopulmonary disease and such as congestive heart failure,
             arrhythmia, poorly controlled hypertension, not able to receive regular follow-up

          -  Patients with known active urinary tract infection, urinary stone or malignancy

          -  Patients have laboratory abnormalities at screening including:

               1. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 3 x upper limit of normal range.

               2. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; 3 x upper limit of normal range.

               3. Patients have abnormal serum creatinine level &gt; 2 x upper limit of normal range.

          -  Patients with urinary retention, PVR≥250 ml

          -  Patients with any other serious disease or condition considered by the investigator
             not suitable for entry into the trial

          -  Patients participated investigational drug trial within 1 month before entering this
             study

          -  Patients with major psychiatric illness or drug abuse
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hann-Chorng Kuo, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Urology, Buddhist Tzu Chi General Hospital and Tzu Chi University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Buddhist Tzu Chi General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hualien</city>
        <zip>970</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abrams P, Kelleher CJ, Kerr LA, Rogers RG. Overactive bladder significantly affects quality of life. Am J Manag Care. 2000 Jul;6(11 Suppl):S580-90. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11183901</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chapple CR. Muscarinic receptor antagonists in the treatment of overactive bladder. Urology. 2000 May;55(5A Suppl):33-46; discussion 50. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10767450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yiangou Y, Facer P, Ford A, Brady C, Wiseman O, Fowler CJ, Anand P. Capsaicin receptor VR1 and ATP-gated ion channel P2X3 in human urinary bladder. BJU Int. 2001 Jun;87(9):774-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11412212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Apostolidis A, Popat R, Yiangou Y, Cockayne D, Ford AP, Davis JB, Dasgupta P, Fowler CJ, Anand P. Decreased sensory receptors P2X3 and TRPV1 in suburothelial nerve fibers following intradetrusor injections of botulinum toxin for human detrusor overactivity. J Urol. 2005 Sep;174(3):977-82; discussion 982-3.</citation>
    <PMID>16094018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simpson LL. Kinetic studies on the interaction between botulinum toxin type A and the cholinergic neuromuscular junction. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1980 Jan;212(1):16-21.</citation>
    <PMID>6243359</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuo HC. Urodynamic evidence of effectiveness of botulinum A toxin injection in treatment of detrusor overactivity refractory to anticholinergic agents. Urology. 2004 May;63(5):868-72.</citation>
    <PMID>15134967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuo HC. Comparison of effectiveness of detrusor, suburothelial and bladder base injections of botulinum toxin a for idiopathic detrusor overactivity. J Urol. 2007 Oct;178(4 Pt 1):1359-63. Epub 2007 Aug 16.</citation>
    <PMID>17706718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 1, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 4, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Buddhist Tzu Chi General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hann-Chorng Kuo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Department of Urology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Refractory overactive bladder syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Antimuscarinic agent</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder, Overactive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tolterodine Tartrate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oxybutynin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscarinic Antagonists</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mandelic Acids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD cannot be released unless approval by the Ethics Committee of the Buddhist Tzu Chi General Hospital, Hualien, Taiwan</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

