<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01820377</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H2008:060</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01820377</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Aboriginal Youth Mentorship Program</brief_title>
  <acronym>AYMP</acronym>
  <official_title>Northern Lights Physical Activity Program for Management of Type 2 Diabetes Early in Life: Aboriginal Youth Mentorship Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Manitoba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Manitoba Institute of Child Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Lawson Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manitoba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Building on the successes of a communal, relationship based approach to Aboriginal youth
      mentoring in an after school physical activity program (AYMP), the investigators are
      evaluating a peer-led approach for diabetes prevention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Building on the successes of a communal, relationship based approach to Aboriginal youth
      mentoring in an after school physical activity program (AYMP), the investigators are
      evaluating a peer-led approach for diabetes prevention. High school students volunteer as
      mentors, and develop an after-school program that they then deliver to children in grade 4.
      The mentors meet twice a week. The first day, they develop an activity plan and decide roles
      and responsibilities to ensure successful delivery of each activity. The second day, they
      deliver the program to the grade 4s, which incorporates a healthy snack, 45-minutes of
      physical activity, and educational games/activities. Our primary goal is to determine the
      health benefits of AYMP; guided by our youth mentors and community advisors, the
      investigators will also develop a number of research questions that will help us to better
      understand the social, emotional, physical and spiritual outcomes of the peer-led mentor
      program. To answer these questions, the investigators will train community members in both
      qualitative and quantitative methods. The quantitative outcomes of this study include
      physical activity, waist circumference, obesity rates, and self-esteem. Qualitative methods
      may include photovoice and focus group interviews. All of these will be used to assess the
      social determinants of health and contextual features of the program.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist Circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome will be waist circumference measured at the level of the iliac crest. Waist circumference is a clinically relevant outcome as it is a robust predictor of Type 2 Diabetes in youth and other cardiometabolic outcomes in youth.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daily Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary outcomes include daily physical activity measured using a pedometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of overweight/obesity between groups</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>Rates of overweight and obesity between the groups will be measured before and after the intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Efficacy in Peer Interactions</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale is designed to measure youths' perceptions of their ability to be successful in social interactions. This includes their ability to be persuasive towards peers in positive ways. The questionnaire contains two subscales that measure social self-efficacy in conflict and non-conflict situations. The subscales can be used separately or combined into a total score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Civic Responsibility Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>This scale measures youths' community awareness, knowledge, and investment in helping to improve their community.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Teacher-on-Pupil Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Teacher on Pupil Questionnaire for the Child Cohort recorded specific information about the Study child, such as temperament, academic performance and school preparedness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent Lifestyle Behaviours Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>Questions about Socioeconomic status, as well as daily physical activity and dietary habits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Social Determinants of Health</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators recognize that the structural social determinants of health including income inequality, local wealth, sex and ethnic inequalities are key aspects to adolescent health in Aboriginal adolescents. The investigators also recognize that these are unlikely to change with the AYMP. Therefore the investigators will focus on a series of proximal factors. Using Indigenous approaches (i.e. sharing circles, storytelling) the investigators will explore the influence of the AYMP on (1) respect (a major theme in pilot testing), (2) perceived changes in the school environment, (3) family connectedness, (4) peer influence and (5) health behaviours. If youth prefer to discuss issues in a private setting, opportunities will be provided.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">246</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aboriginal Youth Mentorship Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>High school students volunteer as mentors, and develop an after-school program that they then deliver to children in grade 4. The mentors meet twice a week. The first day, they develop an activity plan and decide roles and responsibilities to ensure successful delivery of each activity. The second day, they deliver the program to the grade 4 students, which incorporates a healthy snack, 45-minutes of physical activity, and educational games/activities. Grade 4s act as the intervention group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group acts as a control, and are not apart of the Aboriginal Youth Mentorship Program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aboriginal Youth Mentorship Program</intervention_name>
    <description>High school students volunteer as mentors, and develop an after-school program that they then deliver to children in grade 4. The mentors meet twice a week. The first day, they develop an activity plan and decide roles and responsibilities to ensure successful delivery of each activity. The second day, they deliver the program to the grade 4s, which incorporates a healthy snack, 45-minutes of physical activity, and educational games/activities. Grade 4s are our intervention group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aboriginal Youth Mentorship Program</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AYMP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Grade 4 students. We chose to intervene with youth in grade 4 for four primary
             reasons: (1) the large majority of youth in grade 4 are in tanner stage 1 and will not
             experience puberty-related weight gain during the school year; (2) previous experience
             by our group revealed that attendance throughout the school year is higher in students
             in grade 4 relative to students in grade 5 or 6; (3) students in grade 4 are old
             enough to perform low organized games included in the intervention; and (4) retention
             rates in the intervention are greater than students in grades 5 and 6.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  While all students will be invited to participate in the intervention, for measurement
             purposes, we will exclude data from those students who may not respond to the
             intervention or would be unable to participate in the physical activity aspects of the
             component. This includes children with: (1) musculoskeletal injuries that limit
             physical activities; (2) treatment for chronic conditions that would elicit weight
             gain or limit participation in physical activity (insulin, corticosteroids, blood
             pressure medications); (3) poor attendance (&lt;60% of school days) in the first
             semester; (4) children whose parents are unwilling to provide consent. Note: the
             intervention will be offered to youth with chronic conditions, however their data will
             not be included in the final analysis, due to confounding effects of medications.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan M McGavock, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Manitoba, Manitoba Institute of Child Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joannie Halas, PhD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Manitoba</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Research Institute of Manitoba</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winnipeg</city>
        <state>Manitoba</state>
        <zip>R3E 3P4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 21, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 25, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 28, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 2, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 2, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Manitoba</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jon McGavock</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Peer-mentoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Type 2 Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
  <keyword>After-school program</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

