<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00272363</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>060059</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>06-EI-0059</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00272363</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical and Molecular Studies in Families With Glaucoma and Related Diseases</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical and Molecular Studies in Families With Glaucoma and Related Diseases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will document the clinical and genetic features of glaucoma and related diseases,
      including normal tension glaucoma (NTG). Researchers would like to define genetic influences
      and eventually isolate the genes causing those diseases.

      Glaucoma is an important cause of vision loss in the United States and worldwide. The disease
      is marked by a wearing down of the retina and optic nerve, often associated with increased
      pressure in the eye. It is often an inherited trait. This study will involve between 250 and
      2,000 patients over a 5-year period. It will examine the natural history of the genotype, or
      genetic makeup, of a person and the phenotype, that is, visible situations produced by the
      interaction of the genotype and one's environment.

      Patients 4 and older who have glaucoma or related diseases or whose family members have those
      diseases may be eligible for this study. They will complete a medical history for the doctors
      to verify the diagnosis, inquire about medical problems and surgical operations, and gather
      data about vision problems in a patient's family (by drawing a family tree). The complete eye
      examination may take several hours. Eye drops will be used to dilate, or enlarge, the pupils
      of patients' eyes, and the pupils will stay dilated for 4 to 6 hours. There may be some
      temporary glare in brightly lit areas, which can be reduced by wearing of sunglasses.
      Patients may experience some blurring of vision. There may be a localized allergic reaction
      to the medication used or an increase of pressure inside the eye. If that occurs, medication
      to control the reaction will be given. In addition, photographs of the retina and perhaps
      even the lens will be taken. For that procedure, eye drops will dilate the pupils of the
      eyes. The light that is involved with the specialized photography may cause some mild
      discomfort. Patients will undergo eye tests regarding color vision, field of vision, and
      ability to see the dark. Also, there will be a measurement of pressure in the eye and
      thickness of the cornea.

      To study patients' DNA, the researchers will obtain a blood sample of about 4 teaspoons from
      patients 10 years or older. A smaller amount of about 1 teaspoon for each 5 lb. of body
      weight will be collected from younger patients. Those DNA samples will be used only for
      research in the genetic disorder in a patient's family. No other testing or research will be
      conducted on the blood samples without patients' separate permission. Also, the DNA will be
      stored by codes that the researchers define and contained in a secured building.

      In this study, researchers will not provide information about a patient's health to patient
      family members or to other people. They will not discuss information such as adoption or
      biological fatherhood unless it has medical implications for the patient or the patient's
      family members.

      If information obtained from this study may be important to patients' health, they will be
      informed when it is available. There are no plans to give patients the results of any medical
      tests, evaluations, or other research data. Further research may be needed before such
      results become meaningful.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: This project, Clinical and Molecular Studies in Families with Glaucoma and Related
      Diseases, will study the inheritance of glaucoma in families of many nationalities and ethnic
      backgrounds in order to identify the genes that, when mutated, cause glaucoma, elevated
      intraocular pressure, or similar diseases and the pathophysiology through which they act.

      Study Population: The number of subjects to be enrolled has no logical upper limit, but will
      be at least 250 and not more than 2000 during the next 5 years.

      Design: The study consists of ascertaining individuals and especially families with multiple
      individuals, affected by glaucoma or related retinal and anterior chamber diseases. These
      patients and their families will undergo detailed ophthalmological examinations and, where
      indicated, additional non-investigational examinations to characterize disease in their
      families and determine their affectation status. A blood sample will be collected from each
      individual for isolation of DNA and in some individuals biochemical testing or for
      lymphoblastoid transformation to establish a renewable source of DNA. Linkage analysis,
      physical mapping, SNP and microsatellite analysis for association studies, and mutational
      screening will be carried out to identify the specific the gene and the mutations in it that
      are associated with glaucoma in this family. If necessary, the gene product or blood sample
      will be characterized biochemically. The study will enroll subjects at the NEI and at
      collaborating institutions.

      Outcome Measures: Linkage will be determined using the lod score method and mutations in
      specific genes will be assessed using a combination of residue conservation, blosum score,
      and molecular modeling. Biochemical, metabolic, and physiological effects will be
      individualized to the specific assay.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 29, 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 29, 2016</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Family-Based</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Statistically significant linkage</measure>
    <time_frame>ongoing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">484</enrollment>
  <condition>Glaucoma</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects with the following will be recruited:

          1. Individuals or family members of individuals with glaucoma, either congenital,
             childhood, or age related.

          2. Adults must be capable of providing their own consent.

          3. All subjects must be able to cooperate with study examination and phlebotomy.

          4. Older than 4 years of age.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Diseases, infections, or trauma that mimic primary glaucoma.

          2. Children requiring sedation for study procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James F Hejtmancik, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Eye Institute (NEI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eye Research Institute, Zhongstan Ophthalmic Ctr, Sun Yat-Sen University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kubota R, Kudoh J, Mashima Y, Asakawa S, Minoshima S, Hejtmancik JF, Oguchi Y, Shimizu N. Genomic organization of the human myocilin gene (MYOC) responsible for primary open angle glaucoma (GLC1A). Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1998 Jan 14;242(2):396-400.</citation>
    <PMID>9446806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leske MC, Nemesure B, He Q, Wu SY, Fielding Hejtmancik J, Hennis A. Patterns of open-angle glaucoma in the Barbados Family Study. Ophthalmology. 2001 Jun;108(6):1015-22.</citation>
    <PMID>11382622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nemesure B, He Q, Mendell N, Wu SY, Hejtmancik JF, Hennis A, Leske MC; Barbados Family Study Group. Inheritance of open-angle glaucoma in the Barbados family study. Am J Med Genet. 2001 Sep 15;103(1):36-43.</citation>
    <PMID>11562932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 29, 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 4, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 5, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glaucoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

