<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00270062</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR005893</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00270062</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Safety of Epoetin Alfa and Its Effectiveness in Facilitating the Presurgical Collection of Blood From Anemic Patients for Possible Self-transfusion During and After Scheduled Joint Surgery.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Study to Determine Whether R-HuEPO Can Facilitate Presurgical Autologous Blood Donation in Patients With Low Hematocrit Levels</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety of epoetin alfa and its effectiveness in
      facilitating the presurgical collection of blood from anemic patients for possible
      self-transfusion during and after scheduled joint surgery and its effectiveness in reducing
      surgery-related transfusion requirements. Epoetin alfa is a genetically engineered protein
      that stimulates red blood cell production.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Major surgical procedures may require transfusion of several units of blood. Blood
      transfusions from other people may be associated with transfusion reactions that cause fever
      or infections such as hepatitis or AIDS that are carried (and donated) in blood. However,
      self-donations of blood may cause anemia in a patient who will be undergoing surgery a few
      weeks later. Previous research with epoetin alfa suggests that epoetin alfa increases the
      rate of red blood cell production and decreases anemia. This randomized, double-blind,
      placebo-controlled, multicenter study is designed to determine whether epoetin alfa in
      patients with low hematocrit (red blood cell percentage &lt;39 percent) will stimulate the bone
      marrow to produce red blood cells and therefore increase a patient's ability to self-donate
      blood prior to major surgery for joint diseases. Patients will be randomly assigned to
      receive either 600 units of epoetin alfa per kilogram of body weight or matching placebo,
      injected into a vein on the first study day, and every 3 to 4 days thereafter for 21 days.
      Effectiveness will be determined by the number of units of self-donated blood collected, the
      number of units of donor blood used at the time of surgery, and the red blood cell
      percentages just before surgery. Safety evaluations including the incidence of adverse
      events, physical examinations, and clinical laboratory tests will be performed throughout the
      study. The study hypothesis is that patients treated with epoetin alfa will be able to donate
      more units of blood during the 3 weeks prior to surgery, will need fewer donor-donated units
      of blood, and will have a higher level of red blood cells than patients who receive placebo.
      600 units of epoetin alfa per kilogram of body weight, or an equivalent volume of placebo,
      injected into a vein every 3 to 4 days for 21 days (6 doses) during the period before
      surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 1989</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 1991</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of units of blood self-donated; Number of donor-donated units of blood used; Total red blood cell volume; Total red blood cell production; Change in hemoglobin from baseline to after the final dose of study medication, but before surgery</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total transfusion requirements at the time of surgery; incidence of adverse events</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">77</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>epoetin alfa</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients scheduled for surgery involving the joints, 25 to 35 days after starting
             epoetin alfa therapy

          -  having a hematocrit (percentage of red cells in the blood) of &lt;=39%

          -  in good general health.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a history of any primary blood disease

          -  having a history of artery blockage in the heart, body or brain, a history of
             seizures, uncontrolled high blood pressure, or active inflammatory disease, (except
             osteoarthritis or rheumatoid arthritis)

          -  losing blood internally from the stomach or intestines or elsewhere in the body

          -  using of any cell toxic drug, drugs that suppress the immune system, or drugs known to
             influence red blood cell production (such as chemotherapy for cancer) within 1 month
             of therapy

          -  having a folate or vitamin B12 deficiency, iron-deficiency anemia, or a disease that
             destroys blood cells.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L. C. Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_JNJ_6051&amp;studyid=677&amp;filename=CR005893_CSR.pdf</url>
    <description>A study to evaluate the safety of epoetin alfa and its effectiveness in facilitating the presurgical collection of blood from anemic patients for possible self-transfusion during and after scheduled joint surgery.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 22, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 22, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 26, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 18, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>blood transfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>epoetin alfa</keyword>
  <keyword>erythropoietin</keyword>
  <keyword>surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>blood donation</keyword>
  <keyword>blood</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Epoetin Alfa</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

