<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00270907</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2005-0133</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00270907</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CT-2103 in Combination With Gemcitabine in Metastatic Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of CT-2103 in Combination With Gemcitabine in Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CTI BioPharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this phase I clinical study is to find the highest safe dose of gemcitabine and
      CT-2103 that can be given in combination for the treatment of metastatic breast cancer. The
      safety and effectiveness of this combination will also be studied. This clinical trial will
      be offered to patients who are being considered for treatment with gemcitabine. Research lab
      samples and research biopsies will not be requested as part of this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CT-2103 is a chemotherapy drug designed to deliver an active chemotherapy medication
      (paclitaxel) inside of tumor cells. Gemcitabine is FDA approved for the treatment of breast
      cancer.

      Before you can start receiving drug on this study, you will have what are called &quot;screening
      tests.&quot; These tests will help the doctor decide if you are eligible to take part in the
      study. You will have a complete medical history and physical exam. You will have a CT scan of
      the chest and abdomen, a bone scan, and a chest x-ray performed to document the size and
      location of the tumor(s). Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests. Women
      who are able to have children must have a negative blood-pregnancy test.

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be assigned to a dose of
      CT-2103. Participants in this study will be enrolled in groups of 3. The first group will
      receive the lowest dose of CT-2103. Each new group of patients will receive a higher dose
      until the highest safe dose is found. The dose that you receive will depend on how many
      patients have received CT-2103 before you. You will only be assigned to one dose level, and
      you will stay at this same dose level for the entire study unless you have a serious side
      effect that requires the dose to be decreased or stopped. All participants will receive the
      same dose of gemcitabine, though it too may be lowered if severe side effects occur.

      Both CT-2103 and gemcitabine are given through a vein. On the first day of your therapy
      (called 'Day 1'), you will receive a routinely given medication, ondansetron (Zofran), that
      will help decrease the risk of nausea. About 30 minutes later, CT-2103 will be given over
      10-20 minutes followed by gemcitabine over 30 minutes.

      One week later ('Day 8'), you will receive gemcitabine through the vein over about 30
      minutes. You will return to see your doctor 3 weeks after your first dose of chemotherapy
      ('Day 21'), and then this pattern or cycle of treatment will be given again.

      You will continue on therapy as long as the cancer is being controlled and you are not having
      unexpected or intolerable side effects. All chemotherapy will be given at M. D. Anderson.

      You will have blood (about 2 tablespoons) collected once a week while you are on study to
      monitor the effects of chemotherapy on your bone marrow and liver and kidney function. You
      will see your doctor every 3 weeks to monitor how you are tolerating the therapy. At these
      visits, your doctor will discuss any symptoms you are having, and you will have a physical
      exam. If you are taking warfarin (Coumadin) you will need to have blood (about 1 tablespoon)
      collected three times a week to monitor you warfarin levels.

      After each 6 weeks of chemotherapy, you will have repeat scans to evaluate the effects of the
      study drugs upon your cancer.

      Once you have stopped taking therapy with CT-2103 and gemcitabine, you will be asked to
      return to see your physician in about 6 weeks to evaluate how you are doing and to find out
      if there has been any additional change in the cancer. You will have a complete medical
      history and physical exam. You will have a CT scan of the chest and abdomen, a bone scan, and
      a chest x-ray performed to document the size and location of the tumor(s).

      This is an investigational study. Gemcitabine is FDA approved for the treatment of breast
      cancer when given in combination with paclitaxel. Gemcitabine will not be provided free of
      charge. CT-2103 is not yet FDA approved and will be provided free of charge during the study.
      Any laboratory testing that is not standard of care will be paid for by the supporting
      company. About 18 women will take part in this study. All will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of CT-2103</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <description>MTD defined as the level of CT-2103 at which 2 out of 6 patients had dose limiting toxicity (DLT) where the primary DLT events of CT-2103 are uncomplicated neutropenia, febrile neutropenia, and/or grade 3 neuropathy. Assessments during the first cycle of therapy, where cycle is 21 days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Response</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks following chemotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of response in participants with measurable disease after each 6 weeks of chemotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CT-2103 + Gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CT-2103 135 mg/m^2 intravenous (IV) on Day 1. Gemcitabine 1000 mg/m^2 IV on Day 1 and 8.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CT-2103</intervention_name>
    <description>135 mg/m^2 IV on Day 1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CT-2103 + Gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xyotax</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>1000 mg/m^2 IV on Day 1 and 8.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CT-2103 + Gemcitabine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gemzar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must have histologically confirmed breast cancer that is either metastatic or
             unresectable.

          2. Patients must have received anthracyclines as treatment of either early stage or
             metastatic breast cancer.

          3. Previous taxane therapy is allowed.

          4. Age &gt;/= 18 years. There is limited data regarding the use of CT-2103 in children under
             18 and they will be excluded from this combination dose finding study.

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status &lt;/= 2 (Karnofsky &gt;/=
             60%).

          6. Measurable disease is not required.

          7. Previous endocrine therapies are allowed but should be discontinued prior to
             initiation of therapy.

          8. Patients must sign an informed consent indicating that they are aware of the
             investigational nature of the study, in keeping with institutional policy.

          9. The effects of CT-2103 on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason
             women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for
             the duration of study participation. Females of childbearing potential are defined as
             females who have not undergone a hysterectomy or who have not been postmenopausal for
             at least 24 months.

         10. Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below: leukocytes &gt;/=
             3,000/ul; absolute neutrophil count &gt;/= 1,500/ul; platelets &gt;/= 100,000/ul; total
             bilirubin within normal institutional limits; aspartate aminotransferase (AST or SGOT)
             and alanine aminotransferase (ALT or SGPT) &lt;/= 2.5 * institutional upper limit of
             normal; creatinine within normal institutional limits or creatinine clearance &gt;/= 60
             mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal;
             coagulation prothrombin time (PT) and Partial thromboplastin time (PTT) within normal
             limits unless patients are already anti-coagulated for other reasons (i.e., atrial
             fibrillation, etc.).

         11. Patients with Her-2/neu positive tumors should have received prior trastuzumab if
             clinically appropriate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with preexisting neuropathy &gt;/= grade 2.

          2. Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents.

          3. Patients with known brain metastases should be excluded from this clinical trial
             because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop progressive neurologic
             dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic and other adverse events.

          4. History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to CT-2103, gemcitabine or other agents used in study. History of typical
             paclitaxel- or docetaxel-induced Grade 1-2 hypersensitivity reactions is permitted.

          5. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          6. Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to entering
             the study.

          7. Previous history of stem cell transplantation.

          8. History of central nervous system metastases.

          9. While there is no strict exclusion based upon previous number of therapies, patients
             who experienced grade 3 or 4 hematologic toxicity requiring the use of white blood
             count (WBC) growth factor support during their most recent chemotherapy prior to
             enrollment are excluded. Exceptions to this would include patients who received growth
             factor support as mandated by a clinical study, and/or patients who have been off all
             chemotherapy for at least 6 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marjorie Green, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>The University of Texas (UT) MD Anderson Cancer Center official website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 28, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 28, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 29, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 13, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>CT-2103</keyword>
  <keyword>Gemcitabine</keyword>
  <keyword>Xyotax</keyword>
  <keyword>Gemzar</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

