<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00275158</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DK-52876 (completed)</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DK-52876</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00275158</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Glomerular Injury of Preeclampsia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of L-Arginine Therapy on the Glomerular Injury of Pre-Eclampsia: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Research Resources (NCRR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pre-eclampsia complicates 7 - 10% of pregnancies and constitutes a leading cause of fetal
      growth retardation and premature birth, as well as infant and maternal morbidity and
      mortality. The kidney is the primary site of injury resulting in high blood pressure, loss of
      protein into the urine and decreased kidney function. The release of vasoconstrictors over
      vasodilators from an abnormal placenta may underlie pre-eclampsia. Nitric Oxide (NO) is an
      important vasodilator that is thought to play an important role in the kidneys ability to
      accommodate to a healthy pregnancy. Normal pregnancy in the rat is accompanied by increased
      production of NO and its second messenger cGMP. There is a parallel increase in renal
      expression of constitutive nitric oxide synthase (NOS), the enzyme that generates NO from
      arginine. In the pregnant rat, an infusion of NG-nitro-L-arginine methyl ester (L-NAME), an
      exogenous inhibitor of NOS, has been shown to replicate some of the hemodynamic features of
      the syndrome of pre-eclampsia. In a recent animal study, L-arginine supplementation reversed
      the adverse effects of L-NAME on pregnancy by attenuating the high blood pressure and by
      significantly decreasing protein loss in the urine. To date, studies of the use of L-arginine
      supplementation to treat women with pre-eclampsia have been small or uncontrolled and have
      only assessed blood pressure as a primary outcome measure. We report a single center,
      randomized, placebo-controlled trial of L-arginine supplementation for the treatment of
      pre-eclampsia, in which precise physiological techniques have been utilized to assess kidney
      dysfunction in addition to blood pressure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVE: To assess the benefit of L-arginine, the precursor to nitric oxide (NO), to blood
      pressure and recovery of the glomerular lesion in pre-eclampsia.

      METHODS: 45 women with pre-eclampsia were randomized to receive either L-arginine or placebo
      until day 10 post-partum. Primary outcome measures including MAP, glomerular filtration rate
      and proteinuria were assessed on the third and tenth days postpartum by inulin clearance and
      albumin-to-creatinine (A/C) ratio. NO, cyclic guanosine 3'5' monophosphate (cGMP),
      endothelin-1 (ET) and asymmetric-dimethyl-arginine (ADMA) and arginine levels were assayed
      prior to delivery, on the third and tenth day postpartum. Healthy gravid women provided
      control values. Assuming a standard deviation of 10 mmHg, the study was powered to detect a
      10 mmHg difference in MAP (alpha 0.05, beta 0.20) between the study groups.

      RESULTS: No significant differences existed between the groups with pre-eclampsia prior to
      randomization. Compared to the gravid control group, women with pre-eclampsia did not reveal
      significantly depressed levels of serum arginine, but did reveal significantly increased
      serum levels of ET, cGMP and ADMA prior to delivery. Despite a significant increase in serum
      arginine levels due to treatment, no differences were found in the levels of NO, ET, cGMP or
      ADMA between the two groups with pre-eclampsia. Further, there were no significant
      differences in any of the primary outcome measures with both groups demonstrating equivalent
      improvements in both blood pressure and proteinuria.

      CONCLUSION: Blood pressure and kidney function improve markedly in pre-eclampsia by the tenth
      day postpartum. L-arginine supplementation does not hasten this recovery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2003</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Arterial Pressure</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glomerular Filtration Rate (inulin clearance)</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proteinuria (albumin to creatinine ratio)</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vasoactive hormone levels - Nitric Oxide, Endothelin, cGMP, ADMA</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neonatal Outcomes</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>45</enrollment>
  <condition>Pre-Eclampsia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>L-Arginine Supplementation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Women selected for the study were diagnosed with pre-eclampsia in the second half of
        pregnancy.

        i.) an elevation of blood pressure to levels in excess of 140 systolic over 90 diastolic
        ii.) proteinuria determined by a urine dipstick value ≥ 2+, or quantitated at ≥ 0.5 g
        either per gram of creatinine or in a 24 hour urine collection.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with a history of underlying renal disease defined as a pre-pregnancy azotemia
             (serum creatinine ≥ 1.2 mg/dl) or proteinuria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bryan D Myers, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 10, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 11, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 14, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Bryan Myers</name_title>
    <organization>Stanford University</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pre-Eclampsia</keyword>
  <keyword>Glomerular Filtration Rate (GFR)</keyword>
  <keyword>Inulin clearance</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>L-Arginine</keyword>
  <keyword>Nitric Oxide</keyword>
  <keyword>cGMP</keyword>
  <keyword>Endothelin</keyword>
  <keyword>ADMA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Eclampsia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pre-Eclampsia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

