<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00279799</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00041131</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NIMH 5 R01 MH070537-08</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00279799</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HIV Prevention for African American Teens</brief_title>
  <official_title>HIV Prevention Maintenance for African American Teens</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      AFIYA aims to reduce both the risk of Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs) and HIV in young
      African American females through a culturally and gender appropriate intervention (group
      sessions) coupled with an individualized HIV Telephone Maintenance Intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      African-American adolescent females are a population at high risk for HIV infection. Recent
      findings suggest that culturally and gender appropriate HIV educational programs can
      significantly reduce sexual risk behaviors among this vulnerable population over the short
      term. It is unclear as to whether these programs have long-term effects. Thus, the aim of
      this project is to develop and test a culturally and gender-appropriate sexual health
      education program designed to promote long-term maintenance of HIV preventive sexual
      behaviors over a long follow-up period.

      700 African-American female adolescents' between the ages of 14-20 will be enrolled in this
      trial. Adolescents will be recruited from youth currently seeking services at several family
      planning clinics in Atlanta, Georgia. Adolescents who are eligible and willing to participate
      in the project will complete an initial ACASI survey. The survey is designed to assess
      adolescents' sexual risk and preventive behaviors. Biological specimens are collected and
      tested for common STI's. Free DOT (Directly Observed Therapy) is provided through the
      clinics. Urine pregnancy screens will also be conducted. After they complete the assessment,
      adolescents will receive a sexual health education program that was developed by the
      Principal Investigator. This program (HORIZONS) has been shown to be effective in reducing
      sexual risk behaviors over the short-term. Trained African American female health educators
      will deliver the sexual health education program. Adolescents will then be assigned, by
      chance alone, to one of two groups: one group will get periodic telephone contacts designed
      to reinforce sexual health promotion and the other group will get periodic telephone contacts
      that promote healthy dietary practices. Thus, while all adolescents receive the same sexual
      health education program, half will get telephone calls emphasizing sexual health and half
      will get an equal number of telephone calls emphasizing nutritional health.

      The primary aims of the proposed project are:

      Primary Aim 1. To determine whether adding a telephone educational component to a sexual
      health education program will reduce incident STD infection over a 36-month follow-up.

      Primary Aim 2. To determine if adding a telephone educational component to a sexual health
      education program can maintain HIV-preventive behaviors.

      We will ask adolescents to come back to participating clinics to complete follow-up
      assessments at 6 months, 12-months,18-months, 24-months, 30-months and 36-months after
      completing the initial assessment. We will test the effects of adding the telephone sexual
      health educational program to maintain or enhance adolescents' use of HIV prevention
      behaviors and reduce incident STDs. If successful, the findings could have important
      implications for HIV prevention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incident STD infection, particularly chlamydial infections, confirmed by laboratory PRC testing over a 36 month follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months post-randomization.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of condom-protected vaginal sex acts and sex while high or drunk over the 36 month follow-up.</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months post-randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">701</enrollment>
  <condition>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Afiya group intervention + HIV prevention phone sessions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Afiya group-based intervention plus individually tailored HIV prevention phone sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Afiya group session + nutrition phone sessions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Afiya group-based intervention plus individually tailored nutrition phone sessions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Afiya HIV Prevention Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Group-based session plus individually tailored HIV prevention phone sessions</description>
    <arm_group_label>Afiya group intervention + HIV prevention phone sessions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Afiya HIV prevention intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Afiya group-based intervention + nutrition phone sessions (attention control)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Afiya group session + nutrition phone sessions</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female; African American; age 14-20; receiving care at participating clinic;report
             having unprotected vaginal sex in last 6 months; ability to give written informed
             consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnant or trying to get pregnant; married; any condition that would preclude
             attending group-based intervention sessions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>20 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ralph J DiClemente, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fulton County Department of Health and Wellness</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grady Hospital Teen Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Planned Parenthood of GA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>DePadilla L, Windle M, Wingood G, Cooper H, DiClemente R. Condom use among young women: modeling the theory of gender and power. Health Psychol. 2011 May;30(3):310-9. doi: 10.1037/a0022871.</citation>
    <PMID>21553975</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sales JM, Latham TP, Diclemente RJ, Rose E. Differences between dual-method and non-dual-method protection use in a sample of young African American women residing in the Southeastern United States. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2010 Dec;164(12):1125-31. doi: 10.1001/archpediatrics.2010.230.</citation>
    <PMID>21135341</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sales JM, Lang DL, DiClemente RJ, Latham TP, Wingood GM, Hardin JW, Rose ES. The mediating role of partner communication frequency on condom use among African American adolescent females participating in an HIV prevention intervention. Health Psychol. 2012 Jan;31(1):63-9. doi: 10.1037/a0025073. Epub 2011 Aug 15.</citation>
    <PMID>21843001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sales JM, Brown JL, Diclemente RJ, Davis TL, Kottke MJ, Rose ES. Age differences in STDs, sexual behaviors, and correlates of risky sex among sexually experienced adolescent African-American females. J Pediatr Psychol. 2012 Jan-Feb;37(1):33-42. doi: 10.1093/jpepsy/jsr076. Epub 2011 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>21933811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diclemente RJ, Young AM, Painter JL, Wingood GM, Rose E, Sales JM. Prevalence and correlates of recent vaginal douching among African American adolescent females. J Pediatr Adolesc Gynecol. 2012 Feb;25(1):48-53. doi: 10.1016/j.jpag.2011.07.017. Epub 2011 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22051790</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown JL, Sales JM, Diclemente RJ, Latham Davis TP, Rose ES. Characteristics of African American adolescent females who perceive their current boyfriends have concurrent sexual partners. J Adolesc Health. 2012 Apr;50(4):377-82. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2011.07.008. Epub 2011 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>22443842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sales JM, DiClemente RJ, Brody GH, Philibert RA, Rose E. Interaction between 5-HTTLPR polymorphism and abuse history on adolescent African-American females' condom use behavior following participation in an HIV prevention intervention. Prev Sci. 2014 Jun;15(3):257-67. doi: 10.1007/s11121-013-0378-6.</citation>
    <PMID>23479192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 18, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 18, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 19, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ralph J. DiClemente</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sexually Transmitted Diseases, HIV, condom use, adolescents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

