<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02228681</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GOG-3007</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CRAD001CUS236T</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02228681</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Everolimus and Letrozole or Hormonal Therapy to Treat Endometrial Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Phase II Trial of Everolimus and Letrozole or Hormonal Therapy (Tamoxifen/Medroxyprogesterone Acetate) in Women With Advanced, Recurrent, or Persistent Endometria Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gynecologic Oncology Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gynecologic Oncology Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main purpose of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of the combination of the
      drugs Everolimus and Letrozole compared to Tamoxifen and Medroxyprogesterone acetate in
      treating endometrial cancer and to determine the types and severity of side effects caused by
      treatment with these drug combinations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 28, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 3 months from time from study entry to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the objective response rate of patients with advanced, persistent or recurrent endometrial cancer when treated with each of the arms of the trial.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to disease progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 3 months from time from study entry to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate the time to disease progression for each arm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 4 weeks up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the toxicities of each of the arms of the trial when used for patients with advanced/metastatic endometrial cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hormone receptor immunohistochemistry</measure>
    <time_frame>At study entry</time_frame>
    <description>To determine if relevant biomarkers correlate with response to treatment in each of the two arms. Unstained sections of tumor tissue will be used for hormone receptor (estrogen receptor-alpha, estrogen receptor-beta, progesterone receptor-A, progesterone receptor B and the G protein-coupled estrogen receptor, GPR-30) immunohistochemistry.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>mTOR pathway immunohistochemistry</measure>
    <time_frame>At study entry</time_frame>
    <description>To determine if relevant biomarkers correlate with response to treatment in each of the two arms. Unstained sections of tumor tissue will be used for mTOR pathway (including phosphorylated S6 ribosomal protein, PTEN, total and phosphorylated AKT, total and phosphorylated mTOR, and phospho-ERK1/2) immunohistochemistry</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mutation Analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>At study entry</time_frame>
    <description>To determine if relevant biomarkers correlate with response to treatment in each of the two arms. Unstained sections of tumor tissue and DNA extracted from whole blood will be used for mutational analysis (including PTEN, PIK3CA, KRAS, and CTNNB1 (beta-catenin) performed using a sequencing panel assay.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">74</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced, Persistent, or Recurrent Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus and Letrozole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Everolimus 10 mg daily and Letrozole 2.5 mg PO daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hormonal Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tamoxifen 20 mg PO BID; on alternating weeks (even numbered) weeks, Medroxyprogesterone Acetate 200 mg PO daily with Tamoxifen 20 mg PO BID</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Everolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>10mg daily by mouth</description>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus and Letrozole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RAD001</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tamoxifen</intervention_name>
    <description>20 mg daily by mouth on alternating weeks (even numbered) weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hormonal Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nolvadex®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Letrozole</intervention_name>
    <description>2.5mg twice a day by mouth</description>
    <arm_group_label>Everolimus and Letrozole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Femara®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medroxyprogesterone Acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>200 mg daily by mouth</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hormonal Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically confirmed advanced (FIGO Stage III or IV),
             persistent, or recurrent endometrial carcinoma, which is not likely to be curable by
             surgery or radiotherapy. Histologic documentation of the recurrence is not required.

          -  All patients must have measurable disease. Measurable disease is defined by RECIST
             version 1.1). Measurable disease is defined as at least one lesion that can be
             accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded). Each
             lesion must be greater than or equal to 10 mm when measured by CT, MRI or caliper
             measurement by clinical exam; or greater than or equal to 20 mm when measured by chest
             x-ray. Lymph nodes must be greater than or equal to 15 mm in short axis when measured
             by CT or MRI (See section 8).

          -  Patients must have at least one &quot;target lesion&quot; to be used to assess response on this
             protocol as defined by RECIST 1.1 (Section 8.1). Tumors within a previously irradiated
             field will be designated as &quot;non-target&quot; lesions unless progression is documented or a
             biopsy is obtained to confirm persistence at least 90 days following completion of
             radiation therapy.

          -  Prior chemoradiotherapy for a pelvic recurrence is permitted. Prior chemotherapy in
             the adjuvant setting for Stage I, II or III disease is permitted.

        Note: No prior chemotherapy in the setting of Stage IV disease is permitted unless the
        patient was without evidence of disease at the completion of chemotherapy and had at least
        six months of progression-free survival since the completion of chemotherapy.

        Regardless of circumstances, no more than one prior chemotherapy regimen (including
        chemo-radiotherapy) is permitted.

          -  Patient must be able to take p.o. medications.

          -  Performance status must be 0-1.

          -  Patients must have adequate organ and marrow function as defined below:

        NOTE: Institutional/laboratory upper limit of normal = ULN Institutional/laboratory lower
        limit of normal = LLN

          -  Bone marrow function:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than or equal to 1,500/mcl

               -  Platelets greater than or equal to 100,000 cells/mcl

               -  Hemoglobin greater than or equal to 9 g/dL

          -  Coagulation

             • INR less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN (or in range INR, usually between 2 and 3, if a
             patient is on a stable dose of therapeutic warfarin).

          -  Renal function:

             • Creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN

          -  Hepatic function:

               -  Bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN

               -  ALT and AST less than or equal to 3 x ULN

               -  Alkaline phosphatase less than or equal to 2.5 x ULN

               -  Albumin greater than or equal to 2.8 g/dL

          -  Lipid panel:

               -  Fasting serum cholesterol less than or equal to 300 mg/dL

               -  Fasting triglycerides less than or equal to 300 mg/

          -  At least 4 weeks must have elapsed since the patient underwent any major surgery
             (e.g., major: hysterectomy, resection of a lung nodule; minor: central venous access
             catheter placement).

          -  At least 4 weeks must have elapsed since the patient received any radiation therapy.

          -  Patients who have met the pre-entry requirements specified in Section 7.0

          -  Patients must have signed an approved informed consent and authorization permitting
             release of personal health information.

          -  All patients must be at least 18 years of age

          -  Patients of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test prior to
             the study entry and be practicing a highly effective form of contraception.

        During the study treatment and for 8 weeks after stopping the treatment. Highly effective
        contraception methods include combination of any two of the following:

          -  Use of oral, injected or implanted hormonal methods of contraception or;

          -  Placement of an intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS);

          -  Barrier methods of contraception: condom or occlusive cap (diaphragm or cervical/vault
             caps) with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/ vaginal suppository;

          -  Total abstinence or;

          -  Male/female sterilization. Women are considered post-menopausal and not of
             child-bearing potential if they have had 12 months of natural (spontaneous) amenorrhea
             with an appropriate clinical profile (e.g. age appropriate, history of vasomotor
             symptoms) or have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy (with or without hysterectomy)
             or tubal ligation at least six weeks prior to randomization. In the case of
             oophorectomy alone, only when the reproductive status of the woman has been confirmed
             by follow up hormone level assessment is she considered not of child-bearing
             potential.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have previously received everolimus, any another mTOR inhibitor or any
             agent targeting the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway.

          -  Known intolerance or hypersensitivity to Everolimus or other rapamycin analogs (e.g.
             sirolimus, temsirolimus)

          -  Patients who have previously received hormonal therapy for endometrial cancer.

          -  Patients with concomitant invasive malignancy or a history of other invasive
             malignancies, with the exception of non-melanoma skin cancer, are excluded if there is
             any evidence of other malignancy being present within the past five years. Patients
             are also excluded if their previous cancer treatment contraindicates this protocol.

          -  Patients receiving chronic treatment with systemic steroids or another
             immunosuppressive agent.

          -  Patients with active or uncontrolled systemic infection.

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus as defined by HbA1c &gt;8% despite adequate therapy.
             Patients with a known history of impaired fasting glucose or diabetes mellitus (DM)
             may be included, however blood glucose and anti-diabetic treatment must be monitored
             closely throughout the trial and adjusted as necessary.

          -  Known severely impaired lung function, including:

             • CTCAE grade 2 (or greater) hypoxia (decreased oxygen saturation with exercise [e.g.,
             pulse oximeter &lt;88%]; intermittent supplemental oxygen)

          -  Patients with a known history of cardiac disease. This includes:

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension, defined as systolic greater than 150 mm Hg or diastolic
             greater than 90 mm Hg despite antihypertensive medications.

          -  Myocardial infarction or unstable angina within 6 months prior to registration.

          -  New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class II or greater congestive heart failure.

          -  History of serious ventricular arrhythmia (i.e., ventricular tachycardia or
             ventricular fibrillation) or serious cardiac arrhythmia requiring medication. This
             does not include asymptomatic atrial fibrillation with controlled ventricular rate.

          -  Cerebrovascular accident (CVA, stroke), transient ischemic attack (TIA) within 6
             months prior to the first date of study therapy.

          -  Patients who are pregnant or breast-feeding.

          -  Patients with known central nervous system metastases.

          -  Patients with known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection.

          -  Patients with an impairment of gastrointestinal function or gastrointestinal disease
             that may significantly alter the absorption of everolimus (e.g., ulcerative disease;
             uncontrolled nausea, vomiting and/or diarrhea; malabsorption syndrome; clinical signs
             and symptoms of gastrointestinal obstruction; and/or patients who require parenteral
             hydration and/or nutrition).

          -  Patients who plan to receive live attenuated vaccines within 1 week of start of
             everolimus and during the study. Patient should also avoid close contact with others
             who have received live attenuated vaccines. Examples of live attenuated vaccines
             include intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral polio, BCG, yellow fever,
             varicella and TY21a typhoid vaccines.

          -  Patients with active bleeding or pathologic conditions that carry high risk of
             bleeding, such as known bleeding disorder or coagulopathy.

          -  Patients who are currently part of or have participated in any clinical investigation
             with an investigational drug within 30 days prior to dosing.

          -  Patients must be able to follow concomitant medication restrictions:

               -  Avoid the use of strong CYP3A/PgP inhibitors (e.g., ketoconazole, itraconazole,
                  clarithromycin, atazanavir, nefazodone, saquinavir, telithromycin, ritonavir,
                  indinavir, nelfinavir, voriconazole).

               -  Use caution when co-administered with moderate CYP3A4/PgP inhibitors (e.g.,
                  amprenavir, fosamprenavir, aprepitant, erythromycin, fluconazole, verapamil,
                  diltiazem).

               -  Grapefruit, grapefruit juice, and other foods known to inhibit cytochrome P450
                  and PgP activity may increase everolimus exposures and should be avoided during
                  treatment.

               -  Avoid the use of concomitant strong CYP3A4/PgP inducers (e.g., phenytoin,
                  carbamazepine, rifampin, rifabutin, rifapentine, and phenobarbital).

               -  St. John's Wort may decrease everolimus exposure unpredictably and should be
                  avoided.

          -  Patients with active hepatitis B or C. Screening for hepatitis B

        Prior to randomization/start of everolimus, the following three categories of patients
        should be tested for hepatitis B viral load and serologic markers, that is, HBsAg, HBcAb,
        HBsAb and quantitative hepatitis B DNA PCR (HBV-DNA):

        • All patients who currently live in (or have lived in) Asia, Africa, Central and South
        America, Eastern Europe, Spain, Portugal and Greece.

        [http://wwwnc.cdc.gov/travel/yellowbook/2012/chapter-3-infectious-diseases-related-to-trave
        l/hepatitis-b.htm]

          -  Patients with any of the following risk factors:

          -  known or suspected past hepatitis B infection,

          -  blood transfusion(s) prior to 1990,

          -  current or prior IV drug users,

          -  current or prior dialysis,

          -  household contact with hepatitis B infected patient(s),

          -  current or prior high-risk sexual activity,

          -  body piercing or tattoos,

          -  mother known to have hepatitis B

          -  history suggestive of hepatitis B infection, e.g., dark urine, jaundice, right upper
             quadrant pain.

          -  Additional patients at the discretion of the investigator The management guidelines,
             in Section 6, are provided according to the results of the baseline assessment of
             viral load and serological markers for hepatitis B.

        Screening for hepatitis C

        Patients with any of the following risk factors for hepatitis C should be tested using
        quantitative RNA-PCR:

          -  known or suspected past hepatitis C infection (including patients with past interferon
             'curative' treatment),

          -  blood transfusions prior to 1990,

          -  current or prior IV drug users,

          -  current or prior dialysis,

          -  household contact of hepatitis C infected patient(s),

          -  current or prior high-risk sexual activity,

          -  body piercing or tattoos. At the discretion of the investigator, additional patients
             may also be tested for hepatitis C.

        The management guidelines, in Section 6 are provided according to the results of the
        baseline assessment of hepatitis C viral load.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Slomovitz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Gynecologic Oncology Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado - Anschutz Cancer Pavilion</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami - Sylvester Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John B. Amos Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>31904</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Health University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Savannah</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>31404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maine Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scarborough</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>04074</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Massachusetts Memorial Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sanford Clinic North - Bemidji</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bemidji</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>56601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Dominic-Jackson Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jackson</city>
        <state>Mississippi</state>
        <zip>39215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Mississippi Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jackson</city>
        <state>Mississippi</state>
        <zip>39216</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women's Cancer Center of Nevada</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Vegas</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89169</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New Mexico Cancer Alliance</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>87106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Medical Center-Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>87131</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women's Cancer Care Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albany</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>12208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SUNY Downstate Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sanford Roger Maris Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fargo</city>
        <state>North Dakota</state>
        <zip>58122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Case Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Oklahoma</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abington Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Abington</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19001-3788</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Magee Women's Hospital of UPMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women &amp; Infants Hospital of Rhode Island</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sanford Medical Center - Sioux Falls</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sioux Falls</city>
        <state>South Dakota</state>
        <zip>57104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Huntsman Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 14, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 29, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Letrozole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tamoxifen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Medroxyprogesterone Acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Medroxyprogesterone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

