<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02227589</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00053448</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01AA021719-01A1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01AA021735-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02227589</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment for Teens With Alcohol Abuse and Depression</brief_title>
  <acronym>T-TAAD</acronym>
  <official_title>Treatment for Teens With Alcohol Abuse and Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>UConn Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will recruit adolescents with alcohol or cannabis abuse and clinically
      significant depression. All participants will receive 12 sessions of an evidence-based
      treatment for alcohol abuse, Motivation Enhancement Therapy/Cognitive Behavior Therapy-12,
      over 12 to 14 weeks. Those who are still depressed after 4 weeks will be randomized to
      receive treatment augmentation with either an integrated cognitive behavior therapy for
      depression, delivered by their study therapist, or depression treatment-as-usual in the
      community. The study hypothesis is that integrated depression treatment will surpass
      community treatment-as-usual in efficacy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Alcohol and other substance use disorders (AOSUDs), primarily cannabis use disorders,
      continue to be a significant public health concern among American adolescents. AOSUDs are
      commonly accompanied by co-occurring psychiatric disorders including depression. This
      comorbidity has been associated with increased severity of AOSUD, earlier treatment
      termination, poorer outcomes, and increased suicidal risk. Presently there is neither a
      consensus nor a standard, evidence-based intervention to address the need for an effective
      and feasible treatment for both disorders. However, cognitive behavior therapy (CBT) has been
      found to be effective for each of these disorders, separately. In addition, in some, but not
      all, adolescents with both disorders, depression appears to respond rapidly to CBT that
      targets only alcohol or substance abuse. This suggests that early depression responders
      (EDRs) may not need additional treatment that targets depression directly, unlike their
      non-early responding (NEDR) counterparts. However, no studies have compared longer term
      outcomes of adolescent EDRs to NEDRs. Moreover, no randomized, controlled studies have tested
      the hypothesis that an integrated CBT intervention for co-occurring AOSUD and depression will
      be effective for both disorders, in NEDR adolescents.

      In this two-site study, submitted in response to PA: PAS-10-251, we will recruit 170 eligible
      adolescents (102 at the University of Connecticut and 68 at Duke University), ages 13 years
      to 21 years-11 months, with alcohol or cannabis use disorders and clinically significant
      depression. All subjects will receive 12 sessions of Motivation Enhancement Therapy/Cognitive
      Behavior Therapy (MET/CBT-12), a standard, evidence-based intervention for alcohol or drug
      abuse over 12 to 14 weeks. After four weeks, NEDR adolescents will be randomized to
      depression treatment augmentation, either with seven sessions of CBT (CBT-D), integrated with
      MET/CBT-12, or with enhanced depression-treatment-as-usual in the community (D-ETAU). We
      estimate that 120 adolescents will be randomized; we will stratify randomization on gender,
      age, and presence/absence of a Major Depressive Episode. We will assess all 170 participants
      at baseline, weeks 4, 9, and 14 (after treatment), and at 3-, 6-, and 9-month follow-up.

      The first aim of this study is to describe the percentage of depressed AOSUD adolescents who
      demonstrate EDR during alcohol or cannabis abuse treatment alone, examine EDR durability and
      EDR predictors. The second and third aims test the hypotheses that, for NEDR teens, an
      integrated treatment augmentation (CBT-D) will lead to better depression and alcohol or
      cannabis outcomes, respectively, than augmentation with D-ETAU. We will compare outcomes of
      all three groups (EDRs; and NEDRs in each augmentation), on alcohol use, depressive symptoms,
      alcohol- or cannabis-related functional impairment, maintenance of alcohol or cannabis
      treatment gains, and depression remission rates over time, and will analyze the temporal
      ordering of changes in alcohol or cannabis use and depression during and after treatment.
      This is the first study to test an adaptive treatment model with depressed alcohol or
      cannabis use disorder youths, and thus has significant potential to guide clinical practice.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Duke site has masked outcomes assessor; University of Connecticut site does not have masked outcomes assessor</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol use frequency assessed with the Alcohol Consumption Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to week 14; change from baseline to 9 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>At every assessment point (baseline, weeks 4, 9, and 14 [end of treatment]; and then 3, 6, and 9 months after treatment ends, adolescents will be interviewed by an independent evaluator using the Alcohol Consumption Questionnaire regarding alcohol use frequency over the past three months (baseline, and months 3, 6, and 9) or past month (weeks 4, 9, and 14).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of depression, as measured on the Children's Depression Rating Scale-Revised (CDRS-R)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to week 4; Change from baseline to week 14; Change from baseline to 9 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>At every assessment point (baseline, weeks 4, 9, and 14 [end of treatment] and then 3, 6, and 9 months after treatment ends, adolescents and parents will be interviewed by an independent evaluator using the CDRS-R, with reference to the adolescent's depression symptoms during the past week. The week 4 assessment determines whether the adolescent is an early responder on depression, defined as having a 50% reduction in CDRS-R score. One item assesses suicidal thinking or behavior.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol use quantity assessed with the Alcohol Consumption Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to week 14; Change from baseline to 9 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>At every assessment point (baseline, weeks 4, 9, and 14 [end of treatment]; and then 3, 6, and 9 months after treatment ends, adolescents will be interviewed by an independent evaluator regarding alcohol use quantity over the past three months (baseline; months 3, 6, and 9) or past month (weeks 4, 9, and 14), using the Alcohol Consumption Questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cannabis use frequency assessed with the Drug Checklist</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to week 14; Change from baseline to 9 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>At every assessment point (baseline, weeks 4, 9, and 14 [end of treatment]; and then 3, 6, and 9 months after treatment ends, adolescents will be interviewed by an independent evaluator regarding cannabis use frequency over the past three months (baseline; months 3, 6, and 9) or past month (weeks 4, 9, and 14), using the Drug Checklist.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 14; baseline to 9 Months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>At baseline, week 14 (end of treatment), and 9 months after treatment, the adolescent will complete the Voice DISC diagnostic interview to determine whether he or she continues to meet criteria for an alcohol or cannabis use disorder</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Teen-Addiction Severity Index (T-ASI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 14; baseline to 9 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>The Independent Evaluator will complete the T-ASI with the adolescent and parent at every assessment point (baseline, week 4, week 9, week 14, and then 3, 6, and 9 months after treatment ends) to determine whether there are changes in substance-use-related functional problems</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Suicidal Ideation Questionnaire-Jr. High Version (SIQ-Jr)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 14; baseline to 9 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>Adolescents will complete this self-report form at every assessment point (baseline, week 4, week, 9, week 14; and then 3, 6, and 9 months after treatment ends) to determine if there are significant reductions in suicidal ideation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Children's Global Assessment of Functioning (CGAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 14; baseline to 9 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>The Independent Evaluator will make this single item rating of global functioning at every assessment point (baseline, week 4, week 9, week 14, and then 3, 6, and 9 months after treatment ends) to determine if there are significant improvements in adolescent's overall functioning</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression-Improvement in Depression (CGI-I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 14; baseline to 9 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>At every assessment point except baseline (at week 4, week 9, week 14, and then at 3, 6, and 9 months after treatment ends), the independent evaluator will rate the adolescent's improvement since baseline in the domain of depression, using CDRS-R scores as the reference. The CGI-I score determines whether the adolescent is a partial or full responder, or a non-responder to treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 14; baseline to 9 months after treatment ends</time_frame>
    <description>Adolescents will complete this self-report measure of depression severity at all assessment points (baseline, week 4, week 9, week 14; and then 3, 6, and 9 months after treatment ends) to determine if there has been a significant reduction in severity of depressive symptoms. One item assesses suicidal ideation or intent.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Situational Confidence Questionnaire (SCQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 14</time_frame>
    <description>At baseline, week 4, and week 14, the adolescent will self-report perceived self-efficacy to manage potentially stressful situations involving alcohol or cannabis, to determine if this confidence increases during treatment</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Urine analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline through month 9 of follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>At every assessment point (baseline, week 4, week 9, week 14, and then 3, 6, and 9 months after treatment ends), and 8 additional times during treatment, adolescents will complete a 6-panel iCUP Drug Screen Test to check for non-alcohol substance use.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">170</enrollment>
  <condition>AOD Use, Abuse, and Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MET/CBT-12 plus CBT-D</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CBT-D is an integrated cognitive behavior therapy targeting depression, delivered by the same study therapist who delivers MET/CBT-12 to the adolescent. All adolescents receiving CBT-D remain in MET/CBT-12 with their study provider.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MET/CBT-12 plus D-TAU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>D-TAU (Depression Treatment as Usual) consists of referral to a depression treatment provider in the community. In this study D-TAU will be enhanced by assistance from the study team in locating providers and, with consent, an assessment report about the adolescent from the study team to the provider. All adolescents receiving TAU for depression remain in MET/CBT-12 with their study provider.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MET/CBT-12 alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>MET/CBT-12 consists of two sessions of motivation enhancement therapy and 10 sessions of cognitive behavior therapy, targeting alcohol or cannabis abuse. All adolescents in the study receive MET/CBT-12 over 12 to 14 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MET/CBT-12</intervention_name>
    <description>Two sessions of motivation enhancement therapy followed by 10 sessions of cognitive behavior therapy targeting alcohol or cannabis abuse. These 12 sessions will be delivered over 12 to 14 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MET/CBT-12 plus CBT-D</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MET/CBT-12 plus D-TAU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MET/CBT-12 alone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CBT-D</intervention_name>
    <description>CBT-D consists of seven weekly sessions of cognitive behavior therapy targeting depression.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MET/CBT-12 plus CBT-D</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>D-TAU</intervention_name>
    <description>D-TAU is treatment as usual in the community, targeting depression. It may consist of medication and/or behavioral intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MET/CBT-12 plus D-TAU</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 13 years to 21 years, 11 months at baseline

          -  Current alcohol or cannabis abuse or dependence diagnosis (DSM-IV) OR current level of
             potentially harmful drinking or cannabis use as evidenced by (1) consumption of 4 or
             more drinks per drinking day (males) or three or more (females), or use of cannabis at
             least three times in past 90 days (or before admission into a controlled environment)

          -  Current clinically significant depression, defined as a score of 40 or more on the
             Children's Depression Rating Scale-Revised at baseline

          -  If currently taking anti-depressant medication, on a stable dose for at least one
             month

          -  Willingness to accept treatment

          -  Able to speak and read English (5th-grade level)

          -  Residence within 45-minute drive from treatment site

          -  Adolescent and a parent agree to sign Institutional Review Board approved
             consent/assent form; for subjects ages 18-19, parent involvement is optional and is
             the decision of the youth

          -  Parent/guardian agrees to provide collateral information and to designate two third
             parties who could be contacted in case the subject is lost to follow-up; for subjects
             ages 18-19, the participating youth will provide this information

          -  Participant (and parent, if youth is under age 18) not planning to move outside the
             area in the next 9 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Suicidal ideation with a plan, or suicide attempt within 30 days. In addition to such
             suicide risk being indicated in baseline interview material, a score exceeding the
             89th percentile on the Suicide Ideation Questionnaire (SIQ-Jr), will necessitate an
             immediate risk assessment by the Independent Evaluator which may lead to exclusion
             under this criterion.

          -  Homicidal ideation with a plan or any plan to hurt others

          -  Lifetime diagnosis of psychosis, schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, intellectual
             disability or autistic disorder

          -  Current dependence on a substance other than alcohol, marijuana or nicotine

          -  Current non-alcohol or cannabis use disorder or depression primary diagnosis, i.e.,
             the diagnosis requires care more urgently than does alcohol or cannabis use disorder
             or depression
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>263 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John F Curry, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yifrah Kaminer, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UConn Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John F Curry, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>919-681-0020</phone>
    <email>john.curry@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Allison Meyer, BA</last_name>
    <phone>919-668-0065</phone>
    <email>allison.e.meyer@duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Connecticut Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Farmington</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06030-3926</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yifrah Kaminer, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>860-679-4344</phone>
      <email>kaminer@uchc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rebecca Burke, M.S.</last_name>
      <phone>860-679-8478</phone>
      <email>burke@uchc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yifrah Kaminer, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke Child and Family Study Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John F Curry, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>919-681-0020</phone>
      <email>john.curry@duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Allison Meyer, BA</last_name>
      <phone>919-668-0065</phone>
      <email>allison.e.meyer@duke.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John F Curry, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 26, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 26, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 28, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>adolescent,</keyword>
  <keyword>alcohol abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>depression,</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive behavior therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>cannabis abuse</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

