<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02229136</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13026</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CRAD001JUS240T</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02229136</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Miracle Mouthwash Plus Hydrocortisone vs Prednisolone Mouth Rinse for Mouth Sores Caused by Everolimus</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Miracle Mouthwash (MMW) Plus Hydrocortisone and Prednisolone Mouth Rinse as Prophylaxis for Everolimus-Associated Stomatitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>US Oncology Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>US Oncology Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized Phase 2 study to evaluate two different steroid-based mouth rinses
      (Miracle Mouth Wash plus hydrocortisone versus prednisolone oral rinse) for the prevention or
      treatment of everolimus-associated stomatitis (mouth sores) in postmenopausal patients
      undergoing treatment with an aromatase inhibitor plus everolimus. An exploratory analysis
      will also evaluate patient response to next anti-cancer therapy of physician's choice
      following discontinuation of therapy with an aromatase inhibitor plus everolimus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Stomatitis, or inflammation of the mucous membranes lining the mouth and throat, is a common
      side affect associated with chemotherapy and radiation therapy. In addition, stomatitis has
      been reported in approximately 44% - 64% of patients treated with everolimus (Afinitor PI).
      However, mTOR (mammalian target of rapamycin) inhibitor-induced stomatitis (mIAS) is a
      different clinical entity, manifesting more frequently as discrete aphthous-like lesions
      rather than diffuse inflammation. Oral lesions are typically well demarcated, single or
      multiple ovoid-shaped ulcerations, with a grayish-white pseudomembrane.

      In the BOLERO-2 trial, 56% of patients with MBC (metastatic breast cancer) treated with
      exemestane plus everolimus developed stomatitis, with 37% developing grade 2/3 stomatitis.
      These rates are consistent with the rates reported with everolimus therapy in patients with
      other types of cancers (Afinitor PI). Although this adverse event is reversible,
      approximately one-fourth of the patients treated with everolimus in the BOLERO-2 trial
      required dose interruptions or dose reductions, and this may impact the benefit from therapy.
      Despite the frequency of stomatitis associated with mTOR inhibitor therapy, strategies to
      prevent and/or ameliorate this painful side effect are not well defined or documented. Expert
      guidelines on the management of mIAS have been developed, but these guidelines are based on
      retrospective observational and/or anecdotal evidence, and prospective data on the efficacy
      of mIAS prevention and management strategies are needed.

      There is some evidence to suggest steroid therapy may be helpful in the management of mIAS.
      Steroid-containing ointments or mouth rises have also been shown to alleviate symptoms in
      patients with non-chemotherapy associated apthous oral ulcers. Reports on the effectiveness
      of non-steroid mouthwash formulations have been mixed, but agents that induce a topical
      anesthetic effect, may help to reduce discomfort and pain.

      Thus, the present study has been designed to investigate the effectiveness of two oral rinses
      (miracle mouth wash [MMW] plus hydrocortisone, vs prednisolone) to prevent or reduce the
      severity of stomatitis in patients with MBC undergoing treatment with an aromatase inhibitor
      plus everolimus (AIE).

      In addition, because very little is known about the impact of everolimus therapy on response
      to later lines of treatment for MBC, and preclinical data suggest mTOR inhibition may
      resensitize cells to endocrine therapy, this study will also assess tumor response to next
      anti-cancer therapy of physician's choice, including duration of response and sites of
      progression.

      All patients will receive everolimus 10 mg PO QD (by mouth, every day) plus standard dose AI
      (physician choice of Letrozole, Exemestane, or Anastrozole).

      Patients will be randomized 1:1 to 12 weeks of treatment with either:

        -  Arm 1: MMW plus hydrocortisone

        -  Arm 2: Prednisolone oral solution (15mg/5ml)

      Treatment with the oral rinse will start on Day 1 of everolimus therapy, and will be
      self-administered. Patients will be instructed to swish and expectorate (cough or spit out)
      10ml of the assigned mouth rinse 4 times per day. Patients may also gargle 4 times per day
      with the assigned rinse for any symptoms of pharyngitis. Patients will also be instructed to
      fill out the Oral Stomatitis Daily Questionnaire (OSDQ) at home every day.

      The incidence of stomatitis, as well as other adverse events, dose reductions/interruptions,
      and everolimus discontinuation due to toxicity, will be monitored for the first 12 weeks of
      treatment. After the end of the initial 12 week randomized portion of the study, patients
      will continue to be followed every 2 months (for up to 1 year following discontinuation of
      everolimus for progression or intolerable toxicity or progression on subsequent anti-cancer
      therapy, whichever occurs first) to determine when AIE treatment is discontinued and reason
      for discontinuation (toxicity, progression), sites of disease progression, response to next
      anti-cancer therapy of physician's choice (by physician assessment) and duration of response,
      and sites of disease progression to next anti-cancer therapy following progression on AIE.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 4, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Grade ≥ 2 stomatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective of the study is to determine the incidence of Grade ≥ 2 stomatitis in patients undergoing treatment with an aromatase inhibitor plus everolimus (AIE) when treated with either Miracle Mouthwash (MMW) plus hydrocortisone or with a prednisolone mouth rinse during the first 12 weeks of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of all side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>64 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Determination of the incidence of adverse events (all grades)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients requiring dose interruptions and/or dose reductions of everolimus</measure>
    <time_frame>64 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Determination of the percentage of patients requiring dose interruptions and/or dose reductions of everolimus, as well as the percentage of patients discontinuing therapy with everolimus due to toxicity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in pain score on questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the impact of MMW plus hydrocortisone or a prednisolone mouth rinse on the duration and severity of stomatitis, as assessed by the Oral Stomatitis Daily Questionnaire (OSDQ).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Disease Progression of next anti-cancer therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>64 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>An exploratory objective is to assess patient response to the next anti-cancer therapy of physician's choice following progression on AIE, including duration of response and sites of progression.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">104</enrollment>
  <condition>Stomatitis</condition>
  <condition>Oral Mucositis</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasm of the Breast</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Tumor of Breast</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Miracle Mouthwash plus Hydrocortisone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Miracle Mouthwash plus Hydrocortisone, swish and expectorate 10cc (10 mLs) 4 times per day, every day for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prednisolone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prednisolone oral solution 15 mg/5 ml; swish and expectorate 10cc (10 mL) 4 times per day, every day for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Miracle Mouthwash Plus Hydrocortisone</intervention_name>
    <description>Miracle Mouthwash Plus Hydrocortisone (16 oz recipe/480 ml)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Miracle Mouthwash plus Hydrocortisone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prednisolone</intervention_name>
    <description>Prednisolone oral solution 15 mg/5 ml</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prednisolone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Millipred</other_name>
    <other_name>Omnipred</other_name>
    <other_name>Orapred</other_name>
    <other_name>Econopred</other_name>
    <other_name>Flo-Pred</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 years;

          2. ECOG (Eastern Cooperative Group) Performance status ≤ 2;

          3. Histologic or cytologic confirmation of stage IV hormone receptor-positive breast
             cancer;

          4. Postmenopausal status, defined either by:

               1. Age ≥ 55 years and ≥ 1 year of amenorrhea

               2. Age &lt; 55 years and ≥ 1 year of amenorrhea, with an estradiol assay &lt;20pg/ml

               3. Surgical menopause with bilateral oophorectomy Note: Ovarian radiation or
                  treatment with a luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone (LHRH) agonist (goserelin
                  acetate or leuprolide acetate) is not permitted for induction of ovarian
                  suppression;

          5. Planned treatment with an aromatase inhibitor (letrozole, exemestane, or anastrozole)
             plus everolimus; Note: Prior treatment with an aromatase inhibitor, either for
             early-stage or metastatic breast cancer, is allowed.

          6. Adequate bone marrow function as shown by: ANC (absolute neutrophil count) ≥1.5 x
             109/L, Platelets ≥100 x 109/L, Hb &gt;9 g/dL;

          7. Adequate liver function as shown by:

               1. Total serum bilirubin ≤2.0 mg/dL,

               2. ALT (Alanine aminotransferase) and AST (Aspartate aminotransferase) ≤2.5x ULN
                  (upper limit of normal) (≤5x ULN in patients with liver metastases),

               3. INR (International Normalized Ratio) ≤2;

          8. Adequate renal function: serum creatinine ≤1.5x ULN;

          9. Fasting serum cholesterol ≤300 mg/dL OR ≤7.75 mmol/L AND fasting triglycerides ≤2.5x
             ULN.

             Note: In case one or both of these thresholds are exceeded, the patient can only be
             included after initiation of appropriate lipid lowering medication;

         10. Willingness to complete a daily stomatitis symptom questionnaire;

         11. Signed informed consent obtained prior to any screening procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known intolerance or hypersensitivity to everolimus or other rapamycin analogs (e.g.
             sirolimus, temsirolimus);

          2. Known impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of oral everolimus;

          3. Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus as defined by HbA1c (hemoglobin A1c) &gt;8% despite
             adequate therapy. Patients with a known history of impaired fasting glucose or
             diabetes mellitus (DM) may be included, however blood glucose and antidiabetic
             treatment must be monitored closely throughout the trial and adjusted as necessary;

          4. Patient has any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions such as:

               1. unstable angina pectoris, symptomatic congestive heart failure, myocardial
                  infarction ≤6 months prior to start of Everolimus, serious uncontrolled cardiac
                  arrhythmia, or any other clinically significant cardiac disease

               2. Symptomatic congestive heart failure of New York Heart Association Class III or
                  IV

               3. active (acute or chronic) or uncontrolled severe infection, liver disease such as
                  cirrhosis, decompensated liver disease, and chronic hepatitis (i.e. quantifiable
                  HBV-DNA (Hepatitis B Virus DNA) and/or positive HbsAg, quantifiable HCV-RNA
                  [Hepatitis C Virus RNA]),

               4. known severely impaired lung function (spirometry and DLCO [Diffusing capacity of
                  the Lung for Carbon Monoxide] 50% or less of normal and O2 saturation 88% or less
                  at rest on room air),

               5. active, bleeding diathesis;

          5. Patient requires chronic treatment with corticosteroids (including inhaled
             corticosteroids) or other immunosuppressive agents. Topical corticosteroids are
             allowed;

          6. Known history of HIV seropositivity;

          7. Patient received live attenuated vaccines within 1 week of start of everolimus and
             during the study. Patient should also avoid close contact with others who have
             received live attenuated vaccines. Examples of live attenuated vaccines include
             intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral polio, BCG (Bacillus
             Calmette-Guérin), yellow fever, varicella and TY21a typhoid vaccines;

          8. Patient has a history of another primary malignancy, with the exceptions of:
             non-melanoma skin cancer, and carcinoma in situ of the cervix, uteri, or breast from
             which the patient has been disease free for ≥3 years;

          9. Patient has a history of non-compliance to medical regimens or who are considered
             potentially unreliable or will not be able to complete the entire study;

         10. Patient is currently part of or has participated in any clinical investigation with an
             investigational drug within 1 month prior to dosing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vicky E. Jones, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>US Oncology Research, McKesson Specialty Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>12 sites incl Yakima, WA, Boulder, CO, and Austin, TX</name>
      <address>
        <city>US</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 26, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 29, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mouth sores from chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>mouth sores</keyword>
  <keyword>hormone receptor-positive metastatic breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic breast cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mucositis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone 17-butyrate 21-propionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cortisol succinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydrocortisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

