<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02005432</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRALA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02005432</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PASCAL Laser Versus ETDRS Laser Associated With Intravitreal Ranibizumab (IVR) Versus Only IVR for Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Three Arm, Prospective, Single-blind, Randomized Study Comparing Ranibizumab Plus Green Diode Laser Versus Ranibizumab Plus Pattern Scan Laser (Pascal) Versus Ranibizumab (Monotherapy) for Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objectives:

      Primary objective:

      To evaluate the effects on retinal morphophysiology of full scatter single target panretinal
      photocoagulation (PRP) versus full scatter multiple target panretinal photocoagulation (both
      combined with intravitreous injections of ranibizumab) versus intravitreous ranibizumab (IVR)
      alone in patients with proliferative diabetic retinopathy (PDR).

      Primary outcome:

      The primary endpoint for this study is the mean change in the total area of active retinal
      neovessels, as measured by fluorescein angiography leakage area, in mm2, from baseline to
      week 48.

      Secondary objectives:

        -  To assess the mean changes in best corrected visual acuity (BCVA), the mean changes in
           central subfield foveal thickness (CSFT), the mean changes in wave B amplitude and
           oscillatory potentials on a full-field electroretinogram (ERG), and the mean changes on
           the peripheral visual field by static perimetry (30:2 strategy), from baseline to week
           48.

        -  To assess the incidence of adverse events during the study.

      Strategic goal:

      In the era of anti-VEGF treatment for retinal neovascularization 1, 2, 3, 4 , it is time to
      determine what would be the best association of PRP + anti-VEGF for proliferative diabetic
      retinopathy (PDR), or still, if just intravitreal anti-VEGF treatment would be even better
      regarding morphologic (new vessels area and CSFT) and functional parameters (BCVA, ERG
      response and visual field).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Photocoagulation (thermal laser) was the first modality to be described for the treatment of
      PDR. Different types of laser such as xenon, krypton, argon, red diode and green diode can be
      used for this treatment. The Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study (ETDRS) showed the
      benefit of early treatment of PDR and of macular edema with laser photocoagulation.

      However, several studies have reported loss of visual field after laser photocoagulation of
      the bilateral full-scatter type (PRP) due to the expansion of the thermal injury, possibly
      even compromising the ability to drive automotive vehicles according to the standards of the
      transit authorities of some countries. Thus, this implies a greater impact on the quality of
      life of the patient, especially if he is a young diabetic.6

      The objective of new laser photocoagulation technologies is to provide a treatment that will
      permit the development of a regenerative response of photoreceptors and of the retinal
      pigment epithelium (RPE) with the minimum loss of photoreceptors and the minimum cicatricial
      expansion of the thermal injury on the targeted RPE.7

      The PASCAL photocoagulator (OptiMedica, Santa Clara, California) (a standard scanning laser)
      was introduced in 2005 for retinal photocoagulation. The device functions as if it partially
      automated the procedure by means of a shorter laser pulse (short pulse strategy) combined
      with multiple simultaneous firings in a pattern, performing the procedure within a shorter
      period of time and with less damage to the outer retina or the RPE, in addition to providing
      better patient comfort.8

      Regarding combined therapy, the combination of intravitreous injection of ranibizumab with
      PRP (ETDRS) proved to be more promising in terms of improved visual acuity, stability of
      macular thickness and a greater regression rate of neovessel areas than the use of PRP alone
      (ETDRS) in patients with high risk PDR.1

      Thus, in the present study we would like to determine which would be the best therapeutic
      combination of laser and an anti-VEGF drug for our patients, or whether treatment with an
      anti-VEGF drug alone would be better in terms of the anatomical and functional parameters
      proposed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fluorescein angiography leakage area</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to week 48.</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint for this study is the mean change in the total area of active retinal neovessels, as measured by fluorescein angiography leakage area, in mm2.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">31</enrollment>
  <condition>Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SS-PRP arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>panfotocoagulation (PRP) single shoot (ETDRS) + 0,05ml intravitreal injection anti-VEGF (ranibizumabe)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MS-PRP arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Multiple shoot panfotocoagulation (PASCAL) plus IVR</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IVR arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>only IVR (intravitreal Ranibizumabe)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intravitreal Ranibizumabe</intervention_name>
    <description>Intravitreal injection 0,05ml Ranibizumabe</description>
    <arm_group_label>SS-PRP arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MS-PRP arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>IVR arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>panfotocoagulation (PASCAL)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MS-PRP arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>panfotocoagulation (PRP) single shoot (ETDRS)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SS-PRP arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diabetic patients older than 18 years

          2. Presence of PDR (presence of retinal neovascularization, defined as active neovessels
             (fine retinal vessels with saccular dilatations or extremities covered with blood or
             associated with recurrent vitreous hemorrhage) with visual acuity better than 20/800
             and with no previous laser treatment

          3. Giving written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of advanced PDR, i.e.: vitreous hemorrhage that would prevent documentation
             of the eye fundus or adequate retinal photocoagulation, or presence of traction
             retinal detachment

          2. Presence of ring-shaped retinal neovascularization extending along both temporal
             arcades and the optic disc

          3. Any abnormality of the vitreoretinal interface in the macular region for which the
             investigator would consider vitrectomy via pars plana to be necessary

          4. Intravitreous injection of corticosteroids or of other antiangiogenic drugs 6 months
             before the evaluation for entry into the study

          5. Inability to fixate and to conclude the automated static perimetry exam

          6. Cataract surgery within the last three months

          7. Posterior vitrectomy with scleral introflexion at any time

          8. Acute ocular infection

          9. Allerghy to fluorescein

         10. Medical or psychological conditions that would prevent the patient from giving
             informed consent and concluding the study

         11. Significant uncontrolled diseases which, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             exclude the patient from the study

         12. Renal failure requiring dialysis or renal transplant or renal insufficiency with
             creatinine levels &gt;2.0 mg/dl

         13. Untreated diabetes mellitus

         14. Severe (blood pressure systolic &gt; 160 mmHg or diastolic &gt; 100 mmHg) AND untreated
             hypertension

         15. Inability to comply with study or follow-up procedures.

         16. Impaired or limited legal capacity

         17. Participation in another clinical study in the last 30 days.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Retina and Vitreous service of the University Hospital, Faculty of Medicine of Ribeirão Preto-USP (HCFMRP)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ribeirao Preto</city>
        <state>Sao Paulo</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 6, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 9, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 6, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 6, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 9, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rafael de Montier P. Barroso, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetis</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinal Neovascularization</keyword>
  <keyword>laser treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Retinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ranibizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

