<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02001168</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XinjiangMU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02001168</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Postoperative Adjuvant Chemotherapy With/Without Rh-endostatin on Non-small Cell Lung Cancer in PhaseⅠB</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Postoperative Adjuvant Chemotherapy With/Without Rh-endostatin: a Randomized, PhaseⅢ and Open Clinical Study of Non-small Cell Lung Cancer in PhaseⅠB</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xinjiang Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xinjiang Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      -  Lung cancer is one of causes of the malignant tumor-associated death on a global scale,
           in which the surgery is the only effective approach in patients with non-small cell lung
           cancer (NSCLC). As present, the total postoperative 5-year survival rate of NSCLC is
           40%, while only 4%～15% patients can benefit from adjuvant chemotherapy[1]. American
           National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) manual recommends that adjuvant
           chemotherapy can be performed on NSCLC patients in phase Ⅱ～ⅢA.

        -  In order to assure the necessity of adjuvant chemotherapy on NSCLC patients in phase ⅠB
           or which kind of patients would benefit from it after the establishment of new staging,
           a multi-subject group of lung cancer set up a perspective, randomized, open clinical
           trial to explore whether adjuvant chemotherapy was effective on NSCLC patients in phase
           ⅠB under new staging policy, and to collect the characteristics of patients who could
           benefit from the treatment and the better adjuvant drugs after operation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  In postoperative adjuvant chemotherapy, navelbine plus platinum (NP), the most commonly
           used therapeutic protocol, had more advantages than other 3 generations of new drugs
           plus platinum. With the continuous implementation of individual therapies for lung
           cancer, some new drugs became selective to pathological patterns and gene types, and it
           was unclear whether these drugs would be more effective than conventional drugs in
           postoperative adjuvant chemotherapy. The first- and second-generation of drugs were not
           observed with survival advantages except the third generation, so what conclusion would
           be made in selecting individual chemotherapeutic drugs according to pathological
           patterns? In this study, Pemetrexed plus Platinum were adopted in postoperative adjuvant
           chemotherapy on patients with adeno-carcinoma, while Docetaxel plus Platinum were
           performed on those with non-adeno-carcinoma.

        -  Apart from individual chemotherapy on the basis of different pathological patterns,
           anti-angiogenesis therapy has been quickly developed in recent years, becoming the most
           effective approach to improve chemotherapeutic efficacy. The main mechanism of
           anti-angiogenesis drugs includes inhabiting tumor angiogenesis to postpone or inhabit
           the recurrence of residual tumor through reconstructing the balance of anti-angiogenesis
           and preventing the growth of micro-metastasis to keep it in resting stage. The effect of
           adjuvant chemotherapy can be promoted by increasing the drug sensitivity, and survival
           time can be prolonged though further delaying the time and decreasing the rate of
           postoperative recurrence and metastasis of tumor by anti-angiogenesis therapy combined
           with adjuvant chemotherapy. As more attentions are increasingly given to
           anti-angiogenesis drugs in postoperative adjuvant chemotherapy at present, Endostar, an
           anti-angiogenesis drug studied independently in China, had favorable effect in treating
           advanced lung cancer when combined with chemotherapy. Therefore, this study protocol to
           gather the effect of Endostar on improving the survival of early lung cancer patients by
           observing its effect on partial NSCLC patients in treatment group when combined with
           other therapies.

        -  A total of 392 NSCLC patients in phase ⅠB were selected in this perspective, randomized,
           open and control clinical trial, in which 262 and 130 patients served as research and
           control groups respectively by 2:1. Patients 4-8 weeks after operation were divided
           according to different high risk factors. A total of 4-week different chemotherapies (21
           d as a course) were given to patients with different pathological patterns in research
           group, in which adeno-carcinoma group and non-adeno-carcinoma group were treated by
           Pemetrexed plus Cis-platinum and Docetaxel plus Cis-platinum, respectively. Then, above
           two groups were randomly divided into two subgroups respectively by 1:1, with subgroup 1
           being treated with original chemotherapies while subgroup 2 being added with
           rh-Endostatin therapy.

        -  High risk factors included poor differentiation (including neuro-endocrine carcinoma),
           blood vessel invasion, wedge incision, tumor diameter ＞4 cm, visceral pleura
           involvement, ambiguous N staging and incisal edge ＜1 cm.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed up for 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Disease free survival (DFS)is defined as the time during randomized inclusion to disease recurrence or death.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse reactions of adjuvant chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed up for 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse reactions of adjuvant chemotherapy: gastrointestinal response, bone marrow suppression, hepatic and cardiovascular toxicity, weight loss, neural toxicity and concurrent infection. The classification was decided based on CTCAE v3.0 made by American National Cancer Institute (NCI) in 2003. OS: from the time of randomized inclusion to death caused by any factors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">392</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pemetrexed &amp;Cis-platinum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pemetrexed d1＋Cis-platinum , d1, 21 d as a cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pemetrexed &amp; Cis-platinum &amp; rh-Endostatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pemetrexed d1＋Cis-platinum , d1； rh-Endostatin d1-14; 21 d as a cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel &amp; Cis-platinum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Docetaxel 60mg/m2 d1＋Cis-platinum 60mg/m2, d1, 21 d as a cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel &amp; Cis-platinum &amp; rh-Endostatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Docetaxel ＋ Cis-platinum ＋ rh-Endostatin，21 d as a cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pemetrexed</intervention_name>
    <description>Pemetrexed 500 mg/m2, d1, 21 d as a cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pemetrexed &amp;Cis-platinum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pemetrexed &amp; Cis-platinum &amp; rh-Endostatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alimta</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Docetaxel 60mg/m2 d1＋Cis-platinum 60mg/m2, d1, 21 d as a cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel &amp; Cis-platinum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel &amp; Cis-platinum &amp; rh-Endostatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Taxotere</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rh-Endostatin</intervention_name>
    <description>rh-Endostatin 7.5mg/m2 d1-14; 21 d as a cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pemetrexed &amp; Cis-platinum &amp; rh-Endostatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel &amp; Cis-platinum &amp; rh-Endostatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Endostar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cis-platinum</intervention_name>
    <description>Cis-platinum 60mg/m2, d1, 21 d as a cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pemetrexed &amp;Cis-platinum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pemetrexed &amp; Cis-platinum &amp; rh-Endostatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel &amp; Cis-platinum</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Docetaxel &amp; Cis-platinum &amp; rh-Endostatin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Platinol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are diagnosed with NSCLC pathologically and T stage is T2a in
             postoperative pathological staging. No lymph node and distant metastasis are observed
             and the surgical methods include wedge incision, segmentectomy of right lung or lobe.

          -  Age: 18～70 years

          -  ECOG PS score: 0-1 score

          -  patients who are diagnosed with the high risk factors as follows: poor differentiation
             (including low differentiation, undifferentiation and neuro-endocrine
             differentiation), blood vessel invasion, wedge incision, tumor diameter ＞4 cm,
             visceral pleura involvement, incomplete clear of lymph node and incisal edge ＜1.0 cm.

          -  Patients who are diagnosed without tumor recurrence before adjuvant chemotherapy.

          -  Informed consent is signed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with unexpected pathological patterns or those have received new adjuvant
             chemotherapy.

          -  Patients with other active malignant tumor history beside NSCLC before treatment
             except non-melanoma skin cancer, primary cervical cancer and cured early prostate
             cancer.

          -  Patients who are with chemotherapeutic contraindications, such as white blood count
             ＜4.0×109/L, blood platelet count ＜80×109/L or severe anemia (Hb＜80 g/L); obvious liver
             dysfunction (increased transaminase or bilirubin ＞2.5 folds of normal level);
             un-manageable hypertension, diabetes, arrhythmia, repeated heart failure and chronic
             obstructive pulmonary diseases that could influence ventilation function; active stage
             of diseases infected by bacteria, fungi and virus; or patients who are in pregnancy
             and lactation periods.

          -  Patients who are un-recovered and poor with chemotherapy after 8-week treatment, or
             have received above 8-week treatment before treatment.

          -  Patients who are in poor obedience or other improper symptoms.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pang Zuoliang, Postgraduate</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer Hospital of Xinjiang Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Hospital of Xinjiang Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Urumqi</city>
        <state>Xinjiang</state>
        <zip>830011</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 4, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 26, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 26, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 26, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Xinjiang Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Liu Chunling</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Cancer Hospital Affiliated to Xinjiang Medical University</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endostatins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

