<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02000895</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20100986</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>66787R</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>701170</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02000895</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Detection of Progressive Kidney Disease in Preterm Infants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early Detection of Progressive Kidney Disease in Preterm Infants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Miami</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Infants born preterm and of low birth weight are known to be at increased risk for early
      onset of cardiovascular and renal disease in adult life. This has been related to low nephron
      mass due to inadequate or early termination of glomerulogenesis in utero and during the
      perinatal period. Risks for subsequent development of hypertension and kidney disease include
      proteinuria, excessive weight gain during early life with insulin resistance and supplemental
      high calorie feedings. The long-term goal is for early diagnosis of those infants who are at
      risk for future development of hypertension and kidney disease so that the investigators
      might intervene to potentially avert progression to adult disease. The objective of this
      clinical trial is to acquire data on the natural history of neonatal kidney function and size
      in infants born preterm during the first 2 years of life. This will be done through the use
      of standard serum and urine markers as well as non-invasive ultrasound technology. The
      central hypothesis of this clinical trial is that a subgroup of patients born preterm and of
      low birth weight will demonstrate early markers of kidney injury including elevated serum
      cystatin C, proteinuria and low kidney size. This hypothesis has been formulated on the basis
      of preliminary data from our group studying this question retrospectively in older children
      born prematurely who have developed overt kidney disease. The rationale for the proposed
      research is to develop early serum and demographic markers of pre-clinical kidney disease so
      that early intervention can occur. The proposed clinical trial is innovative because it will
      investigate the risk factors for kidney dysfunction at a pre-clinical stage with the idea of
      gaining more knowledge regarding therapeutic interventions. In addition, the study will
      assess serum cystatin C as a surrogate test for glomerular filtration rate which could
      indicate worsening kidney function at an earlier stage than serum creatinine.

      The proposed research is significant because it is expected to identify at-risk patients for
      future renal impairment and to prospectively monitor the persistence of proteinuria and its
      effect on kidney function in the short term.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives and Hypotheses:

      Infants born preterm and of low birth weight are known to be at increased risk for early
      onset of cardiovascular and renal disease in later life. This has been related to low nephron
      mass due to inadequate or early termination of glomerulogenesis in utero and during the
      perinatal period. Risks for subsequent development of hypertension and kidney disease include
      excessive weight gain during early life with insulin resistance and supplemental high calorie
      feedings.

      Specific Aims The long-term goal is for early diagnosis of those infants who are at risk for
      future development of hypertension and kidney disease so that investigators might intervene
      to potentially avert progression to adult disease. The objective of this clinical trial is to
      acquire data on the natural history of neonatal kidney function and size in infants born
      preterm during the first year of life. This will be done through the use of standard serum
      and urine markers as well as non-invasive ultrasound technology. The central hypothesis of
      this clinical trial is that a subgroup of patients born preterm will demonstrate early
      markers of kidney injury including elevated serum cystatin C, proteinuria and hypertension.
      This hypothesis has been formulated on the basis of preliminary data from the group studying
      this question retrospectively in older children born prematurely who have developed overt
      kidney disease. The rationale for the proposed research is to develop early serum and
      demographic markers of pre-clinical kidney disease so that early intervention may occur.

      Study Design. This is a single-center case-controlled prospective observational study with
      the rationale of evaluating parameters of renal function including proteinuria,
      microalbuminuria and cystatin C in preterm infants and associating this with kidney size and
      blood pressure during the first 10 years of life. Demographics including race, gender and
      growth will provide important perspectives relative to formula and/or breast feeding
      with/without high calorie supplements during the first year.

      Part I of the Trial is enrollment from birth with collection of blood, urine and umbilical
      cords for histomorphometry.

      Part II will be the &quot;call-back&quot; at 6 to 10 years of age for follow-up assessment of
      anthropometric and kidney growth, blood pressure and kidney function.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>10 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in total kidney volume (TKV) from birth to 6 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth, 1 year, 2 years, 6 years, 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>TKV will be measured by 2-D renal ultrasound</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of Hypertension</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year, 2 years, 6 years, 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Blood pressure measurements by sphygmomanometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vascular density and vascular stiffness</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year, 2 years, 6 years, 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Pulse wave velocity measurements and capillary density</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) from birth to 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth, 1 year, 2 years, 6 years, 10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated GFR will be calculated from serum creatinine and Cystatin C</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Disease</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Preterm infants</arm_group_label>
    <description>&gt;24 weeks &lt;37 weeks gestational age</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Term infants</arm_group_label>
    <description>&gt;37 weeks' gestational age</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Follow-up at 6 Years</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children enrolled from the birth cohort(s) to be followed at 6 to 10 years of age.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Urine Cord Blood Umbilical cords
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Preterm infants from 24 to 37 weeks' gestation enrolled at birth to be studied for kidney
        size and function. Term infants &gt;37 weeks' gestation who are stable without complications
        to serve as controls. Follow-up of preterm and term birth cohort(s) at 6-10 years of age.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Stable preterm infants &lt;37 weeks' gestational age; Stable term infants &gt;37 weeks'
        gestational age

        Exclusion Criteria:

        &lt;24 weeks gestational age; &lt;600 grams Any anomalies of the genital-urinary or
        gastrointestinal tract
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carolyn L Abitbol, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami/ Holtz Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Abitbol CL, Seeherunvong W, Galarza MG, Katsoufis C, Francoeur D, Defreitas M, Edwards-Richards A, Master Sankar Raj V, Chandar J, Duara S, Yasin S, Zilleruelo G. Neonatal kidney size and function in preterm infants: what is a true estimate of glomerular filtration rate? J Pediatr. 2014 May;164(5):1026-1031.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2014.01.044. Epub 2014 Mar 5.</citation>
    <PMID>24607244</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>DeFreitas MJ, Seeherunvong W, Katsoufis CP, RamachandraRao S, Duara S, Yasin S, Zilleruelo G, Rodriguez MM, Abitbol CL. Longitudinal patterns of urine biomarkers in infants across gestational ages. Pediatr Nephrol. 2016 Jul;31(7):1179-88. doi: 10.1007/s00467-016-3327-3. Epub 2016 Feb 9.</citation>
    <PMID>26862052</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>DeFreitas MJ, Mathur D, Seeherunvong W, Cano T, Katsoufis CP, Duara S, Yasin S, Zilleruelo G, Rodriguez MM, Abitbol CL. Umbilical artery histomorphometry: a link between the intrauterine environment and kidney development. J Dev Orig Health Dis. 2017 Jun;8(3):349-356. doi: 10.1017/S2040174417000113. Epub 2017 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>28260559</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 22, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 27, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Miami</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carolyn Abitbol</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

