<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02307500</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ONC-2014-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02307500</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Regorafenib in Patients With Metastatic Solid Tumors Who Have Progressed After Standard Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>RESOUND</acronym>
  <official_title>An Open-label Phase II Study of Regorafenib in Patients With Metastatic Solid Tumors Who Have Progressed After Standard Therapy - RESOUND</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single arm, single-stage, phase II trial to evaluate the activity of Regorafenib in
      patients with metastatic solid tumors (pancreatic cancer, ovarian cancer, melanoma, sarcoma
      who have progressed after standard therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Each tumour will be assessed by itself. Regorafenib 40 mg tablets will be used in the study.
      Subjects will receive 160 mg regorafenib po every day (qd) for 3 weeks of every 4 week cycle
      (i.e., 3 weeks on, 1 week off).

      Subjects will continue on treatment until at least one of the following occurs (main
      criteria):

        -  Progressive Disease (PD) by radiological assessments or clinical progression

        -  Death

        -  Unacceptable toxicity

        -  Subject withdraws consent

        -  Treating physician determines discontinuation of treatment is in the subject's best
           interest

        -  Substantial non-compliance with the protocol
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>activity of regorafenib screening, in terms of 2-months progression free survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>to evaluate activity of regorafenib, in terms of 2-months progression free survival rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>prognosis in terms of progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>to explore the prognosis in terms of progression-free survival calculated from the first day of regorafenib treatment to the date of tumor progression or death, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>to explore overall survival (OS) measured from the first day of regorafenib treatment until the date of death from any cause or the date of the last contact, at which the patients will be censored</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety profile of regorafenib according to NCI-CTC v.3</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>to assess the safety profile of regorafenib according to the National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria (NCI-CTC) version 3</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreas Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Regorafenib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Regorafenib 160 mg (40 mg tablets), po, every day for 3 weeks of every 4 week cycle</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Regorafenib</intervention_name>
    <description>oral therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Regorafenib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Stivarga</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed informed consent

          2. Patients older then 18 years.

          3. Locally advanced, recurrent or metastatic histologically confirmed malignancy
             refractory to available standard treatment, included Pancreatic cancer, Ovarian
             cancer, Melanoma, Sarcoma

          4. At least one measurable lesion according to Response Evaluation Criteria In solid
             tumor

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status: 0-1

          6. Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks

          7. Adequate bone marrow, liver and renal function as assessed by the following laboratory
             : Hemoglobin &gt; 9.0 g/dl Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1,500/mm3 Platelet count &gt;
             100,000/μl White blood cells &gt;3.0 x 109/L Total bilirubin &lt;1.5 times the upper limit
             of normal Alanine amino transferase and aspartate amino transferase &lt;2.5 x upper limit
             of normal (&lt;5 x upper limit of normal for patients with liver involvement) Serum
             creatinine &lt;1.5 x upper limit of normal Alkaline phosphatase &lt;2.5 x Upper Limit of
             Normal Prothrombin time / Partial prothrombin time &lt;1.5 x Upper Limit of Normal Lipase
             ≤ 1.5 x the Upper Limit of Normal

          8. Able to swallow and retain oral medication.

          9. Estimated creatinine clearance &gt; 30ml/min as calculated using the Cockcroft-Gault
             equation

         10. Resolution of any toxic effects of prior therapy to NCI Common Terminology Criteria
             for Adverse Event, Version 4.0, grade ≤ 1 .

         11. Women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior treatment with regorafenib.

          2. Major surgical procedure, open biopsy, or significant traumatic injury within 28 days
             before start of study drug

          3. Congestive heart failure &gt;New York Heart Association class 2

          4. Unstable angina), new-onset angina.Myocardial infarction less than 6 months before
             start of study drug

          5. Myocardial infarction less than 6 months before start of study drug.

          6. Cardiac arrhythmias requiring anti-arrhythmic therapy

          7. Uncontrolled hypertension.

          8. Pleural effusion or ascites that causes respiratory compromise

          9. Ongoing infection &gt; Grade 2

         10. Known history of human immunodeficiency virus infection.

         11. Active hepatitis B or C, or chronic hepatitis B or C requiring treatment with
             antiviral therapy.

         12. Subjects with seizure disorder requiring medication.

         13. History of organ allograft. Subjects with evidence or history of any bleeding
             diathesis, irrespective of severity.

         14. Any hemorrhage or bleeding event &gt; Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Effects Grade
             3

         15. Arterial or venous thrombotic or embolic events within the 6 months before start of
             study medication

         16. Known history or symptomatic metastatic brain or meningeal tumors

         17. Suggestive or consistent with central nervous system disease

         18. Renal failure requiring hemo-or peritoneal dialysis.

         19. Dehydration Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Effects v. 4.0 Grade &gt;1.

         20. Substance abuse, medical, psychological or social conditions that may interfere with
             the subject's participation in the study or evaluation of the study results.

         21. Known hypersensitivity to any of the study drugs, study drug classes, or excipients in
             the formulation.

         22. Any illness or medical conditions that are unstable or could jeopardize the safety of
             the subject and his/her compliance in the study.

         23. Interstitial lung disease with ongoing signs and symptoms

         24. Persistent proteinuria of CTCAE Grade 3

         25. Any malabsorption condition.

         26. Concomitant participation or participation within the last 30 days in another clinical
             trial

         27. Systemic anticancer therapy including cytotoxic therapy, signal transduction
             inhibitors, immunotherapy, and hormonal therapy during this trial or within 4 weeks
             before starting to receive study medication.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Armando Santoro, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Armando Santoro, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 02 8224 4080</phone>
    <email>armando.santoro@cancercenter.humanitas.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Silvia Bozzarelli, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 02 8224 7255</phone>
    <email>silvia.bozzarelli@cancercenter.humanitas.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rozzano</city>
        <state>Milan</state>
        <zip>20089</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilhelm SM, Dumas J, Adnane L, Lynch M, Carter CA, Schütz G, Thierauch KH, Zopf D. Regorafenib (BAY 73-4506): a new oral multikinase inhibitor of angiogenic, stromal and oncogenic receptor tyrosine kinases with potent preclinical antitumor activity. Int J Cancer. 2011 Jul 1;129(1):245-55. doi: 10.1002/ijc.25864. Epub 2011 Apr 22.</citation>
    <PMID>21170960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carmeliet P, Jain RK. Angiogenesis in cancer and other diseases. Nature. 2000 Sep 14;407(6801):249-57. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11001068</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferrara N. Vascular endothelial growth factor as a target for anticancer therapy. Oncologist. 2004;9 Suppl 1:2-10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15178810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fong GH, Rossant J, Gertsenstein M, Breitman ML. Role of the Flt-1 receptor tyrosine kinase in regulating the assembly of vascular endothelium. Nature. 1995 Jul 6;376(6535):66-70.</citation>
    <PMID>7596436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shalaby F, Rossant J, Yamaguchi TP, Gertsenstein M, Wu XF, Breitman ML, Schuh AC. Failure of blood-island formation and vasculogenesis in Flk-1-deficient mice. Nature. 1995 Jul 6;376(6535):62-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7596435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goodman VL, Rock EP, Dagher R, Ramchandani RP, Abraham S, Gobburu JV, Booth BP, Verbois SL, Morse DE, Liang CY, Chidambaram N, Jiang JX, Tang S, Mahjoob K, Justice R, Pazdur R. Approval summary: sunitinib for the treatment of imatinib refractory or intolerant gastrointestinal stromal tumors and advanced renal cell carcinoma. Clin Cancer Res. 2007 Mar 1;13(5):1367-73. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17332278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amit L, Ben-Aharon I, Vidal L, Leibovici L, Stemmer S. The impact of Bevacizumab (Avastin) on survival in metastatic solid tumors--a meta-analysis and systematic review. PLoS One. 2013;8(1):e51780. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0051780. Epub 2013 Jan 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23349675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yancopoulos GD, Davis S, Gale NW, Rudge JS, Wiegand SJ, Holash J. Vascular-specific growth factors and blood vessel formation. Nature. 2000 Sep 14;407(6801):242-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11001067</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Acevedo VD, Ittmann M, Spencer DM. Paths of FGFR-driven tumorigenesis. Cell Cycle. 2009 Feb 15;8(4):580-8. Epub 2009 Feb 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19182515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bergers G, Song S, Meyer-Morse N, Bergsland E, Hanahan D. Benefits of targeting both pericytes and endothelial cells in the tumor vasculature with kinase inhibitors. J Clin Invest. 2003 May;111(9):1287-95.</citation>
    <PMID>12727920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Augustin HG, Koh GY, Thurston G, Alitalo K. Control of vascular morphogenesis and homeostasis through the angiopoietin-Tie system. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol. 2009 Mar;10(3):165-77. doi: 10.1038/nrm2639. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19234476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang J, Bae JO, Tsai JP, Kadenhe-Chiweshe A, Papa J, Lee A, Zeng S, Kornfeld ZN, Ullner P, Zaghloul N, Ioffe E, Nandor S, Burova E, Holash J, Thurston G, Rudge J, Yancopoulos GD, Yamashiro DJ, Kandel JJ. Angiopoietin-1/Tie-2 activation contributes to vascular survival and tumor growth during VEGF blockade. Int J Oncol. 2009 Jan;34(1):79-87.</citation>
    <PMID>19082480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bach F, Uddin FJ, Burke D. Angiopoietins in malignancy. Eur J Surg Oncol. 2007 Feb;33(1):7-15. Epub 2006 Sep 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16962282</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saito M, Watanabe J, Fujisawa T, Kamata Y, Nishimura Y, Arai T, Miyamoto T, Obokata A, Kuramoto H. Angiopoietin-1, 2 and Tie2 expressions in endometrial adenocarcinoma--the Ang2 dominant balance up-regulates tumor angiogenesis in the presence of VEGF. Eur J Gynaecol Oncol. 2006;27(2):129-34.</citation>
    <PMID>16620053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Szarvas T, Jäger T, Tötsch M, vom Dorp F, Kempkensteffen C, Kovalszky I, Romics I, Ergün S, Rübben H. Angiogenic switch of angiopietins-Tie2 system and its prognostic value in bladder cancer. Clin Cancer Res. 2008 Dec 15;14(24):8253-62. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-08-0677.</citation>
    <PMID>19088043</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turner N, Grose R. Fibroblast growth factor signalling: from development to cancer. Nat Rev Cancer. 2010 Feb;10(2):116-29. doi: 10.1038/nrc2780. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20094046</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fletcher JA, Rubin BP. KIT mutations in GIST. Curr Opin Genet Dev. 2007 Feb;17(1):3-7. Epub 2007 Jan 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17208434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lanzi C, Cassinelli G, Nicolini V, Zunino F. Targeting RET for thyroid cancer therapy. Biochem Pharmacol. 2009 Feb 1;77(3):297-309. doi: 10.1016/j.bcp.2008.10.033. Epub 2008 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19028457</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marshall CJ. MAP kinase kinase kinase, MAP kinase kinase and MAP kinase. Curr Opin Genet Dev. 1994 Feb;4(1):82-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8193545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herrera R, Sebolt-Leopold JS. Unraveling the complexities of the Raf/MAP kinase pathway for pharmacological intervention. Trends Mol Med. 2002;8(4 Suppl):S27-31. Review. Erratum in: Trends Mol Med 2002 May;8(5):243.</citation>
    <PMID>11927284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferrara N. VEGF and the quest for tumour angiogenesis factors. Nat Rev Cancer. 2002 Oct;2(10):795-803. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12360282</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sawyers CL. Finding the next Gleevec: FLT3 targeted kinase inhibitor therapy for acute myeloid leukemia. Cancer Cell. 2002 Jun;1(5):413-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12124170</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heinrich MC, Blanke CD, Druker BJ, Corless CL. Inhibition of KIT tyrosine kinase activity: a novel molecular approach to the treatment of KIT-positive malignancies. J Clin Oncol. 2002 Mar 15;20(6):1692-703. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11896121</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nikiforov YE. Thyroid carcinoma: molecular pathways and therapeutic targets. Mod Pathol. 2008 May;21 Suppl 2:S37-43. doi: 10.1038/modpathol.2008.10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18437172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Apperley JF, Gardembas M, Melo JV, Russell-Jones R, Bain BJ, Baxter EJ, Chase A, Chessells JM, Colombat M, Dearden CE, Dimitrijevic S, Mahon FX, Marin D, Nikolova Z, Olavarria E, Silberman S, Schultheis B, Cross NC, Goldman JM. Response to imatinib mesylate in patients with chronic myeloproliferative diseases with rearrangements of the platelet-derived growth factor receptor beta. N Engl J Med. 2002 Aug 15;347(7):481-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12181402</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mross K, Frost A, Steinbild S, Hedbom S, Büchert M, Fasol U, Unger C, Krätzschmar J, Heinig R, Boix O, Christensen O. A phase I dose-escalation study of regorafenib (BAY 73-4506), an inhibitor of oncogenic, angiogenic, and stromal kinases, in patients with advanced solid tumors. Clin Cancer Res. 2012 May 1;18(9):2658-67. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-11-1900. Epub 2012 Mar 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22421192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grothey A, Van Cutsem E, Sobrero A, Siena S, Falcone A, Ychou M, Humblet Y, Bouché O, Mineur L, Barone C, Adenis A, Tabernero J, Yoshino T, Lenz HJ, Goldberg RM, Sargent DJ, Cihon F, Cupit L, Wagner A, Laurent D; CORRECT Study Group. Regorafenib monotherapy for previously treated metastatic colorectal cancer (CORRECT): an international, multicentre, randomised, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. Lancet. 2013 Jan 26;381(9863):303-12. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61900-X. Epub 2012 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>23177514</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 25, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 3, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 31, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 31, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

