<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02302898</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201409107</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02302898</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass and Weight Regain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Characteristics Associated With Weight Regain After Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study compares eating behaviors, meal size, and the size of the gastric pouch and
      connection between the gastric pouch and small intestine in patients who had gastric bypass
      surgery two or more years ago and regained weight compared with patients who had gastric
      bypass surgery two or more years ago and maintained their weight loss.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obesity affects a third of adults in the United States. The most effective treatment for
      weight loss is bariatric surgery, and the most common surgery performed in the US is
      Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass (RYGB). However, a significant number of patients regain weight that
      was lost after surgery. The mechanisms for weight regain are likely multifactorial, but not
      well understood. Disordered eating behaviors and dilated gastrojejunostomies (GJ), which
      presumably allows a patient to consume larger portion sizes during a meal, correlate with
      weight regain. Moreover, some data suggest that changes to the gut anatomy may drive eating
      behaviors and food preferences. However, no studies have simultaneously evaluated functional
      gastric volume (the volume of solid or liquid food that can be consumed to a level of
      comfortable fullness in one sitting), anatomical gastric pouch size and GJ diameter, and
      eating behaviors in patients who maintained their post RYGB weight compared with patients who
      have regained weight from their maximum weight loss after RYGB to determine the relationship
      among post RYGB eating behavior, functional and anatomical gastric pouch size, GJ diameter
      and weight change. Accordingly, the objectives of this proposal are to compare 1) eating
      behaviors 2) functional gastric volume and 3) anatomical dimensions of the gastric pouch and
      GJ in patients who are &gt;2 years post RYGB and have regained &gt;20% of their maximum lost weight
      and those who are &gt;2 years post RYGB and have maintained at least 90% weight loss since
      surgery. The following specific aims will be evaluated:

      Aim 1. Evaluate whether differences in eating behaviors exist between subjects who have
      maintained weight loss after RYGB or regained &gt;20% of their maximum lost weight. The
      investigators hypothesize that subjects who have regained weight after RYGB will have higher
      scores on binge eating behaviors and an increased craving for sweets compared with patients
      who have maintained weight loss after RYGB. Eating behaviors will be determined by performing
      the Yale Food Addiction Scale (YFAS), Eating Disorder Examination (EDE), The Food Craving
      Inventory (FCI), and the National Cancer Institute (NCI) ASA24.

      Aim 2. Evaluate whether differences exist in functional gastric volume between subjects who
      have maintained weight loss after RYGB or regained &gt;20% of their maximum lost weight. The
      investigators hypothesize that patients who have regained weight after RYGB will have an
      increased functional gastric volume to both solids and liquids compared to subjects who have
      maintained weight loss after RYGB. Functional gastric volume will be measured during both a
      solid and liquid meal test.

      Aim 3. Evaluate whether differences exist in gastric pouch and GJ sizes between subjects who
      have maintained weight loss after RYGB or regained &gt;20% of their maximum lost weight. The
      investigators hypothesize that patients who have regained weight after RYGB will have
      increased gastric pouch size and GJ diameter compared with patients who have maintained their
      weight loss after RYGB. Anatomical dimensions of the gastric pouch and GJ will be determined
      by using an articulated measuring tool during upper GI tract endoscopy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating Behavior Assessment scores will be compared between both groups</measure>
    <time_frame>Greater than 2 years post RYGB</time_frame>
    <description>Eating behaviors will be determined by performing the Yale Food Addiction Scale (YFAS), Eating Disorder Examination (EDE), The Food Craving Inventory (FCI), and the National Cancer Institute (NCI) ASA24.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional gastric volume will be measured</measure>
    <time_frame>Greater than 2 years post RYGB</time_frame>
    <description>The functional gastric volume is the amount of food or liquid that can be consumed to a feeling of comfortably full in one meal.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastric pouch size and GJ diameter will be measured</measure>
    <time_frame>Greater than 2 years post RYGB</time_frame>
    <description>Anatomical dimensions of the gastric pouch and GJ will be determined by using an articulated measuring tool during upper GI tract endoscopy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wt maintenance</arm_group_label>
    <description>Eating Behavior Evaluation Measurement of Functional gastric volume Measurement of gastric pouch and GJ sizes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wt Regain</arm_group_label>
    <description>Eating Behavior Evaluation Measurement of Functional gastric volume Measurement of gastric pouch and GJ sizes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eating Behavior Evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>Scores will be measured on binge eating behaviors and an increased craving for sweets.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Wt maintenance</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Wt Regain</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Yale Food Addiction Scale (YFAS)</other_name>
    <other_name>Eating Disorder Examination (EDE)</other_name>
    <other_name>The Food Craving Inventory (FCI)</other_name>
    <other_name>National Cancer Institute (NCI) ASA24</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Measurement of Functional gastric volume</intervention_name>
    <description>The functional gastric volume is the amount of food or liquid that can be consumed to a feeling of comfortably full in one meal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Wt maintenance</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Wt Regain</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Measurement of gastric pouch and GJ size</intervention_name>
    <description>Anatomical dimensions of the gastric pouch and GJ will be determined by using an articulated measuring tool during upper GI tract endoscopy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Wt maintenance</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Wt Regain</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population will consist of 20 patients who had laparoscopic RYGB surgery &gt;2 years
        before screening and have regained &gt;20% weight from their maximum weight lost after surgery
        and 20 patients who had laparoscopic RYGB surgery &gt;2 years before screening and have
        maintained at least 90% weight loss from the maximum weight loss after surgery. These
        patients will be identified from the bariatric surgical population at Washington University
        School of Medicine.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages of 21 and 60

          -  Laparoscopic RYGB surgery &gt;2 years before screening

          -  Regained &gt;20% weight from their maximum weight lost after surgery or maintained at
             least 90% weight loss from the maximum weight loss after surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergy to lidocaine, nut allergies, milk intolerance or any other food
             allergies/restrictions that are included in our test meals

          -  A history of alcohol abuse

          -  Currently consuming &gt;20 gm of alcohol per day

          -  Greater than 2 points on the MAST

          -  Severe organ dysfunction

          -  Anemia (hemoglobin &lt;10mg/dl)

          -  PT, PTT and INR &gt; 1.5x UNL

          -  Triglycerides &gt; 400

          -  LFT &gt; 2x UNL

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating

          -  Participants that smoke greater than 20 pack years

          -  Actively using illegal drugs

          -  Depression or other psychological disorders that are untreated

          -  Diabetics receiving Insulin

          -  Patients that have been hospitalized and/or had surgery in the last three months that
             may be unstable (PI will determine this at Physical Exam)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shelby Sullivan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pories WJ, Swanson MS, MacDonald KG, Long SB, Morris PG, Brown BM, Barakat HA, deRamon RA, Israel G, Dolezal JM, et al. Who would have thought it? An operation proves to be the most effective therapy for adult-onset diabetes mellitus. Ann Surg. 1995 Sep;222(3):339-50; discussion 350-2.</citation>
    <PMID>7677463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Magro DO, Geloneze B, Delfini R, Pareja BC, Callejas F, Pareja JC. Long-term weight regain after gastric bypass: a 5-year prospective study. Obes Surg. 2008 Jun;18(6):648-51. doi: 10.1007/s11695-007-9265-1. Epub 2008 Apr 8.</citation>
    <PMID>18392907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brethauer SA, Aminian A, Romero-Talamás H, Batayyah E, Mackey J, Kennedy L, Kashyap SR, Kirwan JP, Rogula T, Kroh M, Chand B, Schauer PR. Can diabetes be surgically cured? Long-term metabolic effects of bariatric surgery in obese patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Ann Surg. 2013 Oct;258(4):628-36; discussion 636-7. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e3182a5034b.</citation>
    <PMID>24018646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freire RH, Borges MC, Alvarez-Leite JI, Toulson Davisson Correia MI. Food quality, physical activity, and nutritional follow-up as determinant of weight regain after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass. Nutrition. 2012 Jan;28(1):53-8. doi: 10.1016/j.nut.2011.01.011. Epub 2011 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>21885246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schultes B, Ernst B, Wilms B, Thurnheer M, Hallschmid M. Hedonic hunger is increased in severely obese patients and is reduced after gastric bypass surgery. Am J Clin Nutr. 2010 Aug;92(2):277-83. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.2009.29007. Epub 2010 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>20519559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miras AD, Jackson RN, Jackson SN, Goldstone AP, Olbers T, Hackenberg T, Spector AC, le Roux CW. Gastric bypass surgery for obesity decreases the reward value of a sweet-fat stimulus as assessed in a progressive ratio task. Am J Clin Nutr. 2012 Sep;96(3):467-73. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.112.036921. Epub 2012 Jul 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22836034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pepino MY, Bradley D, Eagon JC, Sullivan S, Abumrad NA, Klein S. Changes in taste perception and eating behavior after bariatric surgery-induced weight loss in women. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2014 May;22(5):E13-20. doi: 10.1002/oby.20649. Epub 2013 Dec 6. Erratum in: Obesity (Silver Spring). 2014 Oct;22(10):2276.</citation>
    <PMID>24167016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsu LK, Betancourt S, Sullivan SP. Eating disturbances before and after vertical banded gastroplasty: a pilot study. Int J Eat Disord. 1996 Jan;19(1):23-34.</citation>
    <PMID>8640199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>White MA, Kalarchian MA, Masheb RM, Marcus MD, Grilo CM. Loss of control over eating predicts outcomes in bariatric surgery patients: a prospective, 24-month follow-up study. J Clin Psychiatry. 2010 Feb;71(2):175-84. doi: 10.4088/JCP.08m04328blu. Epub 2009 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>19852902</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saunders R. &quot;Grazing&quot;: a high-risk behavior. Obes Surg. 2004 Jan;14(1):98-102.</citation>
    <PMID>14980042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Christou NV, Look D, Maclean LD. Weight gain after short- and long-limb gastric bypass in patients followed for longer than 10 years. Ann Surg. 2006 Nov;244(5):734-40.</citation>
    <PMID>17060766</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sjöström L, Lindroos AK, Peltonen M, Torgerson J, Bouchard C, Carlsson B, Dahlgren S, Larsson B, Narbro K, Sjöström CD, Sullivan M, Wedel H; Swedish Obese Subjects Study Scientific Group. Lifestyle, diabetes, and cardiovascular risk factors 10 years after bariatric surgery. N Engl J Med. 2004 Dec 23;351(26):2683-93.</citation>
    <PMID>15616203</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Franco JV, Ruiz PA, Palermo M, Gagner M. A review of studies comparing three laparoscopic procedures in bariatric surgery: sleeve gastrectomy, Roux-en-Y gastric bypass and adjustable gastric banding. Obes Surg. 2011 Sep;21(9):1458-68. doi: 10.1007/s11695-011-0390-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21455833</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Buchwald H, Avidor Y, Braunwald E, Jensen MD, Pories W, Fahrbach K, Schoelles K. Bariatric surgery: a systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA. 2004 Oct 13;292(14):1724-37. Review. Erratum in: JAMA. 2005 Apr 13;293(14):1728.</citation>
    <PMID>15479938</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hall JC, Watts JM, O'Brien PE, Dunstan RE, Walsh JF, Slavotinek AH, Elmslie RG. Gastric surgery for morbid obesity. The Adelaide Study. Ann Surg. 1990 Apr;211(4):419-27.</citation>
    <PMID>2181950</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ullrich J, Ernst B, Wilms B, Thurnheer M, Schultes B. Roux-en Y gastric bypass surgery reduces hedonic hunger and improves dietary habits in severely obese subjects. Obes Surg. 2013 Jan;23(1):50-5. doi: 10.1007/s11695-012-0754-5.</citation>
    <PMID>22941334</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hsu LK, Benotti PN, Dwyer J, Roberts SB, Saltzman E, Shikora S, Rolls BJ, Rand W. Nonsurgical factors that influence the outcome of bariatric surgery: a review. Psychosom Med. 1998 May-Jun;60(3):338-46. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9625222</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kalarchian MA, Marcus MD, Wilson GT, Labouvie EW, Brolin RE, LaMarca LB. Binge eating among gastric bypass patients at long-term follow-up. Obes Surg. 2002 Apr;12(2):270-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11975227</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kofman MD, Lent MR, Swencionis C. Maladaptive eating patterns, quality of life, and weight outcomes following gastric bypass: results of an Internet survey. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2010 Oct;18(10):1938-43. doi: 10.1038/oby.2010.27. Epub 2010 Feb 18.</citation>
    <PMID>20168309</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Livhits M, Mercado C, Yermilov I, Parikh JA, Dutson E, Mehran A, Ko CY, Gibbons MM. Preoperative predictors of weight loss following bariatric surgery: systematic review. Obes Surg. 2012 Jan;22(1):70-89. doi: 10.1007/s11695-011-0472-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21833817</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cooper Z, Cooper PJ, Fairburn CG. The validity of the eating disorder examination and its subscales. Br J Psychiatry. 1989 Jun;154:807-12.</citation>
    <PMID>2597887</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fairburn CG, Cooper Z. Binge eating: Nature, assessment and treatment. In: Fairburn CG, Wilson G, eds. The Eating Disorder Examination. 12 ed. New York, New York: Guilford Press, 1993:317-360.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>White MA, Whisenhunt BL, Williamson DA, Greenway FL, Netemeyer RG. Development and validation of the food-craving inventory. Obes Res. 2002 Feb;10(2):107-14.</citation>
    <PMID>11836456</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gearhardt AN, Corbin WR, Brownell KD. Preliminary validation of the Yale Food Addiction Scale. Appetite. 2009 Apr;52(2):430-6. doi: 10.1016/j.appet.2008.12.003. Epub 2008 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>19121351</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Subar AF, Kirkpatrick SI, Mittl B, Zimmerman TP, Thompson FE, Bingley C, Willis G, Islam NG, Baranowski T, McNutt S, Potischman N. The Automated Self-Administered 24-hour dietary recall (ASA24): a resource for researchers, clinicians, and educators from the National Cancer Institute. J Acad Nutr Diet. 2012 Aug;112(8):1134-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jand.2012.04.016. Epub 2012 Jun 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22704899</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Flanagan L. Measurement of Functional Pouch Volume following the Gastric Bypass Procedure. Obes Surg. 1996 Feb;6(1):38-43.</citation>
    <PMID>10731248</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Laurenius A, Larsson I, Bueter M, Melanson KJ, Bosaeus I, Forslund HB, Lönroth H, Fändriks L, Olbers T. Changes in eating behaviour and meal pattern following Roux-en-Y gastric bypass. Int J Obes (Lond). 2012 Mar;36(3):348-55. doi: 10.1038/ijo.2011.217. Epub 2011 Nov 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22124454</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Abu Dayyeh BK, Lautz DB, Thompson CC. Gastrojejunal stoma diameter predicts weight regain after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2011 Mar;9(3):228-33. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2010.11.004. Epub 2010 Nov 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21092760</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Heneghan HM, Yimcharoen P, Brethauer SA, Kroh M, Chand B. Influence of pouch and stoma size on weight loss after gastric bypass. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2012 Jul-Aug;8(4):408-15. doi: 10.1016/j.soard.2011.09.010. Epub 2011 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>22055390</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hallowell PT, Stellato TA, Yao DA, Robinson A, Schuster MM, Graf KN. Should bariatric revisional surgery be avoided secondary to increased morbidity and mortality? Am J Surg. 2009 Mar;197(3):391-6. doi: 10.1016/j.amjsurg.2008.11.011.</citation>
    <PMID>19245921</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zingg U, McQuinn A, DiValentino D, Kinsey-Trotman S, Game P, Watson D. Revisional vs. primary Roux-en-Y gastric bypass--a case-matched analysis: less weight loss in revisions. Obes Surg. 2010 Dec;20(12):1627-32. doi: 10.1007/s11695-010-0214-z.</citation>
    <PMID>20577830</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Radtka JF 3rd, Puleo FJ, Wang L, Cooney RN. Revisional bariatric surgery: who, what, where, and when? Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2010 Nov-Dec;6(6):635-42. doi: 10.1016/j.soard.2010.04.005. Epub 2010 May 4.</citation>
    <PMID>20702147</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Morales MP, Wheeler AA, Ramaswamy A, Scott JS, de la Torre RA. Laparoscopic revisional surgery after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass and sleeve gastrectomy. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2010 Sep-Oct;6(5):485-90. doi: 10.1016/j.soard.2009.09.022. Epub 2010 Jan 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20870181</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Thompson CC, Slattery J, Bundga ME, Lautz DB. Peroral endoscopic reduction of dilated gastrojejunal anastomosis after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass: a possible new option for patients with weight regain. Surg Endosc. 2006 Nov;20(11):1744-8. Epub 2006 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>17024527</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Herron DM, Birkett DH, Thompson CC, Bessler M, Swanström LL. Gastric bypass pouch and stoma reduction using a transoral endoscopic anchor placement system: a feasibility study. Surg Endosc. 2008 Apr;22(4):1093-9. Epub 2007 Nov 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18027049</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Thompson CC, Chand B, Chen YK, Demarco DC, Miller L, Schweitzer M, Rothstein RI, Lautz DB, Slattery J, Ryan MB, Brethauer S, Schauer P, Mitchell MC, Starpoli A, Haber GB, Catalano MF, Edmundowicz S, Fagnant AM, Kaplan LM, Roslin MS. Endoscopic suturing for transoral outlet reduction increases weight loss after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery. Gastroenterology. 2013 Jul;145(1):129-137.e3. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2013.04.002. Epub 2013 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>23567348</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Thompson CC, Jacobsen GR, Schroder GL, Horgan S. Stoma size critical to 12-month outcomes in endoscopic suturing for gastric bypass repair. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2012 May-Jun;8(3):282-7. doi: 10.1016/j.soard.2011.03.014. Epub 2011 Apr 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21640665</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jirapinyo P, Slattery J, Ryan MB, Abu Dayyeh BK, Lautz DB, Thompson CC. Evaluation of an endoscopic suturing device for transoral outlet reduction in patients with weight regain following Roux-en-Y gastric bypass. Endoscopy. 2013 Jul;45(7):532-6. doi: 10.1055/s-0032-1326638. Epub 2013 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23801313</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Abu Dayyeh BK, Ryan MB, Thompson CC. 309 Ghrelin and Gastric Pouch Parameters Are Associated With Feeding Behaviors After Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass. Gastroenterology 2013;144:S-64.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Selzer ML. The Michigan alcoholism screening test: the quest for a new diagnostic instrument. Am J Psychiatry. 1971 Jun;127(12):1653-8.</citation>
    <PMID>5565851</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Geliebter A, Gibson CD, Hernandez DB, Atalayer D, Kwon A, Lee MI, Mehta N, Phair D, Gluck ME. Plasma cortisol levels in response to a cold pressor test did not predict appetite or ad libitum test meal intake in obese women. Appetite. 2012 Dec;59(3):956-9. doi: 10.1016/j.appet.2012.08.025. Epub 2012 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22983369</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sullivan S, Stein R, Jonnalagadda S, Mullady D, Edmundowicz S. Aspiration therapy leads to weight loss in obese subjects: a pilot study. Gastroenterology. 2013 Dec;145(6):1245-52.e1-5. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2013.08.056. Epub 2013 Sep 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24012983</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 19, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 26, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 27, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Weight Regain</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

