<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02305459</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CIRSECIRT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02305459</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CIRSE Registry for SIR-Spheres Therapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>CIRT</acronym>
  <official_title>CIRSE Registry for SIR-Spheres Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cardiovascular and Interventional Radiological Society of Europe</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cardiovascular and Interventional Radiological Society of Europe</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The administration of SIR-Spheres microspheres (yttrium-90 resin microspheres) is a form of
      selective internal radiation therapy (SIRT) for the treatment of patients with primary and
      secondary liver tumours. The CIRT Registry has two major objectives: 1) To collect robust
      data on the real-life clinical practice of radioembolisation with SIR-Spheres microspheres in
      a pan-European context, and 2) to collect data on the Quality of Life of patients treated
      with SIR-Spheres microspheres.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Selective internal radiation therapy (SIRT), also called radioembolisation (RE), with
      SIR-Spheres microspheres is an endovascular procedure, included within the interventional
      oncologic technologies to treat primary and secondary liver tumours. Using a microcatheter, a
      precise dose of resin microspheres is released in the hepatic artery, where they are carried
      into the arterioles and selectively lodge in the tumour microvasculature. The microspheres
      are loaded with the radioactive yttrium-90, a high-energy beta-emitting isotope with a
      half-life of 64.1 hours. Following administration, 94% of the radiation is delivered in 11
      days. Previous reports on the safety and efficacy of yttrium-90 resin microspheres for the
      treatment of primary and secondary liver tumours are very promising. In order to further
      improve the understanding of this therapy in its true clinical setting, the Cardiovascular
      and Interventional Radiological Society of Europe (CIRSE) initiated the CIRSE Registry for
      SIR-Spheres Therapy (CIRT), a phase 4 observational study that aims to collect robust data on
      the real-life clinical practice of radioembolisation with SIR-Spheres microspheres. Further,
      using the quality of life questionnaire QLQ-C30 with its hepatocellular carcinoma module
      (developed and verified by the European Organisation of Research and Treatment of Cancer
      (EORTC)), CIRT aims to collect data on the quality of life of patients treated with
      SIR-Spheres microspheres.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>12 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Quality of Life questionnaire QLQ-C30 with HCC Module</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, on average every 3 months up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients treated with Radioembolisation</arm_group_label>
    <description>All Patients treated with Radioembolisation with yttrium-90 loaded SIR-Spheres microspheres are asked to be enrolled. In no way will participation in the registry influence the way in which the patient is treated or will it influence the quality of the treatment.
In order to measure the palliative aspect of RE with SIR-Spheres microspheres, CIRT will incorporate a quality-of-life questionnaire. CIRT will be using EORTC's QLQ-C30 with HCC Module to measure changes in the quality of life of the patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Yttrium-90 loaded SIR-Spheres microspheres</intervention_name>
    <description>Selective internal radiation therapy (SIRT), also called radioembolisation (RE), with SIR-Spheres microspheres is an endovascular procedure, included within the interventional oncologic technologies to treat primary and secondary liver tumours. Using a microcatheter, a precise dose of resin microspheres is released in the hepatic artery, where they are carried into the arterioles and selectively lodge in the tumour microvasculature. The microspheres are loaded with the radioactive yttrium-90, a high-energy beta-emitting isotope with a half-life of 64.1 hours. SIR-Spheres microspheres are manufactured by Sirtex Medical.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients treated with Radioembolisation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>QLQ-C30 with HCC module</intervention_name>
    <description>In order to measure the palliative aspect of RE with SIR-Spheres microspheres, CIRT will incorporate a quality-of-life questionnaire. CIRT will be using EORTC's QLQ-C30 with HCC Module to measure changes in the quality of life of the patient. The quality-of-life questionnaire will be offered to the patient before the treatment, shortly after the treatment (as soon as possible) and at every follow-up. Filling out the quality-of-life questionnaire is entirely voluntary for the patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients treated with Radioembolisation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients are only asked to be enrolled when they are treated with SIR-Spheres microspheres
        as part of the treatment determined by the treating clinician.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Treatment of liver tumour with SIR-spheres microspheres

          -  Primary or secondary liver tumours

          -  Signed informed consent form

          -  18 years or older

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Under 18 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>José Ignacio Bilbao, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CIRSE Cardiovascular and Interventional Radiological Society of Europe</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Niels de Jong, MA</last_name>
    <phone>+43 1 904 2003-47</phone>
    <email>dejong@cirse.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardiovascular and Interventional Radiological Society of Europe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1010</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Niels de Jong</last_name>
      <phone>+43 1 904 2003-47</phone>
      <email>dejong@cirse.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Robert Bauer</last_name>
      <phone>+43 1 904 2003-37</phone>
      <email>bauer@cirse.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>José Bilbao, Professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 11, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 27, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 2, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 17, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 17, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>SIRT</keyword>
  <keyword>microcatheter</keyword>
  <keyword>primary liver tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>secondary liver tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>radioembolisation</keyword>
  <keyword>QLQ-C30</keyword>
  <keyword>CIRSE</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

