<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02301182</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VEK-44819</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02301182</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Functional Results of ADM X3-MoP Cup (Stryker) and a CoC Cup (Zimmer) in Young Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Center Randomized, Patient-Blinded, Prospective Five-Year Study to Compare the Functional Results After Insertion of ADM X3-MoP Cup (Stryker) and a CoC Cup (Zimmer) in Primary THA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aarhus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aarhus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Single-Center Randomized, Patient-Blinded, Prospective Five-Year Study to Compare the
      Functional Results after Insertion of ADM X3-MoP Cup (Stryker) and a CoC Cup (Zimmer) in
      Primary THA. 60 patients will be enrolled during a 2 year period. At surgery tantalum beads
      will be inserted into predrilled holes of the polyethylene rim for assessment of motion of
      the large mobile poly in the ADM Trident Cup by use of RSA. Patients will be followed by
      functional examinations as well as PROM assessment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      With Metal-on-Metal (MoM) articulations leaving the marked the THA bearing choice for younger
      patients is currently debated and overall the choice stands between CoC and MoP. New HXLPE is
      wear-resistant and safe and clinical HXLPE wear (RSA) hardly exceed the wear measured in
      retrieval CoC implants. For CoC articulations stripe wear on edge loading is a reported
      problem leading to increased wear in examined retrieval components and CoC wear is dependent
      on component position. Although the risk is very small, CoC bearings are at still at risk of
      fracture, and functional squeaking is a complication that adversely affects the quality of
      life in about 1% of CoC THA patient. Dual mobility MoP cups were designed for reducing hip
      dislocations in older patients treated with THA after medial hip fractures. The concept
      provides good stability and mobility and may also be an optimal solution for younger and
      active patients; however, dual mobility MoP has not previously been documented for use in
      younger patients. The anatomical dual mobility (ADM) cup design (Stryker) is soft tissue
      sparing (iliopsoas tendon) potentially leading to lesser groin-pain and squeaking is not a
      concern. It is currently unknown if the outer-articulation of the dual mobility PE liner
      keeps moving over time or could impinge in the joint capsule in an undesirable position and
      result in unwanted edge loading and higher wear-rates. Metal ions are produced even in MoP
      bearings and even though in dual-articulation MoP bearings most (90%) of the motion is
      believed to occur between the head and liner (ceramic-polyenthylene), the metal ion levels
      may be higher than expected for MoP hips (large poly contact in metal shell), while
      expectedly there will be no metal ions in CoC THA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Motion analysis (accelerometer (Ax3 Axivity) based activity monitoring)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 year</time_frame>
    <description>For all participants: Inertia sensors are a new technology for patient motion analysis which allows simple and fast routine clinical movement analysis and long-term activity monitoring. We will employ the newest generation of accelerometer (Ax3 Axivity) based activity monitoring (small, light, low cost, validated for orthopaedic patients also with walking aids) to count, in real life, the number of events and the duration of postures and activities. Further muscle power investigations such as by use of the legg extension power rig will be used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>questionnaires (&quot;the Harris Hip Score&quot; (HHS), the Oxford Hip Score (OHS), the HOOS score, satisfaction, dislocation, and revisions)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 year</time_frame>
    <description>For all participants: Pre- and postoperative clinical evaluations will be made according to &quot;the Harris Hip Score&quot; (HHS), the Oxford Hip Score (OHS), the HOOS score, and satisfaction, dislocations and revisions will be noted. Moreover, pre-operative rest and motion pains will be assessed by visual analogue scale scores (VAS).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiography (implant migration and wear)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 year</time_frame>
    <description>For all participants: Within a week following surgery a stereo x-ray is performed and this functions as the baseline for future follow-up (in this study at 1 year, 2 years and 5 years). When comparing all stereo x-rays in a patient series, implant migration with respect to a set of bone markers can be calculated in three dimensions as a function of time - similarly wear of the implant surfaces can be evaluated.Fluoroscopic stereoradiometric recordings (Dynamic RSA) can be used to assess the functional motion of implants at desired motion speeds. In this study we record the liner motion of the ADM cup with the patients in different positions that in theory stresses the motion of the liner into new positions at edge-motions. The purpose is to gain knowledge on the safety function of the implant in vivo - if the liner moves and if it positions safely like it is supposed to.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthroplasties, Hip Replacement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADM X3-MoP Cup</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>THA: ADM dual-mobility hydroxyapatite coated cups with X3TM HXLPE liners on 28mm BIOLOX® delta femoral heads (Stryker) with femoral stems being 2nd generation Accolade stems of the taper lock type, proximal circumferential coated with a 50µm plasma-spray PureFix HA coating to aid the mechanical engagement in bone coating (Stryker)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CoC Cup</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>THA: CoC BIOLOX® delta-delta large-head single-mobility cementless fiber-mesh titanium coated acetabular system from Zimmer (Zimmer TrilogyIT cup/CLS spotorno stem) with a grit-blasted osteophilic titanium alloy CLS® Spotorno femoral stems (Zimmer) that has a three-dimensional wedge shape and sharpened ribs in the proximal region</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ADM X3-MoP Cup</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>ADM X3-MoP Cup</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CoC Cup</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>CoC Cup</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  primary hip osteoarthritis

          -  sufficient bone quality for total hip arthroplasty

          -  age 40 through 65 years of age

          -  informed and written consent

          -  patient can only enter the project with one hip

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  neuromuscular or vascular disease in the affected leg

          -  patients with osteoporosis

          -  fracture sequelae or previous extensive hip surgery

          -  patients with metabolic bone disease including rheumatoid arthritis

          -  non-Danish citizenship

          -  patients who do not comprehend the Danish language

          -  senile dementia

          -  alcoholism and drug abuse

          -  major psychiatric disease

          -  current metastatic cancer disease and on-going treatment with radiation
             therapy/chemotherapy

          -  severe systemic disease affecting gait

          -  contralateral knee, hip and/or spine disease

          -  on-going case regarding industrial injury insurance of the hip

          -  patients with very poor dental status
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aarhus University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus</city>
        <zip>8000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 21, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 24, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 24, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

