<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02306122</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PHARxMOS</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>7RC4AG039072-02</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02306122</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacy Home Adherence Reporting and Monitoring Outcomes Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>PHARxMOS</acronym>
  <official_title>Nudging Doctors to Collaborate With Pharmacists to Improve Medication Adherence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tufts Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Harvard University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brown University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a pilot test of an intervention that delivers timely diagnostic information
      about medication nonadherence to doctors, and then offers the services of clinical
      pharmacists to treat these nonadherence problems. Participating doctors will be notified when
      a patient is 10 days late refilling a medication for diabetes, hypertension, or
      hypercholesterolemia. In one randomization arm the pharmacist will contact the patient as the
      default option (with no action required by the doctor), and in the other the pharmacist will
      contact the patient only if the doctor actively chooses that the pharmacist take action.
      Patients of participating doctors will be randomized to 1) one of these two pharmacist
      options, 2) an information only control arm in which the doctor gets adherence information
      but does not have access to a pharmacist for that patient, and 3) a no information control
      arm. The investigators' central hypothesis is that the pharmacist will be consulted more
      often when intervention by the pharmacist is the default outcome and that the default
      pharmacist intervention will be the most beneficial for adherence outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Poor adherence with prescription medications is ubiquitous, regardless of the disease,
      medication, patient population, or country studied. It is also expensive - annual costs of
      poor adherence in the United States were recently estimated at $290 billion. This problem has
      two components: diagnosis and treatment. Regarding diagnosis, doctors' assessments of
      patients' adherence are inaccurate, and doctors often do not discuss adherence problems with
      their patients. This makes it attractive to use pharmacy claims to identify nonadherence.
      While diagnostic data is necessary to solve the non-adherence problem, it is not sufficient.
      Once diagnosed, doctors must take action to treat nonadherence. Research shows that simply
      giving doctors claims data about nonadherence is ineffective, probably because it is not
      clear what action to take, and because the costs in time and energy of taking action are too
      great. What is currently lacking is a practical way to effectively integrate this diagnostic
      information and treatment expertise into work flows in primary care doctors' offices, and an
      effective method of inducing doctors to act on it. Behavioral economics suggests that
      barriers to doctors' action may be overcome in a cost effective way by altering the
      architecture of choices doctors face.

      The long term goal of this research is to develop systems that effectively connect pharmacy
      benefits managers (PBMs), primary care doctors, clinical pharmacists, and patients in ways
      that improve medication adherence and patients' health outcomes. The overall objective of
      this application, which is the next step toward attainment of the investigators long term
      goal, is to conduct a pilot test of an intervention that delivers timely diagnostic
      information about nonadherence to doctors, and then offers the services of clinical
      pharmacists to treat these nonadherence problems. Participating doctors will be notified when
      a patient is 10 days late refilling a medication for diabetes, hypertension, or
      hypercholesterolemia. Taking advantage of the principle of intelligent choice architecture
      from behavioral economics, in one arm the pharmacist will contact the patient as the default
      option (with no action required by the doctor), and in the other the pharmacist will contact
      the patient only if the doctor actively chooses that the pharmacist take action. Patients of
      participating doctors will be randomized to 1) one of these two pharmacist options, 2) an
      information only control arm in which the doctor gets adherence information but does not have
      access to a pharmacist for that patient, and 3) a no information control arm. Further
      randomization for patients in the experimental arms will occur where the patient's Health
      Maintenance Organization (HMO)/Preferred Provider Organization (PPO) status will be revealed
      to the physician, or not. The investigators central hypothesis, which is strongly supported
      by work in other fields, is that the pharmacist will be consulted more often when
      intervention by the pharmacist is the default outcome and that the default pharmacist
      intervention will be the most beneficial for adherence outcomes.

      This study is a collaboration between researchers at Brown University, Tufts University,
      Harvard University, and Johns Hopkins University; Express Scripts; Blue Cross Blue Shield;
      and a network of primary care doctors in Eastern Massachusetts. The team is led by Dr. Ira
      Wilson, an experienced adherence researcher, and includes behavioral and health economists,
      and a statistician experienced in adherence issues. The investigators will accomplish the
      investigators overall objectives by pursuing the following Specific Aims:

        1. Establish and test the technical and communications infrastructure required for the
           conduct of this clinical trial. The following steps must occur in a secure environment:
           a) Express Scripts notifies the study that a patient is late filling a prescription, b)
           the study notifies the doctor, c) the doctor makes a choice about how to respond, and d)
           a pharmacist, in some cases, contacts the patient.

        2. Conduct and evaluate a clinical trial of an intervention comparing methods of offering
           pharmacist services to primary care doctors. Eligible doctors and patients will be
           randomized to a) pharmacist services under one of two choice architecture conditions
           (default or choice), b) adherence information only, or c) no information; further
           randomization for patients in the experimental arms will occur where the patient's
           HMO/PPO status will be revealed to the physician, or not. Outcomes include medication
           adherence, duration of nonadherence event, and physician participant behavioral
           outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient participant medication adherence outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed over 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patients who are more than 10 days late refilling a chronic medication prescription will be considered the analytic sample frame and will be targeted for intervention according to how they are randomized. The primary adherence outcome, for which the study is powered, is the rate at which these patients have filled a prescription by 30 days. Specifically, each patient will have a 0 or 1 outcome based on whether that patient fills the prescription by 30 days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of non-adherence event</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed over 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure the duration of a non-adherence event in days, truncating those that were never resolved.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician participant behavioral outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed over 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using within doctor comparisons, we will be able to determine whether doctors' behavior changes when they have information about adherence and when they have an option to consult a pharmacist. Examining cross doctor effects, we will be able to compare outcomes of the default and choice arms. By comparing control patients of doctors who receive adherence information for other patients to control patients of doctors who receive no adherence information for any patients, we can determine whether simply calling attention to the problem of adherence improves adherence and patient outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician participant engagement with the system</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed over 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will study the physicians' use of the PHARxMOS system, including patterns of logins, utilization of the pharmacists, etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>13</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2697</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Hypercholesterolemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Default patient default doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient nonadherence information sent to physician; Pharmacist calls patient unless physician cancels call</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient default doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient nonadherence information sent to physician</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control patient default doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control - no intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Choice patient choice doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient nonadherence information sent to physician; Pharmacist calls patient if physician requests call</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient choice doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient nonadherence information sent to physician</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control patient choice doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control - no intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient information doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient nonadherence information sent to physician</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control patient information doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control - no intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Default patient default doctor status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient HMO/PPO status revealed to physician; Patient nonadherence information sent to physician; Pharmacist calls patient unless physician cancels call</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient default doc status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient HMO/PPO status revealed to physician; Patient nonadherence information sent to physician</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Choice patient choice doc status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient HMO/PPO status revealed to physician; Patient nonadherence information sent to physician; Pharmacist calls patient if physician requests call</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient choice doc status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient HMO/PPO status revealed to physician; Patient nonadherence information sent to physician</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient info doc status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient HMO/PPO status revealed to physician; Patient nonadherence information sent to physician</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacist calls patient unless physician cancels call</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Default patient default doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Default patient default doctor status</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient nonadherence information sent to physician</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Default patient default doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient default doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Choice patient choice doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient choice doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient information doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Default patient default doctor status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient default doc status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Choice patient choice doc status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient choice doc status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient info doc status</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacist calls patient if physician requests call</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Choice patient choice doctor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Choice patient choice doc status</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient HMO/PPO status revealed to physician</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Default patient default doctor status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient default doc status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Choice patient choice doc status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient choice doc status</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Information patient info doc status</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult patients of consented New England Quality Care Alliance (NEQCA) primary care
             physicians

          -  Insured through Blue Cross Blue Shield of Massachusetts

          -  Prescribed chronic medications for one or more of the three study conditions in the
             past six months

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ira B Wilson, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brown University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brown University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02913</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 30, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 30, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 30, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brown University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ira B. Wilson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Chair, Department of Health Services, Policy &amp; Practice</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>medication adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>choice architecture</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacy home</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypercholesterolemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

