<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02309710</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>595330-3</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02309710</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Male Circumcision (MC) Using the ShangRing™ Device in Malawi</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Study of Male Circumcision Using the ShangRing Device in Routine Clinical Settings in Malawi</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>FHI 360</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>FHI 360</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This prospective study will evaluate the safety and acceptability of the ShangRing device for
      medical male circumcision (MMC) during routine service delivery in Namitete, Malawi
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although voluntary medical male circumcision (VMMC) was adopted as a prevention strategy in
      2011, MMC prevalence in Malawi is low with estimates between 2 and 20%. The 5-year national
      VMMC target for Malawi is 80% of men ages 15 - 49, or more than two million procedures. Since
      2011, only 42,700 VMMCs have been done for HIV prevention, about 2% of the target. Of the 29
      healthcare districts in Malawi, only a minority are supported by non-governmental (NGO) and
      U.S. government-funded VMMC programs. Major obstacles include few VMMC service-delivery
      points; few trained service providers; poor availability of prepackaged disposable VMMC kits
      requiring re-use of instruments and supplies; few organized campaigns or community
      mobilization programs; and drop-in services only.

      Scale-up of adult MMC services in Malawi could be accelerated by the availability of
      simplified, bloodless methods. Methods of MMC using devices may also increase safety,
      efficiency and acceptability. Although many devices are available and widely used for infant
      circumcision, fewer devices exist for use in adult male circumcision and there are limited
      data on device use in adults. Small-scale safety studies, randomized controlled trials
      (RCTs), and field demonstration studies are required before the safety, effectiveness,
      acceptability, and feasibility of any device is assured.

      Several devices have recently been developed that have the potential to simplify and shorten
      both training time and surgical duration by eliminating the need for suturing and hemostasis
      as well as allow for task-shifting to lower-level cadres of healthcare providers (i.e.
      non-physician), thereby reducing the strain on healthcare systems by having more healthcare
      workers available to provide MMC services. One such device is the ShangRing.

      In the WHO framework, smaller bridging studies are recommended to address additional
      questions about particular sub-populations and specific conditions of use (WHO 2011). This
      research study will assess the safety and acceptability of the ShangRing within the context
      of routine service delivery in Namitete, Malawi. The investigators will enroll 500
      HIV-uninfected adult men aged 18 to 49 years voluntarily seeking medical male circumcision.
      The men will be scheduled for two follow-up visits at 7 and 42 days after ShangRing placement
      for device removal and a healing check, respectively. Results from this study will inform the
      Malawi Ministry of Health (MOH) as it decides on the integration of MMC devices into its
      national VMMC program.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The percentage of men with moderate and severe adverse events will be tabulated with 95% confidence intervals</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 42 days following circumcision procedure</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of men ineligible for MMC with ShangRing</measure>
    <time_frame>up to four months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion and 95% confidence interval (CI) of men who did not receive ShangRing circumcision because of inability to find an appropriate size will be reported</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage distribution of overall satisfaction for study participants</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 42 visit</time_frame>
    <description>Study participants will be interviewed using a standardized questionnaire with items on overall satisfaction with the ShangRing procedure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage preference for ShangRing procedure among study MC providers</measure>
    <time_frame>an expected average of one month after study initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Study circumcision providers will complete the first questionnaire after receiving training and completing 20 circumcision and device removal procedures. Providers will be interviewed using a standardized questionnaire that includes items on preference for ShangRing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Healing at final follow up visit</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 42 days</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of men with complete healing at 42 days for all study participants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage preference for ShangRing procedure among study MC providers</measure>
    <time_frame>An expected average of six months after study initiation</time_frame>
    <description>Providers will complete a second questionnaire at the end of the study after all follow-up visits are completed. Study circumcision providers will be interviewed using a standardized questionnaire that includes items on preference for ShangRing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Male Circumcision</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ShangRing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ShangRing administered to men seeking medical male circumcision</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ShangRing</intervention_name>
    <description>ShangRing administered to males seeking medical male circumcision</description>
    <arm_group_label>ShangRing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be aged 18 to 49 years;

          -  Must be HIV-uninfected per same-day routine HIV testing and counseling (HTC) at the
             clinic;

          -  Must be uncircumcised (on examination);

          -  Must be in good general health, at the discretion of the clinician;

          -  Must be free of genital ulcerations or other visible signs of sexually transmitted
             infections(STI) on examination;

          -  Must be able to understand study procedures, and agree to abide by them including the
             follow-up visit schedule;

          -  Must be able to communicate in English or Chichewa;

          -  Must freely consent to participate in the study, be available for follow-up visits,
             and sign a written informed consent form (ICF); and

          -  Must provide full contact information including cell phone number, address, and other
             locator information

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has an anatomic abnormality (e.g. phimosis or hypospadias) that contraindicates
             ShangRing MMC;

          -  Takes a medication that would be a contraindication for elective surgery, such as an
             anticoagulant or steroid;

          -  Has a self-reported medical condition that would be a contraindication for elective
             surgery, e.g. hemophilia, extreme obesity, poorly controlled diabetes, sickle cell
             anemia;

          -  Has a self-reported allergy or sensitivity to lidocaine or other local anesthesia; or

          -  Is not available to be circumcised on the same day as screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Feldblum, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>FHI 360</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Christian Health Association of Malawi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lilongwe</city>
        <country>Malawi</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Gabriel's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Namitete</city>
        <country>Malawi</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malawi</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 3, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 20, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 20, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 21, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

