<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02305433</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1236/00.01.05.01.00/2013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02305433</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Long-term Intensive Home-based Physiotherapy on Older People With an Operated Hip Fracture or Frailty (RCT).</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Long-term Intensive Home-based Physiotherapy on Older People With an Operated Hip Fracture or Frailty (RCT).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>South Karelia, Social and Health Care District</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Social Insurance Institution, Finland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Helsinki University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Jyvaskyla</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Eastern Finland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Poitiers</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>South Karelia, Social and Health Care District</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Our objective is to study the effects of 12 months' intensive home-based physiotherapy with
      12 months' follow-up in two groups of older people: 1) those with an operated hip fracture
      (60+ y), and 2) those with signs of frailty (65+ y). The primary outcome measure is duration
      of living at home. Power calculations are based on the assumption that persons assigned to
      physiotherapy will live at home for six months longer vs. those in usual care. Secondary
      outcomes are physical functioning, falls, health-related quality-of-life, use and costs of
      social and health services, and mortality.

      We will recruit 300 persons with hip fracture and 300 with signs of frailty in Eksote (South
      Karelia Social and Health Care District), Finland (population 133 000). The groups will be
      randomized separately into an intervention arm (home-based physiotherapy twice a week for 12
      months) and a control arm (usual care), resulting in 150 patients in each group.

      An assessor-physiotherapist and assessor-nurse performs measurements at the participant's
      home at baseline, and after 3, 6 and 12 months. Assessments include, among others, Fried's
      frailty criteria, Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB), Functional Independence Measure
      (FIM), Health-related quality-of-life (HRQoL, 15-D), Mini Nutritional Assessment (MNA), Falls
      Efficacy Scale - International (FES-I), Social Provision Scale (SPS), Mini Mental State
      Examination (MMSE), and Geriatric Depression Scale-15 (GDS-15). At 24 months we collect
      register information on mortality and the usage of health care services.

      Recruitment will begin in December 2014 and last for three years. Data analyses and reporting
      will take place in 2017-20. The study is supported by the Social Insurance Institution of
      Finland.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is increasing need to develop new models of rehabilitation to postpone older people's
      disabilities and institutional care. One alternative is home-based rehabilitation with
      emphasis on functional-based exercises and nutrition.

      Our objective is to study the effects of home-based physiotherapy for 12 months followed by
      12 months' follow-up in older people, either with an operated hip fracture (60+ y) or with
      signs of frailty (65+ y). The primary outcome measure is duration of living at home (vs.
      assisted living and institutional care). Power calculations are based on the assumption that
      at 24 months persons assigned to physiotherapy have lived at home for six months longer vs.
      those in usual care. Usual care follows the standard care procedures in South Karelia social
      and health care district (Eksote), Finland. The population in Eksote area is 133, 000.
      Secondary outcomes are physical functioning, falls, health-related quality-of-life (HRQoL),
      use and costs of social and health services, and mortality.

      We will recruit 300 persons with hip fracture and 300 with signs of frailty. After the
      operation, persons with hip fracture will be transferred from the surgery unit to a
      rehabilitation hospital, where spend approximately four weeks before discharge. The other
      patient group includes persons with frailty signs. They will be screened among outpatients
      and inpatients using modified frailty questionnaires by Abellan van Kan et al. (2008) and
      Morley et al. (2012). Diagnosis of frailty is based on Fried´s criteria (2001). Both patient
      groups will be randomized separately into an intervention arm (home-based physiotherapy twice
      a week for 12 months) and a control arm (usual care), resulting in 150 patients in each
      group.

      Physiotherapy is carried out by private physiotherapists, who have been trained to follow the
      intervention protocol. Physiotherapy is individually designed to meet the patient's
      functional capacity and needs but at the same time it is progressive. Each physiotherapy
      session includes muscle strength and endurance training (especially for lower limbs), balance
      and coordination training and functional training. Functional training includes activities of
      daily living (ADL) and walking exercises. In addition, the physiotherapists give counseling
      on nutrition (based on Mini Nutritional Assessment, MNA) and follow the participant´s weight.

      An assessor-physiotherapist and assessor-nurse performs measurements at the participant's
      home at baseline, and after 3, 6 and 12 months. Assessments include, among others, modified
      Fried's frailty criteria, Short Physical Performance Battery (SPPB), Functional Independence
      Measure (FIM), HRQoL (15 D), MNA, Falls Efficacy Scale - International (FES-I), Social
      Provision Scale (SPS), Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE), and Geriatric Depression
      Scale-15 (GDS-15). In addition we collect register data on living and housing conditions, use
      and costs of social and health care services, and mortality at the end of the follow-up (24
      months since the beginning of the study).

      Recruitment will begin in December 2014 and last for three years. Data analyses and reporting
      will take place in 2017-20. The study is supported by the Social Insurance Institution of
      Finland.

      References

        -  Abellan van Kan G, Rolland Y, Bergman H, Morley JE, Kritchevsky SB, Vellas B. (2008).
           The I.A.N.A Task Force on frailty assessment of older people in clinical practice. J
           Nutr Health Aging.12(1):29-37

        -  Fried LP, Tangen CM, Walston J, Newman AB, Hirsch C, Gottdiener J, Seeman T, Tracy R,
           Kop WJ, Burke G, McBurnie MA. (2001). Cardiovascular Health Study Collaborative Research
           Group. Frailty in older adults: evidence for a phenotype. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med
           Sci;56(3):M146-56.

        -  Morley JE, Malmstrom TK, Miller DK.(2012). A simple frailty questionnaire (FRAIL)
           predicts outcomes in middle aged African Americans. J Nutr Health Aging 16(7):601-8.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>duration of time living at home</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>register information</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in physical functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3, 6, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Short Physical Performance Battery, Hand grip strength, Functional Independence Measure, Instrumental Activities of Daily Living, physical activity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the amount of falls</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3, 6, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>diary, register information</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in health-related quality-of-life</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3, 6, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>HRQoL questionnaire 15-D</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the amount of use and costs of social and health services</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>register information</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>all cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>3, 6, 12 and 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>register information</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in severity of frailty</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>modified Fried´s frailty criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">421</enrollment>
  <condition>Frail Elderly</condition>
  <condition>Hip Fracture</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physiotherapy for frail elderly</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individually tailored, long-term home-based physiotherapy twice a week for 12 months. The duration of one session is 60 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physiotherapy for operated hip fracture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individually tailored, long-term home-based physiotherapy twice a week for 12 months. The duration of one session is 60 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care for frail elderly</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care follows the standard care procedures in the South Karelia Social and Health Care District in health care and in assisted home living.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care for operated hip fracture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care follows the standard care procedures in the South Karelia Social and Health Care District in health care and in assisted home living.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home-based physiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Each physiotherapy session includes muscle strength and endurance training (especially for lower limbs), balance and coordination training and functional training. Functional training includes walking exercises and ADL (activities of daily living) exercises. In addition the physiotherapist gives counseling on nutrition.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Physiotherapy for frail elderly</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Physiotherapy for operated hip fracture</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age 65+

          -  home-dwelling but an increased risk for disabilities or for institutional care

          -  ability to walk inside one´s own home with or without mobility aids

          -  ability to communicate in Finnish

          -  in case of hip fracture: the first operated hip fracture

          -  in case of frailty: signs of frailty assessed by modified Fried's frailty criteria

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  living in nursing home or institutional care facility

          -  severe neurological diseases (Parkinson, MS, stroke)

          -  severe heart diseases with physical capacities significantly impaired (NYHA class III
             or IV)

          -  severe musculoskeletal diseases which prevent from participating in long-term
             physiotherapy

          -  terminal illnesses (e.g. cancer) that diminish the estimated home-dwelling time to
             less than two years

          -  severe mental problems (severe depression, psychosis or schizophrenia)

          -  severe alcohol or drug abuse

          -  severe problems with hearing or eyesight
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Markku T Hupli, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>South Karelia, Social and Health Care District</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Karelia, Social anh Health Care District</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lappeenranta</city>
        <state>South Karelia</state>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 28, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 28, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 2, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>South Karelia, Social and Health Care District</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paula Soukkio</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Project Manager</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>functional-based physiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>frailty syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>osteoporotic hip fractures</keyword>
  <keyword>home-based physiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>home-dwelling</keyword>
  <keyword>intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>randomised controlled trial</keyword>
  <keyword>costs of social and health care</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>physical functioning</keyword>
  <keyword>mobility</keyword>
  <keyword>nutrition</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hip Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

