<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02303678</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00053325</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02303678</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>D2C7 for Adult Patients With Recurrent Malignant Glioma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Single-Center, Dose Escalation Study of D2C7-IT Administered Intratumorally Via Convection-Enhanced Delivery for Adult Patients With Recurrent Malignant Glioma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Darell D. Bigner, MD, PhD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I study to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of D2C7-IT (D2C7
      Immunotoxin) when delivered intratumorally by convection-enhanced delivery (CED) to recurrent
      World Health Organization (WHO) grade III (dose escalation only) and IV (dose escalation and
      dose expansion) malignant glioma patients, and to determine what dose will be considered in a
      single-arm Phase II trial. Patients with recurrent WHO grade III (dose escalation only) and
      IV (dose escalation and dose expansion) malignant glioma who meet eligibility criteria will
      be enrolled into the study. Immediately following stereotactically-guided tumor biopsy,
      subjects will have catheters inserted. If the frozen section of the biopsy indicates a proven
      diagnosis of recurrent malignant glioma (diagnosis results are typically received within
      24-48 hours following biopsy), the investigators will proceed with the D2C7-IT infusion. If
      not, the catheters will be removed. A continuous intratumoral infusion of D2C7-IT will be
      administered and the same total flow rate for all catheters will be set at 0.5 ml/hour per
      catheter for 72 hours.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I study to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of D2C7-IT, when
      delivered intratumorally by convection-enhanced delivery (CED) following confirmatory
      diagnostic biopsy in recurrent World Health Organization (WHO) grade III and IV malignant
      glioma patients, and to determine what dose will be considered in a phase II trial.

      A two-stage continual reassessment method (CRM) design will be used to determine the MTD of
      D2C7-IT where the first stage involves dose escalation in successive patients until an
      initial DLT is observed. Cohorts of 2 patients will be accrued to this study within both
      stages of the trial. The first patient of each cohort will be observed through the completion
      of the D2C7-IT infusion, before additional patients in that cohort are treated. Once the
      optimal dose level of D2C7-IT is determined (dose escalation completed), a total of 27
      recurrent patients with WHO grade IV malignant glioma patients will be treated at that dose
      level as a dose expansion cohort.

      Patients diagnosed with recurrent malignant glioma based on radiographic evidence may be
      enrolled onto the study prior to biopsy. Up to four intratumoral catheters will be placed in
      areas at greatest risk for infiltrating disease and in any solid-contrast-enhancing disease.
      Catheter placement will be based on the BrainLab software. If frozen section of the biopsy
      indicates a proven diagnosis of recurrent WHO Grade III or IV malignant glioma (diagnosis
      results are typically received within 24-48 hours following biopsy), the investigators will
      proceed with D2C7-IT infusion. If not, the catheters will be removed. Molecular genetic
      tests, such as, but not limited to, DNA sequencing, gene amplification, and gene expression,
      will be performed on the tissue obtained at biopsy. The goal of these molecular genetic tests
      is to identify genetic predictors of response or failure of response to treatment with
      D2C7-IT.

      A continuous intratumoral infusion of D2C7-IT will be administered in the Neurosciences Step
      down unit at Duke for 72 hours. Patients who are taking (and are stable on) less than or
      equal to 4 mg per day of dexamethasone (i.e. low-dose corticosteroid) within the 2 weeks
      prior to admission for D2C7-IT infusion (i.e. patients who meet the relevant eligibility
      criterion) may continue on this dose. Patients taking corticosteroids for other medical
      indications (e.g., asthma or skin condition) will be advised to continue use of these
      medications. The patient will remain in the hospital during the entire infusion. At the
      completion of the infusion, the catheters will be removed within 6 hours and a CT scan will
      be obtained after the catheters are pulled. The patient will be observed in hospital for a
      minimum of another 6 hours.

      Following D2C7-IT infusion, subjects will be evaluated in clinic at 2 weeks for adverse
      events and followed at 4 and 8 weeks and every 8 weeks thereafter until 48 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 5, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of D2C7-IT</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks after D2C7 administration</time_frame>
    <description>The MTD is the dose that results in an estimated DLT rate based upon the CRM model that is nearest to the target DLT rate of 0.25. DLTs include any ≥ Gr.3 non-hematologic toxicities, any ≥ Gr.3 neurological toxicities, and any ≥ Gr.3 hematologic toxicities that do not resolve to pre-treatment baseline or ≤ Gr.1 within 2 weeks or any toxicity that resolves within the 2 week period, but then recurs during that same 2 week period. Adverse events will be collected using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>OS is defined at the time between administration of D2C7-IT and death. For patients alive, OS will be censored at the time of last follow-up. Kaplan-Meier methods will be used to estimate median OS and PFS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between EGFRvIII and EGFRwt expression and PFS and OS.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cox proportional hazards models will explore the relationship between EGFRvIII and EGFRwt expression as measured by immunohistochemistry (IHC), polymerase chain reactions (PCR), and fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) and PFS and OS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Brain Tumor, Recurrent</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>D2C7-IT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recurrent malignant glioma patients will receive D2C7-IT, delivered intratumorally by CED following confirmatory diagnostic biopsy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>D2C7-IT</intervention_name>
    <description>D2C7-IT is a single-chain fragment variable (scFv) monoclonal antibody (Mab) fragment immunotoxin with high binding affinity for both EGFRwt- and EGFRvIII-expressing glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) cells.</description>
    <arm_group_label>D2C7-IT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Dose escalation only: Patients must have a recurrent supratentorial WHO grade III or
             IV malignant glioma based on imaging studies;

          -  Dose expansion only: Patients must have a recurrent supratentorial WHO grade IV
             malignant glioma based on imaging studies

          -  Prior histopathology consistent with a supratentorial WHO grade III (dose escalation
             only) or IV (dose escalation and dose expansion) malignant glioma;

          -  Following biopsy, prior to administration of D2C7-IT, the presence of recurrent tumor
             must be confirmed by histopathological analysis;

          -  Age ≥ 18 years of age;

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status (KPS) ≥ 70%;

          -  Laboratory Values:

               -  Platelet Count ≥ 125,000 cells/mm3 prior to biopsy. Platelets ≥ 100,000 cells/mm3
                  prior to infusion;

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 10 gm/dL prior to biopsy;

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1500 cells/mm3 prior to biopsy;

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.2 x the upper limit of normal (ULN) prior to biopsy;

               -  Liver Function: Total bilirubin ≤ 1.6 mg/dL prior to biopsy; AST/ALT ≤ 2.5 x the
                  ULN prior to biopsy;

               -  Prothrombin (PT) and activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) ≤ 1.2 x upper
                  limit of normal (ULN) prior to biopsy. Patients with prior history of
                  thrombosis/embolism are allowed to be on anticoagulation, understanding that
                  anti-coagulation will be held in the peri-operative period per the neurosurgical
                  team's recommendations. Low molecular weight heparin (LMWH) is preferred. If a
                  patient is on warfarin, the international normalized ratio (INR) is to be
                  obtained and value should be below 2.0 prior to biopsy;

          -  Ability to comply with study and follow-up procedures;

          -  If the patient is a sexually active female of child bearing potential, whose partner
             is male, or if the patient is a sexually active male, whose partner is a female of
             child bearing potential, the patient must agree to use appropriate contraceptive
             measures for the duration of the treatment of the tumor and for 6 months afterwards as
             stated in the informed consent. Female patients of child bearing potential must have a
             negative serum pregnancy test at the time of screening and within 48 hours of starting
             the D2C7-IT infusion

          -  Patients will sign an IRB-approved informed consent form prior to any study-related
             procedures.

          -  Able to undergo brain MRI with and without contrast.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior, unrelated malignancy requiring current active treatment with the exception of
             cervical carcinoma in situ and adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin;

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding;

          -  Patients with contrast-enhancing tumor component crossing the midline, actively
             growing multi-focal tumor, infratentorial tumor or tumor dissemination (subependymal
             or leptomeningeal);

          -  Patients with clinically significant increased intracranial pressure (e.g., impending
             herniation), uncontrolled seizures, or requirement for immediate palliative treatment;

          -  Patients with a known allergy to Gadolinium-DTPA;

          -  Unstable systemic disease in the opinion of the treating physician, for example active
             infection requiring IV antibiotics;

          -  Patients on greater than 4mg per day of dexamethasone within the 2 weeks prior to
             admission for D2C7-IT infusion;

          -  Patients with worsening steroid myopathy (history of gradual progression of bilateral
             proximal muscle weakness, and atrophy of proximal muscle groups);

          -  Less than 12 weeks from radiation therapy, unless progressive disease outside of the
             radiation field or 2 progressive scans at least 4 weeks apart or histopathologic
             confirmation;

          -  Treated with immunotherapeutic agents within 4 weeks before enrollment, unless the
             patient has recovered from the expected toxic effects of such therapy;

          -  Treated with antiangiogenic agents (like bevacizumab) within 4 weeks before biopsy;

          -  Treated with alkylating agents within 4 weeks before enrollment (6 weeks for
             nitrosoureas) or treated within 1 week before enrollment with daily or metronomic
             chemotherapy, unless the patient has recovered from the expected toxic effects of such
             therapy;

          -  Prior chemotherapy (non-alkylating agents) within 2 weeks before enrollment, unless
             the patient has recovered from the expected toxic effects of such therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dina Randazzo, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center at Duke University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susan Boulton, RN, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>919-684-5301</phone>
    <email>dukebrain1@dm.duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stevie Threatt</last_name>
    <phone>919-684-5301</phone>
    <email>dukebrain1@dm.duke.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center at Duke</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stevie Threatt</last_name>
      <phone>919-684-5301</phone>
      <email>dukebrain1@duke.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://tischbraintumorcenter.duke.edu/</url>
    <description>The Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dukecancerinstitute.org/</url>
    <description>Duke Cancer Institute</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 19, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 28, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 1, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 29, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 29, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Darell D. Bigner, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Edwin L. Jones, Jr. and Lucille Finch Jones Cancer Research Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>D2C7</keyword>
  <keyword>Randazzo</keyword>
  <keyword>Bigner</keyword>
  <keyword>Pro00053325</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent malignant glioma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

