<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03116048</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GZA-ANE-PECS-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03116048</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Persistent Postsurgical Pain After Breast Surgery With a Pectoral Nerves Block (Pecs) Type II</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Persistent Postsurgical Pain After Breast Surgery With a Pectoral Nerves Block (Pecs) Type II: a Prospective Follow-up After a Prospective Double Blind Placebo-controlled Randomized Controlled Trail</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GZA Ziekenhuizen Campus Sint-Augustinus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GZA Ziekenhuizen Campus Sint-Augustinus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background and objectives The Pectoral Nerves Block (Pecs) Type II is a regional anesthesia
      technique that provides post-surgical pain relief for patients undergoing breast surgery.
      Post-procedural pain relief is known to diminish persistent pain. In this prospective
      follow-up, the investigators evaluated whether the Pecs II block, compared to placebo, is
      effective in reducing persistent post-procedural pain after breast cancer surgery in female
      patients.

      Patients and methods 140 breast cancer stage 1-3 patients undergoing mastectomy or
      tumorectomy with sentinel node or axillary node dissection under general anesthesia were
      randomized to receive a Pecs block (levobupivacaine 0.25%) or placebo (saline 0.9%). Patients
      were invited between 9 and 31 months after surgery to complete a persistent postsurgical pain
      survey.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Breast cancer is the most common cancer in women. For breast cancer patients, surgery is the
      most effective therapeutic intervention. Up to two thirds of female patients undergoing
      breast cancer surgery develop chronic post-procedural pain. This can be best understood by
      the fact that chronic post-procedural pain is strongly associated with acute post-procedural
      pain and that even minimal breast surgery can result in significant post-procedural pain.

      Regional anesthesia techniques can improve acute and chronic post-procedural pain outcomes.
      In the prospective double blind placebo-controlled randomized controlled trial, the
      investigators found that the pectoral nerves (Pecs) block type II, as described by Blanco et
      al., provides reliable and effective post-procedural analgesia for patients undergoing breast
      surgery.

      In this prospective follow-up, the investigators evaluate whether the Pecs II block is
      effective in reducing chronic post-procedural pain in female adult patients undergoing breast
      cancer surgery compared to placebo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 24, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 12, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic post- procedural pain evaluation through questionaire</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the chronic post procedural pain in breast surgery under general anesthesia with a pecs or placebo block</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">121</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Post-Procedural Pain</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pecs group (study group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chronic pain assessment with study questionnaire</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group (placebo group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chronic pain assessment with study questionnaire</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chronic pain evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>Chronic pain assessment with study questionnaire</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pecs group (study group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control group (placebo group)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  participated in the Large-scale Prospective Double-blind Randomized Controlled Trial
             of Pecs II Block for Breast Surgery (NCT02544282)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patient refusal
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick Van Houwe, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GZA Ziekenhuizen Campus Sint-Augustinus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GZA Sint Augustinus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wilrijk</city>
        <state>Antwerpen</state>
        <zip>2610</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferlay J, Soerjomataram I, Dikshit R, Eser S, Mathers C, Rebelo M, Parkin DM, Forman D, Bray F. Cancer incidence and mortality worldwide: sources, methods and major patterns in GLOBOCAN 2012. Int J Cancer. 2015 Mar 1;136(5):E359-86. doi: 10.1002/ijc.29210. Epub 2014 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25220842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>El-Tamer MB, Ward BM, Schifftner T, Neumayer L, Khuri S, Henderson W. Morbidity and mortality following breast cancer surgery in women: national benchmarks for standards of care. Ann Surg. 2007 May;245(5):665-71.</citation>
    <PMID>17457156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poleshuck EL, Katz J, Andrus CH, Hogan LA, Jung BF, Kulick DI, Dworkin RH. Risk factors for chronic pain following breast cancer surgery: a prospective study. J Pain. 2006 Sep;7(9):626-34.</citation>
    <PMID>16942948</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mejdahl MK, Andersen KG, Gärtner R, Kroman N, Kehlet H. Persistent pain and sensory disturbances after treatment for breast cancer: six year nationwide follow-up study. BMJ. 2013 Apr 11;346:f1865. doi: 10.1136/bmj.f1865.</citation>
    <PMID>23580693</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kehlet H, Jensen TS, Woolf CJ. Persistent postsurgical pain: risk factors and prevention. Lancet. 2006 May 13;367(9522):1618-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16698416</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein SM, Bergh A, Steele SM, Georgiade GS, Greengrass RA. Thoracic paravertebral block for breast surgery. Anesth Analg. 2000 Jun;90(6):1402-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10825328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu CL, Raja SN. Treatment of acute postoperative pain. Lancet. 2011 Jun 25;377(9784):2215-25. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60245-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21704871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blanco R, Fajardo M, Parras Maldonado T. Ultrasound description of Pecs II (modified Pecs I): a novel approach to breast surgery. Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim. 2012 Nov;59(9):470-5. doi: 10.1016/j.redar.2012.07.003. Epub 2012 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22939099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gärtner R, Jensen MB, Nielsen J, Ewertz M, Kroman N, Kehlet H. Prevalence of and factors associated with persistent pain following breast cancer surgery. JAMA. 2009 Nov 11;302(18):1985-92. doi: 10.1001/jama.2009.1568. Erratum in: JAMA. 2012 Nov 21;308(19):1973.</citation>
    <PMID>19903919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dworkin RH, Turk DC, McDermott MP, Peirce-Sandner S, Burke LB, Cowan P, Farrar JT, Hertz S, Raja SN, Rappaport BA, Rauschkolb C, Sampaio C. Interpreting the clinical importance of group differences in chronic pain clinical trials: IMMPACT recommendations. Pain. 2009 Dec;146(3):238-44. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2009.08.019. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19836888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wijayasinghe N, Andersen KG, Kehlet H. Analgesic and Sensory Effects of the Pecs Local Anesthetic Block in Patients with Persistent Pain after Breast Cancer Surgery: A Pilot Study. Pain Pract. 2017 Feb;17(2):185-191. doi: 10.1111/papr.12423. Epub 2016 Feb 9.</citation>
    <PMID>26857336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 3, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

