<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03116022</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>62443916.5.0000.5440</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03116022</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Estriol at Distal Third of Vagina Improving Coital Pain in Post-menopause Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Use of Estriol at Distal Third of the Vaginal Wall Relieving Coital Pain in Women After Menopause: a Randomized, Blinded and Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hypoestrogenism leads to vaginal wall changes resulting in diminished vaginal lubrication
      and, consequently, causing pain during intercourse. Topical estrogen therapy (THT) may
      control this complaint. However, there are limitations on its use, especially in patients
      with breast cancer and diagnosed endometrial cancer. This randomized clinical trial aims to
      assess the impact of local estriol therapy in postmenopausal women complaining of coital pain
      and to assess serum concentrations of estriol in these women after estriol use.
      One-hundred-thirty-two women aged between 40 and 65 years will be randomized into three
      groups: Women using estriol 1 mg / 1g at the proximal third of vagina every other night -
      estriol proximal group (PEG), women in using estriol 1 mg / 1g at the distal third of the
      vagina every other night - estriol distal group (DEG), gel group (GG) using water-based
      during intercourse.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction The daily application of estrogen in the vagina can improve the hydrogen
      potential (pH), vaginal dryness, burning sensation, dyspareunia, and urinary symptoms.
      Dyspareunia is highly prevalent after menopause as well as in women after gynecological and
      breast cancer treatment. However, prescription of topical estrogen therapy (THT) to these
      women is still controversial, and they are allowed to use only moisturizing cream and vaginal
      lubricants.

      Studies have shown increased serum concentrations of estrogens (estradiol and estrone) after
      intravaginal suppository containing estradiol use. However, a cohort of 13,479 women treated
      for breast cancer, 271 received topical hormone therapy (THT), and no increased risk for
      recurrence was shown in this population.

      The main blood supplement to the vagina is mainly from vessels that irrigate proximal vaginal
      wall, a region where possibly the drug uptake is more intense. However, one study showed that
      the concentration of estradiol is similarly high regardless of whether the drug was applied
      to the proximal or distal wall of the vagina. Nevertheless, this study has not been
      replicated yet.

      THT promotes an improvement of coital pain when used in the proximal vagina, but a large
      population of women with clinical conditions such as thrombophilia and breast cancer cannot
      benefit from this resource. It is not known if the estriol applied in the distal vagina wall
      can lead to high serum levels of this hormone.

      OBJECTIVES This study aims to evaluate the impact of topic estriol therapy applied in distal
      vagina wall in coital pain, sexual function, and mood after estriol use. To evaluate serum
      level of this hormone after estriol use.

      METHODS Study design This is a prospective, blind, and randomized clinical trial including
      post-menopausal women complaining of pain during intercourse. The selected women will be
      randomized into three groups: estriol proximal group (PEG), estriol distal group (DEG), and
      gel group (GG). Participants and the assistance staff will not be blinded to the
      intervention.

      Sample Size The sample size was based on the estimated Cohen effect size. Assuming an effect
      size measure of 0.7 (considered large by Cohen) between groups, and considering a power test
      of 90% and a significance level of 5%, at least 44 subjects in each arm are required for a
      total of 132 participants.

      Randomization Randomization will be conducted in blocks of random sizes to generate the
      random allocation sequence. Participants will be randomized in 23 blocks and distributed in
      intervention groups according to their position in each block.

      Participants Sexually-active post-menopausal women between 40 to 65 years old complaining of
      coital pain will be invited to participate in this study. Sexual activity must include
      penis-vagina penetration.

      Hormonal profile evaluation Blood samples will be collected before the intervention to
      measure basal serum levels of fasting glucose, thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH),
      follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and serum estriol. These parameters will be applied in the
      12th week of intervention. The measurements of FSH, TSH, and estriol will be performed by
      chemiluminescence with IMMULITE® 2000 device (DPC IMMULITE® 2000 (Diagnostic Products
      Corporation, Los Angeles, California, United States of America (USA)). For the measurement of
      estriol free will be used IMMULITE® kit 2000 unconjugated estriol (SIEMENS, USA). The
      measurement of hormonal status will be held before the intervention (time 1) and at the end
      of the intervention (12 weeks). Glucose will be determined by automated spectrophotometry
      using the liquid enzymatic glycemia kit (Wiener Laboratory, 2000, Rosario, Argentina) Sexual
      function Sexual function will be evaluated with the Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI). It
      has 19 questions, with 6 subscales that assess desire, arousal, lubrication, orgasm,
      satisfaction, and pain. Each question is multiple choice and scored from 0 or 1 to 5. For
      calculation of the total score (range: 2 to 36), the score of each subscale was multiplied by
      a factor, and the 6 scores were summed. A lower score corresponds to a worse sexual function,
      and a score below 26.55 indicates sexual dysfunction.

      Emotional condition The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HAD) was used to assess mood.
      This scale has 14 items and two subscales, with 7 questions regarding anxiety (HAD-A) and 7
      regarding depression (HAD-D). There are four responses to each question (score of 0 to 3),
      and the sum of scores of each subscale provides a total score from 0 to 21. A cut-off score ≥
      9 for anxiety and depression characterizes the mental state of the woman.

      All questionnaires will be applied individually by a gynecologist before the intervention
      (time 1) and at the end of the intervention (12 weeks) when women attend to collect blood
      samples. Before applying the questionnaires, women will be informed about the content and
      objectives of the research, and will also be informed about the issue of confidentiality.

      Coital pain evaluation Coital pain will be assessed by the Analogic Visual Scale and the
      McGill Pain Questionnaire, a multi-dimensional tool that consists of 4 groups of constructs
      divided into 20 subgroups: Sensory-discriminative group (subgroups 1 to 10) relates to
      traction, heat, twist, among others; the motivational-affective group (subgroups 11 to 15)
      describes the affective dimension aspects of tension, as well as fear punishment, and
      neurovegetative responses; the descriptors of the cognitive component evaluation (subgroup
      16) allows the patient to express the overall assessment of the painful experience; subgroups
      17-20 comprise miscellaneous items. The subject can choose only one alternative for each
      subgroup, so the greater the number of most marked pain intensity descriptors, wherein the
      maximum score is 78. This questionnaire will be applied individually by a gynecologist at the
      beginning and at 12 weeks of intervention.

      INTERVENTION For the PEG group, women will receive professional guidance to use an applicator
      only 3 cm inside the vagina, once at night, each other night, while lying down to sleep, with
      a woman in the dorsal position inserting the applicator 3 cm through the vaginal introitus.
      For the DEG group, women will receive professional guidance to use an applicator totally
      inside the vagina. The application will be recommended once each other night, while lying
      down to sleep, with a woman in the dorsal position inserting the applicator 10 cm through the
      vaginal introitus. Lubricant will be acquired by the researcher in commercial form and should
      be used during sexual intercourse in the vagina introitus prior to penetration of the penis.

      Certification of correct use of prescription A researcher will contact the patient by
      telephone every two weeks to certify the proper use or any adverse symptoms related to the
      use of medication.

      ETHICAL ASPECTS This project was approved by the Institutional Ethics Committee in Research,
      and all women shall sign the Informed Consent. This project will be guided according to the
      ethical standards by Resolution 196/96 of the National Health Council on research with the
      human being.

      Statistical analysis Qualitative variables are described considering the absolute and
      relative frequencies, as quantitative variables are expressed by central position and
      dispersion measurements. The comparison between the study groups will be performed using the
      linear regression model of mixed effects; the model residue analysis will be representing
      through normal graphics. Cohen measure will be used as the size measure, which is expressed
      by the difference between the mean divided by the standard deviation. The Statistical
      Analysis System (SAS) will be used for data analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in pain score after estriol use</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of women with lower score of pain assessed by the McGill Pain Questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with risk for sexual dysfunction after estriol use</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison will be made between the total number of subjects with Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI) total score ≤ 26.55 before after estriol use</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with risk for anxiety after estriol use</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison will be made between the total number of subjects with Hospital Anxiety Scale total score ≥ 9 for anxiety after estriol treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with risk for depression after estriol use</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison will be made between the total number of subjects with Hospital Anxiety Scale total score ≥ 9 for anxiety after estriol treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of de degree of coital pain</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of women with lower degree of pain accessed by the Analogic Visual Scale graded from 0 to 10, with 0 being no pain and 10 being the maximum level of pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variation in serum levels of estriol after estriol use</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment of serum concentration of estriol at baseline and week 12.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of women with abnormal laboratory values of estriol after estriol use assessed by chemiluminescence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variation in serum levels of follicle-stimulating hormone after estriol use</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment of serum concentration of follicle-stimulating hormone at baseline and week 12.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of women with abnormal laboratory values of follicle-stimulating hormone after estriol use assessed by chemiluminescence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variation in serum levels of thyroid-stimulating hormone after estriol use</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment of serum concentration of thyroid-stimulating hormone at baseline and week 12.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of women with abnormal laboratory values of thyroid-stimulating hormone after estriol use assessed by chemiluminescence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events that are related to estriol use</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment of laboratory values at baseline and week 12. Adverse events assessed each 4 weeks from date of randomization until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 48 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Variation in serum levels of estriol, follicle-stimulating hormone, and thyroid-stimulating hormone will be performed by chemiluminescence. Adverse events will be assessed clinically by telephone</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variation in blood glucose after estriol use</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and on week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of women with abnormal laboratory values for blood glucose determined by the glucose oxidase-phenol (GOD-POD) method</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variation in weight after estriol use Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and on week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of women with weight gain after estriol use</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variation in body mass index (BMI) after estriol use</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline and on week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Number of women with modified BMI after estriol use</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">132</enrollment>
  <condition>Dyspareunia</condition>
  <condition>Menopause</condition>
  <condition>Sexual Dysfunction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>proximal estriol group (PEG )</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm is composed of women using estriol 1 mg / 1g in the proximal third of vagina every other night</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>distal estriol group (DEG)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm is composed of women using estriol 1 mg / 1g in the distal third of the vagina every other night</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group (CG)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm is composed of women using vaginal gel lubricant base water during intercourse</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Estriol</intervention_name>
    <description>Women using drug 1 mg / 1g in the proximal third of the vagina every other night for 12 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>proximal estriol group (PEG )</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PEG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Distal estriol</intervention_name>
    <description>Women using drug 1 mg / 1g at the distal third of the vagina every other night for 12 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>distal estriol group (DEG)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DEG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vaginal Gel</intervention_name>
    <description>Women using a base water gel lubricant during intercourse</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group (CG)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with a clinical diagnosis of menopause

          -  FSH&gt; 40 milli-International unit (mIU/ml)

          -  Having sex including penetration of penis into vagina

          -  Pain during penetration

          -  Active sexual partners

          -  Stable relationship.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous use of steroids in genital area in the last month

          -  Thromboembolism history

          -  Renal insufficiency

          -  Cholestatic jaundice

          -  Degenerative vulvar pathology

          -  Breast cancer

          -  Endometrial cancer

          -  Vulvar cancer

          -  Vaginal cancer history

          -  Prior radiotherapy to the genital region

          -  Smoking

          -  Acute urogenital infections

          -  Vulvovaginitis

          -  Urinary tract infection

          -  Genital herpes

          -  Genital prolapse grades II, III and IV by Baden Walker

          -  Systemic hormonal therapy in the last three months

          -  Use of antidepressants drugs

          -  Diabetes

          -  Thyroid disorder

          -  Cognitive restrictions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>lucia a Silva Lara, M.D, phD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto - Universidade de Sao Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sérgio H Pires Okano, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+5516988120532</phone>
    <email>sergio.okano@usp.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lucia A Silva Lara, M.D, phD</last_name>
    <phone>+551636021000</phone>
    <email>luciaalvess@yahoo.com.br</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital das Clínicas de Ribeirão Preto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ribeirão Preto</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>14049-900</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sergio Okano, MD</last_name>
      <phone>16988120532</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lovejoy TI, Turk DC, Morasco BJ. Evaluation of the psychometric properties of the revised short-form McGill Pain Questionnaire. J Pain. 2012 Dec;13(12):1250-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2012.09.011.</citation>
    <PMID>23182230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Varoli FK, Pedrazzi V. Adapted version of the McGill Pain Questionnaire to Brazilian Portuguese. Braz Dent J. 2006;17(4):328-35.</citation>
    <PMID>17262148</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Weisberg E, Ayton R, Darling G, Farrell E, Murkies A, O'Neill S, Kirkegard Y, Fraser IS. Endometrial and vaginal effects of low-dose estradiol delivered by vaginal ring or vaginal tablet. Climacteric. 2005 Mar;8(1):83-92.</citation>
    <PMID>15804736</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zigmond AS, Snaith RP. The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 1983 Jun;67(6):361-70.</citation>
    <PMID>6880820</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Resplande J, Gholami SS, Graziottin TM, Rogers R, Lin CS, Leng W, Lue TF. Long-term effect of ovariectomy and simulated birth trauma on the lower urinary tract of female rats. J Urol. 2002 Jul;168(1):323-30.</citation>
    <PMID>12050564</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rosen R, Brown C, Heiman J, Leiblum S, Meston C, Shabsigh R, Ferguson D, D'Agostino R Jr. The Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI): a multidimensional self-report instrument for the assessment of female sexual function. J Sex Marital Ther. 2000 Apr-Jun;26(2):191-208.</citation>
    <PMID>10782451</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Simon JA, Maamari RV. Ultra-low-dose vaginal estrogen tablets for the treatment of postmenopausal vaginal atrophy. Climacteric. 2013 Aug;16 Suppl 1:37-43. doi: 10.3109/13697137.2013.807606. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23848490</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Suckling J, Lethaby A, Kennedy R. Local oestrogen for vaginal atrophy in postmenopausal women. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2003;(4):CD001500. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2006;(4):CD001500.</citation>
    <PMID>14583935</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ting AY, Blacklock AD, Smith PG. Estrogen regulates vaginal sensory and autonomic nerve density in the rat. Biol Reprod. 2004 Oct;71(4):1397-404. Epub 2004 Jun 9.</citation>
    <PMID>15189832</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lara LA, Useche B, Ferriani RA, Reis RM, de Sá MF, de Freitas MM, Rosa e Silva JC, Rosa e Silva AC. The effects of hypoestrogenism on the vaginal wall: interference with the normal sexual response. J Sex Med. 2009 Jan;6(1):30-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1743-6109.2008.01052.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19170834</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 15, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 12, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lucia Alves da Silva Lara</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>M.D, Ph.D. Gynecology &amp; Obstetrics, Sexual Health.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>menopause</keyword>
  <keyword>sexual dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>coital pain</keyword>
  <keyword>vagina</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyspareunia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

