<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03118882</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pratica 2008.1405 Prot.1362</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03118882</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>STI.VI. Study: How to Improve Lifestyles in Screening Contexts</brief_title>
  <acronym>STIVI</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot RCT on Lifestyles Impact on Health Outcomes in the General Population Invited to Mammography and Colorectal Cancer Screening Programmes. (STI.li di VI.ta - Lifestyles) STI.VI.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centro di Riferimento per l'Epidemiologia e la Prev. Oncologica Piemonte</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Azienda Sanitaria Locale Torino 1</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centro di Riferimento per l'Epidemiologia e la Prev. Oncologica Piemonte</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main study objective is to determine the feasibility and impact (effectiveness) of
      intervention models for lifestyle changing (diet and physical activity) on health outcomes.
      Women 50 to 54-year-old attending the local breast cancer screening and 58-year-old people
      (both sexes) undergoing colorectal cancer screening are invited to participate in the study.
      Compliers are randomized into 3 intervention groups (Diet, Physical Activity, and Physical
      Activity and Diet) and into the 'usual care' Control group. Biological sampling (blood and
      saliva) is collected from all participants. All participants undergo also anthropometric
      measurements and fill in a self-administered validated questionnaire on their dietary and
      physical activity habits. All enrolled subjects receive a booklet with basic information
      about diet and physical activity. Subjects randomized to the 3 intervention groups are also
      offered one theoretical and three training courses. The courses are specifically designed for
      the different interventions proposed and aimed at reinforcing the educational counseling and
      at supporting behavioral changes.

      Follow-up is performed at 8 (intermediate follow-up) and 12-14 (final follow-up) months for
      repeating anthropometric measurements and questionnaire filling and blood sampling (at the
      final one).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study aims to evaluate the effectiveness of intervention models on diet and physical
      activity.

      The study randomizes eligible subjects into four groups: Diet group, Physical Activity group,
      Physical Activity and Diet group and &quot;Usual Care&quot; control group. To each group a specific
      intervention is delivered, consisting of counselling, informative material, and dedicated
      training.

      All participants (with the exception of the control group) receive a basic counselling by
      field experts. Afterwards they are offered an advanced training including more specific and
      detailed actions.

      An information booklet specifically developed for this study is distributed to all
      participants. The booklet contains general information on primary prevention, based on the
      most reliable and updated bibliographic sources on diet and physical exercise.

      Together with the letter of screening invitation eligible men and women receive the proposal
      to participate in the STI.VI. study. Participation to screening is not considered a
      prerequisite for study participation. A direct phone number and e-mail address are given for
      extra information.

      At the time of screening A screening receptionist asks people who received the STI.VI.
      invitation (identified through a flag) whether they are interested in the STI.VI. study and
      therefore refers them to the STI.VI. desk.

      At the STI.VI. desk, trained research assistants give further explanations and additional
      material (patient information sheet, informed consent form and the STI.VI. questionnaire). If
      informed consent is signed, an appointment is fixed for anthropometric measurements and for
      taking blood and saliva samples.

      People are asked to fill in the questionnaire and to hand it back at the time of the blood
      sampling.

      The STI.VI. questionnaire consists of 5 sections (physical activity, dietary habits, smoking
      habits, general health conditions, and general information) in order to collect baseline
      information on lifestyle habits. Type, amount and frequencies of dietary consumptions and
      physical activities are collected. The questionnaire also investigates the perception of
      one's own lifestyle and an motivation towards change.

      In this study phase all participants are randomly allocated to the 4 study groups.

      This is achieved through a permuted block design with block size of 12, 16, and 20 units
      width (W.F. Rosenberger, J. Lachin. Randomization in clinical trials: theory and practice.
      Wiley and sons, 2002, pag. 57). This method allows an almost complete uniform distribution of
      the randomisation groups in every moment of the study; this is necessary in order to simplify
      the subsequent courses management (see below). Participants are told about their group
      allocation at the time of biological sampling / anthropometric measurements, only.

      At baseline appointment.

      Participant subjects undergo anthropometric measurements. The following information are
      collected:

        -  Reproductive and eventual menopause history (women only)

        -  Eventual drug therapy under way,

        -  Height,

        -  Body composition,

        -  Waist circumference

        -  Arterial pressure. Then participants undergo blood drawing. Two types of blood samples
           are drawn: one for immediate biochemical analysis and another to be frozen. The freshly
           blood is used for instantaneous examinations for the following clinic-biochemical
           parameters: Insulin, Glucose, Total Cholesterol, LDL,HDL, Triglycerides, Minerals
           (Sodium, Potassium, Calcium, Iron), IGF-I, Testosterone, 17-ß-Estradiol, SHBG. These
           analyses are made for women invited to mammography screening while for people invited to
           colorectal screening supplemental tests are made also for vitamin D, 25 OH, PRC and high
           sensitive PRC.

      Cryopreserved blood samples are stored in a bio-bank for epigenetic, metabolomics and
      metabonomics analyses. Bio-banking includes a security system and a data base specifically
      implemented for samples storage and traceability.

      About 3 ml of saliva are also collected to investigate variations in genetic and metabolic
      parameters. Saliva samples are cryopreserved with the same modalities as blood samples.

      Immediately after biological sampling / anthropometric measurements a short counselling takes
      place. Trained counsellors answer all eventual questions on the study posed by participants
      and inform them on the next steps. They also deliver to all participants a basic booklet
      containing general information on primary prevention, based on the most reliable and updated
      bibliographic sources on diet and physical exercise (World Cancer Research Fund/American
      Institute for Cancer Research. Food, nutrition, physical activity, and the prevention of
      cancer: a global perspective. Washington, DC: AICR, 2007; WHO, Move for Health, 2002; EU
      Working Group &quot;Sport and Health&quot;, EU Physical Activity Guidelines, 2008).

      Follow-up phase

      Two follow-ups are planned:

      • Intermediate, after 8 months since biological sampling / anthropometric measurements (the
      exact date is reckoned calculating 6 months + the average intervention duration ± 2 weeks,
      for managing reasons): it consists of repeating anthropometric measurements and questionnaire
      filling, and counselling.

      All participants are contacted by letter and/or telephone, inviting them to contact the study
      secretariat in order to fix an appointment for repeating anthropometric measurements and
      questionnaire filling; during the follow-up visit trained counsellors verify participants'
      compliance with the provided recommendations, examine eventual encountered difficulties and
      provide support if needed.

      • Final, after 6 months from intermediate follow-up (i.e., after 14 months since biological
      sampling / anthropometric measurements): it consists of repeating anthropometric
      measurements, biological sampling, and questionnaire filling, and counselling.

      All participants are contacted by letter and/or telephone, inviting them to contact the study
      secretariat in order to fix an appointment for repeating once again anthropometric
      measurements, questionnaire filling and also biological sampling.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>feasibility outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <description>initial participation rate overall and stratified by intervention group, age, and gender;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>impact of intervention model</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <description>compliance to lifestyle recommendations and their maintenance assessed through the STI.VI. questionnaire;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>impact of intervention model</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <description>changes in anthropometric measurements</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>impact of intervention model</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <description>comparison of metabolic parameters (insulin, glucose, total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, HDL cholesterol, triglycerides, IGF-1, testosterone)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>impact of intervention model</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months</time_frame>
    <description>evaluation of potential genetic and/or metabolic biomarkers in cancer development;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>screening-related indicators</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 10 years after study end</time_frame>
    <description>screening participation rate in subjects enrolled in the STI.VI. study and, viceversa, STI.VI. participation rate in screened subjects;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>screening-related indicators</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 10 years after study end</time_frame>
    <description>evaluation of breast and colorectal screening outcomes among STI.VI. participants</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biobank implementation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 10 years after study end</time_frame>
    <description>number of blood sample and saliva sample cryopreserved at baseline and at final follow up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating biomarkers association with breast and colorectal cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 10 years after study end</time_frame>
    <description>investigate whether selected circulating miRNAs previously found associated to brast and colorectal risk are significantly altered in the plasma of cancer patients compared to matched healthy controls and if they satisfy pre-specified true- and false positive rates that are considered minimally acceptable in the screening setting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1270</enrollment>
  <condition>Lifestyle Risk Reduction</condition>
  <condition>Weight Changes, Body</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diet Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical activity group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical activity and diet group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Diet group</intervention_name>
    <description>A meeting where an expert illustrates the scientific basis of a proper diet. Moreover, clear and practical indications for dietary habits improvement and for suggested food purchase are provided. After having completed the basic module, participants are offered the opportunity of deepening the educational process through an advanced module:hree theoretical and practical cooking meetings (total of 10 hours) held by cooks with an expertise in natural cuisine and by trained dieticians.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diet Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical activity group</intervention_name>
    <description>A meeting where an expert illustrates the benefits of a constant PA. Moreover, indications are given on sport opportunities and walking groups in the city organised by public authorities. After having completed the basic module, participants are offered the opportunity of deepening the educational process through an advanced module: three theoretical and practical lessons (total of 10 hours) held by expert physical trainers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Physical activity group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical activity and diet group</intervention_name>
    <description>A meeting where the indications given to the previous groups are presented simultaneously. Particular attention is paid to the interaction between the two activities. After having completed the basic module, participants are offered the opportunity of deepening the educational process through an advanced module: four theoretical and practical meetings (total of 12 hours), two lessons focus on diet and two on PA.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Physical activity and diet group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  49 to 55-year-old women invited to mammography screening,

          -  58 to 61 year-old people (both sexes) invited to colorectal screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  psychiatric disorders,

          -  disabling disease

          -  life expectancy &lt;6 months

          -  eating or deambulation disorders

          -  in physiotherapy at the time of recruitment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>49 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>61 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nereo Segnan, MD MSc Epi</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Director</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>S.C.D.O. Epidemiologia dei Tumori - Azienda Ospedaliera S. Giovanni Battista di Torino</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <state>Piedmont</state>
        <zip>10123</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.aicr.org/assets/docs/pdf/reports/Second_Expert_Report.pdf</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/67447/1/WHO_NMH_NPH_WHD_02.13.pdf</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://ec.europa.eu/sport/library/policy_documents/eu-physical-activity-guidelines-2008_en.pdf</url>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>McBride CM, Emmons KM, Lipkus IM. Understanding the potential of teachable moments: the case of smoking cessation. Health Educ Res. 2003 Apr;18(2):156-70.</citation>
    <PMID>12729175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robb KA, Power E, Kralj-Hans I, Atkin WS, Wardle J. The impact of individually-tailored lifestyle advice in the colorectal cancer screening context: a randomised pilot study in North-West London. Prev Med. 2010 Dec;51(6):505-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2010.10.002. Epub 2010 Oct 13.</citation>
    <PMID>20950640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson AS, Mackison D, Boath C, Steele R. Promoting changes in diet and physical activity in breast and colorectal cancer screening settings: an unexplored opportunity for endorsing healthy behaviors. Cancer Prev Res (Phila). 2013 Mar;6(3):165-72. doi: 10.1158/1940-6207.CAPR-12-0385. Epub 2013 Jan 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23324132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Assfalg M, Bertini I, Colangiuli D, Luchinat C, Schäfer H, Schütz B, Spraul M. Evidence of different metabolic phenotypes in humans. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2008 Feb 5;105(5):1420-4. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0705685105. Epub 2008 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>18230739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steindorf K, Ritte R, Eomois PP, Lukanova A, Tjonneland A, Johnsen NF, Overvad K, Østergaard JN, Clavel-Chapelon F, Fournier A, Dossus L, Teucher B, Rohrmann S, Boeing H, Wientzek A, Trichopoulou A, Karapetyan T, Trichopoulos D, Masala G, Berrino F, Mattiello A, Tumino R, Ricceri F, Quirós JR, Travier N, Sánchez MJ, Navarro C, Ardanaz E, Amiano P, Bueno-de-Mesquita HB, van Duijnhoven F, Monninkhof E, May AM, Khaw KT, Wareham N, Key TJ, Travis RC, Borch KB, Sund M, Andersson A, Fedirko V, Rinaldi S, Romieu I, Wahrendorf J, Riboli E, Kaaks R. Physical activity and risk of breast cancer overall and by hormone receptor status: the European prospective investigation into cancer and nutrition. Int J Cancer. 2013 Apr 1;132(7):1667-78. doi: 10.1002/ijc.27778. Epub 2012 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>22903273</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 31, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 12, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centro di Riferimento per l'Epidemiologia e la Prev. Oncologica Piemonte</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nereo Segnan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, S.C. Epidemiologia, Screening e Registro Tumori Centre for Cancer Prevention, Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast cancer screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Colorectal Cancer screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Lifestyles</keyword>
  <keyword>Teachable moment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Body Weight Changes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

