<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03112486</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201700133</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03112486</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Out-of-hospital Cardiac Arrest (OHCA) Biomarkers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Predicting Neurological Outcome Following Out of Hospital Cardiac Arrest (OHCA) by Quantitative Measurement of Serial Serum Biomarkers of Brain Injury.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Few early prognostic indicators are currently available for patients' families and clinicians
      following out of hospital cardiac arrest (OHCA), and blood biomarkers may be of prognostic
      value in these cases. Brain tissue is highly dependent upon aerobic respiration, and oxygen
      deprivation result in irreversible neuronal cell injury. Peptides released into the blood by
      injured neuronal cells can be measured to estimate degree of injury, and potentially predict
      long term neurological outcome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aggressive treatment for patients with out-of-hospital cardiac arrest (OHCA) can result in
      return of spontaneous circulation (ROSC). However, prognosis for these patients remains poor,
      with low rates of survival to hospital admission and low rates of survival to hospital
      discharge. Furthermore, due to the exquisite sensitivity to hypoxic injury of neural tissue
      (dependent on aerobic respiration) relative to that of cardiac muscle, patients for whom ROSC
      can be obtained often suffer devastating neurological injury, with potential poor long-term
      neurological outcome. In some ischemic processes, for example, myocardial infarction, rapid
      measurement of cardiac biomarkers (e.g. Troponin isoform) is invaluable to current diagnosis
      and management. However, with regards to ischemic brain injury, there is currently no rapid,
      definitive diagnostic test to prognosticate outcome in OHCA. Biomarkers measurable in blood
      would have vital applications in prognosis and clinical research of neurological outcome in
      OHCA.

      Other groups have studied the neurological predictive values of biomarkers after OHCA. A
      variety of proteins including S100B, neuron-specific enolase, and G-FAP, co-peptin, Tau,
      neurofilament light/ heavy chain, and secretoneurin have been proposed as potential
      biomarkers of neurological outcome at OHCA. Unfortunately, many of these have been shown to
      have several drawbacks. For example, some lack specificity due to being released during
      resuscitation (e.g., S100B is found extracerebrally in muscle, adipocytes, and chondrocytes,
      creating a confounding factor in CA patients receiving chest compressions). Others have
      lacked sufficient sensitivity in the prognosticating of neurological outcome (ref).
      Furthermore, there is a paucity of human studies in cardiac arrest on newer biomarkers that
      have been studied in other acute brain injury disease processes that could potentially serve
      as candidate biomarkers predicting neurological outcome at post cardiac arrest hypoxic brain
      injuries. Biomarkers such as UCH-L1, SBDP, and MBP have not been studied in a OHCA cohort.

      The Investigator therefore propose a prospective, observational study in which the
      investigator will incorporate a minimally invasive and minimal risk measurement of blood
      biomarkers at time of ROSC. This would be done by drawing blood at ROSC (0-59mins), and
      additional blood draws at hours 6, 12, 18, 24, 48, 72, and on day 4, 5, and 6. The
      Investigator will then determine whether biomarker levels correlates with survival to
      hospital admission, survival to hospital discharge, and functional neurologic outcome at
      discharge and at 6 months. The Investigator intend to sample patients that present to the
      emergency department with non-CA chest pain in our study as well, which will allow us to draw
      stable inferences.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 26, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>In-hospital mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Higher blood biomarker levels will correlate with reduced rate of survival to hospital admission, survival to hospital discharge, and 6-month survival.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional neurological outcome at discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Higher blood biomarker levels will correlate with higher degree of neurological impairment as measured by Cerebral Performance Category.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional neurological outcome at 6 months after discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Higher blood biomarker levels will correlate with higher degree of neurological impairment as measured by Cerebral Performance Category.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of renal and liver disease on blood biomarker(s) level post-OHCA</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Renal and liver disease may affect levels of protein biomarkers after cardiac arrest</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Neurological Outcome</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Arrest</condition>
  <condition>Out-Of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest</condition>
  <condition>Brain Anoxia Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Hypoxia, Brain</condition>
  <condition>Hypoxia-Ischemia, Brain</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Arrest With Successful Resuscitation</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Arrest, Out-Of-Hospital</condition>
  <condition>Brain Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiac Arrest cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>adult patients (≥ 18 years of age) with non-traumatic out of hospital cardiac arrest</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>matched control population will include hemodynamically stable patients who present to the ED with chest pain that is not of cardiac etiology (non-traumatic chief complaints).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>blood draw</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood draws will be collected via venipuncture or IV at hours 0, 6, 12, 18, 24, 48, 72, 96, 120, 144 (10 draws total). Each draw would be approximately 20 mL of blood (but no less than 10 mL).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiac Arrest cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      blood biomarkers
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population will include all adult patients (≥ 18 years of age) with non-traumatic
        out of hospital cardiac arrest. Exclusions will include patients with advanced directives
        precluding resuscitation, traumatic cardiac arrest, and irreversible signs of death (e.g.
        rigor mortis). A matched control population will include hemodynamically stable patients
        who present to the ED with chest pain that is not of cardiac etiology (non-traumatic chief
        complaints). Blood draws in this cohort will be collected as per protocol and will end upon
        the termination of medical care or as per protocol - whichever is of the least duration.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - &gt;18 years old

        Study cohort:

          -  Non-traumatic out of hospital cardiac arrest

          -  Control cohort:

          -  Chest pain of non-cardiac etiology

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Both cohorts:

          -  Females of child bearing age with positive pregnancy test

          -  Neurodegenerative disease or other neurological disorder (dementia, Parkinson's
             disease, multiple sclerosis, seizure disorder, or brain tumours)

          -  History of neurosurgery within the last 30 days Acute brain injury within the last 30
             days (ischemic/ haemorrhagic stroke, traumatic brain injury) Subject is anemic OR
             donated blood within the last 8 weeks OR has a hematological disorder that requires
             transfusions Subject has history of liver failure OR renal failure

        Study cohort:

        Advanced directives against resuscitation Traumatic cardiac arrest In hospital cardiac
        arrest Failure to attain ROSC + visible signs of death (livor mortis, rigor mortis)

        Control cohort:

        EKG changes: New ST-elevation consistent with myocardial infarction NSTEMI Hemodynamically
        unstable
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph A Tyndall, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chairman Department Emergency Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joseph A Tyndall, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>352 672 3294</phone>
    <email>tyndall@ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univeristy of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Writing Group Members, Mozaffarian D, Benjamin EJ, Go AS, Arnett DK, Blaha MJ, Cushman M, Das SR, de Ferranti S, Després JP, Fullerton HJ, Howard VJ, Huffman MD, Isasi CR, Jiménez MC, Judd SE, Kissela BM, Lichtman JH, Lisabeth LD, Liu S, Mackey RH, Magid DJ, McGuire DK, Mohler ER 3rd, Moy CS, Muntner P, Mussolino ME, Nasir K, Neumar RW, Nichol G, Palaniappan L, Pandey DK, Reeves MJ, Rodriguez CJ, Rosamond W, Sorlie PD, Stein J, Towfighi A, Turan TN, Virani SS, Woo D, Yeh RW, Turner MB; American Heart Association Statistics Committee; Stroke Statistics Subcommittee. Heart Disease and Stroke Statistics-2016 Update: A Report From the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2016 Jan 26;133(4):e38-360. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000350. Epub 2015 Dec 16. Erratum in: Circulation. 2016 Apr 12;133(15):e599.</citation>
    <PMID>26673558</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sasson C, Hegg AJ, Macy M, Park A, Kellermann A, McNally B; CARES Surveillance Group. Prehospital termination of resuscitation in cases of refractory out-of-hospital cardiac arrest. JAMA. 2008 Sep 24;300(12):1432-8. doi: 10.1001/jama.300.12.1432.</citation>
    <PMID>18812534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan PS, McNally B, Tang F, Kellermann A; CARES Surveillance Group. Recent trends in survival from out-of-hospital cardiac arrest in the United States. Circulation. 2014 Nov 18;130(21):1876-82. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.114.009711.</citation>
    <PMID>25399396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neumar RW, Nolan JP, Adrie C, Aibiki M, Berg RA, Böttiger BW, Callaway C, Clark RS, Geocadin RG, Jauch EC, Kern KB, Laurent I, Longstreth WT Jr, Merchant RM, Morley P, Morrison LJ, Nadkarni V, Peberdy MA, Rivers EP, Rodriguez-Nunez A, Sellke FW, Spaulding C, Sunde K, Vanden Hoek T. Post-cardiac arrest syndrome: epidemiology, pathophysiology, treatment, and prognostication. A consensus statement from the International Liaison Committee on Resuscitation (American Heart Association, Australian and New Zealand Council on Resuscitation, European Resuscitation Council, Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada, InterAmerican Heart Foundation, Resuscitation Council of Asia, and the Resuscitation Council of Southern Africa); the American Heart Association Emergency Cardiovascular Care Committee; the Council on Cardiovascular Surgery and Anesthesia; the Council on Cardiopulmonary, Perioperative, and Critical Care; the Council on Clinical Cardiology; and the Stroke Council. Circulation. 2008 Dec 2;118(23):2452-83. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.108.190652. Epub 2008 Oct 23.</citation>
    <PMID>18948368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laver S, Farrow C, Turner D, Nolan J. Mode of death after admission to an intensive care unit following cardiac arrest. Intensive Care Med. 2004 Nov;30(11):2126-8. Epub 2004 Sep 9.</citation>
    <PMID>15365608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moulaert VR, Verbunt JA, van Heugten CM, Wade DT. Cognitive impairments in survivors of out-of-hospital cardiac arrest: a systematic review. Resuscitation. 2009 Mar;80(3):297-305. doi: 10.1016/j.resuscitation.2008.10.034. Epub 2008 Dec 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19117659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lim C, Verfaellie M, Schnyer D, Lafleche G, Alexander MP. Recovery, long-term cognitive outcome and quality of life following out-of-hospital cardiac arrest. J Rehabil Med. 2014 Jul;46(7):691-7. doi: 10.2340/16501977-1816.</citation>
    <PMID>24849762</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsson IM, Wallin E, Rubertsson S, Kristofferzon ML. Health-related quality of life improves during the first six months after cardiac arrest and hypothermia treatment. Resuscitation. 2014 Feb;85(2):215-20. doi: 10.1016/j.resuscitation.2013.09.017. Epub 2013 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24096198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pusswald G, Fertl E, Faltl M, Auff E. Neurological rehabilitation of severely disabled cardiac arrest survivors. Part II. Life situation of patients and families after treatment. Resuscitation. 2000 Nov;47(3):241-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11114453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandroni C, Cavallaro F, Callaway CW, Sanna T, D'Arrigo S, Kuiper M, Della Marca G, Nolan JP. Predictors of poor neurological outcome in adult comatose survivors of cardiac arrest: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Part 1: patients not treated with therapeutic hypothermia. Resuscitation. 2013 Oct;84(10):1310-23. doi: 10.1016/j.resuscitation.2013.05.013. Epub 2013 Jun 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23811182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandroni C, Cavallaro F, Callaway CW, D'Arrigo S, Sanna T, Kuiper MA, Biancone M, Della Marca G, Farcomeni A, Nolan JP. Predictors of poor neurological outcome in adult comatose survivors of cardiac arrest: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Part 2: Patients treated with therapeutic hypothermia. Resuscitation. 2013 Oct;84(10):1324-38. doi: 10.1016/j.resuscitation.2013.06.020. Epub 2013 Jul 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23831242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandroni C, Geocadin RG. Neurological prognostication after cardiac arrest. Curr Opin Crit Care. 2015 Jun;21(3):209-14. doi: 10.1097/MCC.0000000000000202. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25922894</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perkins GD, Jacobs IG, Nadkarni VM, Berg RA, Bhanji F, Biarent D, Bossaert LL, Brett SJ, Chamberlain D, de Caen AR, Deakin CD, Finn JC, Gräsner JT, Hazinski MF, Iwami T, Koster RW, Lim SH, Huei-Ming Ma M, McNally BF, Morley PT, Morrison LJ, Monsieurs KG, Montgomery W, Nichol G, Okada K, Eng Hock Ong M, Travers AH, Nolan JP; Utstein Collaborators. Cardiac arrest and cardiopulmonary resuscitation outcome reports: update of the Utstein Resuscitation Registry Templates for Out-of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest: a statement for healthcare professionals from a task force of the International Liaison Committee on Resuscitation (American Heart Association, European Resuscitation Council, Australian and New Zealand Council on Resuscitation, Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada, InterAmerican Heart Foundation, Resuscitation Council of Southern Africa, Resuscitation Council of Asia); and the American Heart Association Emergency Cardiovascular Care Committee and the Council on Cardiopulmonary, Critical Care, Perioperative and Resuscitation. Circulation. 2015 Sep 29;132(13):1286-300. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000144. Epub 2014 Nov 11. Erratum in: Circulation. 2015 Sep 29;132(13):e168-9.</citation>
    <PMID>25391522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>out-of-hospital cardiac arrest</keyword>
  <keyword>neurological outcome</keyword>
  <keyword>prognostication</keyword>
  <keyword>cerebral performance category</keyword>
  <keyword>hypoxic-ischemic brain injury</keyword>
  <keyword>biomarkers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Out-of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia, Brain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia-Ischemia, Brain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

