<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03110614</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F121120003</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23HL133438-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03110614</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diastolic Dysfunction and Pauci-inflammatory Acute Exacerbations of COPD</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diastolic Dysfunction and Pauci-inflammatory Acute Exacerbations of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alabama at Birmingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective study to determine the relationships between pauci-inflammatory
      exacerbations and diastolic dysfunction, and their implications in hospitalized patients with
      acute exacerbations of COPD. To assess changes within subjects from stable to acute phase, a
      number of comparisons will be made in subjects enrolled during acute exacerbation with
      similar measurements made in the stable phase after recovery from exacerbation after at least
      35 days from index hospitalization or prior exacerbation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Informed consent will be obtained within the first 24 hours of admission. Written informed
      consent will be obtained from the subject or a legally authorized representative.

      Visit Schedule:

      V1 (Day 0 of Hospitalization):

      Demographic and clinical information including age, gender, race, smoking status, number of
      pack-years of smoking, body mass index, waist hip circumference, co-morbidities such as
      diabetes mellitus, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, depression, coronary artery disease and
      chronic kidney disease, history of previous exacerbations, detailed occupation history, and
      detailed medication history with emphasis on cardiovascular medications will be conducted.
      The COPD Assessment Test (CAT) questionnaire and the modified Medical Research Council (mMRC)
      assessment will be administered. Bed-side spirometry will be conducted. Blood will be drawn
      for lab tests (about 30 mL or 6 teaspoons). Electrocardiography (ECG), lung ultrasound and
      echocardiography will be performed.

      V2 (hospital discharge day or day 3 of hospitalization whichever is earlier):

      Blood will be drawn for lab test- CRP only ( about 5mL or 1 teaspoon). Participant will be
      scheduled for a follow-up visit at the Lung Health Center.

      V3 (Day 35- Follow-up visit at Lung Health Center):

      The COPD Assessment Test (CAT) questionnaire and the modified Medical Research Council (mMRC)
      assessment will be administered. The following Pulmonary Function Tests will be conducted:
      Spirometry, lung Volumes and DLCO. Six-minute walk test will be conducted. Blood will be
      drawn for lab tests (about 30 mL or 6 teaspoons). Electrocardiography, lung ultrasound and
      echocardiography will be performed.

      Telephone follow-up: The participant will be called once every 6 months for one year, to ask
      about COPD symptoms.

      Description of procedures:

      Questionnaires:

      Dyspnea: will be assessed using the modified Medical Research Council (mMRC). The mMRC scale
      is a simple grading system to assess a patient's level of dyspnea, ranging from 0 for minimal
      to 4 for severe dyspnea.

      COPD related Quality of life: will be assessed using the COPD Assessment Test (CAT) The CAT
      questionnaire consists of 8 simple questions which are graded from 0 to 5. The total score
      can range from 0 to 40. A change of 2 units is considered clinically significant (minimal
      clinically important difference).

      Pulmonary Function Tests (PFTs):

      Bedside spirometry will be performed using a handheld spirometer, and the following
      parameters will be recorded: forced expiratory volume in the first second (FEV1), forced
      vital capacity (FVC), FEV1/FVC ratio , forced expiratory flow in the middle 25 to 75% of flow
      (FEF25-75%), inspiratory capacity (IC), and peak expiratory flow rate (PEFR). A subsequent
      full set of pulmonary function tests will be obtained in the recovery phase on day 35 using a
      hand held spirometer and body plethysmography. This will include FEV1 , FVC, FEV1/FVC,
      FEF25-75%, IC, PEFR, total lung capacity (TLC), residual volume (RV), and diffusing capacity
      of carbon monoxide (DLCO).

      Blood: will be collected to measure markers of systemic inflammation such as C-reactive
      protein (CRP), fibrinogen, IL-6 and TNF-alpha, and measures of cardiac function such as
      troponin and brain natriuretic peptide (BNP).

      Six-Minute Walk Test: The 6 minute walk test measures the mean distance walked on a 100 meter
      straight, hard-surfaced coarse in 6 minutes while being continuously monitored by the study
      coordinator.

      Ultrasound of lungs: B mode ultrasonography will be used to assess pulmonary congestion.

      Echocardiography: Parameters of systolic and diastolic function will be assessed using 2D and
      Doppler echocardiography using standard echo windows.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 25, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in the proportion of diastolic dysfunction in pauci-inflammatory exacerbations vs. inflammatory exacerbations</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (at time of hospitalization)</time_frame>
    <description>We will estimate the frequency of diastolic dysfunction on echocardiogram in exacerbations that are pauci-inflammatory vs. inflammatory at the time of enrollment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of exacerbations</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year post hospitalization</time_frame>
    <description>Number of exacerbations in the year following index admission between those with and without diastolic dysfunction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in COPD Assessment Test (CAT) in those with and without diastolic dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>at or after 35 days post hospitalization</time_frame>
    <description>The CAT questionnaire consists of 8 simple questions which are graded from 0 to 5. The total score can range from 0 to 40. This measure will be compared between those with and without diastolic dysfunction at the follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in dyspnea using the modified Medical Research Council (mMRC) scale</measure>
    <time_frame>at or after 35 days post hospitalization</time_frame>
    <description>Dyspnea will be assessed using the modified Medical Research Council (mMRC) scale, ranging from 0 for minimal to 4 for severe dyspnea. We will also assess dyspnea using the more sensitive San Diego Shortness Of Breath Questionnaire (SOBQ), which rates dyspnea associated with activities of daily living (range 0 to 120). These measures will be compared between those with and without diastolic dysfunction at the follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in dyspnea using the San Diego Shortness of Breath Questionnaire (SOBQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>at or after 35 days post hospitalization</time_frame>
    <description>Dyspnea will be assessed using the San Diego Shortness Of Breath Questionnaire (SOBQ), which rates dyspnea associated with activities of daily living (range 0 to 120). These measures will be compared between those with and without diastolic dysfunction at the follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in 6-minute walk distance</measure>
    <time_frame>at or after 35 days post hospitalization.</time_frame>
    <description>This measure of exercise capacity will be compared between those with and without diastolic dysfunction at the follow-up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">188</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Diastolic Dysfunction</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood and Exhaled breath condensate for inflammatory markers.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Hospitalized patients with acute exacerbations of COPD will be approached for participation
        in the study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients age 18 and older

          -  Patients admitted to the general medicine or pulmonary floors, or the medical
             intensive care unit with a primary diagnosis of acute exacerbation of COPD will be
             eligible for the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a secondary diagnosis of congestive heart failure and other respiratory
             conditions that the investigator's deem could confound the diagnosis including but not
             limited to pneumonia, bronchiectasis and lung cancer will be excluded.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women will be excluded.

          -  Patients with conditions that preclude an adequate echocardiogram such as
             hemodynamically significant arrhythmias will also be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Surya P Bhatt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Surya P Bhatt, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(205) 934-5555</phone>
    <email>sbhatt@uabmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UAB Lung Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mark T Dransfield, MD</last_name>
      <phone>205-934-5555</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark T Dransfield, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 15, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 6, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alabama at Birmingham</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Surya P Bhatt</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>COPD</keyword>
  <keyword>acute</keyword>
  <keyword>exacerbation</keyword>
  <keyword>lung ultrasound</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

