<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03118388</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R34MH082804-01A2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03118388</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Engaging Homeless Youth in Vocational Training to Meet Their Mental Health Needs</brief_title>
  <acronym>SEI</acronym>
  <official_title>Engaging Homeless Youth in Vocational Training to Meet Their Mental Health Needs</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Arizona State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Arizona State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized controlled trial (RCT) compared the efficacy between the Social Enterprise
      Intervention (SEI) and Individual Placement and Support (IPS) with homeless youth with mental
      illness.

      Methods: Non-probability quota sampling sampling was used to recruit 72 homeless youth from
      one agency, who were randomized to the SEI (n=36) or IPS (n=36) conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In response to the limited use of RCTs with homeless youth to test research-supported
      interventions, this study compares the efficacy and short-term outcomes of two interventions
      that combine employment and clinical services with homeless youth experiencing mental
      illness. The Social Enterprise Intervention (SEI) is a research-supported intervention using
      a group approach that engages homeless youth in paid employment as well as case-management
      and mental health services through involvement in an agency-run social enterprise. The
      Individual Placement and Support (IPS) model of supported employment is an individually
      focused, evidence-based intervention , which provides individuals with severe mental illness
      with customized, long-term, and integrated vocational, case-management, and clinical services
      to help them gain and maintain competitive employment.

      A randomized comparative efficacy trial of the short-term, nonvocational outcomes
      (depression, self-esteem, social support, housing stability) of the SEI and IPS was conducted
      over 20 months with 72 homeless youth at a homeless youth drop-in center in Los Angeles. This
      study answered two research questions: 1) Do homeless youth with mental illness participating
      in an employment intervention integrated with clinical services (SEI or IPS) experience
      improvements in their a) mental health status (self-esteem and depression); b) housing
      stability, and c) social support; and 2) What are the differences between the SEI and IPS
      groups on mental health, housing stability, and social support outcomes between baseline and
      follow-up?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 18, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The SEI model was implemented in four stages: 1) Vocational skill acquisition (4 months); 2) Small business skill acquisition (4 months); 3) SEI formation and product distribution (12 months); and 4) Clinical/case-management services, (ongoing for 20 months). The eight IPS principles were implemented over 20 months by an employment specialist, clinician, and case manager.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depression between baseline and follow-up (using the Adult Self-Report)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Depression was assessed using the Adult Self-Report (ASR) DSM-Oriented Scale for Depressive Problems, consisting of 14 items that measure related emotions and behaviors (Achenbach, 1997). Scoring profiles used normed scales for adults ages 18-35. Higher scores reflected a higher presence of emotions and behaviors. For men, raw scores between 10 and 12 (11 and 13 for women) were within the borderline clinical range, whereas scores 13 and greater (14 and greater for women) were considered in the clinical range.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in social support between baseline and follow-up (using the Adult Self-Report)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Social support was a composite-score variable of the sum of four items on the ASR Friends Subscale. The response categories for each item range from none to 5 or more for questions including: &quot;About how many close friends do you have?&quot; The range of scores is from 0 to 12, with higher scores indicating greater social support for the youth.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in housing stability status between baseline and follow-up (using a 3-item self-report measure of housing status)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Youth were asked at 20 months about their housing status (i.e., whether they had lived on the streets, in a shelter or institution [i.e., youth or adult shelter, or detention facility, jail, or prison], or in a private residence with family [i.e., biological or foster], relatives, friends, a partner, roommate or alone). Each item was dichotomous and scored as 0 = no or 1 = yes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in self-esteem between baseline and follow-up (using the Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-esteem was measured using the Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale (RSE; Rosenberg, 1979), a 10-question assessment of feelings about self-worth. Each item is rated using a 4-point Likert-type scale ranging from strongly disagree to strongly agree. Five items are recoded so that higher scores indicate higher levels of self-esteem. The possible range of RSE raw scores is 0 to 30. Scores between 15 and 25 are within normal range, whereas scores below 15 suggest low self-esteem.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Mental Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Mental Health</condition>
  <condition>Employment</condition>
  <condition>Housing Problems</condition>
  <condition>Social Support</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>36 SEI youth</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>36 homeless youth (ages 16-24) randomized to the SEI intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>36 IPS youth</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>36 homeless youth (ages 16-24) randomized to the IPS intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Social Enterprise Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The SEI model was implemented in four stages: 1) Vocational skill acquisition (4 months); 2) Small business skill acquisition (4 months); 3) SEI formation and product distribution (12 months); and 4) Clinical/case-management services, (ongoing for 20 months).</description>
    <arm_group_label>36 SEI youth</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SEI</other_name>
    <other_name>social enterprise</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IPS</intervention_name>
    <description>To implement the IPS at the host agency, one employment specialist, two case managers, and two clinicians were assigned the 22 available IPS cases among them at baseline. Over the 20 months, all IPS participants met individually with the employment specialist, one case manager, and one clinician at least weekly. Regarding job development in the community, the IPS employment specialist also spent about 40% of each week out in the community building relationships with new and existing employers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>36 IPS youth</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Individual Placement and Support</other_name>
    <other_name>supported employment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 16-24

          -  English speaking

          -  Primary clinical diagnosis in the past year (with at least one symptom in the past 4
             weeks) using the DISC-Y interview for one of six mental illnesses (i.e., Major
             Depressive Episode, Mania/ Hypomania, Generalized Anxiety, Post-traumatic Stress
             Disorder, Conduct Disorder, and Alcohol/Substance Use Disorders

          -  Desire to work.

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 6, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Arizona State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kristin Ferguson-Colvin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

