<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03119779</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CEBD-CU-2014-09-15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03119779</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Pulpotomy Using TheraCal Versus MTA on Survival Rate of Cariously-Exposed Vital Permanent Molars</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Pulpotomy (Partial or Complete) Using Resin-Modified Calcium Silicate Versus MTA-Anglus on Survival Rate of Cariously-Exposed Vital Young Permanent Molars:A Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      To assess which is the most efficient pulpotomy medicament on tooth survival in patients with
      a cariously-exposed vital young permanent molar regarding: absence of postoperative pain,
      sinus or swelling, internal/ external root resorption, periapical radiolucency), root
      maturation and decrease chair side time of treated patient.

      Trial design Randomized Clinical Trial (RCT), double-blinded with parallel group and
      allocation ratio (1:1), equivalence framework.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Preoperative records will be taken (photos, conventional periapical radiographs, and
      impression to construct acrylic stent to help standardization on follow up apical
      radiographs). Administration of inferior alveolar nerve block then using rubber dam isolation
      one of the investigators will remove the caries using large round but under copious amount of
      coolant and if carious exposure occur, part of the pulp chamber will be removed using sharp
      spoon excavator. Then the pulp status will be assessed if bleeding is controlled with direct
      irrigation with distilled water for 2 minutes then next step will be taken but if not
      continue excavation of the pulp till bleeding is controlled. if bleeding is not controlled
      after performing complete pulpotomy, tooth will be excluded from the study Then direct
      application of capping materials (TheraCal or MTA) according to manufacturer instructions,
      then Riva self-cure glass-ionomer base and composite resin final restoration. One of the
      investigators will take immediate standardized postoperative periapical radiographs.
      Follow-up will be for 12 months. Pre-calibrated blinded dentists will assess out comes
      separately.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 30, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>absence of any complication or complementary treatment (absence of spontaneous pain or swelling)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>periapical radiolucency</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>presence or absence of periapical radiolucency radiographically</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>internal/ external root resorption</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>presence or absence of internal/ external root resorption radiographically</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Root maturation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Root maturation assessment radiographically</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time lapse till final restoration performed</measure>
    <time_frame>from 5 till 20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>measured using stop watch to assess which material needs less chair side time to be finished.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Caries, Dental</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TheraCal vital pulp therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Using rubber dam isolation we will remove the caries using large round but under copious amount of coolant and if carious exposure occur, part of the pulp chamber will be removed using sharp spoon excavator. After complete removal of the caries and control of bleeding, then direct application of incremental layers of TheraCal using the tip of the syringe container of the material and each layer should not exceed 1 mm then light curing each increment. Then Riva self-cure glass-ionomer base and composite resin final restoration. We will take immediate standardized postoperative periapical radiographs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MTA vital pulp therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Using rubber dam isolation we will remove the caries using large round but under copious amount of coolant and if carious exposure occur, part of the pulp chamber will be removed using sharp spoon excavator. After complete removal of the caries and control of bleeding, then direct application of freshly mixed MTA-Anglus on sterile glass slap. MTA application then gentle condensation over wet cotton till MTA thickness is about 2-3 mm thickness and removal of excess material from walls of pulp chamber. Application of wet cotton for 15 min. to achieve initial setting of MTA. Then Riva self-cure glass-ionomer base and composite resin final restoration. We will take immediate standardized postoperative periapical radiographs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MTA-Anglus</intervention_name>
    <description>MTA-Anglus freshly mixed according to manufacturer instructions over glass slap and applied to pulp stump and application of wet cotton for 15 min. till initial setting occur.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MTA vital pulp therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MTA-Anglus vital pulp therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TheraCal</intervention_name>
    <description>TheraCal directly applied from the syringe container tip to pulp stump over incremental layers each layer should not exceed 1 mm thickness and each layer will be light cured for 20 sec.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TheraCal vital pulp therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TheraCal vital pulp therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Restorable permanent molars with deep caries and pain could be relieved with
             analgesics

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  criteria of exclusion of teeth were:

               -  pathological mobility, swelling or tenderness to percussion/palpation;

               -  pathology is shown in the pre-operative radiographic as resorption periradicular
                  or furcation radiolucency, or a widened periodontal ligament space;

               -  at the operative procedure, hemorrhage control is unachievable
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>9 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Passant Nagi, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assisternt lecturer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 14, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Passant Nagy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pulpotomy</keyword>
  <keyword>deep caries</keyword>
  <keyword>permanent molars</keyword>
  <keyword>MTA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dental Caries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

