<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03111810</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>212634</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03111810</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Targeting Iatrogenic Cushing's Syndrome With 11β-hydroxysteroid Dehydrogenase Type 1 Inhibition</brief_title>
  <acronym>TICSI</acronym>
  <official_title>Targeting Iatrogenic Cushing's Syndrome With 11β-hydroxysteroid Dehydrogenase Type 1 Inhibition (TICSI)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Currently, 2-3% of the population of the United Kingdom and United States of America receive
      glucocorticoid therapy. Significant adverse effects are not confined to chronic use;
      recurrent short-course administration is associated with increased morbidity and mortality.
      The adverse metabolic features associated with glucocorticoid use include obesity, skeletal
      muscle myopathy, hypertension, insulin resistance and diabetes and are collectively termed
      'iatrogenic Cushing's syndrome'. The efficacy of glucocorticoid therapy is not in doubt, but
      there are no interventions to reduce their metabolic consequences. Within metabolic tissues
      (liver, skeletal muscle, adipose), 11β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase type 1 (11β-HSD1)
      regenerates active glucocorticoid and therefore is able to tightly control the availability
      of glucocorticoids to activate the glucocorticoid receptor. In preclinical studies, the
      investigators have shown that 11β-HSD1 is critical in regulating the development of the
      adverse features associated with circulating glucocorticoid excess, endorsing our
      observations in a patient with Cushing's disease, who was protected from a classical
      phenotype due to a functional deficit in 11β-HSD1.

      This study is the first clinical evaluation of the impact of the selective 11β-HSD1
      inhibitor, AZD4017, in healthy volunteers taking exogenous glucocorticoids (prednisolone).
      The investigators propose that in tissues expressing high levels of 11β-HSD1, prednisolone
      action will be amplified, driving adverse effects within these tissues and have hypothesized
      that AZD4017 in humans will reduce the adverse metabolic consequences of Prednisolone
      administration without compromise to its anti-inflammatory action.

      Our specific research objectives are:

        1. To demonstrate the beneficial effect of the selective 11β-HSD1 inhibitor, AZD4017, upon
           the prednisolone-induced deterioration in metabolic phenotype, including glucose
           disposal and endogenous glucose production rates.

        2. To determine the impact of AZD4017 on the anti-inflammatory actions of Prednisolone.

        3. To identify the tissue-specific (skeletal muscle, adipose) mechanisms underpinning the
           response to Prednisolone therapy administered in conjunction with AZD4017.

      The investigators will perform a randomized, double-blind placebo controlled study to
      determine if co-administration of the selective 11β-HSD1 inhibitor, AZD4017, limits the
      adverse effects of short-course exogenous glucocorticoid administration. 32 healthy male
      volunteers will have detailed metabolic investigations including 2-step hyperinsulinaemic
      euglycaemic clamps (with stable isotope measurements of lipid and carbohydrate metabolism),
      as well as assessment of skeletal muscle forearm glucose uptake. All volunteers will then be
      treated with Prednisolone (20mg daily) and randomized to the co-administration of placebo or
      AZD4017. After 1 week of therapy, all investigations will be repeated. Our hypothesis is that
      the adverse metabolic effects of Prednisolone will be reduced by co-administration of
      AZD4017.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 25, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the detrimental side effects of prednisolone by AZD4017.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate whether AZD4017 can limit the detrimental effect of prednisolone (20mg) on glucose disposal. This will be achieved by measuring glucose disposal during a hyperinsulinaemic euglycaemic clamp.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in hepatic insulin sensitivity by AZD4017 when given with prednisolone (20mg) compared to prednisolone (20mg) given alone.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of endogenous glucose production rate during a hyperinsulinaemic euglycaemic clamp.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in blood pressure associated with prednisolone and AZD4017 administration</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The participants will have 24h ambulatory blood pressure measurements taken.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in adipose tissue gene expression profile associated with prednisolone and AZD4017 administration.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Gene expression changes will be measured from adipose tissue biopsies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in whole body oxidation associated with prednisolone and AZD4017 administration</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of incorporation of carbon-13 into breath carbon dioxide using Gas chromatography combustion isotope ratio mass spectrometry.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in skeletal muscle gene expression profile associated with prednisolone and AZD4017 administration.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Gene expression changes measured in skeletal muscle biopsies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in circulating inflammatory cytokines and inflammatory response in circulating inflammatory cells associated with prednisolone and AZD4017 administration.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of inflammatory cytokines, isolation of peripheral blood mononuclear cells and defining their response to inflammatory stress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in bone turnover associated with prednisolone and AZD4017 administration.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of serum and urine markers of bone turnover including type I collagen cross-linked N-telopeptide and osteocalcin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in body composition (total and regional lean and fat mass) associated with prednisolone and AZD4017 administration.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of total and regional lean and fat mass on dual energy x-ray absorptiometry scan.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in urinary steroid metabolite profile associated with prednisolone and AZD4017 administration.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Steroid metabolites measured by gas chromatography, mass spectrometry in a timed overnight urine sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Iatrogenic Cushing's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prednisolone 20mg once daily and AZD4017 400mg twice daily for 7 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Oral Tablet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prednisolone 20mg once daily and placebo twice daily for 7 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AZD4017 and prednisolone</intervention_name>
    <description>The drug AZD4017 will be given together with prednisolone 20mg daily for 7 days to compare its effects on metabolic tissues against the placebo arm where the participants will take placebo and prednisolone 20mg daily for 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>11 beta-Hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase inhibitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Oral Tablet and prednisolone</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo Oral tablet will be given together with prednisolone 20mg daily for 7 days to compare the effects on metabolic tissues of AZD4017 and prednisolone 20mg daily against the placebo arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Oral Tablet</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The following criteria apply to both arms and each volunteer who has a successful screening
        visit will be randomized to one of the arms defined above (see section 6): We estimate that
        we will need to screen 40-50 patients in order to achieve our recruitment target.

          -  Male volunteers without diabetes (HbA1C &lt; 48mmol/mol at screening)

          -  BMI 20-30kg/m2

          -  Age 18-60years

          -  For individuals identified from Oxford Biobank - fasting insulin and / or glucose and
             / or insulin resistance as measured by Homeostatic model assessment (HOMA) - insulin
             resistance in the 40th-60th percentile

          -  BP&lt;160/100 mmHg with stable antihypertensive therapy for &gt;3 months

          -  Stable lipid lowering therapy for &gt;3 months

          -  No contraindications to AZD4017 or prednisolone treatment Study participants who are
             sexually active with a female partner of childbearing potential must be surgically
             sterilized, practicing true abstinence (when this is in line with the preferred and
             usual lifestyle of the subject. Periodic abstinence, e.g. calendar, ovulation,
             symptothermal, post-ovulation methods, declaration of abstinence for the duration of a
             trial, and withdrawal are not acceptable methods of contraception) or agree, along
             with their partners, to use two forms of highly effective methods of birth control
             (i.e. condom plus another highly effective method defined below), and not rely on
             barrier methods and spermicide alone, from the time of screening and for the duration
             of the study. For the proposed clinical study, all study subjects will be male.

        For male study subjects whose partner is pregnant, or whose partner is a woman of
        child-bearing potential (WOCBP) who is established on and continuing to use a highly
        effective method of contraception, in addition to the stipulations above, males should
        continue to use a condom (in addition to the highly effective method) for 1 week following
        the last dose of study drug (5 drug elimination half-lives rounded up to 1 week).

        For male study subjects whose partner is not pregnant but is a WOCBP who is not established
        on and continuing to use a highly effective method of contraception, males should continue
        to use a condom (in addition to the highly effective method) for 3 weeks following the last
        dose of study drug (5 drug elimination half-lives plus 2 weeks).

        Male study participants must also not donate sperm from the time of screening until 3 weeks
        after final dose of study drug (5 drug elimination half-lives plus 2 weeks).

        Highly effective methods of contraception are defined as combined (estrogen and progestogen
        containing) hormonal contraception associated with inhibition of ovulation (either oral,
        intravaginal or transdermal), progestogen-only hormonal contraception associated with
        inhibition of ovulation (either oral [specifically Cerazette™], injectable or implantable),
        intrauterine device (IUD), intrauterine hormone-releasing system (IUS), bilateral tubal
        occlusion, vasectomized partner or sexual abstinence.

        We would advise that competitive elite athletes do not take part in the study as there is
        the possibility that the prednisolone could impact upon their athletic performance

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The participant may not enter the study if any of the following apply:

          -  Age &lt;18 or &gt;60years

          -  Body mass index &lt;20 or &gt;30kg/m2

          -  A diagnosis of diabetes (type 1 or type 2)

          -  A blood haemoglobin &lt;120mg/dL

          -  Haemorrhagic disorders

          -  Anticoagulant treatment

          -  Renal impairment with estimated Glomerular Filtration Rate &lt;60ml/min

          -  Abnormal liver chemistry with aspartate aminotransferase, alanine transaminase and/or
             Gamma-glutamyltransferase and/or bilirubin more than the upper limit of normal

          -  Glucocorticoid therapy (including inhaled, topical or oral) within the last 6 months

          -  Concomitant anti-inflammatory medication including NSAIDs, disease modifying
             anti-rheumatic drugs (DMARDs) / steroid-sparing medications (e.g. methotrexate,
             sulphasalazine, hydroxychloroquine, azathioprine, leflunomide, biologics [anti-Tumor
             necrosis factor alpha, interleukin-1ra]).

          -  Any medical condition in the opinion of the investigator that might impact upon safety
             or validity of the results - recent (within 2 weeks) or active infection, known liver
             disease, known thyroid disease, active malignancy, existing inflammatory condition
             (e.g. inflammatory arthropathy, inflammatory bowel disease, autoimmune disease,
             connective tissue disease)

          -  Current evidence of alcohol abuse or a significant history of alcohol abuse, as judged
             by the investigator.

          -  Contraindication to any of the study treatments or known or suspected hypersensitivity
             to the investigational product, compounds of the same class, other study treatments or
             any excipients.

          -  Unwilling, or unable, to give informed consent.

          -  Participation in another investigational medicinal product trial / study within the
             past 6 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jeremy W Tomlinson, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>44(0)1865 857359</phone>
    <email>jeremy.tomlinson@ocdem.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nadia Othonos, MB ChB</last_name>
    <phone>44(0)1865 857359</phone>
    <email>nantia.othonos@ocdem.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Oxford</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeremy W Tomlinson, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>44(0)1865 857359</phone>
      <email>jeremy.tomlinson@ocdem.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nadia Othonos, MD</last_name>
      <email>Nantia.Othonos@ocdem.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Staa TP, Leufkens HG, Abenhaim L, Begaud B, Zhang B, Cooper C. Use of oral corticosteroids in the United Kingdom. QJM. 2000 Feb;93(2):105-11.</citation>
    <PMID>10700481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Overman RA, Yeh JY, Deal CL. Prevalence of oral glucocorticoid usage in the United States: a general population perspective. Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken). 2013 Feb;65(2):294-8. doi: 10.1002/acr.21796.</citation>
    <PMID>22807233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gathercole LL, Lavery GG, Morgan SA, Cooper MS, Sinclair AJ, Tomlinson JW, Stewart PM. 11β-Hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 1: translational and therapeutic aspects. Endocr Rev. 2013 Aug;34(4):525-55. doi: 10.1210/er.2012-1050. Epub 2013 Apr 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23612224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morgan SA, McCabe EL, Gathercole LL, Hassan-Smith ZK, Larner DP, Bujalska IJ, Stewart PM, Tomlinson JW, Lavery GG. 11β-HSD1 is the major regulator of the tissue-specific effects of circulating glucocorticoid excess. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2014 Jun 17;111(24):E2482-91. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1323681111. Epub 2014 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24889609</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tomlinson JW, Draper N, Mackie J, Johnson AP, Holder G, Wood P, Stewart PM. Absence of Cushingoid phenotype in a patient with Cushing's disease due to defective cortisone to cortisol conversion. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2002 Jan;87(1):57-62.</citation>
    <PMID>11788623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott JS, Bowker SS, Deschoolmeester J, Gerhardt S, Hargreaves D, Kilgour E, Lloyd A, Mayers RM, McCoull W, Newcombe NJ, Ogg D, Packer MJ, Rees A, Revill J, Schofield P, Selmi N, Swales JG, Whittamore PR. Discovery of a potent, selective, and orally bioavailable acidic 11β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase type 1 (11β-HSD1) inhibitor: discovery of 2-[(3S)-1-[5-(cyclohexylcarbamoyl)-6-propylsulfanylpyridin-2-yl]-3-piperidyl]acet ic acid (AZD4017). J Med Chem. 2012 Jun 28;55(12):5951-64. doi: 10.1021/jm300592r. Epub 2012 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22691057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hazlehurst JM, Gathercole LL, Nasiri M, Armstrong MJ, Borrows S, Yu J, Wagenmakers AJ, Stewart PM, Tomlinson JW. Glucocorticoids fail to cause insulin resistance in human subcutaneous adipose tissue in vivo. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2013 Apr;98(4):1631-40. doi: 10.1210/jc.2012-3523. Epub 2013 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23426618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tripathy D, Daniele G, Fiorentino TV, Perez-Cadena Z, Chavez-Velasquez A, Kamath S, Fanti P, Jenkinson C, Andreozzi F, Federici M, Gastaldelli A, Defronzo RA, Folli F. Pioglitazone improves glucose metabolism and modulates skeletal muscle TIMP-3-TACE dyad in type 2 diabetes mellitus: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, mechanistic study. Diabetologia. 2013 Oct;56(10):2153-63. doi: 10.1007/s00125-013-2976-z. Epub 2013 Jun 30.</citation>
    <PMID>23811853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Corticosteroids</keyword>
  <keyword>Prednisolone</keyword>
  <keyword>11 beta-Hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase1 inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Iatrogenic Cushing's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>AZD4017</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cushing Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pituitary ACTH Hypersecretion</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>ACTH-Secreting Pituitary Adenoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methylprednisolone Hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone hemisuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisolone phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niacinamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

