<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01238133</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2011-03813</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2011-03813</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CDR0000687152</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>OSU-OH007</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2010C0043</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>OSU 10011</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>8518</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016058</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U01CA076576</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01238133</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gamma-Secretase/Notch Signalling Pathway Inhibitor RO4929097, Paclitaxel, and Carboplatin Before Surgery in Treating Patients With Stage II or Stage III Triple-Negative Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study of Neoadjuvant Chemotherapy With the Gamma Secretase Inhibitor RO4929097 in Combination With Paclitaxel and Carboplatin in Patients With Clinical Stage II-III Triple Negative Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and the best dose of gamma-secretase inhibitor
      RO4929097 when given together with paclitaxel and carboplatin in patients with stage II or
      stage III triple-negative breast cancer. Gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 may stop the
      growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth. Drugs use in
      chemotherapy, such as paclitaxel and carboplatin, work in different ways to stop the growth
      of tumor cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from dividing, or by stopping
      them from spreading. Giving gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 together with paclitaxel and
      carboplatin before surgery may make the tumor smaller and reduce the amount of normal tissue
      that needs to be removed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the maximum-tolerated dose (MTD) and dose limiting toxicity (DLT) of
      RO4929097 (gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097) given 3 days on, 4 days off in combination
      with weekly paclitaxel and every 3 weeks carboplatin that will not cause a 30% or more
      decrease in paclitaxel area under the plasma-concentration time curve (AUC)0-24hr on day 15
      compared to day -1 in patients with clinical stage II-III triple negative breast cancer
      (TNBC).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To measure real-time pharmacokinetics of RO4929097 when administered in combination with
      weekly paclitaxel and every 3 weeks carboplatin in patients with stage II-III TNBC.

      II. To measure real-time pharmacokinetics of paclitaxel when administered in combination with
      RO4929097 (3 days on, 4 days off) and every 3 weeks carboplatin in patients with stage II-III
      TNBC.

      III. To evaluate the rate of pathologic and clinical complete response to the treatment with
      combination of RO492097, paclitaxel, and carboplatin in patients with clinical stage II-III
      TNBC.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of gamma secretase inhibitor RO4929097 (RO4929097).

      Patients receive gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-3,
      8-10, and 15-17, paclitaxel intravenously (IV) over 60 minutes on days 1, 8, and 15 (day -1
      of course one), and carboplatin IV over 60 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days
      for 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Within 4 weeks
      after completion of neoadjuvant therapy, patients undergo definitive breast surgery.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 1 year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events of gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 as assessed by CTCAE v 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MTD of gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 based on DLT as assessed by CTCAE version (v) 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis will consist of descriptive statistics only. Frequency will be computed for discrete variables with 95% confidence intervals for the proportion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters of gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 and paclitaxel</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, at 30, 55, 70 and 90 minutes, and 2, 3, 4, 6, 8 and 24 hours of days 1, 8, 15, and 17 of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>AUC0-24hrs, clearance, maximum concentration, and maximum time (for gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 only) when each drug is administered alone versus when they are co-administered will be compared. Only descriptive statistics will be provided.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Estrogen Receptor Negative</condition>
  <condition>HER2/Neu Negative</condition>
  <condition>Progesterone Receptor Negative</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIA Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Triple-Negative Breast Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (RO4929097, paclitaxel, carboplatin, surgery)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive gamma-secretase inhibitor RO4929097 PO QD on days 1-3, 8-10, and 15-17, paclitaxel IV over 60 minutes on days 1, 8, and 15 (day -1 of course one), and carboplatin IV over 60 minutes on day 1. Treatment repeats every 21 days for 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Within 4 weeks after completion of neoadjuvant therapy, patients undergo definitive breast surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (RO4929097, paclitaxel, carboplatin, surgery)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blastocarb</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatin Hexal</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatino</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosin</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosol</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbotec</other_name>
    <other_name>CBDCA</other_name>
    <other_name>Displata</other_name>
    <other_name>Ercar</other_name>
    <other_name>JM-8</other_name>
    <other_name>Nealorin</other_name>
    <other_name>Novoplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatine</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinwas</other_name>
    <other_name>Ribocarbo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gamma-Secretase Inhibitor RO4929097</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (RO4929097, paclitaxel, carboplatin, surgery)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RO4929097</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (RO4929097, paclitaxel, carboplatin, surgery)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (RO4929097, paclitaxel, carboplatin, surgery)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anzatax</other_name>
    <other_name>Asotax</other_name>
    <other_name>Bristaxol</other_name>
    <other_name>Praxel</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxol</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxol Konzentrat</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological Study</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (RO4929097, paclitaxel, carboplatin, surgery)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Therapeutic Conventional Surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (RO4929097, paclitaxel, carboplatin, surgery)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The patients must have histologically confirmed breast cancer that is human epidermal
             growth factor receptor 2 (Her-2) negative (immunohistochemistry [IHC] 0-1+ patients
             are eligible without fluorescence in situ hybridization [FISH]; IHC2+ patients are
             eligible with negative FISH; if FISH only is done HER2/chromosome enumeration probe
             [CEP]17 &lt; 2.0); the invasive tumor must be hormone receptor negative defined as both
             estrogen receptor and progesterone receptor IHC staining present in less than 10% of
             invasive cancer cells

          -  Eligible patients must have clinical stage II-III breast cancer; patients with
             inflammatory breast cancer are not eligible

          -  Patients must have clinically or radiographically measurable primary breast tumor that
             measures &gt;= 2.0 cm

          -  No prior treatment including radiation therapy, chemotherapy or biotherapy for the
             currently diagnosed breast cancer is allowed

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 1 (Karnofsky &gt; 80%)

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             &lt; 2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

          -  Creatinine &lt; 1.5 X institutional upper limit of normal OR creatinine clearance &gt;= 60
             mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

          -  Women of childbearing potential and men must use two forms of contraception (i.e.,
             barrier contraception and one other method of contraception) at least 4 weeks prior to
             study entry, for the duration of study participation, and for at least 12 months
             post-treatment; should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while she or
             her partner are participating in this study and for 12 months after study
             participation, the patient should inform the treating physician immediately

          -  Pregnancy testing; women of childbearing potential are required to have a negative
             serum pregnancy test (with a sensitivity of at least 25 mIU/mL) within 10-14 days and
             within 24 hours prior to the first dose of RO4929097 (serum or urine); a pregnancy
             test (serum or urine) will be administered every 4 weeks if their menstrual cycles are
             regular or every 2 weeks if their cycles are irregular while on study within the
             24-hour period prior to the administration of RO4929097; a positive urine test must be
             confirmed by a serum pregnancy test; prior to dispensing RO4929097, the investigator
             must confirm and document the patient's use of two contraceptive methods, dates of
             negative pregnancy test, and confirm the patient's understanding of the teratogenic
             potential of RO4929097

          -  Female patients of childbearing potential are defined as follows:

               -  Patients with regular menses

               -  Patients, after menarche with amenorrhea, irregular cycles, or using a
                  contraceptive method that precludes withdrawal bleeding

               -  Women who have had tubal ligation

          -  Female patients may be considered to NOT be of childbearing potential for the
             following reasons:

               -  The patient has undergone total abdominal hysterectomy with bilateral
                  salpingo-oophorectomy or bilateral oophorectomy

               -  The patient is medically confirmed to be menopausal (no menstrual period) for 24
                  consecutive months

          -  Ability to swallow pills

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Patients with inflammatory breast cancer are not eligible

          -  Prior history of invasive breast cancer treated with systemic chemotherapy (patients
             with a history of ductal carcinoma in situ [DCIS] and lobular carcinoma in situ [LCIS]
             are eligible)

          -  Other malignancies unless the patient is considered to be disease-free for 5 or more
             years prior to study registration; patients with the following cancers are eligible if
             diagnosed and treated within the past 5 years: carcinoma in situ of the cervix,
             carcinoma in situ of the colon, melanoma in situ, and basal and squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to RO4929097 or other agents used in the study

          -  Patients taking medications with narrow therapeutic indices that are metabolized by
             cytochrome P450 (CYP450), including warfarin sodium (Coumadin) are ineligible

          -  Preclinical studies indicate that RO4929097 is a substrate of cytochrome P450, family
             3, subfamily A, polypeptide 4 (CYP3A4) and inducer of CYP3A4 enzyme activity; caution
             should be exercised when dosing RO4929097 concurrently with CYP3A4 substrates,
             inducers, and/or inhibitors; furthermore, patients who are taking concurrent
             medications that are strong inducers/inhibitors or substrates of CYP3A4 should be
             switched to alternative medications to minimize any potential risk; if such patients
             cannot be switched to alternative medications, they will be ineligible to participate
             in this study

          -  Preclinical studies indicate that RO4929097 is a substrate of cytochrome P450, family
             2, subfamily C, polypeptide 8 (CYP2C8) and inducer of CYP2C8 enzyme activity; caution
             should be exercised when dosing RO4929097 concurrently with CYP2C8 substrates,
             inducers, and/or inhibitors; furthermore, patients who are taking concurrent
             medications that are strong inducers/inhibitors or substrates of CYP2C8 should be
             switched to alternative medications to minimize any potential risk; if such patients
             cannot be switched to alternative medications, they will be ineligible to participate
             in this study

          -  Patients with malabsorption syndrome or other condition that would interfere with
             intestinal absorption; patients must be able to swallow tablets

          -  Patients who are serologically positive for hepatitis A, B or C, or have a history of
             liver disease, other forms of hepatitis or cirrhosis are ineligible

          -  Uncontrolled electrolyte abnormalities including hypocalcemia, hypomagnesemia,and
             hypokalemia; symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, and a
             history of torsades de pointes or other significant cardiac arrhythmias

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated with RO4929097

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients on combination antiretroviral
             therapy are ineligible

          -  Cardiovascular: baseline corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 450 msec in males or QTc &gt; 470
             msec in females

          -  A requirement for antiarrhythmics or other medications known to prolong QTc

          -  Patients who have not recovered to &lt; Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events
             (CTCAE) grade 2 toxicities related to prior therapy are not eligible to participate in
             this study

          -  Peripheral neuropathy of grade 2 or higher
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ewa Mrozek</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 9, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 9, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 10, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 3, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 3, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 4, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triple Negative Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

