<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01237652</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ESA 5971</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01237652</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Perioperative Myocardial Ischemia in Isolated Systolic Hypertension</brief_title>
  <acronym>PROMISE</acronym>
  <official_title>Perioperative Myocardial Ischemia in Isolated Systolic Hypertension (PROMISE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Heart and Stroke Foundation of Ontario</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      During or after surgery, patients may suffer heart attacks or other heart complications,
      increasing the hospital stay by 11 days on average and costing an estimated US$20 billion in
      1990.Many risk factors have been identified but there are no properly conducted studies to
      look at Blood pressure (BP) as a risk factor around the time of surgery. The investigators
      believe there is a good possibility that systolic BP (SBP) is a risk factor but currently
      unrecognized. When measuring BP, two numbers are obtained. The upper number is called SBP and
      a lower number called diastolic BP (DBP). If the numbers are high, this means that the
      patient has a high BP or hypertension. If the SBP is high while DBP is normal, it is called
      isolated systolic hypertension (ISH)&gt; ISH is increasingly recognized as a major risk factor
      for heart problems. The relationship between ISH and heart complications around the time of
      surgery is poorly understood. Previous studies did not look at such a relationship. Because
      of that, there are no guidelines for ISH management at the time of surgery. Generally, these
      patients go through surgery as if they have no increased risk. Studies are starting to show
      that the bulk of these heart complications happen in patients thought to have low risk
      factors not yet identified, including ISH.

      The investigators believe that the oxygen supply to the heart can be compromised around the
      time of surgery in ISH patients Chemicals known as stress hormones are secreted around the
      time of surgery, increasing oxygen needs in the heart and may make the oxygen supply to the
      heart muscle critical (know as myocardial ischemia). This in turn may result in a heart
      attack and death. Studies have shown that patients with myocardial ischemia stand a 9-fold
      increase in odds ratio of suffering a heart attack, worsening of angina, or death.

      This study aims to compare the incidence of myocardial ischemia in patients with ISH and
      normal BP patients around the time of surgery using a special heart monitor. In addition, the
      study aims to determine the prevalence of ISH among surgical patients and to document
      complications like heart attacks, heart failure, stroke and death after surgery.

      This research project will be conducted at the Ottawa Hospital by a multi-disciplinary
      research group (perioperative research group)which includes anesthesiology, cardiology,
      general surgery and epidemiology. The research group secured HSFO funding for this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ethics approval is already obtained. Consented patients will be screened for ISH in the
      pre-surgical clinic, utilizing BP automated machine. Patients with ISH or normal diastolic
      function (control group) will be enrolled. During and after surgery, they will be monitored
      for changes consistent with myocardial ischemia. A special heart monitor, called ambulatory
      ECG monitor (Holter monitor), will be used to record, document and count any episodes of
      myocardial ischemia. A designated research coordinator will be assigned to the study for the
      recruitment, screening, daily tracking and data collection. The heart monitoring for each
      patient in the study will be reviewed by the research group. Data will be collected and
      analysed.

      This is the first study looking exclusively at ISH as a risk factor around the time of
      surgery. Studies suggest that investigators may be labelling surgical patients at risk of a
      heart attack as &quot;low risk&quot; when in fact the bulk of those heart attacks are in patients
      labeled &quot;low risk&quot;. The finding that ISH patients have a higher incidence of myocardial
      ischemia will provide evidence for the next level of research. If ISH is in fact a risk
      factor for heart attacks around the time of surgery, the investigators will identify a group
      of patients in whom the investigators can lower this risk by instituting appropriate
      management.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of perioperative myocardial ischemia in ISH patients</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours postop</time_frame>
    <description>To determine if the incidence of perioperative myocardial ischemia in ISH patients is triple that of normotensive patients admitted for non-cardiac surgery, as determined by 48-hour ambulatory ST segment ECG monitoring.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of ISH Patients admitted for non-cardiac surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the proportion of patients admitted for non-cardiac surgery with treated and untreated Isolated Systolic Hypertension, normotension, and systemic hypertension with diastolic elevation;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the demographics of patients admitted for non-cardiac surgery with Isolated Systolic Hypertension</measure>
    <time_frame>day of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Demographics include age, diabetes, ASA status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the overall incidence of perioperative MI, Cardiovascular death, cardiac arrests, or CVA in RCRI Class I or II patients admitted for non cardiac surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Outcomes and complications data are collected from the day of surgery until discharge from hospital.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">312</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ISH and normotensive</arm_group_label>
    <description>This is a prospective cohort study to compare the incidence of perioperative myocardial ischemia between ISH and normotensive patients admitted for elective non-cardiac surgery. To reduce the number of confounding factors for perioperative myocardial ischemia, RCRI Class I or II patients will be recruited.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ISH, Normotensive</arm_group_label>
    <description>This is a prospective cohort study to compare the incidence of perioperative myocardial ischemia between ISH and normotensive patients admitted for elective non-cardiac surgery. To reduce the number of confounding factors for perioperative myocardial ischemia, RCRI Class I or II patients will be recruited.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Perioperative ISH and normotensive presenting for Non-cardiac surgery
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 45 years

          -  ISH or normotensive (as per Patient Recruitment and Informed Consent section)

          -  Elective non cardiac surgical procedure

          -  Expected to stay in hospital ≥ 48 hours

          -  Revised cardiac risk index (RCRI) ≤ 251

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Atrial fibrillation

          -  Left bundle branch block (LBBB)

          -  Myocardial infarction &lt; 3 months

          -  Decompensated congestive heart failure

          -  Unstable coronary syndrome

          -  Dialysis

          -  Emergency surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ashraf Fayad, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ottawa Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y 4E9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 13, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 9, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 9, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Ashraf Fayad</name_title>
    <organization>The Ottawa Hospita, University of Ottawa</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Isolated Systolic Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Perioperative Myocardial Ischemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Perioperative Cardiovascular adverse events</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

