<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00785967</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MK0518-048-00, Version 2.2</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HC-TPD Control # 120132</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00785967</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immune Responses in Patients Treated With Raltegravir</brief_title>
  <acronym>RAG-1/2</acronym>
  <official_title>Immune Responses to Neo-Antigens in Patients Treated With Raltegravir: Insights on V(D)J Recombination and RAG-1/2 Recombinase Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McGill University Health Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McGill University Health Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hypothesis: Treatment with raltegravir does not alter V(D)J recombination or immune responses
      to neoantigens.

      A process known as V(D)J recombination is essential for developing lymphocytes and the
      specific functioning of the immune system. Raltegravir is the first approved drug of the new
      integrase inhibitor class of anti-HIV drugs. Integrase inhibitors have been shown in some
      studies to interfere with DNA cleavage and the activities of RAG-1/2. These studies suggest a
      potential to affect aspects of both B-cell and T-cell development, therefore, it is important
      to evaluate the potential effects that integrase inhibitors may have in clinical use. If
      immunoglobulin and T-cell receptor genes are altered by HIV integrase, then patient
      lymphocytes will fail to display normal responses to vaccinations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      V(D)J recombination is essential for developing lymphocytes and the specific functioning of
      the immune system. Germline gene coding segments become rearranged to create functional
      immunoglobulin and T-cell receptor genes by this recombination. The process depends on
      site-specific cleavage of chromosomal DNA by RAG-1 and RAG-2 recombinase. Two
      recombination-activating gene proteins (RAG-1/2) in conjunction make up a complex of enzymes
      that join gene segments of B-cell and T-cell receptor genes. RAG-1 contains most of the V(D)J
      recombinase active site and RAG-2 is essential in joining DNA segments during V(D)J
      recombination. RAG-1/2 have similarity in action to other DNA transposases and HIV-1
      integrase. These similarities suggest that HIV-1 integrase inhibitors may have the potential
      to affect aspects of both B-cell and T-cell development.

      Induction of primary immune responses to neoantigens involves the generation of specific
      T-cells and immunoglobulin M (IgM) antibody secreting B-cells. As part of this process, T and
      B memory cells are also generated, which have specific cell surface receptors to the antigen.
      On repeat exposure to the antigen, these memory T- and B-cells are triggered to generate
      rapid and intense secondary responses. During this secondary response, B-cells secrete
      abundant specific IgG antibodies with greater affinity to the antigen than for the IgM
      isotope. This memory response is mediated by T-cells with CD45+ RO+ phenotype. These T-cells
      provide B-cells the help required to generate the specific IgG. Sub-optimal antibody
      responses are seen in both acquired and hereditary immunodeficiency, which are due to
      impaired T-cell function including poor T-helper responses to B-cells and defective
      neo-antigen responses.

      An established method to evaluate T-cell function involves testing antibody production to
      vaccination with phiX174, a stable bacteriophage of E. Coli that is critical in demonstrating
      T-cell competence. Antibody titers after primary and secondary immunization correlate with
      abnormal CD4 cell help. Patients with functional B-cells that lack T-cell help show a
      characteristic failure to switch from IgM to IgG, making this assay essential in the
      evaluation of V(D)J recombination.

      Currently, raltegravir is the only approved integrase inhibitor that targets the integration
      stage of the HIV-1 lifecycle. The clinical manifestations of raltegravir-related potential
      adverse effects on V(D)J recombination may be so rare that they may only be observed after
      large numbers of patients are exposed to this drug. Evaluating the direct in vivo interaction
      of HIV integrase inhibitors on RAG-1/2 is difficult, therefore the best approach may be to
      evaluate the potential negative effects on recombinase activity downstream by studying immune
      function. If gene rearrangements of immunoglobulin and T-cell receptor genes are altered by
      HIV integrase, then patient lymphocytes will fail to display normal responses to neo-antigen
      exposure. Since untreated HIV-infected individuals have an impaired ability to respond to new
      antigens, it is difficult to evaluate the responses to neo-antigens in these individuals.
      Therefore, to test this hypothesis, it would be best to choose patients with long-term
      control of HIV that have recovered immune function.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Unexpected and severe difficulties in recruitment.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of patients with phiX174 IgG greater than or equal to 30% of total anti-phiX174 titers</measure>
    <time_frame>Two weeks after fourth phiX174 immunization</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total phiX174 antibody titers</measure>
    <time_frame>2 and 4 weeks after each immunization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>raltegravir 400mg bid + Truvada 1 tab qd</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>efavirenz 600mg qhs + Truvada 1 tab qd (or Atripla 1 tab qhs)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Various vaccines</intervention_name>
    <description>VAQTA: 1.0ml IM at weeks 24 &amp; 48; Pneumovax 23: 0.5ml IM at screening; Td ADSORBED: 0.5ml IM at screening; phiX174 bacteriophage: 0.02ml/kg body weight IV at weeks 28, 32, 36, 40.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VAQTA;</other_name>
    <other_name>Pneumovax 23;</other_name>
    <other_name>Td ADSORBED;</other_name>
    <other_name>phiX174 bacteriophage</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. HIV-1 infected males, as determined by ELISA and Western blot;

          2. &gt;18 years of age;

          3. Current ARV therapy with efavirenz + Truvada® for &gt;52 weeks;

          4. HIV-1 RNA (bDNA) &lt;50 copies/ml for at least 52 weeks;

          5. No history of hepatitis A vaccine, and HAV antibody negative.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. any immunomodulatory therapy within 24 weeks of screening or during the trial;

          2. any type of vaccine within 24 weeks of screening or during the trial;

          3. current opportunistic infection, malignancy, acute infection, or febrile illness;

          4. history of hypersensitivity to a vaccine, components of a vaccine, or components of a
             vaccine container.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christos M Tsoukas, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McGill University Health Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Immune Deficiency Treatment Centre, Montreal General Hospital, McGill University Health Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3G 1A4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melek M, Jones JM, O'Dea MH, Pais G, Burke TR Jr, Pommier Y, Neamati N, Gellert M. Effect of HIV integrase inhibitors on the RAG1/2 recombinase. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2002 Jan 8;99(1):134-7. Epub 2001 Dec 26.</citation>
    <PMID>11756686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 4, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 5, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>McGill University Health Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chris Tsoukas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Division of Allergy &amp; CLinical Immunology, MUHC</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>V(D)J recombination; RAG-1/2 recombinase function</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Raltegravir Potassium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heptavalent Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

