<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00789776</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2230.00</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2010-00106</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2230.00</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P01CA078902</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00789776</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fludarabine Phosphate, Cyclophosphamide, Total-Body Irradiation, and Donor Bone Marrow Transplant Followed by Donor Natural Killer Cell Therapy, Mycophenolate Mofetil, and Tacrolimus in Treating Patients With Hematologic Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of Adding a Single Prophylactic Donor Lymphocyte Infusion (DLI) of Natural Killer Cells Early After Nonmyeloablative, HLA-Haploidentical Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation - A Multi Center Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Wayne D. Kuni and Joan E. Kuni Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies the side effects and best dose of donor natural killer (NK)
      cell therapy and to see how well it works when given together with fludarabine phosphate,
      cyclophosphamide, total-body irradiation, donor bone marrow transplant, mycophenolate
      mofetil, and tacrolimus in treating patients with hematologic cancer. Giving chemotherapy,
      such as fludarabine phosphate and cyclophosphamide, and total-body irradiation before a donor
      bone marrow transplant helps stop the growth of cancer cells. It may also stop the patient's
      immune system from rejecting the donor's stem cells. When the healthy stem cells from a donor
      are infused into the patient they may help the patient's bone marrow make stem cells, red
      blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets. Giving an infusion of the donor's T cells
      (donor lymphocyte infusion) may help the patient's immune system see any remaining cancer
      cells as not belonging in the patient's body and destroy them (called graft-versus-tumor
      effect). Sometimes the transplanted cells from a donor can make an immune response against
      the body's normal cells. Giving mycophenolate mofetil and tacrolimus after the transplant may
      stop this from happening.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Identification of the maximal feasible dose of NK cells that can be infused one week after
      nonmyeloablative, human leukocyte antigen (HLA)-haploidentical hematopoietic cell transplant
      (HCT). (Phase I)

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      Once the maximal feasible dose has been identified, accrual will be limited to the cohort
      containing this cell dose to determine:

      I. Incidence of relapse. (Phase II)

      II. Incidence of grades III-IV acute graft-versus-host disease (GVHD). (Phase II)

      III. Incidence of non-relapse mortality. (Phase II)

      OUTLINE: This is a phase I, dose-escalation study of donor NK cell therapy followed by a
      phase II study.

      CONDITIONING: Patients receive fludarabine intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes on days -6 to
      -2 and cyclophosphamide IV over 1 hour on days -6 and -5. Patients undergo total-body
      irradiation on day -1.

      DONOR BONE MARROW TRANSPLANTATION: Patients undergo donor bone marrow transplantation on day
      0.

      POST-TRANSPLANTATION IMMUNOSUPPRESSION: Patients receive cyclophosphamide IV over 1 hour on
      day 3 and mycophenolate mofetil orally (PO) thrice daily (TID) on days 4 to 40, followed by a
      taper until day 84 in the absence of GVHD. Patients also receive tacrolimus IV continuously
      or IV once daily (QD) over 1-2 hours or PO twice daily (BID) on days 4 to 84, followed by a
      taper until day 180 in the absence of GVHD.

      DONOR NK CELL INFUSION: Patients undergo donor lymphocyte infusion of NK cells on day 7.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 6 months, 1 year, 1.5 years,
      and then every year thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 13, 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 18, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 18, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-limiting toxicity (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 35 (28 days after NK cell infusion)</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as having at least one of the following adverse events, independent of the attribution to the NK cell infusion: grade IV infusional toxicity (based on the Adapted Common Toxicity Criteria or CTC); grade IV regimen-related toxicity (based on Adapted CTC); grade IV acute GVHD; non-relapse mortality.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as presence of malignant cells in marrow (&gt; 5% blasts by morphology), peripheral blood (circulating blasts), or extramedullary sites (enlarging lymphadenopathy, soft tissue masses) not evident at the time of HCT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute GvHD (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 100</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic extensive GvHD (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Contribution of KIR ligand alloreactivity to relapse (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Engraftment (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of rejection (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NK cell infusion on post-transplant immune reconstitution (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-relapse mortality (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 200</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as death in any patient for whom there has not been a diagnosis of relapse or disease progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as advancement of malignancy after HCT despite previous achievement of stable disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Aggressive Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Previously Treated Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia, BCR-ABL1 Positive</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Indolent Adult Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Mantle Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Plasma Cell Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Plasma Cell Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Small Lymphocytic Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Waldenstrom Macroglobulinemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (non-myeloablative transplant)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CONDITIONING: Patients receive fludarabine IV over 30 minutes on days -6 to -2 and cyclophosphamide IV over 1 hour on days -6 and -5. Patients undergo total-body irradiation on day -1.
DONOR BONE MARROW TRANSPLANTATION: Patients undergo donor bone marrow transplantation on day 0.
POST-TRANSPLANTATION IMMUNOSUPPRESSION: Patients receive cyclophosphamide IV over 1 hour on day 3 and mycophenolate mofetil PO TID on days 4 to 40, followed by a taper until day 84 in the absence of GVHD. Patients also receive tacrolimus IV continuously or IV QD over 1-2 hours or PO BID on days 4 to 84, followed by a taper until day 180 in the absence of GVHD.
NK CELL INFUSION: Patients undergo donor lymphocyte infusion of NK cells on day 7.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Allogeneic Bone Marrow Transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo donor bone marrow transplantation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (non-myeloablative transplant)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Allo BMT</other_name>
    <other_name>Allogeneic BMT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (non-myeloablative transplant)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(-)-Cyclophosphamide</other_name>
    <other_name>2H-1,3,2-Oxazaphosphorine, 2-[bis(2-chloroethyl)amino]tetrahydro-, 2-oxide, monohydrate</other_name>
    <other_name>Carloxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Ciclofosfamida</other_name>
    <other_name>Ciclofosfamide</other_name>
    <other_name>Cicloxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Clafen</other_name>
    <other_name>Claphene</other_name>
    <other_name>CP monohydrate</other_name>
    <other_name>CTX</other_name>
    <other_name>CYCLO-cell</other_name>
    <other_name>Cycloblastin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cycloblastine</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophospham</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphamid monohydrate</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphamidum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphan</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphane</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphanum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclostin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cyclostine</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytophosphan</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytophosphane</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Fosfaseron</other_name>
    <other_name>Genoxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Genuxal</other_name>
    <other_name>Ledoxina</other_name>
    <other_name>Mitoxan</other_name>
    <other_name>Neosar</other_name>
    <other_name>Revimmune</other_name>
    <other_name>Syklofosfamid</other_name>
    <other_name>WR- 138719</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine Phosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (non-myeloablative transplant)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2-F-ara-AMP</other_name>
    <other_name>9H-Purin-6-amine, 2-fluoro-9-(5-O-phosphono-.beta.-D-arabinofuranosyl)-</other_name>
    <other_name>Beneflur</other_name>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
    <other_name>Oforta</other_name>
    <other_name>SH T 586</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (non-myeloablative transplant)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mycophenolate Mofetil</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (non-myeloablative transplant)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cellcept</other_name>
    <other_name>MMF</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Natural Killer Cell Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (non-myeloablative transplant)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV or PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (non-myeloablative transplant)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FK 506</other_name>
    <other_name>Fujimycin</other_name>
    <other_name>Hecoria</other_name>
    <other_name>Prograf</other_name>
    <other_name>Protopic</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Total-Body Irradiation</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo total-body irradiation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (non-myeloablative transplant)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TOTAL BODY IRRADIATION</other_name>
    <other_name>Whole-Body Irradiation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with the following hematologic malignancies will be permitted although other
             diagnoses can be considered if approved by Patient Care Conference (PCC) and the
             principal investigators:

          -  Aggressive non-Hodgkin lymphomas (NHL) and other histologies such as diffuse large B
             cell (DLBC) NHL - a) not eligible for autologous HCT, b) not eligible for high-dose
             HCT, c) after failed autologous HCT, or d) be part of a tandem auto-allo approach for
             high risk patients

          -  Mantle cell NHL must be beyond first complete response (CR)

          -  Low-grade NHL with &lt; 6 month duration of CR between courses of conventional therapy

          -  Chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) must have either

               -  1) Failed to meet National Cancer Institute (NCI) Working Group criteria for
                  complete or partial response after therapy with a regimen containing FLU
                  (fludarabine phosphate) (or another nucleoside analog, e.g.
                  2-chlorodeoxyadenosine [2-CDA], pentostatin) or experience disease relapse within
                  12 months after completing therapy with a regimen containing FLU (or another
                  nucleoside analog)

               -  2) Failed FLU- CY (cyclophosphamide)-rituximab (FCR) combination chemotherapy at
                  any time point; or

               -  3) Have &quot;17p deletion&quot; cytogenetic abnormality and relapsed at any time point
                  after any initial chemotherapy

          -  Hodgkin lymphoma - must have received and a) failed frontline therapy, b) not be
             eligible for autologous HCT, or c) or be part of a tandem auto-allo approach for high
             risk patients

          -  Multiple myeloma or plasma cell leukemia must have received more than one line of
             prior chemotherapy; consolidation of chemotherapy by autografting prior to
             nonmyeloablative HCT is permitted

          -  Acute myeloid leukemia (AML) must have &lt; 5% marrow blasts at the time of HCT

          -  Acute lymphocytic leukemia (ALL) must have &lt; 5% marrow blasts at the time of HCT

          -  Chronic myeloid leukemia (CML) accepted if they are beyond chronic phase (CP)1 and if
             they have received previous myelosuppressive chemotherapy or HCT and have &lt; 5% marrow
             blasts at time of transplant

          -  Myelodysplasia (MDS)/myeloproliferative syndrome (MPS) - (&gt; intermediate 1 [int-1] per
             International Prognostic Scoring System [IPSS]) after &gt; or = 1 prior cycle of
             induction chemotherapy; must have &lt; 5% marrow blasts at time of transplant

          -  Waldenstrom's macroglobulinemia must have failed 2 courses of therapy

          -  Patients must be expected to have disease controlled for at least 60 days after HCT

          -  Patients for whom HLA-matched unrelated donor search could not be initiated or
             completed due to insurance reasons, concerns of rapidly progressive disease, and/or
             discretion of attending physician are eligible for this protocol

          -  DONOR: Related, HLA-haploidentical donors who are identical for one HLA haplotype and
             mismatched for any number of HLA-A, -B, -C, DRB1 or DQB1 loci of the unshared
             haplotype

          -  DONOR: Marrow will be the only allowed hematopoietic stem cell source

          -  DONOR: Haploidentical donor selection will be based on standard institutional
             criteria, otherwise no specific prioritization will be made amongst the suitable
             available donors; donors will not be selected based on killer cell immunoglobulin-like
             receptor (KIR) status

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with available HLA-matched related donors

          -  Patients eligible for a curative autologous HCT

          -  Significant organ dysfunction that would prevent compliance with conditioning, GVHD
             prophylaxis, or would severely limit the probability of survival:

               -  1) Symptomatic coronary artery disease or ejection fraction &lt; 35% or other
                  cardiac failure requiring therapy (or, if unable to obtain ejection fraction,
                  shortening fraction of &lt; 26%); if shortening fraction is &lt; 26% a cardiology
                  consult is required with the principal investigator (PI) having final approval of
                  eligibility

               -  2) Diffusion capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide (DLCO) &lt; 40% total lung
                  capacity (TLC) &lt; 40%, forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) &lt; 40% and/or
                  receiving supplementary continuous oxygen; the Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research
                  Center (FHCRC) study PI must approve enrollment of all patients with pulmonary
                  nodules

               -  3) Liver function abnormalities: patient with clinical or laboratory evidence of
                  liver disease will be evaluated for the cause of liver disease, its clinical
                  severity in terms of liver function, bridging fibrosis, and the degree of portal
                  hypertension; the patient will be excluded if he/she is found to have fulminant
                  liver failure, cirrhosis of the liver with evidence of portal hypertension,
                  alcoholic hepatitis, esophageal varices, a history of bleeding esophageal
                  varices, hepatic encephalopathy, uncorrectable hepatic synthetic dysfunction
                  evinced by prolongation of the prothrombin time, ascites related to portal
                  hypertension, bacterial or fungal liver abscess, biliary obstruction, chronic
                  viral hepatitis with total serum bilirubin &gt; 3 mg/dL, or symptomatic biliary
                  disease

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositive patients

          -  Patients with poorly controlled hypertension despite multiple antihypertensive
             medications

          -  Fertile females who are unwilling to use contraceptive techniques during and for the
             twelve months following treatment, as well as females who are pregnant or actively
             breast feeding

          -  Fertile males who are unwilling to use contraceptive techniques during and for the
             twelve months following treatment

          -  Patients with active non-hematologic malignancies (except non-melanoma skin cancers)
             or those with non-hematologic malignancies (except non-melanoma skin cancers) who have
             been rendered with no evidence of disease, but have a greater than 20% chance of
             having disease recurrence within five years; this exclusion does not apply to patients
             with non-hematologic malignancies that do not require therapy

          -  Active infectious disease concerns

          -  Karnofsky performance score &lt; 60 Lansky performance score &lt; 60

          -  Life expectancy severely limited by diseases other than malignancy

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of chronic myelomonocytic leukemia (CMML)

          -  Central nervous system (CNS) involvement with disease refractory to intrathecal
             chemotherapy

          -  Patients with AML, MDS, ALL, or CML must not have presence of circulating leukemic
             blasts detected by standard pathology

          -  Patients with aggressive lymphomas (such as DLBC) must not have bulky, rapidly
             progressive disease immediately prior to HCT

          -  Patients who have received a prior allogeneic HCT must have no active GVHD requiring
             immunosuppressive therapy for at least 21 days prior to start of conditioning

          -  DONOR: Children less than 12 years of age.

          -  DONOR: Children greater than or equal to 12 years of age who have not provided
             informed assent in the presence of a parent and an attending physician who is not a
             member of the recipient's care team

          -  DONOR: Children greater than or equal to 12 years of age who have inadequate
             peripheral vein access to safely undergo apheresis

          -  DONOR: Donors unable or unwilling to undergo marrow harvest for the initial HCT,
             storage of autologous blood prior to marrow harvest or apheresis one week after marrow
             harvest

          -  DONOR: Donors who are not expected to meet the minimum target dose of marrow cells (1
             x 10^8 nucleated cells/kg recipient ideal body weight [IBW]) for the initial HCT; the
             average nucleated cell content of harvested marrow is 22 x 10^6 nucleated cells/mL or
             220 x 10^8 nucleated cells/Liter

          -  DONOR: HIV-positive donors

          -  DONOR: Donors who are cross-match positive with recipient
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brenda Sandmaier</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutch/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutch/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Froedtert and the Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 12, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 12, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 13, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Mantle-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Waldenstrom Macroglobulinemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>May 2, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

