<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01783067</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13-1430</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01783067</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zinc and Iron Bioavailability From Biofortified Pearl Millet</brief_title>
  <official_title>Zinc and Iron Bioavailability From Bio-fortified Pearl Millet</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jawaharlal Nehru Medical College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>HarvestPlus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>International Atomic Energy Agency</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Populations who consume non-fortified plant-based diets are at increased risk of iron and
      zinc deficiencies. The purpose of this randomized controlled study is to determine the
      absorption of iron and zinc from pearl millet biofortified with these two micronutrients.
      Forty children aged 2 years in Kanartaka, India are randomized to consume biofortified pearl
      millet (Group 1) or control pearl millet (Group 2) for two days. Quantities of zinc and iron
      absorbed are measured with established stable isotope extrinsic labeling techniques and
      analyses of duplicate diets.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nutritional deficiency of iron in 30-70% of young children in different communities in India
      is well documented and has proved challenging to eradicate both in India and globally. Less
      is known about zinc deficiency, but zinc and iron are generally present in the same foods and
      there is also growing evidence for the public health importance of zinc deficiency in young
      children on a global basis. In populations that depend primarily on plant-based foods,
      biofortification of major food staples by traditional selective plant breeding procedures
      offers an attractive strategy for preventing iron and zinc deficiency in all age groups.
      Pearl millet, a major food staple in several areas of India, has both naturally relatively
      high concentrations of iron and zinc with demonstrated potential to increase these levels
      further with plant breeding. Before embarking on complex, costly efficacy, effectiveness
      studies of the potential health benefits of this biofortified grain, the objective of this
      project is to determine the extent to which iron and zinc absorption is increased in very
      young children who consume pearl millet as the primary grain and major food staple. This is a
      short term, cross-sectional double-blinded study in which the test or control pearl millet is
      fed for a total of 9 days. Primary outcome measures are the increases in iron and zinc
      absorption over a two-day period. Test meals will be labeled with a zinc stable isotope on
      Day 8 and an iron stable isotope on Days 8 and 9 during which days participants and their
      mothers will stay in their community health center. Food intake will be weighed and duplicate
      diets obtained. Percentage iron absorption will be determined from erythrocyte enrichment on
      Day 23. Fractional zinc absorption will be measured from urine enrichment with orally and
      intravenously administered zinc isotopes from timed samples collected on Days 12-15. Daily
      absorption of these minerals will be determined. Increases in intake and absorption of these
      minerals (mg/d) will be evaluated with respect to estimated dietary and physiologic
      requirements.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absorption of iron from pearl millet</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <description>Absorption of iron will be measured while the participants are eating pearl millet as their major food staple which will provide at least 50% energy and at least 75% iron, zinc and phytate of the diet. Fractional absorption of iron for two days will be measured by extrinsic labeling with stable isotopes of iron and measuring erythrocyte enrichment. Measurement of total iron in duplicate diets on test days will allow determination of quantity of this micronutrient absorbed (mg/d).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absorption of zinc from pearl millet</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Absorption of zinc will be measured while the participants are eating pearl millet as their major food staple which will provide at least 50% energy and at least 75% iron, zinc and phytate of the diet. Fractional absorption of zinc for a day will be measured by extrinsic labeling with stable isotopes of zinc. Fractional absorption of zinc will be measured by a dual isotope tracer ratio technique. Measurement of total zinc in duplicate diets on test day will allow determination of quantity of this micronutrient absorbed (mg/d).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Nutritional Deficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iron and zinc biofortified pearl millet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the experimental arm consume pearl millet which has been biofortified with iron and zinc.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pearl millet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the control arm consume non-biofortified pearl millet.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pearl millet</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the control arm consume pearl millet which has not been biofortified. The intervention is consumed for two days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pearl millet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biofortified pearl millet</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the experimental arm consume pearl millet biofortified with iron and zinc. The intervention is consumed for two days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iron and zinc biofortified pearl millet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  lives in one of the targeted communities

          -  apparently healthy

          -  23 m of age [may need modification]

          -  Hemoglobin (Hb) &gt; 8 g/dl

          -  ferritin ≤ 12mg/L

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Hemoglobin (Hb) &lt; 8g/dl

          -  serum ferritin &gt; 12 (even after correction for C-reactive protein (CRP)/ Alpha Glyco
             Protein (AGP)

          -  thalassemia

          -  birth weight &lt; 2,500 g

          -  birth defect affecting growth and development

          -  chronic infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>36 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Hambidge, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Denver</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>JN Medical College (Human field studies)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belgaum</city>
        <state>Karnataka</state>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kodkany BS, Bellad RM, Mahantshetti NS, Westcott JE, Krebs NF, Kemp JF, Hambidge KM. Biofortification of pearl millet with iron and zinc in a randomized controlled trial increases absorption of these minerals above physiologic requirements in young children. J Nutr. 2013 Sep;143(9):1489-93. doi: 10.3945/jn.113.176677. Epub 2013 Jul 10. Erratum in: J Nutr. 2013 Dec;143(12):2055.</citation>
    <PMID>23843474</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller LV, Hambidge KM, Krebs NF. Zinc Absorption Is Not Related to Dietary Phytate Intake in Infants and Young Children Based on Modeling Combined Data from Multiple Studies. J Nutr. 2015 Aug;145(8):1763-9. doi: 10.3945/jn.115.213074. Epub 2015 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>26108545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 28, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 1, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 28, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biofortification</keyword>
  <keyword>Pearl millet</keyword>
  <keyword>Iron absorption</keyword>
  <keyword>Zinc absorption</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malnutrition</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Iron</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Zinc</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

