<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01781390</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ANG.AMI-IC001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01781390</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of Allogeneic Mesenchymal Precursor Cell Infusion in MyoCardial Infarction</brief_title>
  <acronym>AMICI</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective, DB, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Clinical Trial of IC Infusion of Mesenchymal Precursor Cells (MPC) in the Treatment of Patients With ST-elevation Myocardial Infarction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mesoblast, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mesoblast, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a double blind, randomized, placebo controlled study that will enroll 105 subjects
      with de novo anterior myocardial infarction due to a lesion of the left anterior descending
      coronary artery undergoing PCI. Eligible subjects will be enrolled and undergo
      revascularization of the culprit LAD followed by an intracoronary (IC) delivery of the
      assigned treatment, infused into the stented culprit artery. The study will determine the
      safety and feasibility of the IC infusion of investigational MPCs in this patient population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled study that will enroll
      approximately 105 subjects with de novo anterior STEMI due to a lesion involving LAD coronary
      artery who undergo primary PCI at approximately 25 clinical study sites.

      This study will compare two doses of MPCs and a placebo control group. Study subjects will be
      randomly assigned in 1:1:1 fashion to receive either 12.5 Million or 25 Million MPCs or
      placebo (saline). Each group will have approximately 35 subjects.

      Potential subjects will be approached by a site investigator prior to PCI and must sign an
      informed consent form before initiation of the cardiac catheterization procedure in order to
      participate in this trial. Following successful and uneventful PCI and stenting of the
      culprit LAD lesion, the subjects will be randomized. The randomization and treatment
      assignment will be obtained from an interactive voice-response system (IVRS/interactive web
      response system (IWRS)). The following stratification for duration of cardiac ischemia will
      be performed to ensure balanced randomization across the treatment groups:

        -  ≤2 hours

        -  &gt;2 hours to ≤6 hours

        -  &gt;6 to ≤12 hours

      Eligible subjects will receive intracoronary delivery of the assigned treatment infused via a
      microcatheter into the stented culprit artery.

      After approximately 50% of the intracoronary infusion of investigational agent has been
      completed, an angiographic determination of coronary flow will be performed. The following
      guidelines will be used to determine if the remaining investigational agent should be
      infused:

      • The study infusion should be continued if either TIMI 2 or TIMI 3 flow is present in the
      absence of ALL of the following:

        -  Sustained hypotension not responsive to fluid administration;

        -  Clinical signs/symptoms indicating an acute cerebrovascular event;

        -  Re-elevation of ST-segments if previously resolved with PCI;

        -  Onset of the subject's symptoms of myocardial ischemia unresponsive to appropriate
           interventions;

        -  Two episodes of sustained ventricular tachycardia (VT)/ventricular fibrillation (VF)
           requiring cardioversion (infusion can continue if a single episode of sustained VT/VF
           requiring cardioversion occurred).

      If for any reason, the site investigator withdraws a randomized subject prior to infusion of
      the investigational agent, the reason for early termination and data from the screening visit
      will be entered into the eCRF by the study site. The subject will not remain in the study. If
      for any reason, a subject's study infusion is halted due to safety considerations, the
      subject will remain in the study. A subject who prematurely withdraws from the study, post-
      study infusion will remain in the study. Subjects will be followed for up to 24 months and
      will undergo cardiac imaging using cMRI and 2D-echocardiography, Holter monitoring, clinical
      evaluation, and laboratory testing. Evaluations will be performed at 6, 12, 18 and 24 hours
      post infusion of investigational agent, during the index hospitalization as well as at 14 and
      30 days and 3, 6, 12, 18, and 24 months after the procedure as outlined in Table 2 Schedule
      of Assessments and Procedures.

      An independent Data Monitoring Safety Board (DSMB) will review all relevant acute
      peri-procedural data, serious adverse events (SAE), other adverse events (AE), and efficacy
      data (if requested) periodically dependent on subject enrollment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of the total major adverse cardiac and cerebrovascular events (MACCE)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of MACCE events including cardiac death, myocardial infarction, target vessel revascularization, stroke, new or worsening congestive heart failure during index hospitalization and cardiac hospitalizations due to congestive heart failure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">105</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>12.5M Mesenchymal Precursor Cells (MPC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12.5M Mesenchymal Precursor Cell (MPC) administered via IC infusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>25M Mesenchymal Precursor Cells (MPC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>25M Mesenchymal Precursor Cell (MPC) administered via IC infusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo via IC infusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>12.5 M Mesenchymal Precursor Cells (MPC)</intervention_name>
    <description>MPCs</description>
    <arm_group_label>12.5M Mesenchymal Precursor Cells (MPC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>25M Mesenchymal Precursor Cells (MPC)</intervention_name>
    <description>MPC</description>
    <arm_group_label>25M Mesenchymal Precursor Cells (MPC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical symptoms consistent with AMI (pain, etc.) for a maximum of 12 hours from
             onset of symptoms to percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI)

          -  De Novo anterior Acute Myocardial Infarct (AMI)

          -  Successful revascularization of the culprit lesion

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior AMI, known cardiomyopathy, or hospital admission for heart failure (HF)

          -  Significant valvular disease

          -  Need for other interventional or surgical procedure to treat heart disease (planned or
             scheduled)

          -  Cardiogenic shock or hemodynamic instability within 24 hours of randomization

          -  Prior PCI to LAD

          -  Pacemaker, ICD (Implantable Cardioverter Defibrillator), or any other
             contra-indication for cardiac MRI

          -  Prior or current participation in any stem cell study or any other investigational
             trial in the past 30 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donna Skerrett, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Mesoblast, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy Henry, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedar-Sinai Heart Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>New Zealand</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 14, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 30, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 1, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute Myocardial Infarction</keyword>
  <keyword>STEMI</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Attack</keyword>
  <keyword>AMI</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem Cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

