<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01787331</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>125513</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-02375</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>12-10472</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CC#125513</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>125513</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA082103</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01787331</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Itraconazole in Treating Patients With Biochemically Relapsed Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hedgehog Inhibition as a Non-Castrating Approach to Hormone Sensitive Prostate Cancer: A Phase II Study of Itraconazole in Biochemical Relapse</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well itraconazole works in treating patients with
      biochemically relapsed prostate cancer. Itraconazole may stop the growth of tumor cells by
      blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine whether the proportion of patients who achieve a &gt;= 50% decline in serum
      prostate-specific antigen (PSA) after 12 weeks of protocol therapy with itraconazole dosed at
      300 mg orally (PO) twice daily (BID) is superior to a historical control based upon the
      observed PSA response proportion in prior studies of non-castrating systemic therapy in men
      with biochemically relapsed hormone sensitive prostate cancer.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the median time to PSA progression from the start of protocol therapy with
      itraconazole among men with biochemically relapsed prostate cancer.

      II. To determine the median time to clinical progression measured from the start of protocol
      therapy with itraconazole among men with biochemically relapsed prostate cancer.

      III. To determine the median metastasis-free survival measured from the start of protocol
      therapy in patients treated with itraconazole for biochemically relapsed prostate cancer.

      IV. To determine the mean percent change from baseline after 12 weeks of protocol therapy
      compared with pre-treatment in PSA doubling time.

      V. To characterize the safety profile of itraconazole in the biochemically relapsed hormone
      sensitive prostate cancer population, as graded by Common Toxicity Criteria (CTCAE) version
      4.03 VI. To determine the mean steady-state itraconazole and hydroxy-itraconazole serum
      levels after 4 weeks of therapy with itraconazole.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the mean percent change from baseline in serum androgen levels, including
      serum testosterone, dehydroepiandrosterone-sulfate (DHEA-S), and androstenedione, after 4 and
      12 weeks of protocol therapy with itraconazole.

      II. To determine the mean percent change from baseline in additional serum hormone levels,
      including adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH), aldosterone, deoxycorticosterone (DOC),
      11-deoxycortisol, and cortisol after 4 and 12 weeks of protocol therapy with itraconazole.

      III. To determine if there is a relationship between baseline and/or percent change in serum
      hormone levels and achieving a decline of &gt;= 50% in serum PSA after 12 weeks of protocol
      therapy.

      IV. To determine the proportion of patients treated with itraconazole who display a
      down-regulation of the Hedgehog pathway, as assessed by measurement of GLI family zinc finger
      1 (GLI1) messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA) expression by quantitative reverse
      transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) on serial skin biopsies obtained at
      baseline and after 4 weeks of protocol therapy.

      V. To determine if there is a relationship between down-regulation of the Hedgehog pathway
      and PSA modulation, including proportion of patients achieving a decline of &gt;= 50% in serum
      PSA as well as time to PSA progression.

      VI. To evaluate archived primary prostate cancer tissue (biopsy or prostatectomy specimen)
      for baseline Hedgehog pathway status, using both qRT-PCR-based mRNA expression analysis and
      protein-based immunohistochemical (IHC) analysis of key Hedgehog (Hh) pathway components
      (GLI1, patched 1 [PCTH1], smoothened [SMO]) and Sonic hedgehog ligand.

      VII. To determine if there is a relationship between mRNA and ICH expression of components in
      the Hedgehog pathway in primary prostate cancer tissue and PSA modulation on itraconazole
      therapy, including the proportion of patients achieving a decline of &gt;= 50% in serum PSA as
      well as time to PSA progression.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive itraconazole PO BID in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 30 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 29, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who achieve a greater than or equal to 50% decline in serum prostate specific antigen (PSA)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The results will be summarized by the proportion of patients who achieve a greater than or equal to 50% decline in serum PSA along with a 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median time to PSA progression</measure>
    <time_frame>From day 1 of study treatment to the first date of PSA progression, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The probability distribution of the time to PSA progression will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier product limit method measured from the start of protocol therapy. The results will be summarized by the estimated median with 95% confidence intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median time to clinical progression</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of start of protocol therapy to first occurrence of either development of overt metastases or initiation of non-protocol therapy, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The probability distribution of the time to clinical progression will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier product limit method measured from the time of start of protocol therapy. The results will be summarized by the estimated median with 95% confidence intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median metastasis-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of start of protocol therapy to development of metastatic disease, assessed up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The probability distribution of the time to first metastasis will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier product limit method measured from the time of start of protocol therapy. The results will be summarized by the estimated median with 95% confidence intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percent change in PSA doubling time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The mean percent change in PSA doubling time after 12 weeks of protocol therapy from pre-treatment PSA doubling time will be calculated. Descriptive statistics will be presented to summarize the PSA doubling time at baseline and after 12 weeks of protocol therapy as well as the change between time points. Pearson's correlation will be used to estimate the relationship between pre-treatment PSA doubling time and percent change in PSA doubling time after 12 weeks of protocol therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events observed during treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>All adverse events will be tabulated by grade according to CTCAE version 4.03. Reported grades will be based on the worst grade experienced by each patient for any given adverse event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean steady-state trough level of serum itraconazole and its active metabolite, hydroxy-itraconazole</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics including the mean, standard deviation, and range of steady-state trough serum levels of itraconazole and its active metabolite hydroxy-itraconazole will be determined.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percent change in serum androgen levels, including serum testosterone, DHEA-S, and androstenedione</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To summarize the outcome, descriptive statistics including the mean percent change from baseline in serum hormone levels at 4 and 12 weeks will be presented with a standard deviation and Pearson?s correlation will be used to estimate the relationship between the baseline hormone level and percent change in hormone level after 4 and 12 weeks of treatment. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) methods for mixed models allowing for variable number of follow-up measurements with linear contrasts will be used to evaluate the change in serum hormone levels after 4 and 12 weeks of protocol therapy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percent change in serum hormone levels, including ACTH, aldosterone, DOC, 11-deoxycortisol, and cortisol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To summarize the outcome, descriptive statistics including the mean percent change from baseline in serum hormone levels at 4 and 12 weeks will be presented with a standard deviation and Pearson?s correlation will be used to estimate the relationship between the baseline hormone level and percent change in hormone level after 4 and 12 weeks of treatment. ANOVA methods for mixed models allowing for variable number of follow-up measurements with linear contrasts will be used to evaluate the change in serum hormone levels after 4 and 12 weeks of protocol therapy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percent change in serum hormone levels among patients achieving greater than or equal to 50% decline in serum PSA</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Depending upon the observed frequency, the ANOVA model will include a factor to test for the effect of PSA decline on change in serum hormone levels. Otherwise, analyses will compare the baseline and percent change in serum hormone levels at 4 and 12 weeks between patients achieving a PSA decline &gt;= 50% or not using a two group t statistic.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in proportion of patients who display a down-regulation of the Hedgehog pathway, as assessed by measurement of GLI1 messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA) expression by real time polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) on serial skin biopsies</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Down-regulation will be defined as a decline of any magnitude in GLI1 mRNA expression after 4 weeks of protocol therapy compared to baseline expression level. Descriptive statistics will be used to summarize the proportion of patients with down-regulation of GLI1 expression after 4 weeks of treatment with itraconazole. The patient cohort will be dichotomized by whether there is up- or down-regulation of GLI1 expression.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in proportion of patients with and without at least a 50% decline in PSA exhibiting a down-regulation of the Hedgehog pathway</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Fisher?s exact test will be used to test for an association between down-regulation of GLI1 expression and PSA decline &gt;= 50% on protocol therapy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Median time to PSA progression between patients with and without down-regulation of the Hedgehog pathway on itraconazole therapy as assessed by serial skin biopsy</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The probability distributions for each GLI1 expression subset (as defined above) of the time to PSA progression will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier product limit method. The results will be summarized by the estimated median with 95% confidence intervals.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with and without at least 50% decline in PSA exhibiting over-activation of Hedgehog pathway components as assessed by immunohistochemical (IHC) and mRNA expression analysis of primary prostate cancer tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Fisher?s exact test will be used to test for an association between IHC expression and PSA decline &gt; 50% on protocol therapy.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Median time to PSA progression between patients with and without Hedgehog pathway over-activation in archived primary prostate cancer tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The probability distributions for each expression subset of the time to PSA progression will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier product limit method. The results will be summarized by the estimated median with 95% confidence intervals.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Prostate Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Prostate Adenocarcinoma AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Prostate Adenocarcinoma AJCC v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Prostate Adenocarcinoma AJCC v7</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (itraconazole)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive itraconazole PO BID in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Itraconazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (itraconazole)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lozanoc</other_name>
    <other_name>Oriconazole</other_name>
    <other_name>R 51,211</other_name>
    <other_name>Sporanox</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (itraconazole)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological Study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (itraconazole)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologic confirmation of adenocarcinoma of the prostate

          -  Biochemically relapsed disease with a rising PSA on at least two successive
             measurements at least two weeks apart after prior definitive local therapy (radical
             prostatectomy, external beam radiation, or brachytherapy) or combination of radical
             prostatectomy and radiotherapy (RT) with curative intent; if the confirmatory PSA
             value is less than the screening PSA value, then an additional test for rising PSA
             will be required to documents progression

          -  Prior primary or salvage radiation or not a candidate for salvage radiation due to
             patient preference or clinical assessment based upon disease characteristics and/or
             patient co-morbidities

          -  Minimum PSA:

               -  If no prior androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) for biochemical relapse:

                    -  1.0 ng/mL if prior radical prostatectomy with or without adjuvant/salvage
                       radiation therapy, confirmed by repeat measurement at least 2 weeks later,
                       or

                    -  Nadir + 2 ng/mL if prior RT alone without prior radical prostatectomy,
                       confirmed by repeat measurement at least 2 weeks later

               -  If prior ADT for biochemical relapse:

                    -  4.0 ng/mL or &gt; 2 ng/mL above nadir on prior cycle of ADT, whichever is
                       higher, confirmed by repeat measurement at least 2 weeks later

          -  No evidence of metastatic disease on imaging by whole body bone scan (technetium-99 or
             sodium fluoride [Na-F] positron emission tomography [PET] bone scan) and
             cross-sectional imaging of the abdomen/pelvis (computed tomography [CT] or magnetic
             resonance imaging [MRI]) within 6 weeks of day 1 of protocol therapy

          -  Prior androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) with luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone
             (LHRH) agonist and/or antagonist allowed for either (neo)adjuvant treatment with local
             therapy or for biochemical relapse

          -  Last effective dose of LHRH agonist/antagonist ?expired? &gt; 3 months prior to study
             entry; for example, a patient receiving LHRH agonist injection every 3 months would be
             eligible provided their last injection was &gt; 6 months prior to day 1 of protocol
             therapy; a patient receiving LHRH agonist injections every 4 months will be eligible
             provided last injection was &gt; 7 months prior to day 1 of protocol therapy

          -  Serum testosterone level:

               -  If no prior androgen deprivation therapy:

                    -  A single measurement greater than 150 ng/dL within 3 months of day 1 of
                       protocol therapy

               -  If prior androgen deprivation therapy (either in adjuvant or biochemical relapse
                  setting):

                    -  The two most recent measurements of serum testosterone prior to day 1 of
                       protocol therapy must fulfill the following criteria:

                         -  Both measurements are greater than 150 ng/dL

                         -  The two measurements are spaced at least 14 days apart

                         -  Both must be measured within 3 months of day 1 of protocol therapy

                         -  There must not be an increase of &gt; 50 ng/dL between these two
                            successive measurements

          -  PSA doubling time (PSADT) =&lt; 15 months, calculated based upon all serum PSA
             measurements obtained within 3 months prior to day 1 of protocol therapy, with a
             minimum of three PSA measurements spaced at least 14 days apart ; PSA values obtained
             when serum testosterone was known to be less than 150 ng/dL, prior to local therapy,
             or within three months of last dose of LHRH agonist/antagonist or antiandrogen will be
             excluded from the calculation of the PSADT

          -  Total bilirubin less than 1.5 times upper limit of normal (ULN), or less than 3 times
             ULN at study entry in a patient with documented Gilbert?s disease

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) levels less than
             1.5 times ULN at study entry

          -  Serum potassium greater than 3.5 mmol/L without oral supplementation

          -  No history of uncontrolled hypertension (blood pressure &gt; 160/100 mm Hg despite
             anti-hypertensive medication)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Estimated life expectancy greater than 5 years

          -  Ability to sign written informed consent

          -  Ability to swallow study drug whole as a capsule

          -  Primary prostate cancer tissue available for analysis is not required for inclusion
             onto this study but is strongly encouraged

          -  Patients who have partners of childbearing potential must be willing to use a method
             of birth control with adequate barrier protection as determined to be acceptable by
             the principal investigator and sponsor during the study and for 1 week after last
             study drug administration

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Castrate-resistant disease, as evidenced by either:

               -  Rising PSA on 2 consecutive measurements at least 2 weeks apart with concurrent
                  documented serum testosterone &lt; 50 ng/dL at the time of PSA measurement, or

               -  Rising PSA on 2 consecutive measurements at least 2 weeks apart measured within 3
                  months after last LHRH agonist/antagonist injection

          -  Prior bilateral orchiectomy

          -  Congestive heart failure of New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III or higher
             severity at study entry

          -  History of chronic active hepatitis

          -  Grade 2 or higher peripheral neuropathy at the time of study entry

          -  Use of 5-alpha reductase antagonist (i.e. finasteride, dutasteride) or antiandrogen
             (i.e. flutamide, bicalutamide) within 6 weeks of day 1 of protocol therapy

          -  Use of systemic steroids at an equivalent dose of prednisone 5 mg/day or higher within
             6 weeks of day 1 of protocol therapy

          -  Use of medications or herbal supplements which are known to potentially lower serum
             PSA within 6 weeks of day 1 of protocol therapy

          -  Use of other medications that may potentially interact with itraconazole within 1 week
             of study entry

          -  Use of other investigational agents within 6 weeks of day 1 of protocol therapy

          -  Prior pathology consistent with small cell carcinoma or prostate cancer with
             predominantly neuroendocrine differentiation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rahul Aggarwal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 8, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Itraconazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxyitraconazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

