<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02772848</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FDI-81</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02772848</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fertility in Healthy Premenopausal Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Collection of Peripheral Blood Specimens to Study Fertility in Healthy, Premenopausal Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fujirebio Diagnostics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fujirebio Diagnostics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study objectives are described below:

        1. Obtain serum specimens collected for one ovulatory cycle or a maximum of 33 days, but
           not to exceed a total of 550 ml of whole blood per subject from a minimum of 60 healthy,
           premenopausal subjects. Specimens will be used to determine a reference range for
           estradiol, FSH, LH, and progesterone assays, used as an aid in the assessment of
           fertility in adult, premenopausal women.

        2. To store any remaining specimens for use in future assay development and to evaluate as
           yet undetermined assays for the development of IVDs, including additional estradiol,
           FSH, LH, and progesterone assays.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to obtain sufficient specimens and correlating clinical data
      from a well-controlled prospective clinical trial collecting specimens from healthy,
      premenopausal subjects to support domestic and international regulatory submissions on
      fertility biomarker assays, and to establish a collection of specimens that will support
      future assay discovery and validation efforts.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of fertility hormone levels in 60 + healthy premenopausal women</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Fertility</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Serum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A minimum of 60 subjects will be enrolled in this study. Healthy, premenopausal women
        greater than or equal to 21 years of age having donated a serial blood collection
        throughout a single ovulation cycle or a maximum of 33 days will be eligible.

        Each site or mobile center will evaluate and select patients for enrollment using the
        inclusion and exclusion criteria listed below. Study subjects should be selected from all
        available patients at the site or mobile center. Each patient may be entered into the study
        only once. Subject enrollment and/or Day 1 blood draw is not associated with a specific
        time point in the ovulatory cycle.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Females, age ≥ 21 years

          -  Premenopausal (defined as a woman that has had at least one menstrual cycle in the
             last 365 days).

          -  A minimum weight of 110 lbs

          -  The subject is not anemic (Hemoglobin ≥ 12.5 g/dL)

          -  Willing to provide a daily blood draw for one ovulatory cycle or a maximum of 33 days

          -  Able to understand and willing to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Males

          -  Females, age &lt;21 years

          -  Weighing &lt; 110 lbs

          -  Anemic (Hemoglobin &lt; 12.5 g/dL)

          -  History of bilateral oophorectomy

          -  Females taking any form of hormonal birth control including:

               -  Oral contraceptive pill (combined or progestin-only) within five days enrollment.

               -  Contraceptive patch (such as Ortho Evra®) within seven days of enrollment.

               -  Vaginal contraceptive ring (such as NuvaRing™) within 21 days of enrollment.

               -  Contraceptive injection (such as Depo-Provera®) within 90 days of enrollment.

               -  Intra-uterine system (IUS) within 90 days of enrollment. An intra-uterine device
                  (IUD) made of copper does not exclude the patient from participating in this
                  study.

               -  Subdermal contraceptive implants (such as Nexplanon®) within 90 days of
                  enrollment.

               -  Emergency contraceptive within 30 days of enrollment.

          -  Women in menopause (defined as the end of menstrual cycles or at least more than 365
             days since the last menstrual cycle)

          -  Amenorrhea except for women that continue to ovulate as documented in a physician note
             available to the enrolling center.

          -  Has a current diagnosis of any clinically significant cardiac, respiratory,
             neurological, immunological, hematological, liver disease, renal disease,
             gastrointestinal (GI) disorder, including any history of hyper- or hypothyroid, peptic
             or gastric ulcers or GI bleeding, or any other condition which, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would deem the subject unhealthy and therefore, ineligible.

          -  Has a history of any clinically significant cardiac, respiratory, neurological,
             immunological, hematological, liver disease, renal disease, gastrointestinal (GI)
             disorder, including any history of hyper- or hypothyroid, peptic or gastric ulcers or
             GI bleeding, or any other condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, is
             unstable at the time of enrollment.

          -  Is receiving systemic chemotherapy or radiation treatment, has an active malignancy of
             any type, or has been diagnosed with cancer within 5 years before screening other than
             basal or squamous cell skin cancers or in-situ cervical cancer.

          -  History of seizures

          -  Diagnosed with an infectious disease including any sexually transmitted diseases.

          -  Diagnosed with HIV/AIDS or ever tested positive for HIV.

          -  History of hepatitis

          -  Subject that has had sexual contact with a person who has hepatitis within the last 12
             months.

          -  Pregnancy, lactation or actively seeking to conceive (trying to become pregnant).

          -  Unable to provide informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Diana Dickson</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Fujirebio Diagnostics, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vita Pharma</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hialeah</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>American Blood Bank, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33193</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 19, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 9, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 9, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 10, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

