<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02778334</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COPING</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02778334</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Links Between Depression, Anxiety, Coping and Quality of Life After a Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>COPING</acronym>
  <official_title>Links Between Depression, Anxiety, Coping and Quality of Life After a Stroke: Depressive and Anxiety Symptoms and Individual Coping Strategies of the Acute Phase in the Fourth Month as a Factor Influencing Mental Health and Quality of Life</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Paris 5 - Rene Descartes</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Laboratoire Psychopathologie et Processus de Santé</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Introduction and literature review With 130 000 cases per year in France in 2010, stroke is
      one of the most common neurological diseases, often leaving many disabling sequelae physical
      and cognitive levels (currently live 500 000 disabled following a stroke) and leading and a
      loss of significant autonomy in these patients. However, many stroke survivors soon find a
      range comparable to their previous state. Investigators can then ask ourselves about the
      impact of this life event in these people who apparently do not show visible effects: what
      about the psychological repercussions of stroke in these patients healthy; what is changed in
      their daily lives, particularly in their mental functioning after this brutal confrontation
      with their own mortality?

      Objectives Our project aims to better understand the psychological repercussions of stroke in
      patients who quickly find a health and autonomy comparable to their previous state. The
      objective will be to investigate the relationship between depressive symptoms and anxiety,
      coping strategies and quality of life from the acute phase and during the first months after
      the onset of stroke. This period is particularly demanding for these patients must therefore
      adapt and readjust continuously: shock stroke, hospitalization in several services (intensive
      care, neurology, rehabilitation), back home, &quot;new&quot; life with the changes related stroke,
      resumption of a professional activity, etc ...

      Our methodology will combine tools conventionally used (standardized interview, validated
      questionnaires) to newer, ecological and true methods (Experience Sampling Method applied by
      the use of a smarphone application) to assess different variables studied.

      This initially be determined whether the various symptoms of the depression on the one hand
      and anxiety on the other hand, depending on their mode of expression (vs. outsourced
      internalized; ie emotional, cognitive, somatic), observed from the acute phase of stroke, are
      related and predict the quality of life, depression and anxiety in the longer term (four
      months after the stroke).

      Furthermore, our study will observe if the individual coping strategies (coping) daily and
      evolution influence the psychological status and quality of life during the months following
      the stroke.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction and literature review With 130 000 cases per year in France in 2010, stroke is
      one of the most common neurological diseases, often leaving many disabling sequelae physical
      and cognitive levels (currently live 500 000 disabled following a stroke) and leading and a
      loss of significant autonomy in these patients. However, many stroke survivors soon find a
      range comparable to their previous state. Investigators can then ask ourselves about the
      impact of this life event in these people who apparently do not show visible effects: what
      about the psychological repercussions of stroke in these patients healthy; what is changed in
      their daily lives, particularly in their mental functioning after this brutal confrontation
      with their own mortality? Research on psychology and psychiatric disorders post-stroke
      indicate a frequency of occurrence of depression in 30-40% of patients, while the occurrence
      of anxiety disorders in 20% to 30% of patients. Depression and anxiety after stroke is
      influenced by the presence of sequels, but in a preliminary study (see Psycho-stroke current
      study) with patients with no impairment of their independence three months after stroke
      Investigators observed the presence of depressive and anxious symptoms.

      The psychological health influences the patient's quality of life overall. Recent results
      have thus demonstrated that post-stroke depression increased the risk of short- and long-term
      mortality. It therefore seems essential to identify risk factors and influence of depression
      and anxiety after stroke, particularly in patients rapidly and almost completely recovering
      from the aftermath of their accident, to prevent the emergence and to support them.

      In the scientific literature, individual coping strategies or coping strategies, and their
      development are identified as a factor of influence of post-stroke psychological health.
      Thus, an active coping centered on the problem would be associated with better mental health
      status, while a passive coping centered on managing emotions would instead be a poor
      prognostic factor. However, the clinical understanding of the everyday process of adaptation
      among survivors of stroke is limited by the assessment methods conventionally used in the
      research, which questioned the memory &quot;in general&quot; of the subject.

      Modern techniques and increasingly used, as Experiences Sampling Method (ESM) or the
      Ecological Momentary Assessment (EMA) allow the assessment of individual functioning in more
      ecologically being carried out in the natural environment of the subject and greatly limit
      through retrospective recall. The application of these methods to a population of stroke
      survivors has already been validated and one study also shows that the active behaviors
      (work, sport) would be a post-stroke depression risk factor, whereas the presence of a social
      environment (among friends, relatives) would be a protective factor. However, this study is
      only interested in certain types of behavior, comparable to some coping strategies (active
      coping, social support research) but not representative of a whole, while other studies
      specifically interested in the evaluation of coping with this method but not with stroke
      patients. It seems interesting to use a similar methodology to observe in vivo finer and more
      accurate adaptation strategies in stroke survivors, and thus have an ecological
      representation of their coping.

      The other factor of influence that Investigators chose to investigate in our study relates to
      the symptomatic forms of depression and anxiety. It is important first to note that the
      somatic and cognitive consequences of stroke are close to some depression and anxiety
      manifestations. This symptomatic overlap makes it difficult locating and diagnosing these
      disorders. Determine their specific seems necessary, and would involve the identification of
      symptoms of these psychopathological that would significantly associated with depression and
      anxiety lasting and intense.

      Studies of post-stroke depression reveal that symptoms related to mood, thoughts and
      depressive emotions are more durable and predict diagnosis and depression intensity in the
      longer term, then somatic symptoms (fatigue) during the acute phase of stroke showed no
      significant association with long-term mental health.

      Investigators found no published studies indicating the results on this subject regarding
      post-stroke anxiety. However, in the Psycho-stroke current study, initial results show that
      the psychic symptoms of anxiety three months after the stroke predicted anxiety in six
      months. Investigators would like to deepen these results by focusing on these shorter-term
      variables, that is to say from the first days after the occurrence of the accident, and study
      their links with the mental health status and quality life during the first months following
      the stroke.

      Again, the use of modern evaluation methods (ESM / EMA) will capture the emotional and
      psychological phenomena almost instantaneously, and thus promote the clinical understanding
      of mental disorders after stroke. This approach, already applied in the context of
      post-stroke depression, however, was not used in the study of anxiety in this population,
      although research with d other populations are interested in anxiety as assessed.

      Objectives:

      Our project aims to better understand the psychological repercussions of stroke in patients
      who quickly find a health and autonomy comparable to their previous state. The objective will
      be to investigate the relationship between depressive symptoms and anxiety, coping strategies
      and quality of life from the acute phase and during the first months after the onset of
      stroke. This period is particularly demanding for these patients must therefore adapt and
      readjust continuously: shock stroke, hospitalization in several services (intensive care,
      neurology, rehabilitation), back home, &quot;new&quot; life with the changes related stroke, resumption
      of a professional activity, etc ...

      Our methodology will combine tools conventionally used (standardized interview, validated
      questionnaires) to newer, ecological and true methods (Experience Sampling Method applied by
      the use of a smarphone application) to assess different variables studied.

      This initially be determined whether the various symptoms of the depression on the one hand
      and anxiety on the other hand, depending on their mode of expression (vs. outsourced
      internalized; ie emotional, cognitive, somatic), observed from the acute phase of stroke, are
      related and predict the quality of life, depression and anxiety in the longer term (four
      months after the stroke).

      Furthermore, our study will observe if the individual coping strategies (coping) daily and
      evolution influence the psychological status and quality of life during the months following
      the stroke.

      Methodology

      Population

      N waited 75 patients. Recruitment Location: Neuro-Vascular Unit at St. Joseph Hospital.

      Study duration: 18 to 24 months depending on the pace of inclusion.

      Procedure

      After submission and approval of the project by the Patient Protection Committee will be
      proposed to patients fulfilling the inclusion criteria to participate in the study after
      being informed of its progress and its objectives (note (cf. . Annexes) and meeting with the
      psychologist). Camille Vansimaeys, psychologist and principal investigator of this study will
      also be the only one to see patients and to conduct interviews as part of this research.
      Patients who accept will be seen in maintenance during hospitalization in Neuro-Vascular Unit
      (T0 = 4 to 7 days post-stroke) to assess depression and anxiety (hetero-evaluation).
      Socio-demographic and medical data will be collected in files and anonymous.

      At the time of the release of the UNV (T1 = 12 day average hospitalization), patients will be
      divided into two groups: 1) patients who return home and 2) patients who continued
      hospitalization in rehabilitation. Depression, anxiety, quality of life and coping strategies
      will be assessed by self-administered questionnaires. A first phase of ambulatory (ESM / EMA)
      will also take place following the UNV output: 5 times a day for 7 days patients will respond
      to questions evaluating depression, anxiety and coping strategies. Patients will answer these
      questions via a smartphone app (issues ESM). The application will be directly installed on
      personal smartphones patients who have them. For patients who do not own a smartphone
      configured only to be used for the application will be lent their time to the study by the
      University Paris Descartes. Patients who will be entrusted these smartphones will sign an
      additional form framing the terms of the loan. An explanation of the operation of the
      application and smartphones will be made at the time of the first interview in hospital, a
      training phase is then performed during hospitalization.

      During phase measurements by smartphones, patients will be contacted three days after the
      first evaluation, to address and resolve any difficulties of use, and to remind people with a
      smartphone lent loading.

      Another ambulatory phase on the same model as that performed at T1 (5 times daily for 7 days)
      accompanied by a self-assessment of depression, anxiety, coping strategies and quality of
      life will made 2 months post-stroke (T2).

      The last time the study will take place 4 months after stroke onset (T3). Patients will be
      reviewed in interview to assess depression and anxiety (hetero and self assessments) as well
      as coping strategies and quality of life (self-questionnaires). Ambulatory measurement phase
      (for 1 week, 5 times a day) also accompanied this evaluation. It will be made before the
      interview to half our population, and then the other half to control a possible parasitic
      effect.

      ethical implications The intervention of this research with vulnerable patients by the
      occurrence of a stroke, and therefore may have a certain psychic and emotional vulnerability
      in a particularly challenging time for them, implies that Investigators are attentive to many
      ethical considerations.

      First, it is important to emphasize that proper monitoring will be offered to patients whose
      psychic suffering is manifest in the different assessments. Investigators will verify if they
      have followed up to these difficulties, and if so Investigators redirect to health
      professionals so that they can be supported.

      Similarly, patients who simply express a follow-up request will be directed to an appropriate
      care.

      It will also be checked that each patient and willing to participate in this research has
      understood the objectives and conduct.

      It will also be specified clearly that their participation, their refusal to participate or
      withdrawal during the study in no case affect the management or the relationship with the
      medical and nursing teams.

      Tools

      All tools used were validated their French version.

      • Straight-evaluation The hetero-evaluative tools involve the identification of semiotic
      elements in a semi-structured clinical interview conducted by an experienced evaluator and
      trained in the award of these tools (in this case the clinical psychologist in charge of the
      study). They are not filled by patients, it is the investigator (psychologist) who asks
      questions based on these questionnaires, but that can be formulated differently in different
      patients.

      MINI (Mini International Neuropsychiatric Inventory) (Sheehan et al., 1998; Lecrubier et al.,
      1998). This is a must-semi-structured interview guide in psychological research, the use of
      which is part of the professional practice of psychologist. This inventory is to gather
      information and semiotic elements to assist in the diagnosis of certain psychiatric disorders
      according to DSM-IV. Modules A (major depressive disorder), B (dysthymia), I (post-traumatic
      stress disorder), O (GAD) and L (psychotic disorders) MINI will be used to assess the
      presence or absence of disorders mood (major depression, dysthymia), anxiety disorders
      (generalized anxiety or post-traumatic stress, assess relevant in our study by the
      traumatogenic dimension of Stroke) and identify subjects which present a psychotic disorder
      to not to include in the study, mainly because of their altered perception of reality. In
      addition, the module for psychotic disorders is introduced to the patient by telling him that
      now the invastigator will ask him questions about some unusual or bizarre experiments that
      can occur in some people. &quot;Thereby depersonalize maintenance reassurance on the fact that
      these issues are part of a standard valuation method and they are not raised in order to
      argue a diagnostic hypothesis concerning him .

      MADRS (10 items) (Montgomery and Asberg Depression Rating Scale) (Montgomery and Asberg,
      1979; Lempérière, 1984) will be used to assess the intensity of depressive symptoms. This
      scale is the reference scale in this area, it includes ten items that assess different
      aspects of depressive symptomatology.

      HAM-A (14 items) (Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale) (Hamilton, 1959 Pichot, 1959) is a scale for
      measuring state anxiety. This scale have an intensity score of general anxiety, consisting of
      two sub-scores for somatic anxiety one hand, and on the other psychic anxiety.

      • Self evaluation These tools are questionnaires that are completed by the person who
      self-evaluated.

      BDI-II (21 items) (Beck Depression Inventory 2nd ed) assesses the severity of depressive
      symptoms. Twenty-one groups of statements on the different symptoms of depression are
      available, the patient selects the one that best matches how he feels. The advantage of
      choosing this tool is that it assesses different aspects of depression both in terms of
      physical symptoms that cognitive and emotional.

      HADS (14 items) (Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale). This scale assesses the severity of
      depressive and anxious symptomatology. This is the most used tool in all somatic diseases and
      neurological particular. This survey presents the advantage of being very short, while
      assessing symptoms both somatic and psychological symptomatology of these.

      Brief-COPE (28 items):

      This questionnaire assesses 14 separate dimensions of coping (two items per dimensions):
      active coping, planning, instrumental support, emotional support, expression of feelings,
      positive reinterpretation, acceptance, denial, blame, humor, religion, entertainment,
      substance use and disengagement behavioral.

      WHOQOL BREF is a scale assessing the quality of life using 26 items, including two related to
      the overall quality of life. This questionnaire allows us to understand dimensionally the
      subjective perception of the person's life, in the different fields that can compose.
      Physical health: including aspects such as pain, fatigue or working abilities; mental health:
      composed among others by the positive and negative emotions and self-esteem; social
      relations: including personal, private life or the available social support; and finally the
      living environment with elements such as financial resources, access to information
      resources, recreation, etc ...

      • Ambulatory Measures: ESM / EMA These measures will be carried out via a smartphone app. The
      selected items are from previous studies that measured these variables, or built specifically
      for the study on the basis of validated tools.

      Symptoms of depression and anxiety: the symptoms of depression and anxiety present in the
      DSM-IV-TR and show a variability in a day will be assessed dimensionally on a Likert scale 7
      points. Eg for depression: sad mood, anhedonia, fatigue, difficulty concentrating, negative /
      pessimistic thoughts.

      Life events: questions will focus on the occurrence in the last three hours of events that
      have a positive impact on one hand, and negative on the other. Participants should indicate
      the specific areas of life for these events.

      strategies to adapt to stressful events: coping strategies will be evaluated by adapting the
      questions brief-COPE. Participants will indicate how they reacted to the negative event
      previously identified by selecting from a list of statements those that match their response,
      for example: &quot;I turned (e) to work or other activities to take my mind. &quot;

      Evaluation methods used at different times of the study:

      Preservation and analysis of data:

      A basic anonymous data will be created. Only the investigator will have access to the
      concordance table to link the questionnaires completed by patients with data in the database
      is created.

      The statistical study will be conducted by the investigator himself locally in the hospital
      Saint Joseph group. There will be no exchange of data. Different statistical tests will be
      used to analyze the data: analyzes of variances, correlations, regressions. Investigators
      will try and update significant associations between depressive and anxious symptoms, coping
      and quality of life during the first months after stroke, controlling the influence variables
      effect (neurological status, level autonomy, hospital stay and time of return home, etc ...).
      Investigators will compare the evolution of different dimensions between the two subgroups of
      patients (back home or inpatient rehabilitation T1 service).

      Medical information on stroke and data on the effects (cognitive and motor functions
      affected, severity of sequelae, areas in which autonomy would eventually be reduced, type and
      location of stroke, etc ...) will be account when analyzing the results to investigate the
      possible existence of links between and anxiety and depression levels.

      The data stored on smartphones will be transferred directly to the smartphone to the computer
      that will store the data; is hosted on a secure server certified. In this case, the server
      will either already obtained the necessary authorizations CNIL; or an application will be
      made.

      Expected results

      The general clinical significance of this project is to determine the elements for
      identifying, at the time of initial hospitalization following a stroke, patients at risk of
      adversely psychological evolution as physical and medical condition allows them to quickly
      return home.

      The results will have an interest in both the assessment on the management of post-stroke
      psychiatric disorders: distinguishing characteristics of depression and anxiety consecutive
      in this event in order to facilitate the diagnosis from the acute phase stroke and direct
      support. The symptomatological risk profiles can thus be detected and specific therapies on
      the prominent symptoms such disorders in the field of stroke may be proposed and / or
      developed.

      Moreover, the results will enable a greener and more detailed understanding of the process
      connecting the individual coping strategies, post-stroke psychological problems and quality
      of life in various important time of the disease.

      project interests Our project has several interests. First, it provides a longitudinal study
      tracking over the first months post-stroke, combining several complementary assessment
      methods that will enable a more comprehensive representation of psychological manifestations:
      standardized tools traditionally used and more environmentally friendly methods.

      This design study should provide a better understanding of psychic and their development at
      key stages of life process for patients after stroke (hospitalization in another service,
      return home).

      Several clinical implications are expected: develop prevention of post-stroke psychological
      problems by allowing the specific identification of depression and anxiety from the acute
      phase; identify targeted supported on the specifics of these disorders in the field of
      stroke; improve Supported favoring the development of coping strategies associated with
      long-term mental health and to reduce those associated with negative development; understand
      how these healthy patients after stroke and quickly return home, live these important steps
      to provide support tailored to suit their specific needs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 13, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 11, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment the change of WHOQOL BREF (Life QUALITY) change</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (Day 0 outside the neurovascular unit).T2 (Month 2 after Cerebral Stoke). T3 (Month 4 After Cerebral Stoke)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment the change of MINI (Mini International Neuropsychiatric Inventory) score</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (Day 4-7 after Cerebral Stoke). T3 (Month 4 after Cerebral Stoke)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment the change of MADRS (Montgoméry and Asberg Depression Rating Scale) score</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (Day 4-7 after Cerebral Stoke). T3 (Month 4 after Cerebral Stoke)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment the change of HAM-A (Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale) score</measure>
    <time_frame>T0 (Day 4-7 after Cerebral Stoke). T3 (Month 4 after Cerebral Stoke)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment the change of BDI-II (Beck Depression Inventory 2e ed) score</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (Day 0 outside the neurovascular unit).T2 (Month 2 after Cerebral Stoke). T3 (Month 4 After Cerebral Stoke)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment the change of HADS (Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale) score</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (Day 0 outside the neurovascular unit).T2 (Month 2 after Cerebral Stoke). T3 (Month 4 After Cerebral Stoke)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment the change of Brief-COPE score</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (Day 0 outside the neurovascular unit).T2 (Month 2 after Cerebral Stoke). T3 (Month 4 After Cerebral Stoke)</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire assesses 14 separate dimensions of coping (two items per dimensions): active coping, planning, instrumental support, emotional support, expression of feelings, positive reinterpretation, acceptance, denial, blame, humor, religion, entertainment, substance use and disengagement Behavioural</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment the change of ESM score</measure>
    <time_frame>T1 (Day 0 outside the neurovascular unit).T2 (Month 2 after Cerebral Stoke). T3 (Month 4 After Cerebral Stoke)</time_frame>
    <description>These measures will be carried out via a smartphone app. Symptoms of depression and anxiety: the symptoms of depression and anxiety present in the DSM-IV-TR and show a variability in a day will be assessed dimensionally on a Likert scale 7 points. Eg for depression: sad mood, anhedonia, fatigue, difficulty concentrating, negative / pessimistic thoughts.
Life events: questions will focus on the occurrence in the last three hours of events that have a positive impact on one hand, and negative on the other. Participants should indicate the specific areas of life for these events .
strategies to adapt to stressful events: coping strategies will be evaluated by adapting the questions brief-COPE. Participants will indicate how they reacted to the negative event previously identified by selecting from a list of st</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>patients who return home</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>patients who continued hospitalization in rehabilitation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>survey</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients who accept will be seen in maintenance during hospitalization in Neuro-Vascular Unit (UNV) (T0 = 4 to 7 days post-stroke)
At the time of the release of the UNV two groups:
patients who return home and
patients who continued hospitalization in rehabilitation. Depression, anxiety, quality of life and coping strategies will be assessed by self-administered questionnaires. A first phase of ambulatory (ESM / EMA) will also take place following the (UNV) output: 5 times a day for 7 days patients will respond to questions evaluating depression, anxiety and coping strategies. Patients will answer these questions via a smartphone app (issues ESM).
Another ambulatory phase on the same model as that performed at T1 (5 times daily for 7 days) accompanied by a self-assessment of depression, anxiety, coping strategies and quality of life will made 2 months post-stroke (T2).
The last time the study will take place 4 months after stroke onset (T3).</description>
    <arm_group_label>patients who continued hospitalization in rehabilitation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  over 18 years,

          -  first diagnosis of ischemic or hemorrhagic stroke,

          -  with a rapid recovery prognosis from hospitalization in intensive care (NIHSS score
             less than or equal to 6 at the output of the intensive care unit).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosis of other somatic or neurological chronic,

          -  Current diagnosis of psychotic disorder or past,

          -  Diagnosis of dementia,

          -  Severe aphasia (NIHSS subscore),

          -  Visual or motor disabilities prevent participation in the study (subscores NIHSS),

          -  Reduced autonomy (Rankin score greater than 3).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mathieu ZUBER, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Groupe Hopitalier Paris Saint Joseph Service de neurologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <state>Ile-de-France</state>
        <zip>75014</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alpers GW. Ambulatory assessment in panic disorder and specific phobia. Psychol Assess. 2009 Dec;21(4):476-85. doi: 10.1037/a0017489. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19947782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

