<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02774395</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-AOI-09</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02774395</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endometrial Cancer and Fractalkine-receptor Axis of Fractalkine</brief_title>
  <official_title>Endometrial Cancer and Fractalkine-receptor Axis of Fractalkine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nice</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The endometrial cancers are among the most common malignancies in postmenopausal women with
      an incidence on the rise. It is most often a endometrioid adenocarcinoma (grade I, II, III).
      Other histological types are represented mainly by the clear cell carcinoma, papillary serous
      carcinoma, the carcinosarcoma. The main risk factors for endometrial cancer are age, obesity,
      diabetes, hypertension, hormone replacement therapy with estrogen and tamoxifen.

      Endometrial hyperplasia usually precedes endometrial cancer is classified by degree of
      cytologic atypia. Tumor grade quantifies the degree of differentiation and significantly
      influences the prognosis. Most research has been applied to define the role of estrogen in
      these cancers, however an accumulation of data indicate that the general process of
      tumorigenesis is closely related to immune and inflammatory microenvironment of the tumor. In
      fact, the microenvironment may be seen as a prognostic parameter of tumors or even predictive
      of therapeutic response.

      Recognized as the key molecules responsible for leukocyte recruitment into the tissues, the
      chemokine-receptor pairs are key players in the immune response, including the anti-tumor
      immune response but also the inflammatory response. The chemokine-receptor pairs are also
      involved in many other basic processes such as proliferation, survival or cell death.

      The objective of this study was to evaluate the prognostic value of the expression of the
      chemokine fractalkine (FKN) and its receptor CX3CR1 for the development of endometrioid
      adenocarcinomas.

      Chemokine FKN has the particularity to exist in two forms, a soluble (FKNs), like all
      chemokines and membrane form (FKNm). The FKNs, resulting from proteolytic cleavage of the
      FKNm, is provided with chémoattractantes properties. FKNm the present adhesion molecule
      properties.

      The role of FKN in cancer biology is complex.

      To date, the role of FKN in endometrial cancer has not been reported. Similarly, the precise
      role of FKN in the physiology of the endometrium is unknown.

      Nevertheless, fractalkine is one of the most expressed in endometrial chemokines. The
      expression of FKN and its CX3CR1 receptor is detected in the endometrium at all stages of the
      menstrual cycle. The respective levels of expression of each are fluctuating and largely
      dependent on the cycle of stage suggesting a possible control by estrogen and progesterone
      control described elsewhere ovarian level and endothelial. The cells of the endometrial
      glandular epithelium, macrophages, neutrophils and NK cells infiltrated in this tissue as
      well as the endothelial cells of blood vessels express FKN. Interestingly, all the cells
      mentioned above express CX3CR1, except for NK cells and unlike most tissues, the CD8 cells,
      present in the endometrium, do not express CX3CR1.

      In addition, the strongest expression of FKN and CX3CR1 cells by endometrial epithelial
      coincides with the maximum activity of the glandular epithelium suggesting a possible
      autocrine loop promoting cell proliferation of the endometrium. Concurrently with the peak of
      fractalkine, an accumulation of monocytes / macrophages and neutrophils is observed in the
      endometrium. It appears, moreover, that the balance between the soluble and membrane forms of
      FKN is important for positioning, infiltration and activity of immune cells within the
      endometrium.

      Current knowledge on the involvement of FKN / CX3CR1 axis in the physiology of the
      endometrium, although incomplete, point unequivocally the potential role of this ligand pair
      / receptor in the physiology of the tissue and also suggest that a malfunction of this axis
      could easily cause various diseases.

      Chronic inflammation of a tissue, largely dependent on macrophage infiltration rate,
      generally represents the tumor development. The endometrium is subjected to physiologically
      cyclic and regular inflammatory episodes, mirrors for the expression of chemokines and
      leukocyte infiltration. However, prolonged leukocyte infiltration establishing chronic or
      prolonged inflammation of the endometrium could help shape a favorable microenvironment in
      tumor development. Curiously, the axis FKN / CX3CR1 is involved in the development of several
      inflammatory diseases, including obesity and diabetes are also risk factors for endometrial
      cancer.

      A change in the expression of FKN and / or CX3CR1 is potentially capable of altering the
      inflammatory physiological cycle of the endometrium and therefore likely to be an element to
      consider in the evaluation of cancer risk factors of the endometrium.

      The assumption is that the FKN / CX3CR1 couple could intervene in the pathophysiology of
      endometrioid adenocarcinomas.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>expression rate of FKN</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>expression rate of CX3CR1</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>expression rate of the couple FKN / CX3CR1</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>relationship between the expression levels of the couple FKN / CX3CR1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>infiltration rate of certain leukocyte populations</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>expression rate of estrogen receptor</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>expression rate of progesterone hormones</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>expression rate of mitotic index or tumor grade</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>endometrioid adenocarcinoma grade I</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>endometrioid adenocarcinoma grade II</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>endometrioid adenocarcinoma garde III</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy endometrioid</arm_group_label>
    <description>obtain after hysterectomia provided for</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      endometrioid adenocarcinoma and healthy endometrioid (obtain after hysterectomia)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients suffering from endometrial hypertrophy or endometrial cancer
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients suffering from endometrial hypertrophy or endometrial cancer

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jerome DELOTTE, PHD</last_name>
    <email>delotte.j@chu-nice.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>mélanie Bonnard</last_name>
    <email>bonnard.m@chu-nice.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Nice</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <zip>06200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>jerome DELOTTE</last_name>
      <email>delotte.j@chu-nice.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>melanie BONNARD</last_name>
      <email>bonnard.m@chu-nice.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 13, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 17, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 17, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

