<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02778321</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SPIDERFLASH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02778321</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Study Evaluating the Interest of Long-term Cardiac Recording in Cerebral Infarction</brief_title>
  <acronym>SPIDERFLASH</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Study Evaluating the Interest of Long-term Cardiac Recording in Cerebral Infarction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cerebral infarction (CI) can be linked to atherosclerosis of large vessels, occlusion of
      small vessels intracerebral (gaps), a cardioembolic disease or other rare causes. However, up
      to 40% of CI remains unexplained after a thorough diagnostic workup. They are called
      cryptogenic IC.

      Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the cause of 25% of the CI but it is recognized that episodes of
      paroxysmal AF, asymptomatic and unnoticed, may be responsible for a portion of the IC
      cryptogenic pace. Recognition of these episodes is of great importance since they have the
      same risk embolic the FA continues [1, 2] and motivate anticoagulant therapy startup.

      Several recording techniques heart rate were evaluated after the IC for detecting the AF.
      Their profitability increases with the duration of the recording: about 3% for a typical
      24-hour Holter, the AF detection rate increases to 6% for a 7-day surveillance period, to
      12-23% for 30 days and 17-26% with implantable recorders long.

      Otherwise brief rhythmic heart abnormalities can be detected with the waning of an CI without
      the significance of these episodes is known.

      Investigators decided to conduct this study because there is no prospective study of good
      quality with a sufficient number of patients that evaluated the interest of a non-invasive
      recording of long duration. The only randomized CRYSTAL AF is used for invasive subcutaneous
      implantable monitor (Reveal XT).

      To clarify the significance of arrhythmias and because the presence of several causes is
      common after 65, investigators propose to record all patients hospitalized for HF.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Main objective / secondary The objectives of our study were to assess the prevalence of AF in
      patients hospitalized for an IC and to detect and describe all heart rhythmic abnormalities
      reported immediately to the waning of an IC cryptogenic (ie without cause or without obvious
      cause ) for non-invasive cardiac monitoring.

        1. The primary endpoint: number of patients in whom it was found AF

        2. Secondary Endpoints: typical patient subgroups in which it was discovered AF and other
           rhythm abnormalities; Description of the population under prescribed anticoagulation
           following SpiderFlash® recordings, cardiac ultrasound parameters (including the surface
           of the left atrium and the index of the function of the mitral annulus) and rhythmic
           anomalies in groups with atheromatous and cryptogenic stroke.

      Inclusion / non inclusion Inclusion criteria

        -  Patients over 65 years, hospitalized for cerebral infarction ICU Neurovascular

        -  No history of atrial fibrillation or flutter

        -  No hypercoagulable

        -  Patient unopposed and capable of carrying 21-day monitoring Exclusion criteria

        -  Patients with severe cognitive impairment that can not keep SpiderFlash® for 21 days

        -  Previous history of AF or flutter

        -  Significant artery stenosis requiring specific treatment (endarterectomy or stenting)

        -  FA on arrival at the ICU Neurovascular

        -  Trucks of a pacemaker or cardiac defibrillator

        -  Deadline for the IC more than 10 days

        -  Other sources of cardiac embolism

        -  Pejorative prognosis (mRS≥5)

      The IC is defined as a central focal neurological deficit of sudden onset and is confirmed by
      a CT scan or MRI.

      The minimum workup includes ECG monitoring by continuous cardiac monitoring, transthoracic
      echocardiography (transesophageal +/-) and a Doppler ultrasound of the supra-aortic trunks
      and transcranial.

      Methodology :

      This is an interventional study in routine care, prospective, single-center, blinded for
      heart rhythm specialist.

      Investigators will use the SpiderFlash®, Holter monitor (technology &quot;Secure Data&quot;) to have a
      storage capacity enabling a registration up to 30 days with sufficient autonomy. The
      SpiderFlash® is currently registered in the GHPSJ for use in various directions including
      through cryptogenic cerebral infarction.

      The data collected will (see Annex 2 CRF):

        -  Demographic data: age, sex, vascular risk factors, antithrombotic therapy at the
           entrance, history of Transient Ischemic Accident (TIA) or CI

        -  Data on the IC: arterial territory, side (right / left) or insular cortex reached
           severity (NIHSS score) made further examinations, echocardiography result, become during
           hospitalization (mRS)

        -  Monitoring Results scope ICU Neurovascular.

        -  Presence palpitations

        -  Treatment influencing the rate (beta-blockers or antiarrhythmic)

        -  Data on cardiac monitoring: time, duration, number of detected events

      A questionnaire evaluating the safety of SpiderFlash® will be given to the patient (Appendix
      3) and the results of Holter will be communicated at the end of the recording (as will be
      shown them in the Circular).

      During a screening period of one month, 33 eligible patients over 65 admitted to CI 17
      patients (51%) were identified including 9 with cryptogenic CI 8 and having either a
      non-significant atheroma is a rhythm disorder ( ESSV or atrial hyperexcitability). Among 16
      ineligible patients, 4 had severe dementia, 11 had previous FA to 1 significant extracranial
      stenosis.

      The patient recruitment period will be one year for one further year or two-year inclusion
      period to recruit 200 patients originally planned to study (the first year of inclusion has
      allowed us to include 73 patients) The data will be entered manually on paper CRF and Excel
      anonymized so not including the patient identifiers (name or IPP).

      The originality of our study:

        -  Prospective study

        -  Inclusion of CI cryptogenic and non cryptogenic

        -  Laying SpiderFlash® early after CI

        -  Correlation with cardiac ultrasound parameters

        -  Analysis by the blind rhythm specialist (will not be aware of patient characteristics)

        -  Changing all events while recording (not just the passages FA)

        -  Questionnaire &quot;comfort&quot; given to the patient

      Investigators specify that the data on the comfort of the patient questionnaire will not be
      transferred to the company Sorin; this questionnaire meets strict medical interest (including
      estimate the patient's ability to carry equipment during the full period).

      Ethics / Regulatory:

      The data processing will be carried out locally on the GHPSJ of anonymized way. The inclusion
      of patients will occur after patient information collection and its non-opposition traced in
      his medical records (Appendix 1). The data will be entered by the vascular neurologist
      anonymously. All patient information will remain confidential.

      partnerships:

      The Sorin company, manufacturer of SpiderFlash® provide (loan) material in sufficient
      quantity for the duration of the study.

      The GHPSJ: neurologist time and CRA The SELARL rythmo: time heart rhythm specialists
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 17, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>NIHSS score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SCOPE at ICU neurovascular</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Monitoring Results scope ICU neurovascular.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence palpitations</measure>
    <time_frame>During the 30 days of monitoring</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment influencing the rate</measure>
    <time_frame>During the 30 days of monitoring</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment influencing the rate (beta blockers or antiarrhythmic drugs)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>During the 30 days of monitoring</time_frame>
    <description>Data concerning cardiac monitoring: time, duration, number of detected events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">108</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuropathology</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients admitted in ICU neurovascular</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Uses of SpiderFlash monitor</intervention_name>
    <description>Investigators will use the SpiderFlash®, Holter monitor (technology &quot;Secure Data&quot;) to have a storage capacity enabling a registration up to 30 days with sufficient autonomy.
The data collected :
Demographic data: age, sex, vascular risk factors, antithrombotic therapy at the entrance, history of Transient Ischemic Accident (TIA) or Cerebral infarct (CI)
Data on the CI:
Monitoring Results scope ICU Neurovascular.
Presence palpitations
Treatment influencing the rate (beta-blockers or antiarrhythmic)
Data on cardiac monitoring:
A questionnaire evaluating the safety of SpiderFlash® will be given to the patient and the results of Holter will be communicated at the end of the recording to the blinded rhythm specialist</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients admitted in ICU neurovascular</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ICU Neurovascular hospitalized for cerebral infarction CI

          -  No history of atrial fibrillation or flutter

          -  No hypercoagulable

          -  Patient unopposed and capable of carrying 21-day monitoring

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with severe cognitive impairment that can not keep SpiderFlash® for 21 days

          -  Previous history of AF or flutter

          -  Significant artery stenosis requiring specific treatment (endarterectomy or stenting)

          -  FA on arrival at the ICU Neurovascular

          -  Trucks of a pacemaker or cardiac defibrillator

          -  Deadline for the CI more than 10 days

          -  Other sources of cardiac embolism

          -  Pejorative prognosis (mRS≥5)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mathieu ZUBER</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint-Joseph (FRANCE)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <state>Ile-de-France</state>
        <zip>75014</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

