<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02770742</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HRC[058465]</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02770742</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient Satisfaction With Sedated vs. Unsedated Colonoscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Patient Satisfaction With Sedated vs. Unsedated Colonoscopy - Which Factors Affect Satisfaction and Pain in Routine Care?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Helios Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Helios Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, observational study to evaluate patient satisfaction with colonoscopy,
      depending on whether sedation is used during the procedure or not. Patients will receive
      questionnaires before the procedure to assess the potential influence of patient criteria and
      after the procedure to assess satisfaction-scores and pain-scores. A validated satisfaction
      score (Schoen et al.) will be used for the primary outcome. As secondary parameters, pain-
      and sedation-scores will be assessed by the validated NAPCOMS score, as well as procedural
      quality indicators. The study will assess, whether adequate selection in regards to risk
      factors for sedated or unsedated colonoscopy, leads to similar satisfaction-scores within
      both groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, observational study of consecutive patients presenting for outpatient
      colonoscopy in a tertiary care hospital with a large ambulatory care section (DKD Helios
      Klinik Wiesbaden). The primary endpoint of the study is the comparison of a validated patient
      satisfaction score in patients undergoing colonoscopy with or without sedation. The aim is to
      assess whether patients, who are deemed appropriate for an unsedated procedure by predefined
      risk factors and who wish to avoid sedation, will have similar satisfaction scores, as those
      who undergo sedation. As secondary aims, pain scores (validated NAPCOMS score) and markers of
      procedural quality (such as completion rates or withdrawal times) will be assessed.

      Considering a 2-point difference in the 15-point satisfaction score as clinically relevant
      and suspecting a 7:3 distribution of procedures with and without sedation, respectively, 1070
      patients must be included (at least 749 sedated and 321 unsedated) in order to reach a
      significance level of 0.05.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction-score (Schoen et al.)</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1-2 weeks after the procedure</time_frame>
    <description>The satisfaction score is based on the following three statements: (a) &quot;I was very satisfied with the care I received&quot;; (b) &quot;I would strongly recommend this procedure to friends who qualify for it&quot;; (c) &quot;I would be willing to repeat the exam in the future if necessary.&quot; Each statement is coded on a 5−point ordinate scale that includes the following choices: strongly agree, agree, not sure, disagree and strongly disagree. The average of the scores for the three statements will be used as the satisfaction score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NAPCOMS score</measure>
    <time_frame>within the procedure and modified 1-2 weeks after the procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>The NAPCOMS was designed to be completed by the endoscopy nurse assisting during the procedure. It is a composite measure that includes 3 domains: pain, sedation, and a global subjective assessment of tolerability.
The pain domain is defined by using the dimensions of intensity, frequency, and duration, which are each rated with a score from 0 (no occurrence) to 3 (severe, frequent, or prolonged). Sedation is rated according to level of consciousness ranging from 0 (wide awake) to 3 (unconscious), whereas the global tolerability score is rated from 0 (very well tolerated) to 3 (poorly tolerated). The Overall NAPCOMS was defined as the sum of the severity, frequency, and duration of pain domains. Level of sedation and overall global tolerability ratings are assessed separately.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1070</enrollment>
  <condition>Satisfaction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients for outpatient colonoscopy</arm_group_label>
    <description>The cohort consists of subsequent patients who present for routine colonoscopy. There is no active Intervention. However, groups who choose to perform colonoscopy with or without sedation will be compared.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Consecutive patients, presenting for outpatient colonoscopy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Consecutive patients presenting for colonoscopy

          -  Age &gt;18 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients not giving written consent

          -  Colonic stenosis or suspected Stenosis

          -  Active inflammatory bowel disease

          -  Previous partial resection of the colon

          -  Polyposis syndromes

          -  Inability to speak German or fill out a questionnaire in German language

          -  Vulnerable patients (prisoners, pregnant women, patients with mental retardation,
             which would affect filling out a questionnaire or answering questions)

          -  American Society of Anesthesiology (ASA) grade &gt; III.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexander J Eckardt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>DKD Helios Klinik Wiesbaden, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexander J. Eckardt, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 611 577 14 245</phone>
    <email>alexander.eckardt@helios-kliniken.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michaela Müller, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+ 49 611 577 14 248</phone>
    <email>michaela-mueller@helios-kliniken.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DKD Helios Klinik Wiesbaden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wiesbaden</city>
        <state>Hesse</state>
        <zip>65191</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexander J. Eckardt, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 611 577 14245</phone>
      <email>alexander.eckardt@helios-kliniken.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eckardt VF, Kanzler G, Schmitt T, Eckardt AJ, Bernhard G. Complications and adverse effects of colonoscopy with selective sedation. Gastrointest Endosc. 1999 May;49(5):560-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10228252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petrini JL, Egan JV, Hahn WV. Unsedated colonoscopy: patient characteristics and satisfaction in a community-based endoscopy unit. Gastrointest Endosc. 2009 Mar;69(3 Pt 1):567-72. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.10.027.</citation>
    <PMID>19231501</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eckardt AJ, Swales C, Bhattacharya K, Wassef WY, Phelan NP, Zubair S, Martins N, Patel S, Moquin B, Anwar N, Leung K, Levey JM. Open access colonoscopy in the training setting: which factors affect patient satisfaction and pain? Endoscopy. 2008 Feb;40(2):98-105. doi: 10.1055/s-2007-995469.</citation>
    <PMID>18253904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cockburn J, Hill D, Irwig L, De Luise T, Turnbull D, Schofield P. Development and validation of an instrument to measure satisfaction of participants at breast screening programmes. Eur J Cancer. 1991;27(7):827-31.</citation>
    <PMID>1834111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schoen RE, Weissfeld JL, Baum A. Development of a simple instrument to measure patient satisfaction with flexible sigmoidoscopy. Gastroenterology 1995; 108: A34</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 12, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Helios Research Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alexander Eckardt</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PD Dr. med. Alexander Eckardt</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>patient satisfaction</keyword>
  <keyword>unsedated colonoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>intestinal diseases</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

