<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02773277</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>vHIT_surgery</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02773277</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Assessment of Peripheral-vestibular Function After Skull Base Surgery</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Zurich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Due to its localization in the cerebello-pontine angle, the vestibulo-cochlear nerve is at
      risk to damage during surgery performed nearby. In most cases, peripheral-cochleovestibular
      hypofunction recovers over the following weeks as the mechanism of damage is rather
      demyelination than axonal damage. The rate, intensity and extent of recovery of such
      perioperative peripheral-vestibular damage is not known.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Due to its localization in the cerebello-pontine angle, the vestibulo-cochlear nerve is at
      risk to damage during surgery performed nearby, e.g. when removing an epidermoid cyst,
      treating a neuro-vascular conflict of the trigeminal nerve or resecting a petroclival
      meningeoma. Intense vertigo and dizziness accompanied by spontaneous nystagmus following
      Alexander's law, nausea and gait imbalance may be noted in these patients along with cochlear
      hypofunction (hearing loss). In most cases, peripheral-cochleovestibular hypofunction
      recovers over the following weeks as the mechanism of damage is rather demyelination than
      axonal damage. The rate, intensity and extent of recovery of such perioperative
      peripheral-vestibular damage is not known. Besides peripheral-vestibular hypofunction,
      transient cerebellar hypofunction may arise, presenting with similar complaints (vertigo,
      nausea, gait imbalance), however, distinct subtle ocular motor findings.

      The aim of this study is to characterize the frequency and pattern of iatrogenic
      peripheral-vestibular and cochlear hypofunction and to follow-up on the speed and extent of
      recovery. The investigators hypothesize that peripheral-vestibular and cochlear damage may be
      observed in a significant fraction of neurosurgical treatments in the posterior fossa
      including the cerebello-pontine angle. While initially deficits may be major, recovery is
      expected to be substantial or even complete due to peripheral restoration. As an important
      differential diagnosis, the investigators will evaluate also for potential (transient)
      cerebellar loss of function.

      In order to quantify peripheral-vestibular function the investigators will use a CE-certified
      videooculography device to record responses to the head-impulse test before and in the days
      following elective skull base surgery. the video-head impulse test (vHIT) allows a
      quantitative video-based assessment of the functional integrity of all semicircular canals
      (MacDougall et al. 2013). By use of a high-speed video-camera mounted on goggles this test
      quantifies the vestibulo-ocular reflex (VOR), which is the fastest human reflex and allows
      the recognition and visual fixation of objects while head turns or ambulation. This test is
      used on a routine basis in our clinic and includes brief and fast, but small amplitude head
      turns (10-15째 excursion) in the planes of the different semi-circular canals (SCCs). The SCCs
      are tested in three pairs in the horizontal, RALP (right anterior, left posterior) and LARP
      (left anterior, right posterior) plane (Weber et al. 2008). During testing the participant is
      asked to fixate a visual target straight ahead. Duration of this test: about 15 minutes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>gain of the angular vestibulo-ocular reflex</measure>
    <time_frame>comparison before surgery and up to 30 days post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>in all patients the mean gain for each semicircular canal will be determined</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative saccade amplitudes per trial [째/trial] of the angular vestibulo-ocular reflex</measure>
    <time_frame>comparison before surgery and up to 30 days post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>in all patients the cumulative saccade amplitudes per trial for each semicircular canal will be determined</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>clinical testing of the horizontal head-impulse test</measure>
    <time_frame>comparison before surgery and up to 30 days post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>besides the vHIT, patients will be examined clinically, including testing for central-type acute vestibular syndrome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>clinical testing for gaze-evoked nystagmus</measure>
    <time_frame>comparison before surgery and up to 30 days post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>besides the vHIT, patients will be examined clinically, including testing for central-type acute vestibular syndrome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>clinical testing for skew deviation by use of the alternating cover test</measure>
    <time_frame>comparison before surgery and up to 30 days post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>besides the vHIT, patients will be examined clinically, including testing for central-type acute vestibular syndrome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Vestibular</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single intervention arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will be assigned the intervention arm and will receive head-impulse testing before and in the days after skull base surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>head-impulse testing</intervention_name>
    <description>all patients will receive quantitative head impulse testing using video goggles for all six semicircular canals.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single intervention arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. aged 18 years or older

          2. informed consent

          3. absence of exclusion criteria

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. peripheral-vestibular deficit before surgery

          2. disturbed consciousness

          3. diagnosis of vestibular schwannoma

          4. other neurological or systemic disorder which can cause dementia or cognitive
             dysfunction

          5. known neck pain or status post neck trauma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Niklaus Krayenb체hl, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Zurich, Neurology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Niklaus Krayenb체hl, MD</last_name>
    <phone>044 255 11 11</phone>
    <email>Niklaus.Krayenbuehl@usz.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alexander Tarnutzer, MD</last_name>
    <phone>044 255 11 11</phone>
    <email>alexander.tarnutzer@usz.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 13, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

