<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02777554</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CC-10004-CP-035</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02777554</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Open Label Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetic Exposure of Apremilast in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open Label, Randomized, Two Part Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetic Exposure of a Once-Daily (QD) Apremilast Formulation Relative to the Twice-Daily (BID) Reference Immediate Release (IR) Tablet and the Effect of Food on the QD Apremilast Formulation in Healthy Subjects.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Celgene</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Celgene</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will be conducted in 2 Parts. The purpose of this study is to measure how much of
      apremilast is found in the blood when administered as a once daily tablet compared to a twice
      a day tablet, when given as multiple doses (Part 1) and when administered as a single dose
      under fasting and fed conditions (Part 2). Information on the safety and tolerability of
      apremilast will also be obtained. In addition, the effect of apremilast on certain biomarkers
      in the blood will be evaluated in 16 assigned subjects (Part 1 only). Biomarkers are
      substances such as proteins that tell us how the study drug is working in your body.

      Part 1: This is a multi-center, phase 1, open-label, randomized, two-period, two-sequence,
      crossover study in healthy subjects. The study will consist of a screening phase, a baseline
      phase, two treatment periods, and a follow-up phone call. Each Period will be ten days in
      duration (Day 1 through Day 10) for dosing and sample collection for up to 72 hours post Day
      7 morning dose of Periods 1 and 2. There will be a washout between Period 1 and Period 2.
      Part 2: This is a single center, open-label, randomized, four-period, four-sequence crossover
      study to evaluate the PK and exposure of apremilast following single dose administration of
      different formulations of apremilast. Part 2 will consist of a Screening phase, Baseline,
      four Treatment periods, and a follow-up phone call. Each Period will be four days in duration
      (Day 1 through Day 4) for dosing and sample collection for up to 72 hours post Day 1 of
      Period 1, 2, 3, and 4.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Objectives

      Part 1 Primary Objectives To evaluate the pharmacokinetics (PK) and exposure of apremilast
      following multiple-dose administration of a QD apremilast formulation relative to the BID
      reference IR tablet under the fed condition with a standard meal.

      Secondary Objectives To evaluate the safety and tolerability of a QD apremilast formulation
      and the BID reference IR tablet.

      Exploratory Objective To evaluate the pharmacodynamics (PD) of apremilast following
      multiple-dose administration of the QD apremilast formulation relative to the BID reference
      IR tablet under the fed condition with a standard meal.

      Part 2 Primary Objectives To estimate the PK and exposure of apremilast following single dose
      administration of a QD apremilast formulation relative to the BID reference IR tablet under
      the fasting condition To estimate the effect of food on the PK of a single oral dose of a QD
      apremilast formulation.

      Secondary Objectives To evaluate the safety and tolerability of a QD apremilast formulation
      and the BID reference IR tablet.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 17, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 22, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 22, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Peak maximum plasma concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak (maximum) plasma concentration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - AUC0-24</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to 24 hours postdose</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - AUC0-∞</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to infinity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - AUC0-t</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to the last observable concentration at time t</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Terminal-phase elimination half-life</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - CL/F</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Apparent clearance of drug from plasma after extravascular administration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - Vz/F</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Apparent volume of distribution during the terminal (Tz) phase after extravascular administration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - Ctrough</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Observed plasma concentration 24 hours after the morning dose on Day 7</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - Tz</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Apparent volume of distribution during the terminal phase after extravascular administration</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - Cmin</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Observed minimum plasma concentration Day 7</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - Cavg</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Average concentration during the 24- hour period on Day 7</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - tlag</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Delay between time of administration and start of absorption lag time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic - Ratio of accumulation (RA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Ratio of accumulation based on Day 1 and Day 7 area under the plasma concentration-time curve during a 24-hour period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">164</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment A: 60mg Apremilast reference IR formulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One 30 mg Immediate Release oral tablet in the morning and one 30 mg IR oral tablet in the evening of the dosing days) for 7 days under the fed condition.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment B: 75mg Apremilast Once-daily (QD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>75 mg apremilast QD formulation once daily for 7 days under the fed conditions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment C: 60 mg reference IR tablet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One 30 mg IR oral tablet administered in the morning in the fasting state and one 30 mg IR oral tablet administered in the evening after a minimum of a 2 hr fast for 1 day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment D: Single dose of QD apremilast</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of 75mg apremilast QD administered in the fasting state</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment E: Single dose of QD apremilast</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of 75mg apremilast QD administered approximately 30 minutes after a standard meal</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment F: Single dose of QD apremilast</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of 75mg apremilast QD administered approximately 30 minutes after a high-fat meal</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Apremilast</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment A: 60mg Apremilast reference IR formulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment B: 75mg Apremilast Once-daily (QD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment C: 60 mg reference IR tablet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment D: Single dose of QD apremilast</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment E: Single dose of QD apremilast</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment F: Single dose of QD apremilast</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects must satisfy the following criteria to be enrolled in the study (Part 1 and Part
        2):

          1. Must understand and voluntarily sign a written Informed consent form (ICF) prior to
             any study-related procedures being performed.

          2. Must be able to communicate with the investigator, understand and comply with the
             requirements of the study, and agree to adhere to restrictions and examination
             schedules.

          3. Male and female subjects of any race between 18 to 55 years of age (inclusive), and in
             good health as determined by the Investigator at the time of signing the informed
             consent document.

          4. Have a body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 33 kg/m2 (inclusive).

          5. No clinically significant laboratory test results as determined by the investigator.

          6. At the screening visit, must be afebrile, with supine systolic BP: 90 to 140 mmHg,
             supine diastolic BP: 50 to 90 mmHg, and pulse rate: 40 to 110 bpm. Eligibility
             criteria for vital signs performed during check-in and/or predose on Day 1 will be at
             the discretion of the Investigator.

          7. Must have a normal or clinically acceptable 12-lead Electrocardiogram (ECG). Subjects
             must have a QT interval corrected using the Fridericia formula (QTcF) value ≤ 450
             msec.

          8. Female subjects

               1. Must have a negative pregnancy test

               2. If postmenopausal: must have follicular stimulating hormone (FSH) test result &gt;
                  40 IU/L and a negative pregnancy test

          9. Contraception Requirements:

             Must comply with the following acceptable forms of contraception. All Female of child
             bearing potential (FCBP)1 must use one of the approved contraceptive options as
             described below while taking apremilast and for at least 28 days after administration
             of the last dose of the apremilast. At the time of study entry, and at any time during
             the study when a FCBP's contraceptive measures or ability to become pregnant changes,
             the Investigator will educate the subject regarding contraception options and the
             correct and consistent use of effective contraceptive methods in order to successfully
             prevent pregnancy.

             All FCBP must have a negative pregnancy test at Screening and Day -1 of each Treatment
             Period. All FCBP subjects who engage in activity in which conception is possible must
             use one of the approved contraceptive options described below:

             Option 1: Any one of the following highly effective methods: hormonal contraception
             (oral, injection, implant, transdermal patch, vaginal ring); intrauterine device
             (IUD); tubal ligation; or partner's vasectomy; OR Option 2: Male or female condom
             (latex condom or non-latex condom NOT made out of natural [animal] membrane [for
             example, polyurethane]); Plus one additional barrier(c) contraceptive sponge with
             spermicide.

             Male subjects (including those who have had a vasectomy) who engage in activity in
             which conception is possible must use barrier contraception (latex or non-latex
             condoms NOT made out of natural [animal] membrane [for example, polyurethane]) while
             on Investigational Product (IP) and for at least 28 days after the last dose of IP.

         10. Must agree to refrain from donating sperm, blood or plasma (other than for this study)
             while participating in this study and for at least 28 days after the last dose of
             investigational product.

         11. Subject is willing and able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol
             requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The presence of any of the following will exclude a subject from enrollment:

          1. History of any clinically significant and relevant neurological, psychiatric,
             gastrointestinal, renal, hepatic, cardiovascular, psychological, pulmonary, metabolic,
             endocrine, hematological, allergic disease, drug allergies, or other major disorders.

          2. Any condition which places the subject at unacceptable risk if he were to participate
             in the study, or confounds the ability to interpret data from the study.

        1 A female of childbearing potential is a sexually mature female who 1) has not undergone a
        hysterectomy (the surgical removal of the uterus) or bilateral oophorectomy (the surgical
        removal of both ovaries) or 2) has not been postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive
        months (that is, has had menses at any time during the preceding 24 consecutive months).

        3. Use of any prescribed systemic or topical medication within 30 days of the first dose
        administration (exception, FCBP may use hormonal contraception).

        4. Use of any non-prescribed systemic or topical medication (including vitamin/mineral
        supplements, and herbal medicines) within 14 days of the first dose administration.

        5. Any surgical or medical condition possibly affecting drug absorption, distribution,
        metabolism and excretion, eg, bariatric procedure, colon resection, irritable bowel
        syndrome, Crohn's disease, etc. Subjects with cholecystectomy and appendectomy may be
        included.

        6. Exposure to an investigational drug (new chemical entity) within 30 days prior to the
        first dose administration or 5 half-lives of that investigational drug, if known (whichever
        is longer). 7. Donated blood or plasma within 8 weeks before the first dose administration
        to a blood bank or blood donation center.

        8. History of drug abuse (as defined by the current version of the Diagnostic and
        Statistical Manual [DSM]) within 2 years before dosing, or a positive drug screen
        reflecting consumption of illicit drugs.

        9. History of alcohol abuse (as defined by the current version of the DSM) within 2 years
        before dosing, or a positive alcohol screen.

        10. Known to have hepatitis, or known to be a carrier of the hepatitis B surface antigen
        (HBsAg) or hepatitis C antibody (HCV Ab), or have a positive result to the test for human
        immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibodies at screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francisco Ramirez-Valle, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Celgene Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Covance-Daytona Beach</name>
      <address>
        <city>Daytona Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32117</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Covance Clinical Research Unit Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53704</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy Subjects</keyword>
  <keyword>Apremilast</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetic</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apremilast</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

