<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02776904</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>205006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02776904</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Movement Assessment for Concussion Management</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comprehensive Dynamic Movement Assessment for Concussion Management</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Arkansas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Arkansas Children's Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arkansas</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Previous work in the area of concussion management has focused heavily on neuro-cognitive
      testing. In addition to routine neuro-cognitive testing through Immediate Post-Concussion
      Assessment and Cognitive Testing (ImPACT),this pilot study is designed to establish a
      comprehensive battery of clinical assessment through the utilization of functional movement
      and dynamic postural control assessments. The immediate application of these assessments will
      be focused on the male high school football player (who is at risk for concussion) and both
      female and male soccer players. Our pilot study aims determine the stability of ImPACT
      testing in youth athletes in light of ongoing neurodevelopment in this population. In
      addition, this pilot work will implement additional tools focused on assessment of dynamic
      balance, reaction time, and agility. This approach will significantly enhance predictions of
      subsequent musculoskeletal injuries that have been shown to occur in concussed collegiate and
      professional athletes and that we believe are also occurring in our high school athletes.
      This battery of tests will provide clinicians with invaluable information to guide both
      rehabilitation of and return to play (RTP) decisions for concussed high school athletes. This
      pilot study will further track those athletes who sustain a concussion and assess increased
      risks for musculoskeletal injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Experiment 1. High school athletes will complete a battery of tests including the Star
      Excursion Balance Test (SEBT), a divided attention gait task, the Psychomotor Vigilance Task
      (PVT), and the Change of Direction (COD) Illinois agility test (IAGT). The SEBT is an
      established, reliable outcome measure of dynamic postural stability through measurement of
      lower extremity reach distance. Our study will also utilize a force plate during SEBT testing
      to allow the investigators to sensitively measure center of mass in all planes. To test gait
      balance control and adaptation of gait strategy which have been shown to be impaired in
      concussed individuals acutely and chronically, athletes will walk at self-selected speed on
      the GAITRite® portable gait analysis walkway for three undivided attention trials and three
      divided attention trials during which a cognitive task, will be imposed.The GaitRite® will
      calculate spatio-temporal parameters during gait and has been used in the concussion
      literature. The PVT is a reliable and valid measurement of simple reaction time to an
      auditory cue. The outcome measure will be the mean reaction time. The COD IAGT is a valid and
      reliable protocol to assess agility in male team athletes. This test yields a completion time
      in seconds. These tests were administered by licensed physical therapists, assisted by
      students from both the Doctorate of Physical Therapy (DPT) and PhD physical therapy programs
      at UCA, before the initiation of summer 2016 football practices for all athletes in the
      program. The total testing time per athlete will not exceed 1.5 hours. The battery will be
      administered again to all athletes in the football program after the season has ended and
      prior to the end of the school year in the spring 2017. The 2017-2018 season will test both
      football and soccer (male and female athletes) and will include functional testing for
      athletes who have had a concussion through concussion clinic.

      Experiment 2. Qualified athletic trainers or Physical Therapists, with oversight by Dr.
      Israel, will administer the ImPACT using the same schedule as described in Experiment 1. The
      ImPACT is a widely used neurocognitive testing component of the standard three-prong approach
      to concussion management which also includes symptom inventories and static balance
      assessment. The computerized test evaluates concentration, attention, memory, visual motor
      speed, and reaction time. High sensitivity and specificity for concussion using the ImPACT
      has been shown. The test also has been shown to be a valid and reliable measure in the high
      school and collegiate populations. Composite scores for each of the non-injured athletes will
      be stratified by age to examine changes across the three assessments. Hunt and Ferrara have
      shown significant change in baseline assessments between 9th grade and 11th and 12th grade
      age groups driven by 9th grade test scores indicating that biennial testing for young
      adolescents may not be sufficient.The current recommendation for this younger age group is
      annual testing, though recent studies call for the investigation of even more frequent
      testing, thus our plan to test at six months. ImPACT testing will not exceed 1 hour. The
      2017-2018 season will test both football and soccer (male and female athletes) for ImPACT
      testing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Neurocognitive score</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline through 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Auditory reaction time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline through 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Star excursion balance test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Balance test will be recorded in cm in 3 directions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Athlete</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neuro-cognitive Assessment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Immediate Post-concussion Assessment and Cognitive Testing will be administered three times (pre-season, post season and end of year) during the school year and testing will not exceed 1 hour per athlete.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Psychomotor Vigilance Task</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Psychomotor Vigilance Task will be administered to each athlete and scores will be compared to the reaction time portion of the Immediate Post-concussion Assessment and Cognitive Testing examination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Immediate Post-concussion Assessment and Cognitive Testing</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Neuro-cognitive Assessment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Psychomotor Vigilance Task</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychomotor Vigilance Task</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Psychomotor Vigilance Task</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male football players (2016 and 2017 season)

          -  Male and female soccer players (2017 season) OR Athletes who have been diagnosed with
             a sports related concussion during the season of their assigned sport and is being
             seen through concussion clinic at Arkansas children's hospital

               -  Age 14-18

               -  Written informed consent from the parent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Athletes who have not completed pre-participation physicals

          -  Any condition that the investigator determines would put the subject at risk if
             participating in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Male football players and both male and female soccer players</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Joe T. Robinson High School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72223</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langlois JA, Rutland-Brown W, Wald MM. The epidemiology and impact of traumatic brain injury: a brief overview. J Head Trauma Rehabil. 2006 Sep-Oct;21(5):375-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16983222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Concussion</keyword>
  <keyword>Football player</keyword>
  <keyword>Movement assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>Soccer player</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

