<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02773498</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC31/15/7840</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02773498</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Medical Results of Testicular Sperm Extraction by Conventional Surgery and Microsurgical Track</brief_title>
  <acronym>Microsperm</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparison of Medical Results of Testicular Sperm Extraction by Conventional Surgery and Microsurgical Track</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Toulouse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Toulouse</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To compare motile sperm extraction rate between microTESE and conventional TESE in 18-50
      years-old men with non obstructive azoospermia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      About one in ten couples cannot have children without medical assistance. Male factors for
      infertility are identified in half cases with 10% azoospermia, non-obstructive in most cases.
      Up to date, testis surgical sperm retrieval for use in ICSI-IVF is the only possibility for
      those men to have children with their own sperm. Several options are available for surgically
      retrieving sperm from testis: During conventional testicular sperm extraction (cTESE), the
      testis is exposed through a small incision, then 1 or more biopsies are randomly made. Up to
      date, cTESE is considered as the gold-standard for sperm extraction in this population.

      However, the success of surgical sperm extraction concerns a man out of two having cTESE for
      non-obstructive azoospermia.

      On the other hand, Schlegel showed in 1997 that cTESE induces a significative loss of
      testicular tissue with possible impact on male endocrine balance with occurence of hematomas,
      inflammatory reshuffles and ischaemic lesions, compromising some regions in the testicular
      parenchyme. Another option for surgical sperm extraction is micro-surgery called microTESE
      (or µTESE). It consists in examining the testicular parenchyme under a high-power microscope
      (up to 25 magnification), screening for white opaque tubules with higher diameter which
      indicates possible active spermatogenesis. The benefits of µTESE are: (1) a better
      identification of sites of sperm production in the testis, (2) a better preservation of
      testicular vasculature decreasing the risk of postoperative hematoma or tissue ischemia and
      (3) excision of 3 to 10 times less tissue.

      Nevertheless, no randomized studies have compared both techniques to validate such an
      assumption. In 2014, the results of a meta-analysis performed by Deruyver showed that, among
      the 7 original articles comparing cTESE to µTESE, 3 were retrospective studies and the
      remaining 4 prospective studies were not randomized.

      It is highly unlikely that this better outcome is related to patient selection. Nevertheless,
      the relatively small number of studies comparing both methods makes it difficult to draw
      definitive conclusions This study is based on the hypothesis that µTESE is a superior
      technique than cTESE with a difference of 20% like observed in Deruyver's meta-analysis.

      The principal objective is to compare motile sperm extraction rate between μTESE and cTESE in
      18-50 years-old men with NOA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 26, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>sperm extraction</measure>
    <time_frame>time of surgery</time_frame>
    <description>positivity (presence, coded 1) or negativity (absence, coded 0) of the sperm extraction, based on possibility of having at least 1 mobile sperm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">220</enrollment>
  <condition>Azoospermia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>conventional TESE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional multiple TESE is performed under general or locoregional anesthesia. Through a small vertical incision in the median scrotal raphe, the skin, dartos muscle, and tunica vaginalis are opened to expose the tunica albuginea. The tunica albuginea is ordinarily incised for about 4 mm at the medium region of the testis. A similar biopsy will be systematically performed in the contralateral testis. The biopsy is analyzed by the biologist in the theatre in order to precise if sufficient spermatozoa is retrieved.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>micro TESE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Microdissection TESE is also performed under general or locoregional anesthesia. After the tunica albuginea is opened widely along the antiepididymal border, direct examination of the testicular parenchyma is performed under the operating microscope. An attempt is made to identify individual seminiferous tubules that are larger, more opaque and whiter than other tubules in the testicular parenchyma, which are considered to contain spermatozoa. The extracted tubules are analyzed by the biologist in the theatre. The procedure is terminated when sperm are retrieved or further biopsy is thought likely to jeopardize the blood supply of the testis. If all tubules are seen to have an identical morphological appearance, at least three samples (upper, middle, and lower) are obtained. A similar microTESE will be systematically performed in the contralateral testis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>conventional TESE</intervention_name>
    <description>usual procedure for sperm extraction</description>
    <arm_group_label>conventional TESE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>conventional surgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Micro TESE</intervention_name>
    <description>procedure of extraction is performed under the operating microscope</description>
    <arm_group_label>micro TESE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Microdissection surgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  2 consecutive spermograms (with ±3 months interval) confirming absence of sperm
             (azoospermia)

          -  diagnosis of non-obstructive azoospermia on the basis of a complete history, physical
             examination, endocrine profile, ultrasound and chromosomal analysis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of previous testicular surgery, except orchiopexy for undescended testis.

          -  Monochordy

          -  Ultrasound revealed testicular nodule

          -  Y chromosome microdeletions type AZFa and b.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric Huyghe, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>U H Toulouse</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <zip>33 000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <zip>59037</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <zip>69437</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75015</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen</city>
        <zip>76031</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31 059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsujimura A, Matsumiya K, Miyagawa Y, Tohda A, Miura H, Nishimura K, Koga M, Takeyama M, Fujioka H, Okuyama A. Conventional multiple or microdissection testicular sperm extraction: a comparative study. Hum Reprod. 2002 Nov;17(11):2924-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12407050</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 13, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 13, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Azoospermia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

