<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02180659</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Braeburn PRO-814</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02180659</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Adult Outpatients With Opioid Dependence Transitioned From a Daily SL Buprenorphine to Probuphine® Subdermal Implants</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRO-814</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Double-Dummy, Active-Controlled Multicenter Study of Adult Outpatients With Opioid Dependence Transitioned From a Daily Maintenance Dose of 8 mg or Less of Sublingual Buprenorphine or Buprenorphine/Naloxone to Four Probuphine® Subdermal Implants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Braeburn Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Braeburn Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study is to demonstrate maintenance of treatment efficacy when
      transferring adult outpatients with opioid dependence, who are clinically stabilized on 8 mg
      or less of sublingual (SL) buprenorphine (BPN), to 4 Probuphine implants compared to SL BPN.

      The secondary objective of the study is to confirm safety of 4 Probuphine implants in adult
      outpatients with opioid dependence who are clinically stabilized on 8 mg or less of SL BPN.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, double-dummy, active-controlled multi-center study to
      evaluate the efficacy of transition to four 80 mg Probuphine implants in adult outpatients
      with opioid dependence, who are clinically stabilized on 8 mg or less of SL BPN. The study
      will include 3 Phases; Screening, Maintenance and Follow-up.

      Medical and eligibility screening should occur within 2 weeks of the first Maintenance Phase
      visit. The Screening Visit will include standard medical screening procedures, complete
      medical/psychosocial history, urine toxicology and detailed substance use and treatment
      history.

      All subjects who have provided written informed consent and have met the other study entry
      criteria will be eligible for randomization. Following confirmation of eligibility, subjects
      will be randomized to one of two treatment groups in a 1:1 ratio:

        -  Treatment Group A: Daily SL BPN tablets (≤8 mg/daily) + four placebo implants

        -  Treatment Group B: Four 80 mg Probuphine implants + daily SL placebo tablets

      Implants will be surgically inserted on Day 1 (Baseline and Initiation of Study Drugs Visit).
      On Post-Implant Visit, additional follow-up safety and implant assessment procedures will be
      conducted. Subjects will return for monthly study visits on Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, and 24
      (End of Treatment Visit). In addition to the monthly scheduled visits, subjects will provide
      4 random urine toxicology samples throughout the 24-week treatment period.

      A total of 10 urine toxicology samples will be collected; 6 at scheduled visits (1 per month)
      and 4 at random urine toxicology visits throughout the 24-week treatment period. At the
      scheduled visits, other assessments of efficacy and safety will be collected. Implants will
      be removed at the End of Treatment Visit on Week 24.

      Following Week 24, subjects will be re-transitioned back to usual care (pre-trial), as
      needed. During Week 25, telephone contact will be made with all subjects. and Week 26 will
      include an on-site visit to the clinic for final follow-up assessments (Follow-up Visit).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary efficacy endpoint is a responder rate analysis, where a responder is defined as a patient with no more than 2 of 6 months with any evidence of illicit opioid use.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary efficacy endpoint is a responder analysis. A subject will be designated as a responder (meaning they have maintained stability) if they have no more than 2 of 6 months with any evidence of illicit opioid use. Evidence of illicit opioid use is defined as a positive opioid urine toxicology result or self-reported illicit opioid use.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Desire/need to use opioids</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary efficacy endpoints will include average scores over 24 weeks of treatment and average change from baseline (Day 1) scores over 24 weeks of treatment for the following outcome measures:
- Measures of desire/need to use:
Desire to Use VAS
Need to Use VAS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measures of withdrawal</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary efficacy endpoints will include average scores over 24 weeks of treatment and average change from baseline (Day 1) scores over 24 weeks of treatment for the following outcome measures:
- Measures of withdrawal:
Clinical Opiate Withdrawal Scale (COWS)
Subjective Opioid Withdrawal Scale (SOWS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">177</enrollment>
  <condition>Opioid Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>buprenorphine implants + placebo tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Four 80 mg Probuphine implants + daily SL placebo tablets</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>buprenorphine tablets + placebo implants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Daily SL BPN tablets (≤8 mg/daily) + four placebo implants</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sublingual buprenorphine tablets</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>buprenorphine tablets + placebo implants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Buprenorphine implant</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>buprenorphine implants + placebo tablets</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo implants</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>buprenorphine tablets + placebo implants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sublingual placebo tablets</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>buprenorphine implants + placebo tablets</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject must provide written informed consent prior to the conduct of any
             study-related procedures.

          2. Male or female, 18-65 years of age, inclusive.

          3. Primary diagnosis of opioid dependence (DSM-IV-TR).

          4. Subject is considered clinically stable by their treating healthcare provider and
             confirmed by the following:

               1. Subject must be on SL BPN treatment for at least 6 months.

               2. Subject must have been on a SL BPN dose of 8 mg or less daily for at least the
                  last 90 days prior to Screening.

               3. No positive urine toxicology results for illicit opioids in the last 90 days.

          5. Free from significant withdrawal symptoms (score of ≤ 5 on the Clinical Opiate
             Withdrawal Scale [COWS]), as measured at the Screening Visit.

          6. Female subjects of childbearing potential must be willing to use a reliable method of
             contraception during the entire study (Screening Visit to Follow-Up Visit).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current diagnosis of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS).

          2. Current diagnosis of chronic pain syndrome requiring chronic opioid treatment, or
             conditions associated with acute episodic flares that require opioid treatment.

          3. Pregnant or lactating or planning to become pregnant during the study.

          4. Hypersensitivity or allergy to ethylene vinyl acetate (EVA)-containing substances or
             naloxone.

          5. Recent scarring or tattoos on their upper arms, or a history of keloid scarring.

          6. Requires current use of agents metabolized through CYP 3A4 such as azole antifungals
             (e.g., ketoconazole), macrolide antibiotics (e.g., erythromycin), or protease
             inhibitors (e.g., ritonavir, indinavir, and saquinavir).

          7. History of coagulopathy within the past 90 days, and/or current anti-coagulant therapy
             such as warfarin.

          8. Current DSM-IV-TR diagnosis for substance dependence on any other psychoactive
             substances other than opioids or nicotine (e.g., alcohol, cocaine).

          9. Significant symptoms or other factors which in the opinion of the Investigator would
             preclude compliance with the protocol, subject safety, adequate cooperation in the
             study, or obtaining informed consent.

         10. Current medical conditions such as severe respiratory insufficiency that may prevent
             the subject from safely participating in study.

         11. Any pending legal action that could prohibit participation or compliance in the study.

         12. Exposure to any investigational drug within the 8 weeks prior to Screening.

         13. Aspartate aminotransferase levels ≥3 X the upper limit of normal, alanine
             aminotransferase levels ≥ 3 X the upper limit of normal, total bilirubin ≥ 1.5 X the
             upper limit of normal, or creatinine ≥ 1.5 X upper limit of normal on the Screening
             laboratory assessments.

         14. Clinically significant low platelet count on the Screening laboratory assessments,
             according to the Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 1, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 3, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 5, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 5, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 6, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Buprenorphine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>June 12, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>July 12, 2017</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

