<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00628537</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BT4</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00628537</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Post-Stroke Hand/Wrist Flexion Deformity</brief_title>
  <official_title>BION Implantable Microstimulator</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Southern California</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study looks at a new treatment for wrist and finger contractures -- a condition where the
      affected hand is in a &quot;closed&quot; position, with the wrist and fingers stiff and difficult to
      move from that position. We want to study if stimulation of wrist and finger muscles using an
      implanted neuromuscular stimulator (BION) will be more or less effective than doing passive
      exercises of the affected hand to improve the range of movement at wrist and finger joints.
      Subjects of this study will be randomized into one of three groups: one doing passive
      movement therapy; one receiving surface stimulation (electrical stimulation with electrodes
      on the skin of the arm) and one doing BION® therapy. The passive movement group will do
      therapy for 12 weeks. Subjects in either stimulation group will receive stimulation for 6
      weeks and then only passive therapy for 6 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BION™ Experimental Group

      Following implantation, the patients receiving BIONs will have a 3 to 7 day healing period.
      During this period, subjects will not receive active therapy. At the end of this healing
      period, subjects will come to the testing center so that the examiner can program the
      exercise patterns. They will be instructed to increase the strength of their muscle
      contractions as tolerance permits. The goal for the BION™ patients is to achieve 30 minutes
      of stimulation twice daily, using a cycled stimulation at frequencies adequate to produce
      tetanic contraction, (typically 25-35 pps) that raises the joint through full range of motion
      against gravity (a range graded as 3/5) based on the available range of motion. The
      intensity, duration and frequency of the exercise program will be modified according to the
      progress of the participant, so that the strength of the contraction is increased over time.

      Surface Stimulation Group

      Patients will be instructed to stimulate twice daily for 30 minutes through surface
      electrodes placed according to instructions that the subject has been given. Stimulus
      parameters will be similar to those reported in earlier successful stimulation studies. The
      parameters should achieve a tetanic contraction that raises the joint through full range of
      motion against gravity (graded 3/5) based on the patient's available range of motion, and
      cycled, typically at 25-35 pps, using stimulus ramps as necessary so that contractions are
      smoothly graded and comfortable. Every effort will be made to ensure that the parameters
      needed in this group are chosen to produce a similar type of contraction to that obtained
      with BION™ stimulation.

      Control Group with conservative therapy (Range of motion exercises)

      The research participant is instructed in self-administered, standard range of motion
      stretching exercises. If the patient is unable to stretch the fingers into extension, a
      family member or a care-giver will be instructed to assist. They will be instructed to
      exercise the affected hand twice daily, repeating the exercise a minimum of 15 times in each
      session for 6 weeks. Control subjects will return to the clinic every two weeks for the first
      6 weeks and every 3 weeks during the follow-up period. During these visits, passive range of
      motion testing will be administered.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>passive Range of Motion, active Range of Motion, Rancho Arm Function Scale, Fugl Meyer Function Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks, 4 weeks and 6 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Hand Deformities</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BION™ Experimental Group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Surface Stimulation Group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control Group with conservative therapy (Range of motion exercises)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BION stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>BION™ Experimental Group
The goal for the BION™ patients is to achieve 30 minutes of stimulation twice daily, using a cycled stimulation at frequencies adequate to produce tetanic contraction, (typically 25-35 pps) that raises the joint through full range of motion against gravity (a range graded as 3/5) based on the available range of motion.
Surface Stimulation Group
Patients will be instructed to stimulate twice daily for 30 minutes through surface electrodes placed according to instructions that the subject has been given. Every effort will be made to ensure that the parameters needed in this group are chosen to produce a similar type of contraction to that obtained with BION™ stimulation.
Control Group with conservative therapy (Range of motion exercises)
The research participant is instructed in self-administered, standard range of motion stretching exercises.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of hemiplegic stroke 6 months to 20 years prior to enrollment in this study;

          2. Paresis of extensors in the forearm;

          3. Demonstrable restriction of hand or wrist mobility (i.e. significant stretch response,
             defined as a 2+ or greater on the Ashworth scale, can be elicited in the finger or
             wrist flexor muscles, and the patient's resting hand posture is flexed when the
             patient is standing with the upper arm pendant and the elbow flexed);

          4. Age 18 years or older;

          5. Stable pattern of pain-medication use for at least one month prior to enrollment;

          6. Medically stable;

          7. Able to travel to the testing center;

          8. Mentally capable to understand and carry out the procedures and communicate concerns;
             and

          9. Able and willing to participate and provide informed consent.

         10. Ability to bring the wrist into neutral posture and the MCP joints into 30 degrees of
             flexion

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant, nursing, or planning to become pregnant within the study timeframe;

          2. Presence of electronic implants (e.g., cardiac pacemaker, cochlear implant,
             neurostimulator, etc.);

          3. Presence of metallic implants, such as artificial elbow implants or metal screws, in
             the immediate field of the magnetic coil (on the arm between the fingers and the
             shoulder).

          4. Use of electrical stimulation for treatment of relevant extensor muscles in the past
             month;

          5. Inability to recruit muscles through surface electrical stimulation because of
             excessive adipose tissue;

          6. Presence of other unrelated hand or wrist pathologies; participating in other
             treatments including active physical therapy or drug therapy that affect their hand or
             wrist.

          7. Severe hemineglect; and

          8. Cancer or other serious illness, including a disease other than stroke resulting in
             motor dysfunction.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lucinda Baker, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Southern California</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rancho Los Angeles National Rehabilitation Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Downey</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Loeb GE, Richmond FJ, Baker LL. The BION devices: injectable interfaces with peripheral nerves and muscles. Neurosurg Focus. 2006 May 15;20(5):E2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16711659</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 25, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 5, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Southern California</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gerald E. Loeb, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neuromuscular stimulator</keyword>
  <keyword>Flexor deformities of wrist and fingers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hand Deformities</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

