<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00627250</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-02-06A</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>H133A020522</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00627250</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Utility of Amantadine Hydrochloride in the Treatment of Post-traumatic Irritability</brief_title>
  <official_title>Utility of Amantadine Hydrochloride in the Treatment of Post-traumatic Irritability: A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carolinas Healthcare System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>U.S. Department of Education</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Carolinas Healthcare System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if amantadine hydrochloride given 100 mg in the
      morning and at noon is safe and effective in the treatment of mood and behavior changes (i.e.
      irritability) after sustaining traumatic brain injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Amantadine hydrochloride is a drug used commonly in clinical practice at the Carolinas
      Rehabilitation for the treatment of mood and behavior changes following traumatic brain
      injury. Clinical observation suggests that the use of amantadine improves caregiver report of
      &quot;irritability&quot; though there are no studies to validate this observation. This study
      investigates the efficacy and side effect profile of amantadine hydrochloride given in 2
      doses of 100 mgs each. Subjects are screened during regularly scheduled clinic appointments
      for the presence of irritability. If they are interested in possible participation in the
      study, they will be invited to meet with the research coordinator who will obtain informed
      consent. If the subject meets all the inclusion/exclusion requirements, they will leave
      clinic with study medication and begin taking the drug the next day. There will be a safety
      call between day 3 and 5 where the dose may be reduced to once per day. Follow-up assessment
      occurs at day 14 (by phone) and day 28 (in clinic). At study completion, the subject will
      have the opportunity to receive a prescription for amantadine as part of ongoing clinical
      care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychiatric Inventory (Irritability Domain frequency and severity)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychiatric Inventory Irritability and Aggression(Caregiver distress scores)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychiatric Inventory Aggression Domain (frequency and severity)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Impression of Change rated by clinician, individual with brain injury and caregiver</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">76</enrollment>
  <condition>Irritable Mood</condition>
  <condition>Aggression</condition>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Amantadine 100 mg every morning and 12 noon</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo tablet every morning and 12 noon</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amantadine</intervention_name>
    <description>Amantadine 100 mg every morning and 12 noon</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Symmetrel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Closed head injury (defined as brain injury or impaired brain function resulting from
             externally inflicted trauma without penetrating injury) at least 6 months prior to
             enrollment.

          -  Age at time of enrollment: 16 - 65 inclusive (i.e., on or after 16th birthday, up to
             day before 66th birthday).

          -  Voluntary informed consent of patient and informant.

          -  Subject and informant willing to comply with the protocol, &amp; are available for all
             scheduled clinic visits.

          -  Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI) Irritability Domain score &gt; 2.

          -  Medically and neurologically stable during the month prior to enrollment.

          -  If taking antidepressant, anxiolytic, hypnotic, or stimulant medications, no change
             anticipated in these medications during the month prior to enrollment.

          -  No change in therapies or medications planned during the 28-day participation.

          -  No surgeries planned during the 28-day participation.

          -  Vision, hearing, speech, motor function, and comprehension must be sufficient for
             compliance with all testing procedures. Ability to interact and verbalize sufficient
             to participate in assessments.

          -  Informant (family member or close friend) who lives with the participant with daily
             interaction in order to observe occurrences of irritability.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients without a reliable informant

          -  Penetrating head injury

          -  Injury &lt; 6 months prior to enrollment

          -  Inability to interact sufficient for communication with caregiver

          -  Acute and rehabilitation records unavailable or incomplete

          -  DSM-IV diagnosis of schizophrenia or psychosis

          -  Diagnosis of progressive or additional neurologic disease (such as, Alzheimer's
             disease, parkinson's disease, multi-infarct dementia, other cerebrovascular disorders
             with dementia, prior cerebrovascular accident, Huntington's disease,
             olivopontocerebellar atrophy, multisystem atrophy, multiple sclerosis, ALS, CNS tumor,
             progressive supranuclear palsy).

          -  Diagnosis of seizure in the month prior to enrollment.

          -  Previous allergy or adverse reaction to study drug

          -  Ingestion of amantadine hydrochloride during the month prior to enrollment.

          -  Concomitant use of neuroleptic agents or phenelzine

          -  Creatinine clearance &lt;60

          -  Pregnancy (Beta-HCG performed on all females of child-bearing potential) and lactating
             females.

          -  Clinical signs of active infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Flora M Hammond, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Carolinas Rehabilitation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gualtieri T, Chandler M, Coons TB, Brown LT. Amantadine: a new clinical profile for traumatic brain injury. Clin Neuropharmacol. 1989 Aug;12(4):258-70. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2680078</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herrman EC, Grabliks J, Engle C, et al. Antiviral activity of L-adamantanamine (amantadine). Proc Soc Exp Biol Med 1960;103:625</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwab RS, England AC Jr, Poskanzer DC, Young RR. Amantadine in the treatment of Parkinson's disease. JAMA. 1969 May 19;208(7):1168-70.</citation>
    <PMID>5818715</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beers SR, Skold A, Dixon CE, Adelson PD. Neurobehavioral effects of amantadine after pediatric traumatic brain injury: a preliminary report. J Head Trauma Rehabil. 2005 Sep-Oct;20(5):450-63.</citation>
    <PMID>16170253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gianutsos G, Chute S, Dunn JP. Pharmacological changes in dopaminergic systems induced by long-term administration of amantadine. Eur J Pharmacol. 1985 Apr 16;110(3):357-61.</citation>
    <PMID>2861102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aoki FY, Sitar DS. Clinical pharmacokinetics of amantadine hydrochloride. Clin Pharmacokinet. 1988 Jan;14(1):35-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3280212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen RM. Role of amantadine in the management of neuroleptic-induced extrapyramidal syndromes: overview and pharmacology. Clin Neuropharmacol. 1983;6 Suppl 1:S64-73. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>6196112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stone TW. Evidence for a non-dopaminergic action of amantadine. Neurosci Lett. 1977 May;4(6):343-6.</citation>
    <PMID>19556187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weller M, Kornhuber J. A rationale for NMDA receptor antagonist therapy of the neuroleptic malignant syndrome. Med Hypotheses. 1992 Aug;38(4):329-33.</citation>
    <PMID>1337136</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riederer P, Lange KW, Kornhuber J, Danielczyk W. Pharmacotoxic psychosis after memantine in Parkinson's disease. Lancet. 1991 Oct 19;338(8773):1022-3.</citation>
    <PMID>1681331</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edby K, Larsson J, Eek M, von Wendt L, Ostergård B. Amantadine treatment of a patient with anoxic brain injury. Childs Nerv Syst. 1995 Oct;11(10):607-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8556729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chandler MC, Barnhill JL, Gualtieri CT. Amantadine for the agitated head-injury patient. Brain Inj. 1988 Oct-Dec;2(4):309-11.</citation>
    <PMID>3203176</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosati DL. Early polyneuropharmacologic intervention in brain injury agitation. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 2002 Feb;81(2):90-3.</citation>
    <PMID>11807342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shiller AD, Burke DT, Kim HJ, Calvanio R, Dechman KG, Santini C. Treatment with amantadine potentiated motor learning in a patient with traumatic brain injury of 15 years' duration. Brain Inj. 1999 Sep;13(9):715-21.</citation>
    <PMID>10507453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneider WN, Drew-Cates J, Wong TM, Dombovy ML. Cognitive and behavioural efficacy of amantadine in acute traumatic brain injury: an initial double-blind placebo-controlled study. Brain Inj. 1999 Nov;13(11):863-72.</citation>
    <PMID>10579658</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Reekum R, Bayley M, Garner S, Burke IM, Fawcett S, Hart A, Thompson W. N of 1 study: amantadine for the amotivational syndrome in a patient with traumatic brain injury. Brain Inj. 1995 Jan;9(1):49-53.</citation>
    <PMID>7874096</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zafonte RD, Watanabe T, Mann NR. Amantadine: a potential treatment for the minimally conscious state. Brain Inj. 1998 Jul;12(7):617-21.</citation>
    <PMID>9653525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 21, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 29, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 24, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Flora Hammond, M.D.</name_title>
    <organization>Carolinas HealthCare System</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Irritability</keyword>
  <keyword>Aggression</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Amantadine</keyword>
  <keyword>Irritability and Aggression Due to Traumatic Brain Injury</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aggression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amantadine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

