<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00627627</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MI-CP153</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00627627</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Antitumor Activity and Safety of IPI-504 in Patients With Advanced Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Open-Label, Single-Arm, Multicenter, Multinational Study to Evaluate the Antitumor Activity and Safety of IPI-504, A Novel Small Molecule Inhibitor of Heat Shock Protein 90(HSP90), in Patients With Locally Advanced or Metastatic Human Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor 2-Positive(HER2+) Breast Cancer That Has Progressed Despite Prior Her2=Targeted Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MedImmune LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MedImmune LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the antitumor activity following treatment with IPI-504 in patients with breast
      cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the antitumor activity following treatment with IPI-504 in patients with locally
      advanced or metastatic HER2+ breast cancer that has progressed despite prior HER2-targeted
      therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Redirect focus of the indication
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2008</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the antitumor activity, assessed by ORR which will be determined using RECIST, following treatment with IPI-504 in patients with locally advanced or metastatic HER2+ breast cancer that has progressed despite prior HER2-targeted therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after discontinuation of IPI-504</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate other antitumor activities, safety, and PK parameters of IPI-504 in this patient population.</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after discontinuation of IPI-504</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>IPI-504</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IPI-504</intervention_name>
    <description>dose of 400 mg/m2 as a 30-60 minute IV infusion as part of a 21-day treatment cycle</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult women at least 18 years of age at the time of signing the Informed Consent Form;

          -  Written informed consent and HIPAA authorization (applies to covered entities in the
             USA only) obtained from the patient prior to performing any study-related procedures,
             including screening visits;

          -  Pathologically confirmed breast cancer from assessment of primary or metastatic breast
             cancer;

          -  Locally advanced or metastatic breast cancer as defined as a T4 primary tumor and
             Stage IIIB/ IIIC disease or Stage IV disease, respectively, according to the Sixth
             Edition of the American Joint Committee on Cancer [AJCC] TNM System (Appendix A);

          -  Measurable disease according to RECIST - lesions that can be accurately measured in at
             least one dimension with longest diameter ³ 20 mm using conventional computed
             tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan or ³ 10 mm with spiral CT
             scan; the use of chest x-ray is not encouraged, however, it may be used if necessary;

          -  HER2-expressing primary or metastatic tumor (Grade 3+ staining intensity [on a scale
             of 0 to 3] via IHC assays or HER2 amplification on fluorescence in situ
             hybridization), with results of the most recent biopsy taken as indicative of HER2
             status;

          -  Progression after treatment with at least 1 but not more than 3 regimens containing
             trastuzumab or lapatinib (treatment regimens that do not include trastuzumab or
             lapatinib do not qualify) for adjuvant, neoadjuvant, locally advanced, or metastatic
             disease with either one of the following stipulations:

               1. Patients may have received neoadjuvant or adjuvant treatment with prior
                  trastuzumab or lapatinib treatment but must have demonstrated no evidence of
                  disease progression for &gt;12 months following completion of therapy;

               2. Patients have received a trastuzumab-based therapy for locally advanced or
                  metastatic disease for a minimum of 9 weeks duration. Patients may have received
                  more than 1 trastuzumab-based combination therapy; Patients have received a
                  lapatinib-based therapy for locally advanced or metastatic diseases for a minimum
                  of 9 weeks duration;

          -  Resolution of all toxic side effects of prior chemotherapy, radiotherapy or surgical
             procedures to NCI CTCAE Grade ≤ 1 or patient's baseline;

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 2 (see Appendix
             B);

          -  Life expectancy of at least 3 months;

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction &gt; 45%;

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,500 cells/mm3; platelet count ≥ 100,000 cells/mm3;
             hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL (may be increased to this level with transfusion as long as
             there is no evidence of active bleeding);

          -  Prothrombin time or international normalized ratio within normal range (unless a
             patient is receiving anticoagulation therapy), or PTT within normal range;

          -  AST and ALT ≤ 2.5 ´ upper limit of normal (ULN) or ≤ 5 ´ ULN for patients with liver
             metastases; total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 ´ ULN [unless due to Gilbert's syndrome
             (unconjugated hyperbilirubinemia) in which case the bilirubin should be &lt; 3.5mg/dL);
             hepatic alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 ´ ULN;

          -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 ´ ULN and calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 30 mL/min;

          -  Women with central nervous system (CNS) metastases are eligible if they are clinically
             stable for at least 3 months after the discontinuation of prior corticosteroid
             therapy;

          -  Female patients must be of non child-bearing potential or using effective
             contraception, eg, use of oral contraceptives with an additional barrier method (since
             the study drug may impair the effectiveness of oral contraceptives), double barrier
             methods (diaphragm with spermicidal gel or condoms with contraceptive foam),
             Depo-Provera, partner vasectomy, total abstinence, and willing to continue the
             effective contraception method for 30 days after the last dose of IPI-504; and

          -  Patients must be able to adhere to the study visit schedule and all protocol
             requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous treatment with 17-AAG, 17-DMAG, or other known Hsp90 inhibitor;

          -  Concurrent radiation or surgery therapy;

          -  Treatment for breast cancer with any approved or investigational product, including
             any local or systemic therapy within 4 weeks prior to first dose of IPI-504 in this
             study;

          -  Initiation or discontinuation of concurrent medication that alters CYP3A activity
             within 2 weeks prior to treatment with IPI-504. Patients who are on a stable dose of
             drugs known to alter CYP3A activity for &gt; 2 weeks are eligible to enroll;

          -  Presence of active infection or systemic use of antimicrobials within 72 hours prior
             to treatment with IPI-504;

          -  Untreated brain metastases (patients with a history of brain metastases are eligible
             as long as definitive treatment has been given and patients are clinically stable for
             at least 3 months after the discontinuation of prior corticosteroid therapy);

          -  Significant co-morbid condition or disease which in the judgment of the Investigator
             would place the patient at undue risk or interfere with the study (eg, cardiac disease
             such as acute coronary syndrome or unstable angina within 6 months, uncontrolled
             hypertension, arrhythmia requiring medication or mechanical control, conduction system
             abnormality such as left bundle branch block or second degree heart block, cirrhotic
             liver disease, cerebrovascular accident, or other conditions);

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating;

          -  Sinus bradycardia (resting heart rate &lt; 50 bpm) secondary to intrinsic conduction
             system disease; Patients with sinus bradycardia secondary to pharmacologic treatment
             may enroll if withdrawal of the treatment results in normalization of the resting
             heart rate to within normal limits;

          -  Screening QTc &gt; 470 msec, or previous history of QTc prolongation while taking other
             medications; or

          -  Active or recent history (within 3 months) of keratitis or keratoconjunctivitis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David E. Weng, M.D., PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>MedImmune LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgetown Univ Medical Cntr, Lombardi Comprehensive Cancer Center,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lynn Regional Cancer - West Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boca Raton</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33428</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical Specialists of the Palm Beaches</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lake Worth</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33454</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>&quot;Duke University Med Cntr Breast Oncology Research Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals Case Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44122</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Low County Hen/Onc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mt. Pleasant</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29464</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 21, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 21, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 3, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 1, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 1, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>David E. Weng, M.D., Ph. D.</name_title>
    <organization>MedImmune Inc.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

