<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00625092</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2005LS068</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>0601M79448</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00625092</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hyperthermic Intraperitoneal Oxaliplatin for Peritoneal Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Hyperthermic Intraperitoneal Oxaliplatin for Peritoneal Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as oxaliplatin, leucovorin, and fluorouracil,
      work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by
      stopping them from dividing. Hyperthermia therapy kills tumor cells by heating them to
      several degrees above normal body temperature. Peritoneal infusion of heated and nonheated
      chemotherapy drugs after surgery may kill more tumor cells.

      PURPOSE: This phase I trial is studying the side effects and best dose of hyperthermic
      intraperitoneal oxaliplatin followed by intraperitoneal leucovorin and fluorouracil in
      treating patients with peritoneal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To determine the safety and optimal dose of hyperthermic intraperitoneal oxaliplatin
           when administered during cytoreductive surgery and followed by intraperitoneal
           leucovorin calcium and fluorouracil in patients with peritoneal malignancies.

      Secondary

        -  To determine the outcome of cytoreductive surgery in these patients.

        -  To determine the time to disease progression and pattern of failure in patients treated
           with this regimen.

        -  To determine the 1 and 5 year survival in patients treated with this regimen.

        -  To compare quality-of-life pre- and post-surgery in these patients.

        -  To characterize total- and free-platinum pharmacokinetics in the plasma and total
           platinum in the intraperitoneal space at baseline, during, and after hyperthermic
           intraperitoneal chemotherapy (HIPC).

        -  To assess for the presence of genetic polymorphisms in the XDP and XRCC1 DNA repair
           genes.

        -  To assess tumor and normal tissue concentrations for total platinum obtained at baseline
           and immediately after HIPC.

      OUTLINE:

        -  Cytoreductive Surgery: Patients undergo an exploratory laparotomy to remove all tumor
           nodules from all peritoneal surfaces prior to gastrointestinal anastomoses. An
           intraperitoneal drain is placed for postoperative intraperitoneal chemotherapy.

        -  Hyperthermic peritoneal chemotherapy (HIPC): After cytoreductive surgery, but before
           intestinal anastomosis, patients receive oxaliplatin into the abdomen cavity at
           approximately 1 liter/min at 41-42º C and held for 30 minutes at the maximum tolerated
           dose. A heat exchanger maintains the fluid temperature at 44-46º C to maintain the
           intraperitoneal temperature at 41-42º C. Patients may receive fluid challenges,
           furosemide, mannitol, or renal dose dopamine to maintain a brisk diuresis at the
           discretion of the anesthesiologist.

        -  Intraperitoneal chemotherapy: After HIPC, patients receive leucovorin calcium
           intraperitoneally through an intraperitoneal drain where it will remain for 2 hours and
           then drained. Patients then receive fluorouracil intraperitoneally through the
           intraperitoneal drain on day 1 and remain in the peritoneal fluid for 23 hours and then
           drained. The infusion will be repeated on day 2.

      Blood samples are collected prior to surgery for pharmacogenetic studies and analyzed for the
      presence of genetic polymorphisms in the XPD and XRCC1 DNA repair genes and the GSTP1 and
      GSTM1 glutathione-S-transferase enzymes (i.e., XPD, Asp312Asn, XPD K751Q, XRCC1 Arg399GIn,
      XRCC1 Arg399Q, GSTP1 l105V, and GSTM1 DEL). Blood samples are also collected periodically for
      pharmacokinetic studies and analyzed for oxaliplatin concentrations. Normal and tumor tissue
      are collected periodically and analyzed for total platinum concentrations.

      Quality of life is assessed at baseline and at 4, 8, and 12 months.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed every 4 months for 2 years and
      then every 6 months for at least 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose of hyperthermic intraperitoneal oxaliplatin</measure>
    <time_frame>30 Days Post Treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in quality-of-life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at 4, 8, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy for Colorectal Cancer (FACT-C) and SF-36 (Quality of Life Evaluation in Dialysis Patients) questionnaires, the quality of life following cytoreductive surgery and hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy (HIPC) will be reported and compared to the preoperative baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year and 5 Years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Disease Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Monthly</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Peritoneal Cavity Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hyperthermic Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receiving combination of hyperthermic intraperitoneal chemotherapy (HIPC) with oxaliplatin plus intraperitoneal 5-Fu and intraperitoneal leucovorin with peritoneal metastases.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorouracil</intervention_name>
    <description>Post-operative day 1 and day 2, 600mg/m^2 intraperitoneal (IP) held for 23 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hyperthermic Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-FU</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>leucovorin calcium</intervention_name>
    <description>Day 0 200 mg/m^2 intraperitoneal held for 2 hours</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hyperthermic Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>oxaliplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Day 0 hyperthermic intraperitoneal oxaliplatin held for 30 minutes - assigned dose level: Levels 1 through 7 - 300 to 600 mg/m^2</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hyperthermic Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Eloxatin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cytoreductive surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Day 0 Cytoreductive surgery is a systematic attempt to remove all or nearly all peritoneal nodules.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hyperthermic Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>conventional surgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologic proof of peritoneal metastases (includes adenomucinosis)

          -  Complete tumor resection possible (may include liver metastasis if treatable by
             resection or radiofrequency ablation)

          -  Patients may have received previous chemotherapy (except peritoneal) and/or
             immunotherapy. If previous chemotherapy, at least 4 weeks must have passed since last
             dose.

          -  Patients may have received previous radiation therapy, however radiation to the large
             bowel, small bowel and/or stomach will make the patient ineligible for this study.

          -  Patients must have a Karnofsky performance score of ≥ 80%.

          -  Adequate hematologic, renal and hepatic function within 14 days of registration
             defined as:

               -  White blood count (WBC) ≥ 3,000

               -  platelet count ≥ 70,000,

               -  serum bilirubin ≤ 2.0 mg/dL,

               -  serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg/dL

          -  Patients must be at least 18 years of age

          -  Patients must be able to provide informed consent

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Metastatic disease is present outside the peritoneal cavity

          -  Diagnosis of mesothelioma

          -  Grade 2 or higher sensory neuropathy at time of study enrollment

          -  History of allergic reaction to platinum compounds

          -  Pregnant or lactating women. Pregnancy is a contraindication for receiving therapy,
             thus where relevant, patients will be required to use effective birth control. The
             agents used in this study include those which are pregnancy category D - clear
             evidence of risk in pregnancy. There is no information on the excretion of agents into
             breast milk therefore patients must refrain from breastfeeding while receiving study
             therapy.

          -  Previous peritoneal chemotherapy.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled concurrent medical problems (i.e. diabetes mellitus) or
             history of uncontrolled cardiovascular disease (no history of hospitalization for
             acute myocardial infarction or congestive heart failure (CHF) within 3 months prior to
             registration).

          -  Patients have psychiatric or addictive disorders that preclude obtaining informed
             consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Todd M. Tuttle, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 28, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>peritoneal cavity cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Peritoneal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fever</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

