<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00628420</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>082004-051</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00628420</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of ACP-104: To Demonstrate the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACP-104</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double Blind, Placebo Controlled, Single Oral Dose Study to Demonstrate the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of ACP-104 (N-desmethylclozapine) in Schizophrenia, or Other Psychotic Disorders.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stanley Medical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ACADIA Pharmaceuticals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the safety and tolerability of ACP-104 after oral administration of single doses
      in comparison with placebo to schizophrenia or other psychotic disorders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Thirty-six healthy patients with schizophrenia or psychotic disorders, each of whom will be
      drug-free at study initiation, will be admitted to the hospital and will each receive two
      doses of ACP-104, and one dose of placebo, orally every 3-5 days over a two-week period. The
      patients will be divided into six groups of up to six and minimum of 3 patients each. Group 1
      will consist of six patients who will receive single 25mg and 50mg doses of ACP-104 and
      placebo in random, but rising dose, order over a two-week period. Data from group one will be
      collected to determine ACP-104's safety, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics. Group 2 will be
      enrolled in the study once study data from Group 1 has demonstrated the safety of ACP-104.
      Group 2 will receive a 25mg pre-conditioning dose of ACP-104. Following the pre-conditioning
      dose, 75mg and 100mg single doses of ACP-104 will be administered in random, but rising dose,
      order, over a two-week period. Group 3 will be enrolled in the study once study data from
      Group 2 has demonstrated the safety of ACP-104. Group 3 will receive a 25mg pre-conditioning
      dose of ACP-104. Following the pre-conditioning dose, 125mg and 150mg single doses of ACP-104
      will be administered in random, but rising dose, order, over a two-week period. Group 4 will
      be enrolled in the study once study data from Group 3 has demonstrated the safety of ACP-104.
      Group 4 will receive a 25mg pre-conditioning dose of ACP-104. Following the pre-conditioning
      dose, 175mg and 200mg single doses of ACP-104 will be administered in random, but rising
      dose, order, over a two-week period. Group 5 will be enrolled in the study once study data
      from Group 4 has demonstrated the safety of ACP-104. Group 5 will receive a 25mg
      pre-conditioning dose of ACP-104. Following the pre-conditioning dose, 225mg and 250mg single
      doses of ACP-104 will be administered in random, but rising dose, order, over a two week
      period. Group 6 will be enrolled in the study once study data from Group 5 has demonstrated
      the safety of ACP-104. Group 6 will receive a 25mg pre-conditioning dose of ACP-104.
      Following the pre-conditioning dose, 275mg and 300mg single doses of ACP-104 will be
      administered in random, but rising dose, order, over a two-week period. Groups 1-6 will be
      monitored closely and safety procedures and evaluations will be performed on all medication
      days. Safety assessments will include: physical examinations, vital signs (3-positional blood
      pressure and pulse rate, respiration rate, and oral body temperature), clinical laboratory
      tests, ECGs (Electrocardiogram), coordination tests, questions about symptoms and side
      effects. Once all medication days have been completed, the condition of the patient will be
      assessed, and, at that time, it will be determined whether the patient's condition is
      suitable for release from the hospital or whether further monitoring of the patient's
      condition as an inpatient is needed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients recieved single low dose of ACP-104</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients recieved a high dose of ACP-104</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients recieved a placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ACP-104</intervention_name>
    <description>25mg, 75mg, 125mg, 175mg, 225mg, or 275mg once a day for 2 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ACP-104</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient will be given either 50mg, 100mg, 150mg, 200mg, 250mg, or 300mg daily for 2 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>patients will be given a placebo: 25mg, 50mg, 75mg, 100mg, 125mg, 150mg, 175mg, 200mg, 225mg, 250mg, 275mg, or 300mg (to match the doses given) daily for 2 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>cornstarch capsule</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females, who have been surgically sterilized or at least 1 year post
             menopausal, in good health (based on medical history, physical examination,
             electrocardiograms, and clinical laboratory tests)

          -  Between 20 and 50 years old (inclusive)

          -  History of schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, bipolar with psychosis, major
             depression with psychosis, PTSD with psychosis, or psychosis NOS and not experiencing
             an acute exacerbation of severe psychosis

          -  Able to execute informed written consent

          -  Willing to follow dietary restrictions as outlined in Section 6.2 General and dietary
             restrictions,

          -  Willing to remain hospitalized for the in-patient portion of the study and return for
             follow up visit(s) as required by the protocol and as deemed necessary by principal
             investigator,

          -  Will be in need of treatment with an antipsychotic medication,

          -  Fluent and literate in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient that has received clozapine within the last three months, or any depot
             antipsychotic within the last six months,

          -  Likely allergy or insensitivity to ACP-104 or clozapine based on known allergies to
             drugs of the same class, or which in the opinion of the principle investigator,
             suggests an increased potential for an adverse hypersensitivity to ACP-104

          -  Any prior history of drug-induced leukopenia or neutropenia,

          -  Any prior history of neuroleptic malignant syndrome

          -  History of seizure, epilepsy, severe head injury, multiple sclerosis, or other known
             neurological condition

          -  Prior history of cardiovascular disease, including arrhythmia or myocarditis

          -  Abnormal pre-admission vital signs or clinical laboratory evaluations

          -  Any patient with a history, within the last three months, of alcohol and/or drug
             dependency or alcohol and/or drug abuse in the last month

          -  History of hepatic or renal disease

          -  Any patient scheduled to undergo any surgical procedure during the duration of the
             study,

          -  Any patient taking any concurrent medications for a major medical illness

          -  Any patient who has donated plasma or blood within 30 days before the first dose of
             study medication,

          -  Any patient who has received any known hepatic or renal clearance altering agents
             (e.g., erythromycin, cimetidine, barbiturates, phenothiazines, etc.) for a period of 3
             months before the first dose of study medication

          -  Ingestion or use of any investigational medication or device within 3 months before
             the first dose of study medication

          -  Acute illness within 5 days before the first dose of study medication

          -  Mental capacity is limited to the extent that the patient cannot provide legal consent
             or understand information regarding the side effects or tolerance of the study drug

          -  Any patient judged by the principal investigator to be inappropriate for the study.

               -  We do not have the resources necessary to properly study non-English speaking
                  patients in this study. The need to provide such resources would be prohibitive
                  to the successful completion of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Veteran's Affairs Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75216</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 24, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 24, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 5, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 27, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 27, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Carol A. Tamminga, MD, Professor</name_title>
    <organization>UT Southwestern Medical Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>N-desmethylclozapine</keyword>
  <keyword>clozapine</keyword>
  <keyword>psychosis</keyword>
  <keyword>randomized</keyword>
  <keyword>placebo studies</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Norclozapine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

