<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00627991</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SU-01282008-990</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>7599</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00627991</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blood Pressure Lowering in Acute Stroke Trial (BLAST)</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Use of Valsartan for the Management of Blood Pressure in Acute Stroke: Effects on Cerebral Blood Flow.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients who are suffering from a stroke often present to the hospital with elevated blood
      pressure. Elevated blood pressure in the setting of stroke increases the risk of brain
      swelling or bleeding into the brain. Even so, there has been concern about lowering the blood
      pressure with medications because the newly injured parts of the brain may not get the blood
      flow they need, thereby worsening the damage from the initial stroke. We hope to demonstrate
      that the drug valsartan can be used safely and modestly to lower blood pressure in acute
      stroke patients, without having a detrimental effect on brain blood flow or neurologic
      status. Novel MRI techniques to measure brain blood flow will be used in conjunction with
      clinical scales to demonstrate safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypertension is an important modifiable risk factor for the prevention of ischemic stroke.
      Whether specific antihypertensive medications confer an added benefit for recurrent stroke
      reduction beyond their ability to lower blood pressure remains a controversial subject.
      Because of their varied mechanisms of action, and their potential role as neuroprotective
      agents, there has been particular interest in drugs that affect the
      renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS). Several large multi-national randomized clinical
      trials have suggested a unique benefit of these agents, namely angiotensin converting enzyme
      (ACE) inhibitors and ARBs, for the prevention of vascular events. Even with the very modest
      reductions in blood pressure achieved in the HOPE trial, ramipril was found to have a
      significant benefit on recurrent stroke prevention (Heart Outcomes Prevention Evaluation
      Study Investigators, 2000). In the LIFE study, losartan was shown to be more efficacious for
      the prevention of recurrent strokes in hypertensive patients than atenolol, despite nearly
      identical reductions in blood pressure (Dahlöf et al, 2002). This is an area of some debate,
      however, as some data may support the lowering of blood pressure in general over the use of
      specific agents such as ACE inhibitors for the prevention of recurrent stroke (PROGRESS
      Collaborative Group, 2001). More recently, the ACCESS study showed a benefit of early
      treatment with candesartan cilexetil on 12-month mortality and the number of vascular events
      in patients who had suffered an acute stroke (Schrader et al, 2003). The mechanisms that
      underlie this are uncertain, but the study suggests that early treatment of blood pressure in
      acute stroke may have long-term benefits, presumably independent of hemodynamic factors.

      The use of antihypertensives in the setting of an acute infarct is an area of great interest.
      A transient rise in blood pressure is frequently seen in acute stroke patients (Semplicini et
      al, 2003). Although blood pressure typically normalizes within one week without treatment,
      about one-third of patients remain hypertensive (Britton et al, 1986; Harper et al, 1994).
      Currently, there is insufficient data for a clear recommendation on deliberately altering
      blood pressure in these acute ischemic stroke patients (BASC, 2004). That being said,
      hypertension in acute stroke has been associated with poor outcome (Warlow et al, 1996),
      although the relationship may be a 'J'-shaped curve, with both low and high mean blood
      pressures being detrimental (Leonardi-Bee et al, 2002). The potential mechanisms that
      underlie the association between hypertension and poor outcome in acute stroke are several,
      but may include an increase in peri-infarct edema and an increased risk of hemorrhagic
      transformation. The potential benefits of the early treatment of high blood pressure in acute
      stroke must be weighed against the theoretical risk of worsening ischemia in compromised
      neural tissue. The INWEST trial showed increased mortality in patients actively treated with
      a calcium-channel blocker within 72 hours of an acute stroke (Wahlgren et al, 1994), an
      effect that may be related to the lowering of diastolic blood pressure (Ahmed et al, 2000).
      This data is in keeping with the long-standing hypothesis that impaired autoregulation in the
      ischemic brain tissue renders cerebral blood flow purely pressure-dependent. A decrease in
      systemic blood pressure would then translate to decreased local perfusion to vulnerable
      tissue in the ischemic penumbra. It is in this setting that drugs that modulate the RAAS may
      have a unique role. In recent years, animal and human data has accrued that suggests CBF is
      maintained with these agents, even in the face of decreased systemic blood pressure.

      There are human data regarding cerebral blood flow and drugs that affect the RAAS, in both
      normal patients and those with recent ischemia. Studies with ACE inhibitors have demonstrated
      a moderate lowering of blood pressure in hypertensive patients, without a corresponding
      decrease in CBP, as measure with xenon CT (Minematsu et al, 1987; Waldemar et al, 1990).
      Dyker et al (1997) used Doppler ultrasound to show that cerebral blood flow is maintained in
      the setting of acute stroke when systemic blood pressure is lowered with perindopril. A
      similar result was seen in hypertensive stroke patients with moderate to severe internal
      carotid artery stenosis or occlusion (Walters et al, 2001). When losartan was introduced in
      hypertensive patients within 2-7 days of a mild ischemic stroke, there was no adverse effect
      on global or region cerebral blood flow, as measured by carotid Doppler and brain
      hexamethylpropyleneamine oxime single photon emission computed tomography (HMPAO SPECT; Nazir
      et al, 2004). There is no published data on the effects of these drugs on cerebral perfusion
      as measured with MRI, nor on changes in infarct volume as measure by DWI.

      Brain imaging with MRI is available at all major centers that admit patients for the care of
      ischemic stroke. Diffusion-weighted imaging is considered the 'gold standard' for the
      detection of ischemia in the acute setting, with restricted diffusion being visible within 30
      minutes of symptom onset (Fisher and Albers, 1999). Semi-quantitative measures of cerebral
      blood flow can be obtained with perfusion-weighted imaging (PWI) with only a minimal increase
      in the total scanning time. The acquisition of perfusion data with MRI is more readily
      available than such modalities as PET, SPECT, or xenon CT. Data is ongoing to identify
      analysis regimens for PWI that best represent true cerebral perfusion. We will use these
      techniques to assess brain perfusion before and after the lowering of blood pressure with
      valsartan.

      We hope to show that valsartan can be used safely in the setting of acute stroke to lower
      elevated blood pressure. There are novel properties of this class of drug (an
      angiotensive-receptor blocker or ARB), and promising human and animal data, that would
      suggest this drug can be safely used to lower blood pressure in the setting of acute stroke
      without compromising brain blood flow (i.e. cerebral perfusion). If this is proved to be the
      case, this compound could potentially be used routinely in this setting, with the hope of
      improving outcome. This pilot study may pave the way for a larger randomized trial looking at
      outcome measures in stroke patients. Further, a positive result in the this pilot study will
      serve as proof of concept that ARBs maintain cerebral perfusion while decreasing blood
      pressure, an overall favorable property.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2007</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>30 day glascow outcome score</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>30 day modified Rankin</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebrovascular Accident</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Valsartan</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Men and non-pregnant women over age 18 who have had an acute ischemic stroke referable
             to the anterior circulation, as diagnosed by one of more of the following: clinical
             judgment, head CT, and/or MR imaging [i.e. a positive diffusion-weighted imaging (DWI)
             abnormality].

          2. Clinical syndrome not likely to represent transient ischemic attack (TIA) or other
             non-stroke etiology

          3. Patient must be neurologically stable at the time of first MRI scan (i.e. stable NIH
             Stroke Scale score).

          4. Initial MRI scan obtainable within 48 hours of symptom onset.

          5. A pre-existing diagnosis of hypertension, either treated or untreated.

          6. Average of two mean arterial blood pressures (separated by at least five minutes) at
             time of enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have taken an angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitor or
             angiotensin receptor blocker (ARB) within seven (7) days of admission.

          2. Patients who received intravenous or intra-arterial r-TPA for their current symptoms,
             or those who underwent mechanical thrombolysis.

          3. Patients with hemorrhagic strokes, as seen on the initial head CT.

          4. Patients with stroke-like symptoms, but no demonstrable lesion on DWI, or a DWI lesion
             &lt; 2 cm in diameter (greatest dimension).

          5. Patients with high-grade (&gt;70%) internal carotid artery stenosis or occlusion
             ipsilateral to the current stroke.

          6. Patients with high-grade aortic or mitral stenosis.

          7. Patients with a previous adverse reaction to valsartan or other ARBs.

          8. Patients with contraindications for MRI, including pacemakers, claustrophobia, or
             severe obesity.

          9. Patients who are medically unstable for MR imaging, as determined by the treating
             team.

         10. Patients with a severe co-existing disease that may interfere with the conduct of the
             study.

         11. Patients receiving investigational drug therapies.

         12. Informed consent cannot be obtained from the patient or an appropriate surrogate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gregory W Albers</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 22, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 12, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 12, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gregory W Albers</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Valsartan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

