<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00827437</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DECID4</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00827437</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Family-Staff Communication Intervention at the Time of Difficult Treatment Decision Making</brief_title>
  <official_title>Family-Staff Communication Intervention at the Time of Difficult Treatment Decision Making</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this single site study was to assess the feasibility of implementing a
      staff/parent communication intervention within 72 hours of the parents making an end-of-life
      decision on behalf of their child.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Parents/guardians of children with incurable cancer face end-of-life decisions on behalf of
      their child including whether or not to enroll their child in a Phase I study, whether or not
      to agree to a 'do not resuscitate' status, or to begin terminal care. Descriptive research to
      date indicates that one of the factors that most helps parents to make these decisions and to
      remain satisfied with the decision afterward is their perception that they decided as a 'good
      parent' would decide. Parents define being a 'good parent' as making a decision that is in
      the best interest of their child. Parents' perception of their success in being a good parent
      is influenced by their interactions with the child's health care providers. Health care
      providers who are not fully informed about the decision and the parents' rationale for the
      decision are likely to convey doubt about the decision to parents and to other health care
      providers. Parents interpret this doubt as staff questioning the parents' ability to make
      good decisions. Lack of adequate information also creates staff tension. This single-site
      feasibility study will implement and evaluate a two-part communication intervention designed
      to identify parents' definition of being a good parent, and to communicate this definition
      and the rationale for the parents' decision to staff. The intervention will be implemented in
      60 to 80 end-of-life clinical care situations in which parents have made a decision on behalf
      of a child who is still living. The feasibility study is guided by the Pediatric Quality of
      Life at End of Life model. The parent/guardian intervention includes a face-to-face interview
      with parents regarding their definition of a 'good parent' and their basis for the decision
      they made. Parents/guardians will be interviewed within 72 hours after making the end of life
      decision and again 1 to 3 weeks after making the decision. Health care professionals assigned
      to the terminally ill child will receive the communication intervention within hours of the
      parent interview, and will evaluate its usefulness 1 to 2 weeks after receiving it.

      1.1 To assess the feasibility of delivering the two-part communication intervention. The
      definition of feasible is that 50% of all interventions are successfully implemented.

      1.1.1 To identify all three types of difficult treatment decisions within the defined time
      frame (thus identifying eligible parents/guardians and obtaining consent within 72 hours
      after the decision was made), document the study team's ability to successfully implement the
      intervention before the child's death (obtaining the parent/guardian information and sharing
      that with the defined staff such that the family achieves the definition of being fully
      evaluable as a study participant), and document the participation rate by tracking the number
      of eligible parents/guardians who agree to participate, decline to participate or withdraw
      from the study.

      1.2: To assess staff perceptions of the impact of the communication intervention on staff 1
      to 2 weeks after the intervention.

      1.2.1 to measure: a) staff recall of the definition of a good parent and the rationale for
      the decision; b) staff perception of how this knowledge influenced their care for the family;
      c) staff satisfaction with the verbal and written communication intervention forms; and d)
      the impact of the communication intervention on team tension and team communication about the
      parents' decisions.

      1.3: To assess the impact of the communication on parents/guardians by recording their
      perceptions of the positive and negative aspects of the intervention at the time of the
      intervention and 1 to 3 weeks after the decision making.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2004</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the feasibility of delivering the two-part communication intervention. The definition of feasible is that 50% of all interventions are successfully implemented.</measure>
    <time_frame>22 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">401</enrollment>
  <condition>Difficult Decision Making</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Parent Interview</intervention_name>
    <description>To include the PI, Nursing Research Specialist,Clinical Research Associate or Clinical Nurse Specialist</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eligible parents/guardian can be enrolled only one time and will be:

          -  21 years of age and older.

          -  This study will enroll only parents/guardians who are 21 years of age and older. The
             investigators clinical experience is that when the parent/guardian is younger,
             additional adult members of the family are involved in the decision making and that
             asking a single person to identify him or herself as the primary parent/guardian
             creates difficulties for the family.

          -  As a result, no parent/guardian younger than age 21 will be enrolled in this study.

          -  English-speaking.

          -  Willing to give written consent to participate.

          -  The parents/guardians of a child with incurable cancer or a fatal cancer-related
             condition who is being treated at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital

          -  The parents/guardians who made an end-of-life decision on behalf of the seriously ill
             child within the previous 72-hours.

          -  Eligible staff can be enrolled more than one time and will be:

          -  English-speaking

          -  Willing to give written consent to participate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Parents/guardians who meet the above criteria but are identified by their attending or
             social support staff member (an assigned social worker or psychologist at St. Jude
             Children's Research Hospital) as emotionally or mentally unable to participate in the
             informed consent process will not be approached about participating in the study.

          -  Parents who are identified by their attending or social support staff member as likely
             to find the study too burdensome because of their emotional or mental state.

          -  Parents who did not make the end-of-life decision (i.e., when the patient made the
             decision).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pamela S Hinds, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 6, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 21, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 22, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 23, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Pamela S. Hinds PhD, RN</name_title>
    <organization>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

