<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00820508</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHR-2845-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00820508</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Tolerability of CHR-2845 to Treat Haematological Diseases or Lymphoid Malignancies</brief_title>
  <acronym>CHR-2845-001</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study to Evaluate the Safety and Tolerability of the Histone Deacetylase Inhibitor, CHR-2845, in Patients With Advanced or Treatment Refractory Haematological Diseases or Lymphoid Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chroma Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chroma Therapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the histone deacetylase inhibitor CHR-2845
      is tolerated in patients with haematological diseases and lymphoid malignancies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CHR-2845 is a novel type of histone deacetylase inhibitor (HDACi) for use in cancer that, in
      addition to having broad ranging anti-proliferative activity against transformed cells, is
      designed to have an increased therapeutic window against diseases which involve cells of the
      monocyte-macrophage lineage. There are several HDACi's in clinical development and one, SAHA
      (Vorinostat, Zolinza®), has recently been approved for use in the treatment of cutaneous
      T-cell lymphoma. CHR-2845 is a cell-permeant ester that is metabolised to give an active
      acid, CHR-2847, which selectively accumulates in monocytes and macrophages. This results in a
      20-100 fold increase in anti-proliferative potency of CHR-2845 for monocytic over
      non-monocytic tumour cells. This selectivity should lead to an increased therapeutic window
      in haematological malignancies involving cells of the monocyte lineage (AML M4, AML M5 and
      CMML). In addition, there is increasing evidence that monocytes and macrophages associated
      with some haematological tumours (tumour-associated macrophages (TAMs)) are involved in
      supporting the growth and spread of the tumour. This clinical trial will focus on
      haematological and lymphoid malignancies with the intention of evaluating the safety and
      tolerability of CHR-2845. Additionally it will compare response in patients where
      monocytes/macrophages are important disease drivers, with the response in other patients.
      This will allow an early determination of the potential improvement in therapeutic window
      afforded by the monocyte/macrophage directed HDACi activity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the safety, tolerability, dose-limiting toxicities (DLT), maximum acceptable dose (MAD) and maximum tolerated dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine pharmacokinetic parameters of CHR-2845 and the active metabolite CHR-2847</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Hematological Disease</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoid Malignancies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral, once daily administration of CHR-2845 to determine safety and tolerability</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CHR-2845</intervention_name>
    <description>Once daily oral ingestion of capsules (10, 40 or 80mg), dose depending on cohort, treatment cycle of 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed, informed consent

          2. Confirmed malignant haematological disease or lymphoid malignancy refractory to
             standard therapy or for which no standard therapy exists, including acute leukemias,
             MDS, CML, CLL, CMML, multiple myeloma and Non-Hodgkin's Lymphomas/Hodgkin's disease

          3. Patients shall have recovered from all acute adverse effects of prior therapies, with
             the exception of alopecia and grade 1 neuropathy where recovery is not required

          4. Adequate bone marrow, hepatic and renal function including the following:

               1. Patients with high blast counts can be included if they can be controlled by the
                  use of hydroxyurea (500 mg -3,000 mg daily).

               2. Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper normal limit, excluding cases where elevated
                  bilirubin can be attributed to Gilbert's Syndrome

               3. AST (SGOT), ALT (SGPT) ≤ 2.5 x upper normal limit

               4. Creatinine ≤ 1.5 x upper normal limit

          5. Age ≥ 18 years

          6. Performance status (PS) ≤ 2 - Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) scale

          7. Estimated life expectancy greater than 3 months

          8. Female patients with reproductive potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test
             within 7 days prior to start of trial. Both women and men must agree to use a
             medically acceptable method of contraception throughout the treatment period and for 3
             months after discontinuation of treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients receiving anti-cancer therapy or use of other investigational agents within
             21 days prior to trial entry (or a longer period depending on the defined
             characteristics of the agents used. Bisphosphonates for bone disease and
             corticosteroids are permitted provided the dose does not change during the trial.
             Patients must have recovered from all transient toxicity induced by prior therapy

          2. Patients with co-existing active infection, graft versus host disease or serious
             concurrent illness

          3. Patients who have failed to recover from or after a bone marrow transplantation or
             haematopoietic stem cell transplantation

          4. The following diseases are excluded: Burkitt's lymphoma, primary effusion lymphoma,
             precursor B-cell lymphoblastic lymphoma, symptomatic central nervous system (CNS)
             lymphoma, CML blast crisis

          5. Patients with significant cardiovascular disease as defined by:

               1. history of congestive heart failure requiring therapy

               2. history of angina pectoris requiring treatment or myocardial infarction within 6
                  months prior to trial entry

               3. presence of severe valvular heart disease

               4. presence of an atrial or ventricular arrhythmia requiring treatment

               5. Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) below the normal range at the study
                  centre

               6. Uncontrolled hypertension

               7. A history of abnormal QTc intervals or an average QTc interval at screening ≥450
                  msec

          6. Any medical or other condition that in the investigator's opinion renders the patient
             unsuitable for this study due to unacceptable risk

          7. Psychiatric disorders or altered mental status precluding understanding of the
             informed consent process and/or completion of the necessary studies

          8. Gastrointestinal disorders that may interfere with absorption of the study drug

          9. Patients with known brain tumours or metastases

         10. More than 6 prior chemotherapy regimens

         11. Patients requiring growth factor support (erythropoietin, Granulocyte/monocyte Colony
             Stimulating Factor (GM/CSF), etc)

         12. Patients requiring palliative radiotherapy within the last 4 weeks prior to study
             entry

         13. Uncontrolled hypercalcaemia (CTCAE v3 grade 2 or higher)

         14. Abnormal plasma potassium or magnesium levels (Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse
             Events (CTCAE) v3 grade 3 or greater) despite therapy

         15. Pregnant or breast-feeding women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bob Löwenberg, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Erasmus Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gert Ossenkoppele, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VU University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pierre Zachee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ZNA Stuivenberg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Norbert Vey, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut Paoli-Calmettes</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ZNA Stuivenberg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antwerp</city>
        <zip>2060</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Paoli-Calmettes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VU University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1007 MB</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Erasmus University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <zip>3015 CE</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 12, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 25, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 25, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 28, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Haematological disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoid malignancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Histone deacetylase inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>dose escalation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Histone Deacetylase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

