<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03172039</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-6388</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03172039</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Antimicrobial Use and Stewardship in an Outpatient Hemodialysis Unit</brief_title>
  <official_title>Antimicrobial Use and Stewardship in an Outpatient Hemodialysis Unit</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This quality improvement study will assess the antimicrobial use and prescribing practices of
      hospital and community prescribers for the ambulatory hemodialysis (HD) population in an
      urban academic outpatient HD unit in Ontario. Currently, in the outpatient HD unit at Toronto
      General Hospital (TGH), it is the standard of care for the patients to be screened on a
      weekly basis by the nephrology care team for the use of any oral or intravenous
      antimicrobials. Patient charts, pharmacy patient profiles and electronic medical records for
      these patients from September 1 2016 - April 30 2017 will be retrospectively reviewed in
      order to characterize antimicrobial use and its concordance with available clinical
      guidelines and antimicrobial stewardship principles described by the Centers for Disease
      Control and Prevention (CDC). The primary objective of the study is to determine the
      prevalence of antimicrobial use in an ambulatory HD population. The secondary objective of
      the study is to determine the congruence of prescribed antimicrobial regimens with available
      clinical guidelines and antimicrobial stewardship principles described by the CDC. It is
      hypothesized that antimicrobial use among HD patients will be common and that antimicrobial
      prescribing practices are not congruent with recommendations from published clinical
      guidelines and antimicrobial stewardship principles for a significant proportion of patients
      included in the retrospective review. Descriptive analysis of the data will summarize the
      findings. Future research will build upon the results of this project, and may include the
      development of interventions that target gaps in knowledge and prescribing behaviours of
      prescribers who provide care to the ambulatory HD population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Description of Study:

      Patients who make up the ambulatory hemodialysis (HD) population at Toronto General Hospital
      (TGH) are interviewed on a weekly basis about their antimicrobial use during the nursing-led
      bedside huddle as part of the standard of care. These huddles take place daily during each of
      the four HD shifts: morning, afternoon, evening and nocturnal. During the huddle the nurse or
      patient care coordinator asks the patient if they have been prescribed an oral or intravenous
      antimicrobial by a hospital or community prescriber in the past 7 days. A Best Possible
      Medication History (BPMH) is completed by a HD Pharmacy team member for all patients who
      stated they have started a new antimicrobial. A BPMH is a patient's medication history which
      is defined as &quot;a systematic process of interviewing the patient/family&quot;, and &quot;a review of at
      least one other reliable source of information&quot; (e.g., dispensing pharmacy records, hospital
      discharge records etc.) to confirm medication use. The BPMH is part of routine care in the HD
      unit and obtained at regular intervals (e.g., when a medication is started, changed or
      discontinued) to ensure the most accurate medication history is available. The BPMH
      containing information about the antimicrobial treatment is documented in the patient's
      medical chart, as well as in the electronic pharmacy patient profile. There will be no
      disruption to the current pharmacy practice and workflow in the HD unit by this study.

      At the end of the data collection period, a panel compromising of a pharmacy resident,
      antimicrobial stewardship pharmacist, nephrology pharmacist, nurse practitioner and
      nephrologist will adjudicate each antimicrobial prescription with a presumed indication for
      congruence with available clinical guidelines and antimicrobial principles described by CDC.
      Each antimicrobial regimen will be categorized as congruent or non-congruent; any regimen for
      which there is inadequate or unavailable documentation in support of congruence will be
      classified as unknown congruence. The primary tool for assessing antimicrobial therapy will
      be against antimicrobial stewardship best practices guiding principles established by CDC,
      supplemented by applicable guidelines for each site of suspected infection published by major
      infectious disease and nephrology societies. Evidence-based resources for drug dosing in
      renal failure will be used to determine whether the prescribed antimicrobial regimen is
      consistent with literature-based dosing recommendations. The prescription will be assessed
      for types of stewardship-discordant prescribing that will be defined based on general
      stewardship principles a priori such as the following:

      i) antimicrobial regimen has incorrect dose/route/frequency for intended infectious syndrome,
      pathogens and/or patient factors ii) length of treatment too short (discontinuation before
      adequate source control or clinical stability) or too long (prolonged therapy despite
      documented microbiologic clearance or resolution of symptoms) iii) empiric therapy spectrum
      too broad or narrow considering possible causative pathogens iv) antimicrobial therapy not
      tailored/streamlined/de-escalated for microbiology results v) non-infectious syndrome

      Number of subjects:

      The outpatient HD unit at TGH has a typical census of 300 patients. It is estimated that
      approximately 300 patient charts will be identified for inclusion as this study will be a
      non-comparative analysis of all patients admitted to the HD unit.

      Statistics:

      Data will be tabulated and analyzed using Microsoft Excel software. Descriptive statistics
      will be used to analyze the data. Means and standard deviations, as well as counts and
      proportions will be calculated for baseline parameters and relevant endpoints as appropriate.
      No interim analyses of the data are anticipated.

      Procedure for accounting for missing, unused, and spurious data:

      A patient's medical chart and pharmacy patient profile are comprehensive for obtaining a
      patient's medication history and therefore missing data should not be a concern. If this
      issue arises all available data sources will be exhausted (e.g., electronic patient record,
      pharmacy patient profiles).

      Quality Assurance:

      All data will be collected by the designated study team member using a data collection sheet
      and following a systematic approach approved by the project team. Raw data will be validated
      and reviewed by the project team following the completion of data collection and prior to
      data analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 12, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of antimicrobial prescriptions in an ambulatory hemodialysis population</measure>
    <time_frame>September 1 2016 - April 30 2017</time_frame>
    <description>Prevalence will be determined by the total number of antimicrobial prescriptions in the study population over the period of study. An antimicrobial prescription will be defined as any oral or intravenous antibacterial or antifungal or antiviral agent prescribed by a community or hospital prescriber to a patient receiving hemodialysis (HD) from Toronto General Hospital's outpatient HD unit. An antimicrobial prescription will follow the 21-day rule.The 21-day rule is that there must be 21 or more days from the end of one antimicrobial course to the beginning of a second antimicrobial course for two courses to be reported as separate prescriptions. If antimicrobials are stopped for fewer than 21 days and then restarted, the second start is not considered a new prescription, and therefore will not be reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Congruence of prescribed antimicrobial regimens</measure>
    <time_frame>September 1 2016 - April 30 2017</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of antimicrobial prescriptions congruent with available clinical guidelines and antimicrobial stewardship principles based on:
i) indication ii) antimicrobial agent iii) spectrum of activity against most likely causative pathogen iv) dose v) route of administration vi) dosing frequency vii) length of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">53</enrollment>
  <condition>End Stage Renal Failure on Dialysis</condition>
  <condition>Infection, Bacterial</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The population to be studied in this retrospective chart review includes patients with
        end-stage renal disease receiving outpatient hemodialysis (HD) treatment at Toronto General
        Hospital (TGH) who were prescribed at least one antimicrobial during the study period.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Receiving outpatient hemodialysis (HD) for at least 3 months

          -  Prescribed at least one oral or intravenous antimicrobial (antibacterial or antifungal
             or antiviral) by a hospital or community prescriber between September 2016 to April 30
             2017 inclusive

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  In-patients admitted to hospital
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2C4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 1, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marisa Battistella</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinician Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hemodialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>antimicrobial stewardship</keyword>
  <keyword>antimicrobial agents</keyword>
  <keyword>bacterial infections</keyword>
  <keyword>ambulatory care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bacterial Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Infective Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

