<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03171272</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>65028517.0.0000.0022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03171272</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Inspiratory Muscle Training on the Functional Gait Performance of Individuals After Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Inspiratory Muscle Training on the Functional Gait Performance of Individuals After Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lorena de Oliveira Vaz Miranda</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sarah Network of Rehabilitation Hospitals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The most commonly observed sequel after stroke is muscle weakness, which can also be
      identified in respiratory muscles, in the acute and chronic phases, and may compromise the
      lung function of these individuals. Studies have shown that lower Pimax values are found in
      non-community ambulators, and gait velocity has been reported as an important indicator of
      functionality after stroke, with higher gait velocity values associated with greater
      community participation and better quality of life.

      This study will test the hypothesis that training of the inspiratory muscles is effective in
      improving strength and endurance of the inspiratory muscles and functionality, including
      speed of gait, functional gait perfomarnce, activities of daily living and quality of life
      with stroke subjects.

      For this clinical trial, people after stroke will be randomly allocated into either
      experimental or control/sham groups. The experimental group will undertake training of the
      inspiratory muscles with the Power Breath Medical Classic device regulated at 50% of the
      subjects' maximal inspiratory pressure values, five times/week over six weeks, twice a day
      for 15 minutes, totaling 30 minutes/day. The control group will undertake the same protocol,
      but the participants will receive the devices with a minimal load, wich corresponds to
      1cmH2O. Both groups will participate in the rehabilitation program for 6 weeks. At baseline
      and post intervention, after the cessation of the interventions, researchers blinded to group
      allocations will collect the following outcome measures: maximal respiratory pressures,
      respiratory muscle endurance, functional gait performance, activities of daily living and
      quality of life. After 12 weeks will collect again maximal inspiratory pressures and
      functional gait performance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The most commonly observed sequel after stroke is muscle weakness, which can also be
      identified in respiratory muscles, in the acute and chronic phases, and may compromise the
      lung function of these individuals. Studies have shown that lower Pimax values are found in
      non-community ambulators, and gait velocity has been reported as an important indicator of
      functionality after stroke, with higher gait velocity values associated with greater
      community participation and better Quality of life.

      Aim: This study will test the hypothesis that training of the inspiratory muscles is
      effective in improving strength and endurance of the inspiratory muscles and functional gait
      perfomarnce, activities of daily living and quality of life with stroke subjects.

      Design: For this prospective, triple-blinded, randomized clinical trial, people after stroke
      will be randomly allocated into either experimental or control/sham groups. The experimental
      group will undertake training of the inspiratory muscles with the PowerBreath Medic Plus
      regulated at 50% of the subjects' maximal inspiratory pressure (MIP) values, five times/week
      over six weeks during 30 minutes/day. The control group will undertake the same protocol, but
      the participants will receive the threshold devices with minimal resistance valves. At
      baseline and post intervention after the cessation of the interventions, researchers blinded
      to group allocations will collect all outcome measures. After 12 weeks will collect again
      maximal inspiratory pressures and functional gait performance.

      Study outcomes: Primary outcomes will be functional gait perfomarnce. Secondary outcomes will
      include inspiratory endurance, activities of daily living and quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change in functional gait perfomarnce</measure>
    <time_frame>change from Baseline at 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>functional gait perfomarnce will be assessed by six minute walk test. (6MWT)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>endurance muscular respiratory</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>inspiratory and expiratory endurance will be assessed by the threshold devices, following previously described protocols.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>maximal respiratory pressures</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, after 6 six weeks and three-monsth follow-ups</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal respiratory pressures will be assessed by a analogic manovacuometer, following previously described protocols.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>functional gait perfomarnce</measure>
    <time_frame>three-monsth follow-ups</time_frame>
    <description>functional gait perfomarnce will be assessed by six minute walk test. (6MWT)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>activities of daily living</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>activities of daily living: will be assessed by measure independence functional (MIF)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, after 6 weeks and three-monsth follow-ups</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life will be assessed by the Brazilian version of the EQ5D.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Inspiratory Muscle Training</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <condition>Gait</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inspiratory Muscle Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Experimental: IMT will include training of the inspiratory muscles five times per week over six weeks, divided into two fiftten-minute sessions of inspiratory training totaling 30 minutes of training. Thresholds regulated at 50% of the subjects' maximal inspiratory pressure values, the load being increased weekly. Associated with the IMT, subjects will participate in the rehabilitation program, when they will perform 7 sessions of physiotherapy per week, totaling 42 sessions, as well as 180 minutes per week of aerobic exercise, for six weeks.
Sham Group: This group will underwent exactly the same protocol but the participants will receive the threshold devices with the minimum resistance of the spring, which will be also concealed. The control group will also participate in the rehabilitation program and undergo the same procedures, except for the load adjustments.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults with hemiparesis after stroke, of any etiology, ischemic or hemorrhagic, that
             carry out walking with or without assistance locomotion; Aged between 18 and 80 years
             of age; In the chronic period (between 6 months and 5 years); clinically stable
             (Measured through clinical and hemodynamic stability: vital signs within normal and
             released for physical activity by the physician), who present with inspiratory muscle
             weakness, defined as Pimáx less than -80cmH2O and score in the normal Mini Mental
             State Examination (MMSE) For schooling.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Smokers and ex-smokers for more than five years, presence of facial paralysis that
             prevents lip occlusion, associated neurological diseases, orthopedic alterations that
             include distortions of the chest cavity or pains that prevent the tests from being
             performed, respiratory dysfunctions, cardiac dysfunctions that Compromise hemodynamic
             stability.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jamary Oliveira Filho</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Bahia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lorena Vaz</last_name>
    <phone>71 32063273</phone>
    <email>lorena.fisio@yahoo.com.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jamary Oliveira Filho</last_name>
    <email>jamary@mail.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lorena de Oliveira Vaz Miranda</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salvador</city>
        <state>Bahia</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lorena Vaz</last_name>
      <phone>71 3206 3273</phone>
      <email>lorena.fisio@yahoo.com.br</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 31, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sarah Network of Rehabilitation Hospitals</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lorena de Oliveira Vaz Miranda</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Graduated in Physiotherapy by UFMG (2009) and specialist in Respiratory Physiotherapy by ASSOBRAFIR (2016)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Aspiration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The data collected in this study will be made available on this basis and will be published in a scientific journal. A master's dissertation will also be built. Further said reports will be provided to the ethics committee while conducting the study.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

