<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03171337</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SouthSNU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03171337</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Efficacy of Acupuncture and Fu's Subcutaneous Needling (FSN ) in Treating Chronic Tension-type Headache by fMRI</brief_title>
  <official_title>To Explore the Cerebral Function Efficacy of Acupuncture and Fu's Subcutaneous Needling (FSN) in the Treatment of Chronic Tension-type Headache by Means of fMRI: a Single-blinded, Randomized Controlled Trials.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jiang Xumei</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Guangdong Provincial Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>South China Normal University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Epidemiological studies show a one-year prevalence of 30%-60% for episodic tension-type
      headache (TTH) and 2%-3% for chronic TTH (CTTH). Many TTH patients seek acupuncture treatment
      worldwide, and CTTH is one of the most commonly treated. FSN has been used to treat CTTH
      recently; the curative effect of it was especially good for CTTH accompanying pericranial
      tenderness. Nonetheless, the effectiveness of acupuncture and FSN for CTTH remains
      controversial. Several research results showed that symptoms of TTH improve after acupuncture
      treatment, but these improvements were more subjective than objective measures. So, the aim
      of this study is to determine the cerebral function efficacy of acupuncture and FSN in the
      treatment of CTTH, using Headache impact test questionnaire (HIT-6), VAS to evaluate the
      subjective symptom and fMRI to detect the objective cerebral function changes.

      Intervention: device: acupuncture; Fu's subcutaneous; placebo sham acupuncture
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tension-type headache (TTH) is the most prevalent type of primary headache. Unlike migraine,
      however, there have been no significant treatment advances for chronic TTH in the past few
      decades, probably due to the limited understanding of its pathophysiology compared with that
      of migraine. The objective of the present study is to investigate the cerebral function
      imaging changes in patients with chronic tension headache trough comparing that in healthy
      people, focus on the regional homogeneity (ReHo) of ROIs of brain. In addition, the effect of
      acupuncture and Fu's subcutaneous needing (FSN) on the cerebral function will also be
      studied. This is a clinical trial study, randomized, in parallel, single-blinded assessor,
      and with a sham placebo control.

      The study will be carried out in the （Traditional therapy center, Guangdong Hospital of
      Traditional Chinese Medicine）. Patients will be collected according to the inclusion criteria
      (conform to diagnose criterion for headache ICHD-3), with age between 18 and 45 years old.
      Healthy people will be collected too according to the inclusion criteria for healthy people,
      with age matching with the patients. The participants will respond to questionnaires at the
      beginning and end of the first, fifth and last therapeutic intervention and their fMRI of
      brain will be acquired. The therapeutic intervention will include: 8 acupuncture sessions, 8
      FSN sessions and 8 placebo sham acupuncture sessions (twice per week for 4 weeks). The
      measurements taken will be: impact of headache on daily life, severity of headache, emotional
      problem of headache, the cerebral function of ROIs (by means of fMRI) of headache and so on.

      Through these interventions it is hoped that patients will present an improvement in their
      pain presentation, quality of life and emotional problem, as well as cerebral function
      imaging in certain region of brain. Evidence for these hypotheses will provide the cerebral
      function effect mechanism of acupuncture and FSN to CTTH, and some evidence in the research
      will perhaps support that acupuncture and FSN are two type minimally-invasive treatment
      methods, with few side-effects and low cost.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 10, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The parallel group includes the positive and negative controls, the positive control is Fu's Subcutaneous Needling group and the negative is Sham acupuncture group. And the other parallel control is the fMRI of patients with CTTH VS fMRI of healthy people.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes of Regional homogeneity data (ReHo) (using Kendall's coefficient of concordance as index) of Resting state fMRI of the whole brain (from the Vertex to Basicranial)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
    <description>ReHo data before and after the first/last, as well as after the fourth acupuncture, FSN and sham acupuncture treatment, Changes of ReHo data from baseline to after the first, fourth, last treatment will be calculated in each treatment group and will be compared with each other.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Visual Analogue Scale (VAS）</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months.</time_frame>
    <description>The intensity of pain was measured by a 10 cm VAS. The scores range from no pain (zero) to the worst possible pain (10 cm).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Headache Impact Test (HIT-6)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months.</time_frame>
    <description>It consists of six questions that assess the impact of headache on the ability to work, study, at home and in social situations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Tension-Type Headache</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Acupuncture at acupoints for CTTH according to TCM theory, twice 1 week for 4 weeks，fMRI will be used to detect the cerebral function changes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fu's subcutaneous needling (FSN)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>FSN at the points related with CTTH, twice 1 week for 4 weeks, fMRI will be used to detect the cerebral function changes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham acupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Streitberger placebo needles at nonacupoint for CTTH, twice 1 week for 4 weeks,fMRI will be used to detect the cerebral function changes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acupuncture</intervention_name>
    <description>Acupuncture at acupoints for CTTH according to TCM theory using stainless filiform needle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Filiform needle</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fu's Subcutaneous Needling (FSN)</intervention_name>
    <description>Fu's subcutaneous needling at specific points for CTTH using soft casing needle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fu's subcutaneous needling (FSN)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fu's Acupuncture; Floating Needling; Fu Needling</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham acupuncture</intervention_name>
    <description>Sham acupuncture at non-acupoints using Steinberger placebo needles</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham acupuncture</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo Acupuncture</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Conforms to clinical diagnostic criteria of CTTH associated with pericranial
             tenderness（ICHD-3 beta version）, Han nationality.

          2. Aged between 18 and 45 years old men or women with right-handed.

          3. No history of cognitive dysfunction.

          4. Seeking medical advice for TTH for the first time.

          5. Providing informed consent to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Taking analgesics or other drugs may affect the resting state fMRI scans of brain
             within two weeks.

          2. Have hypertension, diabetes, anxiety, depression and other systemic diseases, other
             chronic pain etc. Psychiatric or neurologic disorder that unable patient to consent
             and follow study protocol.

          3. Combined with other type headache.

          4. Intracranial lesions are found in MRI or CT scans.

          5. Headache breaks out within 24h after fMRI scan.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhouyi Guo, Pro</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>SATCM Third Grade Laboratory of Chinese Medicine and Photonics Technology, College of Biophotonics and fMRI chamber, research resources center, South China Normal University.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jian Sun, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Traditional therapy center, Guangdong Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xuemei Jiang, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>（86）13751847873</phone>
    <email>jxmacu01@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Zhouyi Guo, Pro</last_name>
    <phone>（86）13503004488</phone>
    <email>ann@scnu.edu.cn</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 31, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>South China Normal University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jiang Xumei</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Postdoctor;Lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic tension-type headache</keyword>
  <keyword>Acupuncture</keyword>
  <keyword>Fu's subcutaneous needling(FSN)</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Regional homogeneity (ReHo)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Headache</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tension-Type Headache</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

