<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03177252</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201701037</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03177252</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Scalp Block: Hemodynamic Stability and Patient Comfort In Craniotomy Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>Scalp block</acronym>
  <official_title>Scalp Block: Hemodynamic Stability and Patient Comfort In Craniotomy Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Making sure the heart rate and or the blood pressure [called hemodynamic instability] during
      surgery is stable, setting up for a rapid postoperative recovery, and ensuring that patients
      have adequate pain relief are some of the important goals of neurosurgical anesthesia. Scalp
      block anesthesia [injection of a numbing agent into the area of the scalp where the incision
      will be] together with general anesthesia is used to achieve these goals. There has been some
      research on whether or not scalp block improves patient recovery and pain management, but the
      studies have not be large enough to say for certain. This is true even though scalp block is
      used with almost every patient that is having brain surgery. The investigators propose to
      determine if scalp block in combination with asleep anesthesia is better than asleep
      anesthesia alone in patients who are having brain surgery for tumors in the cerebral area of
      the brain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Avoidance of hemodynamic fluctuations in the heart rate and or the blood pressure
      perioperatively, rapid postoperative recovery, and adequate postoperative pain relief are
      some of the important goals of neurosurgical anesthesia. Scalp block in association with
      general anesthesia is used to achieve these goals. Previous studies have been published
      related to the effect of scalp block on the perioperative outcomes on the craniotomy
      patients. The results reported so far are controversial and one cannot at this point define a
      positive effect for post-operative pain relief. This disparity in results may be the
      consequences of the size of the patient population. However scalp block is an accepted
      practice in the craniotomy patients. The investigators believe this is the first study which
      assesses the effectiveness of scalp block for asleep craniotomy with the largest sample size
      study so far conducted in the literature related to this topic. The aim of this study is to
      assess the effectiveness of scalp block for the perioperative comfort of the craniotomy
      patients undergoing resection for supratentorial tumors.

      After the consent for the participation and enrollment in the study is done, patients will be
      randomized to two groups, a study group will receive a scalp block with a mixture of 2%
      lidocaine and 0.5% bupivacaine while the control group will receive the scalp block with
      saline. Intraoperatively, all patients will be preoxygenated, fentanyl (1-2mcg/kg) will be
      given and anesthesia will be induced with propofol (1-2mg/kg) and lidocaine (1-1.5mg/kg).
      Tracheal intubation will be facilitated by using either rocuronium (0.6 mg/kg) or
      succinylcholine (1-1.5mg/kg) intravenously. The lungs will be ventilated with a fresh gas
      flow of oxygen for 2 minutes before tracheal intubation with cuffed oral endotracheal tube.
      Anesthesia will be maintained with inhalational anesthetic Isoflurane, Sevoflurane or
      Desflurane (0.8-1 MAC) and fentanyl infusion (1-2mcg/kg) with the dose adjusted according to
      the patient's hemodynamics. Bilateral BIS or EEG to maintain an adequate level of depth of
      anesthesia will be used whenever feasible. After intubation, a scalp block will be performed.
      The randomization of the scalp block syringes will be provided by the pharmacy and neither
      the scalp block performer nor the attending will be aware of the syringe content. To
      standardize the block, a pain specialist is involved. Response to the pinning will be
      assessed using the hemodynamic parameters and rescue analgesics (fentanyl bolus 50 - 100 mcg)
      and/or propofol bolus 50 - 100 mg will be given as a bolus if significant response is noted.
      Significant response being a rise in the patient's heart rate and/or the blood pressure more
      than 20% from the patient's baseline heart rate and/or the blood pressure just before
      pinning. Similarly, response to the surgical incision will be noted and rescue analgesics
      will be given if needed. Intraoperative propofol requirement and opioid requirements will be
      recorded. The post-operative orders for pain control will be standardized for all the
      patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall perioperative comfort of the patient as measured by hemodynamic fluctuations</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Hemodynamic fluctuations during pinning of the head with a Mayfield head-holder and skin incision which represents the most extreme painful stimulation for the entire surgery (significant response being rise in the patient's heart rate and/or the blood pressure more than 20% from the patient's baseline heart rate and/or the blood pressure prior pinning)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall perioperative comfort as measured by opioid requirements</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Overall perioperative opioid requirements until the next morning of the surgery as an overall evaluation of the patient's comfort.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness of scalp block</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Scalp block for the craniotomy
lowers overall administration of opioids, which will decrease the side effects of opioids
improve the immediate postoperative pain which may decrease the occurrence of chronic postoperative pain and
may result in the early discharge from the hospital contributing to shorter hospital stay reducing the financial burden for both the patient and the hospital.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Tumor, Brain</condition>
  <condition>Anesthesia, Local</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Scalp block with lidocaine and bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Scalp block with a mixture of 2% lidocaine and 0.5% bupivacaine
Once the surgery is completed, patients will be awaken and extubated following a basic neurological exam. If the extubation is delayed or if the patient is taken to ICU intubated, those patients will be excluded from the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Scalp block with saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Scalp block with saline
Once the surgery is completed, patients will be awaken and extubated following a basic neurological exam. If the extubation is delayed or if the patient is taken to ICU intubated, those patients will be excluded from the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lidocaine</intervention_name>
    <description>-2% lidocaine will be given</description>
    <arm_group_label>Scalp block with lidocaine and bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sodium chloride</intervention_name>
    <description>-Normal saline will be given</description>
    <arm_group_label>Scalp block with saline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Saline</other_name>
    <other_name>Normal Saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>-0.5% bupivacaine will be given</description>
    <arm_group_label>Scalp block with lidocaine and bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        -&gt;18years of age undergoing elective craniotomy for supratentorial tumors

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age group &lt; 18

          -  Emergency craniotomies

          -  Infratentorial tumors.

          -  Patients who need intraoperative evoked potential monitoring which precludes the scalp
             block.

          -  Patients with known cranial defects.

          -  Patients who are on medications for chronic pain.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Umeshkumar Athiraman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Umeshkumar Athiraman, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>314-362-2330</phone>
    <email>uathira@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University in St Louis School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Umeshkumar Athiraman, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-2330</phone>
      <email>uathira@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Umeshkumar Athiraman, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rene Tempelhoff, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gregory Zipfel, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Bottros, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aaron Norris, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexandre Todorov, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.siteman.wustl.edu</url>
    <description>Alvin J. Siteman Cancer Center at Barnes-Jewish Hospital and Washington University School of Medicine</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 1, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

