<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03174886</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AC-TP-001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-000643-41</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03174886</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A 24-month Phase 1 Pilot Study of AADvac1 in Patients With Non Fluent Primary Progressive Aphasia</brief_title>
  <acronym>AIDA</acronym>
  <official_title>A 24-month Randomised Parallel Group Single-blinded Multi-centre Phase 1 Pilot Study of AADvac1 in Patients With Non Fluent Primary Progressive Aphasia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Axon Neuroscience SE</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Axon Neuroscience SE</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a pilot trial evaluating the safety and immunogenicity of AADvac1 in patients
      with the non-fluent variant of Primary Progressive Aphasia.

      50% of participants will receive the 40 µg dosage of AADvac1 and 50% of participants will
      receive the 160 µg dosage of AADvac1. No placebo is used.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The non-fluent variant of Primary progressive Aphasia (nfvPPA) is a chronic progressive
      neurodegenerative disorder of the brain. Over the course of the disease, pathological
      proteins accumulate in the brain, damaging neurons, thus causing them to lose their
      connections and die.

      No treatments are currently available; symptomatic medications are used off-label in nfvPPA.

      AADvac1 is designed to raise antibodies against pathological tau protein (the primary
      constituent of neurofibrillary pathology, which is the underlying cause of disease in ~80% of
      nfvPPA cases). These antibodies are expected to prevent tau protein from aggregating, to
      facilitate the removal of tau protein aggregates and prevent the spreading of pathology,
      slowing or halting the progress of the disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 31, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients will be allocated to one of two dosage strengths of AADvac1. No placebo is used. No active comparator is used.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Patients are unaware of the dosage strength they are receiving. The AADvac1 vials are numbered, and the coding unknown to the patient. The investigator handles the vaccine vials and administers the IMP.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events [Safety and Tolerability]</measure>
    <time_frame>25 months</time_frame>
    <description>The safety assessment is based on the number, type and severity of adverse events (AEs).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity (Percentage of patients who develop an IgG immune response, geometric mean titre of titre of antibodies against Axon Peptide 108, IgG to IgM ratio of antibodies against Axon Peptide 108)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>AADvac1 depends on raising antibodies that mediate its treatment effects. Immunogenicity assessment includes: Percentage of AADvac1-treated patients who develop an immune response (responder rate), geometric mean titre of antibodies against Axon Peptide 108, IgG to IgM ratio of antibodies against Axon Peptide 108.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in total CSF neurogranin, phosphorylated neurofilament heavy chain protein, ubiquitin, β-synuclein, tau protein, phospho-tau pT181, N-terminal tau protein, amyloid β1-40, amyloid-β1-42, ubiquitin, α-, β- and γ-synuclein, Chitinase-3-like protein (YKL-40), Monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1), and other CSF markers</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serum neurofilament light chain protein (and other blood biomarkers of nfvPPA)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in neurofilament light chain protein and other blood biomarkers (exploratory measure; biomarker panel to be finalised based on the state of the art at the time of analysis)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) volumetry</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in whole brain volume and set of regions of interest, as measured by MRI</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Frontotemporal lobar degeneration - Clinical Dementia Rating - Sum of Boxes (FTLD-CDR-SB)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in FTLD-CDR SB score</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician's Global Impression - Improvement (CGI-I)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in CGI-I score</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (IADL)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in Amsterdam IADL</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Custom Cognitive Battery</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in the custom Cognitive Battery score</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Addenbrooke's Cognitive Examination</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in Addenbrooke's Cognitive Examination score</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Unified Parkinson's disease rating scale (UPDRS) part III</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in UPDRS part III score</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Frontal Systems Behavior Scale (FrSBe)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in FrSBe score</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Immune cell (granulocyte, monocyte, and lymphocyte populations)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Temporal change in immunological variables (monocytes, lymphocytes, basophil and neutrophil granulocytes; a range of lymphocyte sub-populations - CD3+, CD3+/CD4+, CD3+/CD4+/CD28+, CD3+/CD4+/CD28+/CD45RA+, CD3+/CD4+/CD28+/CD45RO+, CD3+/CD8+, CD3+/CD8+/CD28+, CD3+/CD8+/CD28+/CD45RA+, CD3+/CD8+/CD28+/CD45RO+) over 24 months</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of a range of potential immunological predictors with IgG antibody titres against Axon Peptide 108</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of measures of immune response with immunological variables (monocytes, lymphocytes, basophil and neutrophil granulocytes; a range of lymphocyte sub-populations - CD3+, CD3+/CD4+, CD3+/CD4+/CD28+, CD3+/CD4+/CD28+/CD45RA+, CD3+/CD4+/CD28+/CD45RO+, CD3+/CD8+, CD3+/CD8+/CD28+, CD3+/CD8+/CD28+/CD45RA+, CD3+/CD8+/CD28+/CD45RO+) will individually be assessed for correlation with IgG antibody titres. The possibility of multiple independent predictors of the antibody response will be examined using regression trees analysis)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Progressive Nonfluent Aphasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AADvac1 40 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention consists of Axon Peptide 108 coupled to keyhole limpet haemocyanin (KLH) 40 µg/0.30 mL suspension for injection; and aluminium hydroxide Al(OH)3 (containing approx. 0.5 mg Al3+/0.30 mL), administered subcutaneously. The basic immunisation regimen consists of 6 doses administered subcutaneously in 6-week intervals. Subsequently, 5 booster doses are applied in 13-week intervals, for a total of 11 administrations.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AADvac1 160 µg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention consists of Axon Peptide 108 coupled to KLH 160 µg/0.30 mL suspension for injection; and aluminium hydroxide Al(OH)3 (containing approx. 0.5 mg Al3+/0.30 mL), administered subcutaneously. The basic immunisation regimen consists of 6 doses administered subcutaneously in 6-week intervals. Subsequently, 5 booster doses are applied in 13-week intervals, for a total of 11 administrations.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AADvac1 40 µg</intervention_name>
    <description>Active immunotherapy against neurofibrillary pathology.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AADvac1 40 µg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AADvac1 160 µg</intervention_name>
    <description>Active immunotherapy against neurofibrillary pathology.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AADvac1 160 µg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          1. Patient has a clinical diagnosis of non-fluent/agrammatic variant PPA according to the
             criteria by Gorno-Tempini et al. (2011) with evidence of left frontal brain
             hypometabolism. Patients with right-sided hypometabolism are eligible for the study
             only if they are left-handed.

          2. Patient has a FTLD-CDR language domain score of ≤ 2, and other individual FTLD-CDR
             domain scores ≤ 1.

          3. Patient's age is 18 - 85 years inclusive at the time of having provided informed
             consent.

          4. Patient has adequate visual and auditory abilities and premorbid local language skills
             to allow neuropsychological testing.

          5. Sexually active female patients must be using highly effective contraception methods,
             or be surgically sterile, or be at least 2 years post-menopausal.

          6. Sexually active male patients must be using highly effective contraception methods, or
             be surgically sterile.

          7. Patient and caregiver have signed and dated written informed consent.

          8. Availability of a partner/caregiver knowing the patient and being able to accompany
             the patient to the visits.

          9. Patient is legally competent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The patient's brain MRI is incompatible with a diagnosis of nfvPPA.

          2. Patient has a history or evidence of a central nervous system (CNS) disorder other
             than nfvPPA which may cause symptoms of aphasia or dementia (Alzheimer's disease,
             Dementia with Lewy Bodies, inflammatory/demyelinating CNS conditions,
             Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, Huntington's disease, etc.)

          3. Patient has a history or currently suffers from a significant psychiatric illness such
             as schizophrenia, any type of psychotic disorder or bipolar affective disorder.

          4. Patient has a history or evidence of cerebrovascular disease (ischemic or haemorrhagic
             stroke), or diagnosis of possible, probable or definite vascular dementia.

          5. Patient has Wernicke's encephalopathy.

          6. Patient has metabolic or toxic encephalopathy or dementia due to a general medical
             condition.

          7. Patient suffers from hypothyroidism, defined as thyroid-stimulating hormone elevation
             &gt; 5.000 mcIU/mL, and/or fT4 levels &lt; 0.7 ng/dL. Patients with corrected hypothyroidism
             are eligible for the study provided that treatment has been stable for 12 weeks before
             study entry.

          8. Patient has a known pathogenic mutation in GRN or C9orf72.

          9. Presence or history of allergy to components of the vaccine.

         10. Presence and/or history of immunodeficiency (e.g., HIV).

         11. Patient is currently being treated with immunosuppressive drugs.

         12. Patient has a history and/or currently suffers from a clinically significant
             autoimmune disease, or is expected to receive immunosuppressive or immunomodulatory
             treatment at the present or in the future.

         13. Patient has a recent (≤ 5 years since last specific treatment) history of cancer
             (Exceptions: basal cell carcinoma, intraepithelial cervical neoplasia).

         14. Patient has an active infectious disease (e.g., Hepatitis B, C).

         15. Patient had a myocardial infarction within the last 2 years.

         16. Patient has a current clinically important systemic illness that is likely to result
             in deterioration of the patient's condition or affect the subject's safety during the
             study:

               1. poorly controlled congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association [NYHA]
                  score ≥ 3),

               2. poorly controlled diabetes,

               3. severe renal insufficiency (Estimated glomerular filtration rate &lt; 30 mL/min),

               4. chronic liver disease - ALT (alanine aminotransferase) &gt; 2x upper limit of normal
                  range (ULN), AST (aspartate aminotransferase) &gt; 2x ULN

               5. other clinically significant systemic illness, if considered relevant by the
                  investigator.

         17. Patient had alcohol or drug dependence within the past year.

         18. Patient has a current diagnosis of epilepsy.

         19. Pregnant or breastfeeding women.

         20. Patient has participated in another interventional clinical trial within 12 weeks
             before Visit 01.

         21. Patient has contraindication for MRI imaging such as metallic endoprosthesis or
             MRI-incompatible stent implantation.

         22. Patient has contraindications for other study procedures, such as CSF sampling.

         23. Patient had surgery (under general anaesthesia) within 12 weeks prior to Visit 01
             and/or scheduled surgery (under general anaesthesia) during the whole study period.

         24. Patient is currently being treated or was treated in the past with any active vaccines
             for a neurodegenerative disorder.

         25. Patients not expected to complete the clinical trial.

         26. Patient, in the opinion of the investigator, is unlikely to comply with the clinical
             study protocol, or is unsuitable for other reasons.

         27. Patient is dependent from Sponsor or investigator (e.g. as an employee or as a
             relative).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Markus Otto, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universitat Ulm</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matej Ondrus, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00421 220 921 620</phone>
    <email>ondrus@axon-neuroscience.eu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Petr Novak, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>00421 220 921 620</phone>
    <email>petr.novak@axon-neuroscience.eu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsmedizin Göttingen, Klinik für Psychiatrie und Psychotherapie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Göttingen</city>
        <zip>37075</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jens Wiltfang, Prof</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Anne Elisa Sagebiel, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0049 (0)5513966610</phone>
      <email>anneelisa.sagebiel@med.uni-goettingen.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum Rechts der Isar der TU München, Klinik und Poliklinik für Psychiatrie und Psychotherapie</name>
      <address>
        <city>München</city>
        <zip>81675</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Timo Grimmer, Prof</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Janine Diehl-Schmid, Prof</last_name>
      <phone>0049 (0)8941406488</phone>
      <email>janine.diehl-schmid@tum.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsklinikum Ulm</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulm</city>
        <zip>89081</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Markus Otto, Prof</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sarah Straub, Dr</last_name>
      <phone>0049 (0)73150063099</phone>
      <email>sarah.straub@uni.ulm.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kontsekova E, Zilka N, Kovacech B, Skrabana R, Novak M. Identification of structural determinants on tau protein essential for its pathological function: novel therapeutic target for tau immunotherapy in Alzheimer's disease. Alzheimers Res Ther. 2014 Aug 1;6(4):45. doi: 10.1186/alzrt277. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25478018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kontsekova E, Zilka N, Kovacech B, Novak P, Novak M. First-in-man tau vaccine targeting structural determinants essential for pathological tau-tau interaction reduces tau oligomerisation and neurofibrillary degeneration in an Alzheimer's disease model. Alzheimers Res Ther. 2014 Aug 1;6(4):44. doi: 10.1186/alzrt278. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25478017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Novak P, Schmidt R, Kontsekova E, Zilka N, Kovacech B, Skrabana R, Vince-Kazmerova Z, Katina S, Fialova L, Prcina M, Parrak V, Dal-Bianco P, Brunner M, Staffen W, Rainer M, Ondrus M, Ropele S, Smisek M, Sivak R, Winblad B, Novak M. Safety and immunogenicity of the tau vaccine AADvac1 in patients with Alzheimer's disease: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 1 trial. Lancet Neurol. 2017 Feb;16(2):123-134. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(16)30331-3. Epub 2016 Dec 10.</citation>
    <PMID>27955995</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 29, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 31, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>tau</keyword>
  <keyword>neurofibrillary</keyword>
  <keyword>degeneration</keyword>
  <keyword>primary progressive aphasia</keyword>
  <keyword>agrammatic</keyword>
  <keyword>tauopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>immunization</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aphasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aphasia, Primary Progressive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pick Disease of the Brain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Frontotemporal Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aphasia, Broca</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Primary Progressive Nonfluent Aphasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aluminum Hydroxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

