<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01161641</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PGX-ODSH-2009-PLE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01161641</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot/Ph I Safety and Efficacy of ODSH in Protein Losing Enteropathy Secondary to Single Ventricle Palliative Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>&quot; An Open Label Pilot Study Evaluating Safety and Evidence of Therapeutic Effect of IV Admin of 2-0, 3-0 Desulfated Heparin, Treatment of Exacerbation of Protein Losing Enteropathy (PLE) Associated With Single Ventricle Palliative Surgery&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cantex Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cantex Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Protein Losing Enteropathy (PLE) is a serious medical condition that may develop in children
      and adults with congenital heart disease for which a palliative procedure known as the
      &quot;Fontan procedure&quot; has been performed. The loss of serum proteins into the gastrointestinal
      tract that is associated with PLE can cause serious symptoms and life-threatening
      complications. A number of clinical studies have suggested that heparin administration can
      have clinical benefit in children with PLE, however the risk of bleeding associated with the
      administration of heparin is an important concern and commonly limits its administration.
      ODSH is a desulfated heparin with minimal anticoagulation properties but which, in
      pre-clinical studies, appears to have the potential to replace heparin and greatly reduce the
      risk of bleeding. This open label study is to assess the safety and evidence of therapeutic
      effect of the administration of ODSH as a 4-day continuous intravenous infusion in patients
      with an exacerbation of their PLE.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Protein Losing Enteropathy (PLE)is a serious and sometimes fatal condition that develops in
      approximately 10% of children who have undergone the single ventricle palliative surgery
      known as the Fontan procedure. The mechanisms by which PLE develops are not fully understood,
      however a recent mechanism has been proposed consistent with the specific loss of heparan
      sulfate proteoglycans from the basolateral surface of the intestinal epithelial cells
      resulting in the loss of serum protein including albumin and immunoglobulins into the
      gastrointestinal tract that is associated with protein losing enteropathy. A number of
      clinical studies have suggested that heparin administration can have clinical benefit in
      children with PLE, however the risk of bleeding as a consequence of treatment is an important
      concern and commonly limits its administration. ODSH (2-0, 3-0 desulfated heparin) is a
      modified heparin that preserves the anti-inflammatory properties of heparin with minimal or
      no anticoagulation effects. ODSH has been studied in the rodent model of PLE an has shown
      improvement of PLE in this model due to restoration of heparan sulfate and Syndecan 1 with
      stabilization of the cell matrix of the capillary endothelium.

      This open label clinical study will enroll 9 subjects with a dose escalation (3 doses) study
      design. Three subjects will be treated with the lower dose of ODSH then an ad hoc safety
      committee will assess the safety information to make a recommendation regarding advancing to
      the next higher dose of ODSH until, if appropriate, the 3 dose cohorts have been completed.
      Plasma albumin and fecal alpha 1 antitrypsin which are both biological markers of protein
      loss through the intestinal lumen in this condition, are the primary variables that will be
      evaluated as evidence of a therapeutic effect together with the improvement of PLE signs and
      symptoms. The effect of ODSH on the associated diarrhea, abdominal pain, and peripheral edema
      or ascites will be evaluated using visual/categorical scales for the patients to assess
      symptoms and clinical evaluation by the investigator.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Extremely slow accural due to rarity of medical condition studied.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical improvement of PLE symptoms and signs.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 4 after 96 hours of IV continuous infusion of ODSH</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical Improvement of signs &amp; symptoms of PLE such as diarrhea, abdominal pain, peripheral edema, and ascites. Visual/categorical scales will be used by the study subjects and the investigators to assess diarrhea/abdominal pain intensity as well as The Global Impression of Improvement. The investigator will assess peripheral edema and ascites.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fecal alpha 1 antitrypsin (FA1AT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 4 after 96 hours of ODSH IV continuous infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Decrease of Fecal alpha 1 antitrypsin level at Day 4 compared to baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum albumin levels.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 4 after 96 hours of continuous IV infusion of ODSH</time_frame>
    <description>Serum albumin levels at Day 4 compared to Baseline. A serum albumin level of 3 or more mg/dL or at least an increase of 25% from baseline at Day 4 or the reduction in the need for additional albumin infusions will be considered as clinically significant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ODSH safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 2, 3 and 4</time_frame>
    <description>aPTT as a measure of coagulation effect from ODSH will be measured every day. If the aPTT value is 8 or more seconds higher than the upper limit of normal value of aPTT for the study site then the ODSH infusion rate will be decreased as recommended in the protocol. Coagulation and bleeding abnormalities will be monitored closely by the investigator. Liver enzymes will also be monitored during the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK: ODSH plasma blood levels at steady state</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 3 (during Day 3 of ODSH IV continuous infusion)</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the plasma levels of ODSH at steady state</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Protein Losing Enteropathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ODSH at 0.125 mg/kg/h</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>First cohort of 3 subjects to be administered the lowest dose of ODSH.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ODSH at 0.250 mg/kg/h</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Second cohort of 3 subjects to receive the medium dose of ODSH</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ODSH at 0.375 mg/kg/h</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Third and last cohort of subject to receive the high dose of ODSH.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ODSH at 0.125 mg/kg/h</intervention_name>
    <description>ODSH 1000 mg vials containing 20 cc of normal saline (50 mg/ml) to be prepared for 96-h IV infusion with normal saline based on subject's weight and dose assigned by Study Cohort 1 of 0.125 mg/kg/h.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ODSH at 0.125 mg/kg/h</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cohort 1</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ODSH at 0.375 mg/kg/h</intervention_name>
    <description>ODSH 1000 mg vials containing 20 cc of normal saline (50 mg/ml) to be prepared for 96-h IV infusion with normal saline based on subject's weight and dose assigned by Study Cohort 3 of 0.375 mg/kg/h.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ODSH at 0.375 mg/kg/h</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cohort 3</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ODSH at 0.250 mg/kg/h</intervention_name>
    <description>ODSH 1000 mg vials containing 20 cc of normal saline (50 mg/ml) to be prepared for 96-h IV infusion with normal saline based on subject's weight and dose assigned by Study Cohort 2 of 0.250 mg/kg/h.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ODSH at 0.250 mg/kg/h</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cohort 2</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female ≥ 6 years old.

          2. History of single ventricle palliative surgery.

          3. Anticipated need for four or more days of hospitalization, in the investigator's
             judgment, for the treatment of exacerbation of PLE.

             Clinically significant PLE is defined as the presence of clinically significant
             symptoms (including, but not limited to, diarrhea, abdominal pain, peripheral edema
             and/or ascites), AND increased fecal alpha 1-antitrypsin (FA1AT; &gt; 200 mg/dl) OR
             hypoalbuminemia of &lt; 3 gr/dL; requiring supplemental albumin infusions.

          4. Prothrombin time (PT) and activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) not higher than
             1.25 times the ULN for age.

          5. Platelet count of &gt; 80,000 per mm3, hemoglobin of &gt; 9.5 g/dL.

          6. The adult subject or the underage subject/legal guardian is willing to provide
             informed consent and to comply with the study procedures.

          7. Female subject of childbearing potential who is not pregnant, and is not lactating and
             is not planning to become pregnant during the study and will use medically acceptable
             contraception method for the duration of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has congenital or acquired hematologic disease or coagulation disorder.

          2. Has other type of PLE not associated with single ventricle palliative surgery e.g.
             subjects with congenital defects of glycation or with Crohn's disease; congenital
             trypsinogen or enterokinase deficiency;

          3. Has a clinical need for prophylactic or therapeutic treatment with oral or parenteral
             anticoagulant medications within 72 hours from the start of ODSH treatment or during
             the study. [The use of antithrombotic agents such as acetyl salicylic acid for
             cardiovascular prophylaxis or clopidogrel (or similar drug class agents) is
             permitted].

          4. Has documented liver failure or a serum ALT or AST greater than 1.5 times the upper
             limit of normal, or total bilirubin greater than 1.5 the upper limit of normal;

          5. Has clinically significant proteinuria or severe renal failure based on a creatinine
             clearance &lt; 30 mL/min calculated from plasma creatinine (Appendix B) with the
             Cockcroft-Gault formula for adults or with any of the recommended formulas for
             subjects 6 to 18 years old;

          6. Has active gastrointestinal ulcer disease or evidence of gastrointestinal bleeding or
             urinary tract bleeding or any other source of bleeding within 60 days of the Screening
             visit.

          7. History of HIV, hepatitis B or hepatitis C; and

          8. Major surgery, stroke or myocardial infarction within the past 60 days from screening.
             Subjects with recent minor surgery can be enrolled in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Russell, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Division of Pediatric Cardiology, University of Michigan Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Los Angeles ( Gastroenterology &amp; Nutrition)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>20027-6016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Cardiology, Children's Hospital Boston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Division of Pediatric Cardiology, University of Michigan Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109-5204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sanford Children's ( Sanford Research / USD)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sioux Falls</city>
        <state>South Dakota</state>
        <zip>57104-4707</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 9, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 5, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 5, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Protein Losing Enteropathy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Intestinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Protein-Losing Enteropathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

