<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01163383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2005-02-4159</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CHP-830</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01163383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>131-I-MIBG Therapy for Refractory Neuroblastoma and Metastatic Paraganglioma/Pheochromocytoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>I-Metaiodobenzylguanidine (131 I-MIBG) Therapy for Refractory Neuroblastoma and Paraganglioma/Pheochromocytoma Expanded Access Protocol</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Metaiodobenzylguanidine (MIBG) is a substance that is taken up by neuroblastoma or
      pheochromocytoma/paraganglioma tumor cells. MIBG is combined with radioactive iodine (131 I)
      in the laboratory to form a radioactive compound 131 I-MIBG. This radioactive compound
      delivers radiation specifically to the cancer cells and causes them to die.

      The purpose of this research protocol is to provides a mechanism to deliver MIBG therapy when
      clinically indicated, but also to provide a mechanism to continue to collect efficacy and
      toxicity data that will be provided.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      131I-MIBG is experimental, but has been used in more than 100 children in the United States
      by itself to treat relapsed neuroblastoma and metastatic pheochromocytoma/ganglioma. A recent
      study using increasing doses of 131I-MIBG in both children and adults with relapsed
      neuroblastoma or metastatic pheochromocytoma/ganglioma showed anti-cancer effects in some of
      these patients. The main side effect of this treatment was a decrease in the number of normal
      blood-forming cells (called stem cells) in the bone marrow, but a dose of 12 mCi/kg did not
      cause permanent damage to the bone marrow in a small number of patients.

      There are certain tests or procedures that will need to be done to confirm that the subject
      is eligible for this therapy. These include lab work, physical exam and MIBG scan. A CT scan,
      an MRI, a bone scan, Bone marrow aspirate and biopsy and urine tests will be done to evaluate
      your disease status when clinically indicated. Your doctor will determine which tests are
      required.

      Subjects will need to have an intravenous catheter (tube) placed in a vein before beginning
      study treatment. An existing central venous catheter can be used to administer the medicine.

      Because subjects' urine will be radioactive, a urinary catheter may be inserted to ensure
      drainage of the urine, which will be radioactive. The catheter will be removed 3-5 days
      following the treatment. General anesthesia or sedation is typically given for the procedure
      of inserting the catheter.

      Subjects will be treated in a specially prepared room in the CHOP Pediatric Oncology Unit.
      Upon admission, the nursing staff will instruct caregivers on the care of the subject
      following the MIBG infusion. Because of the frequent exposure of the nursing staff to
      radiation and the high level of radiation surrounding the subject during therapy, the nurses'
      contact will be limited to complex medical care, so that they are available for subjects in
      the event of an emergency. Adult family members will be expected to be present at all times
      during the hospitalization to:

        -  Assist with hygiene

        -  Give oral medications

        -  Offer and empty bedpans

        -  Assist with meals

        -  Change diapers (if used)

        -  Change clothing and bed linens if soiled

        -  Entertain or distract individuals who become upset or restless due to the isolation or
           procedures.

        -  Record Dosimeter readings.

      Isolation: For 2-5 days subjects will be placed in a single room with a bed surrounded by
      lead shielding to prevent exposure of visitors and hospital personnel to radioactivity.
      Family members may visit in the room, but must wear a radiation badge to measure exposure. A
      single family member can sleep in the room, but no one is allowed to go behind the shields or
      sleep in the bed with the child.

      Subjects will receive fluids through the central venous catheter. The fluids will begin at
      least four hours before and continue at least 72 hours after the 131I-MIBG treatment begins.

      Subjects will take a medicine by mouth, potassium iodide, to prevent thyroid damage from the
      radioactive iodine contained in the 131I-MIBG. This medication will be taken on the day of
      the treatment and will continue for a total of 6 weeks.

      The 131I-MIBG will be given through an intravenous catheter over 1-2 hours.

      During the administration of the drug, subject's blood pressure and heart rate will be
      checked frequently.

      Before and at regular intervals after treatment, subjects will have routine blood tests to
      check his/her blood counts, hormone, liver and kidney functions. Blood will be checked
      frequently for the first 1-6 weeks, and 6 weeks after the treatment. Approximately 1 teaspoon
      of blood will be drawn each time during the first 6 weeks to perform the tests listed above.

      An MIBG scan will be performed to see where the drug is concentrating in the body following
      treatment. No injection of a radioactive marker will be required and this is usually done on
      the day for discharge. It is identical to the pretherapy MIBG scan except for not needing
      MIBG injection and it is usually shorter (15-30 minutes).

      Six to eight weeks after treatment, an MIBG and other scans will be done to evaluate the
      response of the tumor to the treatment.

      If the subject's tumor is responding or stable 6-7 weeks after each treatment, they may be
      eligible for a second and third course of treatment, as long as their white blood counts have
      recovered from the treatment and the patient has stem cells available if needed. If another
      MIBG treatment is given, it will be at the same dose as the first treatment, unless it is
      thought to be necessary for safety reasons (based on toxicity information from the first
      infusion) to decrease the dose.

      If the subject's blood counts decrease following the therapy, treatment with Filgrastim
      (G-CSF) or Neulasta may be required. G-CSF/neulasta is a medicine that helps increase the
      white blood cells. This is given by a subcutaneous (under the skin) injection (like an
      insulin shot). GCSF is given daily and Neulasta is given every 14 days instead of GCSF.
      Neulasta works like GCSF to help increase the white blood counts but lasts longer in your
      child's body. This medicine will start if the absolute neutrophil count (ANC), a measure of
      the infection fighting cells, goes below 750 and will continue until it rises above 5000.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Available</overall_status>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <condition>Neuroblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Childhood Metastatic Pheochromocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Paraganglioma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>131 I-Metaiodobenzylguanidine (131 I-MIBG)</intervention_name>
    <description>131 I-MIBG 1-18mCi/kg given intravenously on day 1. Subjects may receive multiple courses every 4-8 weeks depending on the dose given.</description>
    <other_name>MIBG</other_name>
    <other_name>131 I-Metaiodobenzylguanidine</other_name>
    <other_name>radioactive Iodine (131)</other_name>
    <other_name>Metaiodobenzylguanidine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>131 I-MIBG</intervention_name>
    <description>131-I-MIBG will be infused intravenously over 60-90 minutes once per course. The dose will be determined by the treating physician.</description>
    <other_name>131 I- Metaidobenzylguanidine</other_name>
    <other_name>MIBG</other_name>
    <other_name>Radioactive iodine</other_name>
    <other_name>Metaiodobenzylguanidine therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Refractory or relapsed neuroblastoma OR malignant Paraganglioma or Pheochromocytoma

          -  Age greater than 1 year and able to cooperate with radiation safety restrictions
             during therapy period.

          -  Performance Level: Patients must have a Karnofsky or Lansky performance status of
             equal to or greater than 50 percent

          -  Disease status: Failure to respond to standard therapy (usually combination
             chemotherapy with or without radiation and surgery) or development of progressive
             disease at any time. Disease evaluable by MIBG scan must be present within 8 weeks of
             study entry and subsequent to any intervening therapy. The principal or
             co-investigator can waive the requirement for intervening therapy if in their judgment
             this would pose undue risk and would not affect ability to judge treatment
             effectiveness.

          -  Stem cells: Patients must have a hematopoietic stem cell product available for
             re-infusion after MIBG treatment at doses of at least 12 mCi/kg. The recommended
             minimum quantity for peripheral blood stem cells is 1.0 x 10^6 CD34+ cells/kg. The
             minimum dose for bone marrow is 1.0 x 10^8 mononuclear cells/kg. If no stem cells are
             available, the dose of 131 I-MIBG should be 12mCi/kg or less.

          -  Prior Therapy: Patients may enter this study with or without re-induction therapy for
             recurrent tumor. Patients must have fully recovered from the toxic effects of any
             prior therapy. Subjects cannot be receiving chemotherapy, cytokine therapy or other
             investigational agents, and must have fully recovered from the toxic effects of any
             prior therapy.

          -  Liver function: Bilirubin ≤2x upper limit of normal; AST/ALT ≤10x upper limit of
             normal

          -  Kidney function: Creatinine ≤3x upper limit of normal

          -  Signed informed consent: The patient and/or the patient's legally authorized guardian
             must provide written informed consent to participate in this expanded access protocol.

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Patients with disease of any major organ system that would compromise their ability to
             withstand therapy, as deemed by the principal investigator or treating
             sub-investigator.

          -  Because of the teratogenic potential of the study medications, no patients who are
             pregnant or lactating will be allowed. Patients of childbearing potential must
             practice an effective method of birth control while participating on this study, to
             avoid possible damage to the fetus.

          -  Patients who are on hemodialysis

          -  Patients with uncontrolled infections

          -  Exceptions to the above eligibility criteria may be allowed if approved by the
             principal investigator as long as exception does not compromise the safety of the
             subject and the exception is clearly documented. Each protocol exception must be
             reviewed by the Institutional Review Board before therapy is initiated.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John M Maris, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John Maris, MD</last_name>
    <email>maris@email.chop.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yael Mosse, MD</last_name>
    <email>mosse@email.chop.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.research.chop.edu/people/john-matthew-maris</url>
    <description>MIBG information site</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 13, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 14, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Refractory Neuroblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Recurrent Neuroblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuroblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV neuroblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic pheochromocytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>paraganglioma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuroblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pheochromocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paraganglioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carotid Body Tumor</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Iodine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>3-Iodobenzylguanidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

