<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01165411</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Registry</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01165411</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Developing and Maintaining a Central Venous Catheter Registry</brief_title>
  <official_title>Developing and Maintaining a Central Venous Catheter Registry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lehigh Valley Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lehigh Valley Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It has been estimated that 90% of bloodstream infections associated with catheters, are due
      to CVCs, and that 500 to 4,000 patients in the United States die annually due to these
      bloodstream infections. The risk of central line associated bloodstream infections is
      typically expressed as the number of line infections per 1000 catheter days. This study's
      goal is to develop a uniform CL protocol, updated practice guidelines based on current
      evidence, and a standard procedural checklist based on CL care bundles recommended by the
      Institute for Healthcare Improvement. A secondary goal is to create a CL registry to capture
      and store data relevant to each CL placed throughout the institution. This registry will
      provide a wealth of data on CL insertions and complications that may be used as a valuable
      source of information for quality assurance, performance improvement, and research. With the
      knowledge and information obtained through this registry, educational offerings can be
      created, and a standardized institutional process for CL insertion can be developed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The use of central venous catheters(CVCs) has increased in both the inpatient and outpatient
      settings.CVCs disturb skin integrity and create vulnerability for bacterial and fungal
      infections. It has been estimated that 90% of bloodstream infections associated with
      catheters, are due to CVCs, and that 500 to 4,000 patients in the United States die annually
      due to these bloodstream infections (Mermel, 2000). The risk of central line (CL)associated
      bloodstream infections (CLAB) is typically expressed as the number of line infections per
      1000 catheter days.A recent study demonstrated that following a set of standardized
      procedures can reduce the mean CLAB rate from 7.7 per 1000 catheter days to 1.4 (Pronovost et
      al., 2006).In an effort to decrease hospital acquired bloodstream infections and
      complications resulting from CVCs, an initiative to standardize and track CL placement
      throughout the institution is proposed. A uniform CL protocol will be developed;practice
      guidelines will be updated based on current evidence, and a standard procedural checklist
      will be developed based on CL care bundles recommended by the Institute for Healthcare
      Improvement (IHI)(5 Million Lives, 2007).Generally,a care bundle is a series of best
      practices that each enhances care when applied individually, but considerably improves care
      when implemented together.The CL care bundle includes hand hygiene, barrier precautions,
      chlorhexidine skin antisepsis, optimal site selection, and daily consideration of line
      necessity, with timely removal of unnecessary lines(5 Million Lives, 2007).Another goal of
      this initiative is to create a CL registry to capture and store data relevant to each CL
      placed throughout the institution.This registry will provide a wealth of data on CL
      insertions and complications which may be used as a valuable source of information for
      quality assurance, performance improvement, and research.Finally,with the knowledge and
      information obtained through this registry, educational offerings can be created, and a
      standardized institutional process for CL insertion can be developed.

      Objective: 1.To capture information on each CL insertion throughout the institution.2.To
      capture and track the amount of days a patient has a CL in place.3.To capture and track CL
      infectious complications.4.To capture and track mechanical complications.5.To capture
      data,which may be used as a valuable source of information for quality assurance, performance
      improvement, education, and research.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Track and store data on central line insertions and complications which may be used as a valuable source of information for quality assurance, performance improvement, and research</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of complication or infection</time_frame>
    <description>All data elements collected are either part of the standard of care during routine insertion of Central Venous Catheters (CVCs) and Peripheral Inserted Central Catheter (PICCs) or are undergoing process improvement so that they become the standard of care for these lines.
The hospital data warehouse will be automatically fed information from multiple existing databases that are maintained within different locations of the hospital. Once merged, data will be transferred into the Horizon Business Insight database for performance improvement, quality assurance, and research purposes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4530</enrollment>
  <condition>Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with CVCs and PICC lines placed</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will have either Standard of Care (control) or Process Improvement infection control changes administered.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients that have CVCs and PICC lines placed at LVH
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients that have CVCs and PICC lines placed at LVH.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The patient has a CVC or PICC that was placed outside of LVHN.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Valerie A Rupp, RN, BSN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lehigh Valley Health Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lehigh Valley Health Network</name>
      <address>
        <city>Allentown</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>18102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mermel LA. Prevention of intravascular catheter-related infections. Ann Intern Med. 2000 Mar 7;132(5):391-402. Erratum in: Ann Intern Med 2000 Sep 5;133(5):395.</citation>
    <PMID>10691590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Institute for Healthcare Improvement (2007). Five Million Lives Campaign.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pronovost P, Needham D, Berenholtz S, Sinopoli D, Chu H, Cosgrove S, Sexton B, Hyzy R, Welsh R, Roth G, Bander J, Kepros J, Goeschel C. An intervention to decrease catheter-related bloodstream infections in the ICU. N Engl J Med. 2006 Dec 28;355(26):2725-32. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2007 Jun 21;356(25):2660.</citation>
    <PMID>17192537</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 19, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Lehigh Valley Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marna Rayl Greenberg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of EM Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Central Catheterization</keyword>
  <keyword>Central Line</keyword>
  <keyword>Database</keyword>
  <keyword>Registry</keyword>
  <keyword>Registries</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

