<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02718872</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FRUITFUL GB-13520139</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02718872</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tobacco Cessation Training Program in Spanish-speaking Countries</brief_title>
  <acronym>FRUITFUL</acronym>
  <official_title>Development and Dissemination of a Tobacco Cessation Training Program for Healthcare Professionals in Spanish-speaking Countries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut Català d'Oncologia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto Oncológico del Oriente Boliviano</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto de Cancerología y Hospital Dr. Bernardo del Valle</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto de Enfermedades Respiratoiras INERAM Prof. Dr. Juan Max Boettner</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut Català d'Oncologia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project is responsive to the identified gap of lack of tobacco cessation training
      programs in Latin American &amp; Caribbean countries. Currently, smoking rates in the Latin
      American and Caribbean region are high, and previous surveys show that health professionals
      do not have enough skills to help smokers to quit. In consequence, in absence of trained
      health professionals, many smokers who visit health care services are under-treated. The
      Fruitful Project aims to adapt an original on-line course developed in Spain to the reality
      of the three Latin American countries (Bolivia, Guatemala and Paraguay) and disseminate
      evidence-based tobacco cessation interventions among health care professionals.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tobacco cessation training programs to treat tobacco dependence have measureable effects on
      patients' smoking. Tobacco consumption in low and middle income countries is increasing, but
      these countries usually lack measures to face the epidemic, including tobacco cessation
      training programs addressed to their health professionals and organizations.

      Based on a previous online training program for hospital workers in Spain, the Fruitful Study
      aims are twofold:

        1. to adapt the course to the reality of 3 Spanish-speaking low and middle income countries
           (Bolivia, Guatemala, and Paraguay) and;

        2. to evaluate the effectiveness of the program among the participant hospitals and
           workers.

      Investigators use a mixed methods design with a pre-post evaluation (quantitative approach)
      and in-depth interviews and focus groups (qualitative approach). The main outcomes will be:

        1. participants' attitudes, knowledge and behaviors before and after the training and

        2. the level of implementation of tobacco control policies within the hospitals before and
           after the training.

      The theoretical framework for this project includes Card's adapting model and Roger's
      diffusion of innovations model.

      This study will show whether it is possible to adapt an online course to the reality of
      developing countries. In addition, investigator will measure whether an online program will
      produce changes in tobacco control policies at the organizational level and increase the
      level of knowledge, attitudes and perception in tobacco cessation at participants' level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge, attitudes, and behaviors of trainees</measure>
    <time_frame>six month</time_frame>
    <description>Trainers' attitudes, knowledge and behaviors will be assessed by using a questionnaire composed of 63-items. The web-site delivered questionnaire is e-mailed to the participants at baseline and 6 months after finishing the training. The questionnaire takes 30-40 minutes to complete. It has been designed according to Sheffer work. The questionnaire gathers information about the provider gender, tobacco use history, previous tobacco cessation education, level of proactivity addressing tobacco use, and perceived success in helping patients stop using tobacco.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance with tobacco control policies in hospitals</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Score in the self-audit questionnaire,</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking</condition>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tobacco cessation online training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Six hour smoking cessation online training addressed to health professionals from hospitals in 3 Latin American Countries. Participants are monitored by local coordinators that act as champions. They offer their assistance to log into the online platform, fill out the questionnaires, complete the evaluation, including other technical support. Participants' progress is monitored in real time onto the web platform. The project coordinator at ICO sends a report of the participants progress every other week to coordinators, and if necessary personal emails to motivate students to finish the course and complete the evaluations.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tobacco cessation online training</intervention_name>
    <description>The original course has been developed in the online platform e-oncologia (http://www.e-oncologia.org/en/) based on the in-person courses offered during the last 10 years by the Tobacco Control Unit of the Catalan Institute of Oncology. The theoretical framework underpinning the training program is the Stages of Change Model and the curriculum was developed with the content of numerous meta-analysis and clinical practice guidelines. We created a fully referenced curriculum online, with feedback from an expert advisory group that oriented in the instructional design to ensure the course content was palatable for an online format and aligned with the learning objectives. The final curriculum content of the &quot;Brief Intervention for Smoking Cessation Training Program&quot; is composed of 4 modules.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tobacco cessation online training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Health professionals of the participating centers

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No exclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Crisitna Martínez, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institut Català d'Oncologia - Institut d'Investigació Biomèdica de Bellvitge - Universitat de Barcelona ICO-IDIBELL-UB</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 24, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 21, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 21, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 22, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Institut Català d'Oncologia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cristina Martínez Martínez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>NO plans for data sharing</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

