<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02715856</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-0966</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-00051255-Y1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2016-00544</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02715856</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Telemonitoring to Optimize the Mobility of Cancer Survivors With Skeletal Metastases After Surgery to Preserve Limb Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>Using Telemonitoring to Optimize the Mobility of Cancer Survivors With Skeletal Metastases After Surgery to Preserve Limb Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to learn about performing follow-up care using mobile devices
      (smartphones or tablet computers) after surgery.

      This is an investigational study.

      Up to 60 participants will be enrolled in this study. Up to 12 clinicians will also take part
      in this study. All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Groups:

      If you agree to take part in this study, you will be randomly assigned (as in the flip of a
      coin) to 1 of 2 groups. You will have an equal (50/50) chance of being assigned to either
      group.

      Both Group 1 and Group 2 will have standard, face-to-face follow-up visits. Group 1 will be
      the control group and will have no mobile device intervention. However, if you are assigned
      to Group 2, you will also be asked to record videos between follow-up visits and send them to
      the study staff. The study staff will provide the mobile device for recording the videos.

      Visits for Group 1 (Control Group):

      About 2, 6, 12, and 24 weeks after surgery, you will have standard follow-up visits. You will
      not have any visits or procedures that are specific to this study. However, you will complete
      questionnaires that are specific to this study.

      You will be asked to sit in a chair, stand, walk about 10 feet, turn around, return to the
      chair, and sit down. During another test, you will be asked to walk a certain distance (about
      30 feet) while a physical therapist watches your steps. You will be asked to walk around the
      room in certain ways, and step over lines on the floor. You will also fill out a survey about
      your physical and emotional health as well as your pain. At the end of the study, you will be
      asked to fill out another questionnaire regarding the study. Both the physical tests and the
      surveys should take about 15 minutes to complete. In addition, at the end of the study, you
      will be asked to fill out a questionnaire about the study.

      Visits for Group 2:

      At a scheduled clinic visit before your surgery, you will be taught how to take photos of
      your surgical wounds and make videos using a mobile device.

      About 2, 6,12, and 24 weeks after surgery, you will have standard follow-up visits which will
      include the same surveys and physical therapy measures described above. However, at Weeks 3,
      7, 13, and 25 you will use a mobile device to send the study staff photos of your surgical
      wound and video of you walking. These updates will help your doctor to check your recovery.
      The photos you will take will only be of a small area of skin near your wound.

      For the videos, you will need a family member or friend to hold the mobile device camera and
      record video of you as you walk 10 feet away from the camera and then walk back toward the
      camera. You will also repeat this with the camera viewing from the side as you walk 10 feet
      back and forth.

      At the end of each follow-up visit, you will complete an electronic questionnaire about your
      quality of life. This should take about 10 minutes.

      In addition, your doctor will have a video conference at Weeks 3, 7, 13, and 25. At any time
      the doctor thinks it is needed, you will also have a video conference with your doctor. You
      will be asked basic follow-up information about your wound and overall health questions. This
      should take about 5-10 minutes.

      You will return the mobile device after completion of your 25-week follow up visit using the
      mobile device.

      Length of Study:

      If you are in Group 1, your participation in this study will be over after the 24-week
      follow-up has been completed. If you are in Group 2, your participation will be over after
      the 25-week follow-up has been completed.

      Your study participation may end early if you are unable to follow study directions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Inter-Rater Agreement on the Physician Assessed Score</measure>
    <time_frame>7 months</time_frame>
    <description>Inter-rater agreement on the physician assessed score defined as less than 10% difference between the Musculoskeletal Tumor Society (MSTS) scores evaluated using video vs. face-to-face follow ups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Completion of Follow-Up Assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>7 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participant considered having completed the follow-up assessments if the three outcomes are documented for the 2-, 6-, 12, and 24-week evaluations. Follow-up assessment information taken from Musculoskeletal Tumor Society Scores (MSTS), Timed &quot;Up and Go&quot; test (TUG), and Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Bone Metastases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 - Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>About 2, 6, 12, and 24 weeks after surgery, participant has standard follow-up visits. At these visits, participant asked to perform different physical tasks. Physical therapist will observe one of the walking tests.
After each visit, participant completes a survey about their physical and emotional health as well as their pain. At the end of the study, participant completes a survey regarding the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 - Mobile Devices</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>At a clinic visit before surgery, participant taught how to take photos of their surgical wounds and make videos using a mobile device.
About 2, 6, 12, and 24 weeks after surgery, participant has standard follow-up visits. At these visits, participant asked to perform different physical tasks. Physical therapist will observe one of the walking tests. After each visit, participant completes a survey about their physical and emotional health as well as their pain.
At weeks 3, 7, 13, and 25 participant uses a mobile device to send the study staff photos of their surgical wound and videos of their walking tests.
At the end of each follow-up visit, participant completes an electronic questionnaire about their quality of life. At the end of the study, participant completes a survey regarding the study and use of the mobile device.
A video conference held with physician at Weeks 3, 7, 13, and 25.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Tasks</intervention_name>
    <description>About 2, 6, 12, and 24 weeks after surgery, participant has standard follow-up visits. At these visits, participant asked to perform different physical tasks. Physical therapist will observe one of the walking tests.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 - Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 - Mobile Devices</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Follow Up with Mobile Device</intervention_name>
    <description>At weeks 3, 7, 13, and 25 participant uses a mobile device to send the study staff photos of their surgical wound and videos of their walking tests.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 - Mobile Devices</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Smartphone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surveys</intervention_name>
    <description>After each visit, participant completes a survey about their physical and emotional health as well as their pain. At the end of the study, participant completes a survey regarding the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 - Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Questionnaires</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electronic Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>At the end of each follow-up visit, participant completes an electronic questionnaire about their quality of life. At the end of the study, participant completes a survey regarding the study and use of the mobile device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 - Mobile Devices</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surveys</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mobile Device Training</intervention_name>
    <description>At a clinic visit before surgery, participant taught how to take photos of their surgical wounds and make videos using a mobile device.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 - Mobile Devices</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Smartphone</other_name>
    <other_name>Tablet</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. have been scheduled for an Intramedullary nailing (IM) surgery with the department of
             Orthopaedic Oncology at University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center.

          2. Are able to read and write English

          3. Are 18 years or older

          4. Are willing and able to use a smartphone or tablet comfortably

          5. Have access to mobile hot spot, wireless internet, and/or cellular service

          6. Must have a caregiver or assistance at home who can assist with collecting physical
             therapy (PT) measures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1) Patients who have difficulty walking or may not be able to complete the Physical therapy
        measures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert L. Satcher, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robert L. Satcher, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>713-745-4117</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bone metastases</keyword>
  <keyword>Intramedullary nailing surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>IM</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical tasks</keyword>
  <keyword>Surveys</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>Smartphone</keyword>
  <keyword>Tablet</keyword>
  <keyword>Telemedicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Telemonitoring</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

