<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02713490</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>402-C-331</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02713490</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Local Infiltration Analgesia With and Without EXPAREL Following Total Knee Arthroplasty</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Randomized, Double-Blind, Controlled Trial Comparing Local Infiltration Analgesia With EXPAREL to Local Infiltration Analgesia Without EXPAREL to Manage Postsurgical Pain Following Total Knee Arthroplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pacira Pharmaceuticals, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pacira Pharmaceuticals, Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 4, multicenter, randomized, double-blind, controlled trial in approximately
      300 adult subjects undergoing primary unilateral TKA under spinal anesthesia with bupivacaine
      HCl (10-15 mg).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      On Day 0, eligible subjects will be randomized 1:1 to two treatment groups. Subjects in Group
      1 will receive local infiltration analgesia (LIA) with EXPAREL 266 mg in 20 mL admixed with
      bupivacaine hydrochloride (HCl) 0.5% in 20 mL and expanded in volume with 80 mL normal saline
      (total volume of 120 mL). Subjects in Group 2 will receive LIA with bupivacaine HCl 0.5% in
      20 mL expanded in volume with 100 mL normal saline (total volume of 120 mL). Investigators
      will use their usual surgical technique to perform the TKA.

      Study drug will be administered using six 20 cc syringes with 22-gauge needles prior to wound
      closure. Each stick should deliver approximately 1-1.5 cc to the intended area. The tissue
      should visibly expand with minimal leakage. Study drug should be injected in the prescribed
      locations based on the areas of highest nerve density.

      Infiltration Technique

      Prior to cementation

      Syringe #1: Posterior capsule (8-10 sticks medial and 8-10 sticks lateral).

      Syringe #2: Femur medial and lateral periosteum, posterior periosteum,
      suprapatellar/quadriceps tendon (20 sticks).

      Syringe #3: Tibia fat pad (5 sticks); pes anserinus, medial collateral ligament, and gutter
      (15 sticks).

      Syringe #4: Circumferential periosteum (15-20 sticks).

      After cementation

      Syringe #5: Midline quadriceps tendon (10 sticks); retinaculum, medial gutter, femoral to
      tibia (10 sticks).

      Syringe #6: Lateral gutter, femoral to tibial (10 sticks); subcutaneous/closure (10 sticks).

      In addition to LIA, all study participants will receive a standardized approach for managing
      postsurgical pain that includes a scheduled multimodal pain regimen including adjunctive
      analgesics, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), and rescue analgesics as needed.

      Postsurgical clinical assessments will include pain intensity scores using a 10-cm visual
      analog scale (VAS); overall benefit of analgesia score (OBAS) questionnaire; total
      postsurgical opioid consumption; physical therapy assessment; nurse's satisfaction with
      overall analgesia; and discharge readiness. Adverse events (AEs) will be recorded from the
      time the informed consent form is signed through postsurgical Day 29.

      Postsurgical health economic outcome assessments will include hospital length of stay (LOS),
      use of skilled nursing facility, outpatient physical therapy use, hospital readmissions, and
      use of other health services following discharge (phone calls related to postsurgical pain,
      unscheduled visits related to postsurgical pain, and visits to emergency department) through
      postsurgical Day 29.

      A follow-up visit will be scheduled for all subjects on postsurgical Day 14. A follow-up
      phone call will be made on postsurgical Day 29 to all subjects who received study drug to
      assess for AEs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the curve (AUC) of the VAS pain intensity scores</measure>
    <time_frame>From 12-48 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total opioid consumption (in IV morphine equivalents)</measure>
    <time_frame>From 0-48 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The AUC of the VAS pain intensity score through 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The AUC of the VAS pain intensity score through 36 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 36 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The AUC of the VAS pain intensity score through 48 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 48 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The AUC of the VAS pain intensity score through 60 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 60 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The AUC of the VAS pain intensity score through 72 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 72 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events or serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Through postsurgical Day 29</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EXPAREL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of EXPAREL 266 mg in 20 mL admixed with bupivacaine HCl 0.5% in 20 mL and expanded in volume with 80 mL normal saline (total volume of 120 mL).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bupivacaine HCl 0.5% in 20 mL expanded in volume with 100 mL normal saline (total volume of 120 mL).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EXPAREL</intervention_name>
    <description>EXPAREL and bupivacaine HCl</description>
    <arm_group_label>EXPAREL</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>bupivacaine liposome injectable suspension</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupivacaine</intervention_name>
    <description>Single dose of bupivacaine HCl 0.5%</description>
    <arm_group_label>EXPAREL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bupivacaine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>bupivacaine HCl</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female, at least 18 years of age at screening.

          2. Scheduled to undergo primary, unilateral, tricompartmental TKA under spinal
             anesthesia.

          3. Primary indication for TKA is degenerative osteoarthritis of the knee.

          4. American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status 1, 2, or 3.

          5. Female subjects must be surgically sterile; or at least 2 years postmenopausal; or
             have a monogamous partner who is surgically sterile; or practicing double-barrier
             contraception; or practicing abstinence (must agree to use double-barrier
             contraception in the event of sexual activity); or using an insertable, injectable,
             transdermal, or combination oral contraceptive approved by the FDA for greater than 2
             months prior to screening and commit to the use of an acceptable form of birth control
             for the duration of the study and for 30 days after completion of the study.

          6. Able to provide informed consent, adhere to the study visit schedule, and complete all
             study assessments.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Currently pregnant, nursing, or planning to become pregnant during the study or within
             1 month after study drug administration.

          2. History of previous prior contralateral TKA or open knee surgery on the knee being
             considered for TKA. Prior arthroscopy is permitted.

          3. Planned concurrent surgical procedure (e.g., bilateral TKA).

          4. Undergoing unicompartmental TKA or revision TKA.

          5. Concurrent painful physical condition that may require analgesic treatment (such as an
             NSAID or opioid) in the postsurgical period for pain that is not strictly related to
             the knee surgery and which may confound the postsurgical assessments (e.g.,
             significant pain from other joints including the non-index knee joint, chronic
             neuropathic pain, concurrent or prior contralateral TKA, concurrent foot surgery).

          6. Comorbidity impacting current physical function of Investigator opinion that it may
             impact postsurgical rehabilitation.

          7. Allergy, hypersensitivity, or contraindication to any of the study medications (i.e.,
             bupivacaine, pregabalin, acetaminophen/paracetamol, celecoxib, oxycodone, morphine,
             hydromorphone, or tranexamic acid).

          8. Use of any of the following medications within the times specified before surgery:
             long-acting opioid medication or NSAIDs (except for low-dose aspirin used for
             cardioprotection) within 3 days, or any opioid medication within 24 hours.

          9. Initiation of treatment with any of the following medications within 1 month of study
             drug administration or if the medication(s) are being given to control pain: selective
             serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs), selective norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors
             (SNRIs), gabapentin, pregabalin (Lyrica®), or duloxetine (Cymbalta®). If a subject is
             taking one of these medications for a reason other than pain control, he or she must
             be on a stable dose for at least 1 month prior to study drug administration.

         10. Current use of systemic glucocorticosteroids within 1 month of enrollment in this
             study.

         11. Use of dexmedetomidine HCl (Precedex®) within 3 days of study drug administration.

         12. History of coronary or vascular stent placed within the past 3 months (may be extended
             to 1 year if medically indicated per physician discretion).

         13. Have been treated for a deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, myocardial
             infarction, or ischemic stroke within the past 6 months (may be extended to 1 year if
             medically indicated per physician discretion).

         14. Rheumatoid or inflammatory arthritis or disease.

         15. Severely impaired renal or hepatic function (e.g., serum creatinine level &gt;2 mg/dL
             [176.8 µmol/L], blood urea nitrogen level &gt;50 mg/dL [17.9 mmol/L], serum aspartate
             aminotransferase [AST] level &gt;3 times the upper limit of normal [ULN], or serum
             alanine aminotransferase [ALT] level &gt;3 times the ULN.)

         16. Any neurologic or psychiatric disorder that might impact postsurgical pain or
             interfere with study assessments.

         17. Malignancy in the last 2 years, per physician discretion.

         18. History of misuse, abuse, or dependence on opioid analgesics, other prescription
             drugs, illicit drugs, or alcohol.

         19. Failure to pass the alcohol breath test or urine drug screen.

         20. Body weight &lt;50 kg (110 pounds) or a body mass index &gt;40 kg/m2.

         21. Previous participation in an EXPAREL study.

         22. Administration of an investigational drug within 30 days or 5 elimination half-lives
             of such investigational drug, whichever is longer, prior to study drug administration,
             or planned administration of another investigational product or procedure during the
             subject's participation in this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James B Jones, MD, PharmD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pacira Pharmaceuticals, Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute for Joint Restoration</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fremont</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94538</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Loma Linda University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loma Linda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92354</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Holy Cross Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Lauderdale</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33334</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Weston</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33331</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pinnacle Orthopaedics &amp; Sports</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marietta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30060</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central DuPage Hospital, Northwestern Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winfield</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60190</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sinai Hospital of Baltimore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orthopaedic Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Towson</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21204</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Hospital for Joint Disease</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lenox Hill Hospital/Northwell Health Orthopaedic Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10075</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC Orthopaedics Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OrthoCarolina, PA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28207</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wellington Orthopaedics and Sports Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Antonio Military Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Sam Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78234</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor Medical Center, Plano Orthopedics Sports Medical &amp; Spine Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frisco</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75034</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Utah University Orthopedic Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 15, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

