<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02710383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BCF 04-2016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02710383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Biomarker for Patients With a Cystic Fibrosis Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>BioCyFi</acronym>
  <official_title>Biomarker for Patients With a Cystic Fibrosis Disease - AN INTERNATIONAL, MULTICENTER, EPIDEMIOLOGICAL PROTOCOL</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Rostock</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centogene AG Rostock</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Rostock</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Development of a new MS-based biomarker for the early and sensitive diagnosis of a cystic
      fibrosis disease from plasma
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cystic fibrosis is an inherited disease characterized by the buildup of thick, sticky mucus
      that can damage many of the body's organs. The disorder's most common signs and symptoms
      include progressive damage to the respiratory system and chronic digestive system problems.
      The feature of the disorder and their severity varies among affected individuals. Mucus is a
      slippery substance that lubricates and protects the linings of the airways, di-gestive
      system, reproductive system, and other organs and tissues. In people with cystic fibrosis,
      the body produces mucus that is abnormally thick and sticky. This abnormal mucus can clog the
      airways, leading to severe problems with breathing and bacterial in-fections in the lungs.
      These infections cause chronic coughing, wheezing, and inflamma-tion. Over time, mucus
      buildup and infections result in permanent lung damage, including the formation of scar
      tissue (fibrosis) and cysts in the lungs. Most people with cystic fibrosis also have
      digestive problems. Some affected babies have meconium ileus, a blockage of the intestine
      that occurs shortly after birth. Other di-gestive problems result from a buildup of thick,
      sticky mucus in the pancreas. The pan-creas is an organ that produces insulin (a hormone that
      helps control blood sugar levels). It also makes enzymes that help digest food. In people
      with cystic fibrosis, mucus blocks the ducts of the pancreas, reducing the production of
      insulin and preventing digestive enzymes from reaching the intestines to aid digestion.
      Problems with digestion can lead to diarrhea, malnutrition, poor growth, and weight loss. In
      adolescence or adulthood, a shortage of insulin can cause a form of diabetes known as cystic
      fibrosis-related diabetes mellitus (CFRDM).

      Cystic fibrosis used to be considered a fatal disease of childhood. With improved treat-ments
      and better ways to manage the disease, many people with cystic fibrosis now live well into
      adulthood. Adults with cystic fibrosis experience health problems affecting the respiratory,
      digestive, and reproductive systems. Most men with cystic fibrosis have con-genital bilateral
      absence of the vas deferens (CBAVD), a condition in which the tubes that carry sperm (the vas
      deferens) are blocked by mucus and do not develop properly. Men with CBAVD are unable to
      father children (infertile) unless they undergo fertility treatment. Women with cystic
      fibrosis may experience complications in pregnancy.

      What genes are related to cystic fibrosis? Mutations in the CFTR gene cause cystic fibrosis.
      The CFTR gene provides instructions for making a channel that transports negatively charged
      particles called chloride ions into and out of cells. Chloride is a component of sodium
      chloride, a common salt found in sweat. Chloride also has important functions in cells; for
      example, the flow of chloride ions helps control the movement of water in tissues, which is
      necessary for the produc-tion of thin, freely flowing mucus.

      Mutations in the CFTR gene disrupt the function of the chloride channels, preventing them
      from regulating the flow of chloride ions and water across cell membranes. As a result, cells
      that line the passageways of the lungs, pancreas, and other organs produce mucus that is
      unusually thick and sticky. This mucus clogs the airways and various ducts, causing the
      characteristic signs and symptoms of cystic fibrosis.

      Other genetic and environmental factors likely influence the severity of the condition. For
      example, mutations in genes other than CFTR might help explain why some people with cystic
      fibrosis are more severely affected than others. Most of these genetic changes have not been
      identified, however.

      New methods, like mass-spectrometry give a good chance to characterize specific metabolic
      alterations in the blood (plasma) of affected patients that allow diagnosing in the future
      the disease earlier, with a higher sensitivity and specificity.

      Therefore it is the goal of the study to identify and validate a new biochemical marker from
      the plasma of the affected patients helping to benefit other patients by an early diagnose
      and thereby with an earlier treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of a new MS-based biomarker for the early diagnosis of a cystic fibrosis disease from plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of correctly identified patients with a cystic fibrosis disease</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <condition>Mucoviscidosis</condition>
  <condition>Hereditary Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients at 2 months with a cystic fibrosis disease or high-grade suspicion for a cystic fibrosis disease</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      For the development of the new biomarkers using the technique of Mass-spectrometry 7, 5 ml
      EDTA blood and a dry blood spot filter card are taken. To proof the correct diagnosis of a
      cystic fibrosis in those patients where up to the enrollment in the study no genetic testing
      has been done, sequencing of a cystic fibrosis disease will be done.

      The analyses are done in the Centogene AG Schillingallee 68 D-18057 Rostock Germany
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients of both gender with a Cystic Fibrosis or high-grade suspicion for a Cystic
        Fibrosis
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed consent will be obtained from the patient or the parents before any study
             related procedures.

          -  Patients of both genders older than 2 months

          -  The patient has a diagnosis of a Cystic Fibrosis or a high-grade suspicion for a
             Cystic Fibrosis

          -  High-grade suspicion present, if one or more inclusion criteria are valid:

               -  Positive family anamnesis for a Cystic Fibrosis

               -  A persistent cough that produces thick (sputum) mucus

               -  Breathlessness

               -  Repeated lung infections

               -  Inflamed nasal passages or a stuffy nose

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No Informed consent from the patient or the parents before any study related
             procedures

          -  Patients of both gender younger than 2 months

          -  No diagnosis of a Cystic Fibrosis or no valid criteria for profound suspicion of a
             Cystic Fibrosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arndt Rolfs, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Albrecht Kossel Institute Rostock</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Arndt Rolfs, MD</last_name>
    <phone>49 381 494</phone>
    <phone_ext>9540</phone_ext>
    <email>arndt.rolfs@med.uni-rostock.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Susanne Zielke</last_name>
    <phone>49 381 494</phone>
    <phone_ext>4739</phone_ext>
    <email>susanne.zielke@med.uni-rostock.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albrecht-Kossel-Institute for Neuroregeneration (AKos) Centre for Mental Health Disease University of Rostock</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rostock</city>
        <zip>18147</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arndt Rolfs, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 381 494</phone>
      <phone_ext>9540</phone_ext>
      <email>arndt.rolfs@med.uni-rostock.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Susanne Zielke</last_name>
      <phone>+49 381 494</phone>
      <phone_ext>4739</phone_ext>
      <email>susanne.zielke@med.uni-rostock.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://centogene.com</url>
    <description>Centogene is one of the leading laboratories focusing on genetic testing for rare hereditary disorders. We now offer more than 2200 routine genetic and biochemical tests.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 16, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Rostock</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Dr. Arndt Rolfs</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Genetic Diseases, Inborn</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

