<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02715687</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AF Treatment</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02715687</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Postoperative Atrial Fibrillation - Comparison of Amiodarone and Placebo.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment of Postoperative Atrial Fibrillation - Comparison of Amiodarone and Placebo.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rambam Health Care Campus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rambam Health Care Campus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Post-operative atrial fibrillation (POAF) is the most common complication encountered after
      cardiac surgery; reports show POAF to occur in ~ 35% of patients after CABG. Prophylactic use
      amiodarone was found to be effective, however, due to serious extracardiac adverse effects
      therapy is probably appropriate just for patients at high risk for POAF.

      the common practice for management of POAF is treatment with intravenous Amiodarone until
      return to sinus rhythm, following which the drug is given orally. Our protocol involves
      continued treatment with amiodarone for 30 day post-discharge from the hospital in a dose of
      200mg per day.

      This protocol is a common practice in many cardiac surgical departments worldwide,
      nevertheless, it is not evidence-based protocol and it was never examined as such.

      This study is a randomized placebo controlled trial, to evaluate the requirement for
      post-discharge treatment with oral Amiodarone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most widespread complication encountered after cardiac
      surgery, associated with prolonged hospitalization, morbidity, mortality, and an annual cost
      of more than $1 billion to the American healthcare system.

      AF has been reported to predict postoperative stroke, congestive heart failure, and late AF
      among patients undergoing mitral valve surgery. Postoperative AF (POAF) occurs in 62% of
      patients undergoing combined aortic valve and coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery, in
      49% of patients undergoing aortic valve surgery alone, in 42% of patients undergoing mitral
      valve surgery, and in 32% of patients undergoing CABG surgery alone. These figures are
      expected to rise in the future, given that the patients undergoing cardiac surgery are
      getting elder and that the incidence of AF in the general population is markedly
      age-dependent.

      POAF peak incidence occurs on the 2nd and 3rd postoperative days (PODs). Seventy percent of
      patients develop this arrhythmia before the end of the 4th POD and 94% before the end of the
      6th. Although generally well-tolerated and seen as a temporary problem related to surgery,
      POAF can be life-threatening, particularly in elderly patients and those with left
      ventricular dysfunction.

      Recent guidelines for the prevention and management of POAF were jointly published in 2006 by
      the American College of Cardiology, the American Heart Association (AHA), and the European
      Society of Cardiology. These guidelines recommended (i) preoperative treatment with an oral
      beta-blocker drug for prevention of POAF as a class IA indication, and (ii) preoperative
      administration of amiodarone for patients at a high risk for POAF as a class IIA indication.

      Amiodarone is associated with several complications, both cardiac, and extracardiac; among
      the cardiac complications, it is predominantly related to increased risk of bradycardia and
      hypotension, particularly when (i) administered intravenously, (ii) using average daily doses
      exceeding 1 g, and (iii) initiating prophylaxis during the postoperative period.45 Among the
      most severe extracardiac complications, amiodarone is associated with thyroid toxicity, lung
      fibrosis, and corneal damage, which may be aggravated by the drug's delayed onset of action
      (2 - 3 days) and long elimination half-life time (up to 6 months).

      Currently the common practice for management of POAF is treatment with intravenous Amiodarone
      until return to sinus rhythm, following which the drug is given orally. Our protocol involves
      continued treatment with amiodarone for 30 day post-discharge from the hospital in a dose of
      200mg per day.

      This protocol is a common practice in many cardiac surgical departments worldwide,
      nevertheless, it is not evidence-based protocol and it was never examined as such.

      This study is a randomized placebo controlled trial, to evaluate the requirement for
      post-discharge treatment with oral Amiodarone.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative atrial fibrillation</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Post-discharge monitoring with a continous loop-recorder type of ECG monitoring device named &quot;CardioR&quot; will be provided for all participants. The device will continuously record and transmit ECG monitoring to a dedicated monitoring company. All arrhythmias will be recorded and reported.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-discharge return to admission</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Any return to admission will be recorded and reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Will receive 30 days treatment with oral placebo of 200mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Will receive 30 days treatment with oral Amiodarone of 200mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amiodarone</intervention_name>
    <description>Will receive 30 days treatment with oral amniodarone of 200mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>amiodacore</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Will receive 30 days treatment with oral placebo of 200mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All post-cardiac surgery patients who developed a hemodynamically stable postoperative
             atrial fibrillation and returned to sinus rhythm with intravenous amiodarone
             tretament.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Post-cardiac surgery patients who developed a non- hemodynamically stable
             postoperative atrial fibrillation.

          -  Patients with chronic and/or paroxysmal atrial fibrillation and/or known other cardiac
             arrhythmia or conduction disturbance.

          -  Patients with pacemakers.

          -  Patients with lactose intolerance
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 16, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 22, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rambam Health Care Campus</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ziv Beckerman MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amiodarone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

