<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02716987</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TAK-831-1003</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-004509-17</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1176-7493</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>15/LO/1916</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02716987</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Determine D-Amino Acid Oxidase Brain Enzyme Occupancy of TAK-831 After Single-Dose Oral Administration</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-Label, Positron Emission Tomography Study in Healthy Subjects to Determine D-Amino Acid Oxidase Brain Enzyme Occupancy of TAK-831 After Single-Dose Oral Administration</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the relationship between TAK-831 plasma exposure
      and the extent and duration of brain D-amino acid oxidase (DAO) enzyme occupancy following
      single oral dosing of TAK-831 in healthy participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is called TAK-831. TAK-831 is a highly selective and
      potent inhibitor of d-amino oxidase (DAO), a peroxisomal enzyme active towards neutral
      D-amino acids which potentially effects cerebellar dysfunction. This study will look at the
      relationship between TAK-831 plasma exposure and the extent and duration of brain DAO enzyme
      occupancy after single oral dosing of TAK-831 in healthy male participants using [18F]PGM299
      radioactive tracer injection and PET imaging.

      The study will enroll up to 22 participants in two different sets. Up to 16 participants will
      be enrolled in Set A. Within that total, up to 5 dose levels of TAK-831 may be evaluated,
      with up to 6 participants per dose level, although typically, there will be 2 to 3
      participants per dose level. All participants in Set A will also receive up to 3 doses of
      [18F]PGM299. Up to 6 participants will be enrolled in Set B. All participants in Set B will
      be assigned to single treatment group to receive 2 doses of [18F]PGM299.

      All participants in Set A will be asked to take single oral dose of TAK-831 suspension on Day
      1. In Set A, each of the participant will receive a maximum of 3 PET scans with [18F]PGM299;
      1 at baseline 2 following a single oral dose of TAK-831 on Day 1 and 5. In Set B, each of the
      participant will receive 2 PET scans with [18F]PGM299 on Day 1 and 5. Set B will be conducted
      after the confirmation of blockade of [18F]PGM299 binding by TAK-831 in 2 to 4 participants
      of Set A.

      This multi-center trial will be conducted in the United Kingdom. The overall time to
      participate in this study is 62 days. Participants in Set A will make 4 visits to the clinic,
      and participants in Set B will make 3 visits to the clinic and all will be contacted by
      telephone on Day 15 (Set A) and Day 12 (Set B) of treatment period for a follow-up
      assessment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For each PET scan, Total Volume of Distribution (Vt) of [18F]PGM299 in Regions of Interest (ROI) including, but not limited to the cerebellum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Days 1 and 2: for Set A; Days 1 and 10 (+/- 5) for Set B</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For each PET scan, Regional Non-displaceable Binding Potential (BPnd) of [18F]PGM299 in the ROI including, but not limited to the cerebellum</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Days 1 and 2: for Set A; Days 1 and 10 (+/- 5): for Set B</time_frame>
    <description>BPnd will be estimated for each scan from the regional Vt data and/or directly from the positron emission tomography (PET) emission using a reference tissue model</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>DAO Occupancy Estimation: Percent Difference From Baseline for each post-TAK-831 PET scan</measure>
    <time_frame>Estimated on Days 1 and 2 for Set A and compared to Baseline</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Concentration of TAK-831 Corresponding to D-Amino Acid Oxidase (DAO) Brain Enzyme Occupancy of 50%</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 2 for Set A</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose of TAK-831 Corresponding to DAO Brain Enzyme Occupancy of 50%</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 2 for Set A</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coefficient of Variation of [18F]PGM299 Binding in Brain</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 10 (+/- 5) for Set B</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Concentrations of TAK-831 during each postdose PET imaging period</measure>
    <time_frame>At t=0 (just before tracer injection), 60 minutes after tracer injection, and 120 minutes after tracer injection post-TAK-831 dose on Days 1 and 2 for Set A</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Change From Baseline to Day 2 in AUEC(0-30)serine: Area Under the Effect-Time Curve From Time 0 to 30 Hours Postdose for Dextro-Serine (D-serine), Levo-serine (L-serine) and D-Serine/ L-Serine</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 2: (up to 30 hours) post-TAK-831 dose for Set A</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Change in Maximum Drug-Induced Effect (Emax,serine). From Baseline in Plasma Concentrations of Dextro-Serine (D-serine), Levo-serine (L-serine) and D-Serine/ L-Serine</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 2: at multiple time-points (up to 30 hours) post-TAK-831 dose for Set A</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Reach the Maximum Pharmacodynamic (PD) Effect (time to Emax,serine) for Dextro-Serine (D-serine), Levo-serine (L-serine) and D-Serine/ L-Serine Obtained Directly From the Effect-Time Curve of Serine</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 2: at multiple time-points (up to 30 hours) post-TAK-831 dose for Set A</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Set A: TAK-831 + [18F]PGM299</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TAK-831 500 mg, suspension, orally, once only on Day 1. Subsequent dose levels may be lower or higher (up to the highest safe dose level administered in the TAK-831-1001 study). [18F]PGM299 up to 12.5 mcg maximal mass per intravenous injection, not to exceed 300 MBq total for up to 3 PET scans (Baseline, Day 1, Day 2).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Set B: [18F]PGM299</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>[18F]PGM299 up to 12.5 mcg maximal mass per intravenous injection, not to exceed 300 MBq total for 2 PET scans (Day 1 and 10 [+/- 5]).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TAK-831</intervention_name>
    <description>TAK-831 Suspension</description>
    <arm_group_label>Set A: TAK-831 + [18F]PGM299</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[18F]PGM299</intervention_name>
    <description>[18F]PGM299 Injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Set A: TAK-831 + [18F]PGM299</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Set B: [18F]PGM299</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Is capable of understanding and complying with protocol requirements.

          2. Signs and dates a written, informed consent form and any required privacy
             authorization prior to the initiation of any study procedures.

          3. Is in good health as determined by physical examination, electrocardiogram (ECG), and
             laboratory evaluations.

          4. Is a healthy male aged 25 to 55 years, inclusive, at the time of informed consent and
             first injection of the PET tracer.

          5. Weighs at least 45 kilogram (kg) and has a body mass index (BMI) from 18.0 to 30.0
             kilogram per square meters (kg/m^2), inclusive, at Screening.

          6. Agrees to use adequate contraception from signing of informed consent throughout the
             duration of the study and for 90 days after last dose.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has received any investigational compound or device within 3 months or 5 half-lives,
             whichever is longer, prior to Check-in for Screening.

          2. Is an immediate family member, study site employee, or is in a dependent relationship
             with a study site employee who is involved in the conduct of this study (eg, spouse,
             parent, child, sibling) or may consent under duress.

          3. Has uncontrolled, clinically significant, neurologic (including seizure disorder),
             cardiovascular, pulmonary, hepatic, renal, metabolic, gastrointestinal, urologic,
             immunologic, or endocrine disease or psychiatric disorder, or other abnormality, which
             may impact the ability of the participant to participate or potentially confound the
             study results.

          4. Has a known hypersensitivity to any component of the formulation of TAK-831 or related
             compounds, or to [18 F]PGM299 or to any of its components.

          5. Has a positive urine or breath test result for drugs of abuse (defined as any illicit
             drug use), ethanol (alcohol), or cotinine at Screening, Check-in for Baseline
             Imaging/Confinement Period 1, or Check-in for the Treatment/Confinement Period 2(Day
             -1) for a participant participating in Set A or at Screening, Check-in for Tracer TEST
             PET Imaging/Confinement Period 1, or Check-in for RE-TEST PET Imaging/Confinement
             Period 2 for a participant participating in Set B.

          6. Has a history of drug abuse (defined as any illicit drug use) or a history of ethanol
             (alcohol) abuse within 1 year prior to the Screening Visit or is unwilling to agree to
             abstain from ethanol (alcohol) and drugs throughout the study.

          7. Has taken any medication, supplements, or food products during the time periods listed
             in the Excluded Medications and Dietary Products table.

          8. Intends to donate sperm during the course of this study or for 90 days after the last
             dose of study medication.

          9. Has evidence of current cardiovascular, central nervous system, hepatic, or
             hematopoietic disease; renal, metabolic or endocrine dysfunction; serious allergy,
             asthma, hypoxemia, hypertension, or allergic skin rash; or there is any finding in the
             participant's medical history, physical examination, or safety laboratory tests giving
             reasonable suspicion of a disease that would contraindicate taking TAK-831 or a
             similar drug in the same class, which might interfere with the conduct of the study.
             This includes, but is not limited to, peptic ulcer disease and cardiac arrhythmias.

         10. Has current or recent (within 6 months) gastrointestinal (GI) disease that would be
             expected to influence the absorption of drugs (i.e., a history of malabsorption), any
             surgical intervention known to impact absorption (e.g., bariatric surgery or bowel
             resection), esophageal reflux, peptic ulcer disease, erosive esophagitis, or frequent
             (more than once per week) occurrence of heartburn.

         11. Has a history of cancer, except basal cell carcinoma that has been in remission for at
             least 5 years prior to Day 1.

         12. Has a positive test result for hepatitis B virus surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis C
             virus (HCV) antibody (HCAB), or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection at
             Screening.

         13. Has used nicotine-containing products (including but not limited to cigarettes, pipes,
             cigars, chewing tobacco, nicotine patch or nicotine gum) within 44 days prior to
             Check-in for Confinement Period 1. Cotinine test is positive at Screening, or Check-in
             for Confinement Period 1, or Confinement Period 2.

         14. Has poor peripheral venous access.

         15. Has an abnormal Allen's test in either upper extremity.

         16. Has donated or lost 450 milliliters (mL) or more of his blood volume (including
             plasmapheresis), or had a transfusion of any blood product within 90 days prior to
             Confinement Period 1.

         17. Has an abnormal clinically significant ECG at Screening, Check-in for Confinement
             Period 1, or at Check-in for Confinement Period 2. Entry of any participant with an
             abnormal (not clinically significant [NCS]) ECG must be approved and documented by
             signature of the coordinating investigator or delegate.

         18. Has a supine blood pressure outside the ranges of 100 to 140 millimeters of mercury
             (mm Hg) for systolic and 50 to 90 mm Hg for diastolic, confirmed with 1 repeat testing
             within a maximum of 30 minutes, at the Screening Visit, Check-in for Confinement
             Period 1, or Confinement Period 2.

         19. Has a resting heart rate outside the range of 50 to 90 beats/minute, confirmed with 1
             repeat testing within a maximum of 30 minutes, at the Screening Visit, Check-in for
             Confinement Period 1, or Confinement Period 2.

         20. Has a QTcF - Fridericia's Correction Formula (QTcF) interval &gt;450 millisecond (msec)
             or PR outside the range of 120 to 220 msec, confirmed with 1 repeat testing within a
             maximum of 30 minutes, at the Screening Visit, Check-in for Confinement Period 1, or
             Confinement Period 2.

         21. Has abnormal Screening laboratory values that suggest a CS underlying disease or the
             following laboratory abnormalities: Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) and/or Alanine
             serum transaminase AST &gt;1.5*upper limit of normal (ULN).

         22. Has a risk of suicide according to the investigator's clinical judgment (eg, per
             Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale [C-SSRS]) or has made an attempt in the
             previous 6 months.

         23. Has had a seizure or convulsion (lifetime), including absence seizure and febrile
             convulsion.

         24. In the opinion of the investigator, is unlikely to comply with the protocol or is
             unsuitable for any other reason.

         25. Has had previous exposure to ionizing radiation such that, in combination with the
             exposure from this study, their exposure will be greater than (&gt;) 10 millisievert
             (mSv) for the previous year.

         26. Has a contraindication to medical resonance imaging (MRI) based on the standard MRI
             screening questionnaire. Contraindications include ferromagnetic foreign bodies (eg,
             shrapnel, ferromagnetic fragments in the orbital area), certain implanted medical
             devices (eg, aneurysm clips, cardiac pacemakers) or claustrophobia.

         27. Has findings on screening brain MRI scan that will potentially compromise participant
             safety or the scientific integrity of the study data, if the participant were to
             participate in this study.

         28. Has prolonged prothrombin time (PT) or activated partial thromboplastin time (PTT) or
             reduced platelet count (less than [&lt;] 100*10^9/Liters [L]).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

