<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02716519</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>017-101-09-037</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02716519</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Santyl Within an Accountable Care Organization</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Outcomes for Chronic Ulcers Treated With Clostridial Collagenase (SANTYL®) Versus Standard Care Within the Continuum of Care of an Accountable Care Organization (ACO)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Smith &amp; Nephew, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Smith &amp; Nephew, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to assess the comparative effectiveness of SANTYL® versus standard of
      care in the treatment of pressure ulcers and diabetic foot ulcers within the continuum of
      care of an ACO. After meeting study criteria, participants will be randomly assigned to apply
      Santyl or standard care to their pressure ulcer or diabetic foot ulcer for up to 6 weeks.
      Participants will be followed for one year from the date of randomization to assess ulcer
      status and ulcer complications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Business Decision
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Target Ulcer Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Target ulcer complications from baseline to the end of the assessment period in each treatment group:
increase in size by more than 25%,
cellulitis,
ulcer infections,
osteomyelitis,
requirement for surgical intervention</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of increase in ulcer size by more than 25% between treatment groups during the assessment period</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of cellulitis between treatment groups during the assessment period</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of ulcer infections between treatment groups during the assessment period</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of osteomyelitis between treatment groups during the assessment period</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of requirement for surgical intervention between treatment groups during the assessment period</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage change in ulcer area from baseline to the end of treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study discontinuations (target ulcer related)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital readmission for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency department visits for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the acute phase, daily time at bedside for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the acute phase, daily wound care products (including dressings) for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>During the acute phase, the quantity of daily wound care products (including dressings) for target ulcer treatment will be collected. At the conclusion of the study, the wound care products used will be costed using national costing averages. Total costs will be aggregated on a per patient basis and then compared between the standard of care group and the Santyl group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the acute phase, daily antibiotics and analgesics used for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the acute phase, daily lab tests for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the acute phase, daily surgical procedures for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the post-acute phase, weekly clinician time at bedside for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the post-acute phase, weekly patient and caregiver time for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the post-acute phase, weekly wound care products (including dressings) for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the post-acute phase, weekly antibiotics and analgesics used for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the post-acute phase, weekly lab tests for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>During the post-acute phase, weekly surgical procedures for target ulcer treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Pressure Ulcer</condition>
  <condition>Foot Ulcer, Diabetic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Santyl</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Collagenase ointment applied topically once per day for up to six weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Card</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard Care not specified by the protocol; Investigators choose the appropriate standard care treatment for each participant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Santyl</intervention_name>
    <description>Collagenase ointment applied topically once per day for up to six weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Santyl</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard Care not specified by the protocol; Investigators choose the appropriate standard care treatment for each participant</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Card</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA

          1. Provide written informed consent, which will consist of reading, signing, and dating
             the informed consent document after the Investigator, sub-Investigator or other
             designated study staff member has explained the study procedures, risks, and contact
             information.

          2. Eighteen (18) years of age or older, of either sex, and of any race or skin type.

          3. Willing and able to make all required study visits.

          4. Able to follow instructions and perform the dressing changes at home or have a
             caregiver who can perform the dressing changes according to the protocol.

          5. Subject is currently being treated in an in-patient acute care setting.

          6. Willing to use an appropriate off-loading device to keep weight off of foot ulcers;
             currently receiving adequate pressure redistribution according to local protocol in
             the affected area for pressure ulcers.

          7. For DFU: An ulcer present on any part of the plantar surface of the foot or plantar
             surface of the hallux which is 0.5 cm2 - 10 cm2 inclusive (as measured at the
             Screening Visit using the ARANZ Silhouette imaging device).

             For PU: Stage II-IV ulcer that is 1 cm2 to 64 cm2 inclusive (as measured at the
             Screening Visit using the ARANZ Silhouette imaging device).

             - Subjects may have more than one ulcer without limitation on the ulcer burden, but
             only one qualifying ulcer per subject will be selected for the study (selection based
             on greatest clinical need, as determined by the Investigator).

          8. For lower extremity ulcers: Adequate arterial blood flow as evidenced by an ankle
             brachial index (ABI) of &gt; 0.70 and ≤ 1.2. If ABI &gt; 1.2, perfusion at or near the site
             of the ulcer must be confirmed: i.e., the foot is warm to the touch and has palpable
             pulses. Availability of an ABI completed within the 90 days of Screening is
             acceptable.

          9. Separation of at least 5 cm (closest ulcer edge to other closest ulcer edge) as
             measured using the ARANZ Silhouette imaging device if ≥ 2 ulcers are present.

         10. Target ulcer is not infected based on clinical assessment.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          1. Contraindications or hypersensitivity to the use of clostridial collagenase.

          2. Participation in another clinical trial within thirty (30) days of Screening, or
             planned participation overlapping with this study.

          3. Bleeding disorder that would preclude sharp debridement during the study.

          4. Active cellulitis of the target ulcer, lymphangitic streaking, deep tissue abscess, or
             infection of muscle, tendon, joint or bone.

          5. Co-morbidities leading to systemic organ dysfunction or severe single- or multi-organ
             failure that in the opinion of the Investigator would preclude safe subject
             participation in the study.

          6. A target ulcer which involves the underlying tissues of tendon.

          7. Diagnosis of chronic granulomatous disease, leukocyte adhesion defects, or severe
             neutropenia.

          8. Current treatment (at the time of the Screening Visit) with any of the following:

               -  Systemic corticosteroids. If corticosteroid treatment was for ≥ 10 days, there
                  must be a 1 week interval between discontinuation and screening.

               -  Immunosuppressive agents

               -  Chemotherapeutic agents

               -  Antiviral agents

               -  Systemic antibiotic therapy for acute wound-related infection

               -  Topical antibiotic treatment of the target ulcer

          9. Treatment of target ulcer with bioactive therapies within 1 month of screening:

               -  Platelet-derived growth factor (e.g., Regranex)

               -  Cellular or Tissue-based Products (e.g., Apligraf, Dermagraft, Integra, Oasis,
                  etc.)

               -  Amniotic membrane products (e.g., EpiFix, Grafix, etc.)

         10. Prior treatment of target ulcer for any length of time with CCO (SANTYL) within 30
             days of screening.

         11. Any prior radiation therapy to the affected area

         12. Medical or physical condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would preclude
             safe subject participation in the study.

         13. Blood counts and blood chemistry values as follows:

        NOTE: Availability of lab results within the 30 days of Screening is acceptable.

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; 3x upper limit of normal

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 3x upper limit of normal

          -  Gamma Glutamyl Transferase (GGT) &gt; 2.5x upper limit of normal

          -  Serum albumin &lt; 2.0 g/dL

          -  Pre-albumin levels of &lt; 10 mg/dL

          -  Alkaline phosphatase &gt; 500 U/L

          -  Serum total bilirubin &gt; 3.0 mg/dL

          -  Serum BUN &gt; 75 mg/dL

          -  Serum creatinine &gt; 4.5 mg/dL

          -  HbA1c &gt; 12%

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) &lt; 8.0 g/dL

          -  WBC &lt; 2.0 x 109/L

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1.0 x 109/L

          -  Platelet count &lt; 50 x 109/L
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jaime E Dickerson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Smith &amp; Nephew, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandeep Kathju, MD/PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>16066</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>diabetic foot ulcer</keyword>
  <keyword>foot sore</keyword>
  <keyword>type 2 diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>type 1 diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>DFU</keyword>
  <keyword>pressure ulcers</keyword>
  <keyword>bed sores</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pressure Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Foot</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

