<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02716493</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20994</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02716493</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility of a 8-week Telerehabilitation Program for Patients With Thoracic Neoplasia Receiving Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>TELErp</acronym>
  <official_title>Feasibility of an Eight-week Telerehabilitation Program for Patients With Unresectable Thoracic Neoplasia Receiving Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre de Recherche de l'Institut Universitaire de Cardiologie et de Pneumologie de Quebec</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre de Recherche de l'Institut Universitaire de Cardiologie et de Pneumologie de Quebec</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Exercise-based rehabilitation improves physical function, fatigue and quality of life in
      patients with thoracic neoplasia. Consequently, the need for rehabilitation across the
      continuum of care in oncology is growing rapidly. However, the implementation of this type of
      intervention is limited because of many barriers such as patients' symptoms and poor
      accessibility to programs. In this context, healthcare systems should develop and implement
      new approaches to dispense these services. Consequently, telerehabilitation is a promising
      strategy to improve access and adherence to rehabilitation.

      OBJECTIVES To investigate the feasibility, adherence and satisfaction of a home-based
      telerehabilitation program (TELERP) with real-time physiological parameters acquisition in
      patients with unresectable thoracic neoplasia receiving chemotherapy and to explore its
      effects on patients' functional capacity.

      METHODS Five patients receiving chemotherapy followed an 8-week TELERP using real-time
      monitoring combined with interactive exercises. The TELERP included supervised (15) and
      unsupervised (9) strengthening and cardiovascular exercise sessions at a rate of 3
      sessions/week. The feasibility of the TELERP, adverse outcomes, technical issues, program
      adherence and satisfaction were analysed. Prior to and after the program, a six-minute
      walking test (6MWT), a timed up and go (TUG) and a timed stair test (TST) were done to assess
      functional capacity
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of adverse events during the 8-week telerehabilitation program</measure>
    <time_frame>Along the 8-week program</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence of the participants to the 8-week telerehabilitation program.</measure>
    <time_frame>Along the 8-week program</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence was defined as the number of sessions done over the prescribed sessions (supervised and unsupervised) and as percentage of time spent within the target heart rate range (intensities) throughout the cardiovascular exercise sessions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants satisfaction with the telerehabilitation platform with the Québec User Evaluation of Satisfaction with Assistive Technology questionnaire (QUEST 2.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of the 8-week telerehabilitation program</time_frame>
    <description>The satisfaction of the patients was evaluated using a questionnaire adapted from the Québec User Evaluation of Satisfaction with Assistive Technology questionnaire (QUEST 2.0) that calculates both satisfaction scores for technological aspects and services. It consists of 12 items rated on a scale from 1 to 5 (1: not satisfied at all to 5: very satisfied).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>User satisfaction with health services received with the French version of the Health Care Satisfaction Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of the 8-week telerehabilitation program</time_frame>
    <description>To assess more specifically the user satisfaction with health services received, we used the French version of the Health Care Satisfaction Questionnaire. This is a 26-item questionnaire answered on a four-point Likert scale, where ''1'' represents ''not at all satisfied'' and ''4'' represents ''highly satisfied&quot;. The total score is calculated in percentage and can be computed as the mean overall satisfaction divided in three domains: i) relationship with the professional, ii) delivery of services and iii) organization of services. Higher scores indicate a higher level of satisfaction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiopulmonary maximal exercise test (CPET)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Constant workrate cycle exercise test at 80% of the maximal capacity of the patient</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Isokinetic quadriceps muscle functions</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
    <description>Quadriceps muscle function (strength and endurance) was assessed during an isokinetic endurance test performed at a rate of 30 repetitions at 90°/sec of angular velocity (Biodex, system pro 4, Biodex Medical System, 20 Ramsay Road, Shirley, New York )</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lean body mass</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
    <description>Lean body mass (in Kg) were measured by bioelectrical impedance analysis (TBF-300WA Tanita, Arlington Heights, IL, USA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fat body mass</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
    <description>Fat body mass (in Kg) were measured by bioelectrical impedance analysis (TBF-300WA Tanita, Arlington Heights, IL, USA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
    <description>Weight (in Kg) of the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Height</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
    <description>Height (in meters) of the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed up and go test</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed stairs test</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distance achieved during the 6 minutes walking test</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer specific quality of life with the self-reported European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
    <description>The cancer related quality of life was assessed using the self-reported European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-30) including the lung cancer specific questionnaire QLQ-LC13</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety and depression with the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
    <description>The French Canadian version of the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) was used to identify patients suffering of anxiety disorders or depression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nutritional status with the mini-nutritional assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and following the 8-week program</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Telerehabilitation group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with unresectable thoracic neoplasia receiving chemotherapy treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telerehabilitation program</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention was an 8-week home-based telerehabilitation program (three sessions of about 75 minutes per week) using the eChez-Soi telerehabilitation platform.
Through a unique software interface, the eChez-Soi allows for the following three technological aspects: 1- continuous data acquisition and recording from commercial biometric sensors; 2- continuous transmission of the collected data via the Internet to the clinician's computer, allowing the clinician to visualize the biomechanical and physiological parameters in real time; and 3- a challenging gaming environment with interactive exercises performed on musical rhythms.
In total, 15 supervised sessions and 9 unsupervised sessions were planned for a total of 24 exercise sessions</description>
    <arm_group_label>Telerehabilitation group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients had to have an ECOG functional status of 0 (Asymptomatic) or 1 (Symptomatic
             but completely ambulatory);

          -  Have a sufficient understanding of verbal and written French instructions

          -  Live in a geographic region served by a high speed Internet connection.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  oxygen pulsed saturation (SpO2) &lt;80% during the cardiopulmonary exercise test

          -  contraindications to exercise testing according to the American Thoracic Society and
             American College of Chest Physicians Exercise Testing Guidelines

          -  cerebral or bone metastasis

          -  a history of significant cardiovascular disease, hypertension, diabetes or
             musculoskeletal concerns that might limit their ability to perform active exercises

          -  severe psychiatric illness compromising adherence to the rehabilitation training
             routine.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CRIUCPQ</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quebec</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centre de Recherche de l'Institut Universitaire de Cardiologie et de Pneumologie de Quebec</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Didier Saey</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Telerehabilitation</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

