<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02717585</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-0112-B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02717585</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of CPAP on Symptoms of Patients With Fibromyalgia and Obstructive Sleep Apnea</brief_title>
  <acronym>FM-OSA</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) on Symptoms of Patients With Fibromyalgia Syndrome and Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA): A Prospective Randomized Controlled Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Women's College Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Women's College Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fibromyalgia (FM) is a chronic pain disorder associated with a wide spectrum of sleep
      disorders. In fact, insomnia and waking unrefreshed are currently considered part of the
      criteria for diagnosis. Recent studies show that sleep quality and symptoms of FM are
      inversely correlated. Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a sleep disorder characterized by
      repeated episodes of complete or partial blockage of the upper airway. Nonrestorative sleep
      and fatigue are common symptoms of FM and OSA and may suggest related pathophysiology or
      co-morbidity that is yet to be diagnosed. This prospective randomized controlled clinical
      trial will enroll adult FM patients who screen positive for OSA by the STOP-Bang
      questionnaire. OSA will be confirmed by a laboratory polysomnography (PSG) study. After
      undergoing further baseline questionnaires and investigations, patients confirmed to have FM
      with moderate to severe OSA will be randomized to one of two different treatments: 1)
      Treatment for FM at the Chronic Pain Clinic together with Continuous Positive Airway Pressure
      (CPAP) devices for their OSA OR 2) Control group receiving treatment for FM at the Chronic
      Pain Clinic only.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sleep, pain and breathing have a complex multidimensional relationship. Pain disturbs sleep,
      poor sleep alters the perception of pain and sleep is a vulnerable state of breathing. The
      central system sensitization affecting the sensation of widespread pain in FM is due to a
      decrease in the neurophysiologic inhibition of perception of painful stimuli. This is caused
      by disturbed sleep. Rheumatic disease pathology can be understood in the light of the
      interference of cytokines and cellular immune functions with the sleeping/waking brain. Sleep
      disturbances such as unrefreshing sleep, difficulty falling asleep and frequent night
      awakenings have been reported by over 90% of FM patients. Sleep disturbances may be related
      to depression through pain and alteration of physical functioning. Depression and sleep
      disturbances have been proven to contribute to fatigue in FM patients. Although
      non-restorative sleep and fatigue are the most commonly reported symptoms by FM patients, the
      exact cause of these problems is not well understood. A study reported that 50% of the women
      with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome or upper airway resistance syndrome had chronic pain
      and more than 11 tender points. One case report has suggested OSA as a possible cause for FM.
      No studies have been conducted to demonstrate the effect of CPAP treatment on symptoms of FM
      syndrome in patients with OSA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Lack of funding available
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Score</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pain scores will measured on a Numerical Rating Scale (NRS) on the Brief Pain Inventory (BPI), reported at monthly intervals after allocation to a treatment group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sleep Quality will be measured via the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) and the Pain and Sleep Questionnaire (PSQ)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleepiness</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sleepiness will be measured via the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>QoL will be measured via both the revised Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire (FIQR) and the Short Form 12 Health Survey (SF-12)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory Marker</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of serum levels of C-Reactive protein</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the no intervention group (Control), patients will only receive standardized treatment for FM at the Pain Clinic. All patients will receive a multifaceted tailored regimen that incorporates one or more lines of pharmacological and/or non-pharmacological therapy. All assessment and management will be performed according to evidence-based therapeutic recommendations put forward by the Canadian Rheumatology Association and Canadian Pain Society.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group (CPAP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In addition to standard FM treatment at the Pain Clinic, patients who are randomized to the treatment will meet with a sleep physician for possible therapy with a Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) machine. A CPAP titration study will be arranged for in a laboratory setting, where in addition to the regular parameters of a diagnostic sleep study, CPAP will be titrated upwards starting from 5cm H2O to an optimal setting where the obstructive respiratory events are abolished. Patients will undergo regular follow-up as determined by their sleep physician. Adherence to CPAP treatment will be recorded at follow-up visits.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure Therapy (CPAP)</intervention_name>
    <description>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure Therapy (CPAP) consists of a mask, fitted to the patient's face and hooked to a machine that generates positive pressure at the end of expiration to abolish obstructive apneic episodes during sleep.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group (CPAP)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Possesses cognitive and physical capability necessary to comprehend and complete the
             study questionnaires, as well as how to use CPAP machines.

          -  Be proficient in English, reading and comprehension at a Grade 6 level (patient or
             accompanying person).

          -  Be accessible for follow-up via interview appointments.

          -  Be able to provide informed consent.

          -  Has a Widespread Pain Index (WPI) score of ≥7 and Symptom Severity Score (SSS) of ≥5
             OR a WPI 3-6 and SSS ≥9 according to 2010 American College of Rheumatology criteria
             for Fibromyalgia.

          -  Constant pain scores over the past 8 weeks.

          -  Newly diagnosed OSA patients with an AHI ≥15 OR AHI ≥5 on laboratory polysomnography
             with significant symptoms such as daytime sleepiness (Epworth Sleepiness Scale
             (ESS&gt;10), or nocturnal symptoms (frequent nocturnal awakenings).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Conditions potentially interfering with comprehension and delivery of informed consent
             or unwillingness to provide consent.

          -  Psychiatric conditions interfering with necessary capability to comprehend and
             complete study questionnaires.

          -  Non-English speaking.

          -  Pregnant and lactating women.

          -  Uncorrectable coagulopathy interfering with phlebotomy.

          -  Contraindication to the application of a CPAP interface such as significant facial
             deformities, or skin lesions.

          -  History of drug or alcohol dependence or abuse within the last 3 months.

          -  History of primary pain disorders other than Fibromyalgia such as chronic pain
             disorder.

          -  History of primary sleep disorders associated with daytime sleepiness other than OSA,
             such as narcolepsy.

          -  Patients who do not meet the 2010 American College of Rheumatology Criteria for
             Fibromyalgia.

          -  Patients with previously diagnosed OSA who are already on CPAP before the initiation
             of the study.

          -  Patients receiving trigger point injections or intravenous lidocaine for pain
             treatment.

          -  Patients requiring an urgent sleep physician referral (within four weeks) due to
             serious medical conditions or safety critical-occupations according to the 2011
             Canadian Thoracic Society (CTS) guidelines update e.g. unstable ischemic heart
             disease, recent cerebrovascular disease, congestive heart failure, refractory systemic
             hypertension, obstructive/restrictive lung disease, pulmonary hypertension,
             hypercapnic respiratory failure or pregnancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frances Chung, MBBS,FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Health Network, Toronto Western Hospital and Women's College Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women's College Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5S 1B2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 2S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stopbang.ca</url>
    <description>The Official STOP-Bang Website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolfe F, Smythe HA, Yunus MB, Bennett RM, Bombardier C, Goldenberg DL, Tugwell P, Campbell SM, Abeles M, Clark P, et al. The American College of Rheumatology 1990 Criteria for the Classification of Fibromyalgia. Report of the Multicenter Criteria Committee. Arthritis Rheum. 1990 Feb;33(2):160-72.</citation>
    <PMID>2306288</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yunus MB. Editorial review: an update on central sensitivity syndromes and the issues of nosology and psychobiology. Curr Rheumatol Rev. 2015;11(2):70-85. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26138918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roizenblatt S, Neto NS, Tufik S. Sleep disorders and fibromyalgia. Curr Pain Headache Rep. 2011 Oct;15(5):347-57. doi: 10.1007/s11916-011-0213-3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21594765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fitzcharles MA, Ste-Marie PA, Goldenberg DL, Pereira JX, Abbey S, Choinière M, Ko G, Moulin DE, Panopalis P, Proulx J, Shir Y; National Fibromyalgia Guideline Advisory Panel. 2012 Canadian Guidelines for the diagnosis and management of fibromyalgia syndrome: executive summary. Pain Res Manag. 2013 May-Jun;18(3):119-26.</citation>
    <PMID>23748251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peppard PE, Young T, Barnet JH, Palta M, Hagen EW, Hla KM. Increased prevalence of sleep-disordered breathing in adults. Am J Epidemiol. 2013 May 1;177(9):1006-14. doi: 10.1093/aje/kws342. Epub 2013 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23589584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sepici V, Tosun A, Köktürk O. Obstructive sleep apnea syndrome as an uncommon cause of fibromyalgia: a case report. Rheumatol Int. 2007 Nov;28(1):69-71. Epub 2007 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>17589851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chung F, Subramanyam R, Liao P, Sasaki E, Shapiro C, Sun Y. High STOP-Bang score indicates a high probability of obstructive sleep apnoea. Br J Anaesth. 2012 May;108(5):768-75. doi: 10.1093/bja/aes022. Epub 2012 Mar 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22401881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Khalid I, Roehrs TA, Hudgel DW, Roth T. Continuous positive airway pressure in severe obstructive sleep apnea reduces pain sensitivity. Sleep. 2011 Dec 1;34(12):1687-91. doi: 10.5665/sleep.1436.</citation>
    <PMID>22131606</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep Disturbance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

