<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02716038</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAQ3153</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02716038</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neoadjuvant MPDL3280A, Nab-paclitaxel and Carboplatin (MAC) in NSCLC</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-arm, Phase II Study of Neoadjuvant MPDL3280A, Nab-paclitaxel and Carboplatin (MAC) in Resectable Non-small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a research study to test the effectiveness of nab-paclitaxel + carboplatin +
      MPDL3280A for treatment of non-small-cell lung carcinoma (NSCLC), which is a type of lung
      cancer. The study aims to determine if chemotherapy combined with immune-based therapy can
      lead to improvement in tumor response rates over historical response rates with chemotherapy
      alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lung cancer is the most common cancer in both men and women worldwide, accounting for 13% of
      incident cancers. In 2015, it was estimated there would be 221,200 new lung cancers diagnosed
      in the United States, with 158,040 lung cancer deaths. Approximately 85% of all lung cancers
      are characterized as non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC).

      Repeated studies have shown neoadjuvant cytotoxic chemotherapy to be safe prior to surgical
      resection of NSCLC with no difference in extent of surgical procedures performed, operative
      morbidity and mortality. The debate remains as to whether neoadjuvant or adjuvant
      chemotherapy is the best approach, with advantages and disadvantages to each.

      We propose that new therapies such as immune checkpoint inhibitors that demonstrate promising
      clinical activity in the advanced disease setting must be incorporated into the neoadjuvant
      setting, in order to maximize benefit early in a patient's treatment course, and with a
      suitable surrogate endpoint that can be used to establish a preliminary efficacy signal,
      prior to initiation of a large confirmatory study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 7, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with major pathologic response (MPR)</measure>
    <time_frame>84 days</time_frame>
    <description>Major pathologic response rate (MPR) is defined as &gt; 90% decrease in viable tumor.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MPDL3280A, Carboplatin, Nab-paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects with advanced or recurrent cancers receiving:
MPDL3280A every 21 days for up to 84 days
Carboplatin every 21 days for up to 84 days
Nab-paclitaxel every 7 days for up to 84 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MPDL3280A</intervention_name>
    <description>MPDL3280A is a human, Fc optimized, monoclonal antibody directed against the protein ligand PD-L1 (programmed cell death-1 ligand 1), with potential immune checkpoint inhibitory and antineoplastic activities. Atezolizumab binds to PD-L1, blocking its binding to and activation of its receptor programmed death 1 (PD-1) expressed on activated T-cells, which may enhance the T-cell-mediated immune response to neoplasms and reverse T-cell inactivation. MPDL3280A 1200 mg will be administered as a 60 minute IV infusion on first administration, then over 30 minutes subsequently if tolerated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MPDL3280A, Carboplatin, Nab-paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Atezolizumab</other_name>
    <other_name>RG7446</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Carboplatin is a second-generation platinum compound with a broad spectrum of antineoplastic properties. Carboplatin contains a platinum atom complexed with two ammonia groups and a cyclobutane-dicarboxyl residue. This agent is activated intracellularly to form reactive platinum complexes that bind to nucleophilic groups such as GC-rich sites in DNA, thereby inducing intrastrand and interstrand DNA cross-links, as well as DNA-protein cross-links. These carboplatin-induced DNA and protein effects result in apoptosis and cell growth inhibition. Carboplatin AUC=6 will be administered as a 30 minute IV infusion immediately after nab-paclitaxel.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MPDL3280A, Carboplatin, Nab-paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin-AQ</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nab-paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Nab-paclitaxel is a Cremophor EL-free, albumin-stabilized nanoparticle formulation of the natural taxane paclitaxel with antineoplastic activity. Nab-paclitaxel binds to and stabilizes microtubules, preventing their depolymerization and so inhibiting cellular motility, mitosis, and replication. Nab-paclitaxel 100 mg/m2 will be administered as a 30 minute IV infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MPDL3280A, Carboplatin, Nab-paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Abraxane</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have pathologically confirmed non-small cell lung cancer, of either
             squamous or non-squamous histology.

          -  Stage IB-IIIA

          -  Deemed surgically resectable by a thoracic surgeon

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Radiologically measurable disease, as defined by response evaluation criteria in solid
             tumours (RECIST) v1.1

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

          -  Females of child-bearing potential (defined as a sexually mature woman who (1) has not
             undergone hysterectomy [the surgical removal of the uterus] or bilateral oophorectomy
             [the surgical removal of both ovaries] or (2) has not been naturally postmenopausal
             for at least 24 consecutive months [i.e., has had menses at any time during the
             preceding 24 consecutive months]) must:

               -  Either commit to true abstinence from heterosexual contact (which must be
                  reviewed on a monthly basis), or agree to use, and be able to comply with,
                  effective contraception (&lt;/=1% failure rate annually) without interruption, 28
                  days prior to starting therapy (including dose interruptions), and while on study
                  medication or for a period of 90 days following treatment completion. [Periodic
                  abstinence (eg, calendar, ovulation, symptothermal, post-ovulation methods) and
                  withdrawal are not acceptable methods of contraception].

               -  Have a negative serum pregnancy test (β -hCG) result at screening and agree to
                  ongoing pregnancy testing during the course of the study, and after the end of
                  study therapy. This applies even if the subject practices true abstinence from
                  heterosexual contact.

          -  Male subjects must practice true abstinence or agree to use a condom during sexual
             contact with a pregnant female or a female of childbearing potential while
             participating in the study, during dose interruptions and for 6 months following
             treatment discontinuation, even if he has undergone a successful vasectomy.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0 or 1

          -  Representative formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tumor specimens in paraffin
             blocks (blocks are preferred) or at least 10 unstained slides, with an associated
             pathology report, for central testing of tumor PD-L1 expression

               -  Tumor tissue should be of good quality based on total and viable tumor content.
                  Fine-needle aspiration, brushing, cell pellet from pleural effusion, and lavage
                  samples are not acceptable. For core-needle biopsy specimens, at least three
                  cores should be submitted for evaluation.

               -  Patients who do not have tissue specimens meeting eligibility requirements may
                  undergo a biopsy during the screening period. Acceptable samples include
                  core-needle biopsies for deep tumor tissue (minimum of three cores) or
                  excisional, incisional, punch, or forceps biopsies for cutaneous, subcutaneous,
                  or mucosal lesions.

          -  Adequate organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  Lymphocyte count ≥300/mcL

               -  Neutrophil count ≥1,500/mcL

               -  Hemoglobin ≥9.0g/dl

               -  Platelets ≥100,000/mcL

               -  Total bilirubin ≤1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN) (*Patients with
                  Gilbert's disease: ≤3 x ULN)

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)(SGOT)/alanine aminotransferase (ALT)(SGPT) ≤2.5
                  × ULN

               -  Alkaline phosphatase ≤2.5 x ULN

               -  INR and aPTT ≤ 1.5 x ULN (*Unless the patient is on therapeutic anticoagulation)

               -  Serum creatinine ≤1.5 x ULN or

               -  Creatinine clearance ≥50 mL/min/1.73 m2 by Cockcoft-Gault estimation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any approved anticancer therapy, including chemotherapy, hormonal therapy, or
             radiotherapy, within 5 years prior to initiation of study treatment; however, the
             following are allowed:

               -  Hormone-replacement therapy or oral contraceptives

               -  Herbal therapy &gt; 1 week prior to Cycle 1, Day 1 (herbal therapy intended as
                  anticancer therapy must be discontinued at least 1 week prior to Cycle 1, Day 1)

          -  Malignancies other than the disease under study within 5 years prior to Cycle 1, Day
             1, with the exception of those with a negligible risk of metastasis or death and with
             expected curative outcome (such as adequately treated carcinoma in situ of the cervix,
             basal or squamous cell skin cancer, localized prostate cancer treated surgically with
             curative intent, or ductal carcinoma in situ treated surgically with curative intent)
             or undergoing active surveillance per standard-of-care management (e.g., chronic
             lymphocytic leukemia Rai Stage 0, prostate cancer with Gleason score ≤ 6, and
             prostate-specific antigen [PSA] ≤ 10 mg/mL, etc.)

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents concurrently.

          -  Patients with no smoking history

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to MPDL3280A, carboplatin, or paclitaxel.

          -  Patients with active hepatitis B or C infections (defined as a positive Hepatitis B
             DNA or Hepatitis C RNA by PCR) or a history of HIV infection.

               -  Patients with past or resolved hepatitis B infection (defined as having a
                  negative hepatitis B surface antigen [HBsAg] test and a positive anti-HBc
                  [antibody to hepatitis B core antigen] antibody test) are eligible.

               -  Patients positive for hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody are eligible only if
                  polymerase chain reaction (PCR) is negative for HCV RNA.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection including TB, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina
             pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would
             limit compliance with study requirements.

          -  Known clinically significant liver disease, including active viral, alcoholic, or
             other hepatitis; cirrhosis; fatty liver; and inherited liver disease

          -  Known hypersensitivity to Chinese hamster ovary cell products or other recombinant
             human antibodies

          -  History or risk of autoimmune disease, including but not limited to systemic lupus
             erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, inflammatory bowel disease, vascular thrombosis
             associated with antiphospholipid syndrome, Wegener's granulomatosis, Sjögren's
             syndrome, Bell's palsy, Guillain-Barré syndrome, multiple sclerosis, autoimmune
             thyroid disease, vasculitis, or glomerulonephritis

               -  Patients with a history of autoimmune hypothyroidism on a stable dose of thyroid
                  replacement hormone may be eligible.

               -  Patients with controlled Type 1 diabetes mellitus on a stable insulin regimen may
                  be eligible.

               -  Patients with eczema, psoriasis, lichen simplex chronicus of vitiligo with
                  dermatologic manifestations only (e.g., patients with psoriatic arthritis would
                  be excluded) are permitted provided that they meet the following conditions:

                    -  Patients with psoriasis must have a baseline ophthalmologic exam to rule out
                       ocular manifestations

                    -  Rash must cover less than 10% of body surface area (BSA)

                    -  Disease is well controlled at baseline and only requiring low potency
                       topical steroids (e.g., hydrocortisone 2.5%, hydrocortisone butyrate 0.1%,
                       flucinolone 0.01%, desonide 0.05%, aclometasone dipropionate 0.05%)

                    -  No acute exacerbations of underlying condition within the last 12 months
                       (not requiring psoralen plus ultraviolet A radiation [PUVA], methotrexate,
                       retinoids, biologic agents, oral calcineurin inhibitors; high potency or
                       oral steroids)

          -  Severe infections within 4 weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1, including but not limited to
             hospitalization for complications of infection, bacteremia, or severe pneumonia

          -  Signs or symptoms of infection within 2 weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1 Received oral or
             IV antibiotics within 2 weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1. Patients receiving prophylactic
             antibiotics (e.g., for prevention of a urinary tract infection or chronic obstructive
             pulmonary disease) are eligible

          -  Major surgical procedure within 28 days prior to Cycle 1, Day 1 or anticipation of
             need for a major surgical procedure during the course of the study

          -  Patients must not have &gt;/= Grade 2 pre-existing peripheral neuropathy (per CTCAE)

          -  Administration of a live, attenuated vaccine within 4 weeks before Cycle 1, Day 1 or
             anticipation that such a live, attenuated vaccine will be required during the study

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because MPDL3280A, and other members of
             the immune checkpoint blocking class of agents, have the potential for teratogenic or
             abortifacient effects. Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse
             events in nursing infants secondary to treatment of the mother with MPDL3280A,
             breastfeeding should be discontinued if the mother is treated with MPDL3280A.

          -  History of interstitial lung disease or pneumonitis of any cause

        Immunotherapy-Related Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior treatment with anti-PD-1, anti-CTLA-4, or anti-PD-L1 therapeutic antibody or
             pathway-targeting agents

          -  Treatment with systemic immunosuppressive medications (including but not limited to
             prednisone, cyclophosphamide, azathioprine, methotrexate, thalidomide, and anti-tumor
             necrosis factor [anti-TNF] agents) within 2 weeks prior to Cycle 1, Day 1

               -  Patients who have received acute, low-dose, systemic immunosuppressant
                  medications (e.g., a one-time dose of dexamethasone for nausea) may be enrolled.

               -  The use of inhaled corticosteroids and mineralocorticoids (e.g., fludrocortisone)
                  for patients with orthostatic hypotension or adrenocortical insufficiency is
                  allowed.

          -  History of severe allergic, anaphylactic, or other hypersensitivity reactions to
             chimeric or humanized antibodies or fusion proteins.

          -  Patients with prior allogeneic bone marrow transplantation or prior solid organ
             transplantation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Catherine Shu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robert Garofano, BS</last_name>
    <phone>(212) 304-5686</phone>
    <email>rfg2115@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Natalie Busby, BS</last_name>
    <phone>212 305-8487</phone>
    <email>nb2718@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Justin Ganor, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>617-724-4000</phone>
      <email>jgainor@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Beow Yeap, ScD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Justin Ganor, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert Garofano, BA</last_name>
      <phone>212-304-5579</phone>
      <email>rfg2115@cumc.columbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sara Marcus, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>(212) 304-5579</phone>
      <email>sm4100@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Catherine Shu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Stoopler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Naiyer Rizvi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Claud Grigg, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Arindam RoyChoudhury, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://seer.cancer.gov/archive/csr/1975_2011/</url>
    <description>Howlader N, Noone AM, Krapcho M. SEER Cancer Statistics Review, 1975-2011. Based on November 2013 SEER data submission, posted to the SEER web site, April 2014.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pataer A, Kalhor N, Correa AM, Raso MG, Erasmus JJ, Kim ES, Behrens C, Lee JJ, Roth JA, Stewart DJ, Vaporciyan AA, Wistuba II, Swisher SG; University of Texas M. D. Anderson Lung Cancer Collaborative Research Group. Histopathologic response criteria predict survival of patients with resected lung cancer after neoadjuvant chemotherapy. J Thorac Oncol. 2012 May;7(5):825-32. doi: 10.1097/JTO.0b013e318247504a.</citation>
    <PMID>22481232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Bray F, Center MM, Ferlay J, Ward E, Forman D. Global cancer statistics. CA Cancer J Clin. 2011 Mar-Apr;61(2):69-90. doi: 10.3322/caac.20107. Epub 2011 Feb 4. Erratum in: CA Cancer J Clin. 2011 Mar-Apr;61(2):134.</citation>
    <PMID>21296855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siegel RL, Miller KD, Jemal A. Cancer statistics, 2015. CA Cancer J Clin. 2015 Jan-Feb;65(1):5-29. doi: 10.3322/caac.21254. Epub 2015 Jan 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25559415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langer CJ, Besse B, Gualberto A, Brambilla E, Soria JC. The evolving role of histology in the management of advanced non-small-cell lung cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2010 Dec 20;28(36):5311-20. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.28.8126. Epub 2010 Nov 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21079145</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldstraw P, Crowley J, Chansky K, Giroux DJ, Groome PA, Rami-Porta R, Postmus PE, Rusch V, Sobin L; International Association for the Study of Lung Cancer International Staging Committee; Participating Institutions. The IASLC Lung Cancer Staging Project: proposals for the revision of the TNM stage groupings in the forthcoming (seventh) edition of the TNM Classification of malignant tumours. J Thorac Oncol. 2007 Aug;2(8):706-14. Erratum in: J Thorac Oncol. 2007 Oct;2(10):985.</citation>
    <PMID>17762336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pignon JP, Tribodet H, Scagliotti GV, Douillard JY, Shepherd FA, Stephens RJ, Dunant A, Torri V, Rosell R, Seymour L, Spiro SG, Rolland E, Fossati R, Aubert D, Ding K, Waller D, Le Chevalier T; LACE Collaborative Group. Lung adjuvant cisplatin evaluation: a pooled analysis by the LACE Collaborative Group. J Clin Oncol. 2008 Jul 20;26(21):3552-9. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2007.13.9030. Epub 2008 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>18506026</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>NSCLC Meta-analyses Collaborative Group, Arriagada R, Auperin A, Burdett S, Higgins JP, Johnson DH, Le Chevalier T, Le Pechoux C, Parmar MK, Pignon JP, Souhami RL, Stephens RJ, Stewart LA, Tierney JF, Tribodet H, van Meerbeeck J. Adjuvant chemotherapy, with or without postoperative radiotherapy, in operable non-small-cell lung cancer: two meta-analyses of individual patient data. Lancet. 2010 Apr 10;375(9722):1267-77. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60059-1. Epub 2010 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20338627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>NSCLC Meta-analysis Collaborative Group. Preoperative chemotherapy for non-small-cell lung cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis of individual participant data. Lancet. 2014 May 3;383(9928):1561-71. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)62159-5. Epub 2014 Feb 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24576776</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Catherine Shu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-Small-Cell Lung Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Nonsmall Cell Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>NSCLC</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atezolizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

