<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02711800</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00063870</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02711800</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Probiotic Study: Using Bacteria to Calm Your Mind</brief_title>
  <official_title>Probiotic Treatment: The Role of the Gut Microbiome in Childhood Abdominal Pain and Anxiety</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nancy Zucker</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators seek to conduct the first open-label trial of probiotics in young children
      to reduce their anxiety and abdominal pain. Likewise, the investigators aim to assess the
      feasibility and efficacy of this treatment and to elucidate the enteric microbiota in the
      middle-lower GI tract. Self-report measures and a laboratory task will be collected from
      children, ages 9-13 years of age, and self-report measures from their primary caregivers
      prior to and following a 30-day probiotic administration. Children who score above cutoff in
      anxiety and/or abdominal pain meet the inclusion criteria for this study. Because of limited
      sample size and the iterative nature of intervention development, criteria for success at the
      pilot phase are based primarily on clinical rather than statistical criteria. The study
      personnel will do their best to keep and ensure the privacy and confidentiality of our
      participants; however, some of the risks of this study may include psychological discomfort,
      legal risks, and loss of confidentially.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 8, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 18, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 18, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Child Abdominal Pain Rating</measure>
    <time_frame>44 days</time_frame>
    <description>Child and parent report is used to obtain ratings of pain intensity on a 0-12 scale. Ratings are obtained for a one-week period pre and post intervention, and measured 3 times daily. All time points will be averaged and combined across raters (child and parent) resulting in an average pain severity rating pre and post-treatment. The change in this average rating will be assessed as pain severity outcome. This measure will be combined with the pain frequency average score (see Primary Outcome 2) to result in one primary severity/frequency pain rating pre and post treatment. The change in this combined measure is our primary index of change.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Child Abdominal Pain Frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>44 days</time_frame>
    <description>Child and parent report is used to obtain ratings of pain frequency, the number of distinct occasions that pain was reported. Ratings are obtained for a one-week period pre and post intervention, and measured 3 times daily during these intervals. During the 30-day intervention, end of day ratings are made. The average number of episodes across these time points will be calculated pre and post treatment. The change in this average frequency from pre to post treatment will be the measure of change.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Child Anxiety Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will report the score derived from the standard anxiety scale for children at baseline and 30 days from baseline (i.e. pre-treatment and post-treatment). The change in this measure from pre to post treatment will be used as an additional measure of change.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility: ratio of adherence to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence to treatment measured by the ratio between days when the probiotic was taken and total number of days of treatment (i.e. 30 days), ranging from 0% (no probiotics taken at all) to 100% (probiotics taken 30 days out of the 30 day-treatment period). Researcher will subtract the number of pills/packets taken from the total amount. The number of remaining pills/packets will help us deduce the number of days they were taken and the adherence ratio.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in relative quantities of taxa among groups relative to probiotic administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in alpha diversity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Beta diversity (PCoA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in trait-associated co-functional modules of organisms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Salivary Cortisol (ug/dL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Heart Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Beats per minute (Bpm)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">9</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Abdominal Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigators will use Culturelle®, a probiotic composed of the micro-organisms Lactobacillus GG. This formulation has been used for the treatment of gastrointestinal inflammation in numerous clinical trials. Dosing will follow the manufacturer's recommendation for children (1 capsule/packet per day), and will be monitored by Dr. Patrick Seed from the department of pediatrics. Weekly side effects and clinical changes will be monitored by both study therapist and caregiver using the Children's Global Assessment Scale and the Clinical Global Impression Scale (Severity, Improvement, and Efficacy). The intervention duration is 30 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators will use Culturelle®, a probiotic composed of the micro-organisms Lactobacillus GG. This formulation has been used for the treatment of gastrointestinal inflammation in numerous clinical trials. Dosing will follow the manufacturer's recommendation for children (1 capsule/packet per day), and will be monitored by the study Co-PI, Dr. Seed. Weekly side effects and clinical changes will be monitored by both study therapist and caregiver using the Children's Global Assessment Scale and the Clinical Global Impression Scale (Severity, Improvement, and Efficacy). The treatment duration is 30 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Culturelle Kids</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Participants need to meet the criteria for functional abdominal pain as specified by the
        Rome III:

        Scenario #1 Criteria for inclusion

          1. In the last 2 months, how often did the child have pain or an uncomfortable feeling in
             the upper abdomen above the belly button? If ≥ 8 (or if the combination of #1 and #2
             is ≥8)

          2. In the last 2 months, how often did the child have pain or an uncomfortable feeling in
             the upper abdomen below the belly button? If ≥ 8 (or if the combination of #1 and #2
             is ≥8)

        Scenario #2 Criteria for inclusion 3. In the last 2 months, when the child hurt or felt
        uncomfortable above (below) the belly button, how often did your child miss school or stop
        activities? If #1 and #2 is ≥ 2 (or if the combination of #1 and #2 is ≥2) and #3 is ≥ 25%
        of the time.

        They also have to be at or above cutoff (i.e. TS&gt;= 55) for Beck Youth Inventory (BYI) which
        can be determined by finding the corresponding raw score, gender, and age on Appendix A in
        the BYI manual.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1. Participants with immune disorders will be automatically excluded from this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>9 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>13 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nancy Zucker, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke Center for Developmental Epedimiology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 22, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 17, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nancy Zucker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of the Duke Center for Eating Disorders, Associate Professor in the Department of Psychology &amp; Neuroscience</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Abdominal Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Given the pilot nature of the study, resulting data may not be appropriate for sharing within a larger data repository. We will change this policy if we learn otherwise.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

