<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00370396</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>107046</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00370396</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Immunogenicity Study of a Booster Dose of GSK Biologicals' 10-valent Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine.</brief_title>
  <official_title>To Assess the Safety, Reactogenicity &amp; Immunogenicity of a 4th Dose of GSK Biologicals' Pneumococcal Vaccine or Prevenar™ in Children (12-18 Months) Previously Vaccinated in the Primary Study 105553 With Either Pneumococcal Vaccine or Prevenar™</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the safety, reactogenicity and immunogenicity of a booster dose of
      GSK Biologicals' pneumococcal conjugate vaccine compared to Prevenar™ given at 12-18 mo of
      age to children primed with either pneumococcal vaccine or Prevenar™ in study 105553.
      Antibody persistence will be evaluated at 8-14 mo after completion of the 3-dose immunization
      course in study 105553. The immune response to a booster dose of GSK Biologicals'
      pneumococcal conjugate vaccine will also be evaluated when given at 12-18 mo to subjects not
      primed with GSK Biologicals' vaccine but with Prevenar™.

      The study has 3 groups. 1 group of children primed with GSK Biologicals' pneumococcal
      conjugate vaccine will receive a booster dose of the same vaccine. 2nd group of children
      primed with Prevenar™ will receive a booster dose of Prevenar™ (control group). 3rd group of
      children primed with Prevenar™ will receive a booster dose of GSK Biologicals' pneumococcal
      conjugate vaccine. All children will receive concomitantly a booster dose of DTPa-HBV-IPV/Hib
      vaccine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with rectal temperature above (&gt;) 39.0 degrees Celsius (°C) post booster between the Synflorix-Synflorix and Prevenar-Prevenar groups</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 days (Days 0-3) after the booster vaccination at Month 0 in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007</time_frame>
    <description>Fever was measured as rectal temperature. Assessment of occurrences of rectal temperature &gt; 39.0 °C was performed post administration of the booster dose of pneumococcal vaccine (Synflorix™ or Prevenar™ vaccine) in this study. The analysis was performed on the Total vaccinated cohort, which included all subjects vaccinated in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007, solely on subjects with results available.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with any and Grade 3 solicited local symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 days (Days 0-3) after the booster vaccination at Month 0 in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited local symptoms assessed include pain, redness and swelling. Grade 3 pain was defined as crying when limb was moved/spontaneously painful. Grade 3 swelling/redness was defined as swelling/redness larger than (&gt;) 30 millimeters (mm). &quot;Any&quot; is defined as incidence of the specified symptom regardless of intensity. The analysis was performed on the Total vaccinated cohort, which included all subjects vaccinated in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007, solely on subjects with results available.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with any and any Grade 3 solicited general symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 days (Days 0-3) after the booster vaccination at Month 0 in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited general symptoms assessed include drowsiness, fever (defined as rectal temperature ≥ 38.0°C), irritability, and loss of appetite. Grade 3 drowsiness was defined as drowsiness which prevented normal everyday activities. Grade 3 fever was defined as fever (rectal temperature) above (&gt;) 40.0 degree Celsius (°C). Grade 3 irritability was defined as crying that could not be comforted/preventing normal everyday activities. Grade 3 loss of appetite was defined as the subject not eating at all. &quot;Any&quot; is defined as incidence of the specified symptom regardless of intensity or relationship to study vaccination. The analysis was performed on the Total vaccinated cohort, which included all subjects vaccinated in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007, solely on subjects with results available.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with unsolicited adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 31 days (Day 0-30) after the booster vaccination at Month 0 in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation subject, temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product. &quot;Any&quot; is defined an incidence of an unsolicited AE regardless of intensity or relationship to study vaccination. The analysis was performed on the Total vaccinated cohort, which included all subjects vaccinated in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with serious adverse events (SAEs) during the Active Phase of the study</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the Active Phase of the study, that is, within 31 days (Day 0-30) after the booster vaccination at Month 0 in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007</time_frame>
    <description>An SAE is any untoward medical occurrence that: results in death, is life-threatening, requires hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in disability/incapacity, or may evolve into one of the outcomes listed above. &quot;Any&quot; is defined an incidence of a SAE regardless of intensity/severity . The analysis was performed on the Total vaccinated cohort, which included all subjects vaccinated in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with serious adverse events (SAEs) during the entire study</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period, from Month 0 prior to booster vaccination up to Month 6, end of the ESFU in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007</time_frame>
    <description>An SAE is any untoward medical occurrence that: results in death, is life-threatening, requires hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in disability/incapacity, or may evolve into one of the outcomes listed above. &quot;Any&quot; is defined an incidence of a SAE regardless of intensity/severity. The analysis was performed on the Total vaccinated cohort, which included all subjects vaccinated in this study 10PN-PD-DIT-007, solely on subjects enrolled in the ESFU Phase of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects seroprotected as regards anti-pneumococcal serotypes 1, 4, 5, 6B, 7F, 9V, 14, 18C, 19F and 23F antigens - by 22F-inhibition Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to (PRE) and one month after (Month 1) booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>A seroprotected subject as regards anti-pneumococcal serotype antibody was defined as a subject with anti-pneumococcal serotype antibody concentration above than or equal to (≥) 0.20 microgram per millilitre (μg/mL). Anti-pneumococcal serotypes antibodies assessed were antibodies against pneumococcal serotypes 1, 4, 5, 6B, 7F, 9V, 14, 18C, 19F and 23F (Anti-1, -4, -5, -6B, -7F, 9V, -14, -18C, -19F and -23F). Analysis was performed using the 22F-inhibition Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), using ≥ 0.05 μg/mL as seropositivity cut off. For this endpoint, the analysis was performed on the according-to-protocol cohort for immunogenicity, e. a., evaluable subjects for whom assay results were available for antibodies against at least one study vaccine antigen component after booster vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibody concentrations against pneumococcal serotypes 1, 4, 5, 6B, 7F, 9V, 14, 18C, 19F and 23F (Anti-1, -4, -5, -6B, -7F, 9V, -14, -18C, -19F and -23F) - by 22F-inhibition Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to (PRE) and one month (Month 1) post booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-pneumococcal serotypes 1, 4, 5, 6B, 7F, 9V, 14, 18C, 19F and 23F antibody concentrations (Anti-1, -4, -5, -6B, -7F, -9V, -14, -18C, -19F and -23F) were calculated, expressed as geometric mean concentrations (GMCs), in microgram per millilitre (µg/mL). The seropositivity cut-off for the assay was ≥ 0.05 µg/mL. Antibody concentrations below the cut-off of the assay were given an arbitrary value of half the cut-off for the purpose of GMC calculation. For this endpoint, the analysis was performed on the according-to-protocol cohort for immunogenicity, e. a., evaluable subjects for whom assay results were available for antibodies against at least one study vaccine antigen component after booster vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opsonophagocytic activity (OPA) titers against pneumococcal serotypes 1, 4, 5, 6B, 7F, 9V, 14, 18C, 19F and 23F</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to (PRE) and one month (Month 1) post booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>OPA titers against pneumococcal serotypes 1, 4, 5, 6B, 7F, 9V, 14, 18C, 19F and 23F (Opsono-1, -4, -5, -6B, -7F, -9V, -14, -18C, -19F and -23F) were calculated, expressed as geometric mean titers (GMTs) and tabulated. The seropositivity cut-off for the assay was ≥ 8. Antibody titers below the cut-off of the assay were given an arbitrary value of half the cut-off for the purpose of GMT calculation. For this endpoint, the analysis was performed on the according-to-protocol cohort for immunogenicity, e. a., evaluable subjects for whom assay results were available for antibodies against at least one study vaccine antigen component after booster vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibody concentrations to protein D (Anti-PD) - by Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to (PRE) and one month (Month 1) post booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-protein D (Anti-PD) antibody concentrations by Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) were calculated, expressed as geometric mean concentrations (GMCs) in ELISA unit per milli-liter (EL.U/mL) and tabulated. The seropositivity cut-off for the assay was ≥ 100 EL.U/mL. Antibody concentrations below the cut-off of the assay were given an arbitrary value of half the cut-off for the purpose of GMC calculation. For this endpoint, the analysis was performed on the according-to-protocol cohort for immunogenicity, e. a., evaluable subjects for whom assay results were available for antibodies against at least one study vaccine antigen component after booster vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-polyribosyl ribitol phosphate (anti-PRP) antibody concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to (PRE) and one month (Month 1) post booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-PRP antibody concentrations were calculated, expressed as geometric mean concentrations (GMCs), in microgram per milliliter (µg/mL), and tabulated. The seroprotection cut-off for the assay for the purpose of this endpoint was ≥ 0.15 µg/mL. Antibody concentrations below the cut-off of the assay were given an arbitrary value of half the cut-off for the purpose of GMC calculation. For this endpoint, the analysis was performed on the according-to-protocol cohort for immunogenicity, e. a., evaluable subjects for whom assay results were available for antibodies against at least one study vaccine antigen component after booster vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-pertussis toxoid (Anti-PT), anti- filamentous haemagglutinin (Anti-FHA) and anti-pertactin (Anti-PRN) antibody concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to (PRE) and one month (Month 1) post booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-PT, Anti-FHA and Anti-PRN concentrations measured by Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) were calculated, expressed as geometric mean concentrations (GMCs) in ELISA unit per milli-liter (EL.U/mL) and tabulated. The seropositivity cut-off for the assay was ≥ 5 EL.U/mL. Antibody concentrations below the cut-off of the assay were given an arbitrary value of half the cut-off for the purpose of GMC calculation. For this endpoint, the analysis was performed on the according-to-protocol cohort for immunogenicity, e. a., evaluable subjects for whom assay results were available for antibodies against at least one study vaccine antigen component after booster vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-diphtheria (Anti-D) and anti-tetanus toxoids (Anti-TT) antibody concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to (PRE) and one month (Month 1) post booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-D and Anti-TT antibody concentrations were calculated, expressed as geometric mean concentrations (GMCs), in International units per milliliter (IU/mL), and tabulated. The seropositivity cut-off for the assay was ≥ 0.1 IU/mL. Antibody concentrations below the cut-off of the assay were given an arbitrary value of half the cut-off for the purpose of GMC calculation. For this endpoint, the analysis was performed on the according-to-protocol cohort for immunogenicity, e. a., evaluable subjects for whom assay results were available for antibodies against at least one study vaccine antigen component after booster vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-hepatitis B surface antigen (HBs) antibody concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to (PRE) and one month (Month 1) post booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-HBs antibody concentrations were calculated, expressed as geometric mean concentrations (GMCs), in milli-International unit per milliliter (IU/mL), and tabulated. The seropositivity cut-off for the assay was ≥ 10 mIU/mL. Antibody concentrations below the cut-off of the assay were given an arbitrary value of half the cut-off for the purpose of GMC calculation. For this endpoint, the analysis was performed on the according-to-protocol cohort for immunogenicity, e. a., evaluable subjects for whom assay results were available for antibodies against at least one study vaccine antigen component after booster vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-polio type 1, 2 and 3 (Anti-Polio 1, 2 and 3) antibody titers</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to (PRE) and one month (Month 1) post booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-Polio 1, 2 and 3 antibody titers were calculated, expressed as geometric mean titers (GMTs) and tabulated. The seroprotection cut-off for the assay was ≥ 8. Antibody titers below the cut-off of the assay were given an arbitrary value of half the cut-off for the purpose of GMT calculation. For this endpoint, the analysis was performed on the according-to-protocol cohort for immunogenicity, e. a., evaluable subjects for whom assay results were available for antibodies against at least one study vaccine antigen component after booster vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects booster (BST) responder to pertussis toxoid (PT), filamentous haemagglutinin (FHA) and pertactin antigens</measure>
    <time_frame>One month (Month 1) post booster vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>A BST responder to PT, FHA and PRN antigens was defined as a subject with the appearance of antibodies in subjects who were seronegative prior to the booster vaccination or at least 2-fold increase of pre-booster vaccination antibody concentrations in subjects who were seropositive prior to the booster vaccination. A seropositive/seronegative subject as regards Anti-PT/-FHA/ -PRN antibodies was defined as a subject with anti-PT/-FHA/ -PRN antibody concentrations ≥ 5 Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent assay (ELISA) unit per milli-liter (EL.U/mL)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Infections, Streptococcal</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>10 valent pneumococcal conjugate (vaccine)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  a healthy male or female, 12 to 18 months of age at the time of vaccination, who
             received at least one dose of either pneumococcal conjugate vaccine or Prevenar™
             during study 105553 and with written informed consent obtained from the
             parent/guardian of the subject.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  use of any investigational or non-registered drug or vaccine other than the study
             vaccine within 30 days preceding the vaccination, or planned use during the entire
             study period (active phase and safety follow-up).

          -  Planned administration/ administration of a vaccine not foreseen by the study protocol
             during the period starting one month before vaccination up to Visit 2.

          -  Administration of any additional pneumococcal vaccine or DTPa-combined vaccine since
             end of study 105553. Children with a history of seizures or neurological disease,
             allergic disease, immunosuppressive or immunodeficient condition.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Espoo</city>
        <zip>02100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <zip>00100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <zip>00930</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jarvenpaa</city>
        <zip>04400</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jyväskylä</city>
        <zip>40100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kokkola</city>
        <zip>67100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kotka</city>
        <zip>48600</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuopio</city>
        <zip>70100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lahti</city>
        <zip>15140</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oulu</city>
        <zip>90100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pori</city>
        <zip>28120</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seinajoki</city>
        <zip>60100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampere</city>
        <zip>33200</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Turku</city>
        <zip>20520</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vantaa</city>
        <zip>01300</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vantaa</city>
        <zip>01600</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bernay</city>
        <zip>27300</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Colombes</city>
        <zip>92701</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Courbevoie</city>
        <zip>92400</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Créteil</city>
        <zip>94000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dax</city>
        <zip>40100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Draguignan</city>
        <zip>83300</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essey les Nancy</city>
        <zip>54270</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Le Havre</city>
        <zip>76600</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maromme</city>
        <zip>76150</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <zip>06300</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nogent-sur-Marne</city>
        <zip>94130</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75019</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen</city>
        <zip>76000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Quentin</city>
        <zip>02100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bydgoszcz</city>
        <zip>85-021</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Debica</city>
        <zip>39-200</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Krakow</city>
        <zip>31-202</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Olesnica</city>
        <zip>56-400</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poznan</city>
        <zip>61-709</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Siemianowice Slaskie</city>
        <zip>41-103</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</url>
    <description>Researchers can use this site to request access to anonymised patient level data and/or supporting documents from clinical studies to conduct further research.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chevallier B, Vesikari T, Brzostek J, Knuf M, Bermal N, Aristegui J, Borys D, Cleerbout J, Lommel P, Schuerman L. Safety and reactogenicity of the 10-valent pneumococcal non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae protein D conjugate vaccine (PHiD-CV) when coadministered with routine childhood vaccines. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2009 Apr;28(4 Suppl):S109-18. doi: 10.1097/INF.0b013e318199f62d. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19325447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knuf M, Szenborn L, Moro M, Petit C, Bermal N, Bernard L, Dieussaert I, Schuerman L. Immunogenicity of routinely used childhood vaccines when coadministered with the 10-valent pneumococcal non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae protein D conjugate vaccine (PHiD-CV). Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2009 Apr;28(4 Suppl):S97-S108. doi: 10.1097/INF.0b013e318199f61b. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19325452</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vesikari T, Wysocki J, Chevallier B, Karvonen A, Czajka H, Arsène JP, Lommel P, Dieussaert I, Schuerman L. Immunogenicity of the 10-valent pneumococcal non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae protein D conjugate vaccine (PHiD-CV) compared to the licensed 7vCRM vaccine. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2009 Apr;28(4 Suppl):S66-76. doi: 10.1097/INF.0b013e318199f8ef.</citation>
    <PMID>19325449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wysocki J, Tejedor JC, Grunert D, Konior R, Garcia-Sicilia J, Knuf M, Bernard L, Dieussaert I, Schuerman L. Immunogenicity of the 10-valent pneumococcal non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae protein D conjugate vaccine (PHiD-CV) when coadministered with different neisseria meningitidis serogroup C conjugate vaccines. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2009 Apr;28(4 Suppl):S77-88. doi: 10.1097/INF.0b013e318199f609.</citation>
    <PMID>19325450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 30, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 3, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 3, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Streptococcus pneumonia, pneumococcal conjugate vaccine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Streptococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heptavalent Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Patient-level data for this study will be made available through www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com following the timelines and process described on this site.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>107046</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>107046</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Individual Participant Data Set</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>107046</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Informed Consent Form</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>107046</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Clinical Study Report</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>107046</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Study Protocol</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>107046</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Dataset Specification</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>August 31, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>March 30, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>May 15, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

