<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00372177</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Biotectid POC EP 1645</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>EP 1645</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00372177</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Use of Anti-CD4 Monoclonal Antibody (mAb)-Fragment for the Imaging of Chronic Inflammation in Patients With Active Rheumatoid Arthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Use of Anti-CD4 mAb-Fragment for the Imaging of Chronic Inflammation in Patients With Active Rheumatoid Arthritis (an Open Proof of Concept Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Biotectid GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Technische Universität Dresden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Leipzig</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Biotectid GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is a disease with a large economic impact due to the long lasting
      disabling nature of the disease. Furthermore, diagnosis of the disease is difficult and only
      a scheme with different symptoms is used to diagnose rheumatoid arthritis, often only by
      probability.

      Due to the fact that effective disease modifying pharmacological treatment is available and
      should be started early in established cases of RA, in combination with the adverse effect
      potential of these substances (e.g. methotrexate), a fast reliable diagnostic tool to
      diagnose rheumatoid arthritis would be highly appreciated by the medical community and the
      patients. Furthermore, for invasive treatments (surgery, puncture), an imaging method to
      display the activity pattern in different joints would be a major advantage.

      For the evaluation of the effectiveness of pharmacological therapy in rheumatoid arthritis,
      up to now, radiological measurements of the destruction process of the joints are used. This
      method has the disadvantage that it is time consuming insofar as changes in the radiological
      images must occur. It allows only an evaluation if the joints are destructed (which should be
      excluded by the new therapy regimen). Again, a quantifiable method for the determination of
      the effects of new therapeutic approaches would be highly appreciated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The substance will be used as iv injection due to the protein nature of the antibody and, to
      ensure a fast distribution within the body. The study will be performed as an open clinical
      trial due to the fact that the applied radiation has to be documented; the use of &quot;placebo&quot;
      radiation would be unethical.

      It is expected, that the new antibody fragment with its radioactive linkage will display an
      image of the activity distribution of the disease. Due to the fact that only patients with
      active disease have to be imaged and, to allow for comparison of the activity and the
      clinical distribution of the disease, this proof of concept study (phase I study) will be
      performed in patients with active disease. Healthy volunteers could not display an activity
      pattern of the disease. Furthermore, it seems to be unethical to use volunteers for studies
      with radioactivity with such a risk/benefit ratio (radiation risks vs. missing chance of
      display of tissue distribution) in a proof of concept study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>safety and tolerability of this diagnostic agent</measure>
    <time_frame>duration of study</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>endpoint for the proof of concept will be the number of patients needed to obtain a series of equal results</measure>
    <time_frame>duration of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <condition>Polyarthritis</condition>
  <condition>Rheumatism</condition>
  <condition>Autoimmune Disease</condition>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EP1645</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single-Dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fab-fragment of Anti-human CD4</intervention_name>
    <description>Sterile lyophilized Powder for Preparation of a Solution and sterile labelling Buffer labelling with Tc99m-Pertechnetat Intravenous injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>EP1645</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female subjects above 50 years of age

          -  Suffering from joint pain which is due to active rheumatoid arthritis

          -  Obvious signs of inflammation in at least one joint (e.g. swelling, erythema, or local
             elevated temperature)

          -  Otherwise healthy

          -  Informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients 80 years and older

          -  Clinically significant disease of the cardiovascular system, respiratory system,
             hepato-biliary system or central nervous system (CNS)

          -  Excretory hepatic or renal insufficiency

          -  Regular intake of any drug, except for hormone replacement therapy in females

          -  Previous administration of xenogenous proteins

          -  History of anaphylactic reaction to any drug administered by a parenteral pathway

          -  Previous participation in a radiopharmaceutical drug trial (unless the effective dose
             acquired by participation in the current trial will remain below 10 mSv)

          -  Participation in any clinical drug trial within 3 months prior to enrolment

          -  Women of child-bearing potential (child-bearing potential to be ruled out by one of
             the following: at least 2 years past menopause, hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy,
             or bilateral tubal ligation)

          -  Long term medication with strong antiphlogistic agents/pain killers such as
             methotrexate, corticoids, or immunosuppressants prior to enrolment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Osama Sabri, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinic and Policlinic for Nuclear Medicine, Medical Faculty, University of Leipzig, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinic and Policlinic for Nuclear Medicine, Medical faculty, University of Leipzig</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leipzig</city>
        <state>Saxony</state>
        <zip>04103</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.biotectid.de</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://nuklmed.uniklinikum-leipzig.de/</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 5, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 5, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 6, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 26, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 26, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Biotectid GmbH</name_title>
    <organization>Biotectid GmbH</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>monoclonal antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>diagnostics</keyword>
  <keyword>RA</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunoglobulins</keyword>
  <keyword>molecular target</keyword>
  <keyword>Tc99m-pertechnetate</keyword>
  <keyword>Fab-fragment of Anti-human CD4</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiopharmaceutical</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic inflammatory diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>active Rheumatoid Arthritis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autoimmune Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rheumatic Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulin Fab Fragments</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

