<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02400138</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RTS-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02400138</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Home-based Respiratory Training After Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Home-based Respiratory Training After Stroke: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federal University of Minas Gerais</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal University of Minas Gerais</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Weakness of the respiratory muscles demonstrated by individuals with stroke, may generate
      important symptoms, such as fatigue and dyspnea. Since adequate strength of the inspiratory
      and expiratory muscles is required, mainly when performing physical activities,
      rehabilitation interventions for stroke subjects should include respiratory training. This
      study will test the hypothesis that home-based combined training of the inspiratory and
      expiratory muscles is effective in improving strength of the inspiratory and expiratory
      muscles, endurance of the inspiratory muscles, dyspnea, walking capacity, and ocurrence of
      respiratory complications after stroke. For this clinical trial, people after stroke will be
      randomly allocated into either experimental or control/sham groups. The experimental group
      will undertake training of the inspiratory plus expiratory muscles with the Orygen Dual Valve
      device, regulated at 50% of the subjects' maximal inspiratory and expíratory pressure values,
      seven times/week over eight weeks during 40 minutes/day. The control group will undertake the
      same protocol, but the participants will receive the devices without resistance. At baseline,
      post intervention, and four weeks after the cessation of the intervention, researchers
      blinded to group allocations will collect the following outcome measures: maximal inspiratory
      and expiratory pressures, inspiratory endurance, dyspnea, walking capacity, and ocurrence of
      respiratory complications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Weakness of the respiratory muscles demonstrated by individuals with stroke, may
      generate important symptoms, such as fatigue and dyspnea. Since adequate strength of the
      inspiratory and expiratory muscles is required, mainly when performing physical activities,
      rehabilitation interventions for stroke subjects should include respiratory training.

      Aim: This study will test the hypothesis that home-based combined inspiratory muscular
      training (IMT) plus expiratory muscular training (EMT) program is effective in improving
      strength of the inspiratory and expiratory muscles, endurance of the inspiratory muscles,
      dyspnea, walking capacity, and ocurrence of respiratory complications after stroke.

      Design: For this prospective, double-blinded, randomized clinical trial, people after stroke
      will be randomly allocated into either experimental or control/sham groups. The experimental
      group will undertake training of the inspiratory plus expiratory muscles with the Orygen Dual
      Valve, regulated at 50% of the subjects' maximal inspiratory pressure (MIP) and maximal
      expiratory pressure (MEP) values, seven times/week over eight weeks during 40 minutes/day.
      The control group will undertake the same protocol, but the participants will receive the
      devices without resistance. At baseline, post intervention, and four weeks after the
      cessation of the intervention, researchers blinded to group allocations will collect all
      outcome measures.

      Study outcomes: Primary outcomes will be MIP. Secondary outcomes will include MEP,
      inspiratory endurance, dyspnea, walking capacity, and ocurrence of respiratory complications.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 15, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal inspiratory pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (week 0), after training (week 8) and one-month follow-up (weeks 12)</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in maximal inspiratory pressures will be assessed by a digital manovacuometer, following previously described protocols.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal expiratory pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (week 0), after training (week 8) and one-month follow-up (weeks 12)</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in maximal expiratory pressures will be assessed by a digital manovacuometer, following previously described protocols.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inspiratory endurance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (week 0), after training (week 8) and one-month follow-up (weeks 12)</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in inspiratory endurance will be assessed by the powerbreathe device, following previously described protocols.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dyspnea</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (week 0), after training (week 8) and one-month follow-up (weeks 12)</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in dyspnea will be assessed by the Medical Research Council Scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ocurrence of respiratory complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (week 0), after training (week 8) and one-month follow-up (weeks 12)</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in ocurrence of respiratory complications will be assessed by asking the participants, whether and how often they were admitted to a hospital, due to respiratory reasons.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Walking capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (week 0), after training (week 8) and one-month follow-up (weeks 12)</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in walking capacity will be evaluated by the six-minute walking test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Respiratory training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Respiratory training will include training of the inspiratory and expiratory muscles seven times per week over eight weeks, during 40 minutes per day, divided into two 20-min sessions (morning and afternoon). Each 20-min session comprised 4-min sets of respiratory training, followed by 1-min rest between the sets. The training program will be carried-out with the Orygen Dual Valve device, regulated at 50% of the subjects' maximal inspiratory and expiratory pressure values. Once a week, the treating physiotherapist performed a home visit, measured the current values of inspiratory and expiratory strength, and progressed the load to 50% of the new values.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control/sham group will underwent exactly the same protocol and weekly monitoring at home, but the participants will receive the devices without resistance of the spring, which will be also concealed. The control group will also attend the weekly sessions and undergo the same procedures, except for the load adjustments. If the training proves to be effective, the control subjects will be informed and have the choice to receive the training with proper loads.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Respiratory training</intervention_name>
    <description>Respiratory training will include training of the inspiratory and expiratory muscle seven times per week over eight weeks, during 40 minutes, divided into two 20-min sessions (morning and afternoon). Each 20-min session comprised 4-min sets of respiratory training, followed by 1-min rest between the sets. The training program will be carried-out with the Orygen Dual Valve regulated at 50% of the subjects' maximal inspiratory and expiratory pressure values. Once a week, the treating physiotherapist performed a home visit, measured the current values of inspiratory and expiratory strength, and progressed the load to 50% of the new values.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Respiratory training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <description>The control/sham group will underwent exactly the same protocol and weekly monitoring at home, but the participants will receive the devices without resistance of the spring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Stroke survivors will be eligible if they: were &gt;3 months and &lt;5 years after their last
        episode of stroke; were &gt;20 years of age; their maximal inspiratory pressure was &lt;80 cmH2O
        or maximal expiratory pressure was &lt;90 cmH2O [18]; were not undertaking any respiratory
        training; and were able to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects will be excluded if they had cognitive deficits, facial palsy, associated
        respiratory diseases, or unstable conditions which might prevent measurement or training;
        or undergone thoracic or abdominal surgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fatima Rodrigues-de-Paula, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Minas Gerais</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Physical Therapy, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belo Horizonte</city>
        <state>MG</state>
        <zip>31270-901</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NeuroGroup Laboratory</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belo Horizonte</city>
        <state>MG</state>
        <zip>31270-901</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sutbeyaz ST, Koseoglu F, Inan L, Coskun O. Respiratory muscle training improves cardiopulmonary function and exercise tolerance in subjects with subacute stroke: a randomized controlled trial. Clin Rehabil. 2010 Mar;24(3):240-50. doi: 10.1177/0269215509358932. Epub 2010 Feb 15.</citation>
    <PMID>20156979</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Britto RR, Rezende NR, Marinho KC, Torres JL, Parreira VF, Teixeira-Salmela LF. Inspiratory muscular training in chronic stroke survivors: a randomized controlled trial. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2011 Feb;92(2):184-90. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2010.09.029.</citation>
    <PMID>21272713</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 25, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal University of Minas Gerais</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Luci Fuscaldi Teixeira-Salmela</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Titular professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

