<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02401607</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHU-0228</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02401607</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SEEK Study - Study on Emergency Health Care Workers' Job Strain Evaluated by Karasek Questionnaire</brief_title>
  <acronym>SEEK</acronym>
  <official_title>SEEK Study - Study on Emergency Health Care Workers' Job Strain Evaluated by Karasek Questionnaire</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Clermont-Ferrand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Association des Médecins des Urgences de Clermont-Ferrand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>PRES Clermont University of Auvergne, Occupational Medicine, Faculty of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Clermont-Ferrand</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Karasek Job Content Questionnaire includes 2 dimensions: the psychological demands at
      work, and the latitude decision. The combination of these two characteristics explains the
      degree of exposure of a worker to stress. Indeed, a worker is under pressure (job-strain)
      when workload is important and autonomy is poor. The Sumer study was conducted in France on
      25,000 employees and classified occupations taking into account psychological demands and
      latitude decision of occupations. No publication on emergency physicians' responses to
      Karasek questionnaire is referenced, even though theirs exposures to burnout is known. A
      preliminary study on 19 emergency physicians of the CHU of Clermont-Ferrand illustrates
      concretely this &quot;extraordinary situation&quot;, with the lowest decision latitude and the highest
      psychological demands ever recorded. Moreover, there are no data on results at the Karasek
      questionnaire under different conditions within the same participant, i.e. responses to the
      Karasek questionnaire is supposed similar and reflect a constant perception of work.
      Additionally, several biomarkers of stress have been proposed, in particular DHEAS due to its
      long half-life of 16 hours. To our knowledge, the relationship between biomarkers of stress
      and tension at work with Karasek model has never been studied, like this relations with other
      wellness questionnaires. Comparisons between emergency health care workers are also lacking.

      Our study proposes to evaluate the perception of emergency medicine with Karasek
      questionnaire, and to assess possible changes of its perception and in biological response
      between two conditions: after a night shift and on a control day (workday), in emergency
      health care workers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic stress at work is a public health problem increasing morbidity and mortality.
      Emergency physicians is particularly an at risk population. Indeed, their work is a complex
      interaction between stress due to life-threatening emergencies, the lack of sleep and
      accumulated fatigue.

      A way of measuring stress at work is the use of self-reported psychological questionnaire.
      Among them, the Job control demand model from Karasek is widely used to evaluate psychosocial
      factors at work. The Karasek job strain model has been assessed in 25 000 workers in the
      Sumer study and allowed to classify the main types of occupations. However, no data regarding
      emergency physicians scores at the Karasek questionnaire were available, even though burnout
      exposure is a well-known problematic among health care workers. This absence is particularly
      unfortunate as emergency physicians often needs to deals with life threatening emergency in a
      short amount of time, following regularly long and craving shifts. A preliminary study with a
      low sample size reported in concrete terms the atypical &quot;out of limit&quot; situations of
      emergency physicians, with a decision latitude among the lowest and the highest psychological
      demand ever reported. Moreover, variation of stress at work has been linked with professional
      experiences. Karasek questionnaire is supposed to assess a long-term stable perception of
      work, despite the absence of study comparing Karasek scores within different conditions in
      the same participant. It is also important to explore protective factors that might help
      alleviate perceived stress and that are quite easy to integrate into medical organizations or
      in daily lifestyle.

      Finally, several biomarkers of stress have been proposed. Among them, our team previously
      highlighted the potential of DHEAS to assess stress, due to its stability (steroid) and its
      long half-life of 16 hours. To our knowledge, the relationships between biomarkers of stress
      and the Karasek job strain model have never been investigated. Comparisons between emergency
      health care workers are also lacking.

      Therefore, the general aim of this study is to enhance psychological well-being in emergency
      physicians. The primary objective is to verify our preliminary findings at Karasek scores on
      a large sample size of emergency physicians. The secondary objectives are to evaluate whether
      there is a change in perception of work both at short-term (on leave and after a 24-hour
      shift) and long-term (with professional experience). We will further explore its
      relationships with some biomarkers of stress and protective factors. Moreover, we aim to
      compare emergency health care workers specificity.

      Questionnaires and saliva collection will be performed twice: at the beginning of a day work
      and at the end of a night work. Both measures will be recorded at the same time within each
      participant, between 6.30 am and 8.30 am depending of the health care workers. The time
      required by participant is evaluated to about 15min each time.

      The same measures will be repeated every year during 5 years to assess long term changes in
      subjective and objective measures of stress.

      The population description will be achieved with descriptive statistics. Continuous variables
      will be presented as mean and standard deviation, under the normality of distribution
      condition (Shapiro-Wilk needed).

      The primary analysis will be mainly descriptive and will express (as a quantitative and
      categorical variables) the perception scores of emergency physicians work according to the
      Karasek questionnaire, for each dimensions composing the score (decision latitude,
      psychological demands and social support).

      The evolution of the Karasek questionnaire score, obtained for each dimension, will be tested
      with a paired two-sample emergency physician's test (or nonparametric Wilcoxon test if
      necessary). Linear regression models or aleatory effects models (as described by Klar and
      Darlington, 2004, in Statistics in Medicine) will eventualy complete these analyzes. This
      will permit, with multivariate analyzes and the introduction of covariates, to seek for
      possible explanatory factors of the Karasek score and its evolution. The same process will be
      used for quantitative parameters that will be collected.

      All statistical analyses will be performed as bilateral tests with a p &lt;0.05 considered as
      significant. Statistical analyzes will be performed using STATA 12 software (Stata
      Corporation, College Station).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Karasek questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamilton anxiety scale</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maslach Burn-out Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital anxiety and depression scale</measure>
    <time_frame>at day 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Health Care Workers</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Karasek questionnaire</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        health care workers
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any health care workers from any emergency department of France

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frederic DUTHEIL</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Clermont-Ferrand</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patrick LACARIN</last_name>
    <phone>04 73 75 11 95</phone>
    <email>placarin@chu-clermontferrand.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Clermont-Ferrand</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clermont-Ferrand</city>
        <zip>63003</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patrick LACARIN</last_name>
      <phone>04 73 75 11 95</phone>
      <email>placarin@chu-clermontferrand.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 30, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 28, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 28, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 29, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stress</keyword>
  <keyword>emergency physicians</keyword>
  <keyword>health care workers</keyword>
  <keyword>biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>burn-out</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

