<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02407834</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>mestradopt2013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02407834</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Hygiene Solutions on Denture Biofilm</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Evaluation of an Experimental Solution Based on Ricinus Communis Compared to Sodium Hypochlorite for Denture Cleansing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This clinical trial evaluated Ricinus communis and sodium hypochlorite solutions in different
      concentrations for denture cleanliness, regarding biofilm removal capacity, remission of
      atrophic chronic candidiasis, degree of patient satisfaction and antimicrobial action against
      specific microorganism. Sixty-four denture wearers with absence (n=40) or presence of
      Candidiasis (n=24) were selected and oriented to brush their dentures with a specific brush
      and neutral soap for 3 minutes, 3 times a day and immerse them, once a day, in hygiene
      solutions (0.25% sodium hypochlorite - S1 and 0.5% - S2, 10% R. communis - S3; Saline - S4:
      control) during 20 minutes, for 7 days. The solutions were used in a randomized, double blind
      and cross form with washout periods. To quantify biofilm with software ImageTool 3.0, the
      inner surface was disclosed (1% neutral red) and photographed at the end of each period. The
      Candidiasis remission was assessed by scores before and after the use of solutions. Patient
      satisfaction was assessed by questionnaire. Antimicrobial activity was determined by Colony
      Forming Units (CFU) counts of Streptococcus mutans, Candida spp., and gram-negative
      microorganisms. For collecting biofilm, internal surface of each maxillary complete denture
      was brushed with saline solution, and the biofilm suspension obtained. After serial dilutions
      (100 - 10-3), 50 uL aliquots were seeded in Petri dishes containing Mitis salivarius agar
      base, CHROMagar Candida® and MacConkey agar for detecting S. mutans, Candida spp., or
      gram-negative microorganisms, respectively. After incubation, colonies were counted, and
      values in CFU/mL were calculated. Biofilm removal was analyzed as a split-plot with two
      variation factors: inflammation and solutions. The candidiasis remission was analyzed after
      adjustment using multinomial logistic regression. Logistic regression analysis and compound
      symmetry was adopted for patient satisfaction. The antimicrobial action was analyzed with
      Friedman´s test. Antimicrobial action data were processed after transformation - log10 (CFU +
      1) - and were analyzed by Friedman test (α = 0.05).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sixty-four denture wearers with (n=24) and without Candidiasis (n=40) were enrolled and
      instructed to brush and immerse their dentures in 4 different storage solutions (S1: 0.25%
      sodium hypochlorite; S2: 0.5% sodium hypochlorite; S3: 10% R. communis; and S4:
      Saline/Control). The interventions were randomly performed in a double blind and crossover
      format with washout periods. After 7 days of brushing and storage, the biofilm formed in the
      inner surfaces of dentures was disclosed and photographed to quantification. Candidiasis
      remission was assessed by scores and the patient satisfaction by a questionnaire.
      Antimicrobial activity of the solutions was determined by counting the Colony Forming Units
      (CFUs) of Streptococcus mutans, Candida spp., and gram-negative microorganisms. For
      collecting biofilm, each complete upper denture was placed in a Petri dish, its internal
      surface was brushed (Tek brush) with saline solution for 2 min, and the biofilm suspension
      was transferred to a test tube. After serial dilutions (100 - 10-3), 50 uL aliquots were
      seeded in Petri dishes containing Mitis salivarius agar base, CHROMagar Candida® and
      MacConkey agar for detecting S. mutans, Candida spp., or gram-negative microorganisms,
      respectively. After incubation, colonies were counted, and values in CFU/mL were calculated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>biofilm removal capacity using Image Tool software</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>antimicrobial action against specific microorganisms by Colony Forming Units counts</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>remission of atrophic chronic candidiasis using multinomial logistic regression analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>degree of patient satisfaction assessed by specific questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Stomatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>S1 - 0.25% sodium hypochlorite</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Brushing with specific brush and neutral soap, three times a day. After, immesion in 0.25% sodium hypochlorite during 20 minutes, once a day. This protocol was used during 7 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>S2 - 0.5% sodium hypochlorite</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Brushing with specific brush and neutral soap, three times a day. After, immesion in 0.5% sodium hypochlorite during 20 minutes, once a day.This protocol was used during 7 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>S3 - 10% Ricinus communis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Brushing with specific brush and neutral soap, three times a day. After, immesion in 10% Ricinus communis solution during 20 minutes, once a day. This protocol was used during 7 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>S4 - saline solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Brushing with specific brush and neutral soap, three times a day. After, immesion in saline solution during 20 minutes, once a day. This protocol was used during 7 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>S1</intervention_name>
    <description>Immersion in 0.25% sodium hypochlorite for 20 minutes, during 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>S1 - 0.25% sodium hypochlorite</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>0.25% sodium hypochlorite</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>S2</intervention_name>
    <description>Immersion in 0.5% sodium hypochlorite for 20 minutes, during 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>S2 - 0.5% sodium hypochlorite</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>0.5% sodium hypochlorite</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>S3</intervention_name>
    <description>Immersion in 10% Ricinus communis for 20 minutes, during 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>S3 - 10% Ricinus communis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>10% ricinus communis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>S4</intervention_name>
    <description>Immersion in Saline solution for 20 minutes, during 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>S4 - saline solution</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>saline solution</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Edentulous that make regular use of dentures in acrylic resin for at least one year
             with the presence of biofilm.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Problems in adapting, reline, or repair fractures

          -  Patients with limited communication or collaboration as the following recommended
             protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cláudia Helena Lovato da Silva</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Cláudia Helena Lovato da Silva</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biofilms</keyword>
  <keyword>Dentures</keyword>
  <keyword>Denture Cleansers</keyword>
  <keyword>Castor Oil</keyword>
  <keyword>Stomatitis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stomatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sodium Hypochlorite</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eusol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

