<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02401152</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LOGP-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02401152</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Low-osmolaric Glucose Polymer Drink for Gastric Distress and Running Performance</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of a Potato Based Low-osmolaric Glucose Polymer Drink on Gastric Distress and Running Performance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>InnoSportNL</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Avebe U.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>InnoSportNL</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to investigate whether two newly developed sports drink will
      affect gastric distress (GD) and running performance (RP) compared to an iso-caloric control
      drink both in a short and longer distance run. Furthermore, the effect of the newly developed
      sports drinks on gastric emptying will be investigated.

      The study will consist of 3 parts. Firstly, a randomized cross-over design is used for the
      short distance run and the effects on GD and RP. Secondly, a parallel design is used to study
      the effects of the drinks on GD and RP during a longer distance run. Thirdly, the gastric
      emptying tests will be performed in a randomized cross-over design. Participants will be
      asked to fill in questionnaire on the gastric distress they experience. 40 participants will
      be enrolled to participate in part 1 and part 2. 10 out of 40 will participate in part 3 of
      the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived degree of gastric complaints after consumption of sports drink and running exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 10-20 minutes for the 3 km and 40-60 minutes for the 10 km.</time_frame>
    <description>Quantified as the score for the perceived degree of experiencing 7 different gastric complaints on a VAS. The total score for gastric distress and the scores for each different gastric complaint will be analysed separately for the three different time points (before, during and after exercise). The total score is the sum of the scores on the separate complaints.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Finishing time during 10 km running event</measure>
    <time_frame>Depending on the speed of the participant, an average time frame of 40-60 minutes after starting the run is expected.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of gastric emptying</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour after ingestion of sports drink</time_frame>
    <description>During 1 hour after ingestion of the sports drink, subjects will breath into a specific bag which will be analysed for the presence of C13 on specific time points. The decrease of C13 in the exhaled air is a measurement for gastric emptying time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood glucose levels</measure>
    <time_frame>During 1 hour after ingestion of sports drink</time_frame>
    <description>On specific time points within 1 hour after ingestion of the sports drink, blood glucose levels will be determined to calculate area under the curve for the different sport drinks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastric Distress</condition>
  <condition>Running Performance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sports drink containing maltodextrin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sports drink 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sports drink with a specific source of carbohydrates (CHO).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sports drink 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sports drink with a specific source of CHO.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sports drink 1</intervention_name>
    <description>Sports drink with a specific source of CHO.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sports drink 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sports drink 2</intervention_name>
    <description>Sports drink with a specific source of CHO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sports drink 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>iso-caloric sports drink with maltodextrin as CHO source</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 18 and 35 years

          -  A BMI between 18.5 and 25 kg*m-2

          -  Intermediate level runners with at least 1 year of running experience, performing
             moderate to intensive running exercise consistently (two or more times per week for a
             minimum of 30 minutes each time)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Having diseases, such as diabetes, kidney, liver, lung, or bowel disease,
             cardiovascular disease, or mental illness

          -  Abuse of alcohol (&gt;20 alcoholic consumptions per week)

          -  Use of medication and/or drugs

          -  Smoking/having smoked in the last six months

          -  Participating in any scientific intervention providing a treatment potentially
             interfering with this study's treatment (to be decided by the researchers)

          -  Allergic to one of the components present in the drinks, including milk (incl.
             lactose), soy and gluten
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeroen Wouters, Dr. Ir.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>InnoSportlab Papendal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arnhem</city>
        <state>Gelderland</state>
        <zip>6816VD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leiper JB, Aulin KP, Söderlund K. Improved gastric emptying rate in humans of a unique glucose polymer with gel-forming properties. Scand J Gastroenterol. 2000 Nov;35(11):1143-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11145284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takii H, Takii Nagao Y, Kometani T, Nishimura T, Nakae T, Kuriki T, Fushiki T. Fluids containing a highly branched cyclic dextrin influence the gastric emptying rate. Int J Sports Med. 2005 May;26(4):314-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15900642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stephens FB, Roig M, Armstrong G, Greenhaff PL. Post-exercise ingestion of a unique, high molecular weight glucose polymer solution improves performance during a subsequent bout of cycling exercise. J Sports Sci. 2008 Jan 15;26(2):149-54.</citation>
    <PMID>17852670</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rehrer NJ, Brouns F, Beckers EJ, ten Hoor F, Saris WH. Gastric emptying with repeated drinking during running and bicycling. Int J Sports Med. 1990 Jun;11(3):238-43.</citation>
    <PMID>2373584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moses FM. The effect of exercise on the gastrointestinal tract. Sports Med. 1990 Mar;9(3):159-72. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2180030</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Oliveira EP, Burini RC. Food-dependent, exercise-induced gastrointestinal distress. J Int Soc Sports Nutr. 2011 Sep 28;8:12. doi: 10.1186/1550-2783-8-12.</citation>
    <PMID>21955383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ploutz-Snyder L, Foley J, Ploutz-Snyder R, Kanaley J, Sagendorf K, Meyer R. Gastric gas and fluid emptying assessed by magnetic resonance imaging. Eur J Appl Physiol Occup Physiol. 1999 Feb;79(3):212-20.</citation>
    <PMID>10048625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rodriguez NR, DiMarco NM, Langley S; American Dietetic Association; Dietitians of Canada; American College of Sports Medicine: Nutrition and Athletic Performance. Position of the American Dietetic Association, Dietitians of Canada, and the American College of Sports Medicine: Nutrition and athletic performance. J Am Diet Assoc. 2009 Mar;109(3):509-27. Erratum in: J Am Diet Assoc. 2013 Dec;113(12):1759.</citation>
    <PMID>19278045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Dietetic Association; Dietitians of Canada; American College of Sports Medicine, Rodriguez NR, Di Marco NM, Langley S. American College of Sports Medicine position stand. Nutrition and athletic performance. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2009 Mar;41(3):709-31. doi: 10.1249/MSS.0b013e31890eb86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19225360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murray R, Bartoli W, Stofan J, Horn M, Eddy D. A comparison of the gastric emptying characteristics of selected sports drinks. Int J Sport Nutr. 1999 Sep;9(3):263-74.</citation>
    <PMID>10477362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maughan RJ, Leiper JB. Limitations to fluid replacement during exercise. Can J Appl Physiol. 1999 Apr;24(2):173-87. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10198143</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowlands DS, Wallis GA, Shaw C, Jentjens RL, Jeukendrup AE. Glucose polymer molecular weight does not affect exogenous carbohydrate oxidation. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2005 Sep;37(9):1510-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16177602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhu Y, Hsu WH, Hollis JH. The impact of food viscosity on eating rate, subjective appetite, glycemic response and gastric emptying rate. PLoS One. 2013 Jun 20;8(6):e67482. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0067482. Print 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>23818981</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siegel JA, Krevsky B, Maurer AH, Charkes ND, Fisher RS, Malmud LS. Scintigraphic evaluation of gastric emptying: are radiolabeled solids necessary? Clin Nucl Med. 1989 Jan;14(1):40-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2714039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang TM, Passaro E Jr, Shain LR, Chen WL. Physical properties of starch meals in vivo and in vitro and their influence on gastric emptying and oral glucose tolerance test. Nutrition. 1991 Nov-Dec;7(6):410-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1802230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mourot J, Thouvenot P, Couet C, Antoine JM, Krobicka A, Debry G. Relationship between the rate of gastric emptying and glucose and insulin responses to starchy foods in young healthy adults. Am J Clin Nutr. 1988 Oct;48(4):1035-40.</citation>
    <PMID>3048076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 27, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 14, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 14, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>InnoSportNL</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jeroen Wouters</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr. Ir.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

