<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02405832</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHRMS 14-206</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02405832</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zinc Lozenges and Their Effect on Postoperative Sore Throat Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Zinc Lozenges and Their Effect on Postoperative Sore Throat Syndrome: A Randomized, Double-blinded, Placebo-controlled Prospective Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Vermont</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Vermont</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to assess the effect of preoperative administration of oral
      zinc lozenges on the incidence of postoperative sore throat syndrome.

      When patients undergo surgery with general anesthesia, they require ventilation of their
      lungs with the help of a flexible tube (called an endotracheal tube) that is placed through
      the mouth, passing the vocal cords, and into the windpipe (trachea). This tube helps
      oxygenate the patient, delivers anesthetic gas to the lungs, and keeps the airways open to
      prevent asphyxiation. The procedure is invasive and uncomfortable, and one of the most common
      consequences is a sore and inflamed throat after the tube is taken out. This is termed
      postoperative sore throat (POST). Though the intensity and severity of sore throat varies
      from person to person, the reported incidence is as high as 90% of patients undergoing
      general anesthesia.

      Zinc therapy has been shown in multiple studies to reduce the severity and duration of cold
      symptoms, and also to up-regulate the immune system. Recent studies have shown that zinc can
      act as an anti-inflammatory agent and can maintain the integrity of skin and mucosal
      membranes (which cover the inside of the mouth and throat). The aim of this study is to
      evaluate the effects of giving zinc lozenges before tube placement on postoperative sore
      throat.

      After written informed consent is received in pre-op, a sealed and coded envelope with either
      the zinc lozenge or the placebo lozenge will be given to the patient to be administered
      orally, with the instruction to dissolve the lozenge by sucking on it 30 minutes prior to
      surgery. Upon completion of surgery and emergence from general anesthesia, the patient will
      be extubated and transferred to the post-anesthesia care unit (PACU). Once in the PACU, the
      patient will be assessed regarding the incidence and severity of POST by the study
      investigator using a standardized scale. The severity of POST will be graded on a 4-point
      scale ranging from 0 to 3; 0 being no sore throat, 1 being mild discomfort (complains only
      upon questioning), 2 being moderate sore throat (complains on his/her own), and 3 being
      severe sore throat (change in voice, hoarseness, and throat pain). This evaluation will be
      performed at 30 minutes, 2 hours, 4 hours, and 24 hours post-surgery, with the assessment at
      4 hours being the primary outcome of the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overall purpose of this study is to investigate the effects of preoperative
      administration of oral zinc lozenges on postoperative sore throat syndrome which consists of
      pain, dysphagia, and in extreme cases hoarseness. It is associated with coughing (which may
      increase surgical related pain) and difficulty with oral intake. The study will look at the
      changes in incidence and severity of POST in the immediate postoperative period.

      Postoperative sore throat (POST) syndrome is a very common complication of endotracheal
      intubation Prior to earlier studies larger endotracheal tubes were utilized for providing
      general anesthesia. The incidence of POST at that time was 48%, with smaller tubes the
      incidence decreased to 22%. It is now standard of care to utilize endotracheal tubes based on
      size and gender of the patient. In subsequent studies to further reduce the incidence of
      POST, the rate of sore throat in the control groups have been between 17-90%. The cause of
      POST is related to direct local tissue trauma leading to inflammation of the pharyngeal
      mucosa and possibly the drying effect of non-humidified gases across the mucous membranes..
      Although there have been multiple treatments recommended for POST, none of them have been
      exactly effective, and the symptoms usually ameliorate within 72 hr without treatment. Even
      though this is the case, it is still recommended to take preventive measures for POST. The
      presence of POST after surgery is a patient satisfaction issue and has also been associated
      with a longer stay in in the post anesthesia recovery unit(Higgins et al). Both pharmacologic
      and non-pharmacologic measures have been recommended in past studies. Nonpharmacological
      methods for attenuating POST have included using smaller-sized endotracheal tubes,
      lubricating the endotracheal tube with water-soluble jelly, careful airway instrumentation,
      and minimizing cuff pressure. Pharmacologic measures have included gargles with lidocaine,
      aspirin, or ketamine preoperatively, inhalation of beclomethasone or fluticasone propionate,
      and recently the use of licorice gargle or magnesium lozenges 30 min preoperatively
      (Ruetzler, Borazan H).

      Zinc has been utilized for many years as a topical agent to promote epithelial health and
      recovery after injury. Several studies have evaluated the effect of zinc on wound healing and
      epithelial tissue health. These studies have shown that supplementation with zinc sulfate
      causes rapid recovery of leg and gastric ulcers (Worthington et al). It seems zinc not only
      increases re-epithelialization, but it also decreases bacterial activity and causes rapid
      wound healing (Arbabi-kalati et al). Zinc has also been shown to be an immunomodulatory agent
      that monitors and modifies the immune system and T-lymphocytes. Decreases in zinc serum
      levels lead to lymphopenia and declines in cellular and humoral immunity. The effect of oral
      zinc sulfate has also been utilized for treatment of oral wounds by oral surgeons; moreover,
      research has shown zinc supplementation assists with the recovery of mucosal wounds and
      treatment of tongue ulcers (Worthington et al). A recent study by Arbabi-kalati, showed that
      high dose oral zinc sulfate (220 mg TID) decreased the intensity of mucositis, xerostomia,
      and pain in individuals undergoing chemotherapy or radiotherapy treatments. The mechanism by
      which zinc improves tissue health was investigated by Sharir et al. and in a model of
      epithelial injury showed that topical zinc directly activates receptors that promote
      epithelial repair.

      Keeping the above studies in mind, the investigators built this study using the protocols
      devised by Borazan H, in which they evaluated the efficacy of magnesium lozenges on POST.
      There are currently no known studies that look at the efficacy of zinc in the prevention of
      POST. The investigators will use custom compounded lozenges from a local pharmacy with 40 mg
      of elemental zinc (equivalent to 174 mg of zinc sulfate) per lozenge, which is the tolerable
      upper intake level for zinc in adults as defined by the US department of Food and Nutrition
      Board.

      The possible knowledge gained from this study for POST syndrome can be extended to people
      undergoing surgeries requiring endotracheal intubation in the future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Post-Operative Sore Throat</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The severity of POST will be graded on a 4-point scale ranging from 0 to 3; 0 being no sore throat, 1 being mild discomfort (complains only upon questioning), 2 being moderate sore throat (complains on his/her own), and 3 being severe sore throat (change in voice, hoarseness, and throat pain).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Post-Operative Sore Throat at 30 minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Post-Operative Sore Throat at 2 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Post-Operative Sore Throat at 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Sore Throat</condition>
  <condition>Post-Operative Sore Throat</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Zinc - active arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral administration of a 40 mg elemental zinc (in the form of zinc sulfate) lozenge, with sweetener and citrus flavor</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo lozenge, with sweetener and citrus flavor, administered orally</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zinc</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral administration of a 40 mg elemental zinc (in the form of zinc sulfate) lozenge, with sweetener and citrus flavor</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zinc - active arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo lozenge, with sweetener and citrus flavor, administered orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women ages 18 and older

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists physical status classification system I and II
             (healthy patient or patient with mild systemic disease)

          -  Patient coming for elective surgery (except head and neck) requiring general
             anesthesia

          -  Patients staying for at least 24 hours postoperatively

          -  Patients provide informed consent

          -  Patients presenting for surgery &gt;1 hour in length and &lt;6 hours.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of preoperative sore throat, common colds, upper respiratory infections,
             immune deficiencies

          -  Chronic smokers

          -  Patients with Mallampati airway grade of more than 2

          -  Patients requiring more than one attempt for intubation or traumatic intubations

          -  Patients requiring laryngeal mask Airway (LMA) placement

          -  Patients allergic to zinc

          -  Patients requiring quinolones or tetracycline antibiotics pre- or intraoperatively

          -  Patients undergoing head and neck surgeries

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lydia Grondin, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Vermont</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexander Friend, M.S.</last_name>
    <phone>802-847-4259</phone>
    <email>alexander.friend@uvmhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Vermont Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexander Friend, M.S.</last_name>
      <phone>802-847-4259</phone>
      <email>alexander.friend@uvmhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lydia Grondin, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arbabi-kalati F, Arbabi-kalati F, Deghatipour M, Ansari Moghadam A. Evaluation of the efficacy of zinc sulfate in the prevention of chemotherapy-induced mucositis: a double-blind randomized clinical trial. Arch Iran Med. 2012 Jul;15(7):413-7. doi: 012157/AIM.008.</citation>
    <PMID>22724877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borazan H, Kececioglu A, Okesli S, Otelcioglu S. Oral magnesium lozenge reduces postoperative sore throat: a randomized, prospective, placebo-controlled study. Anesthesiology. 2012 Sep;117(3):512-8. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3182639d5f.</citation>
    <PMID>22797283</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Higgins PP, Chung F, Mezei G. Postoperative sore throat after ambulatory surgery. Br J Anaesth. 2002 Apr;88(4):582-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12066737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruetzler K, Fleck M, Nabecker S, Pinter K, Landskron G, Lassnigg A, You J, Sessler DI. A randomized, double-blind comparison of licorice versus sugar-water gargle for prevention of postoperative sore throat and postextubation coughing. Anesth Analg. 2013 Sep;117(3):614-21. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e318299a650. Epub 2013 Aug 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23921656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharir H, Zinger A, Nevo A, Sekler I, Hershfinkel M. Zinc released from injured cells is acting via the Zn2+-sensing receptor, ZnR, to trigger signaling leading to epithelial repair. J Biol Chem. 2010 Aug 20;285(34):26097-106. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M110.107490. Epub 2010 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20522546</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Worthington HV, Clarkson JE, Bryan G, Furness S, Glenny AM, Littlewood A, McCabe MG, Meyer S, Khalid T. Interventions for preventing oral mucositis for patients with cancer receiving treatment. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2010 Dec 8;(12):CD000978. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD000978.pub3. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2011;(4):CD000978.</citation>
    <PMID>21154347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 27, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 1, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 1, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 1, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Vermont</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lydia Grondin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Anesthesiology and Attending Anesthesiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharyngitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Zinc</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

