<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02407925</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>W14_099</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NTR4635</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>FP 13</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02407925</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Implementation of Optical Diagnosis for Diminutive Polyps Amongst Endoscopists: Training and Long-term Quality Assurance</brief_title>
  <acronym>DISCOUNT2</acronym>
  <official_title>Implementation of Optical Diagnosis for Diminutive Polyps Amongst Accredited Endoscopists for the Dutch Bowel Cancer Screening Program: Training and Long-term Quality Assurance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dutch Digestive Diseases Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, Dutch gastroenterologists who are certified for performing colonoscopies on
      FIT-positive patients in the Dutch population screening program are trained in optical
      diagnosis with validated methods. After this training, an ex- and in-vivo test phase leads to
      &quot;accreditation&quot; and endoscopists will be observed in their optical diagnosis for 1 year.
      During this year, half of the endoscopists will be randomized towards 3-monthly feedback and
      the other half will receive feedback on their results after 1 year. The endoscopic prediction
      of endoscopists on polyp histology will be compared to histopathological outcome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Through the recently started nationwide bowel cancer screening programme in the Netherlands,
      an extra 70.000 colonoscopies are annually performed. In current practice, all resected
      colonic lesions are histopathologically analysed. Even diminutive polyps, which rarely
      harbour cancer or advanced histological features. If endoscopists are able to accurately
      differentiate between neoplastic and non-neoplastic lesions during colonoscopy, practice
      could become more efficient and costeffective. This strategy is called optical diagnosis and
      two clinical practice strategies have been proposed by the American Society of
      Gastroenterologists (ASGE). First, diminutive polyps could be resected and discarded if &gt;90%
      of the surveillance intervals predicted on optical diagnosis correlate with the surveillance
      intervals after histopathological validation (if assessed with high confidence). Second,
      hyperplastic polyps in the rectosigmoid could be left in situ if endoscopists are able to
      confidently predict neoplastic histology of diminutive colorectal polyps with a negative
      predictive value (NPV) of ≥90%.

      The accuracy of white light colonoscopy is not acceptable for daily practice (59%-84%), but
      narrow band imaging (NBI) allows higher accuracies up to 98% and it was demonstrated that
      experienced endoscopists could reach a NPV of ≥90% for diminutive colorectal lesions.
      However, recent research shows that community gastroenterologists are not able to meet the
      quality thresholds proposed by the ASGE. Before this strategy could be safely applied in
      daily practice, community gastroenterologists should be able to meet thresholds as well.

      In this study, Dutch gastroenterologists who are certified for performing colonoscopies on
      FIT-positive patients in the Dutch population screening program, are trained in optical
      diagnosis with validated methods. After training, an ex- and in-vivo test phase leads to
      &quot;accreditation&quot; and endoscopists will be observed in their optical diagnosis for 1 year.
      During this year, half of the endoscopists will be randomized towards 3-monthly feedback and
      the other half will receive feedback on their results after 1 year. The endoscopic prediction
      of endoscopists on polyp histology will be compared to histopathological outcome.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of training rounds needed until endoscopists reach a clinical acceptable accuracy of predicting histology of subcentimetric (1-9 mm) colorectal lesions using NBI</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of qualified endoscopists that are able to maintain a clinical acceptable accuracy of predicting histology of subcentimetric (1-9 mm) colorectal lesions using NBI over a year, either with and without regular interim feedback.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of the accredited endoscopists that is able to reach a negative predictive value of at least 90% for predicting neoplastic diminutive (1-5mm) and small (6-9mm) colorectal lesions in the rectosigmoid</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of diminutive (1-5mm) and small (6-9mm) lesions that are correctly predicted with high confidence</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of patients in whom a surveillance interval (according to the Dutch surveillance guideline) can be advised directly after colonoscopy, based on the endoscopic diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of patients in whom the surveillance interval (according to the Dutch surveillance guideline) is correctly predicted based on endoscopic diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the number of correctly diagnosed sessile serrated adenoma/polyps in diminutive (1-5mm) and small (6-9mm) polyps</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the sensitivity for predicting neoplastic histology per endoscopist, time frame and feedback or no feedback group</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the costs in euros that would have been saved by multiplying the amount of high confidence predicted diminutive and small polyps with the histopathology costs per lesion</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3144</enrollment>
  <condition>Colonoscopy</condition>
  <condition>Colonic Polyps</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Endoscopists</arm_group_label>
    <description>Approximately 35 endoscopists whom are certified to perform colonoscopies on FIT-positive patients in the Dutch population screening program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Colonoscopies</arm_group_label>
    <description>Colonoscopies on FIT-positive patients in the Dutch population screening program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Device</arm_group_label>
    <description>Olympus colonoscopes with Narrow Band Imaging</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Feedback</intervention_name>
    <description>3-monthly or no 3-monthly feedback on results of optical diagnosis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Endoscopists</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Endoscopists certified for performing Dutch screening colonoscopies. Colonoscopies in
        patients performed after a positive FIT obtained for the Dutch colorectal cancer screening
        program.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Colonoscopies performed in FIT positive patients obtained for the Dutch colorectal
             cancer screening program.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Colonoscopies in patients with a history of colorectal cancer, inflammatory bowel
             disease or polyposis syndrome.

          -  Colonoscopies in patients with bleeding disorders or anticoagulants and therefore
             cannot undergo polypectomy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Evelien Dekker, Prof. dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>e.dekker@amc.uva.nl</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medisch Centrum Alkmaar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alkmaar</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Flevoziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Almere</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Amstelland Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amstelveen</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Antonie van Leeuwenhoek Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Onze Lieve Vrouwe Gasthuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sint Lucas Andreas Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Slotervaart Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rode Kruis Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beverwijk</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kennemer Gasthuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haarlem</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Spaarne Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hoofddorp</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Fries Gasthuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hoorn</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sint Antonius Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nieuwegein</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diakonessenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ignjatovic A, East JE, Suzuki N, Vance M, Guenther T, Saunders BP. Optical diagnosis of small colorectal polyps at routine colonoscopy (Detect InSpect ChAracterise Resect and Discard; DISCARD trial): a prospective cohort study. Lancet Oncol. 2009 Dec;10(12):1171-8. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(09)70329-8. Epub 2009 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19910250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuiper T, Marsman WA, Jansen JM, van Soest EJ, Haan YC, Bakker GJ, Fockens P, Dekker E. Accuracy for optical diagnosis of small colorectal polyps in nonacademic settings. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2012 Sep;10(9):1016-20; quiz e79. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2012.05.004. Epub 2012 May 18.</citation>
    <PMID>22609999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rex DK, Kahi C, O'Brien M, Levin TR, Pohl H, Rastogi A, Burgart L, Imperiale T, Ladabaum U, Cohen J, Lieberman DA. The American Society for Gastrointestinal Endoscopy PIVI (Preservation and Incorporation of Valuable Endoscopic Innovations) on real-time endoscopic assessment of the histology of diminutive colorectal polyps. Gastrointest Endosc. 2011 Mar;73(3):419-22. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2011.01.023.</citation>
    <PMID>21353837</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kamiński MF, Hassan C, Bisschops R, Pohl J, Pellisé M, Dekker E, Ignjatovic-Wilson A, Hoffman A, Longcroft-Wheaton G, Heresbach D, Dumonceau JM, East JE. Advanced imaging for detection and differentiation of colorectal neoplasia: European Society of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy (ESGE) Guideline. Endoscopy. 2014 May;46(5):435-49. doi: 10.1055/s-0034-1365348. Epub 2014 Mar 17.</citation>
    <PMID>24639382</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wanders LK, East JE, Uitentuis SE, Leeflang MM, Dekker E. Diagnostic performance of narrowed spectrum endoscopy, autofluorescence imaging, and confocal laser endomicroscopy for optical diagnosis of colonic polyps: a meta-analysis. Lancet Oncol. 2013 Dec;14(13):1337-47. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(13)70509-6. Epub 2013 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>24239209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaltenbach T, Rex DK, Wilson A, Hewett DG, Sanduleanu S, Rastogi A, Wallace M, Soetikno R. Implementation of optical diagnosis for colorectal polyps: standardization of studies is needed. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2015 Jan;13(1):6-10.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2014.10.009. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25511846</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumar S, Fioritto A, Mitani A, Desai M, Gunaratnam N, Ladabaum U. Optical biopsy of sessile serrated adenomas: do these lesions resemble hyperplastic polyps under narrow-band imaging? Gastrointest Endosc. 2013 Dec;78(6):902-9. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2013.06.004. Epub 2013 Jul 9.</citation>
    <PMID>23849819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hazewinkel Y, López-Cerón M, East JE, Rastogi A, Pellisé M, Nakajima T, van Eeden S, Tytgat KM, Fockens P, Dekker E. Endoscopic features of sessile serrated adenomas: validation by international experts using high-resolution white-light endoscopy and narrow-band imaging. Gastrointest Endosc. 2013 Jun;77(6):916-24. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2012.12.018. Epub 2013 Feb 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23433877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 19, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 31, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Evelien Dekker, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Optical diagnosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polyps</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colonic Polyps</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

