<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02406352</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-35</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02406352</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multispectral Digital Colposcope With Probe for Detection of Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</brief_title>
  <acronym>MDCwProbe</acronym>
  <official_title>Development and Application of a Multispectral Digital Colposcope and Probe Algorithm for Detection of Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brookdale University Hospital Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brookdale University Hospital Medical Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Although cervical cancer is a preventable cancer, every year more than one-quarter of a
      million women die worldwide from this disease. Internationally and nationally, cervical
      cancer is a disease that affects predominantly women who are poor and who live in resource
      poor settings. With the device the investigators are developing, known as the Multispectral
      Digital Colposcope with probe, our goal is to make detection of precancerous cervical lesions
      easier for the patient and for her provider. For the patient, our goal is to reduce the
      number of clinical visits needed to obtain a diagnosis and treatment and consequently to
      reduce the resulting fear and anxiety which usually accompanies an abnormal Pap smear. For
      the provider and the health care system, our goal is to obtain a more accurate diagnosis than
      the currently available diagnostic methods.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The multispectral digital colposcope (MDC) is a specialized lightsource and imaging device
      mounted on a custom-made colposcope that acquires a sequence of fluorescence images. This
      version of the MDC incorporates an upgraded light source, and updates the firmware and the
      user interface. This results in shorter acquisition times and improved image and spectrum
      quality control. The MDC also consists of a point probe that is used to take detailed light
      measurements (call spectroscopy) from smaller regions of the cervix. The goal of the study is
      to see whether the MDC can perform better than standard methods in detecting cancerous or
      pre-cancerous abnormalities of the cervix.

      Study subjects will be swabbed for detection and typing of the Human Papilloma Virus (HPV).
      After vinegar is applied on the cervix as per usual colposcopy practice, the MDC will then be
      used to take a sequence of images of the cervix. Next 2-4 readings will be taken from the
      cervix using the point probe.

      This data will be used to train, test and validate an algorithm specific to the MDC. The
      ability of the algorithm to detect cervical intraepithelial neoplasia will be compared to
      standard clinical care (colposcopy).

      The MDC images and pathology results will be compared to the spectroscopy data from the MDC
      probe. The investigators will determine if spectroscopy has equal sensitivity to colposcopy
      for detecting high grade lesions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection of precancerous cervical lesions or cervical cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>At point of care for colposcopy or treatment with LEEP (5 minutes).</time_frame>
    <description>Eligible patients who are referred to the colposcopy clinic for a diagnosis following an abnormal Pap smear will be asked to participate in the study. All participating women will receive their standard of care colposcopy as usual. In addition to their routine care, the MDC with probe will also be used to collect images of the cervix and spectroscopic measurements with the probe. All measurements will be compared with the biopsies obtained. The MDC with probe will not be used to determine from where the biopsies need to be obtained. One or two additional biopsies will be obtained from tissue that appears to be unaffected. These will be the control biopsies. Patients may refuse to provide the additional biopsies which are not part of the standard of care.
Patients scheduled for a treatment with the Loop Electrosurgical Excision Procedure (LEEP) will be asked for consent to obtain one or two biopsies prior to the LEEP procedure, but after anesthesia has been applied.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">618</enrollment>
  <condition>Carcinoma in Situ of Uterine Cervix</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasias</condition>
  <condition>High Grade Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Routine colposcopy and MDC with probe</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention which consists of obtaining cervical images with the MDC and spectroscopic data with the probe will be applied to all participants who agreed to participate in the study during their visit for a colposcopy exam or treatment with a LEEP procedure. A control biopsy will also be obtained from patients who agree to provide it. The control biopsy is a biopsy of cervical tissue that does not appear to have atypical changes when observed through a standard of care colposcope.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multispectral Digital Colposcope with probe</intervention_name>
    <description>Cervical images will be obtained with the Multispectral Digital Colposcope. Spectroscopic data will be obtained with the probe from eligible patients who provided consent to participate in the study.
The standard of care for research participants will not change.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Routine colposcopy and MDC with probe</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are at least 18 years old

          -  Are not pregnant (negative urine test) or breastfeeding

          -  Referred for colposcopy or LEEP treatment

          -  Can provide written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who do not meet the inclusion criteria

          -  Women who have had a hysterectomy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michele Follen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brookdale University Hospital and Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Leonid Fradkin, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>718-240-8225</phone>
    <email>lfradkin@bhmcny.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Thelma Carrillo, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>718-240-5978</phone>
    <email>tcarrill@bhmcny.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brookdale University Hospital and Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leonid Fradkin, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>718-240-8225</phone>
      <email>lfradkin@bhmcny.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Thelma Carrillo, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>718-240-5978</phone>
      <email>tcarrill@bhmcny.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michele Follen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cervicalopticalimaging.com/index.html</url>
    <description>Project website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 2, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 9, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 9, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 10, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brookdale University Hospital Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michele Follen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chair of Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma in Situ</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

