<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02281981</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Curcumin</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02281981</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Repeated Bouts of Downhill Running and Curcumin Supplementation on Arterial Stiffness During Recovery</brief_title>
  <acronym>Cur</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effects of Repeated Bouts of Downhill Running and Curcumin Supplementation on Arterial Stiffness During Recovery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Prince Edward Island</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>OmniActive Health Technologies</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Prince Edward Island</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Arterial Stiffness: As a recognized independent indicator of cardiovascular risk, maintaining
      low levels of arterial stiffening is important to cardiovascular health. Increases in
      arterial stiffening results in elevated systolic and mean pressure and it is correlated with
      various cardiovascular conditions such as left ventricular hypertrophy, ischaemic heart
      disease, and myocardial infarction. In contrast, decreased arterial stiffness improves
      ventricular-vascular coupling, ejection fraction, and cardiac output. Arterial stiffness is
      linked to inflammation and oxidative stress. Both inflammation and oxidative stress are
      elevated during DOMS (delayed onset muscle soreness), a state brought on by muscle damage
      often incurred during strenuous exercise. Recent studies have shown that a single bout of
      eccentric exercise can produce acute arterial stiffness during recovery. However,
      anti-oxidants/anti-inflammatories may be effective in reducing the extent of damage by
      decreasing oxidation and inflammation. Curcumin is a powerful antioxidant that could act as
      an anti-inflammatory and diminish the effects of the downhill run. In addition, eccentric
      damage generates a prophylactic protection lasting up to six weeks. The nature of the
      downhill run is primarily eccentric in nature. Therefore, repeated bouts may have diminished
      DOMS development. Any reduction in stress by either the prophylactic repeated bout effect or
      the Curcumin supplement, should attenuate the increase in arterial stiffness due to the
      reduction in inflammation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Baseline Participants will report to the lab on day one to have basic anthropometry and
      clinical measures performed. Following measures of height, weight, blood pressure, blood
      lipids (fasting glucose), creatine kinase, high sensitivity C-reactive protein (HS-CRP) and
      interleukin-6 (IL-6) participants will be allowed to eat a small standardized snack.
      Participants will then have measures of baseline muscle soreness and leg strength measured
      prior to a VO2max test on a cycle ergometer.

      Muscle Soreness will be measured using a standard 10cm analogue scale and girth of the thigh
      will be recorded to account for possible alterations owing to local inflammation/oedema./
      Creatine Kinase (CK) will be tracked as a measure of damage.

      The test termination criteria for the VO2max will include: volitional fatigue, a participant
      rating of perceived exertion of 19-20 (on a scale from 0-20), a plateau in O2 uptake with
      increasing workload, or and RER of &gt;1.15. The VT of each participant will be noted to compare
      with values post- training.

      Testing Day 2 - This day will occur at least 1 full day (48h) following VO2max testing.

      Participants will arrive at the lab having consumed a standardized breakfast. Prior to the
      downhill run, measures of pulse wave velocity (PWV), heart rate variability (HRV), flow
      mediated dilatation (FMD) will be collected according to the protocols to follow.
      Participants will then perform a 40 minute downhill run at a grade of -12 percent using a
      speed that elicits a VO2 of approximately 60% of the maximum value achieved during the max
      test.

      Arterial stiffness will be determined using a Sphygmocor CPVH pulse wave applanation
      tonomoter (Atcor Medical). This device measures arterial pulse waves non-invasively through
      the skin. By matching pulse wave arrival with heart beats (through a standard ECG tracing)
      and measuring the distance between points we can calculate travel time (or velocity). We will
      also use this same device to analyze the shape of the pulse wave, which will give us
      information about reflected pulse waves (and thus the stiffness of the arterial tree).

      Follow-up: At 24h, 48h, and 72h post exercise, participants will return to the lab to have
      all of the non-exercise measures repeated (see figure 1). This will allow temporal tracking
      over time.

      Hypotheses:

      1) The anti-inflammatory potential of Curcumin supplementation should improve post-exercise
      recovery. 2) Repeated bouts of eccentrically biased downhill running should produce a
      prophylactic effect and reduce arterial stiffness and recovery time
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial Stiffness</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 24 hr up to 72hr post baseline</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured using arterial tonometry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood measures of inflammation and muscle damage</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 24 hr up to 72hr post baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Interleukin-6, highsensitivity C-reactive protein, Creatine Kinase</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Delayed onset muscle soreness</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 24 hr up to 72hr post baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective analogue scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Vascular Stiffness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Curcumin supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>200 mg, curcuminoids, 7d of supplementation in capsular form</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>sucrose, capsular</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Curcumin</intervention_name>
    <description>333mg CurcuWin OAHTCUR002-2014</description>
    <arm_group_label>Curcumin supplement</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tumeric extract</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>OAHTCUR005-2014</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will be male or female

          -  18yr - 45yr

          -  Free from any known or suspected chronic conditions.

          -  General health and suitability to participate in an exercise/health research study
             will be confirmed through use of the PAR-Q+ screening questionnaire

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any participant who has a positive answer to a screening question will be required to
             seek physician approval prior to any physical exercise.

          -  Baseline arrhythmia (tachycardia (&gt;100pbm) and systolic or diastolic hypertension
             (&gt;140/90 mmHg) will also be reason for exclusion.

          -  During baseline anthropometric assessment we will confirm that participants all fall
             within a typical BMI range (20-30 kg/m2) of either &quot;normal&quot; weight or &quot;overweight&quot;,
             but not &quot;underweight&quot; or &quot;obese&quot;.

          -  Persons who take cardiovascular medications, metabolic medications, smoke cigarettes,
             excessively consume alcohol, are prone to heartburn, or have a previous diagnosis of
             hyperlipidemia or hyperinsulemia will also be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jamie F Burr, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UPEI</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>September 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 17, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Prince Edward Island</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Jamie Burr</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Curcumin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

