<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02282306</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-2591</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02282306</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phone Interview to Prevent Recurring Opioid Overdoses</brief_title>
  <acronym>TTIP-PRO</acronym>
  <official_title>Pilot Evaluation of the &quot;Tailored Telephone Intervention Delivered by Peers to Prevent Recurring Opioid-Overdoses&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There has been a dramatic rise in opioid overdose (OOD) deaths in recent years. Attempts to
      ameliorate the problem have largely focused on increasing the accessibility of naloxone, an
      opioid antagonist that is effective in OOD reversal. Individuals who have experienced a
      non-fatal OOD are at risk for additional overdoses and yet there are no interventions that
      specifically target this high-risk population. To address this gap, the investigators have
      developed the &quot;Tailored Telephone Intervention delivered by Peers to Prevent Recurring Opioid
      Overdoses&quot; (TTIP-PRO). The overall goal of the present study is to conduct a pilot evaluation
      of the TTIP-PRO. The research literature suggests the need for an intervention targeting
      patients experiencing a non-fatal OOD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-group, unblinded pilot study of the TTIP-PRO, which will be completed with
      approximately 30 participants. Potential participants will be identified by querying the
      University of Cincinnati Medical Center (UCMC) Emergency Department (ED) Electronic Health
      Record (EHR) for patients treated for an OOD (e.g., opioid poisoning). Patients who have
      experienced an OOD in the past 8 months will be eligible to receive the TTIP-PRO. A letter
      about the study will be sent to those patients. Interested patients will call the UC Health
      staff working on this study. A UC Health staff member will inform potential participants
      about the study, confirm eligibility, collect enrollment measures, and schedule a time for
      the TTIP-PRO to be completed with the Peer Interventionist. The participant will be
      instructed to contact the Peer Interventionist at the scheduled time. After the
      peer-delivered TTIP-PRO intervention has been completed, a UC Health employee will contact
      the participant to administer the follow-up measures. The UC Health employee will then send a
      mailing to the participant that will include a copy of the participant's &quot;Personal Risks for
      Overdose&quot; report, general information about overdose prevention, and information about
      treatment for opioid use disorder (see section 2.6 for additional information). The mailing
      will also include a gift card (which is a standard part of the TTIP-PRO) and an additional
      gift card to compensate the participant for his/her time as a study participant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Study Acceptability (proportion of patients who: a). call about the study and b). agree to participate in the study and c). who complete the study.)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Acceptability of the study will be assessed based on the proportion of patients who: a). call about the study and b). agree to participate in the study and c). who complete the study.
Acceptability of the study will be further assessed by peer interventionists who: a). complete the training and b). complete the study (i.e. continue to successfully provide intervention to assigned participants through the end of the study).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of TTIP-PRO on knowledge about Opioid Overdose. (will be assessed with a paired difference test (e.g., paired t-test))</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The impact of the TTIP-PRO on knowledge about OOD will be assessed with a paired difference test (e.g., paired t-test). Finally, summary statistics for the proportion of participants willing to be contacted by a MAT staff member after receiving the TTIP-PRO intervention will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Overdose</condition>
  <condition>Opioid-related Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Drug Addiction</condition>
  <condition>Drug Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Substance Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Use, Unspecified</condition>
  <condition>Opioid Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Drug Overdose</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TTIP-PRO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who have experienced an OOD in the past 8 months will be eligible to receive TTIP-PRO. A letter about the study will be sent to those patients. Interested patients will call the UC Health staff working on this study. The intervention entails administering the Personal Opioid-Overdose Risk Survey and the Opioid Overdose and Treatment Awareness Survey to the patient. The TTIP-PRO computer program uses the information to generate the &quot;Personal Feedback Report&quot;, which is used by the Peer Interventionist to provide the intervention. The TTIP-PRO computer program also creates the &quot;Personal Risk Factors Report&quot; which is mailed to the participant with some other helpful information.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TTIP-PRO</intervention_name>
    <description>The peer-delivered TTIP-PRO intervention is designed to: 1). increase the patient's knowledge of risk factors for OOD, with a particular emphasis on the patient's personal risk factors. This aim is one of harm reduction and is intended to help patients who continue to abuse opioids to use in a safer manner and 2).For patients who are open to considering treatment, to encourage the patient to get treatment for his/her opioid use disorder. This goal is based on research findings that effective treatment reduces the risk of OOD.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TTIP-PRO</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria for participants (receiving the TTIP-PRO intervention):

          -  have been treated for an OOD by the UCMC ED within the prior 8 months

          -  have used heroin and/or abused prescription opioids in the prior 12 months

          -  be 18 years of age or older at time of enrollment

          -  be able to provide verbal consent to participate in English

        Exclusion Criteria for participants (receiving the TTIP-PRO intervention):

          -  demonstrate difficulty understanding the study as assessed with four true-false
             questions (i.e., 1. This is a research study; 2. Your participation is entirely
             voluntary; 3. You will be asked questions about your risk of opioid overdose.; 4. Your
             participation will involve several phone calls).

        Inclusion Criteria for Peer Interventionists:

          -  be 18 years of age or older at time of enrollment

          -  be enrolled in a methadone-maintenance or buprenorphine- maintenance treatment program
             for at least one year

          -  report being opioid-abstinent for at least one year

          -  meet at least one of the following: has experienced/witnessed/lost a family member or
             friend to an overdose

          -  be able to provide informed consent in English

        Exclusion criteria for Peer Interventionists:

          -  have significant treatment/clinical concerns as determined by treatment program staff

        The primary pool of potential Peer Interventionists will be patients enrolled in the UC
        Health (University of Cincinnati Physicians Company) methadone-maintenance or
        buprenorphine- maintenance treatment programs. Recruitment will be through clinic postings
        and word of mouth. It is estimated that 2-3 Peer Interventionists will be enrolled in the
        study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Theresa Winhusen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>3131 Harvey Avenue, Suite 104</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC Physicians Company, LLC Opioid Treatment Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 30, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 3, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 27, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 27, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Cincinnati</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Theresa Winhusen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Drug Overdose</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

