<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02286232</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-0610.01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02286232</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chronic Low Back Pain Randomized Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Trial Comparing a Stretching/Exercise Program and Learning About Self-care Practices From a Self-care Book for Chronic Low Back Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stamford Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wilton Family YMCA</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stamford Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic low back pain is a common condition that can negatively impact quality of life and
      that lacks highly effective treatment options. The YMCA developed different iterations of a
      stretching exercise program as a community based treatment for low back pain from 1974-2004.
      Though anecdotally successful, the YMCA stretching exercise program(s) was not scientifically
      evaluated for efficacy and became obsolete. The purpose of the study is to test the efficacy
      of a previously popular YMCA stretching exercise program(s) for back pain. The stretching
      exercise program that will be studied is a collection of all the resources available for the
      YMCA stretching exercise program(s). The most recent criteria from a National Institutes of
      Health sponsored Task Force to study chronic low back pain were applied to this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will employ a two arm parallel group stratified controlled trial. A total of 60
      subjects from 18 through 64 years old with low back pain on at least half the days over the
      previous 6 months will be recruited by the Wilton Family YMCA to participate in the study.
      The participants within each recruitment cohort will be randomized by a sub-investigator who
      is a statistician to the two treatment arms in a ratio of 1:1 (stretching exercise
      experimental arm: self-care book active comparator arm). Three cohorts of 10 subjects will
      receive the intervention stretching exercise program at the Wilton Family YMCA from January
      2015 to October 2015. The stretching exercise program consists of 12 standardized weekly
      stretching exercise sessions that incrementally increase in duration from 15-30 minutes.
      Participants who receive the stretching exercise intervention will be asked to practice the
      identical stretches that they did in class on non-class days and will be given handouts and a
      companion CD to assist in this. Thirty control subjects will receive a self-care book. All
      analyses will be conducted assuming intent-to-treat principles using SAS statistical
      software. All P values and 95% CIs will be 2-sided with statistical significance at the P =
      0.05 value.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Roland-Morris Disability Questionnaire (RDQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Telephone interviews will be conducted at baseline and at 6, 12, and 26 weeks after randomization. Before randomization, information on sociodemographic characteristics, back pain history, and treatment-related beliefs will be collected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS measures from the NIH task force multidimensional minimal dataset on chronic low back pain</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Telephone interviews will be conducted at baseline and at 6, 12, and 26 weeks after randomization. Before randomization, information on sociodemographic characteristics, back pain history, and treatment-related beliefs will be collected</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Low Back Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stretching exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A series of 12 standardized, weekly stretching exercise classes will be held at the Wilton Family YMCA, designed for people with chronic low back pain unaccustomed to stretching. Participants will be asked to practice the identical routine of that week's stretching exercise class on off days and will be given handouts and CD's to assist in this.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Self-care book</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Back Pain Helpbook (Moore JE, Lorig K, Von Korff M, Gonzalez VM, Laurent DD. The Back Pain Helpbook. Reading, MA: Perseus Books; 1999)provides information on the causes of back pain and advice on exercising, making appropriate lifestyle modifications, and managing flare-ups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stretching exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>This program begins with 10 stretches/exercises over 15 minutes on the initial class and incrementally increases by 1 stretch/exercise each session for a total of 21 stretches/exercises over 30 minutes on the 12th session. The program is designed to stretch/exercise the major muscle groups, emphasizing the neck and arms, trunk, and legs. In addition to the stretches, each class will include breathing exercises and guided imagery for relaxation. Classes will be taught by Physical Therapists who are trained to lead classes through the protocol.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stretching exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-care book</intervention_name>
    <description>The Back Pain Helpbook which provides information on the causes of back pain and advice on exercising, making appropriate lifestyle modifications, and managing flare-ups.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Self-care book</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults from 18 through 64 years old who have had low back pain on at least half the
             days over the previous 6 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  We will exclude persons whose back pain is attributed to systemic or specific disease
             such as known cancer, spinal infection, fracture, or ankylosing spondylitis.

          -  Patients with complex conditions will not participate in the study (eg, sciatica,
             medicolegal issues, or a previous back surgery).

          -  We will also exclude persons who do not speak English.

          -  Finally, persons who are unable to attend classes or unwilling to do home practice
             will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc Brodsky, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stamford Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marc Brodsky, MD</last_name>
    <phone>203-276-4777</phone>
    <email>mbrodsky@stamhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shakeilla Howell, MD</last_name>
    <phone>203-276-4777</phone>
    <email>showell@stamhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stamford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stamford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06902</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc Brodsky, MD</last_name>
      <phone>310-883-4184</phone>
      <email>mbrodsky@stamhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marc Brodsky, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 5, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 6, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 7, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic low back pain</keyword>
  <keyword>stretching exercises</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

