<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02288481</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TBA-354-CL-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02288481</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 1 Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of TBA-354 in Healthy Adult Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Single Ascending Dose Study With a Food Effect Cohort to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of TBA-354 in Healthy Adult Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Global Alliance for TB Drug Development</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Global Alliance for TB Drug Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to evaluate the safety and tolerability of single oral doses
      of TBA‐354 when administered to healthy adult subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double‐blind, placebo‐controlled, single ascending dose study conducted
      at one study center in the United States. Six (6) cohorts of 8 subjects each (6 active and 2
      placebo), with one cohort crossing over to assess food effect, are planned for evaluation.
      Subjects will participate in only one cohort.

      Safety will be assessed throughout the study; serial ECGs and serial blood samples will be
      collected for the safety and PK assessment of TBA‐354.

      Dose escalation to the next cohort (i.e., dose level) will not take place until the Sponsor,
      in conjunction with the Principal Investigator, has determined that adequate safety,
      tolerability and PK from the previous cohort has been demonstrated to permit proceeding to
      the next cohort. Upon review of cohort data, the Sponsor, in conjunction with the Principal
      Investigator, may decide to:

        1. Escalate dose as planned.

        2. Evaluate an intermediate dose level prior to proceeding to the next planned dose level
           if concerns arise from signs and symptoms that do not warrant ceasing escalation as
           described above.

        3. Repeat a given dose level in a new cohort of subjects.

        4. Halt the study.

      Blinded interim PK analyses will be performed for the dose escalation decisions, to select
      the intermediate dose for the food effect cohort, and to reconsider the sampling time points
      as the study progresses.

      Subjects will be housed in the Celerion clinic from at least 24 hours prior (from Day ‐2),
      until 48 hours after dosing. Subjects will return for subsequent follow up safety and PK
      assessments on Days 4 to 7 and will be contacted via a phone call for follow‐up questioning
      about adverse events 7 days later (Study Day 14). One cohort will return after a washout of
      at least 14 days or five half‐lives (whichever is longer) of their fasting dose to receive
      the same intermediate dose (TBD mg) under fed conditions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoint of the study will be the number and severity of treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) following single doses of TBA-354 and placebo.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, 2, 4, 5, 6, 7, 14</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of TBA-354 in plasma following single oral doses. Cmax, AUC0-24</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (Hour 0, 1, 2, 4, 6, 7, 8, 12, 16), Day 2 (Hour 20, 24, 30, 36, 42), Follow up (Hour 72, 96, 120, 144)</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax: Time of the maximum drug concentration (obtained without interpolation). Cmax: Maximum observed drug concentration. AUC0-24: Area under concentration time curve 0 to 24 hours</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of food on the Pharmacokinetics parameters of TBA-354 in plasma following an intermediate single oral dose. Cmax, AUC0-24</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 (Hour 0, 1, 2, 4, 6, 7, 8, 12, 16), Day 2 (Hour 20, 24, 30, 36, 42), Follow up (Hour 72, 96, 120, 144)</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax: Time of the maximum drug concentration (obtained without interpolation). Cmax: Maximum observed drug concentration. AUC0-24: Area under concentration time curve 0 to 24 hours</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects/time points with abnormal findings in safety electrocardiogram</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening; Day 1 (Hour 0, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16); Day 2 Hour 20, 24, 30, 36 and 48; Follow up Hour 144</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated in terms of QT corrected for heart rate according to Fridericia's corrected formula (QTcF) outliers (QTcF &gt; 450, &gt; 480, and &gt; 500 msec; and change-from-baseline QTcF &gt; 30 and &gt; 60 msec).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Placebo-corrected safety electrocardiogram Change-from-baseline heart rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening; Day 1 (Hour 0, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16); Day 2 Hour 20, 24, 30, 36 and 48; Follow up Hour 144</time_frame>
    <description>Change-from-baseline heart rate, QT corrected for heart rate according to Fridericia's corrected formula (QTcF), PR, QRS, QT, and incidence of abnormal T-wave morphology from cardiodynamic electrocardiograms extracted from the pre-specified time points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>12</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 10 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Suspension</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 25 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Suspension</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3 60 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Suspension</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4 150 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Suspension</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5 400 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Suspension</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 6 1000 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 6 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo Suspension</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TBA-354</intervention_name>
    <description>TBA-354 supplied as a 20 mg /mL suspension and matching placebo suspension for oral administration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 10 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 25 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3 60 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4 150 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5 400 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 6 1000 mg TBA-354</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo Suspension</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5 placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 6 placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects must fulfill all of the following inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion
        criteria to be eligible for participation in the study, unless otherwise specified.
        Subjects must continue to meet all inclusion criteria to be able to participate in the Food
        Effect study.

          1. Healthy adult male and females of non‐childbearing potential, 19 to 50 years of age
             (inclusive) at the time of screening.

          2. Body mass index (BMI) ≥ 18.5 and ≤ 32.0 (kg/m2) and a body weight of no less than 50
             kg.

          3. Medically healthy with no clinically significant screening results (e.g., laboratory
             profiles, medical histories, vital signs, electrocardiograms (ECGs), physical
             examination) as deemed by the Principal Investigator.

          4. No use of tobacco or nicotine containing products (including smoking cessation
             products), for a minimum of 6 months prior to dosing.

          5. Females of non‐childbearing potential have undergone one of the following
             sterilization procedures at least 6 months prior to dosing:

             i. Hysteroscopic sterilization

             ii. Bilateral tubal ligation or bilateral salpingectomy

             iii. Hysterectomy

             iv. Bilateral oophorectomy

             v. or be postmenopausal with amenorrhea for at least 1 year prior to the first dose
             with serumfollicle‐stimulating hormone (FSH) levels consistent with postmenopausal
             status at screening.

          6. Non‐vasectomized males (or males vasectomized less than 120 days prior to study
             start), must agree to the following during study participation and for 90 days
             following the last administration of study drug:

               1. use a condom with spermicide while engaging in sexual activity or be sexually
                  abstinent

               2. not donate sperm during this time.

             In the event the sexual partner is surgically sterile, use of a condom with spermicide
             is not necessary. None of the restrictions listed above are required for vasectomized
             males whose procedure was performed more than 120 days prior to study start.

          7. Willing to answer inclusion and exclusion criteria questionnaire at check‐in.

          8. Subject understands study procedures and provides written informed consent for the
             trial.

          9. Be able to comply with the protocol and the assessments therein.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects will be excluded from the study if there is evidence of any of the following
        criteria at screening or check‐in, as appropriate. Subjects must continue to meet none of
        the Exclusion Criteria in order to participate in the Food Effect study.

          1. History or presence of significant cardiovascular, pulmonary, hepatic, renal,
             hematological, gastrointestinal, endocrine, immunologic, dermatologic, neurological,
             or psychiatric disease.

          2. History of any illness that, in the opinion of the Principal Investigator, might
             confound the results of the study or poses an additional risk to the subject by their
             participation in the study.

          3. Surgery within the past 90 days prior to dosing as determined by the Principal
             Investigator to be clinically relevant.

          4. History or presence of alcoholism or drug abuse within the past 2 years.

          5. Hypersensitive or idiosyncratic reactions to compounds related to TBA‐354 (e.g.,
             nitroimidazoles such as metronidazole, etc.).

          6. Female subjects who are pregnant or lactating.

          7. Positive results for the urine drug/alcohol screen at screening or check‐in.

          8. Positive urine cotinine at screening.

          9. Positive results at screening for Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Hepatitis B
             Surface Antigen (HBsAg), or Hepatitis C antibodies (HCV).

         10. Seated blood pressure is less than 90/40 mmHg or greater than 140/90 mmHg at
             screening.

         11. Heart rate is lower than 40 bpm or higher than 99 bpm at screening.

         12. Any clinically significant ECG abnormality at Screening (as deemed by the Principal
             Investigator and the Sponsor's Medical Monitor).

             NOTE: The following can be considered not clinically significant without consulting
             Sponsor's Medical Monitor:

             i. Mild first degree A‐V block (P‐R interval &lt;0.23 sec)

             ii. Right or left axis deviation

             iii. Incomplete right bundle branch block

             iv. Isolated left anterior fascicular block (left anterior hemiblock) in younger
             athletic subjects

         13. QTcF interval &gt;450 msec for males or &gt;470 msec for females (the average value for the
             replicate ECG at screening and Check‐In), or history of prolonged QT syndrome.

         14. Family history of Long‐QT Syndrome or sudden death without a preceding diagnosis of a
             condition that could be causative of sudden death (such as known coronary artery
             disease, congestive heart failure or terminal cancer).

         15. History of one or any combination of, the following:

               1. Seizures or seizure disorders, (excluding febrile seizures of childhood).

               2. Brain trauma or brain surgery.

               3. Any serious disorder of the CNS or related neurological system, particularly one
                  that may lower the seizure threshold.

         16. Use of any prescription medication within 14 days prior to dosing.

         17. Use of any over‐the‐counter (OTC) medication, including herbal products and vitamins,
             within the 7 days prior to dosing. Up to 2 grams per day of acetaminophen is allowed
             at the discretion of the Principal Investigator.

         18. Use of any drugs or substances known to be significant inhibitors of CYP enzymes
             and/or significant inhibitors or substrates of P‐gp and/or OATP within 14 days prior
             to the first dose of study drug.

         19. Use of any drugs or substances known to be inducers of CYP enzymes and/or P‐gp,
             including St. John's Wort, within 28 days prior to the first dose of study drug.

         20. Use of any drugs or substance known to lower the seizure threshold.

         21. Blood donation or significant blood loss within 56 days prior to dosing.

         22. Plasma donation within 7 days prior to dosing.

         23. Participation in another clinical trial within 28 days prior to dosing.

         24. Prior treatment with investigational products PA‐824 or OPC‐67683.

         25. Consumption of the following prior to dosing period:

               1. Alcohol 48 hours prior to dosing

               2. Grapefruit/Mandarin Oranges 10 days prior to dosing

               3. Caffeine/Xanthine 24 hours prior to dosing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Gartner, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Celerion</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Celerion</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lincoln</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68502</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 10, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 11, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 11, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>TBA-354</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>TB</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

