<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02283255</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CAPPesq 3765/12/021</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02283255</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cardiovascular, Pulmonary and Skeletal Muscle Evaluation in Late Postoperative Period of the Fontan Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cardiovascular, Pulmonary and Skeletal Muscle Evaluation in Patients With Univentricular Physiology in the Late Postoperative Period of the Fontan Surgery: Effects of Exercise Training</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>InCor Heart Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: Different variations of the Fontan operation has been used to treat complex
      cardiac anomalies with a single functional ventricle. This procedure has substantially
      improved quality of life and survival in patients with these complex cardiac anomalies.
      However, the cardiovascular and pulmonary functioning as well as skeletal muscle alterations
      that can explain the exercise intolerance in these patients is still poorly understood.

      Objectives: 1) To evaluate effects of different exercise programs on adolescents and adults
      with Fontan circulation.

      Methods: A long-term randomized clinical study that will include 60 patients between 12 and
      30 years, submitted to total cavopulmonary connection for at least 5 years post operative at
      the Heart Institute, University of São Paulo Medical School. The patients will be divided
      into four groups: 1) Exercise training with aerobic exercise + lower and upper limb strength
      exercise (GTF-I); 2) Respiratory training with respiratory muscle exercise (GTF-II); 3)
      Exercise training with aerobic exercise + lower and upper limb strength exercise +
      Respiratory training with respiratory muscle exercise (GTF-III); and A non-exercise group as
      control group (GNTF-IV). The patients will be revaluated after the 4-month period of
      intervention.

      Expected Outcomes: The investigators expect to demonstrate that exercise training and
      respiratory training can substantially improve the cardiovascular and pulmonary responses and
      skeletal muscle system in patients with univentricular circulation. In addition, the
      investigators wil test the hypothesis that the effects of exercise training associated with
      respiratory training on cardiovascular and pulmonary responses and skeletal muscle system may
      be greater than exercise training or respiratory training alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This research proposes to evaluate patients after undergoing the Fontan surgery. The
      investigators want to understanding exercise intolerance and they want to demonstrate the
      effects of exercise training after different programs of physical exercise. As well as, the
      quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement exercise tolerance and physical capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in parameters by cardiopulmonary exercise test; increase in lung volumes and capacities; improvement by neurovascular control and skeletical muscle metabolism</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in the functional capacity post exercise training program</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Increase at least 20% cardiopulmonary exercise test parameters: VO2 peak, oxygen pulse and VE/VCO2 slope</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in pulmonary function post physical exercise program</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Achieve at least 80% of predicted values for age at pulmonary function testing: spirometry, plethysmography, carbon monoxide diffusion capacity and maximal inspiratory pressure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in autonomic function post exercise training program</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Decrease bursts/min and bursts per 100 heart beats by at least 20% from baseline by directly measured by microneurography : direct muscle sympathetic nerve activity (MSNA)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in peripheral blood flow post exercise training program</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Increase forearm blood flow in mL/min/100mL</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the plasma epinephrine level post exercise training program</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Decrease of plasma epinephrine level from baseline</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in muscle metabolism post exercise training program</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Increase of the amplitudes of the phosphocreatine, inorganic phosphate and ATP from baseline by 31P-MRS: Quadriceps femoral 31P-MRS</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Congenital Heart Disease</condition>
  <condition>Single Ventricle</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aerobic Training: Aerobic training and muscle strength exercise for upper and lower limbs, 3 times a week for 4 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Respiratory Training: muscle training using POWERbreathe device, 7 times a week, 3 series of 30 repetitions per day, for 4 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aerobic and Respiratory Training: Aerobic training and muscle strength exercise for upper and lower limbs, 3 times a week for 4 months and respiratory muscle training using POWERbreathe device, 7 times a week, 3 series of 30 repetitions per day, for 4 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No Physical Activity: Control group (usual care)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Activity</intervention_name>
    <description>Physical Activity, Exercise training: aerobic and respiratory exercise with POWERbreathe device</description>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Exercise training: aerobic and respiratory exercise</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Both gender, aged between 12 and 30 years

          -  Patients undergoing the Fontan operation with time postoperatively ≥5 years

          -  Clinically stable patients, no arrhythmia in the last electrocardiogram or clinical
             assessment

          -  Consent by the cardiologist

          -  Patients who voluntarily signed the consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with hypoplastic left heart syndrome

          -  Changes that reduce musculoskeletal walking skills

          -  Neurological sequelae, patients with associated genetic syndrome, disturbance
             cognitive or psychiatric

          -  Patients with a history of ventricular arrhythmias, cardio respiratory arrest, users
             of anti-arrhythmic drugs and / or underwent implantation of pacemaker

          -  Atrial arrhythmia requiring treatment in the last 6 months

          -  Patients with heart failure not controlled by medications and lung hypertension

          -  Patients with protein-losing enteropathy

          -  Severe hypoxemia (oxygen saturation &lt;80% at rest)

          -  Symptomatic patients with a diagnosis of diaphragmatic paresis or paralysis
             postoperative patients, with or without plication

          -  Patients with moderate to severe asthma

          -  Patients who live outside the area of Sao Paulo
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcelo B Jatene, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Heart Institute, University of Sao Paulo, Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aida LR Turquetto, PhD student</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Heart Institute, University of Sao Paulo, Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aida LR Turquetto, PhD Student</last_name>
    <phone>+551126615399</phone>
    <email>aidaturquetto@me.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>InCor Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <zip>05403000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aida LR Turquetto, Researcher</last_name>
      <phone>+55 11 26615399</phone>
      <phone_ext>+5511981140723</phone_ext>
      <email>aidaturquetto@me.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marcelo B Jatene, Researcher</last_name>
      <phone>+551126615399</phone>
      <phone_ext>+551126615399</phone_ext>
      <email>marcelo.jatene@incor.usp.br</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aida LR Turquetto, PhD student</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcelo B Janete, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carlos E Negrão, PhD, Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria A Binotto, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cesar H Nomura, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana LC Sayegh, PhD student</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Maria Isabel CS Lopes, RT</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Glaucia MP Tavares, MD, Ms</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Luiz F Caneo, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcelo R dos Santos, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francis R de Souza, PhD student</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patricia A Oliveira, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Daniela R Agostinho, Educator</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carlos RR Carvalho, MD,PhD,Prof.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Frederico LA Fernandes, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ohuchi H, Ohashi H, Takasugi H, Yamada O, Yagihara T, Echigo S. Restrictive ventilatory impairment and arterial oxygenation characterize rest and exercise ventilation in patients after fontan operation. Pediatr Cardiol. 2004 Sep-Oct;25(5):513-21. Epub 2004 May 12.</citation>
    <PMID>15136907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brassard P, Poirier P, Martin J, Noël M, Nadreau E, Houde C, Cloutier A, Perron J, Jobin J. Impact of exercise training on muscle function and ergoreflex in Fontan patients: a pilot study. Int J Cardiol. 2006 Feb 8;107(1):85-94. Epub 2005 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>16046016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Binotto MA, Maeda NY, Lopes AA. Altered endothelial function following the Fontan procedure. Cardiol Young. 2008 Feb;18(1):70-4. Epub 2007 Dec 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18093358</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steier J, Kaul S, Seymour J, Jolley C, Rafferty G, Man W, Luo YM, Roughton M, Polkey MI, Moxham J. The value of multiple tests of respiratory muscle strength. Thorax. 2007 Nov;62(11):975-80. Epub 2007 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>17557772</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson PA, Sleeper LA, Mahony L, Colan SD, Atz AM, Breitbart RE, Gersony WM, Gallagher D, Geva T, Margossian R, McCrindle BW, Paridon S, Schwartz M, Stylianou M, Williams RV, Clark BJ 3rd; Pediatric Heart Network Investigators. Contemporary outcomes after the Fontan procedure: a Pediatric Heart Network multicenter study. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2008 Jul 8;52(2):85-98. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2008.01.074.</citation>
    <PMID>18598886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trojnarska O, Gwizdała A, Katarzyński S, Katarzyńska A, Szyszka A, Lanocha M, Grajek S, Kramer L. Evaluation of exercise capacity with cardiopulmonary exercise test and B-type natriuretic peptide in adults with congenital heart disease. Cardiol J. 2009;16(2):133-41.</citation>
    <PMID>19387960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>d'Udekem Y, Cheung MM, Setyapranata S, Iyengar AJ, Kelly P, Buckland N, Grigg LE, Weintraub RG, Vance A, Brizard CP, Penny DJ. How good is a good Fontan? Quality of life and exercise capacity of Fontans without arrhythmias. Ann Thorac Surg. 2009 Dec;88(6):1961-9. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2009.07.079.</citation>
    <PMID>19932269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greutmann M, Le TL, Tobler D, Biaggi P, Oechslin EN, Silversides CK, Granton JT. Generalised muscle weakness in young adults with congenital heart disease. Heart. 2011 Jul;97(14):1164-8. doi: 10.1136/hrt.2010.213579. Epub 2011 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21258001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Driscoll DJ, Durongpisitkul K. Exercise testing after the Fontan operation. Pediatr Cardiol. 1999 Jan-Feb;20(1):57-9; discussion 60. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9861079</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Neder JA, Andreoni S, Lerario MC, Nery LE. Reference values for lung function tests. II. Maximal respiratory pressures and voluntary ventilation. Braz J Med Biol Res. 1999 Jun;32(6):719-27.</citation>
    <PMID>10412550</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>McCall R, Humphrey R. Exercise training in a young adult late after a fontan procedure to repair single ventricle physiology. J Cardiopulm Rehabil. 2001 Jul-Aug;21(4):227-30.</citation>
    <PMID>11508184</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Minamisawa S, Nakazawa M, Momma K, Imai Y, Satomi G. Effect of aerobic training on exercise performance in patients after the Fontan operation. Am J Cardiol. 2001 Sep 15;88(6):695-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11564403</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Negrão CE, Rondon MU, Tinucci T, Alves MJ, Roveda F, Braga AM, Reis SF, Nastari L, Barretto AC, Krieger EM, Middlekauff HR. Abnormal neurovascular control during exercise is linked to heart failure severity. Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol. 2001 Mar;280(3):H1286-92.</citation>
    <PMID>11179075</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>American Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society. ATS/ERS Statement on respiratory muscle testing. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2002 Aug 15;166(4):518-624.</citation>
    <PMID>12186831</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Larsson ES, Eriksson BO, Sixt R. Decreased lung function and exercise capacity in Fontan patients. A long-term follow-up. Scand Cardiovasc J. 2003;37(1):58-63.</citation>
    <PMID>12745804</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Inai K, Saita Y, Takeda S, Nakazawa M, Kimura H. Skeletal muscle hemodynamics and endothelial function in patients after Fontan operation. Am J Cardiol. 2004 Mar 15;93(6):792-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15019898</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rhodes J, Curran TJ, Camil L, Rabideau N, Fulton DR, Gauthier NS, Gauvreau K, Jenkins KJ. Impact of cardiac rehabilitation on the exercise function of children with serious congenital heart disease. Pediatrics. 2005 Dec;116(6):1339-45.</citation>
    <PMID>16322156</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Opocher F, Varnier M, Sanders SP, Tosoni A, Zaccaria M, Stellin G, Milanesi O. Effects of aerobic exercise training in children after the Fontan operation. Am J Cardiol. 2005 Jan 1;95(1):150-2.</citation>
    <PMID>15619417</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Inai K, Nakanishi T, Nakazawa M. Clinical correlation and prognostic predictive value of neurohumoral factors in patients late after the Fontan operation. Am Heart J. 2005 Sep;150(3):588-94.</citation>
    <PMID>16169346</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moalla W, Maingourd Y, Gauthier R, Cahalin LP, Tabka Z, Ahmaidi S. Effect of exercise training on respiratory muscle oxygenation in children with congenital heart disease. Eur J Cardiovasc Prev Rehabil. 2006 Aug;13(4):604-11.</citation>
    <PMID>16874152</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Takken T, Hulzebos HJ, Blank AC, Tacken MH, Helders PJ, Strengers JL. Exercise prescription for patients with a Fontan circulation: current evidence and future directions. Neth Heart J. 2007;15(4):142-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17612674</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pianosi PT, Johnson JN, Turchetta A, Johnson BD. Pulmonary function and ventilatory limitation to exercise in congenital heart disease. Congenit Heart Dis. 2009 Jan-Feb;4(1):2-11. doi: 10.1111/j.1747-0803.2008.00244.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19207396</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Goldstein BH, Golbus JR, Sandelin AM, Warnke N, Gooding L, King KK, Donohue JE, Gurney JG, Goldberg CS, Rocchini AP, Charpie JR. Usefulness of peripheral vascular function to predict functional health status in patients with Fontan circulation. Am J Cardiol. 2011 Aug 1;108(3):428-34. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2011.03.064. Epub 2011 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21600541</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lambert E, d'Udekem Y, Cheung M, Sari CI, Inman J, Ahimastos A, Eikelis N, Pathak A, King I, Grigg L, Schlaich M, Lambert G. Sympathetic and vascular dysfunction in adult patients with Fontan circulation. Int J Cardiol. 2013 Aug 20;167(4):1333-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2012.04.015. Epub 2012 Apr 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22525342</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 3, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 31, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 5, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 31, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 31, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 5, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aida Luiza R Turquetto</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>InCor Heart Institute</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fontan</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Function</keyword>
  <keyword>Aerobic Capacity</keyword>
  <keyword>Skeletal Muscle</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

