<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02281409</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-135</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02281409</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Tolerability, and Immunoregulatory Activity of Mogamulizumab (KW-0761) in Subjects With Advanced and/or Metastatic Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of the Safety, Tolerability, and Immunoregulatory Activity of Mogamulizumab (KW-0761) in Subjects With Advanced and/or Metastatic Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kyowa Hakko Kirin Pharma, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out what effects, good and/or bad, KW-0761, an
      investigational drug, has on the patient and their cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>maximum tolerated dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>A standard 3+3 design will be utilized to determine the MTD. Four dose levels of KW-0761 will be investigated (0.5mg/kg, 1mg/kg, 3mg/kg, 10mg/kg). Patients will be treated in cohorts of size three to six and the dosage will be escalated if the clinical toxicity is acceptable.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>using both RECIST v1.1 and immune-related response criteria (irRC) in cohorts of three specific tumor types treated at the MTD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumors</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mogamulizumab (KW-0761)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be enrolled to receive a weekly intravenous (IV) dose of KW-0761 ranging from 0.5 mg/kg to 10.0 mg/kg as feasible starting on Day 1 for 4 weeks. In the absence of toxicity or progression of disease, patients may continue receiving KW-0761 for up to 12 months. Subsequent treatment courses will consist of an infusion every other week. Following end of treatment or treatment completion date, a 24-week short term follow-up (STFU) period of observation will begin. Phase II of the study will enroll a total of 48 subjects, 16 patients in 3 tumor-specific expansion cohorts each treated at the RP2D (MTD, or highest dose tested in Phase I part of trial).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mogamulizumab (KW-0761)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Mogamulizumab (KW-0761)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed Consent form signed by the subject.

          -  Males and females 18 years or older at the time of dose initiation.

          -  Histologically confirmed unresectable solid tumor malignancy with at least 1
             measurable lesion. In the expansion phase, eligibility will be limited to metastatic
             triple negative breast cancer that has received prior taxane and anthracycline
             therapy; Metastatic NSCLC that is not ALK+ and does not have a EGFR sensitizing
             mutation; and metastatic gastric cancer

          -  Previously treated for an advanced cancer and there are no curative therapy options
             available

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status ≥70 in the 30 day baseline period immediately prior to
             dosing.

          -  Evidence of adequate organ function by standard laboratory tests:

               -  Serum creatinine (Cr) ≤1.5 X upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Serum total and (T -Bil ) ≤1.5 X ULN (prior diagnosis or past history consistent
                  with Gilbert's syndrome is an exception)

               -  Serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤2.5 X
                  ULN

               -  Platelets (Plts) ≥ 100,000/μl

               -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) ≥ 9.0 g/dL

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1000/mm3

          -  All female subjects of childbearing age must be either surgically sterile,
             postmenopausal for at least 1 year, or using an acceptable method of contraception.
             Examples of adequate methods of contraception include abstinence, intrauterine device,
             hormonal contraception, use of spermicide and a condom by sexual partner, or partner
             with a vasectomy. Adequate contraception must be used from the beginning of the
             screening period until at least 16 weeks after the last dose of KW-0761. Male subjects
             with partners of childbearing potential must use a barrier method of contraception
             from the day of the first dose of KW-0761 until at least 16 weeks after the last dose.

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 12 weeks

          -  Previously treated for advanced cancer with no additional therapy options available
             known to prolong survival.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence of clinically significant of central nervous system (CNS) metastases or
             symptomatic CNS metastases within 30 days prior to dosing.

        History of autoimmune disease, except for vitiligo, diabetes, and autoimmune thyroiditis.

          -  A history of any major surgery within 6 weeks prior to dosing.

          -  Any history of systemic anticancer therapy (standard or experimental) completed within
             30 days prior to dosing, with the exception of palliative ablation of lesion(s) as
             long as measurable disease lesion(s) remain for evaluation of exploratory endpoints.

          -  Any concomitant serious physical illness other than cancer (i.e., immune deficiency
             disease, bleeding disorder, etc.) within 1 year prior to dosing.

          -  Any history of Stevens-Johnson syndrome.

          -  Clinically significant heart disease, defined as NYHA Class III or IV.

          -  Any allergic reaction to a previously administered monoclonal antibody or other
             therapeutic protein.

          -  Any significant systemic infection within 4 weeks prior to dosing.

          -  Pregnancy or breast-feeding.

          -  An existing diagnosis of HIV, hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or any current laboratory
             findings or clinical signs and symptoms that suggest these conditions.

          -  Subjects with active herpes simplex or herpes zoster. Subjects with a history of
             herpes zoster who have had an outbreak within the last year will also be excluded.
             Subjects on prophylaxis for herpes who started taking medication at least 30 days
             prior to study entry, should continue to take the prescribed medication for the
             duration of the study.

          -  Unresolved immune- related adverse events following prior biological therapy

          -  Use of any investigational drugs within 30 days prior to dosing.

          -  Any condition that requires or is likely to require treatment with systemic
             corticosteroids within the Core Study Period and short term follow-up.

          -  Subjects that have had a myocardial infarction within the last 6 months.

          -  Subjects on any immunomodulatory drug.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jedd Wolchok, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jedd Wolchok, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>646-888-2395</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>George Plitas, MD</last_name>
    <phone>646-888-4587</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jedd Wolchok, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-2395</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>George Plitas, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-888-4587</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jedd Wolchok, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 30, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 3, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mogamulizumab (KW-0761)</keyword>
  <keyword>14-135</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

