<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02289482</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200912</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02289482</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Single Dose Pharmacokinetic (PK) and Safety Study of GSK2838232 With and Without Ritonavir (RTV) Conducted in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Continuation Single Dose Escalation Study to Investigate the Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of GSK2838232 With and Without Ritonavir, and to Evaluate Different Formulations of GSK2838232, in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study investigates the safety, tolerability and PKs of GSK2838232 with and without
      Ritonavir, and to evaluate different formulations of GSK2838232 in healthy subjects. This
      study will evaluate higher single and RTV boosted doses to support continued clinical
      development of GSK2838232 at clinically relevant doses, and subsequently in those infected
      with HIV in a dose ranging phase 2 study. The study is conducted in 2 parts: Part A and Part
      B, study Part A and Part B may be conducted in parallel. Approximately 20 healthy subjects
      will be enrolled into the study, 8 in Part A and 12 in Part B. Part A is a double-blind,
      randomized, placebo-controlled, 4-period, single dose escalation design. Subjects will be
      randomized 3:1 to receive GSK2838232 or placebo. Subjects randomized to placebo will receive
      placebo in all four periods. Following completion of Period 2 PK assessments at 96hr
      post-dose, subjects will begin daily dosing of RTV 100mg for a total of 26 days.

      Part B is a randomized, open-label, unbalanced, 3-period, cross-over design; subjects will be
      randomized 1:1 to each sequence. The relative bioavailability of single 100mg doses of powder
      in a bottle (PIB) active pharmaceutical ingredient (API) of GSK2838232 versus PIB spray-dried
      dispersion (SDD) will be assessed. A single dose of GSK2838232 will co-administered on the
      10th day of RTV dosing; RTV dosing will continue for an additional 4 days (total of 14 days).
      Subjects will have a screening visit within 30 days prior to first dose and a follow-up visit
      7-14 days after the last dose.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study prematurely terminated due to safety concerns leading to clinical hold
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 17, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 10, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 10, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (AEs) assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety was assessed by monitoring AE and serious AEs (SAE). AEs and SAEs will be collected from the start of Study Treatment until the follow-up contact</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety assessed by laboratory evaluations</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory evaluations will include hematology, clinical chemistry, urinalysis assessments</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Vital signs will be measured in semi-supine position after 10 minutes rest and will include systolic and diastolic blood pressure and pulse rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Electrocardiogram (ECG) parameters assessments</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to approximately 7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Triplicate or Single 12-lead ECGs will be obtained at each timepoint during the study after a 10 minute rest using an ECG machine that automatically calculates the heart rate and measures PR, QRS, QT, and QTc intervals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite PK profile of GSK2838232, , with and without RTV for Part A and Part B</measure>
    <time_frame>During Part A: Day 1 to Day 5 (Period 1 &amp; 2), Day 10-Day 15 (Period 3), Day 8 - Day 13 (Period 4). During Part B: Day 1 to Day 4 (Period 1 &amp; 2), Day 10-Day 14 (Period 3)</time_frame>
    <description>PK assessments will include: area under the concentration-time curve from time zero (pre-dose) extrapolated to infinite time (AUC 0-infinity), area under the concentration-time curve over the dosing interval (AUC 0-t), concentration at 24 hours post dose (C24), oral clearance (CL/F), maximum observed concentration (Cmax), last quantifiable concentration (Clast), time of occurrence of Cmax (tmax), time of last observed concentration (tlast), terminal phase half-life (t1/2), and time of first quantifiable concentration (tlag).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite PK profile of GSK2838232 to assess the relative bioavailability of the PIB API suspension versus PIB SDD suspension (Part B)</measure>
    <time_frame>During Part B: Day 1 to Day 4 (Period 1 &amp; 2), Day 10-Day 14 (Period 3)</time_frame>
    <description>PK assessments will include: GSK2838232 AUC(0-infinity), Cmax</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite PK profile of GSK2838232 to assess single dose proportionality of GSK2838232 with and without steady-state RTV (Part A)</measure>
    <time_frame>During Part A: Day 1 to Day 5 (Period 1 &amp; 2), Day 10-Day 15 (Period 3), Day 8 - Day 13 (Period 4).</time_frame>
    <description>PK assessments will include: GSK2838232 AUC(0 - infinity), AUC(0-t) and Cmax</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Infection, Human Immunodeficiency Virus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GSK2838232 Part A: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During Part A, subjects will receive GSK2838232/ placebo (3:1) in 4-period (period 1: GSK2838232 200mg, period 2: GSK2838232 500mg), single dose escalation design. Subjects randomized to placebo will receive placebo in all four periods. Following completion of Period 2 PK assessments at 96hr post-dose, subjects will begin daily dosing of RTV 100mg (period 3: GSK2838232 20 mg + RTV 100 mg, period 4: GSK2838232 50 mg + RTV 100 mg) for a total of 26 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GSK2838232 Part B: Single Dose, 3-Period Crossover, Relative B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During Part B, subjects will receive GSK2838232/ placebo, in an open-label, unbalanced, 3-period, cross-over design; subjects will be randomized (1:1) to each sequence. The relative bioavailability of single 100 mg doses of powder in a bottle (PIB) Active Pharmaceutical Ingredient (API) of GSK2838232 versus PIB Spray-Dried Dispersion (SDD) will be assessed (Period 1: SDD GSK2838232 100 mg vs GSK2838232 API 100 mg; period 2: GSK2838232 API 100 mg Vs SDD GSK2838232 100 mg ). A single dose of GSK2838232 will be co-administered on the 10th day of RTV dosing (period 3:GSK2838232 10 mg + RTV 100 mg); RTV dosing will continue for an additional 4 days (total of 14 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK2838232 PIB (SDD)</intervention_name>
    <description>GSK2838232 will be available as oral suspension dispersion in hydromellulose acetate succinate bulk powder/10, 20, 50, 200 and 500 mg in part A, while 100 mg in Part B. GSK2838232 will be administered orally once daily (QD) as single doses in the morning following an overnight fast of at least 10 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GSK2838232 Part B: Single Dose, 3-Period Crossover, Relative B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>GSK2838232 Part A: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK2838232 PIB (API)</intervention_name>
    <description>GSK2838232 will be available as oral suspension bulk powder/100 mg in Part B. GSK2838232 will be administered orally QD as single doses in the Morning following an overnight fast of at least 10 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GSK2838232 Part B: Single Dose, 3-Period Crossover, Relative B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matching placebo of Suspension to active dose, administered orally QD as single doses in the morning following an overnight fast of at least 10 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GSK2838232 Part B: Single Dose, 3-Period Crossover, Relative B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>GSK2838232 Part A: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ritonavir</intervention_name>
    <description>Ritonavir will be available as white film-coated ovaloid tablets of 100 mg tablet/100mg. Ritonavir will be administered orally, once daily in Part A, Period 3 Days 1-14 and Period 4 from Days 1-12 and will be administer orally once daily in Part B for 9 days prior to dosing in Period 3 and on Days 10-14 of Period 3.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GSK2838232 Part B: Single Dose, 3-Period Crossover, Relative B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>GSK2838232 Part A: Single Dose Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between 18 and 55 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the informed consent

          -  Healthy as determined by the investigator or medically qualified designee based on a
             medical evaluation including medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests
             and cardiac monitoring.

          -  A subject with a clinical abnormality or laboratory parameter(s) which is/are not
             specifically listed in the inclusion or exclusion criteria, outside the reference
             range for the population being studied may be included only if the investigator in
             consultation with the Medical Monitor if required agree and document that the finding
             is unlikely to introduce additional risk factors and will not interfere with the study
             procedures.

          -  A Creatinine clearance (CLcr) &gt;80 millilitre per minute (mL/min) as determined by
             Cockcroft-Gault equation where age is in years, weight (Wt) is in kg, and serum
             creatinine (Scr) is in units of milligram / decilitre (mg/dL); CLcr (mL/min) = (140 -
             age) * Wt / (72 * Scr) (times 0.85 if female).

          -  Body weight &gt;= 50 kilogram (kg [110 pounds {lbs}]) for men and &gt;= 45 kg (99 lbs) for
             women and body mass index (BMI) within the range 18.5-31.0 kilogram per meter square
             kg/m^2 (inclusive)

          -  Male or Female; Female subject of non-reproductive potential : is eligible to
             participate if she is not pregnant (as confirmed by a negative serum or urine human
             chorionic gonadotrophin (hCG) test), not lactating, and at least one of the following
             conditions applies: Pre-menopausal females with one of the following: Documented tubal
             ligation, Documented hysteroscopic tubal occlusion procedure with follow-up
             confirmation of bilateral tubal occlusion, Hysterectomy, Documented Bilateral
             Oophorectomy; Postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous amenorrhea in
             questionable cases a blood sample with simultaneous follicle stimulating hormone (FSH)
             and estradiol levels consistent with menopause (refer to laboratory reference ranges
             for confirmatory levels). Females on hormone replacement therapy (HRT) must
             discontinue HRT to allow confirmation of post-menopausal status prior to study
             enrolment. Male subjects with female partners of child bearing potential must comply
             with the following contraception requirements from the time of first dose of study
             medication until one week after the last dose of study medication. a) Vasectomy with
             documentation of azoospermia, b) Male condom plus partner use of one of the
             contraceptive options below: Contraceptive subdermal implant that meets the standard
             operating procedure (SOP) effectiveness criteria including a &lt;1% rate of failure per
             year, as stated in the product label, Intrauterine device or intrauterine system that
             meets the SOP effectiveness criteria including a &lt;1% rate of failure per year, as
             stated in the product label, Oral Contraceptive, either combined or progestogen alone
             Injectable progestogen, Contraceptive vaginal ring, Percutaneous contraceptive
             patches. These allowed methods of contraception are only effective when used
             consistently, correctly and in accordance with the product label. The investigator is
             responsible for ensuring that subjects understand how to properly use these methods of
             contraception.

          -  Capable of giving signed informed consent which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form and in this protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Alanine aminotransferase and bilirubin &gt;1.5xupper limit of normal (ULN) (isolated
             bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin
             &lt;35%).

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary abnormalities
             (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones)

          -  Subjects who have asthma or a history of asthma.

          -  Medical history of cardiac arrhythmias or cardiac disease or a family and personal
             history of long QT syndrome.

          -  Unable to refrain from the use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, including
             vitamins, herbal and dietary supplements (including St John's Wort) within 7 days (or
             14 days if the drug is a potential enzyme inducer) or 5 half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to the first dose of study medication, unless in the opinion of the
             Investigator and GSK Medical Monitor the medication will not interfere with the study
             procedures or compromise subject safety.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study defined as: an
             average weekly intake of &gt;14 drinks for males or &gt;7 drinks for females. One drink is
             equivalent to 12 g of alcohol: 12 ounces (360 mL) of beer, 5 ounces (150 ml) of wine
             or 1.5 ounces (45 mL) of 80 proof distilled spirits.

          -  Regular use of tobacco- or nicotine-containing products within 6 months prior to
             screening.

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a
             history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or Medical
             Monitor, contraindicates their participation.

          -  Presence of hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), positive hepatitis C antibody test
             result at screening or within 3 months prior to first dose of study treatment.

          -  Screening or baseline cardiac troponin I greater than the 99% cutoff (&gt;.045 nanogram/
             milliliter [ng/mL] by the Dimension Vista Cardiac troponin assay).

          -  A positive pre-study drug/alcohol screen.

          -  A positive test for HIV antibody.

          -  Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or blood products
             in excess of 500 mL within 56 days.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.

          -  Exclusion Criteria for 24-Hour Screening Holter: Any symptomatic arrhythmia (except
             isolated extra systoles), Sustained cardiac arrhythmias (such as atrial fibrillation
             or flutter, supraventricular tachycardia (&gt;=10 consecutive beats), complete heart
             block). Non-sustained or sustained ventricular tachycardia (defined as &gt;= 3
             consecutive ventricular ectopic beats). Any conduction abnormality (including but not
             specific to left or right incomplete or complete bundle branch block, atrioventricular
             (AV) block [2nd degree or higher], Wolff-Parkinson-White [WPW] syndrome etc.). Sinus
             Pauses &gt; 3 seconds. 300 or more supraventricular ectopic beats in 24 hours. 250 or
             more ventricular ectopic beats in 24 hours.

          -  Any clinically significant abnormal echocardiogram finding. Abnormal echocardiogram
             findings should be discussed with the Medical Monitor prior to enrolment.

          -  Exclusion criteria for screening ECG (a single repeat is allowed for eligibility
             determination): Heart rate &lt;45 and &gt;100 beats per minute (bpm) (Males); &lt;50 and &gt;100
             bpm (females); For both Males and Females: PR Interval &lt;120 and &gt;220 msec, QRS
             duration &lt;70 and &gt;120 millisecond (msec); QTc interval (Fridericia's) &gt;450 msec.
             Notes: A heart rate from 100 to 110 bpm can be rechecked by ECG or vitals within 30
             minutes to verify eligibility. Evidence of previous myocardial infarction (Does not
             include ST segment changes associated with repolarization). Any conduction abnormality
             (including but not specific to left or right complete bundle branch block, AV block
             [2nd degree or higher], WPW syndrome). Sinus Pauses &gt; 3 seconds. Any significant
             arrhythmia which, in the opinion of the principal investigator or GlaxoSmithKline
             medical monitor, will interfere with the safety for the individual subject.
             Non-sustained or sustained ventricular tachycardia (&gt;= 3 consecutive ventricular
             ectopic beats).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21225</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://gsk-clinicalstudyregister.com/study/200912?search=study&amp;search_terms=200912#rs</url>
    <description>Results for study 200912 can be found on the GSK Clinical Study Register.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 10, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 13, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ritonavir</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Continuation Single Dose Escalation</keyword>
  <keyword>GSK2838232</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ritonavir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

