<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02288468</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P000568</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DRKS00007526</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02288468</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>One Pass thalamIc aNd subthalamIc stimulatiON</brief_title>
  <acronym>OPINION</acronym>
  <official_title>One Pass thalamIc aNd subthalamIc stimulatiON</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Freiburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston Scientific Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Freiburg</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Randomised, active controlled, double blinded (patient and observer blinded), monocentric
      trial with three treatments, three periods and six treatment sequences allocated according to
      a Williams design
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tremor is the most salient symptom of Parkinson's disease (IPS=idiopathic Parkinson
      syndrome). Other symptoms are bradykinesia, rigidity and postural instability. As much as 75%
      of patients with IPS show resting tremor. Initially, tremor is typically unilateral and only
      visible in stress situation. In the later stage of the disease it becomes bilateral. The
      OPINION trial aims at the investigation of a combined approach to thalamic/subthalamic deep
      brain stimulation (DBS) for the treatment of patients with tremor dominant IPS or patients
      with equivalent type IPS who perceive tremor to be their dominant symptom. The planned
      approach will for the first time allow for the direct comparison of each condition in a
      homogeneous patient population and will furthermore allow an intra-individual comparison of
      the different stimulation conditions (Ventral intermediate nucleus (Vim/DRT) - Subthalamic
      nucleus (STN) - Vim/DRT+STN) with the outcome parameter &quot;quality of life&quot;.

      Patients will be registered to the trial and will undergo screening procedures (for
      eligibility criteria please see Inclusion and Exclusion criteria). If the patient is eligible
      the Investigational Medical Device (IMD) will be implanted (which is the Vercise™ Deep Brain
      Stimulation System manufactured by Boston Scientific). After implantation the IMD will remain
      OFF for a period of 1 month.

      1 month after implantation treatment will be started. Patients will be randomized to one of
      the following 3 treatment groups: Subthalamic nucleus (STN) or Ventral intermediate nucleus
      (Vim/DRT) or combined stimulation (Vim/DRT+STN). Patients will undergo all three treatment
      groups each lasting 3 months. The patient is blinded meaning that study patients will not
      know what kind of treatment (e.g. mode/region of stimulation) they receive.

      10 months after implantation the final visit (end of study visit) will be performed. After
      end of the trial, further treatment will be performed at the Department of Stereotactic and
      Functional Neurosurgery in Freiburg (Germany) according to established guidelines. Devices
      will be monitored 3-6 monthly Patient's medications will be adjusted as to the level of best
      treatment adjunct to stimulation.

      Study endpoints (e.g. quality of life) will be evaluated by a blinded rater. In addition, an
      external video rating will be performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PDQ-39 total score</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline every 3 months up to 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in PDQ-39 total score from base value (i.e. mean value of screening and baseline visit) until end of each treatment (Vim/DRT-DBS, STN-DBS, combined STN+Vim/DRT-DBS) 3 months after start of each treatment up to 9 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in FTMTRS</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline every 3 months up to 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Fahn-Tolosa-Marin Tremor Rating Scale (FTMTRS) every three months after start of each treatment (Vim/DRT-DBS, STN-DBS, combined STN+Vim/DRT-DBS) compared to base value (i.e. mean value of screening and baseline visit)recording at the tremor peak in tremor analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in UPDRS motor score (part III, except items 20 &amp; 21)</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline every 3 months up to 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) motor score (part III, except items 20 &amp; 21) every three months after start of each treatment (Vim/DRT-DBS, STN-DBS, combined STN+Vim/DRT-DBS) compared to base value (i.e. mean value of screening and baseline visit)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in UPDRS (part III, tremor subscore (items 20 &amp; 21)) or total power of accelerometry recording at the tremor peak in tremor analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline every 3 months up to 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in UPDRS (part III, tremor subscore (items 20 &amp; 21)) or total power of accelerometry recording at the tremor peak in tremor analysis every three months after start of each treatment (Vim/DRT-DBS, STN-DBS, combined STN+Vim/DRT-DBS) compared to base value (i.e. mean value of screening and baseline visit)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression Scale (CGI-I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, baseline, then every 3 months until month 10</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of Clinical Global Impression Scale (CGI-I) at screening, at baseline (month 1) and then every three months after start of each treatment (Vim/DRT-DBS, STN-DBS, combined STN+Vim/DRT-DBS) until month 10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychiatric assessment: C-SSRS</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, baseline, then every 3 months until month 10</time_frame>
    <description>Psychiatric assessment: Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) at screening, at baseline (month 1) and then every three months after start of each treatment (Vim/DRT-DBS, STN-DBS, combined STN+Vim/DRT-DBS) until month 10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychiatric assessment: YMRS</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, baseline, then every 3 months until month 10</time_frame>
    <description>Psychiatric assessment: Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS) at screening, at baseline (month 1) and then every three months after start of each treatment (Vim/DRT-DBS, STN-DBS, combined STN+Vim/DRT-DBS) until month 10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychiatric assessment: MADRS</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, baseline, then every 3 months until month 10</time_frame>
    <description>Psychiatric assessment: Montgomery-Asberg Depression Scale (MADRS) at screening, at baseline (month 1) and then every three months after start of each treatment (Vim/DRT-DBS, STN-DBS, combined STN+Vim/DRT-DBS) until month 10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychiatric assessment: BIS-11</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening, baseline, then every 3 months until month 10</time_frame>
    <description>Psychiatric assessment: Barratt Impulsiveness Scale (BIS-11) at screening, at baseline (month 1) and then every three months after start of each treatment (Vim/DRT-DBS, STN-DBS, combined STN+Vim/DRT-DBS) until month 10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of (Serious) Adverse Events related to Investigational Medical Device, surgical procedures, stimulation settings and/or changes to medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Starting from implantation of device until last visit at month 10</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) related to Investigational Medical Device (IMD), surgical procedures, stimulation settings and/or surgical procedures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STN</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Deep Brain Stimulation of Nucleus subthalamicus with Vercise™ Deep Brain Stimulation System.
The STN will be typically reached with the most distal contacts of the DBS electrode (8 contact). Imaging studies (postop helical CT and re-fusion to planning MRI data) will allow for the identification of contacts located in the STN. We expect the STN to be typically covered by contacts 1-4 of the Vercise™ DBS lead. Typically, only the most superficial contacts (3,4) will be activated after a monopolar review of each contact. In this monopolar review the therapeutic widths of each contact will be tested for its effectiveness in tremor reduction, reduction of rigidity and bradykinesia. Typical settings will be: Frequency 130-180 Hz, pulse width 60-90 us, Amplitude 1-7 mA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vim/DRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Deep Brain Stimulation of Ventral intermediate nucleus with Vercise™ Deep Brain Stimulation System.
The thalamic target (Vim/DRT) will be typically reached with the proximal contacts. Imaging studies (postop helical CT and re-fusion to planning MRI data) will allow for the identification of contacts located the thalamic target. We expect the thalamic target to be typically covered by contacts 5-8 of the Vercise™ DBS lead. We will perform a monopolar review of each contact. In this monopolar review the therapeutic widths of each contact will be tested for its effectiveness in tremor reduction and the occurrence of side effects (typically capsular e.g. facial contraction). Typical settings will be: Frequency 130-180 Hz, pulse width 60-90 us, Amplitude 1-7 mA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STN+Vim/DRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combined Deep Brain Stimulation of Nucleus subthalamicus and Ventral intermediate nucleus with Vercise™ Deep Brain Stimulation System.
STN+Vim/DRT stimulation is essentially a combination of the previously described procedure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vercise™ Deep Brain Stimulation System</intervention_name>
    <description>The Vercise™ DBS System includes a Stimulator with DBS Leads for unilateral or bilateral stimulation. There are also DBS Extensions that allow the DBS Leads mounted in the skull to be extended to reach the Stimulator implanted near the clavicle.
The rechargeable Vercise DBS System utilizes current steering across eight contacts per DBS Lead to provide precise positioning of stimulation. The Stimulator is controlled by a handheld Remote Control, and can be interfaced with a Clinician's Programmer using the Bionic Navigator™ Software. Periodically, the Stimulator battery must be replenished with an RF (radiofrequency) charging device provided in the Patient DBS Charging Kit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>STN</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Vim/DRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>STN+Vim/DRT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vercise DBS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female patients aged ≥ 35 and ≤ 75 years with a life expectancy of at least 5
             years

          2. Patients with Parkinson's disease according to the criteria of the British Brain Bank
             as diagnosed by an in movement disorder specialized neurologist

          3. Parkinson patients are included with a medical treatment resistant and disabling
             resting and/or postural tremor as their major complaint and with a less prominent or
             absent hypokinetic-rigid component of their disease.

          4. Absence of postural instability (which would be aggravated under STN DBS)

          5. Hoehn &amp; Yahr stage 1-3. After stadium 3 patients will show increased incidence of
             falling that can be aggravated by (typical) STN DBS

          6. Disease duration for at least 2 years and routine DAT-scan shows clear indication for
             Parkinsonism and atypical Parkinson syndromes are ruled out by routine glucose (FDG)
             PET

          7. PDQ-39 to be completed within 42 days prior surgery

          8. Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Major Depression with suicidal thoughts

          2. Dementia (Mattis Dementia Rating Score ≤ 130)

          3. Patients with lifetime primary psychotic disorder, schizophrenia, or schizoaffective
             disorder

          4. Patients with acute psychosis as diagnosed by a psychiatrist

          5. Nursing care at home

          6. Unable to give written informed consent

          7. Surgical contraindications like deformed or displaced or not discernable target
             region, scarring after brain disease (infarction), need for continuous anticoagulation
             that cannot be bridged in order to obtain normal coagulation

          8. Patients with advanced stage cardiovascular disease

          9. Patients under immunosuppressive or chemotherapy because of malignant disease

         10. Patients who had previous intracranial surgery

         11. Patients who are already under DBS therapy

         12. Patients with aneurysm clips

         13. Patients with cochlear implants

         14. Simultaneous participation or previous participation within 30 days prior to start of
             screening in a clinical trial involving investigational medicinal product(s) or
             investigational medical device(s)

         15. Medications that are likely to cause interactions in the opinion of the investigator

         16. Known or persistent abuse of medication, drugs or alcohol

         17. Persons who are in a relationship of dependence/employment with the sponsor or the
             investigator

         18. Fertile women not using adequate contraceptive methods: female condoms, diaphragm or
             coil, each used in combination with spermicides; intra-uterine device; hormonal
             contraception in combination with a mechanical method of contraception;

         19. Current or planned pregnancy, nursing period

         20. Contraindications according to device instructions or Investigator's Brochure:

               -  Diathermy: Shortwave, microwave, and/or therapeutic ultrasound diathermy. The
                  energy generated by diathermy can be transferred to the Vercise™ DBS System,
                  causing tissue damage at the contact site resulting in severe patient injury or
                  death.

               -  Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI): Patients implanted with the Vercise™ DBS System
                  should not be subjected to MRI.

               -  Patient incapability: Patients who are unable to properly operate the Remote
                  Control and Charging System should not be implanted with the Vercise™ DBS System.

               -  Poor surgical risks: The Vercise™ DBS System is not recommended for patients who
                  - because of their primary disease or additional co-morbidities - are not likely
                  to benefit from the DBS system implantation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Volker Coenen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Freiburg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Freiburg - Medical Center - Dept. of Stereotactic and Functional Neurosurgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freiburg</city>
        <zip>79110</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hilker R, Benecke R, Deuschl G, Fogel W, Kupsch A, Schrader C, Sixel-Döring F, Timmermann L, Volkmann J, Lange M; German Deep Brain Stimulation Association. [Deep brain stimulation for Parkinson's disease. Consensus recommendations of the German Deep Brain Stimulation Association]. Nervenarzt. 2009 Jun;80(6):646-55. doi: 10.1007/s00115-009-2695-3. German.</citation>
    <PMID>19360386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Limousin P, Speelman JD, Gielen F, Janssens M. Multicentre European study of thalamic stimulation in parkinsonian and essential tremor. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 1999 Mar;66(3):289-96.</citation>
    <PMID>10084526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rehncrona S, Johnels B, Widner H, Törnqvist AL, Hariz M, Sydow O. Long-term efficacy of thalamic deep brain stimulation for tremor: double-blind assessments. Mov Disord. 2003 Feb;18(2):163-70.</citation>
    <PMID>12539209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krack P, Pollak P, Limousin P, Benazzouz A, Benabid AL. Stimulation of subthalamic nucleus alleviates tremor in Parkinson's disease. Lancet. 1997 Dec 6;350(9092):1675.</citation>
    <PMID>9400514</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Volkmann J, Daniels C, Witt K. Neuropsychiatric effects of subthalamic neurostimulation in Parkinson disease. Nat Rev Neurol. 2010 Sep;6(9):487-98. doi: 10.1038/nrneurol.2010.111. Epub 2010 Aug 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20680036</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fraix V, Pollak P, Moro E, Chabardes S, Xie J, Ardouin C, Benabid AL. Subthalamic nucleus stimulation in tremor dominant parkinsonian patients with previous thalamic surgery. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2005 Feb;76(2):246-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15654041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deuschl G, Schade-Brittinger C, Krack P, Volkmann J, Schäfer H, Bötzel K, Daniels C, Deutschländer A, Dillmann U, Eisner W, Gruber D, Hamel W, Herzog J, Hilker R, Klebe S, Kloss M, Koy J, Krause M, Kupsch A, Lorenz D, Lorenzl S, Mehdorn HM, Moringlane JR, Oertel W, Pinsker MO, Reichmann H, Reuss A, Schneider GH, Schnitzler A, Steude U, Sturm V, Timmermann L, Tronnier V, Trottenberg T, Wojtecki L, Wolf E, Poewe W, Voges J; German Parkinson Study Group, Neurostimulation Section. A randomized trial of deep-brain stimulation for Parkinson's disease. N Engl J Med. 2006 Aug 31;355(9):896-908. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2006 Sep 21;355(12):1289.</citation>
    <PMID>16943402</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Okun MS, Rodriguez RL, Foote KD, Sudhyadhom A, Bova F, Jacobson C, Bello B, Zeilman P, Fernandez HH. A case-based review of troubleshooting deep brain stimulator issues in movement and neuropsychiatric disorders. Parkinsonism Relat Disord. 2008 Nov;14(7):532-8. doi: 10.1016/j.parkreldis.2008.01.001. Epub 2008 Mar 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18325819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coenen VA, Allert N, Paus S, Kronenbürger M, Urbach H, Mädler B. Modulation of the cerebello-thalamo-cortical network in thalamic deep brain stimulation for tremor: a diffusion tensor imaging study. Neurosurgery. 2014 Dec;75(6):657-69; discussion 669-70. doi: 10.1227/NEU.0000000000000540.</citation>
    <PMID>25161000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>LANCE JW, SCHWAB RS, PETERSON EA. Action tremor and the cogwheel phenomenon in Parkinson's disease. Brain. 1963 Mar;86:95-110.</citation>
    <PMID>13928399</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coenen VA, Prescher A, Schmidt T, Picozzi P, Gielen FL. What is dorso-lateral in the subthalamic Nucleus (STN)?--a topographic and anatomical consideration on the ambiguous description of today's primary target for deep brain stimulation (DBS) surgery. Acta Neurochir (Wien). 2008 Nov;150(11):1163-5; discussion 1165. doi: 10.1007/s00701-008-0136-x. Epub 2008 Oct 29.</citation>
    <PMID>18958389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zrinzo L, Holl EM, Petersen EA, Limousin P, Foltynie T, Hariz MI. Skewering the subthalamic nucleus via a parietal approach. Stereotact Funct Neurosurg. 2011;89(2):70-5. doi: 10.1159/000323371. Epub 2011 Feb 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21293165</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coenen VA, Allert N, Mädler B. A role of diffusion tensor imaging fiber tracking in deep brain stimulation surgery: DBS of the dentato-rubro-thalamic tract (drt) for the treatment of therapy-refractory tremor. Acta Neurochir (Wien). 2011 Aug;153(8):1579-85; discussion 1585. doi: 10.1007/s00701-011-1036-z. Epub 2011 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>21553318</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coenen VA, Mädler B, Schiffbauer H, Urbach H, Allert N. Individual fiber anatomy of the subthalamic region revealed with diffusion tensor imaging: a concept to identify the deep brain stimulation target for tremor suppression. Neurosurgery. 2011 Apr;68(4):1069-75; discussion 1075-6. doi: 10.1227/NEU.0b013e31820a1a20. Erratum in: Neurosurgery. 2011 Jun;68(6):E1780-1.</citation>
    <PMID>21242831</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tomlinson CL, Stowe R, Patel S, Rick C, Gray R, Clarke CE. Systematic review of levodopa dose equivalency reporting in Parkinson's disease. Mov Disord. 2010 Nov 15;25(15):2649-53. doi: 10.1002/mds.23429. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21069833</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patel DM, Walker HC, Brooks R, Omar N, Ditty B, Guthrie BL. Adverse events associated with deep brain stimulation for movement disorders: analysis of 510 consecutive cases. Neurosurgery. 2015 Mar;11 Suppl 2:190-9. doi: 10.1227/NEU.0000000000000659.</citation>
    <PMID>25599204</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deuschl G, Bain P, Brin M. Consensus statement of the Movement Disorder Society on Tremor. Ad Hoc Scientific Committee. Mov Disord. 1998;13 Suppl 3:2-23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9827589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 6, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital Freiburg</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Dr. Volker Arnd Coenen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson's Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

