<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00183781</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01MH063051</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH063051</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>DAHBR AZ-A</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00183781</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of a Telephone Intervention Program in Improving Depression, Coping, and Family Functioning in HIV-Infected Individuals and Caregivers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Adapting to HIV Disease - A Family Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Butler Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Butler Hospital</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the effectiveness of the Family Intervention: Telephone Tracking
      (FITT) program in improving depression, coping, and family functioning in HIV-infected
      individuals and their caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Individuals who are newly diagnosed with HIV often experience a variety of social and
      psychological problems, which can leave them depressed and unable to cope with their disease.
      The complex financial, legal, and psychiatric issues that many HIV-infected individuals must
      face can be stressful and can negatively affect their health; they may miss doctors'
      appointments or fail to adhere to a strict HIV medication regimen. The combination of stress
      and inconsistent medical care can affect the immune system and potentially worsen HIV
      symptoms.

      Because of the multitude of stressors associated with HIV, HIV-infected individuals often
      rely on a network of family and friends for support; these caregivers, however, are often
      overwhelmed by their caregiver roles. They may experience helplessness, fear, and depression
      as a result of their added responsibilities. Family Intervention: Telephone Tracking (FITT)
      is a telephone-based intervention program that assists in identifying problems and resolving
      them through referrals to medical and community organizations that provide HIV-related
      support and services. It is also an educational resource that provides information on the
      many medical and psychological aspects of HIV infection. The main goal of FITT is to
      alleviate stress in both the HIV-infected individual and their support network by providing
      information and resources to help cope with HIV. The purpose of this study is to evaluate the
      effectiveness of FITT in improving family functioning, enhancing coping skills, and reducing
      depression in HIV-infected individuals and their caregivers.

      This 12-month study will enroll recently diagnosed HIV-infected individuals and one family
      member or friend who is identified as their primary caregiver. Each pair will be randomly
      assigned to either the FITT intervention group or to an assessment-only group that will not
      receive FITT. Individuals who are assigned to receive FITT will utilize the service for
      Months 1 through 6. HIV-infected participants in both groups will also receive regular
      medical care throughout the study. Outcome measurements will include self-assessments of
      depression, coping, and family functioning. In addition, participants receiving FITT will be
      asked to evaluate the effectiveness of the telephone intervention. All measurements will be
      assessed at baseline, and Months 3, 6, and 12.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Decreased depression; measured at baseline, and Months 3, 6, and 12</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improved coping; measured at baseline, and Months 3, 6, and 12</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improved family functioning; measured at baseline, and Months 3, 6, and 12</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of FITT intervention; measured at baseline, and Months 3, 6, and 12</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>270</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FITT: Family Intervention - Telephone Tracking</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Recently began HIV care

          -  Currently undergoing HIV care in one of the BRUNAP clinics

          -  Ability to co-enroll with a primary HIV informal caregiver

          -  English- or Spanish-speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Schizophrenia

          -  Lacks regular access to a telephone to receive calls
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Stein, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rhode Island Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Penelope Dennehy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Rhode Island Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rhode Island Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pirraglia PA, Bishop D, Herman DS, Trisvan E, Lopez RA, Torgersen CS, Van Hof AM, Anderson BJ, Miller I, Stein MD. Caregiver burden and depression among informal caregivers of HIV-infected individuals. J Gen Intern Med. 2005 Jun;20(6):510-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15987325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stein M, Herman DS, Trisvan E, Pirraglia P, Engler P, Anderson BJ. Alcohol use and sexual risk behavior among human immunodeficiency virus-positive persons. Alcohol Clin Exp Res. 2005 May;29(5):837-43.</citation>
    <PMID>15897729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 16, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 22, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Michael Stein, M.D./Principal Investigator</name_title>
    <organization>RI Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Telephone intervention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

