<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00186589</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BMT134</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>80109</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>BMT134</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00186589</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>90Y-IBRITUMOMAB Tiuxetan and AHCI With HD Chemotherapy and Autologous Transplantation for Relapsed or Resistant NHL</brief_title>
  <official_title>90Y-Ibritumomab Tiuxetan and Autologous Hematopoietic Cell Infusion Followed by High Dose Chemotherapy and Autologous Transplantation for Relapsed or Resistant Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biogen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To test a new way to approach hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for Relapsed or
      Resistant Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single center phase I dose escalation trial of a single course of IDEC-Y2B8
      (90Y-ibritumomab tiuxetan, Zevalin) with autologous peripheral blood progenitor cell infusion
      followed by high dose chemotherapy and AHCT for patients with relapsed or refractory B-cell
      NHL. In step one, an imaging dose of IDEC-In2B8 (111In- ibritumomab tiuxetan, Zevalin) will
      be followed one week later by IDEC-Y2B; both will be preceded by an infusion of 250 mg/m2
      rituximab. Imaging will be done immediately (within 1 hr), at 4 - 6 hours and at 1, 3, and 6
      days after 90Y-ibritumomab tiuxetan.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Response</measure>
    <time_frame>completed</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</condition>
  <condition>Blood and Marrow Transplant (BMT)</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>90Y Ibritumomab tiuxetan</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:Inclusion Criteria -- Step 1

        4.1 Histologically proven, recurrent or refractory, CD20+ B-cell NHL reviewed at SUMC.

        4.11 The definition of recurrent disease is: previous partial response (PR) or complete
        response (CR) to treatment followed by disease progression.

        4.12 The definition of refractory disease is: failure to achieve a PR or CR with or
        progression during primary induction therapy or subsequent salvage therapy. Patients who
        respond to treatment but progress within 60 days will also be considered refractory.

        4.13 CD20 expression may be determined by immunohistochemistry or flow cytometry. Whenever
        possible, confirmation of CD20+ status should be made on current, active disease.

        4.14 The definition of NHL will be made by SUMC pathologists using the World Health
        Organization Classification of Hematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues (Appendix A).

        4.15 The diagnosis should be made by excisional biopsy whenever possible. Biopsy of
        refractory or recurrent disease is preferred but fine needle aspirate with supportive
        morphology and immunohistochemistry is acceptable. Paraffin tissue for tissue array studies
        will be sought for every patient.

        4.2 Age 18-70 years

        4.21 Age will be based on actual date of birth.

        4.22 Pediatric patients are not eligible for this study because they are transplanted in a
        separate dedicated unit with their own protocols.

        4.3 ECOG performance status 0-2 (Appendix B)

        4.4 Computerized tomography scans of the chest, abdomen and pelvis within 4 weeks of
        registration. Assessment of response to last chemotherapy prior to registration is
        mandatory.

        4.41 Response will be assessed according to the international consensus criteria (Cheson et
        al. J Clin Oncol 17:1244, 1999)

        4.42 Standard definitions of the chest, abdomen and pelvis will be used for radiographic
        studies.

        4.5 Gallium scan or PET scan determination of disease within 4 weeks of registration is
        highly recommended.

        4.51 Gallium or PET scans will be whole body scans

        4.6 Bone marrow biopsy and cytogenetic analysis within 8 weeks of registration. Patients
        must have no or &lt;25% involvement of the intratrabecular bone marrow cellularity by NHL.

        4.7 Adequate (&gt; 4 x 10^6/kg CD34+) peripheral blood progenitor cells collected by
        apheresis.

        4.8 Women of child-bearing potential and sexually active males are strongly advised to use
        an accepted and effective method of birth control.

        4.9 No chemotherapy other than corticosteroids should be administered within 4 weeks of the
        initiation of protocol therapy.

        4.10 Pretreatment absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1000/mm^3 and platelet count &gt; 150,000/ mm^3.

        4.11 Patients must have a pretreatment serum bilirubin &lt; 2 x the institutional ULN,
        transaminases &lt; 2 x the institutional ULN, a serum creatinine &lt; 2 x the institutional ULN
        and measured or estimated creatinine clearance &gt; 60 cc/min by the following formula (all
        tests must be performed within 28 days prior to registration):

        Estimated Creatinine Clearance = (140 age)X WT(kg) X 0.85 if female X creatinine (mg/dl)

        4.12 Patients must have an EKG within 42 days prior to registration that shows no
        significant abnormalities that are suggestive of active cardiac disease.

        4.13 Patients must have a radionuclide ejection fraction &gt;45% within 42 days of
        registration.

        4.14 Patients must have a corrected diffusion capacity 70% or greater.

        4.15 Patients must be informed of the investigational nature of this study and must sign
        and give written informed consent in accordance with institutional and federal guidelines.

        Inclusion Criteria -- Step 2

        4.30 Absolute neutrophil count recovery to &gt; 1000/mm^3 and platelet recovery count to &gt;
        100,000/ mm^3.

        4.31 Corrected diffusing capacity &gt; 60%.

        4.32 Resting ejection fraction of &gt; 45%.

        4.33 Serum bilirubin &lt; 2, SGOT (AST) &lt; 2 x ULN, SGPT (ALT) &lt; 2 x ULN. Creatinine &lt; 2 x the
        ULN and measured or estimated creatinine clearance &gt; 60 cc/min.

        Exclusion Criteria:Exclusion Criteria - Step 1

        4.16 Patients with known allergy to etoposide or a history of Grade 3 hemorrhagic cystitis
        with cyclophosphamide are not eligible.

        4.17 No prior malignancy is allowed except adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell
        skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer or other cancer for which the patients has been
        disease-free for five years.

        4.18 Patients known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive are ineligible
        because the concern for opportunistic infection and hematologic reserve are considered to
        be significantly greater in this population. The antibody test for HIV must be performed
        within 42 days of registration.

        4.19 Patients requiring therapy for coronary artery disease, cardiomyopathy, dysrhythmia,
        or congestive heart failure are not eligible.

        4.20 Pregnant or breast-feeding women are ineligible due to the known birth defects
        associated with the treatments used in this study.

        4.21 Patients with prior radiotherapy to &gt;25% of the active marrow are excluded.

        4.22 Patients treated previously with radioimmunotherapy are excluded.

        4.23 Patients with pleural effusion or ascites are excluded.

        4.24 Patients may have received prior rituximab but not within the past 4 weeks.

        4.25 Patients with prior autologous transplantation are ineligible.

        4.26 Patients with CNS disease are ineligible.

        Exclusion Criteria - Step 2

        4.33 Drop in diffusing capacity of &gt;25% from study entry.

        4.34 Drop in resting ejection fraction &gt; 20%.

        4.35 Failure to recover peripheral blood counts (ANC &gt; 1000/mm^3 and platelet recovery
        count to &gt; 100,000/mm^3 within 4 weeks after radioimmunotherapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandra Jeane Horning</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 16, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 5, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 5, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Sandra Jeane Horning</name_title>
    <organization>Stanford University School of Medicine</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

