<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00183053</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AG0050</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01AG025285</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00183053</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Proximity Alarms to Reduce Patient Falls</brief_title>
  <official_title>Trial of Proximity Alarms to Reduce Patient Falls</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test an intervention to introduce and implement proximity
      alarms on the risk of falls in hospitalized patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Proximity alarm systems are promoted as an approach to reduce falls and decrease use of
      physical restraints in hospitals, but they have not been tested rigorously. This study will
      implement proximity alarms at Methodist-University Hospital (M-UH), a 652-bed urban community
      hospital in Memphis, Tennessee. The hospital provides primary to tertiary care to a diverse
      adult patient population. The group randomized trial will be conducted on 16 25-bed general
      medical-surgical nursing units at M-UH. Nursing units will be randomized within blocks of 2
      based on rates of falls that occur during an initial 3-month observation period. Over a
      15-month intervention, 8 nursing units will be randomized to receive the alarm-based
      intervention, and 8 will utilize existing nursing care methods to minimize falls.
      Intervention units will receive an adequate supply of proximity alarm monitoring systems to
      apply to all patients considered by nursing staff to be at high risk for falls. An
      implementation team, consisting of a nurse-champion, geriatrician and biomedical
      instrumentation specialist, will train and conduct regular follow-up on intervention units to
      address technical issues related to use of the alarms. The primary outcome measure, patient
      falls, will be ascertained prospectively by a nurse-manager using a method developed to
      collect patient (e.g., orientation and postural blood pressure) and environmental data
      collected in a standardized manner. The primary aim of the study is to determine whether
      proximity alarm monitoring reduces falls. The study has been designed to test the hypothesis
      that patient falls will be 25% lower on intervention units compared to control units. The
      secondary aims are to determine whether proximity alarm monitoring reduces the use of
      physical restraints, or decreases patient care costs. This will be the first methodologically
      sound study to evaluate this promising approach to reducing falls in hospitals. Whether or
      not alarms successfully reduce falls, findings from this study have the potential to widely
      impact purchasing decisions and clinical practice related to fall prevention in acute-care
      settings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient falls over 15 months</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Restraint use</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>patient care costs over 15 months</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10000</enrollment>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BedEx Patient Occupancy Monitoring System</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient admitted to one of 16 study units at Methodist University Hospital
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ronald I. Shorr, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Aging &amp; Geriatric Research, University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Methodist-University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tideiksaar R, Feiner CF, Maby J. Falls prevention: the efficacy of a bed alarm system in an acute-care setting. Mt Sinai J Med. 1993 Nov;60(6):522-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8121429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morse JM. Enhancing the safety of hospitalization by reducing patient falls. Am J Infect Control. 2002 Oct;30(6):376-80.</citation>
    <PMID>12360147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bates DW, Pruess K, Souney P, Platt R. Serious falls in hospitalized patients: correlates and resource utilization. Am J Med. 1995 Aug;99(2):137-43.</citation>
    <PMID>7625418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morse JM, Black C, Oberle K, Donahue P. A prospective study to identify the fall-prone patient. Soc Sci Med. 1989;28(1):81-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2928815</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oliver D, Britton M, Seed P, Martin FC, Hopper AH. Development and evaluation of evidence based risk assessment tool (STRATIFY) to predict which elderly inpatients will fall: case-control and cohort studies. BMJ. 1997 Oct 25;315(7115):1049-53.</citation>
    <PMID>9366729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 16, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 29, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 29, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 2, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Hospitalization</keyword>
  <keyword>Fall Risk</keyword>
  <keyword>Frailty</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

