<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00183027</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AG0044</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>3U01AG020480</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00183027</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dietary Energy Restriction and Metabolic Aging in Humans</brief_title>
  <official_title>Dietary Energy Restriction and Metabolic Aging in Humans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to develop an effective calorie restricted diet.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a 3-phase investigation designed to test two caloric restriction (CR) regimens
      for participant compliance and variability in metabolic and physiologic effects. Initially,
      and through phase 1 (1 week pre-phase, and 6 weeks phase 1), participants will maintain
      normal habits at home.

      Then for phase 2 (24 weeks), the 44 participants will be randomized to one of two diets (Diet
      HG or Diet LG), which they will consume at either 70% or 90% of baseline energy intake. The
      participants randomized to 90% CR (both diets) will form the control group. All food will be
      provided during this phase, and participants will be required to attend weekly group or
      individual meetings with the behavioral counselor and dietitian, and perform regular
      self-monitoring.

      During phase 3 (24 weeks), participants will prepare their own food at home according to
      their CR regimen and will eat to maintain the CR specified for phase 2. They will continue to
      attend the weekly meetings and to perform self-monitoring.

      Diet HG: a diet based on the USDA Food Guide Pyramid, but with additional emphasis on
      adequate fiber and low energy density foods, including use of whole grains rather than
      refined carbohydrates, limited liquid calories, high variety of low energy items such as
      fruits and vegetables and low variety of high-energy discretionary foods.

      Diet LG: a modification of the HG diet in which low energy density is maintained even though
      the percent of energy from fat and protein is increased (by increased use of high-protein
      foods and foods with high water content) and use of different carbohydrate sources and
      physically intact food items (whole grains, raw fruits and vegetables) to further lower
      glycemic load through reducing the glycemic index (GI). High fiber intakes, low energy
      density, limited use of liquid calories, high variety of low energy items such as fruits and
      vegetables and low variety of high-energy discretionary foods will be the same as for the HG
      diet.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in body weight, body fatness and total energy expenditure at baseline, 3, 6, and 12 months of caloric restriction (CR).</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in blood pressure, insulin sensitivity and secretion, resting metabolic rate, bone mineral density, disease incidence, cognitive function, immune function, oxidative stress parameters, fertility hormones at baseline, 6, and 12 months</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>44</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dietary composition and energy intake</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy men and women (based on standard laboratory tests and a screening examination)

          -  20-42 years of age

          -  BMI in the range 25-29.9 kg/m2

          -  Proportional representation of minorities in the Greater Boston Area (7 percent Black,
             11 percent Hispanic, 82 percent non-Hispanic white)

          -  Able to accurately complete a food record

          -  Stage of change &gt;1 for weight loss and changing dietary intake

          -  Must have an immediate adult family member who is supportive of weight loss

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known serious disorders that affect longevity, energy metabolism, body composition and
             immune responsiveness, including diabetes, cancer, heart disease, cachexia, eating
             disorders (anorexia and bulimia and any vomiting for means of weight control),
             depression, alcoholism, inflammatory disorders and AIDS, and individuals taking
             medicine that is anticipated to influence lifespan or energy metabolism

          -  Abnormal kidney function as assessed by serum creatinine, BUN and urinalysis, and
             abnormal liver function as assessed by SGPT, SGOT alkaline phosphatase, and bilirubin,
             abnormal normal thyroid function as assessed by serum T4 and TSH and fasting serum
             glucose levels &lt;125 mg/dl

          -  Smoking, highly restrained eating, reported endurance training (participation in
             sports or training &gt;12 hours per week), alcohol intake of 14 oz. per week or more,
             major medical and/or psychiatric disorders, plans to have a child within 3 years (1
             year for Pilot study), past childbearing (for women) within the last 2 years, or
             breastfeeding within the past year

          -  Amputees

          -  Have required treatment for any psychiatric disorder

          -  Gained or lost &gt;15 lb weight within the past year, or taking medications known or
             suspected to have an important influence on lifespan, energy metabolism, body
             composition or immune function

          -  Early death from cardiovascular diseases, cancer, or a diabetes-related illness
             (before the age of 45 years) in one or both of the parents

          -  Unable to remain in the program for at least 1 year, or unsuitable for home-based
             programs (including individuals reporting binge eating disorders or clinical
             depression, and women intending to become pregnant)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>42 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan B. Roberts, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tufts University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jean Mayer USDA Human Nutrition Research Center on Aging at Tufts University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hadley EC, Dutta C, Finkelstein J, Harris TB, Lane MA, Roth GS, Sherman SS, Starke-Reed PE. Human implications of caloric restriction's effects on aging in laboratory animals: an overview of opportunities for research. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2001 Mar;56 Spec No 1:5-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12088212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee IM, Blair SN, Allison DB, Folsom AR, Harris TB, Manson JE, Wing RR. Epidemiologic data on the relationships of caloric intake, energy balance, and weight gain over the life span with longevity and morbidity. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2001 Mar;56 Spec No 1:7-19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12088215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weindruch R, Keenan KP, Carney JM, Fernandes G, Feuers RJ, Floyd RA, Halter JB, Ramsey JJ, Richardson A, Roth GS, Spindler SR. Caloric restriction mimetics: metabolic interventions. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2001 Mar;56 Spec No 1:20-33. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12088209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mobbs CV, Bray GA, Atkinson RL, Bartke A, Finch CE, Maratos-Flier E, Crawley JN, Nelson JF. Neuroendocrine and pharmacological manipulations to assess how caloric restriction increases life span. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2001 Mar;56 Spec No 1:34-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12088210</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poehlman ET, Turturro A, Bodkin N, Cefalu W, Heymsfield S, Holloszy J, Kemnitz J. Caloric restriction mimetics: physical activity and body composition changes. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2001 Mar;56 Spec No 1:45-54. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12088211</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allison DB, Miller RA, Austad SN, Bouchard C, Leibel R, Klebanov S, Johnson T, Harrison DE. Genetic variability in responses to caloric restriction in animals and in regulation of metabolism and obesity in humans. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2001 Mar;56 Spec No 1:55-65. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12088213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Felson DT, Zhang Y, Hannan MT, Kannel WB, Kiel DP. Alcohol intake and bone mineral density in elderly men and women. The Framingham Study. Am J Epidemiol. 1995 Sep 1;142(5):485-92.</citation>
    <PMID>7677127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pittas AG, Das SK, Hajduk CL, Golden J, Saltzman E, Stark PC, Greenberg AS, Roberts SB. A low-glycemic load diet facilitates greater weight loss in overweight adults with high insulin secretion but not in overweight adults with low insulin secretion in the CALERIE Trial. Diabetes Care. 2005 Dec;28(12):2939-41.</citation>
    <PMID>16306558</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 16, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 8, 2006</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 8, 2006</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 9, 2006</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Dietary restriction</keyword>
  <keyword>Caloric restriction</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

