<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00187811</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00/0139</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00187811</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Safety and Efficacy of Photodynamic Therapy for Femoral Artery Stenosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomised Controlled Trial of Adjuvant Photodynamic Therapy to Reduce Restenosis After Percutaneous Transluminal Angioplasty to the Superficial Femoral Angioplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University College London Hospitals</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>UCL/UCLH Clinical Research and Development Fund</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University College London Hospitals</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rstenosis is common after angioplasty of atherosclerotic disease of the femoral artery. Pilot
      study data suggests that adjuvant photodynamic therapy, using delta amino kleavulinic acid as
      a photosensitiserr is feasible and safe. This study will examine safety in a larger
      population and,if recruitment numbers allow, efficacy will be assessed.

      Hypothesis:

      ALA photodynamic therapy is safe and well tolerated as an adjuvant to angioplasty as a
      treatment for femoral artery atherosclerotic stenosis or occlusion. A secondary endpoint will
      be sought : hypothesis : PDT will reduce in restenosis rates following adjuvant photodynamic
      therapy compared with standard balloon angioplasty in the treatment of superficial femoral
      arterial disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Percutaneous Transluminal Angioplasty (PTA) is well recognised as a treatment for obstructive
      vascular disease. Despite an initial high procedural success the technique is limited by the
      subsequent development of restenosis in up to 50% of patients between 3 and 6 months. ,

      The pathological hallmark of restenosis has long been considered to be the development of
      neointimal hyperplasia consisting of smooth muscle cells and extracellular matrix. We now
      realise however that both elastic recoil of the vessel and the concept of remodelling are
      important in determining the overall response of the vessel to injury. Remodelling involves a
      geometric change in the vessel such that the maximum arterial dimension may increase
      (positive remodelling) or decrease (negative remodelling). , ,

      Despite extensive research no pharmacological or interventional strategy has been shown to
      have an overwhelming effect on restenosis rates after angioplasty. Recently attention has
      been focused on the potential of intraluminal radiation therapy (Brachytherapy) and whilst
      this technique has shown considerable promise there are concerns regarding the long term
      complications and safety of the ionising radiation for non-malignant disease with reports of
      vessel wall damage after treatment. ,

      Photodynamic therapy is a novel technique that involves the activation of a previously
      administered photosensitising agent by non thermal laser light. This results in the
      generation of reactive oxidative products with resulting tissue effects. It is a technique
      that has been used in the treatment of a variety of malignancies but the realisation that it
      may influence the response of the vessel wall after balloon injury has been particularly
      promising. 5 Aminolaevulinic acid (ALA) is a relatively new photosensitising agent which is
      converted to an active metabolite, Protoporphyrin IX (PPIX) in the biosynthesis of haem. In
      small animal models photodynamic therapy has been shown to cause medial smooth muscle cell
      depletion and to reduce the degree of neointimal hyperplasia after injury with no detrimental
      effects on the mechanical integrity of the vessel wall. , Large animal work using a swine
      model has confirmed these findings and has also demonstrated that favourable vessel wall
      remodelling occurs after PDT. Repopulation of the media with smooth muscle cells, after early
      depletion, has also been demonstrated which is likely to be important when we consider the
      long term effects of this treatment on the vessel wall.

      The use of a large animal model enabled the development of an endovascular system for the
      delivery of laser light. As a result, and in the light of the findings from large animal
      studies, it has now been possible to conduct a pilot clinical study looking at the safety and
      efficacy of adjuvant PDT in patients undergoing repeat PTA for superficial femoral artery
      (SFA) disease who had restenosed less than 6 months after an earlier angioplasty. In this
      study it was shown that all patients were asymptomatic 6 months after the procedure with
      adjuvant PDT there were no arterial or procedural complications. These findings were
      supported by improvements in non-invasive endpoints and the abscence of significant
      restenosis as assessed by digital subtraction angiography.

      These results were encouraging and we are now in a position to conduct a randomised clinical
      trial looking at standard balloon angioplasty with and without adjuvant photodynamic therapy
      in the treatment of peripheral vascular disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Death</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedural complications (occlusion, haematoma)</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arterial complications: aneursym, thrombus</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical revascularisation (Emergency/Elective)</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Repeat PTA</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Limb loss</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reccurence of claudication</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>&gt; 50% loss of initial lumen gain on duplex scanning</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PSVR &gt; 2.0</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fall in ABPI</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measured Pre procedure, at 24h then at 1, 3 and 6 months.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A final follow up is planned at 3-5 years</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>120</enrollment>
  <condition>Atherosclerotic Narrowing of the Superficial Femoral Artery</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerotic Occlusion of the Superficial Femoral Artery</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Delta amino leavulinic acid photodynamic therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of claudication suggested by preliminary Duplex study to be due to
             superficial femoral artery stenosis or occlusion

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous surgical graft to superficial femoral artery Known liver dysfunction Previous
             history of photosensitivity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean R McEwan, MB ChB FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University College, London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen Bown, PhD FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University College, London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University College London NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1P 9LL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 9, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 9, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 16, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 28, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 28, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 29, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Angioplasty,</keyword>
  <keyword>Restenosis,</keyword>
  <keyword>Photodynamic therapy</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

