<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00560001</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PHS 2003-2 FAST TRACK</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5R42AG021844-02</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00560001</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MD.2 Medication Dispenser Medication Adherence Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Medication Dispenser: MD2: Improving Health Outcomes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Interactive Medical Developments</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Iowa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Department of Health and Human Services</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Interactive Medical Developments</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to quantify the benefits of using the MD.2 on health outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A sizeable portion of admissions to hospital and even nursing homes can be avoided if
      individuals with medication management problems were provided assistive devices to assist
      with their medications. The MD.2 medication dispenser and monitoring system was developed by
      Interactive Medical Developments LC and may offer increased support to the elderly with fewer
      human resources and a substantially reduced cost to the public health system. A rigorous
      evaluation of this technology has not been conducted. The objective of this Phase III
      clinical trial (Phase II of this STTR Fast Track Application) is to quantify the benefits of
      using the MD.2 on health outcomes. The specific aims are to: (1) Quantify healthcare
      utilization including hospitalizations and emergency room visits for MD.2 clients compared to
      control clients, (2) Determine the length of time in case management for MD.2 clients
      compared to control clients, (3) Measure changes in caregiver burden between those with the
      MD.2 and those with usual medication routines and (4) Determine if cognitive and functional
      characteristics influence compliance rates among the MD.2 clients and control clients. This
      study will be conducted in all counties in four of the Area Agencies on Aging in Iowa (who
      participated in the Phase I study), with the Veteran's Administration(VA)in Iowa, and with
      Area Agencies on Aging in Illinois. One hundred and fifty clients will be randomized to
      receive the MD.2 and 150 clients will be randomized to the control group. Primary caregivers
      for these 300 subjects will also be recruited. Nurses employed by Interactive Medical
      Developments LC will collect all data. From homecare charts/claims, age, sex, residence,
      living status, social support, activities of daily living, instrumental activities of daily
      living, cognition, medical conditions and medication lists will be obtained. Enrolled
      subjects will also complete an interviewer-administered survey of the Geriatric Depression
      Scale, SF-12 Health Status Inventory, self-reported medication compliance and recent
      hospitalizations and emergency room visits. Caregivers will complete the Caregiver Burden
      Interview. Poisson regression and Cox proportional hazards models will be the primary
      statistical approaches.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2008</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The rate of hospitalizations and emergency room visits will be compared between the MD.2 and control clients</measure>
    <time_frame>per month (30 client days) over 6 consecutive months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the length of time in case management for MD.2 clients to control clients.</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 6 consecutive months.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure changes in caregiver stressors and burden between those with the MD.2 and those with their usual medication routine.</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 6 consecutive months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine if cognitive and functional characteristics influence compliance rates among the frail elderly using the MD.2.</measure>
    <time_frame>Over 6 consecutive months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Frail Elderly</condition>
  <condition>Medication Errors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Those subjects that receive an MD.2 Medication Dispenser</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control subjects that do not receive an MD.2 Medication Dispenser, but continue to take their medications utilizing standard care, such as pill boxes, etc.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MD.2 Medication Dispenser</intervention_name>
    <description>For those subjects receiving an MD.2 Medication Dispenser, the machine organizes medications and provides verbal and auditory explicit reminders for individuals to take their medications. At the scheduled time, the patient gets a series of reminders. The patient is then expected to push a single button to dispense a pre-filled medication cup. An automatic record is kept of the subject's medication adherence. Interviewer-administered surveys of the Geriatric Depression Scale, SF-12 Health Status Inventory, self-reported medication compliance and recent hospitalizations and emergency room visits will be given. Caregivers will complete the Caregiver Burden Interview.</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        A client must:

          -  Be coming up for regular review in Case or Medication Management

          -  Require medication management services

          -  Have two or more doses of medication per day

          -  Have someone to fill MD.2

          -  Be in independent living (may be assisted living with NO medication management
             services)

          -  Be expected to live through follow-up period of six months

          -  Have an active phone line that can be utilized by the MD.2 system.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        A client cannot have/or be the following:

          -  Have someone available to administer medications for every dose

          -  Have someone in household who is likely to interfere with MD.2

          -  Blind AND deaf

          -  Eligible for hospice

          -  An MD.2 currently
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Farris, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Iowa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen Farris, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>319-384-4516</phone>
    <email>karen-farris@uiowa.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Julie Lang, M.S.; M.B.A</last_name>
    <phone>319-384-2815</phone>
    <email>julie-lang@uiowa.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Iowa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iowa City</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52242-1101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie Lang, M.S.; M.B.A.</last_name>
      <phone>319-384-2815</phone>
      <email>julie-lang@uiowa.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen Farris, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stuck AE, Beers MH, Steiner A, Aronow HU, Rubenstein LZ, Beck JC. Inappropriate medication use in community-residing older persons. Arch Intern Med. 1994 Oct 10;154(19):2195-200.</citation>
    <PMID>7944840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aparasu RR, Mort JR. Inappropriate prescribing for the elderly: beers criteria-based review. Ann Pharmacother. 2000 Mar;34(3):338-46. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10917382</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhan C, Sangl J, Bierman AS, Miller MR, Friedman B, Wickizer SW, Meyer GS. Potentially inappropriate medication use in the community-dwelling elderly: findings from the 1996 Medical Expenditure Panel Survey. JAMA. 2001 Dec 12;286(22):2823-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11735757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gray SL, Mahoney JE, Blough DK. Adverse drug events in elderly patients receiving home health services following hospital discharge. Ann Pharmacother. 1999 Nov;33(11):1147-53.</citation>
    <PMID>10573310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kimura H. Effects of caffeine on cleavage delay of sea urchin eggs induced by ethidium bromide or puromycin. J Radiat Res. 1975 Jun;16(2):125-31.</citation>
    <PMID>1171974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bero LA, Lipton HL, Bird JA. Characterization of geriatric drug-related hospital readmissions. Med Care. 1991 Oct;29(10):989-1003.</citation>
    <PMID>1921531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chrischilles EA, Segar ET, Wallace RB. Self-reported adverse drug reactions and related resource use. A study of community-dwelling persons 65 years of age and older. Ann Intern Med. 1992 Oct 15;117(8):634-40.</citation>
    <PMID>1530194</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farris KD, Kelly MW, Tryon J. Clock drawing test and medication complexity index as indicators of medication management capacity: a pilot study. J Am Pharm Assoc (Wash). 2003 Jan-Feb;43(1):78-81.</citation>
    <PMID>12585756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Col N, Fanale JE, Kronholm P. The role of medication noncompliance and adverse drug reactions in hospitalizations of the elderly. Arch Intern Med. 1990 Apr;150(4):841-5.</citation>
    <PMID>2327844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiMatteo MR, Giordani PJ, Lepper HS, Croghan TW. Patient adherence and medical treatment outcomes: a meta-analysis. Med Care. 2002 Sep;40(9):794-811.</citation>
    <PMID>12218770</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buckwalter KC, Wakefield BJ, Hanna B, Lehmann J. New technology for medication adherence: electronically managed medication dispensing system. J Gerontol Nurs. 2004 Jul;30(7):5-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15287321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maddigan SL, Farris KB, Keating N, Wiens CA, Johnson JA. Predictors of older adults' capacity for medication management in a self-medication program: a retrospective chart review. J Aging Health. 2003 May;15(2):332-52.</citation>
    <PMID>12795276</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morisky DE, Green LW, Levine DM. Concurrent and predictive validity of a self-reported measure of medication adherence. Med Care. 1986 Jan;24(1):67-74.</citation>
    <PMID>3945130</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zarit SH, Reever KE, Bach-Peterson J. Relatives of the impaired elderly: correlates of feelings of burden. Gerontologist. 1980 Dec;20(6):649-55.</citation>
    <PMID>7203086</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 15, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 15, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 19, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 7, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 7, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 8, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>frail elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>medication errors</keyword>
  <keyword>patient compliance &amp; attitudes</keyword>
  <keyword>guideline adherence</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

