<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00567866</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>72900</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00567866</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Methamphetamine-Quetiapine Interactions in Humans</brief_title>
  <official_title>Methamphetamine-Quetiapine Interaction in Humans: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Arkansas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Arkansas</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test the ability of a medicine (Quetiapine) that is used to treat
      schizophrenia or bipolar disorder to reduce the effects of methamphetamine that make it
      difficult for users to stop using it. This study will test the ability of a medicine that is
      used to treat schizophrenia or bipolar disorder to reduce the effects of methamphetamine that
      make it difficult for users to stop using it. The investigator thinks quetiapine will lessen
      the effects of methamphetamine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The specific goal of this project is to examine whether quetiapine will alter the behavioral
      effects of methamphetamine without producing major cardiovascular changes or toxic effects
      under controlled laboratory conditions. This goal will be accomplished using a
      methamphetamine challenge procedure in which quetiapine will be given orally prior to
      intravenous (iv) methamphetamine administration. This will allow rapid and systematic
      evaluation of the therapeutic potential of this medication.

      Results of this drug-interaction study will help determine further investigations of the
      clinical efficacy of this and other dopamine-active agents. We hypothesize that quetiapine
      will reduce the self-reported, performance and cardiovascular effects of methamphetamine.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study was terminated due to insufficient funds
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Responses to Methamphetamine following predosing with placebo or test article.</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to drug administration, and 10 minutes post-drug administration and then hourly for 9 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physiological Responses to methamphetamine following predosing of placebo or test article</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-drug dosing, 5, 20, 35, and 50 minutes postdosing until 4 hours postodose, and then twice hourly until the seventh hour</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Methamphetamine Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo -50 mg quetiapine- 100 mg quetiapine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>50 mg quetiapine -100 mg quetiapine- placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>50 mg quetiapine -placebo- 100 mg quetiapine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quetiapine</intervention_name>
    <description>50 or 100 mg of quetiapine orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Must be between the ages of 18-50.

          2. Must have experience with IV methamphetamine use, with self-reported recent history of
             weekly use being greater than the total administered in the study. Recent use will be
             confirmed by a urine toxicology screen positive for amphetamines. We will recruit
             moderate to frequent users of methamphetamine. Moderate use is defined as use from
             once or twice every six weeks to weekly. Frequent users are defined as individuals who
             use greater than weekly.

          3. Must have recent use confirmed by a urine toxicology screen positive for amphetamines.

          4. Must not be seeking treatment for methamphetamine abuse/dependence.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Ill health (major cardiovascular, renal, endocrine, hepatic disorder).

          2. Current diagnosis of other drug or alcohol physical dependence (other than nicotine or
             caffeine).

          3. History of major organic psychiatric disorder (psychosis, schizophrenia, bipolar,
             mania) or significant psychiatric symptoms at the time of evaluation for study
             participation, including suicidal ideation.

          4. Pregnancy, plans to become pregnant or fertile women without adequate means of
             contraception.

          5. Present or recent use of over-the-counter or prescription psychoactive drug or drugs
             that would have major interaction with drugs to be tested.

          6. Medical contraindication to or prior serious adverse effects from methamphetamine or
             stimulants (i.e., seizures, cardiac arrest) or medical contraindication to test agents
             (see risks section). Significant physical or psychiatric illness which might impair
             the ability to safely complete the study or that might be complicated by the study
             drugs, including prior seizures (after age 8) or other active neurological disease or
             clinically significant abnormalities on physical examination or screening laboratory
             values.

          7. Current enrollment in a methamphetamine, alcohol, or other drug treatment program or
             current legal problems relating to methamphetamine, alcohol, or other drug use,
             including awaiting trial or supervision by a parole or probation officer

          8. Body Mass Index &gt;30 or &lt;18

          9. Currently trying to quit methamphetamine use or seeking treatment for methamphetamine
             use

         10. History of serious adverse event or hypersensitivity to methamphetamine or other study
             drugs

         11. Currently taking any medication (including highly active antiretroviral therapy
             (HAART) for HIV) other than over-the-counter nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory
             medications, topical medications, inhaled asthma therapy, and over-the-counter
             nonsedating antihistamines

         12. Use within the last month of the Vicks Nasal Inhaler or medications that are
             metabolized to methamphetamine (e.g. selegiline)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Brooks Gentry, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Arkansas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 12, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 12, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Carole Hamon</name_title>
    <organization>University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Quetiapine Fumarate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methamphetamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

