<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02906787</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>825425</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA206058</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02906787</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Behavioral Activation for Smoking Cessation and the Prevention of Post-Cessation Weight Gain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Behavioral Activation for Smoking Cessation and the Prevention of Post-Cessation Weight Gain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to better understand (1) why people gain weight when
      they quit smoking and (2) whether certain types of smoking cessation (i.e. quit smoking)
      counseling combined with the nicotine patch help people quit smoking and gain less weight.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized clinical trial of the efficacy of a behavioral activation intervention
      to smoking cessation and to post-cessation weight gain (BAS+) plus transdermal nicotine (TN)
      compared to standard smoking cessation counseling (SC) plus TN in treatment-seeking smokers.
      After completing an Intake Visit (~week -3), eligible smokers will be randomized (stratified
      by nicotine dependence, BMI and gender) to participate in 8 individual sessions of BAS+ or SC
      over a 10-week treatment period with two sessions prior to the target quit date (weeks -2,
      -1) and six sessions post-target quit date (TQD [week 0] and weeks 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8).
      Standard, 8-week; open-label TN will begin on the TQD. Moderators will be assessed
      pre-treatment. Mediating mechanisms will be assessed before, during, and at the end of
      treatment (EOT, week 8). Smoking will be assessed by self-report and biochemically confirmed
      (Carbon Monoxide [CO] &lt; 5) at all in-center visits after quitting, at EOT (week 8), and at
      the 12- and 26-week follow-ups. Weight will be assessed at these same time points. Food
      intake will be measured by three consecutive days of 24-hour food recalls at Baseline [week
      -2] and 4-, 8-, and 12- and 26-weeks post-TQD. Smoking cessation and post-cessation weight
      gain (PCWG) are the primary outcomes and food intake is a secondary outcome at 26-weeks
      post-TQD. Consistent with intent-to-treat (ITT) analyses, the investigators will measure
      smoking cessation and weight gain in the full sample at the 26-week follow-up, evaluating a
      smoking status by treatment interaction for the PCWG analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight Change</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Study Completion (Intake Visit, Baseline Visit, Pre-Quit Visit , Target Quit Date Visit, Mid-Tx. 1 Visit, Mid-Tx 2 Visit, Mid-Tx 3 Visit, Mid-Tx 4 Visit , End of Treatment, 12-Week Follow-Up Visit, and 26-Week Follow-Up Visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Weight will be measured by a physician's scale (pounds) at the beginning of every in-person visit through study completion. Participants will be wearing light clothing without shoes. Pre-cessation weight will be computed as the average of weights at the Intake and Baseline Visits prior to any change in smoking behavior. Weight change from Baseline to the 26-week follow-up will serve as a primary weight outcome variable.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Smoking Cessation</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Study Completion (End of Treatment Visit, 12-Week Follow-Up Visit, and 26-Week Follow-Up Visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Smoking abstinence (primary outcome) will be assessed and biochemically verified at the End of Treatment Visit (week 8), at 12 and 26 weeks after the target quit date. The primary smoking outcome variable will be 7-day point prevalence abstinence (no smoking, not even a puff, for at least 7 days prior to the assessment) biochemically verified by CO &lt; 5 ppm at End of Treatment (week 8), and by saliva cotinine &lt; 15ng/ml at the 12- and 26-week follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Through Study Completion (Baseline Visit, Mid-Tx 3 Visit, End of Treatment Visit, 12-Week Follow-Up Visit, and 26-Week Follow-Up Visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Food intake (secondary outcome) will be assessed via 3 telephone-administered, 24-hour dietary recalls during the week after (or near) the Baseline Visit, Mid-Treatment 3 Visit (week 4), End of Treatment Visit (week 8) and the 12-week and 26-week follow-up Visits (n=15). A trained member of the research staff will use a multi-pass method with an interactive computerized software program, the Automated Self-Administered 24-hour Recall (ASA24®), to determine total kcal/day (outcome variable).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">426</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <condition>Weight Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BAS+</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will attend 8 counseling sessions and receive a behavioral activation intervention to smoking cessation and to post-cessation weight gain (BAS+).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will attend 8 counseling sessions and receive standard smoking cessation counseling (SC).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BAS+</intervention_name>
    <description>The goal of the BAS+ is to maintain a level of overall reward after cessation by structuring and enhancing opportunities for reinforcement to: (1) ensure that not smoking is as reinforcing as smoking; and (2) prevent an over-reliance on food as a substitute reinforcer for smoking so that PCWG does not precipitate smoking relapse.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BAS+</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SC</intervention_name>
    <description>Overeating and weight gain are common concerns reported during smoking cessation treatment. Per convention, SC will address these concerns through standard recommendations to consume low-calorie snack foods, drink water, eat nutritious meals, and exercise, but will not include skills to shape the use of these suggestions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female treatment-seeking smokers who are between 18 and 65 years of age and
             self-report smoking at least 5 cigarettes (menthol and/or non-menthol) per day for at
             least the last 6 months.

          -  Plan to live in the area for the duration of the study (i.e. ~30 weeks/8 months).

          -  Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the combined consent and HIPAA form.

          -  Smokers who wish to make a permanent quit attempt in the next 1-2 months
             (treatment-seeking), because our prior work suggests that motivated subjects are more
             sensitive to medication effects on smoking behavior.

          -  Able to communicate fluently in English (i.e. speaking, writing, and reading).

          -  Provide a Carbon Monoxide (CO) breath test reading greater than or equal to 8 parts
             per million (ppm) at the Intake Visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Smoking Behavior.

          -  Regular use of nicotine containing products other than cigarettes (e.g. chewing
             tobacco, snuff, snus, cigars, e-cigs, etc.). Participants agreeing to abstain from
             using nicotine containing products other than cigarettes and the study-provided TN for
             the duration of trial will be considered eligible.

          -  Current enrollment or plans to enroll in another research and/or smoking cessation
             program over the duration of the study (i.e. ~30 weeks/8 months).

          -  Anticipated use (within the next ~30 weeks/8 months) of any nicotine substitutes
             and/or smoking cessation treatments/medications unless provided through the study.

          -  Provide a CO breath test reading less than 8 ppm at Intake Visit.

        Alcohol and Drug.

          -  History of substance abuse (other than nicotine) in the past 12 months and/or
             currently receiving medical treatment for substance abuse. Counseling and support
             groups (e.g. Alcoholics Anonymous and Narcotics Anonymous) will not be considered
             medical treatment for the purposes of this protocol.

          -  Current alcohol consumption that exceeds 25 standard drinks/week.

          -  Breath alcohol reading (BrAC) greater than .000 at the Intake Visit.

          -  A positive urine drug screen (UDS) for cocaine, opiates, amphetamines,
             methamphetamines, phencyclidine (PCP), ecstasy (MDMA), barbiturates, benzodiazepines,
             methadone, and/or oxycodone at the Intake Visit.

        Medical.

          -  Women who are pregnant, breast feeding, or planning a pregnancy over the duration of
             the study period. Women must agree to use an adequate form of contraception or abstain
             from sexual intercourse for the duration and for at least one month after the end of
             the study.

          -  Current treatment of cancer or diagnosed with cancer (except basal or squamous-cell
             carcinoma not treated with chemotherapy and/or radiation) in the past 6 months.

          -  Poorly controlled, brittle, or pump-dependent Type I diabetes.

          -  Current peptic ulcer bleeding.

          -  Allergy to adhesive tape.

          -  Skin problems or sensitivities. Eligibility will be evaluated on a case-by-case basis
             by the Study Physician.

          -  Active hepatitis or poorly controlled kidney and/or liver disease.

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic blood pressure [SBP] greater than 159 and/or
             diastolic blood pressure [DBP] greater than 99

          -  History of abnormal heart rhythms, tachycardia, and/or cardiovascular disease (e.g.
             stroke, angina, heart attack) may result in ineligibility. These conditions will be
             evaluated on a case-by-case basis by the Study Physician.

          -  History of epilepsy or seizures. Eligibility will be evaluated on a case-by-case basis
             by the Study Physician.

          -  Serious or unstable disease within the past 6 months. Notable diseases will be
             evaluated on a case-by-case basis by the Principal Investigator and/or the Study
             Physician.

          -  Any impairment including, but not limited to, visual, physical, and/or neurological
             impairments preventing proper completion of the study procedures. Notable impairments
             will be evaluated on a case-by-case basis by the Principal Investigator and/or the
             Study Physician.

          -  Low or borderline intellectual functioning - determined by receiving a score of less
             than 85 on the Shipley Institute of Living Scale (SILS), which correlates with the
             Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale-Revised (WAIS-R) Estimated Intelligence Quotient
             (IQ) Test.

          -  Applicable food allergies or disorders:

        Galactosemia, Notable milk allergy (lactose intolerant participants may proceed unless they
        experience severe symptoms), Notable soy allergy, Peanut allergy

        Psychiatric.

          -  Current diagnosis of major depression. Subjects with a history of major depression, in
             remission for 6 months or longer (may be stable on antidepressant medications), are
             eligible.

          -  Lifetime history of a suicide attempt.

          -  Lifetime history of schizophrenia, psychosis, and/or bipolar disorder.

        Medication.

        Current use or recent discontinuation (within the last 14 days) of:

          -  Smoking cessation medication (e.g., Zyban, Wellbutrin, Wellbutrin Standard-Release,
             Chantix).

          -  Benzodiazepines and/or Barbiturates.

          -  Anti-psychotic medications.

          -  Prescription stimulants (e.g., Provigil, Ritalin, Adderall).

          -  Systemic steroids.

        Current use of:

          -  Nicotine replacement therapy (NRT).

          -  Heart medications such as digoxin, quinidine, and nitroglycerin.

        Daily use of:

          -  Opiate-containing medications for chronic pain.

          -  Inhaled corticosteroids.

        General Exclusion.

          -  Past, current, anticipated, or pending enrollment in another research program over the
             study period that could potentially impact subject safety, study data, and/or the
             study design as determined by the Principal Investigator and/or Study Physician.

          -  Any medical condition, illness, disorder, adverse event (AE), or concomitant
             medication that could compromise participant safety or significantly impact study
             performance as determined by the Principal Investigator and/or Study Physician.
             Subjects may be deemed ineligible for any of the aforementioned reasons at any point
             throughout the study, as well as during the initial telephone screen.

          -  Significant non-compliance with protocol and/or study design as determined by the
             Principal Investigator and/or Study Physician. Subjects may be deemed ineligible at
             any point throughout the study.

          -  Subjects failing to complete an in-person Baseline Visit will be excluded (no
             Principal Investigator determination required).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janet Audrain-McGovern, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Interdisciplinary Research on Nicotine Addiction, University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Benjamin F Albelda, B.S.</last_name>
    <phone>215-746-7173</phone>
    <email>albeldab@mail.med.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Interdisciplinary Research on Nicotine Addiction, University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Benjamin Albelda, B.S.</last_name>
      <phone>215-746-7173</phone>
      <email>albeldab@mail.med.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kristin Kristin Tederstrom, B.A.</last_name>
      <phone>215-746-7142</phone>
      <email>tederstr@mail.med.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 20, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Smoking Cessation</keyword>
  <keyword>Weight Loss</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Body Weight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Gain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

