<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02908373</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC15_0053</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02908373</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Risk Management in Nursing Homes</brief_title>
  <acronym>EHPAGE</acronym>
  <official_title>Measuring Impact on Safety Culture in Nursing Homes, a Multifaceted Device for the Analysis of Care Associated Adverse Events</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nantes University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nantes University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Réseau QualiSanté (risk management network) hardly works on risk management in nursing
      homes. A model to help nursing homes managers to structure and analyze adverse events has
      been constructed by a working group of health professionals in the Réseau QualiSanté. Several
      questions appeared: is the model able to increase patient safety culture of professionals
      working in nursing homes? How to characterize adverse events in nursing homes? How frequent
      are they? The main objective of this research project EHPAGE is to measure the impact of the
      model to structure and analyze adverse events in nursing homes on the patient safety culture
      of professionals. The project combines quantitative data (questionnaire) and qualitative data
      (interviews).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The main objective of this research project EHPAGE is to measure the impact of the model to
      structure and analyze adverse events in nursing homes on the patient safety culture of
      professionals. The coaching model is composed of a 20 hours methodological help for each
      nursing home and of an implementation kit.

      To answer to the main objective, quantitative and qualitative data will be collected twice
      during the project: before the implementation of the coaching model and 12 months after.

      Secondary objectives are:

        1. To encourage the place of patient safety culture in strategic issues of nursing homes

        2. To develop patient safety culture of professionals working in nursing homes

        3. To develop a way to structure and make the reporting of adverse events in nursing homes
           more sustainable

        4. To describe epidemiologic characteristic of adverse events in nursing homes

        5. To propose a French validated questionnaire to evaluate patient safety culture reported
           by professionals in nursing homes An ancillary study is perform to describe
           epidemiologic characteristic of adverse events in nursing homes
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>impact of the coaching of the réseau QualiSanté: score expressed by the average percentages of positive responses to the &quot;Overall perception of the safety of residents&quot; dimension (= sum of 2 terms of positive response from the Likert scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 months after initial diagnosis.</time_frame>
    <description>Initial analysis: estimate baseline characteristics of nursing homes (2 groups) Analysis of the primary endpoint primarily for professionals and secondly for nursing homes (consideration of cluster randomization)
Professionals Analysis:
Score of each professional &quot;Overall perception of the safety of residents - OPOTSOR&quot; dimension of NHSOPS questionnaire calculated for both measures in each arm Linear mixed model implemented to reflect the hierarchical data structure: score of the dimension &quot;OPOTSOR&quot; at assessment2 explained by the fixed effect group and the random effect of nursing homes.
Adjustment with other variables if necessary Facility effect estimated with Intraclass correlation coefficient
Nursing homes analysis:
&quot;Global perception of the safety of residents&quot; dimension score of each nursing home calculated at assessment1 and 2 in each group Comparison of the average test scores at assessment2 for each nursing home</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">61</enrollment>
  <condition>Adverse Events Management in Nursing Homes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Case group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Nursing homes benefiting first the implementation of the coaching model (methodological help for professionals on the patient safety culture): just after the first measure (overview of the situation)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Nursing homes benefiting the implementation of the coaching model (methodological help for professionals on the patient safety culture): after the second measure (impact of the device on case group)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Implementation of the coaching model</intervention_name>
    <description>20 hours methodological help for each nursing home and an implementation kit</description>
    <arm_group_label>Case group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        61 nursing home located in Loire-Atlantique and Vendée departments in France.
        Loire-Atlantique and Vendée departments already benefit the risk management model from the
        réseau qualisanté located in Nantes University Hospital
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Nursing homes members of the Réseau QualiSanté (risk management network)

          -  Public or private legal status

          -  Agreeing to participate in the project

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>105 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leila MORET, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nantes University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Noémie Terrien</last_name>
    <email>noemie.terrien@chu-nantes.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Leila Moret, MD - PhD - Prof</last_name>
    <email>leila.moret@chu-nantes.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nantes University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Noémie Terrien</last_name>
      <email>noemie.terrien@chu-nantes.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 15, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 15, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 15, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>risk management</keyword>
  <keyword>nursing home</keyword>
  <keyword>elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>care</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

