<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01012492</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00024488</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Abatacept</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01012492</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Tolerability Trial of Abatacept-based Immunosuppression for Prevention of Acute GvHD During Unrelated Donor Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Tolerability Trial of Abatacept-based Immunosuppression for Prevention of Acute GvHD During Unrelated Donor Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Seattle Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Seattle Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study is to determine the safety and tolerability when adding
      abatacept to acute Graft versus Host Disease in transplants for malignant diseases using
      unrelated donor bone marrow or peripheral blood stem cell grafts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Acute Graft versus Host Disease (aGvHD) is the most deadly complication facing children who
      have allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT). aGvHD occurs, in large part,
      because the T cells in the bone marrow graft do not &quot;accept&quot; the presence of the transplant
      recipient's cells, and mount a severe, debilitating, and often deadly attack against the
      recipient, striking the skin, the liver, and the gastrointestinal track, most prominently.
      For patients receiving bone marrow from an unrelated donor, the rate of aGvHD can reach as
      high as 80%, with up to half of patients dying from this complication. These serious outcomes
      occur despite our best efforts at aGvHD prevention. Given the lack of success in preventing
      aGvHD with current therapies, novel therapies to prevent this disease are desperately needed.

      In this study, we plan to test a novel drug to prevent aGvHD. This drug, known as abatacept,
      specifically blocks the activation pathway critical to T cell function known as &quot;T cell
      costimulation.&quot; In particular, it blocks the CD28-mediated costimulation pathway that is
      critical for optimal T cell activation and proliferation. My research group has done
      extensive pre-clinical work with this compound. Our work has demonstrated its efficacy in
      inducing immune tolerance after transplantation in both mouse models and primate models. In
      addition, patient trials have demonstrated that blocking CD28-directed T cell costimulation
      can prevent T cell-mediated diseases, including rheumatoid arthritis and psoriasis, and can
      improve solid organ transplant acceptance. Abatacept is currently FDA approved for use in
      rheumatoid arthritis. Given this drug's safety and efficacy profile, we have been granted an
      IND-exemption from the FDA for the inclusion of abatacept in a GvHD-prevention strategy.

      This is a safety and tolerability study of the addition of abatacept to a GvHD-prophylaxis
      regimen. Thus, the primary objective of the study is to determine the safety and tolerability
      of the addition of abatacept to aGvHD prophylaxis in transplants for malignant hematologic
      disease using unrelated donor bone marrow or peripheral blood stem cell grafts.

      Three secondary objectives will also be addressed:

        1. We will estimate the incidence and severity of aGvHD in patients receiving the
           abatacept-based protocol.

        2. We will determine the immune phenotype of donor cells in patients receiving abatacept.

        3. We will determine the ability of donor T-cells in patients receiving abatacept to
           respond to both polyclonal and recipient-specific immune stimulation.

      These secondary objectives will allow us to determine the impact of abatacept-containing GvHD
      prevention on both T cell alloreactivity and on T cell-mediated protective immunity.

      This study is for patients older than 12 who have been diagnosed with high-risk leukemia and
      for whom an unrelated bone marrow transplant is planned. We plan to enroll 10 patients on the
      study, over a 1-year period from the opening of the trial. Of these ten patients, at least
      five will be pediatric patients; the other five may be from adult patients taken care of by
      Winship Cancer Center physicians. All clinical study coordination and biologic studies will
      be performed by CHOA personnel.

      Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their
      stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine,
      methotrexate, and abatacept. They will have immunologic analysis for 1 year after transplant
      and clinical analysis for 3 years after transplant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Grade III-IV Acute GVHD by Day 100.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 100 post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Grade III-IV Acute GVHD by Day 100. The incidence of Gr III-IV acute GVHD was measured by the modified Glucksburg scale.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Grades III-IV Acute GVHD at 2 Years</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years after transplant</time_frame>
    <description>The rates of Grades III-IV acute GVHD were measured at 2 years according to standard Glucksberg criteria, which was 10%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunology</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Protective Immunity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years after transplant</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>AML</condition>
  <condition>ALL</condition>
  <condition>Undifferentiated Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Biphenotypic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Anemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Anemia With Ringed Sideroblasts</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Cytopenia With Multilineage Dysplasia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Cytopenia With Multilineage Dysplasia and Ringed Sideroblasts</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Anemia With Excess Blasts-1 (5-10% Blasts)</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Anemia With Excess Blasts-2 (10-20% Blasts)</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndrome, Unclassified</condition>
  <condition>MDS Associated With Isolated Del (5q)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Abatacept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine, methotrexate, and abatacept.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abatacept</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine, methotrexate, and abatacept.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Abatacept</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with AML, with or without a history of myelodysplastic syndrome in one of the
             following categories.

             (a) Patients in first complete remission with high-risk features

          2. Patients with ALL, in either of the following categories:

               1. In 2nd or greater complete remission (complete remission is defined as &gt; 5%
                  blasts in marrow)

               2. Delayed 1st CR-Failure to achieve complete remission after a single round of
                  induction therapy

          3. Patients with undifferentiated or biphenotypic leukemia in 1st or greater complete
             remission.

          4. Patients with Myelodysplastic Syndrome(s) with an IPSS score of &gt;1.5 and &lt;10% blasts
             in the bone marrow at the time of transplant. These conditions will include:

               1. Refractory anemia

               2. Refractory anemia with ringed sideroblasts

               3. Refractory cytopenia with multilineage dysplasia

               4. Refractory cytopenia with multilineage dysplasia and ringed sideroblasts

               5. Refractory anemia with excess blasts-1 (5-10% blasts)

               6. Refractory anemia with excess blasts-2 (10-20% blasts)

               7. Myelodysplastic syndrome, unclassified

               8. MDS associated with isolated del (5q)

               9. Patients diagnosed with AML in CR1 after an initial diagnosis of MDS.

          5. Age 12 years or older.

          6. No prior allogeneic transplant

          7. Karnofsky performance score or Lansky Play-Performance of at least 80.

          8. Signed informed consent for adults and for minors the provision of pediatric assent
             and parental permission.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt;12 years old.

          2. Patients requiring &gt;2 courses of induction chemotherapy to achieve remission status.

          3. HIV infection

          4. Tuberculosis Infection

          5. Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease

          6. Pregnancy (positive serum b-HCG) or breastfeeding

          7. Creatinine clearance or nuclear medicine GFR of &lt; 50 mL/min

          8. Cardiac ejection fraction &lt; 50%

          9. bilirubin &gt; 2 × upper limit of normal or ALT &gt; 4 × upper limit of normal or unresolved
             veno-occlusive disease.

         10. Pulmonary disease with FVC, FEV1 or DLCO parameters &lt;45% predicted (corrected for
             hemoglobin) or O2 saturation &lt;92% on room air.

         11. Karnofsky performance score or Lansky Play-Performance Scale &lt;80

         12. Uncontrolled viral, bacterial, or fungal infection at the time of study enrollment

         13. Availability of a willing and fully MHC-matched related donor.

         14. Positive cytotoxic recipient-donor cross-match or positive HLA antibody screen against
             donor-disparate antigens.

         15. Any active infection.

         16. Unable to obtain informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leslie Kean, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seattle Children's Research Institute, Ben Towne Center for Childhood Cancer Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Koura DT, Horan JT, Langston AA, Qayed M, Mehta A, Khoury HJ, Harvey RD, Suessmuth Y, Couture C, Carr J, Grizzle A, Johnson HR, Cheeseman JA, Conger JA, Robertson J, Stempora L, Johnson BE, Garrett A, Kirk AD, Larsen CP, Waller EK, Kean LS. In vivo T cell costimulation blockade with abatacept for acute graft-versus-host disease prevention: a first-in-disease trial. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2013 Nov;19(11):1638-49. doi: 10.1016/j.bbmt.2013.09.003. Epub 2013 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>24047754</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Suessmuth Y, Mukherjee R, Watkins B, Koura DT, Finstermeier K, Desmarais C, Stempora L, Horan JT, Langston A, Qayed M, Khoury HJ, Grizzle A, Cheeseman JA, Conger JA, Robertson J, Garrett A, Kirk AD, Waller EK, Blazar BR, Mehta AK, Robins HS, Kean LS. CMV reactivation drives posttransplant T-cell reconstitution and results in defects in the underlying TCRβ repertoire. Blood. 2015 Jun 18;125(25):3835-50. doi: 10.1182/blood-2015-03-631853. Epub 2015 Apr 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25852054</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 11, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 12, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 13, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>November 25, 2015</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>August 16, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">September 15, 2017</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Seattle Children's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Leslie Kean</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>bone marrow</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Refractory</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Refractory, with Excess of Blasts</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Abatacept</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <pre_assignment_details>One patient signed consent but was determined to be an assignment failure prior to starting study activities.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Abatacept</title>
          <description>Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine, methotrexate, and abatacept.
Abatacept: Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine, methotrexate, and abatacept.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="10"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="10"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Abatacept</title>
          <description>Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine, methotrexate, and abatacept.
Abatacept: Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine, methotrexate, and abatacept.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="10"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="44.5" spread="27"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Percentage of Participants With Grade III-IV Acute GVHD by Day 100.</title>
        <description>Grade III-IV Acute GVHD by Day 100. The incidence of Gr III-IV acute GVHD was measured by the modified Glucksburg scale.</description>
        <time_frame>Day 100 post-transplant</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Abatacept</title>
            <description>Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine, methotrexate, and abatacept.
Abatacept: Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine, methotrexate, and abatacept.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Percentage of Participants With Grade III-IV Acute GVHD by Day 100.</title>
          <description>Grade III-IV Acute GVHD by Day 100. The incidence of Gr III-IV acute GVHD was measured by the modified Glucksburg scale.</description>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="10"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Percentage of Participants With Grades III-IV Acute GVHD at 2 Years</title>
        <description>The rates of Grades III-IV acute GVHD were measured at 2 years according to standard Glucksberg criteria, which was 10%.</description>
        <time_frame>2 years after transplant</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Abatacept</title>
            <description>Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine, methotrexate, and abatacept.
Abatacept: Participants will receive one of two standard myeloablative conditioning regimens for their stem cell transplant, and will receive an aGvHD prophylaxis regimen including cyclosporine, methotrexate, and abatacept.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Percentage of Participants With Grades III-IV Acute GVHD at 2 Years</title>
          <description>The rates of Grades III-IV acute GVHD were measured at 2 years according to standard Glucksberg criteria, which was 10%.</description>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="10"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Immunology</title>
        <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Protective Immunity</title>
        <time_frame>3 years after transplant</time_frame>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>One year post-transplant.</time_frame>
      <desc>Attribution of adverse events when patients are co-enrolled on other trials: because abatacept’s effects are strictly immunologic and because co-enrollment will only be allowed in trials testing agents without immunomodulatory effects, all adverse events stemming directly or indirectly from immune deficiency or immune dysregulation will be attributed (definite, probable or possible depending on the circumstances) to abatacept and not the agent being tested in the other trial.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Abatacept</title>
          <description>In this trial, we will test the safety and tolerability of the addition of the CD28-B7 blockade agent, abatacept, as an adjunctive therapy for the prevention of GvHD in a high-risk BMT cohort. Four doses of abatacept will be given according to a dosing schedule based on previous trials using CD28-B7 blockade with belatacept in kidney transplantation. Pharmacokinetic and pharmakodynamic analysis of abatacept will be undertaken, as well as an evaluation of the incidence and severity of acute GvHD in this patient cohort.
Dosage: Abatacept is administered as an intravenous infusion under medically controlled conditions. Dose is 10mg/kg with a maximum dose of 1 gram. Abatacept should be administered as a 30-minute intravenous infusion. In this study, abatacept will be dosed on days -1, +5, +14, +28 post-transplant. Small adjustments in dose to accommodate abatacept vial size may be acceptable. These dose adjustments must be approved by the study PI.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_vocab>CTCAE</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title vocab="CTCAE (4.0)">Febrile neutropenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Polyclonal lymphoproliferative disorder</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bacteremia with coagulase negative staphylococcus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Upper Respiratory Infection - Parainfluenza</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bacteremia with E. coli</sub_title>
                <description>i</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Upper Respiratory Infection - Rhinovirus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Perianal cellulitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hemorrhagic cystitis with BK virus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>CTCAE</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="8" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Mucositis oral</sub_title>
                <description>Mucositis oral grade 2</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="5" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bladder toxicity</sub_title>
                <description>bladder grade 2</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Renal and urinary disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Renal toxicity</sub_title>
                <description>Renal toxicity grade 2</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="4" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Leslie S Kean</name_or_title>
      <organization>Emory University School of Medicine</organization>
      <phone>404-376-0187</phone>
      <email>Leslie.kean@emory.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

