<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01011764</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>G09-04-021-01A</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UA3MC11055</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01011764</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Peer Relationships at School</brief_title>
  <acronym>HRSAII</acronym>
  <official_title>Autism Intervention Research Network on Behavior Health (AIR-B): Study of Peer Relationships at School</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Health Resources and Services Administration (HRSA)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Florida State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Health Resources and Services Administration (HRSA)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to compare the effects of two separate, manualized group
      interventions designed to improve social outcomes for young children with autism. The first
      type of group intervention utilizes a social skill curriculum delivered to a small group of
      children with autism at their school. This type of group will be referred to as the Skills
      group (SKILLS intervention). The other intervention delivers a social engagement curriculum
      at the children's school site and includes children with autism and typically developing
      peers, from the same school. This type of group will be referred to as the School Engagement
      Group (ENGAGE intervention).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Once families have decided to join the study, and have completed the informed consent process
      using the &quot;Social Skills Club - Parent Consent&quot;, and once we obtain letters of agreement from
      participating elementary schools, children with ASD will be randomly assigned to one of two
      intervention conditions, SKILLS or ENGAGE, led by two trained doctoral students. Since
      children will be randomized to either the SKILLS or the ENGAGE group, we are hoping to
      determine the active ingredients for successfully integrating children with autism. For both
      the SKILLS and the ENGAGE groups, all interventions and observations of children will take
      place in the target child's school. Thus, upon admission to the project, research personnel
      will attend the participant's classroom at school, and distribute consent forms titled &quot;Peer
      Relationships at School - Classroom Parent Consent&quot; to all children in the class. The
      consenting process should be no more than ten minutes. For those children that return
      informed consent from their parents, as well as offer assent on the &quot;Children's Classroom
      Assent&quot; to join to the project, social network measures (including brief demographic
      information), as well as friendship surveys (Friendships Qualities Scale; FQS), and an
      emotion measure (loneliness questionnaire) will be distributed at pre-intervention
      (baseline), post-intervention, and follow-up time points. These measures will take
      approximately 30-40 minutes per each time point. Graduate students will administer the
      measures and will make every effort to do so at a convenient time for the teacher and for the
      classroom to avoid utilizing instructional time. In addition, the efficacy of the treatment
      interventions will be assessed with ongoing direct behavioral observations at entry, twice
      during treatment, at exit, and at the 2-month follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Friendship Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Before treatment, after treatment, and 2 months after treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Friendship Qualities Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Before treatment, after treatment, and 2 months after treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SKILLS group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The SKILLS intervention targets a specific set of social skills over 8 bi-weekly sessions. The intervention is delivered to a small group of children with autism at school during lunchtime. The content delivered to the group of young children with autism including lessons developed from a manual by Seattle Children's Hospital Research Foundation. Children are given weekly homework assignments to reinforce the topics discussed in the group sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ENGAGE group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The ENGAGE intervention targets two social domains, and two learning contexts. The two social domains are peer acceptance and social engagement with peers. The social group will be small and include children with ASD as well as their typical peers. There will be a greater number of typical peers included to model social behaviors and foster friendships. The typical peers will be selected based on results from the friendship survey and teacher nominations. The two learning contexts are direct instruction in a group social skills format during lunchtime and individualized embedded generalization activities in the school day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SKILLS vs ENGAGE</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators plan to contrast 2 different models for social skills groups. Each model involves 16 45-minute bi-weekly sessions, twice a week with a small group of children with ASD. Details of the 2 intervention models are described below.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SKILLS group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>ENGAGE group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children are between the ages of 7 and 12 years in grades 2-5.

          -  Children have a clinical diagnosis of autism or PDD-NOS, and/or meet criteria on the
             ADOS for ASD or autism.

          -  Children have an IQ of 70 or above

          -  Children are fully included in a typical classroom for 80% or more of the school day

          -  Children are expected to stay in the school or the classroom for the duration of the
             study.

          -  Families with low SES and/or from racial/ethnic minority backgrounds

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children must not have additional diagnoses or sensory or motor impairments.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Connie Kasari, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tallahassee</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kennedy Krieger Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bauminger N, Kasari C. Loneliness and friendship in high-functioning children with autism. Child Dev. 2000 Mar-Apr;71(2):447-56.</citation>
    <PMID>10834476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chamberlain B, Kasari C, Rotheram-Fuller E. Involvement or isolation? The social networks of children with autism in regular classrooms. J Autism Dev Disord. 2007 Feb;37(2):230-42.</citation>
    <PMID>16855874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kasari C, Freeman SF, Bauminger N, Alkin MC. Parental perspectives on inclusion: effects of autism and Down syndrome. J Autism Dev Disord. 1999 Aug;29(4):297-305.</citation>
    <PMID>10478729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robertson K, Chamberlain B, Kasari C. General education teachers' relationships with included students with autism. J Autism Dev Disord. 2003 Apr;33(2):123-30.</citation>
    <PMID>12757351</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 10, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 14, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 14, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 16, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Health Resources and Services Administration (HRSA)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Connie Kasari, Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Psychological Studies in Education and Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>social networks</keyword>
  <keyword>friendships</keyword>
  <keyword>autism spectrum disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

