<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01018407</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01MH084864-01A109</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01MH084864</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>DDTR B2-MBA</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01018407</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interventions for Communication in Autism Network</brief_title>
  <acronym>ICAN</acronym>
  <official_title>Multisite Randomized Control Treatment of Early Intervention for Spoken Communication in Autism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this project is to compare the efficacy of two interventions for improving spoken
      language and reducing symptoms of autism.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While significant progress has been made toward identifying effective interventions for
      preschool-age children with autism (National Research Council, 2001), few scientifically
      rigorous studies have compared active ingredients of these interventions or examined outcomes
      focused on core deficits. To address these areas of need, this collaborative, multi-site
      project combines the expertise of investigators experienced in randomized controlled clinical
      trials (RCTs), in the study of core deficits in young children with autism, and in data
      management and analysis of multi-site clinical trials.

      The goal of this project is to compare the efficacy of two interventions for improving spoken
      language and reducing symptoms of autism: (1) Discrete trial training (DTT)--an applied
      behavior analysis approach emphasizing highly structured teaching of school readiness skills
      (match-to-sample, imitation, functional play, and receptive and expressive language) and (2)
      Interpersonal developmental approach (IDA): a visually supported, child-focused, flexible
      engagement, social communicative engagement approach on joint attention, symbolic play, and
      the use of conventional symbols within socially valid communicative contexts.

      Children will be randomly assigned to DTT or IDA. In each condition, children's ongoing early
      intervention programs will be augmented with two 30-minute sessions daily of the study
      intervention (DTT or IDA) conducted by supervised therapists for 4 months, with transition to
      home therapy for 2 months.

      Potential moderators (e.g., initial mental age and language age) and mediators (e.g. parent
      synchronization of joint attention and changes in parental expectancies) on treatment outcome
      will also be examined.

      The assessment measures will include diagnostic and developmental measures. There are three
      sets of assessments. The first set of assessments is to determine whether the child is
      eligible for the study. If the child is eligible, we will complete the next set of
      assessments, which are completed at three points: (1) prior to entry into the treatment (this
      is a baseline measurement conducted just before the start of the treatment phase); (2) at
      exit; and (3) at a 6 month follow-up. Several assessments will also be completed after 2
      months, 4 months, and 6 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reynell Developmental Language Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 6 months later</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>McArthur-Bates Communicative Development Inventory (Word and Gestures Inventory and/or Words and Sentences Inventory)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 6-month follow up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Caregiver-child Interaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, three times during active intervention, post-treatment, and 6-month follow up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Social Communication Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 6-month follow up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Structured Play Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 6-month follow up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">192</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Discrete Trial Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Targets nonverbal imitation, match-to-sample, verbal imitation, imitation of play activities, receptive language, and expressive language. 5 hours per week of individual instruction for 4 months (Two 30-minute sessions per day, five days per week) with reductions in classroom pull out sessions in months 5 and 6 with implementation of 1 hour per week of in-home parent training for the last 2 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interpersonal Developmental Approach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Targets Joint Attention and Symbolic Play. 5 hours per week of individual instruction for 4 months (Two 30-minute sessions per day, five days per week) with reductions in classroom pull out sessions in months 5 and 6 with implementation of 1 hour per week of in-home parent training for the last 2 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Discrete Trial Training</intervention_name>
    <description>UCLA model, developed by Lovaas and colleagues (Smith, Groen &amp; Wynn, 2000). Two 30-minute sessions daily (5 hours/week) of 1:1 intervention focusing on imitation, match-to-sample, receptive and expressive language. Using operant conditioning, the therapist works individually with a child in a distraction-free setting and administers approximately 10 trials in a sitting, with breaks between sittings.
During months 5 and 6, we will provide parents with training in an apprenticeship format one day per week for an hour per day. The clinician will demonstrate a DTT instructional program, then the parent will take a turn implementing it. The clinician and parent will give each other feedback on their implementation of the program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Discrete Trial Training</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DTT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interpersonal Developmental Approach</intervention_name>
    <description>Focus on teaching joint attention and symbolic play developmentally via floor play milieu teaching approach. Principles applied include following the child's lead and interest in activities, talking about what the child is doing, repeating back what the child says, expanding on what child says, giving corrective feedback, sitting close to the child and making eye-contact, and making environmental adjustments to engage the child (Kasari et al., 2006).
Parents will be incorporated into the treatment to encourage joint engagement with their child and to focus specifically on joint attention and play skills in their interactions. Each home session will last one hour (once a week) during month 5 and 6 and will involve therapist modeling, and coaching of parent in child-directed activities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interpersonal Developmental Approach</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IDA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of an autism spectrum disorder (Autistic Disorder or Pervasive Developmental
             Disorder Not Otherwise Specified) from a licensed doctoral-level clinician, confirmed
             by the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule and clinical judgment.

          2. Chronological age between 33 and 54 months

          3. Must be receiving at least 12.5 hours per week of early intervention or preschool
             developmental services, some of which must be provided in a school setting.

          4. Cognitive and language requirements (at least two of the following three criteria must
             be met:

               -  &gt;12 months for visual reception (as determined by Mullen Scales of Early
                  Learning) or receptive language (as determined by Mullen or Reynell Developmental
                  Language Scales)

               -  a score of 1,2 or 3 on the ADOS Module 1

               -  &lt;30 spontaneous communicative words, as determined by behavior assessments
                  (Mother- Child Interaction, Early Social Communication Scales, and Structured
                  Play Assessment)

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. Major medical conditions other than autism, specifically (a) genetic disorders such as
             Fragile X, Down syndrome, or tuberous sclerosis, (b) sensory disabilities such as
             blindness or deafness, and (c) motor disabilities such as cerebral palsy

          2. Nonverbal mental age &lt; 12 months, based on a nonverbal score from the Mullen Scales of
             Early Learning (Mullen, 1995), as reliability of a diagnosis of autism is questionable
             at this developmental level.

          3. Expressive language level that exceeds the First Words level, as evidenced by an age
             equivalent of 24 months or greater on the Expressive Language Scale of the Reynell

          4. Exposure to English less than 50% of the time
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>33 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>54 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Connie Kasari, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90024</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kennedy Krieger Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.autism.ucla.edu</url>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kasari C, Freeman S, Paparella T. Joint attention and symbolic play in young children with autism: a randomized controlled intervention study. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2006 Jun;47(6):611-20. Erratum in: J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2007 May;48(5):523.</citation>
    <PMID>16712638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith T, Groen AD, Wynn JW. Randomized trial of intensive early intervention for children with pervasive developmental disorder. Am J Ment Retard. 2000 Jul;105(4):269-85. Erratum in: Am J Ment Retard 2001 May;106(3):208. Am J Ment Retard 2000 Nov;105(6):508.</citation>
    <PMID>10934569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 20, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 23, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Connie Kasari, Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Psychological Studies in Education and Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

