<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00414427</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>051420</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00414427</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Ultrasonography to Predict Clinical Response to Intraarticular Corticosteroids in Knee Osteoarthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Using Ultrasonography to Predict Clinical Response to Intraarticular Corticosteroids in Knee Osteoarthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purposes of this study are the following:

        1. To evaluate whether the presence of inflammatory knee osteoarthritis as determined by
           ultrasonography can be used as a clinical predictor of patient response to
           intra-articular corticosteroids.

        2. To prospectively evaluate clinical responsiveness of intraarticular corticosteroids with
           the inflammatory phenotype of knee OA using a randomized, placebo controlled clinical
           design.

        3. To evaluate whether lower extremity strength is improved with intraarticular
           corticosteroid injection.

      The investigators hypothesize that patients with signs of inflammation by ultrasonography
      such as synovitis and effusion will respond better to intraarticular corticosteroid
      injection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Osteoarthritis (OA) has previously been thought to be a non-inflammatory condition whose
      pathologic hallmark is destruction of hyaline cartilage. It is now realized that OA results
      from a complex interplay of multiple factors, including local inflammatory processes.
      Evidence suggests that synovitis which is the usual presenting sign of inflammatory arthritis
      is also frequently present in OA.

      The presence of inflammation in knee OA may explain why intra-articular (IA) corticosteroid
      injections have been shown to result in clinically and statistically significant reduction in
      osteoarthritic knee pain. Randomized controlled trials have shown that treated patients were
      less likely to have continuing pain and had significantly lower scores on a visual analogue
      scale (VAS) for pain. However, studies have failed to determine clinical predictors of
      response to IA steroid injection, including traditional indices of inflammation (heat, fluid,
      stiffness). One possibility is that local corticosteroids do no act to relieve pain by
      reducing synovitis. These putative mechanisms have yet to be elucidated. Perhaps a more
      plausible explanation is that current methods of assessing local inflammation in OA are
      inadequate.

      Recent studies involving ultrasonography (US) demonstrate that US is a valid and reproducible
      tool for the detection of synovitis in the knee. It has been shown to be more sensitive than
      clinical examination and is relatively inexpensive and noninvasive.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate whether the presence of inflammatory knee osteoarthritis as determined by ultrasonography can be used as a clinical predictor of patient response to intra-articular corticosteroids.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To prospectively evaluate clinical responsiveness of intraarticular corticosteroids with the inflammatory phenotype of knee OA using a randomized, placebo controlled clinical design.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate whether lower extremity strength is improved with intraarticular corticosteroid injection.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intraarticular steroids</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Both male and female patients are eligible for the study if they are between 40 and 80
             years old, have symptomatic knee OA requiring treatment, and have not responded
             adequately to treatment with acetominophen or NSAIDs.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe OA as defined by radiographic Kellgren and Lawrence Grade IV

          -  The patient being wheel-chair bound

          -  Previous knee operation on the affected side within the past year or history of total
             knee arthroplasty (affected side)

          -  Any IA steroid or injections in the last 3 months or viscosupplementation in the last
             6 months

          -  Local sepsis

          -  Local skin conditions

          -  Serious concomitant medical illness.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kenneth Kalunian, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Univeristy of California at San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thorton Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>La Jolla Veterans Affairs Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92161</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Godwin M, Dawes M. Intra-articular steroid injections for painful knees. Systematic review with meta-analysis. Can Fam Physician. 2004 Feb;50:241-8. Review. Erratum in: Can Fam Physician. 2009 Jun;55(6):590.</citation>
    <PMID>15000335</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaffney K, Ledingham J, Perry JD. Intra-articular triamcinolone hexacetonide in knee osteoarthritis: factors influencing the clinical response. Ann Rheum Dis. 1995 May;54(5):379-81.</citation>
    <PMID>7794044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walther M, Harms H, Krenn V, Radke S, Faehndrich TP, Gohlke F. Correlation of power Doppler sonography with vascularity of the synovial tissue of the knee joint in patients with osteoarthritis and rheumatoid arthritis. Arthritis Rheum. 2001 Feb;44(2):331-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11229463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karim Z, Wakefield RJ, Quinn M, Conaghan PG, Brown AK, Veale DJ, O'Connor P, Reece R, Emery P. Validation and reproducibility of ultrasonography in the detection of synovitis in the knee: a comparison with arthroscopy and clinical examination. Arthritis Rheum. 2004 Feb;50(2):387-94.</citation>
    <PMID>14872480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones A, Doherty M. Intra-articular corticosteroids are effective in osteoarthritis but there are no clinical predictors of response. Ann Rheum Dis. 1996 Nov;55(11):829-32.</citation>
    <PMID>8976640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2006</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 21, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 8, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Kenneth Kalunian, M.D., Professor of Medicine</name_title>
    <organization>UCSD</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Knee Osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Ultrasonography</keyword>
  <keyword>Corticosteroids</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

