<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00412646</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR006754</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00412646</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TMC125-C203: Phase II Randomized (Patients Are Assigned Different Treatments Based on Chance), Placebo Controlled Dose Escalating Trial of TMC125 in HIV-1 Infected Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Placebo-controlled Phase II Trial in HIV-1-infected, NRTI-, PI and NNRTI-experienced Subjects to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of Different Doses of TMC125 b.i.d. on Top of an Individually Optimized Antiretroviral Therapy by Means of a 2-stage Dose-escalating Design</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tibotec Pharmaceuticals, Ireland</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tibotec Pharmaceuticals, Ireland</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this randomized (patients are assigned different treatments based on chance),
      placebo-controlled, dose-escalating trial is to evaluate the safety, tolerability and
      efficacy of different doses of TMC125 twice daily ( b.i.d.) when added to an individually
      optimized antiretroviral therapy (ART) for 48 weeks. Dose-escalation will be performed in two
      stages. In the first stage approximately one hundred and eighty HIV-1 positive, three-class
      ART experienced patients will be randomized to placebo, 400 or 800 mg of TMC125 b.i.d. In the
      second stage, approximately seventy patients will be randomized to placebo, 800 or 1200 mg
      TMC125 b.i.d. Stage 2 will be opened for enrollment after review of the available safety and
      efficacy data for a specified number of patients and concurrence by the Data Safety and
      Monitoring Board (DSMB). After all patients are treated for a period of 12 weeks, unblinding
      for the sponsor will occur. The trial will continue in a single-blind fashion (sponsor
      unblinded, but investigator and patient blinded) for up to 48 weeks. Upon completion of the
      initial 48 weeks of treatment, patients deriving clinical benefit, in the opinion of the
      investigator, will have the option to prolong the same treatment, in a single-blind setting
      up to a maximum of 144 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study TMC125-C203 is a phase II, randomized, placebo-controlled, dose-escalating trial that
      will be conducted in 2 stages. In total approximately two-hundred and fifty HIV-1 positive
      patients will be included in 2 stages. Patients must be 3-class antiretroviral therapy (ART)
      experienced (i.e. have previously received at least one protease inhibitor (PI), one
      nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NRTI) and one non-nucleoside reverse
      transcriptase inhibitor (NNRTI), each for at least 3 months) and must have a
      VirtualPhenotype™ showing sensitivity to at least 2 antiretroviral drugs used in the
      optimized underlying ART. Stage 1: approximately 180 patients. 60 patients will receive
      placebo, 60 patients TMC125 400 mg b.i.d. and 60 patients TMC125 800 mg b.i.d. Stage 2:
      approximately 70 patients. 10 patients will receive placebo, 20 patients TMC125 800 mg b.i.d.
      and 40 patients TMC125 1200 mg b.i.d. Screening for study TMC125-C203 will be performed up to
      six weeks prior to baseline. If a patient fulfills the eligibility criteria he/she will be
      instructed either not to change his/her current ART until the baseline visit or to continue
      his/her treatment interruption until baseline. At the baseline visit patients will begin
      dosing with TMC125 and their optimized ART (composed at the discretion of the investigator),
      including at least two sensitive antiretroviral drugs as indicated by the VirtualPhenotypeTM.
      The new optimized underlying ART started at baseline should not be changed until the end of
      the trial, except for tolerability reasons. Adverse events that begin after the start of
      study therapy and within 4 weeks after the last dose of study medication will be collected.
      All adverse events still ongoing at the end of the treatment with TMC125 will be followed
      until satisfactory resolution or stabilization. Upon completion of the initial 48-week
      treatment period, patients deriving clinical benefit, in the opinion of the investigator,
      will have the option to prolong their treatment, with a first optional 48-weeks extension
      period, followed by a second optional 48-weeks period (maximum treatment duration is 144
      weeks). They will continue with the dose of study medication they were assigned to at
      randomization, in a blinded setting, in addition to their optimized ART initiated during the
      original treatment period of this study. Four weeks after 120 patients have started treatment
      in stage 1, all available data will be reviewed by a Data Safety and Monitoring Board (DSMB).
      Stage 2 will only be opened after concurrence by the DSMB. The primary analysis will be
      performed once all patients in the two stages have been treated for 24 weeks or have dropped
      out earlier. The final analysis will be performed when all patients have completed the trial
      (up to a maximum of 144 weeks), including the follow-up visits, or dropped out earlier. A
      pharmacokinetic sub-study will be performed within the framework of this trial. The patients
      enrolled in this sub-study will have additional pharmacokinetic samples taken on top of the
      assessments described in this protocol to be able to generate a full pharmacokinetic profile
      of TMC125 and concomitantly administered PIs.The sponsor has the intention to have an
      open-label follow-up study available for patients who participated in this trial.

      Doses of placebo, 400, 800 and 1200 mg TMC125, as twice daily regimens, have been selected
      for the present trial. The investigational medication will be taken orally every 12 hours and
      within 15 minutes after breakfast and dinner for 48 weeks (with optional extension period(s)
      up to a maximum of 144 weeks). All other used underlying antiretroviral drugs will be taken
      as prescribed by the investigator.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2006</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of different doses of TMC125 b.i.d. (taken twice daily) when added to an individually optimized antiretroviral regimen for 48 weeks.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the change in viral load; the proportion of patients with a certain plasma HIV-1 RNA level; the protocol defined virologic endpoints; the degree and duration of immunologic change and the number of patients attaining a virologic response</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">260</enrollment>
  <condition>Anti-Retroviral Agents</condition>
  <condition>HIV-1</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC125</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Plasma viral load at screening visit is above 1,000 HIV-1 RNA copies/ml

          -  Prior use of NRTI, NNRTI and PI, each for at least 3 months

          -  Currently receiving a stable (for 8 weeks) ART consisting of at least 3 antiretroviral
             drugs or currently on a treatment interruption for at least 8 weeks

          -  Further treatment options as defined by sensitivity to at least 2 antiretroviral drugs
             based on VirtualPhenotype™

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active AIDS defining illnesses

          -  Patients with a history of severe allergy, hypersensitivity or dermatological
             manifestation that led to discontinuation while receiving any NNRTI or abacavir

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding female

          -  Female of childbearing potential without the use of effective birth control methods

          -  Any toxicity above grade 2, except for lipids and glucose, according to the ACTG
             grading severity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tibotec Pharmaceuticals Limited Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Tibotec Pharmaceutical Limited</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Montaner J, Yeni P, Clumeck NN, Fätkenheuer G, Gatell J, Hay P, Seminari E, Peeters MP, Schöller-Gyüre M, Simonts M, Woodfall B; TMC125-C203 Study Group. Safety, tolerability, and preliminary efficacy of 48 weeks of etravirine therapy in a phase IIb dose-ranging study involving treatment-experienced patients with HIV-1 infection. Clin Infect Dis. 2008 Oct 1;47(7):969-78. doi: 10.1086/591705.</citation>
    <PMID>18764771</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 15, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 15, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 28, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS</keyword>
  <keyword>Dose finding study</keyword>
  <keyword>TMC125-C203</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Experienced</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etravirine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

