<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01601587</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4.2009.77.2009/1980 ( part 2)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01601587</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Introduction Seminar About Patient Participation and Treatment Options Decisional Preferences</brief_title>
  <official_title>Introduction Seminar About Patient Participation, Treatment Options and Decisional Preferences for Psychiatric Outpatients on Waiting List</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Norwegian University of Science and Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St. Olavs Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Norwegian University of Science and Technology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patient participation (PP) in Hospital is a goal defined by the Norwegian Health Authorities
      and it is a mandatory activity for District Psychiatric out-patient Centres (DPC) in Norway:
      patients are entitled to have influence on their treatment and should receive sufficient
      information directed at empowerment. Nevertheless, studies from Norway have found that
      patients who seek help are dissatisfied with the information they receive and doubt their
      possibility for real influence on their treatment. One way to improve individual PP might be
      to give patients sufficient information and education before they start their treatment in
      the form of an educational group intervention, an introduction seminar (IS); this group
      intervention is less time and resource consuming than individual interventions.

      Aims: The main purpose of this project is to develop and evaluate an IS for patients on a
      waiting list of DPC. The seminar will educate patients, so they can actively participate in
      their own treatment and, thereby, choosing treatment, reducing the risk of dropping out of
      treatment. Another aim is to enable patients to participate in their own treatment, to cope
      with their problems while they are waiting for treatment by providing them contact with
      primary health care and user organizations during their waiting time, and to increase
      adherence.

      Methods: The project involves three components: an exploratory study of educational content
      of the seminar; RCT of that 4-hours program (to examine its effect on treatment preferences
      and choices, activation, satisfaction, mental health and cost-benefit) and then a
      post-seminar qualitative evaluation, which will be used to create a broad yet deep
      understanding of the practical side of the participants`experience and the seminar's effect.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Part I: An exploratory study of educational content of the seminar: a qualitative study
      (started october 2011)

      Part II (RCT)

      The intervention:

      The introduction seminar will be held over one half day, 4 hours. Up to 15 patients can
      participate in each seminar. The content was developed based on study 1. The presentation
      about available treatment options and patient's rights are made by multi professional health
      personnel and user representatives. More specifically, this will be done under the following
      topics:

        1. What is mental health?

        2. Treatment options: orientation about individual and group based treatment modalities.

        3. Former patients experience with their own treatment, self-help and participation.

        4. How to influence and participate actively in the treatment and patient rights.

        5. What can I do while I wait for treatment and where can I otherwise do to avoid
           aggravation?.

      At the end of the day, the patients will be divided into small groups mentored by health
      personnel where they can discuss the presentations and ask questions. In the breaks,
      literature and other kinds of information for patients will be on display. All participants
      will get a folder with details of the program and leaflets from patient organisations and
      governmental agencies.

      Sample size Selected Treatment: The number of patients is calculated based on a significance
      level of 5% and a power of 93%. The numbers needed in each group becomes 25 (calculated using
      IR), and the aim is to include a total of 52 patients in the RCT. It is controlled that it is
      feasible to recruit this number of patients.

      PAM: Number of patients is calculated based on a significance level of 5% and a power of 87%.
      The standard deviation is estimated to be 13.8 and 9.7 (Pilot RCT data). The numbers needed
      in each group becomes 25 (calculated using SamplePower v2.0, SPSS Inc), and the aim is to
      include a total of 52 patients. It is controlled that it is feasible to recruit this number
      of patients.

      Part III Qualitative and quantitative analysis:

      To obtain information about the patients experience after the intervention, a post-seminar
      qualitative evaluation will be conducted:

      15 randomly selected patients will additionally participate in the seminar, and they will be
      take part in Part III and in the quantitative part of the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Selected Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>one single question</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Care utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Health care registration (adherence, attendance, consultations, dropout's rates and cost)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Care utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Health care registration (adherence, attendance, consultations, dropout's rates and cost)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>coping</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Activation Measure (PAM-13)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preferences for involvement in treatment decision making</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1, 4 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Control Preferences Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1, 4, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Client Satisfaction Questionnaire-8 (CSQ-8)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1, 4 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>WHO-Five Well-being Index (WHO-5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motivation</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1, 4 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>One single question about motivation for treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Mental Health Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive treatment as usual</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Introduction Seminar</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Psychoeducational group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>A psychoeducational group intervention.</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is an introduction seminar. It will be held over FOUR hours. Up to 15 patients can participate in each seminar. The content of the was developed based on study 1. The presentation about available treatment options and patient's rights are made by multi professional health personnel and user representatives. More specifically, this will be done under the following topics:
What is mental health?
Treatment options: orientation about individual and group based treatment modalities.
Former patients experience with their own treatment, self-help and participation.
How to influence and participate actively in the treatment and patient rights.
What can I do while I wait for treatment and where can I otherwise do to avoid aggravation?</description>
    <arm_group_label>Introduction Seminar</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  older than 18 years

          -  referred for out-patient treatment

          -  guarantee of starting treatment between 2 and 4 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  guarantee of starting treatment in less than 2 months

          -  Patients who do not understand the consequences of taking part of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Olav Linaker, md phd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NTNU</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tiller DPS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Trondheim</city>
        <zip>7055</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lara-Cabrera ML, Salvesen Ø, Nesset MB, De las Cuevas C, Iversen VC, Gråwe RW. The effect of a brief educational programme added to mental health treatment to improve patient activation: A randomized controlled trial in community mental health centres. Patient Educ Couns. 2016 May;99(5):760-8. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2015.11.028. Epub 2015 Dec 2.</citation>
    <PMID>26682971</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moljord IEO, Lara-Cabrera ML, Salvesen Ø, Rise MB, Bjørgen D, Antonsen DØ, Olsø TM, Evensen GH, Gudde CB, Linaker OM, Steinsbekk A, Eriksen L. Twelve months effect of self-referral to inpatient treatment on patient activation, recovery, symptoms and functioning: A randomized controlled study. Patient Educ Couns. 2017 Jun;100(6):1144-1152. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2017.01.008. Epub 2017 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>28096034</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 18, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Introductory Seminar</keyword>
  <keyword>Waiting list</keyword>
  <keyword>Community Mental Health Centre</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

