<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01600937</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MFA-12-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01600937</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Italian Diabetes and Exercise Study 2</brief_title>
  <acronym>IDES-2</acronym>
  <official_title>Italian Diabetes and Exercise Study 2 - A Long-term Behavioural Intervention for Adoption and Maintenance of a Physically Active Lifestyle</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Metabolic Fitness Association, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Roma La Sapienza</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Metabolic Fitness Association, Italy</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Current guidelines recommend supervised mixed (aerobic+resistance) physical activity to
      ensure optimal benefits to control blood glucose, lipids, blood pressure, and other
      cardiovascular risk and to minimize injuries. However, these guidelines are difficult to put
      into action for a number of barriers and poor long-term patient compliance. This project will
      assess the effect of a behavioral intervention strategy on the promotion and maintenance of
      physical activity in type 2 diabetes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An increasing prevalence of type 2 diabetes is associated with an aging population, a
      significant rise in the prevalence of obesity, and a sedentary lifestyle. In Italy,
      prevalence of diabetes is approximately 6%, with 90-95% of diabetic subjects having type 2.
      Strong evidence supports the importance of physical activity in the management of type 2
      diabetes. However, current guidelines are difficult to put into action in this target
      population because of barriers and poor patient long-term compliance so it is difficult even
      identify the best strategies for physical activity behavior change. Existing studies employ
      small groups and clinically-based approaches with limited theoretical grounding for
      recommended health behavior change. Most fail to offer practical, sustainable, economically
      viable solutions, with documented long-term intervention efficacy. This study proposes to
      monitor any objective measurable changes in LTPA over a 3-year period after behavioral
      interventions (Physician recommendations for daily PA with and without supervised exercise
      training including individual theoretic &amp; practical counseling). Hopefully, such behavioral
      intervention would offer a feasible procedure for long-term maintenance of physical activity
      and thus meet the call for a change of paradigm to move beyond the limited clinical focus by
      including theoretically population-based and &quot;real-life&quot; approaches for the management Type 2
      Diabetes.

      After the selection for eligibility and a run-in period, patients will be randomized in two
      groups: 1) exercise (EXE) group receiving theoretical &amp; practical exercise counseling
      including 2 sessions/ per wk for 1 month of supervised exercise training; and 2) control
      (CON) group receiving standard care including general physician recommendations for daily PA.
      Changes in physical activity behavior will be quantified using an accelerometer, in addition
      to a daily diary.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity Behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Volume of physical activity in METs-hr/wk; sedentary time; time spent in moderate-to-vigorous physical activity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical fitness</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Physical fitness (Cardiorespiratory, fitness, muscle strength, hip and trunk flexibility)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modifiable cardiovascular risk factors</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Modifiable cardiovascular risk factors (HbA1c, lipids, blood pressure, C-reactive protein, CHD 10-year risk scores)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life (Physical and mental SF-36 scores)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Musculo-skeletal disturbances</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Musculo-skeletal symproms and scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard care including physician recommendations for daily PA</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Theoretical &amp; practical exercise counseling including 2 sessions/ per wk for 1 month of supervised exercise training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Theoretical &amp; practical exercise counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>2 sessions/ per wk for 1 month</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Type 2 diabetes

          2. Age 40 to 80 years at screening

          3. BMI &gt;27&lt;40 kg/m2

          4. Sedentary for at least 6 months

          5. Treated with prescribed diet and/or OHA and insulin

          6. Able to walk for 1.6 Km unaided.

          7. Eligible after positive outcome of cardiac evaluation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. All patients with a history of central nervous dysfunction such as hemiparesis,
             myelopathies, cerebral ataxia, significant musculoskeletal deformities such as an
             amputation, dysmetria or scoliosis, patients with movement abnormalities or arthritis
             limited by pain when exercising

          2. A history of clinical evidence of severe cardiovascular disease which may limit or be
             a contraindication for exercise

          3. Clinical evidence of vestibular dysfunction

          4. Angina and related symptoms

          5. Postural hypotension defined as a fall in arterial blood pressure when changing
             position of &gt;20 mmHg (systole) or &gt;10 mmHg (diastole

          6. History of plantar sores
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stefano Balducci, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sant'Andrea Hospital, Diabetes Unit</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rome La Sapienza, Department of Clinical and Molecular Medicine, Sant'Andrea Hospital, Diabetes Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <state>RM</state>
        <zip>00189</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.metabolicfitness.it/</url>
    <description>Study protocol</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balducci S, Zanuso S, Cardelli P, Salvi L, Mazzitelli G, Bazuro A, Iacobini C, Nicolucci A, Pugliese G; Italian Diabetes Exercise Study (IDES) Investigators. Changes in physical fitness predict improvements in modifiable cardiovascular risk factors independently of body weight loss in subjects with type 2 diabetes participating in the Italian Diabetes and Exercise Study (IDES). Diabetes Care. 2012 Jun;35(6):1347-54. doi: 10.2337/dc11-1859. Epub 2012 Mar 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22399699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nicolucci A, Balducci S, Cardelli P, Cavallo S, Fallucca S, Bazuro A, Simonelli P, Iacobini C, Zanuso S, Pugliese G; Italian Diabetes Exercise Study Investigators. Relationship of exercise volume to improvements of quality of life with supervised exercise training in patients with type 2 diabetes in a randomised controlled trial: the Italian Diabetes and Exercise Study (IDES). Diabetologia. 2012 Mar;55(3):579-88. doi: 10.1007/s00125-011-2425-9. Epub 2012 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22234648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balducci S, Zanuso S, Pugliese G, Church T, Sigal RJ. Diet or diet plus physical activity in patients with early type 2 diabetes. Lancet. 2011 Dec 17;378(9809):2066; author reply 2067-8. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)61891-6.</citation>
    <PMID>22177504</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nicolucci A, Balducci S, Cardelli P, Zanuso S, Pugliese G; Italian Diabetes Exercise Study (IDES) Investigators. Improvement of quality of life with supervised exercise training in subjects with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Arch Intern Med. 2011 Nov 28;171(21):1951-3. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2011.561.</citation>
    <PMID>22123809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balducci S, Zanuso S, Cardelli P, Salerno G, Fallucca S, Nicolucci A, Pugliese G; Italian Diabetes Exercise Study (IDES) Investigators. Supervised exercise training counterbalances the adverse effects of insulin therapy in overweight/obese subjects with type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2012 Jan;35(1):39-41. doi: 10.2337/dc11-1450. Epub 2011 Oct 19.</citation>
    <PMID>22011409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balducci S, Zanuso S, Nicolucci A, De Feo P, Cavallo S, Cardelli P, Fallucca S, Alessi E, Fallucca F, Pugliese G; Italian Diabetes Exercise Study (IDES) Investigators. Effect of an intensive exercise intervention strategy on modifiable cardiovascular risk factors in subjects with type 2 diabetes mellitus: a randomized controlled trial: the Italian Diabetes and Exercise Study (IDES). Arch Intern Med. 2010 Nov 8;170(20):1794-803. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2010.380.</citation>
    <PMID>21059972</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balducci S, Zanuso S, Nicolucci A, Fernando F, Cavallo S, Cardelli P, Fallucca S, Alessi E, Letizia C, Jimenez A, Fallucca F, Pugliese G. Anti-inflammatory effect of exercise training in subjects with type 2 diabetes and the metabolic syndrome is dependent on exercise modalities and independent of weight loss. Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis. 2010 Oct;20(8):608-17. doi: 10.1016/j.numecd.2009.04.015. Epub 2009 Aug 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19695853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pugliese G, Zanuso S, Alessi E, Simonelli P, Fallucca S, Fallucca F, Balducci S. Self glucose monitoring and physical exercise in diabetes. Diabetes Metab Res Rev. 2009 Sep;25 Suppl 1:S11-7. doi: 10.1002/dmrr.982. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19662620</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balducci S, Zanuso S, Fernando F, Fallucca S, Fallucca F, Pugliese G; Italian Diabetes Exercise Study (IDES) Group. Physical activity/exercise training in type 2 diabetes. The role of the Italian Diabetes and Exercise Study. Diabetes Metab Res Rev. 2009 Sep;25 Suppl 1:S29-33. doi: 10.1002/dmrr.985. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19662617</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zanuso S, Balducci S, Gutierrez AJ, Bergamin M, Pugliese G. Similar energy expenditure from resistance training at moderate and vigorous intensity in subjects with type 2 diabetes. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2009 Sep;85(3):e40-1. doi: 10.1016/j.diabres.2009.05.003. Epub 2009 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>19500870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zanuso S, Jimenez A, Pugliese G, Corigliano G, Balducci S. Exercise for the management of type 2 diabetes: a review of the evidence. Acta Diabetol. 2010 Mar;47(1):15-22. doi: 10.1007/s00592-009-0126-3. Epub 2009 Jun 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19495557</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balducci S, Zanuso S, Massarini M, Corigliano G, Nicolucci A, Missori S, Cavallo S, Cardelli P, Alessi E, Pugliese G, Fallucca F; Italian Diabetes Exercise Study (IDES) Group. The Italian Diabetes and Exercise Study (IDES): design and methods for a prospective Italian multicentre trial of intensive lifestyle intervention in people with type 2 diabetes and the metabolic syndrome. Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis. 2008 Nov;18(9):585-95. Epub 2007 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>18061415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balducci S, Alessi E, Cardelli P, Cavallo S, Fallucca F, Pugliese G. Effects of different modes of exercise training on glucose control and risk factors for complications in type 2 diabetic patients: a meta-analysis: response to Snowling and Hopkins. Diabetes Care. 2007 Apr;30(4):e25; author reply e26.</citation>
    <PMID>17392536</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 16, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 16, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 17, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Metabolic Fitness Association, Italy</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Giuseppe Pugliese</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>diabetes mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>diabetes education</keyword>
  <keyword>behavioral therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>behavior modification</keyword>
  <keyword>physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>supervised exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>physical fitness</keyword>
  <keyword>HbA1c</keyword>
  <keyword>modifiable cardiovascular risk factors</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

