<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01602692</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2011-0543</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01602692</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Comparison of Tumescence in Breast Reduction Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comparison of Tumescence in Breast Reduction Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators' main hypothesis is that in breast reduction surgery, the use of tumescent
      solution containing both dilute lidocaine and epinephrine will lead to better control of
      postoperative pain, nausea, vomiting, shorter time through postoperative phases of care,
      quicker discharge from the hospital and lower numbers of hospital readmissions than the use
      of tumescent solution containing only dilute epinephrine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative pain is often undermanaged in surgical patients. In the outpatient surgery
      population, such as breast reduction surgery, postoperative pain can lead to increased
      narcotic use, increased nausea, surgical complications and unplanned hospital admission, in
      addition to patient discomfort or dissatisfaction. Tumescence is a method of infiltrating
      tissues, such as the breast, with solutions of very dilute lidocaine and/or very dilute
      epinephrine in order to provide diffuse local anesthesia, hemostasis, and tissue
      manipulation. Both types of solution are considered standard care and both at the University
      of Wisconsin, Madison. There are two main aims to this study. Aim 1 is to determine the
      effect of dilute lidocaine in tumescent solution on post-operative pain following breast
      reduction surgery. Aim 2 of our study is to determine the effect of dilute lidocaine in
      tumescent solution on secondary post-operative outcomes following breast reduction surgery.
      The secondary outcomes that will be measured in this study include average time (minutes)
      spent in the PACU, average time (minutes) spent in Phase 2, total time (minutes) between the
      end of case and discharge home, occurrence of unplanned hospital admission, number of
      episodes of post-operative nausea (subjective feeling vs. emesis) and amount of anti-emetic
      medication used in pacu, phase 2 and the first 24 hours post-op. (mg). The investigators
      hypothesize that tumescence with lidocaine and epinephrine will have improved post-operative
      pain control leading to less narcotic use during the first twenty four hours postoperatively.
      (Aim 1). The investigators also believe that tumescence with lidocaine and epinephrine will
      lead to less time spent in PACU, less time spent in Phase2, less time between the end of the
      case and discharge home, less occurrence of unplanned hospital admissions, less episodes of
      post-operative nausea and less amount of antiemetic medication used in PACU, phase 2 and the
      first 24 hours post-op (Aim 2). The investigators propose that such differences could play a
      significant role in surgical outcomes and patient satisfaction in outpatient plastic surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours following surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Aim 1 is to determine the effect of dilute lidocaine in tumescent solution on post-operative pain following breast reduction surgery. The data points that will be statistically compared will be pain scores determined via a validated pain survey and the amount of narcotic medication administered (in pacu, phase 2 and upto 24 hours post-op) determined from responses to survey questions and by reviewing the medical record.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post operative nausea and vomiting</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary outcomes that will be measured in this study include number of episodes of post-operative nausea (subjective feeling vs. emesis) and amount of anti-emetic medication used in pacu, phase 2 and the first 24 hours post-op. (mg). This data will be attained by reviewing the medical record and through the validated survey questions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The patient's medical record will be reviewed to determine the time it took for the patient to be transitioned from the PACU (post anesthesia care unit) till discharge. This includes the time spent in the PACU, time spent in phase 2 and the total time to discharge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unplanned Hospital Readmission</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 week following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The patient's medical record will be reviewed to see if the patient was readmitted to the hospital (unplanned) due to complications related to this surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain, Postoperative</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tumescent solution with dilute epinephrine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm of the study will be randomized to receive tumescent solution containing dilute epinephrine (1:1,000,000) during their breast reduction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tumescent solution with dilute lidocaine and epinephrine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm of the study will receive tumescent solution containing both dilute lidocaine (0.05%) and dilute epinephrine (1:1,000,000).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tumescent solution with dilute lidocaine and epinephrine</intervention_name>
    <description>Tumescent Solution containing both dilute lidocaine (0.05%) and dilute epinephrine (1:1,000,000)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tumescent solution with dilute lidocaine and epinephrine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tumescent Solution with dilute epinephrine</intervention_name>
    <description>Tumescent Solution containing dilute epinephrine (1:1,000,000) only</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tumescent solution with dilute epinephrine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  all patients presenting for breast reduction surgery at the University of Wisconsin
             Hospital and Clinics and the University of Wisconsin Transformations Surgery Center
             and who do not meet any of the exclusion criteria.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women under the age of 18 years

          -  Breast feeding or pregnant women

          -  Incarcerated women.

          -  Women unable to give consent because of impaired decision making ability.

          -  Women who have reported allergies to the substances that will be used in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Venkat K Rao, M.D. M.B.A</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin Transformations Surgery Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Middleton</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53562</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lu L, Fine NA. The efficacy of continuous local anesthetic infiltration in breast surgery: reduction mammaplasty and reconstruction. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2005 Jun;115(7):1927-34; discussion 1935-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15923838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rawlani V, Kryger ZB, Lu L, Fine NA. A local anesthetic pump reduces postoperative pain and narcotic and antiemetic use in breast reconstruction surgery: a randomized controlled trial. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2008 Jul;122(1):39-52. doi: 10.1097/PRS.0b013e3181774349.</citation>
    <PMID>18594373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kryger ZB, Rawlani V, Lu L, Fine NA. Decreased postoperative pain, narcotic, and antiemetic use after breast reduction using a local anesthetic pain pump. Ann Plast Surg. 2008 Aug;61(2):147-52. doi: 10.1097/SAP.0b013e31815a23ef.</citation>
    <PMID>18650606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schurr MJ, Gordon DB, Pellino TA, Scanlon TA. Continuous local anesthetic infusion for pain management after outpatient inguinal herniorrhaphy. Surgery. 2004 Oct;136(4):761-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15467660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cleeland CS, Ryan KM. Pain assessment: global use of the Brief Pain Inventory. Ann Acad Med Singapore. 1994 Mar;23(2):129-38. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8080219</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quality improvement guidelines for the treatment of acute pain and cancer pain. American Pain Society Quality of Care Committee. JAMA. 1995 Dec 20;274(23):1874-80. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7500539</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein JA. Tumescent technique for regional anesthesia permits lidocaine doses of 35 mg/kg for liposuction. J Dermatol Surg Oncol. 1990 Mar;16(3):248-63. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2179348</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ostad A, Kageyama N, Moy RL. Tumescent anesthesia with a lidocaine dose of 55 mg/kg is safe for liposuction. Dermatol Surg. 1996 Nov;22(11):921-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9063507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larson JD, Gutowski KA, Marcus BC, Rao VK, Avery PG, Stacey DH, Yang RZ. The effect of electroacustimulation on postoperative nausea, vomiting, and pain in outpatient plastic surgery patients: a prospective, randomized, blinded, clinical trial. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2010 Mar;125(3):989-94. doi: 10.1097/PRS.0b013e3181ccdc23.</citation>
    <PMID>20195124</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heller L, Kowalski AM, Wei C, Butler CE. Prospective, randomized, double-blind trial of local anesthetic infusion and intravenous narcotic patient-controlled anesthesia pump for pain management after free TRAM flap breast reconstruction. Plast Reconstr Surg. 2008 Oct;122(4):1010-8. doi: 10.1097/PRS.0b013e3181858c09.</citation>
    <PMID>18827631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 21, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 6, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 6, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 8, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pain, postoperative</keyword>
  <keyword>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient Readmission</keyword>
  <keyword>Time to Discharge</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nausea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Racepinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephryl borate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

