<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01605643</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-001144</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U54CA153605</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01605643</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Biomarker Feedback to Motivate Tobacco Cessation in Pregnant Alaska Native Women</brief_title>
  <acronym>MAW</acronym>
  <official_title>Biomarker Feedback to Motivate Tobacco Cessation in Pregnant Alaska Native Women: Phase 1</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alaska Native Tribal Health Consortium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Use of tobacco is very high among Alaska Native women. The investigators are conducting a
      three phase study. The first phase will examine biomarkers of tobacco exposure in pregnant
      women and their newborns. The second phase is a qualitative study to translate the biomarker
      findings into intervention messages. The third phase is a pilot of the biomarker feedback
      intervention compared with a control condition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Developing effective tobacco cessation interventions during pregnancy for American Indian and
      Alaska Native people is a national priority and will contribute to the U.S. public health
      objective of reducing tobacco-related cancer health disparities. The proposed project builds
      on our successful partnership with the Alaska Native community and previous work with Alaska
      Native pregnant women. We propose to develop and test a novel biomarker feedback intervention
      relating cotinine levels in the urine of pregnant women with the woman and infant's likely
      exposure to the tobacco specific nitrosamine and carcinogen
      4-(methylnitrosamino)-1-(3-pyridyl)-1-butanone) (NNK). This 5-year project will be conducted
      in three phases. In Phase 1 we will utilize a non-randomized, clinical observational trial to
      examine biomarkers of nicotine and carcinogen exposure (urine cotinine and total NNAL [a
      metabolite of NNK], respectively) among 150 maternal-infant pairs with assessments conducted
      during pregnancy and at delivery. In Phase 2, we will obtain qualitative feedback on the
      findings from Phase 1 through individual interviews conducted with 32 women who use tobacco
      to develop the biomarker feedback intervention messages. Phase 3 will consist of a formative
      evaluation of the biomarker feedback intervention with 80 pregnant women using a two-group
      randomized design to assess the intervention's feasibility and acceptability, and the
      biochemically confirmed abstinence rate at the end of pregnancy. All phases of the project
      will be guided by a Community Advisory Committee. Each phase is an important step to advance
      our understanding of the potential for biomarker feedback as a strategy to help Alaska Native
      pregnant women quit tobacco use. The potential reach of the intervention is significant from
      a public health perspective as over 600 tobacco users deliver each year at the Alaska Native
      Medical Center in Anchorage where the proposed project will take place. Developing effective
      interventions for tobacco cessation during pregnancy is important to reduce adverse health
      consequences for the mother and neonate and future risk of tobacco-caused cancers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>NNAL</measure>
    <time_frame>delivery</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cotinine</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed during pregnancy until approximately week 40 gestation and Infants will be assessed at birth only</time_frame>
    <description>tobacco exposure measured during pregnancy and at delivery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Tobacco Use</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      urine and serum specimen samples collected from mother and infant pairs
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pregnant women will be recruited through prenatal care
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        To be eligible the woman must:

          1. be Alaska Native,

          2. be aged 18 years or older,

          3. provide written informed consent,

          4. be currently pregnant (1st, 2nd or 3rd trimester), and

          5. plan to deliver at the ANMC. An additional inclusion criterion for current tobacco
             users is any use in the past 7 days. Our preliminary studies indicate that women may
             use more than one form of tobacco. To enhance feasibility of recruitment and
             generalizability, women will not be excluded if they use more than one form of
             tobacco. Instead, group composition will be based on the primary type of tobacco used.
             An additional inclusion criterion for non-tobacco users is no use of any form of
             tobacco in the last 6 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Women will be excluded if they have used nicotine replacement therapy (NRT) or have
             participated in a behavioral or pharmacological tobacco cessation program within the
             past 30 days.

          2. Alcohol and other drug use will not be an exclusionary criterion because the
             biomarkers are specific to tobacco exposure.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christi A Patten, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alaska Native Tribal Health Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Anchorage</city>
        <state>Alaska</state>
        <zip>99577</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 23, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 25, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christi Patten</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Psychology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>tobacco use</keyword>
  <keyword>pregnancy</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

