<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01602211</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2605.00</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-00743</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2605.00</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA160684</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01602211</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>INSPIRE: Internet and Social-media Program With Information and Resources for Long-Term Cancer Survivors Who Underwent Stem Cell Transplant</brief_title>
  <acronym>INSPIRE</acronym>
  <official_title>INSPIRE for Survivorship After Transplant: A Multicenter Randomized Controlled Trial of an Internet and Social-Media Program for Long-Term Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation Survivors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized clinical trial studies an internet and social-media program for improving
      quality of life in long-term survivors who underwent stem cell transplant. In this study,
      researchers want to compare a survivorship internet program to the standard treatment of
      currently available internet sites for transplant survivors to learn which works better for
      people who have received bone marrow or blood stem cell transplants. A survivorship-focused
      internet program may improve mood, stress, and preventive health care, and provide useful
      health resources for transplant survivors. It is not yet known whether currently available
      internet sites are more effective than a survivorship-focused internet program in improving
      quality of life in cancer survivors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine whether 2-10 year hematopoietic cell transplant (HCT) survivors with elevated
      depression or cancer-related distress who are randomized to receive access to a tailored
      internet-based program report reduced depression and distress when compared with control
      group survivors who receive access to an internet site with links to transplant and
      cancer-specific online resources and delayed access to the internet site (active control).

      II. Determine whether survivors with low survivorship preventive care adherence (PCA) who are
      randomized to receive access to the tailored internet-based program, including a survivorship
      preventive care plan, report increased PCA when compared with the active control group
      survivors.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Secondary outcomes will include process measures of internet study reach and utilization,
      as well as physical function, physical activity level, and knowledge of survivorship needs.
      Further analyses will identify risk factors for disparities in survivorship preventive care
      adherence in HCT survivors.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 arms.

      ARM I: Participants receive full access to the INSPIRE internet site comprising an
      individually tailored program with a greeting home page with links to each target area, a 'My
      Health Action Plan' health care guideline for transplant survivors, self-care tips and tool
      pages for each complication and major issues for HCT survivors, a section for each
      complication (mood, energy, heart health, strengthening bones, second cancers), resource
      pages, opportunities to send secure messages with questions or comments on any topic,
      opportunities to request additional assistance or information, mobile texting options, and
      social media links (Twitter/Facebook/Pinterest) maintained and monitored by the Social Media
      Specialist.

      ARM II: Participants receive annotated website links to existing transplant and cancer
      survivor sites, followed by delayed access to the INSPIRE internet program after 1 year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 14, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 28, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 28, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cancer and treatment distress (CTXD) score as reported on the PCA using binary outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PHQ-8 depression score as reported on the PCA, using binary outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of adherence to recommended survivorship preventive care and barriers to PCA</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Composite measure of health behaviors, including tobacco use, alcohol use, physical activity, use of sunscreen, food intake, body mass index, and sleep.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical function, as assessed by the Patient Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total minutes per week of moderate to vigorous intensity exercise as assessed by the Godin Leisure Time Exercise Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>This measure is a measure of leisure time physical activity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1600</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer Survivor</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Hematopoietic and Lymphoid Cell Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (INSPIRE internet full program access)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive full access to the INSPIRE internet site comprising an individually tailored program with a greeting home page with links to each target area, a 'My Health Action Plan' health care guideline for transplant survivors, self-care tips and tool pages for each complication and major issues for HCT survivors, a section for each complication (mood, energy, heart health, strengthening bones, second cancers), resource pages, opportunities to send secure messages with questions or comments on any topic, opportunities to request additional assistance or information, mobile texting options, and social media links (Twitter/Facebook/Pinterest) maintained and monitored by the Social Media Specialist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (delayed program access control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive annotated website links to existing transplant and cancer survivor sites, followed by delayed access to the INSPIRE internet program after 1 year.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Internet-Based Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Receive full access to INSPIRE</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (INSPIRE internet full program access)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Internet-Based Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Receive access to an annotated list of existing resources for transplant and cancer survivors and delayed access to INSPIRE site</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (delayed program access control)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medical Chart Review</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (delayed program access control)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chart Review</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality-of-Life Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (INSPIRE internet full program access)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (delayed program access control)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Quality of Life Assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire Administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (INSPIRE internet full program access)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (delayed program access control)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Received a transplant at a consortium center for a hematologic malignancy or
             myelodysplasia

          -  Currently 2-10 years after first HCT

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Does not have internet and email access; note that survivors otherwise eligible, but
             excluded from full study participation because of this exclusion, will be asked to
             fill out a mailed copy of the baseline assessment for use in secondary aims analyses;
             they will be sent an information form and a copy of the tailored 'My Health Action
             Plan' health care guideline for transplant survivors also provided to randomized
             participants

          -  English insufficient to complete baseline patient-reported outcomes (PRO) assessments

          -  Has received treatment for a recurrent or 2nd cancer that required &gt; surgical excision
             in the past 2 years or did not have a hematologic malignancy or myelodysplasia
             diagnosis or did not receive a first transplant between 2-10 years before approach for
             the study; (these participants will be ineligible for randomization, but will have
             intervention site access if they complete baseline PRO assessment)

          -  Scores 20 or above on the patient health questionnaire (PHQ)-8 depression measure
             (indicating severe depression); these participants will be contacted by a study
             psychologist to evaluate and provide resources to address their needs (2% of enrollees
             in our previous study); they will be ineligible for randomization, but will have
             intervention site access if they complete baseline PRO assessment

          -  Residing in an institution or other living situation where health care decisions are
             not made by the participant (e.g., hospitalized, prisoners, living in a rehabilitation
             facility)

          -  Does not complete baseline PRO assessment items required to determine stratification
             or whether the survivor meets inclusion and exclusion criteria

          -  Has medical or health issues prohibiting computer use (e.g., vision-impaired,
             cognitively impaired, illness or accident impairing computer function)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Syrjala</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutch/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moffitt Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wayne State University/Karmanos Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Nebraska Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68198</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic Taussig Cancer Institute, Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania/Abramson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutch/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 16, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 18, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stem cell transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer survivors</keyword>
  <keyword>internet</keyword>
  <keyword>social media</keyword>
  <keyword>distress</keyword>
  <keyword>health care adherence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

