<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01605344</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LCCC 1127</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01605344</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Crossover Evaluation of Effect of Atorvastatin on PK of Irinotecan in CRC Patients Receiving FOLFIRI</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Crossover Evaluation of the Effect of Atorvastatin on the Pharmacokinetics of Irinotecan in Colorectal Cancer Patients Receiving FOLFIRI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effect of atorvastatin on the pharmacokinetic
      profile of irinotecan and SN-38. To further evaluate the safety of atorvastatin in
      combination with FOLFIRI. To further evaluate the safety and of irinotecan in combination
      with atorvastatin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, prospective, randomized, crossover study to address the
      pharmacokinetic effects of atorvastatin on irinotecan metabolism in patients receiving their
      first cycle of FOLFIRI (5-fluorouracil + leucovorin + irinotecan).

      Each cycle of FOLFIRI is defined as 28 days, with a dose of FOLFIRI administered on day 1 and
      day 15. Patients will be recruited from the UNC Lineberger Cancer Center, referred by their
      primary oncologist for the treatment of metastatic colorectal cancer (mCRC). After obtaining
      informed consent, the patient will be randomized to either ARM A or ARM B.

      Blood samples will be collected on day 1 and 15 of FOLFIRI prior to treatment with irinotecan
      (baseline), immediately following the end of the irinotecan infusion, and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2,
      4, 6, and 24 hours following the end of the irinotecan infusion.

      ARM A subjects will receive atorvastatin 20 mg orally once daily given for two weeks starting
      on Day -14 during PERIOD ONE. ARM A will then receive no statin during PERIOD TWO. Patients
      will receive FOLFIRI infusion on day 1 and day 15. Blood samples will be collected at
      baseline and periodically through 24 hours.

      ARM B subjects will receive no atorvastatin during PERIOD ONE. ARM B subjects will receive
      atorvastatin 20 mg orally once daily for two weeks during PERIOD TWO (starting on Day 2).
      Patients will receive FOLFIRI infusion on day 1 and day 15. Blood samples will be collected
      at baseline and periodically through 24 hours.

      DNA extraction and genetic analysis of UGT1A1 polymorphisms will be performed in
      collaboration with Dr. Federico Innocenti and those patients homozygous for the UGT1A1*28
      allele will be excluded due to their altered irinotecan metabolism.

      Patients will be followed until Day 1 of Cycle 2 of FOLFIRI. Patients removed from study for
      unacceptable adverse events will be followed until resolution or stabilization of the
      event(s).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study was withdrawn due to lack of patient enrollment.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) of irinotecan.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on day 1 and 15 of FOLFIRI prior to treatment with irinotecan (baseline), immediately following the end of the irinotecan infusion, and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, and 24 hours following the end of the irinotecan infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>At the end of the screening period, eligible patients will be randomly assigned in a 1:1 ratio to receive atorvastatin prior to Day 1 of FOLFIRI (ARM A) or atorvastatin prior to Day 15 FOLFIRI (ARM B). Patients in ARM A must start atorvastatin within 28 days of randomization and patients in ARM B should receive FOLFIRI within 28 days of randomization; if not, the Investigator must be notified.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) of SN-38.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples will be collected on day 1 and 15 of FOLFIRI prior to treatment with irinotecan (baseline), immediately following the end of the irinotecan infusion, and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, and 24 hours following the end of the irinotecan infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>At the end of the screening period, eligible patients will be randomly assigned in a 1:1 ratio to receive atorvastatin prior to Day 1 of FOLFIRI (ARM A) or atorvastatin prior to Day 15 FOLFIRI (ARM B). Patients in ARM A must start atorvastatin within 28 days of randomization and patients in ARM B should receive FOLFIRI within 28 days of randomization; if not, the Investigator must be notified.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Adenocarcinoma of the Colon or Rectum</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ARM A subjects will receive atorvastatin 20 mg orally once daily given for two weeks prior to FOLFIRI. The last dose of atorvastatin will be taken day 1 of FOLFIRI. ARM A will then receive no statin for the next 2 weeks. Patients will receive FOLFIRI infusion on day 1 and day 15. Blood samples will be collected at baseline and periodically through 24 hours on day 1 and 15 of FOLFIRI.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ARM B subjects will receive no atorvastatin prior to day 1 of FOLFIRI. ARM B subjects will receive atorvastatin 20 mg orally once daily for two weeks prior to day 15 of FOLFIRI. The last dose of atorvastatin will be taken day 15 of FOLFIRI. Patients will receive FOLFIRI infusion on day 1 and day 15. Blood samples will be collected at baseline and periodically through 24 hours on day 1 and 15 of FOLFIRI.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FOLFIRI.</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will receive FOLFIRI infusion on day 1 and day 15.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-fluorouracil + leucovorin + irinotecan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atorvastatin</intervention_name>
    <description>A subjects will receive atorvastatin 20 mg orally once daily given for two weeks starting on Day -14 during PERIOD ONE. ARM A will then receive no statin during PERIOD TWO. ARM B subjects will receive no atorvastatin during PERIOD ONE. ARM B subjects will receive atorvastatin 20 mg orally once daily for two weeks during PERIOD TWO (starting on Day 2). One cycle = 28 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lipitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥18 years of age (no upper age limit)

          2. Histological or cytological documentation of adenocarcinoma of the colon or rectum,
             and patient scheduled to begin FOLFIRI for treatment of their metastatic disease

          3. Patients taking statins at the time of enrollment are permitted. Patients taking
             statins (or one of the prohibited drugs, see section 4.2.27 and section 12.1) must
             agree to a 2 week washout prior to treatment with atorvastatin (see Schema) and
             section 5.2

          4. Life expectancy of at least 3 months

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤1

          6. Adequate bone marrow, renal, and hepatic function, as evidenced by the following
             within 7 days of treatment initiation with atorvastatin (or nothing, if enrolled into
             Arm B): absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1,500/mm3 platelets ≥100,000/mm3 hemoglobin
             ≥9.0 g/dL serum creatinine ≤1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) AST and ALT ≤ 3 x ULN
             Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN Alkaline phosphatase ≤2.5 x ULN Amylase and lipase ≤1.5 x
             ULN INR/PTT ≤1.5 x ULN CPK ≤ ULN

          7. Women of childbearing potential and male subjects must agree to use adequate
             contraception for the duration of study participation. Adequate contraception is
             defined as any medically recommended method (or combination of methods) as per
             standard of care.

          8. Medical oncologist agrees that two week window is appropriate/safe prior to start of
             FOLFIRI for trial candidate.

          9. The subject is capable of understanding and complying with parameters as outlined in
             the protocol

         10. Signed, IRB-approved written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any prior allergies to statin therapy or adverse events that precluded further use,
             including but not limited to myopathy, rhabdomyolysis, etc. Patients who had to change
             from atorvastatin to another statin for safety or efficacy reasons will also be
             excluded.

          2. Prior treatment with FOLFIRI or single agent irinotecan is prohibited within six weeks
             of enrollment. All prior toxicity from previous irinotecan administration must be
             resolved prior to enrollment. No more than 2 prior therapeutic regimens for metastatic
             disease are allowed.

          3. Patients will not be allowed to receive bevacizumab or EGFR inhibitors (cetuximab or
             panitumumab) for the duration of the study (1 cycle).

          4. Patients with baseline LDL ≤ 100 mg/dL who are not currently treated with statins

          5. Patients homozygous for the UGT1A1*28 allele, and patients of Asian descent homozygous
             or heterozygous for the UGT1A1*6 allele will be excluded due to their altered
             irinotecan metabolism

          6. Pregnant or breastfeeding patients. Women of childbearing potential must have a
             pregnancy test performed a maximum of 7 days before start of atorvastatin and FOLFIRI
             treatment, and a negative result must be documented before start of treatment with
             atorvastatin or FOLFIRI (whichever is received first by patient).

          7. Patients who have been treated with any hematopoietic colony-stimulating growth
             factors (e.g., G-CSF, GM-CSF) ≤2 weeks prior to starting study drug. Erythropoietin or
             darbepoetin therapy, if initiated ≥2 weeks prior to enrollment, may be continued.

          8. History of Gilbert's syndrome

          9. Pernicious anemia or other anemias due to Vitamin B12 deficiency (due to potential
             masking of deficiency by leucovorin)

         10. Known Dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase (DPD) deficiency

         11. Major surgical procedure, open biopsy, or significant traumatic injury within 28 days
             before start of Day 1 of treatment with FOLFIRI

         12. Any patients with a history of stroke or TIA within 6 months prior to study enrollment

         13. Active cardiac disease including any of the following: Congestive heart failure (New
             York Heart Association [NYHA]) ≥Class 2 (see Appendix C) Unstable angina (angina
             symptoms at rest), new-onset angina (begun within the last 3 months). Myocardial
             infarction less than 6 months before start of Day 1 of FOLFIRI Cardiac arrhythmias
             requiring anti-arrhythmic therapy (beta blockers or digoxin are permitted)

         14. Ongoing infection &gt; Grade 2 according to NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse
             Events version 4.0 (CTCAE v. 4.0)

         15. Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection

         16. Presence of acute or chronic liver disease, renal disease or pancreatitis

         17. Known history of chronic hepatitis B or C

         18. Symptomatic metastatic brain or meningeal tumors unless the patient is &gt;6 months from
             definitive therapy, has a negative imaging study within 4 weeks of FOLFIRI initiation,
             and is clinically stable with respect to the tumor at the time of study entry. Also,
             the patient must not be undergoing acute steroid therapy or taper (chronic steroid
             therapy is acceptable provided that the dose is s4.2.2table for one month prior to D1
             of treatment under this study)

         19. History of organ allograft

         20. Non-healing wound, ulcer, or bone fracture

         21. Known hypersensitivity to any of the study drugs, study drug classes, or excipients in
             the formulation

         22. Inability to swallow oral medications

         23. Evidence or history of bleeding diathesis. Any hemorrhage or bleeding event &gt; Grade 4
             within 4 weeks of start of FOLFIRI

         24. Patients with diarrhea CTCAE v4 grade ≥2

         25. Any malabsorption condition

         26. Unresolved toxicity higher than CTCAE v. 4.0 Grade 1 attributed to any prior
             therapy/procedure excluding alopecia and oxaliplatin-induced neurotoxicity (which must
             be ≤Grade 2)

         27. Patients unable or unwilling to discontinue (and substitute if necessary) use of
             prohibited drugs, juices and herbal supplements for at least 2 weeks prior to
             atorvastatin initiation (see Appendix A for list of prohibited drugs, juices and
             herbal supplements)

         28. Substance abuse, medical, psychological, or social conditions that may interfere with
             the patient's participation in the study or evaluation of the study results

         29. Unwilling to provide consent for genetic studies of whole blood or plasma specimens
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Autumn McRee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://unclineberger.org</url>
    <description>Website for UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 23, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 24, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 27, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced colon cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Advanced rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic colon cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Lipitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Atorvastatin</keyword>
  <keyword>FOLFIRI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atorvastatin Calcium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

