<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01427426</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H11-00426</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01427426</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Does a Nutritional Supplement Increase Vitality, Energy and Perceived Well Being?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does a Nutritional Supplement Increase Vitality, Energy and Perceived Well Being?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Factors Group of Nutritional Companies</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>QualityMetrics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Factors Group is a producer of nutritional supplements. This study aims to determine whether
      one of their products improves the energy and sense of well-being in individuals who consume
      it. Interested subjects will complete a 1 week lead-in phase where they will be asked to
      consume a placebo daily to see if they are a good fit for the study. After the lead-in phase,
      subjects will be randomized to take either All Greens or a different placebo for 12 weeks.
      The investigators expect All Greens to have better results than the placebo, but subjects
      will not know which supplement they are taking. The primary outcome is a score on a
      questionnaire of well being.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PURPOSE To conduct a study to determine the potential benefits of All Greens.

      HYPOTHESIS Our primary hypothesis is that a greater proportion of participants on All Greens
      will score higher on the subjective scores of vitality and energy, as measured by our
      validated survey, than those consuming the control formulation.

      JUSTIFICATION All Greens is a mixture of organic alfalfa powder, barley, wheat grass juice
      powder, lycopene, cranberry juice extract, rosehips, grapeseed phytosomes, soya extract,
      Acidophilus, bromelain, apple pectin, and other ingredients. All Greens is a well-balanced
      phytonutrient formula that nourishes, energizes, cleanses and acts as a whole body tonic.
      Recently, Boon et al (2004) have published results demonstrating some clinical benefits of
      consuming Greens+, a product similar to All Greens. After 12 weeks, women randomized to
      consume Greens+ scored marginally higher on subjective scores on Vitality and significantly
      higher on Energy than those consuming a placebo group (Boon, 2004). However, limitations of
      this study such as incomplete blinding and a high drop-out rate limit the veracity of the
      findings.

      OBJECTIVES To determine if 12 weeks of consumption of All Greens increases vitality, energy,
      and perception of well-being compared to consumption of a placebo in adult women and men
      (18-45 y).

      RESEARCH METHOD The investigators aim to recruit 120 people (18-45 y) through advertisements
      and word of mouth. In a lead-in phase, subjects will be asked to consume an 'initiation
      drink' daily for a week. The purpose of this is to identify those subjects who are unlikely
      to complete the study so they can be excluded before randomization, in order to minimize the
      dropout rate. The lead-in product will be composed primarily of rice flour, with other
      ingredients added to make it comparable to the All Greens and control formulation.

      Participants remaining after the week lead-in phase week will be asked to attend a morning
      clinic at the university. Height and weight will be recorded, health and demographic
      information will be collected by questionnaire, and outcome measure questionnaires will be
      completed. Participants will be randomized to All Greens or the control formulation. Subjects
      will be instructed to record any side effects or adverse events in a study diary. At 6 weeks,
      study staff will phone participants, to check on progress.

      Twelve weeks after randomization, participants will be asked to return to clinic to repeat
      the outcome measure questionnaires. Compliance will be assessed by weighing returned
      supplements and by patient diary. Adverse events will be recorded in the diaries. If patients
      withdraw from the study they will still be encouraged to return at 12 weeks to complete the
      outcome measures to allow for intent-to-treat analysis.

      SAMPLE SIZE The sample size estimate is based on the primary outcome. The mean score on the
      vitality subscale of the SF-36 in a large study of women was 65 with a SD of 18. A ten-point
      change in the SF-36 vitality sub-scale can be considered a &quot;moderate&quot; effect that is
      clinically and socially relevant. Assuming 80% power, P-value of 0.05, an SD of 18, a
      correlation between baseline and follow-up measures of at least R=0.5, 50 subjects per
      treatment group would be needed to detect a 5 point difference between the groups. Assuming
      20% attrition 120 subjects randomized would be required.

      STATISTICAL ANALYSIS Differences in outcomes measures at twelve weeks will be assessed by
      multiple regression analysis with adjustment for baseline values and other predetermined
      factors (i.e. last menstrual period, oral contraceptive use).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in score on the Short-Form 36 (SF-36)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Study End (12 weeks after randomization)</time_frame>
    <description>The Short Form-36 (SF-36) is a validated, multi-purpose, short-form health survey that is a generic measure of health status/quality of life. It provides an overall measure of physical and mental health, as well as eight subscale profiles, of which three were considered to be relevant for this study: general health, vitality, and mental health. The SF-36 is licensed by the company QualityMetric.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in scores on 10 cm Visual Analogue Scales (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Randomization and 12 weeks (study end)</time_frame>
    <description>VAS scores will assess energy levels and sense of well being of subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who report side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>From enrollment to 13 weeks (study end)</time_frame>
    <description>Date, time, description, duration, frequency and severity (on a 5 point scale), of side effects will be recorded by the participant by use of a study diary.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of unused supplement packets</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment to 13 weeks (study end)</time_frame>
    <description>Compliance will be assessed by counting returned supplement packets as well as by review of the subject's study diary.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All Greens</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will consume the All Greens product daily. Product is prepared by mixing with either water, juice or in a smoothie.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control formulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will consume a product of similar consistency and comparable taste that does not have the same healthy ingredients as the All Greens.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>All Greens</intervention_name>
    <description>All Greens is a mixture of organic alfalfa powder, barley, wheat grass juice powder, lycopene, cranberry juice extract, rosehips, grapeseed phytosomes, soya extract, Acidophilus, bromelain, apple pectin, and other ingredients. All Greens is approved by Health Canada and available to the public for purchase.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All Greens</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control Formulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The Control Formulation is a rice-flour based product that has been designed to mimic the All Greens in appearance and taste.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control formulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Not taking any other nutritional supplement (including fish oils, vitamins...) or be
             willing to discontinue use for duration of study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical conditions such as diabetes, asthma, cancer, cardiovascular disease, high
             blood pressure, celiac disease, a history of kidney stones or psychiatric illness.

          -  Currently taking antidepressants, anticoagulant or other medications that may interact
             with the nutritional supplement.

          -  Unable to provide informed consent

          -  Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy J Green, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia, Department of Food, Nutrition and Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of British Columbia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6T 1Z4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boon H, Clitheroe J, Forte T. Effects of greens+: a randomized, controlled trial. Can J Diet Pract Res. 2004 Summer;65(2):66-71.</citation>
    <PMID>15217524</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 31, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 1, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 14, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 14, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 17, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitality</keyword>
  <keyword>Well-being</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutritional Supplement</keyword>
  <keyword>Phytonutrient</keyword>
  <keyword>Greens</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

