<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01429610</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KALLA0804</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01429610</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rituximab+mVPDL for CD20(+) Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <acronym>RADICAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase 2 Study Evaluating the Efficacy of Rituximab Plus Modified VPDL for Newly Diagnosed CD20-Positive Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Asan Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Asan Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators would like to propose a phase-2 prospective multicenter trial evaluating
      the efficacy of rituximab combination with our current chemotherapy strategy for adult Acute
      Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL), in order to prove out whether the addition of rituximab during
      induction, consolidation, and post-alloHCT status can improve the outcome in terms of
      relapse-free survival (RFS) when compared with our prior data as a historical control.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      According to the recent results on the outcome of escalated daunorubicin-based protocol for
      adult ALL which has been performed by 'Adult ALL Working Party of the Korean Society of
      Hematology' (data were announced at 2010 Annual Meeting of ASCO, Chicago, IL), CR rate of
      90.6% was satisfactory, but the 2-year / 3-year disease-free survival (DFS) were
      disappointing (43.6% and 39.9%, respectively), which means that the adequate post-remission
      therapy to control minimal residual disease after the achievement of CR is very important to
      improve the outcome of adult ALL.

      Allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation (AlloHCT) is recommended as a post-remission
      therapy for patients with adult ALL, and reduced intensity conditioning has been tried to
      decrease TRM rate. However, many patients received consolidation chemotherapy rather than
      alloHCT owing to the absence of HLA-matched donor, limitation of age, and combined
      comorbidities (among 190 patients who have been included in our previously-mentioned study,
      only 52.3% received alloHCT).

      Recently, stagnation in the treatment of adult ALL appears to be reached, maybe due to a
      borderline for further intensification of chemotherapeutic dose. Dose-escalation strategy has
      many difficulties in adoption for the treatment of adult ALL in terms of increased morbidity
      and mortality, not to mention the efficacy of such strategies. New, preferably
      non-chemotherapy approaches (maybe targeted therapy) are therefore urgently required.

      For Ph(+) ALL, the introduction of BCR/ABL tyrosine kinase inhibitor has improved the
      treatment outcome with tolerable toxicities. Applying a similar strategy to Ph(-) ALL,
      targeting leukemia surface antigens with monoclonal antibodies is another promising strategy.

      CD 20 expression of at least 20% has been known to be found in 22-48% of pre-B ALL, and
      appears to be associated with a poor prognosis, although there are controversies in pediatric
      patients. Based on the significant improvement of the outcome in B-cell NHL, preliminary data
      regarding the use of rituximab in frontline therapy for CD20-positive precursor B-cell ALL
      suggest its use may be beneficial. Especially, monoclonal antibodies are thought to be more
      effective when combined with chemotherapy and treated in the state of minimal residual
      disease, which suggests the interest of evaluating rituximab combined to current chemotherapy
      of adult ALL. Recent data on the efficacy of rituximab-combined chemotherapy showed that
      rates of CR and OS were superior with the modified hyperCVAD and rituximab regimens compared
      with standard hyper-CVAD (70% versus 38%, p&lt;0.001) in younger (age &lt; 60 years) CD20-positive
      subset, although it was an analysis of different patient groups who were treated with various
      regimen5.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>relapse-free survival (RFS) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>complete remission (CR) rates</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks (from the initiation of induction treatment)</time_frame>
    <description>among total patients / each subset of subsets A.
[Subset A]
Precursor B-cell vs. T-cell
Younger (age&lt;60 years) vs. older (age≥60 years)
Risk group: standard vs. high</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>relapse-free survival rates</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>among patients in each subset of A &amp; B.
[Subset A]
Precursor B-cell vs. T-cell
Younger (age&lt;60 years) vs. older (age≥60 years)
Risk group: standard vs. high.
[Subset B]
AlloHCT recipients vs. non-recipients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival rates</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>among total patients / each subset of A &amp; B
[Subset A]
Precursor B-cell vs. T-cell
Younger (age&lt;60 years) vs. older (age≥60 years)
Risk group: standard vs. high [Subset B]
AlloHCT recipients vs. non-recipients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence and maximal severity of acute / chronic graft-versus-host disease</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>among alloHCT recipients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">78</enrollment>
  <condition>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rituximab+mVPDL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who were CD20(+), newly-diagnosed adult ALL and treated with rituximab + mVPDL treatment plan</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab+mVPDL</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction:
Dauno 90 mg/m2/d by civ (d1-3)
Vinc 2 mg iv (d1, 8)
Pred 60 mg/m2/d po (d1-14)
for Ph(-): L-asp 4,000 units/m2/day im/sc (d17-28) for Ph(+): Imatinib 600mg/d po qd (d8-continue till the end of maintenance or just before alloHCT)
Rituximab 375mg/m2/d (d8)
Consolidation A (cycle1)
D 45 mg/m2/day by continuous iv (d1, 2)
V 2 mg iv (d1, 8)
P 60 mg/m2/day po (d1-14)
for Ph(-): L-asp (d1-14) for Ph(+): Imatinib
Rituximab 375mg/m2/d (d8)
Consolidation B (cycles2&amp;4)
Cyt 2,000 mg/m2/d iv over 2 hr (d1-4)
Eto 150 mg/m2/d iv over 3 hr (d1-4)
Rituximab 375mg/m2/d d8
Consolidation C (cycles 3&amp;5)
Methotrexate 220 mg/m2 iv bolus, then 60mg/m2/h for 36 hr (d1-2, 15-16)
Leucovorin 50 mg/m2 iv every 6hr for 3 doses,
Rituximab 375mg/m2/d (d8&amp;22)
Maintenance (for 2 years)
- for Ph(-): 6- Mercaptopurine 60 mg/m2 po qd Methotrexate 20 mg/m2 po qw for Ph(+): imatinib 600mg/d po qd
Consider alloHCT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rituximab+mVPDL</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mabthera</other_name>
    <other_name>VCS</other_name>
    <other_name>Daunobrastina</other_name>
    <other_name>Solondo</other_name>
    <other_name>Leunase</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytarabine</other_name>
    <other_name>Efosin</other_name>
    <other_name>DBLMethotrexate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who were previously untreated and had either ALL or high-risk lymphoblastic
             lymphoma.

          -  Patients whose leukemic blast cells express ≥20% of CD20 antigens at time of diagnosis

          -  No prior chemotherapy for leukemia (use of hydroxyurea or leukapheresis are
             permitted.)

          -  Estimated life expectancy of more than 3 months

          -  ECOG performance status of 2 or lower, Karnofsky scale &gt; 60

          -  Adequate cardiac function (EF&gt;45%) on echocardiogram or Heart scan (MUGA scan)

          -  15 years of age and over.

          -  Adequate renal function (creatinine&lt;1.5 mg/dL)

          -  Adequate hepatic function. (Bilirubin&lt;1.5 mg/dL, transaminases levels&lt;3 times the
             upper normal limit [5 times for patients with liver metastasis or hepatomegaly]). Even
             the initial level exceed the upper limits, patient will be acceptable when the levels
             on day 8 satisfies the inclusion criteria.

          -  All patients gave written informed consent according to guidelines at each
             institution's committee on human research.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute biphenotypic leukemia, acute biclonal leukemia, or acute mixed leukemia

          -  Presence of significant uncontrolled active infection

          -  Presence of uncontrolled bleeding

          -  Any coexisting major illness or organ failure

          -  Patients with psychiatric disorder or mental deficiency severe as to make compliance
             with the treatment unlike, and making informed consent impossible

          -  Nursing women, pregnant women, women of childbearing potential who do not want
             adequate contraception

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of prior malignancy unless disease-free for at least 5 years
             following therapy with curative intent (except curatively treated nonmelanoma skin
             cancer, in situ carcinoma, or cervical intraepithelial neoplasia)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Young Don Joo, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Inje University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chonnam National University Hwasun Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hwasun</city>
        <state>Chollanamdo</state>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hematologic Oncology Clinic, National Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Koyang</city>
        <state>Kongki</state>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Division of Hematology-Oncology, Dong-A University College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Busan</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dong-A University College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Busan</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inje University Busan Paik Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Busan</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inje University Haeundae-Paik Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Busan</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kosin University College of Medicine, Kosin University Gospel Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Busan</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Catholic University of Daegu School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Daegu</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Keimyung University Dongsan Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Daegu</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kyungpook National Unviersity Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Daegu</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yeungnam University College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Daegu</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chungnam National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Daejeon</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asan Medical Center, University of Ulsan College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chung-Ang University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ewha Womans University Mokdong Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Korea University Anam Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Soonchunhyang University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ulsan University Hospital, University of Ulsan College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulsan</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boissel N, Auclerc MF, Lhéritier V, Perel Y, Thomas X, Leblanc T, Rousselot P, Cayuela JM, Gabert J, Fegueux N, Piguet C, Huguet-Rigal F, Berthou C, Boiron JM, Pautas C, Michel G, Fière D, Leverger G, Dombret H, Baruchel A. Should adolescents with acute lymphoblastic leukemia be treated as old children or young adults? Comparison of the French FRALLE-93 and LALA-94 trials. J Clin Oncol. 2003 Mar 1;21(5):774-80. Epub 2003 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>12610173</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hallböök H, Gustafsson G, Smedmyr B, Söderhäll S, Heyman M; Swedish Adult Acute Lymphocytic Leukemia Group; Swedish Childhood Leukemia Group. Treatment outcome in young adults and children &gt;10 years of age with acute lymphoblastic leukemia in Sweden: a comparison between a pediatric protocol and an adult protocol. Cancer. 2006 Oct 1;107(7):1551-61.</citation>
    <PMID>16955505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Todeschini G, Tecchio C, Meneghini V, Pizzolo G, Veneri D, Zanotti R, Ricetti MM, Solero P, April F, Perona G. Estimated 6-year event-free survival of 55% in 60 consecutive adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia patients treated with an intensive phase II protocol based on high induction dose of daunorubicin. Leukemia. 1998 Feb;12(2):144-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9519775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas D, O'Brien S, Faderl S, Ravandi F, Jabbour E, Pierce S, Cortes J, Kantarjian H. Anthracycline dose intensification in adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia: lack of benefit in the context of the fractionated cyclophosphamide, vincristine, doxorubicin, and dexamethasone regimen. Cancer. 2010 Oct 1;116(19):4580-9. doi: 10.1002/cncr.25319.</citation>
    <PMID>20572037</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tomblyn MB, Arora M, Baker KS, Blazar BR, Brunstein CG, Burns LJ, DeFor TE, Dusenbery KE, Kaufman DS, Kersey JH, MacMillan ML, McGlave PB, Miller JS, Orchard PJ, Slungaard A, Tomblyn MR, Vercellotti GM, Verneris MR, Wagner JE, Weisdorf DJ. Myeloablative hematopoietic cell transplantation for acute lymphoblastic leukemia: analysis of graft sources and long-term outcome. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Aug 1;27(22):3634-41. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2008.20.2960. Epub 2009 Jul 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19581540</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bachanova V, Verneris MR, DeFor T, Brunstein CG, Weisdorf DJ. Prolonged survival in adults with acute lymphoblastic leukemia after reduced-intensity conditioning with cord blood or sibling donor transplantation. Blood. 2009 Mar 26;113(13):2902-5. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-10-184093. Epub 2009 Jan 28.</citation>
    <PMID>19179301</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldstone AH, Richards SM, Lazarus HM, Tallman MS, Buck G, Fielding AK, Burnett AK, Chopra R, Wiernik PH, Foroni L, Paietta E, Litzow MR, Marks DI, Durrant J, McMillan A, Franklin IM, Luger S, Ciobanu N, Rowe JM. In adults with standard-risk acute lymphoblastic leukemia, the greatest benefit is achieved from a matched sibling allogeneic transplantation in first complete remission, and an autologous transplantation is less effective than conventional consolidation/maintenance chemotherapy in all patients: final results of the International ALL Trial (MRC UKALL XII/ECOG E2993). Blood. 2008 Feb 15;111(4):1827-33. Epub 2007 Nov 29.</citation>
    <PMID>18048644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pituch-Noworolska A, Hajto B, Mazur B, Sońta-Jakimczyk D, Balwierz W, Janota-Krawczyk E, Kowalska H, Malinowska I, Modzelewska M, Wasik M. Expression of CD20 on acute lymphoblastic leukemia cells in children. Neoplasma. 2001;48(3):182-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11583286</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maury S, Huguet F, Leguay T, Lacombe F, Maynadié M, Girard S, de Labarthe A, Kuhlein E, Raffoux E, Thomas X, Chevallier P, Buzyn A, Delannoy A, Chalandon Y, Vernant JP, Rousselot P, Macintyre E, Ifrah N, Dombret H, Béné MC; Group for Research on Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia. Adverse prognostic significance of CD20 expression in adults with Philadelphia chromosome-negative B-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Haematologica. 2010 Feb;95(2):324-8. doi: 10.3324/haematol.2009.010306. Epub 2009 Sep 22.</citation>
    <PMID>19773266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borowitz MJ, Shuster J, Carroll AJ, Nash M, Look AT, Camitta B, Mahoney D, Lauer SJ, Pullen DJ. Prognostic significance of fluorescence intensity of surface marker expression in childhood B-precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia. A Pediatric Oncology Group Study. Blood. 1997 Jun 1;89(11):3960-6.</citation>
    <PMID>9166833</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jeha S, Behm F, Pei D, Sandlund JT, Ribeiro RC, Razzouk BI, Rubnitz JE, Hijiya N, Howard SC, Cheng C, Pui CH. Prognostic significance of CD20 expression in childhood B-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood. 2006 Nov 15;108(10):3302-4. Epub 2006 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>16896151</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas DA, O'Brien S, Jorgensen JL, Cortes J, Faderl S, Garcia-Manero G, Verstovsek S, Koller C, Pierce S, Huh Y, Wierda W, Keating MJ, Kantarjian HM. Prognostic significance of CD20 expression in adults with de novo precursor B-lineage acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood. 2009 Jun 18;113(25):6330-7. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-04-151860. Epub 2008 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18703706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al Gwaiz LA, Bassioni W. Immunophenotyping of acute lymphoblastic leukemia using immunohistochemistry in bone marrow biopsy specimens. Histol Histopathol. 2008 Oct;23(10):1223-8. doi: 10.14670/HH-23.1223.</citation>
    <PMID>18712674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Claviez A, Eckert C, Seeger K, Schrauder A, Schrappe M, Henze G, von Stackelberg A. Rituximab plus chemotherapy in children with relapsed or refractory CD20-positive B-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Haematologica. 2006 Feb;91(2):272-3.</citation>
    <PMID>16461321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas DA, Faderl S, O'Brien S, Bueso-Ramos C, Cortes J, Garcia-Manero G, Giles FJ, Verstovsek S, Wierda WG, Pierce SA, Shan J, Brandt M, Hagemeister FB, Keating MJ, Cabanillas F, Kantarjian H. Chemoimmunotherapy with hyper-CVAD plus rituximab for the treatment of adult Burkitt and Burkitt-type lymphoma or acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Cancer. 2006 Apr 1;106(7):1569-80.</citation>
    <PMID>16502413</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas DA, O'Brien S, Faderl S, Garcia-Manero G, Ferrajoli A, Wierda W, Ravandi F, Verstovsek S, Jorgensen JL, Bueso-Ramos C, Andreeff M, Pierce S, Garris R, Keating MJ, Cortes J, Kantarjian HM. Chemoimmunotherapy with a modified hyper-CVAD and rituximab regimen improves outcome in de novo Philadelphia chromosome-negative precursor B-lineage acute lymphoblastic leukemia. J Clin Oncol. 2010 Aug 20;28(24):3880-9. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2009.26.9456. Epub 2010 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>20660823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coiffier B, Lepage E, Briere J, Herbrecht R, Tilly H, Bouabdallah R, Morel P, Van Den Neste E, Salles G, Gaulard P, Reyes F, Lederlin P, Gisselbrecht C. CHOP chemotherapy plus rituximab compared with CHOP alone in elderly patients with diffuse large-B-cell lymphoma. N Engl J Med. 2002 Jan 24;346(4):235-42.</citation>
    <PMID>11807147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feugier P, Van Hoof A, Sebban C, Solal-Celigny P, Bouabdallah R, Fermé C, Christian B, Lepage E, Tilly H, Morschhauser F, Gaulard P, Salles G, Bosly A, Gisselbrecht C, Reyes F, Coiffier B. Long-term results of the R-CHOP study in the treatment of elderly patients with diffuse large B-cell lymphoma: a study by the Groupe d'Etude des Lymphomes de l'Adulte. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Jun 20;23(18):4117-26. Epub 2005 May 2.</citation>
    <PMID>15867204</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hiddemann W, Kneba M, Dreyling M, Schmitz N, Lengfelder E, Schmits R, Reiser M, Metzner B, Harder H, Hegewisch-Becker S, Fischer T, Kropff M, Reis HE, Freund M, Wörmann B, Fuchs R, Planker M, Schimke J, Eimermacher H, Trümper L, Aldaoud A, Parwaresch R, Unterhalt M. Frontline therapy with rituximab added to the combination of cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone (CHOP) significantly improves the outcome for patients with advanced-stage follicular lymphoma compared with therapy with CHOP alone: results of a prospective randomized study of the German Low-Grade Lymphoma Study Group. Blood. 2005 Dec 1;106(12):3725-32. Epub 2005 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>16123223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Griffin TC, Weitzman S, Weinstein H, Chang M, Cairo M, Hutchison R, Shiramizu B, Wiley J, Woods D, Barnich M, Gross TG; Children's Oncology Group. A study of rituximab and ifosfamide, carboplatin, and etoposide chemotherapy in children with recurrent/refractory B-cell (CD20+) non-Hodgkin lymphoma and mature B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia: a report from the Children's Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2009 Feb;52(2):177-81. doi: 10.1002/pbc.21753.</citation>
    <PMID>18816698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hallek M, Fischer K, Fingerle-Rowson G, Fink AM, Busch R, Mayer J, Hensel M, Hopfinger G, Hess G, von Grünhagen U, Bergmann M, Catalano J, Zinzani PL, Caligaris-Cappio F, Seymour JF, Berrebi A, Jäger U, Cazin B, Trneny M, Westermann A, Wendtner CM, Eichhorst BF, Staib P, Bühler A, Winkler D, Zenz T, Böttcher S, Ritgen M, Mendila M, Kneba M, Döhner H, Stilgenbauer S; International Group of Investigators; German Chronic Lymphocytic Leukaemia Study Group. Addition of rituximab to fludarabine and cyclophosphamide in patients with chronic lymphocytic leukaemia: a randomised, open-label, phase 3 trial. Lancet. 2010 Oct 2;376(9747):1164-74. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)61381-5.</citation>
    <PMID>20888994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ratanatharathorn V, Pavletic S, Uberti JP. Clinical applications of rituximab in allogeneic stem cell transplantation: anti-tumor and immunomodulatory effects. Cancer Treat Rev. 2009 Dec;35(8):653-61. doi: 10.1016/j.ctrv.2009.07.004. Epub 2009 Aug 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19682801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dworzak MN, Schumich A, Printz D, Pötschger U, Husak Z, Attarbaschi A, Basso G, Gaipa G, Ratei R, Mann G, Gadner H. CD20 up-regulation in pediatric B-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia during induction treatment: setting the stage for anti-CD20 directed immunotherapy. Blood. 2008 Nov 15;112(10):3982-8. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-06-164129. Epub 2008 Sep 9.</citation>
    <PMID>18780832</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stanciu-Herrera C, Morgan C, Herrera L. Anti-CD19 and anti-CD22 monoclonal antibodies increase the effectiveness of chemotherapy in Pre-B acute lymphoblastic leukemia cell lines. Leuk Res. 2008 Apr;32(4):625-32. Epub 2007 Aug 15.</citation>
    <PMID>17706771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaipa G, Basso G, Maglia O, Leoni V, Faini A, Cazzaniga G, Bugarin C, Veltroni M, Michelotto B, Ratei R, Coliva T, Valsecchi MG, Biondi A, Dworzak MN; I-BFM-ALL-FCM-MRD Study Group. Drug-induced immunophenotypic modulation in childhood ALL: implications for minimal residual disease detection. Leukemia. 2005 Jan;19(1):49-56.</citation>
    <PMID>15538405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gökbuget N, Hoelzer D. Treatment with monoclonal antibodies in acute lymphoblastic leukemia: current knowledge and future prospects. Ann Hematol. 2004 Apr;83(4):201-5. Epub 2003 Nov 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14648023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bachanova V, Sandhu K, Yohe S, Cao Q, Burke MJ, Verneris MR, Weisdorf D. Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation overcomes the adverse prognostic impact of CD20 expression in acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Blood. 2011 May 12;117(19):5261-3. doi: 10.1182/blood-2011-01-329573. Epub 2011 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21403127</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cutler C, Miklos D, Kim HT, Treister N, Woo SB, Bienfang D, Klickstein LB, Levin J, Miller K, Reynolds C, Macdonell R, Pasek M, Lee SJ, Ho V, Soiffer R, Antin JH, Ritz J, Alyea E. Rituximab for steroid-refractory chronic graft-versus-host disease. Blood. 2006 Jul 15;108(2):756-62. Epub 2006 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>16551963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mohty M, Marchetti N, El-Cheikh J, Faucher C, Fürst S, Blaise D. Rituximab as salvage therapy for refractory chronic GVHD. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2008 May;41(10):909-11. doi: 10.1038/bmt.2008.12. Epub 2008 Feb 18.</citation>
    <PMID>18278073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Okamoto M, Okano A, Akamatsu S, Ashihara E, Inaba T, Takenaka H, Katoh N, Kishimoto S, Shimazaki C. Rituximab is effective for steroid-refractory sclerodermatous chronic graft-versus-host disease. Leukemia. 2006 Jan;20(1):172-3.</citation>
    <PMID>16239908</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zaja F, Bacigalupo A, Patriarca F, Stanzani M, Van Lint MT, Filì C, Scimè R, Milone G, Falda M, Vener C, Laszlo D, Alessandrino PE, Narni F, Sica S, Olivieri A, Sperotto A, Bosi A, Bonifazi F, Fanin R; GITMO (Gruppo Italiano Trapianto Midollo Osseo). Treatment of refractory chronic GVHD with rituximab: a GITMO study. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2007 Aug;40(3):273-7. Epub 2007 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>17549053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kebriaei P, Saliba RM, Ma C, Ippoliti C, Couriel DR, de Lima M, Giralt S, Qazilbash MH, Gajewski JL, Ha CS, Champlin RE, Khouri IF. Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation after rituximab-containing myeloablative preparative regimen for acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2006 Aug;38(3):203-9. Epub 2006 Jun 26.</citation>
    <PMID>16799614</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 30, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 3, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 7, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Asan Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Je-Hwan Lee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>acute lymphoblastic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>rituximab</keyword>
  <keyword>VPDL</keyword>
  <keyword>CD20</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

