<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01423006</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-16584</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01423006</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study on Focal Prostate Radio-Frequency Ablation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study on Focal Prostate Radio-Frequency Ablation for the Treatment of Very-Low Risk Prostate Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Trod Medical, US,LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective pilot study. The purpose of this research study is to evaluate the
      safety and efficacy of focal Radio-Frequency Ablation (RFA) in men with low-risk, clinically
      localized prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      RFA is a minimally invasive procedure. It is an image-guided technique that heats and
      destroys cancer cells. In RFA, imaging techniques such as ultrasound or magnetic resonance
      imaging (MRI) are used to help guide a needle electrode into a cancerous tumor.
      High-frequency electrical currents are then passed through the electrode, destroying the
      cancer cells. Use of an RFA device was approved by the Food and Drug Association (FDA) in
      1997 for the purposes of treating soft tissue tumors. The device we (Moffitt Cancer Center)
      will be using in this study has clearance for clinical use from the FDA. The effectiveness of
      the device is measured using biopsy cores at the site of the cancer after the RFA procedure.
      To evaluate the benefits of this procedure, we will also evaluate the change in
      quality-of-life indicators from baseline to 6 months following RFA. RFA is being developed as
      a minimally invasive potential treatment for prostate cancer.

      This research study is a pilot clinical trial. Pilot clinical trials are smaller versions of
      larger studies that are conducted to prepare for the larger study. This pilot study pre-tests
      a research device before a large-scale multicenter study is launched.

      The specific purpose of this pilot trial is to find out if RFA can effectively treat prostate
      cancer with fewer side effects including effects on urination, bowel function, and sexual
      function. RFA for early stage prostate cancer is designed to affect only the part of the
      prostate where cancer has been detected. The reasoning for this approach is the smaller the
      area given RFA, the less damage to surrounding tissues.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Negative Prostate Biopsy Rate at Six Months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary efficacy endpoint is negative biopsy rate at 6 months after focal bipolar RFA. Evaluable patients for this study will be those who complete up through the six month follow-up/evaluation procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Completion of Quality of Life (QOL) Assessment Questionnaires at Six Months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will complete the Expanded Prostate Cancer Index Composite (EPIC), American Urologic (AUA), Rectal Assessment Scale (RAS), and Sexual Health Inventory for Men (SHIM) questionnaires at baseline, 3 month and 6 month visits. QOL will be primarily based on the EPIC, developed to measure health related QOL among men with prostate cancer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Focal Prostate Radio-Frequency Ablation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment is performed under a spinal or general anesthetic and will include the one to three regions of the prostate containing cancer based on the mapping biopsy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radio-Frequency Ablation (RFA) ENCAGE™</intervention_name>
    <description>RFA is a minimally invasive procedure. It is an image-guided technique that heats and destroys cancer cells. In RFA, imaging techniques such as ultrasound or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) are used to help guide a needle electrode into a cancerous tumor. High-frequency electrical currents are then passed through the electrode, destroying the cancer cells.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Focal Prostate Radio-Frequency Ablation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ENCAGE™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of adenocarcinoma of the prostate, confirmed by H.L. Moffitt Cancer Center
             review

          -  No prior treatment for prostate cancer including hormonal therapy

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Prostate Cancer Clinical Stage T1c

          -  prostate-specific antigen (PSA) &lt;10 ng/ml (this will be the PSA level prompting the
             initial prostate biopsy)

          -  Prostate size &lt;60 cc on transrectal ultrasound

          -  If on anti-coagulation medications, must be able to suspend this therapy for a couple
             of weeks

          -  Adequate organ function Pre-enrollment biopsy parameters (as per H.L. Moffitt Cancer
             Center review)

          -  Minimum of 10 biopsy cores

          -  No biopsy Gleason grade 4 or 5

          -  Unilateral cancer (only right-sided or left-sided, not bilateral)

          -  No more than 50% cancer in any one biopsy core

          -  No more than 25% of cores containing cancer

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medically unfit for anesthesia

          -  Histology other than adenocarcinoma

          -  Biopsy does not meet inclusion criteria

          -  Men who have received any hormonal manipulation (antiandrogens; luteinizing
             hormone-releasing hormone (LHRH) agonist; 5-alpha-reductase inhibitors) within the
             previous 6 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julio Pow-Sang, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 24, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 25, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 13, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 13, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 14, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pilot</keyword>
  <keyword>Ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Low Risk</keyword>
  <keyword>Radio Frequency</keyword>
  <keyword>RFA</keyword>
  <keyword>minimally invasive</keyword>
  <keyword>prostate gland</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

