<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01420198</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009/36</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01420198</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficiency and Cost-effectiveness of a Culturally Adopted Lifestyle Intervention Program - the MEDIM Study.</brief_title>
  <acronym>MEDIM</acronym>
  <official_title>A Middle Eastern Immigrant Population At-risk for Diabetes; Contributing Risk Factors and the Efficiency and Cost-effectiveness of a Culturally Adopted Lifestyle Intervention Program - the MEDIM Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Region Skane</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lund University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Region Skane</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An increasing proportion of Sweden's population comprises non-European immigrants, who
      constitute a high risk-population for T2D. Numbering almost 9,000 individuals, Iraqi citizens
      represent the largest immigrant group in Malmoe and are identified as a risk group for Type 2
      Diabetes (T2D) in whom genetic and lifestyle factors probably play significant roles in the
      development of T2D.

      Several studies have shown that adoption of an active lifestyle by at-risk individuals
      dramatically reduces the risk of T2D. However, there are currently no established methods for
      providing support to high-risk individuals from different cultural and social backgrounds to
      help them adopt beneficial lasting lifestyle changes. Instead of just waiting for Iraqi
      high-risk individuals to develop T2D, this project will implement and assess lifestyle
      intervention programs aimed at reducing the risk of developing T2D and tailored to
      individuals with a different social and cultural background.

      The study thus seeks to optimize preventive action in health care and aims to facilitate the
      adoption of permanent changes in lifestyle in high-risk patients, taking account of cultural
      and social barriers.

      Since T2D is associated with a sedentary lifestyle and develops earlier in men than women and
      an average 10 years earlier in immigrants from the Middle East than in native Swedes, it is
      crucial to study pathogenic mechanisms triggering T2D development in relation to sex,
      lifestyle and ethnic background. The results will provide the basis for deciding how health
      care providers can actively work to prevent T2D and other lifestyle-associated diseases in
      this high-risk population that has not been studied before.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this randomized controlled trial, 308 participants (born in Iraq, living in Malmö, Sweden
      and at high risk of type 2 diabetes) will be allocated to either a culturally adapted
      intervention or a control group. The intervention will consist of 10 group counseling
      sessions focusing on diet, physical activity and behavioral change over 6 months, and the
      offer of exercise sessions. Cultural adaptation includes gender-specific exercise sessions,
      and counseling by a health coach community member. The control group will receive the
      information about healthy lifestyle habits provided by the primary health care center. The
      primary outcome is change in fasting glucose level. Secondary outcomes are changes in body
      mass index, insulin sensitivity,physical activity, food habits and health-related quality of
      life. Measurements will be taken at baseline, after 3 and 6 months. Data will be analyzed by
      the intention-to-treat approach. The cost-effectiveness during the trial period and over the
      longer term will be assessed by simulation modeling from patient, health care and societal
      perspectives.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fasting glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>fasting glucose is measured in the fasting state.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QALY</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The effectiveness will be measured as change in health related quality in life measures as Quality adjusted life years (QALY)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Impaired Glucose Tolerance</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lifestyle intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lifestyle intervention: 500 participants from Iraq with obesity and/or prediabetes (impaired fasting glucose) and we expect to recruit 308 participants. Half of them will be randomized to lifestyle intervention i.e. group counseling and physical activity during a period of 1 year. An equal amount of controls will have treatment as usual. Every third month blood tests and a physical exam will be conducted in the intervention group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Controls have treatment as usual. Every third month blood tests and a physical exam will be conducted in the control group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lifestyle intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Increased physical activity and improved food habits</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lifestyle intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  (1) Non-diabetic individuals 30 to 75 years of age, (2) individuals in the baseline
             survey diagnosed with IGT or IFG + IGT or with a moderate or large diabetes risk (i.e.
             over 10% risk of diabetes in 10 years measured with FINDRISC scores).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnancy, severe mental illness, diabetes, and/or cognitive impairment, current CVD
             or history of CVD events. CVD includes stroke, angina or myocardial infarction (MI),
             percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty (PTCA), congestive heart failure (CHF),
             coronary artery bypass graft surgery (CABG), transient ischemic attack (TIA) and
             peripheral vascular disease (PVD) or other physical disorders that prevent physical
             exercise.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Louise Bennet, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Region Skane</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Primary Health Care Research, Region Skåne and Lund University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Malmö</city>
        <state>Skåne</state>
        <zip>20502</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennet L, Odeberg H. Resistance to activated protein C, highly prevalent amongst users of oral contraceptives with venous thromboembolism. J Intern Med. 1998 Jul;244(1):27-32.</citation>
    <PMID>9698021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennet L, Berglund J. Reinfection with Lyme borreliosis: a retrospective follow-up study in southern Sweden. Scand J Infect Dis. 2002;34(3):183-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12030390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennet L, Danell S, Berglund J. Clinical outcome of erythema migrans after treatment with phenoxymethyl penicillin. Scand J Infect Dis. 2003;35(2):129-31.</citation>
    <PMID>12693565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennet L, Halling A, Berglund J. Increased incidence of Lyme borreliosis in southern Sweden following mild winters and during warm, humid summers. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2006 Jul;25(7):426-32.</citation>
    <PMID>16810531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennet L, Fraenkel CJ, Garpmo U, Halling A, Ingman M, Ornstein K, Stjernberg L, Berglund J. Clinical appearance of erythema migrans caused by Borrelia afzelii and Borrelia garinii--effect of the patient's sex. Wien Klin Wochenschr. 2006 Sep;118(17-18):531-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17009065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jarefors S, Bennet L, You E, Forsberg P, Ekerfelt C, Berglund J, Ernerudh J. Lyme borreliosis reinfection: might it be explained by a gender difference in immune response? Immunology. 2006 Jun;118(2):224-32.</citation>
    <PMID>16771857</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennet L, Stiernstedt S, Berglund J, Hagberg L, Karlsson M, Olsson I, Ornstein K. [Penicillin V is the first choice in the treatment of erythema migrans]. Lakartidningen. 2006 May 3-9;103(18):1454; author reply 1455. Swedish.</citation>
    <PMID>16729462</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennet L, Stjernberg L, Berglund J. Effect of gender on clinical and epidemiologic features of Lyme borreliosis. Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis. 2007 Spring;7(1):34-41.</citation>
    <PMID>17417955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ingelsson E, Bennet L, Ridderstråle M, Söderström M, Råstam L, Lindblad U. The PPARGC1A Gly482Ser polymorphism is associated with left ventricular diastolic dysfunction in men. BMC Cardiovasc Disord. 2008 Dec 11;8:37. doi: 10.1186/1471-2261-8-37.</citation>
    <PMID>19077249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leão TS, Sundquist J, Frank G, Johansson LM, Johansson SE, Sundquist K. Incidence of schizophrenia or other psychoses in first- and second-generation immigrants: a national cohort study. J Nerv Ment Dis. 2006 Jan;194(1):27-33.</citation>
    <PMID>16462552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang X, Sundquist J, Zöller B, Memon AA, Palmér K, Sundquist K, Bennet L. Determination of 14 circulating microRNAs in Swedes and Iraqis with and without diabetes mellitus type 2. PLoS One. 2014 Jan 30;9(1):e86792. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0086792. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24497980</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arvidsson D, Lindblad U, Sundquist J, Sundquist K, Groop L, Bennet L. Vigorous physical activity may be important for the insulin sensitivity in immigrants from the Middle East and native Swedes. J Phys Act Health. 2015 Feb;12(2):273-81. doi: 10.1123/jpah.2013-0222. Epub 2014 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24809593</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bennet L, Groop L, Lindblad U, Agardh CD, Franks PW. Ethnicity is an independent risk indicator when estimating diabetes risk with FINDRISC scores: a cross sectional study comparing immigrants from the Middle East and native Swedes. Prim Care Diabetes. 2014 Oct;8(3):231-8. doi: 10.1016/j.pcd.2014.01.002. Epub 2014 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24472421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 18, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 9, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 9, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 10, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes type 2</keyword>
  <keyword>Lifestyle intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>QALY</keyword>
  <keyword>Ethnic group</keyword>
  <keyword>Impaired glucose tolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>Impaired fasting glucose</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glucose Intolerance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

