<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01429142</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AIMS_171002208</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01429142</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AIMS Study: Improving HIV Treatment Adherence</brief_title>
  <acronym>AIMS</acronym>
  <official_title>AIMS Study: Cost-effectiveness of a Nurse-based Intervention to Support HIV-treatment Adherence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wageningen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Academisch Medisch Centrum - Universiteit van Amsterdam (AMC-UvA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ZonMw: The Netherlands Organisation for Health Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Maastricht University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wageningen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objectives of the main study are to evaluate the effectiveness and the cost-effectiveness
      of a counseling intervention to support medication intake among patients treated for HIV. The
      aim is that through the availability of medication intake reports collected through
      electronic monitoring, more adherence problems can be identified and medical decision-making
      improves.

      A substudy focuses on the broader range of nursing care in HIV-treatment, examining the
      content of care delivered to support physical, mental, sexual and social well-being; whether
      the delivery of the AIMS intervention affects the quality of care on domains other than
      adherence; and whether the content of care on these various domains can be linked to patient
      well-being and satisfaction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      **MAIN STUDY**

      BACKGROUND: Adherence to HIV-medication is an important predictor of treatment success, yet
      between 25-40% of the patients does not always take the medication as prescribed. A
      nurse-delivered counseling intervention (AIMS: Adherence Improving self-Management Strategy)
      to optimize patient adherence has shown promising results in a pilot study and a randomized
      controlled trial among Caucasian, treatment-experienced patients. AIMS is a patient-centered
      counseling intervention to support self-regulation of medication intake, using feedback
      reports of electronically monitored adherence. AIMS has been evaluated positively by patients
      and nurses, and has been developed to be implemented in usual patient care against minimal
      time and monetary investments.

      OBJECTIVE: To examine the cost-effectiveness of the AIMS intervention compared to
      &quot;care-as-usual&quot; in Dutch HIV-clinics among a representative sample of patients (all
      ethnicities, starting or already on treatment).

      SETTING AND PARTICIPANTS: The study will be conducted in seven HIV-clinics in the Netherlands
      and select 230 patients (details regarding sample size calculation: see below) eligible for
      intervention based on the following criteria: 1- All treatment experienced patients who
      started combination AntiRetroviral Therapy (cART) ≥1996, are &gt;9 months on treatment, are
      continuing treatment, and had at least one detectable viral load (blips included) during the
      last 3 years (count starts after 9 months cART). 2- All treatment-naïve patients initiating
      treatment.

      After initial inclusion, treatment experienced patients with suboptimal adherence measured
      during a 2-month electronic monitoring baseline period will be eligible for randomization to
      the intervention or the control group. Treatment-initiating patients will be randomized
      directly after consenting.

      DESIGN: A prospective multicenter trial with randomization of patients within nurses.
      Eligible treatment experienced patients with suboptimal adherence after 2 months baseline
      adherence monitoring will be randomized to receive either usual care plus the
      AIMS-intervention, or care as usual. Next, randomized experienced patients will visit the
      clinic every 4-5 months, with a minimum of 3 visits during at least a 15-month period
      (including the baseline period a total of 17 study months). Treatment-naïve patients will be
      randomized directly after consenting. As part of the AIMS-intervention, intervention
      participants are encouraged to start with a 2-week readiness trajectory before initiating
      cART. After initiating cART, control and intervention participants return for a visit after
      2-4 weeks, 3-4 months, 6-7 months, 9-10 months, and 12-15 months.

      PRIMARY MEASURES: Viral load, health care usage, quality of life, and adherence data will be
      obtained. MEMS-data will only be collected among half of the control group (randomly assigned
      to MEMS y/n).

      OUTCOMES: 1- Primary cost-effectiveness outcome: a) costs per point increase in the
      proportion of patients with an undetectable viral load, b) costs per Quality Adjusted Life
      Year (QALY) gained. Secondary: Costs per one point increase in adherence as measured with the
      MEMS-caps.

      2- Primary effectiveness outcome: The number of detectable viral loads at study months 6-7,
      10-11, and 14-15 for experienced patients, and months 6-7, 9-10, and 12-15 for patients
      starting treatment. Secondary: Adherence according to MEMS-caps.

      **PROJECT OBJECTIVES SUB STUDY** BACKGROUND: HIV-nurses' tasks go beyond discussing and
      supporting adherence, and include promoting patients' sexual, mental, physical and social
      well-being. Hence, it will be important to establish whether delivering the AIMS-intervention
      impacts the quality/scope of usual clinic care on these other important domains. In addition,
      measuring the content of usual care during the trial provides the opportunity to explore
      whether this is related to patients' well-being (sexual, mental, physical, social) and
      satisfaction with care.

      OBJECTIVES: 1- To monitor the content of usual care on the different HIV-nursing domains and
      examine whether usual care content predicts patients' well-being and satisfaction with
      HIV-care at follow-up. 2- Explore whether delivering the AIMS-intervention has
      (dis)advantageous effects on the content and impact of usual care on domains other than
      adherence (sexual, mental, physical, social).

      PARTICIPANTS: HIV-nurses and patients in the study clinics.

      DESIGN AND MEASURES: HIV-nurses' usual care with regard to adherence, as well as mental,
      sexual, social and physical health will be assessed through questionnaires at randomization
      and at the end of the study. In addition, HIV-nurses will complete a brief online checklist
      after each study visit indicating the main topics discussed during that meeting. At
      randomization and after the study, patients will complete a brief questionnaire about their
      mental, social, physical and sexual health, and satisfaction with their care on these
      domains.

      PRIMARY OUTCOMES: 1- The relation between the content of care with patient satisfaction and
      well-being. 2- Potential effects of AIMS on the content of care and patient well-being and
      treatment satisfaction.

      SAMPLE SIZE CALCULATION:

      During the initial grant application, a sample size was computed based on the assumption that
      only non-adherent, treatment experienced patients would be approached. However, following the
      input from participating clinics, the final inclusion and exclusion criteria were formulated
      as explained below. An updated sample size computation was done after inclusion had been
      initiated, which was submitted to (date: 27th February, 2013) and accepted by (date: 15th
      April, 2013) the funder (ZonMw, the Netherlands Organisation for Health Research and
      Development) using actual trial data in order to enhance accuracy of the estimates (the
      expected treatment effect is the same in both computations, the other estimates were adjusted
      to match then new criteria and available data).

      Initial sample size calculation:

      The sample size for the primary outcome measure was computed on the basis of a dichotomous
      dependent variable (detectable versus undetectable viral load), The data was planned to be
      analyzed using a multi-level model (patients nested within nurses) that would account for
      differential intervention effects between nurses. A total sample of 432 patients (18 nurses)
      was required to detect significant intervention effects at post-intervention with an alpha =
      .05 (two-sided) and 80% power, based on the following assumptions: depending on the nurse,
      (a) 60% to 80% of the patients have an undetectable viral load during usual care (i.e. ≥ 6
      months after start of cART), (b) this increases in the intervention condition compared to the
      control condition by 5 to 20 percentage points, and (c) a nurse recruits on average 25
      patients for the trial. (d) We expected a maximum dropout of 20%. We therefore intended to
      include 450 patients.

      Updated sample size calculation:

      The updated sample size computation is the following: A sample of 230 patients (22 nurses) is
      required to obtain 80% power to detect a significant intervention effect on viral load for at
      least one of three time points (for treatment-experienced patients: T1, T2, and T3; for
      treatment-initiating patients: T3, T4, and T5) with alpha=.05 (two-sided) and using a
      Bonferroni correction. Viral load at baseline is used as a covariate. A multilevel model is
      used with random intercepts and random treatment effects at the nurse level. The sample size
      calculation is based on the following assumptions: depending on the nurse, (a) 60% to 80% of
      treatment-initiating patients have an undetectable viral load during usual care (i.e. ≥ 6
      months after start of ART), (b) 15% to 20% of treatment experienced-patients and all
      treatment-initiating patients have a detectable viral load at baseline, (c) this increases in
      the intervention condition compared to the control condition by 5 to 20 percentage points,
      (d) a nurse recruits on average 11 patients for the trial, and (e) an expected maximum
      dropout of 10%.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness: Costs per point increase in viral load</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 0-14</time_frame>
    <description>The costs and savings over the whole intervention period (post randomization until end of study) will be weighed against any gains observed in viral load (continuous or dichotomous: see primary effectiveness outcomes).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness: Viral load</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 4-14</time_frame>
    <description>The combined viral load at 3 pre-determined time points after the initial intervention phase will serve as the primary outcome measure. Depending on the distribution, data will be kept continuous (log transformed) or recoded to detectable versus undetectable. Planned measurements naive patients at 6-7 months, 9-10 months, and 12-14 months post-randomization. For treatment experienced patients: 4-5 months, 8-10 months, and 12-15 months after randomization.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness: Costs per point increase in adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 0-14</time_frame>
    <description>The costs and benefits of intervention versus control care during the study will be weighed against any improvements in adherence following the initial intervention stage. For that purpose, adherence data during follow-up (i.e. the last 4 months of the study) will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness: Costs per quality adjusted life year gained</measure>
    <time_frame>month 0-14</time_frame>
    <description>The costs and benefits of the intervention versus control care will be weighed against any differences observed in quality of life measured at 3 time points following the initial intervention period (time points are the same as for the primary effectiveness outcome)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness: Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 0-4, Month 5-8, Month 9-12</time_frame>
    <description>Repeated measures analyses on adherence. Time windows will show some variation due to treatment stage of patient and clinic variation, but stratification and cluster randomization should prevent unequal distribution over groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">226</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AIMS intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>see http://bmchealthservres.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1472-6963-13-274</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>see http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/08870446.2014.1001392</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment as usual</intervention_name>
    <description>In this multi-center trial, the content of usual adherence care is not known prior to the study, but it is part of our data collection to examine the content and variability between clinics and professionals afterwards.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AIMS intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The AIMS-intervention is counseling intervention, using MEMS-data printed in simple plots. The following intervention steps will be followed:
-Discussion of practical, tailored information about adherence -Identification of desired adherence level and motivations -Print of patients' MEMS-report and comparison with desired level -ID causes of non-adherence and how to deal with problems -Designing a tailored action plan. -Follow-up: evaluation of accomplishments, remaining problems and solutions, until desired level of adherence has been accomplished. -Formulation of goals for behavioral maintenance.
Among patients starting treatment, the same elements will be delivered but MEMS-feedback can only be incorporated in the second session (after medication has been used). Moreover, a readiness element is added at treatment initiation, where patients discuss the necessity and concerns of initiating medication and are offered the possibility to practice intake for 2 weeks with placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AIMS intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria treatment-naive patients initiating cART:

        - All patients are eligible

        Inclusion criteria treatment experienced patients:

          -  Started cART after 1996, and

          -  Have been on cART for at least 9 months, and

          -  Had at least one detectable viral load (including blips) during the last 3 years
             (counting of these 3 years starts after the first 9 months on cART), and

          -  Had suboptimal adherence (&lt;95% BID, &lt;100% QD) during 2 months baseline measurement.

        Exclusion criteria for treatment-naive and experienced patients:

          -  Age &lt;18 years

          -  Psychiatric disorders or other comorbidities precluding compliance with study
             procedures

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Plans to interrupt treatment in the next 14 months

          -  Life expectancy less than one year as determined by physician

          -  Not able to communicate in English or Dutch

          -  HIV resistant to three or more of the currently available antiretroviral drug classes

          -  About to initiate intensive hepatitis C treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jan M Prins, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Academic Medical Center - University of Amsterdam (AMC-UVA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marijn de Bruin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Aberdeen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Erasmus Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <state>South Holland</state>
        <zip>3000 CA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sint Lucas Andreas Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1006 AE</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Slotervaartziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1066 EC</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Academic Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1105AZ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leiden Universitair MEdisch Centrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leidern</city>
        <zip>2333 ZA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Haga Ziekenhuis, location Leyweg</name>
      <address>
        <city>The Hague</city>
        <zip>2545 CH</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Isala Klinieken</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zwolle</city>
        <zip>8011 JW</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 25, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 2, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 12, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 12, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Aberdeen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marijn de Bruin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Upon request</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

