<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00932308</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PHO-0588</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00932308</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Colorectal Inflammatory Response to a Western-Style Diet</brief_title>
  <official_title>Colorectal Inflammatory Response to a Western-Style Diet</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rockefeller University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rockefeller University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators are involved in a research program to understand how different diets may
      affect the risk of colorectal polyps and cancer. To that end, the investigators are
      conducting a study of a western style diet versus a &quot;prudent style&quot; diet in which volunteer
      subjects are provided a different diet for 2 separate 4 week periods at the Rockefeller
      University Hospital. During one of these 4 week inpatient periods they receive a Western
      style diet and during the other 4 week inpatient period they receive a &quot;Prudent style&quot; diet.
      The investigators will determine changes within the colon as a result of the two different
      diets. A more detailed description of the study is provided below.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study subjects participate for about 3 months. During this time, there is one outpatient
      visit, a 4 week inpatient period, a 4 week outpatient period known as a wash out period and
      finally another 4 week inpatient period. During the inpatient periods The Rockefeller
      University Hospital becomes your home the subject must sleep here every night and consume all
      the food provided. During the screening visit blood and urine samples will be taken and an
      EKC (electrocardiogram) and a complete physical exam will be done. After enrollment into the
      study, the first 4 week inpatient period begins. You may continue to go to work or do other
      activities as long as you eat the diet provided and sleep at the Rockefeller University
      Hospital. You must eat everything that we give you and you may not substitute or supplement
      the diet in any way. During each 4 week stay at The Rockefeller University Hospital, there
      will be three flexible sigmoidoscopies done and biopsies taken of the mucosal lining of the
      colorectum. This procedure is painless and takes about 5 minutes. In addition, blood and
      stool samples will be taken every few days for follow-up and research, two 24 hour urine
      samples will be done on separate days during the hospitalization. Vital signs are measured
      every day and your weight will be measured three times per week. During the four week wash
      out period, the subject will return to their home, go about their normal activities and
      consume their normal diet. The subject will return to The Rockefeller University Hospital for
      the second 4 week inpatient period. The procedures and laboratory tests are the same during
      the second inpatient period. The study concludes with the subjects discharge from the RUH.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The degree of inflammation in the rectosigmoid epithelium as judged by the density and composition of the cellular infiltration.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 28</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Expression Profiles of pro- and anti-inflammatory genes in rectosigmoid biopsies as determined by microarray assay and RT-PCR.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Selected pro- and anti-inflammatory proteins in rectal biopsies</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The levels of selected circulating and potential urinary inflammatory markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 27</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The concentration of fecal calprotectin</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -1, 7,14,21 and 27</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in bulk fecal and epithelial associated microbiota that may determine changes in colorectal epithelial cell biologic pathways.</measure>
    <time_frame>Days -1, 7,14,21 and 27</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Western-style, high-fat, low-calcium diet (WD)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prudent, low-fat, calcium sufficient diet (PD)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Western-style diet (WD)</intervention_name>
    <description>Will comprise of approximately 40% fat, 40% carbohydrates, 20% protein, and 350mg calcium, prepared by the Bionutrition Department using the USDA Nutrient Database.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prudent Diet (PD)</intervention_name>
    <description>Will contain approximately 20% fat, 60% carbohydrate, 20% protein, and 1100mg calcium; the diets will consist of a 2-day rotating metabolic menu.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male and post-menopausal healthy female subjects, aged 50-72 years, who have
             had a colorectal adenoma removed, or have a first or second degree relative with
             colorectal neoplasia and thus are themselves at risk for colorectal cancer.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Personal history of cancer other than non-melanoma skin cancer within the past 10
             years

          -  History of hereditary non-polyposis colon cancer

          -  Intestinal malabsorption, inflammatory bowel disease

          -  Prior gastrointestinal surgery other than appendectomy or surgery of the esophagus

          -  Any excess bleeding or coagulation disorders

          -  Subjects taking anti-coagulants, sterol-binding resins, NSAIDs other than aspirin, &lt;
             600mg per day, other study medications, or other multiple medications that might, in
             the view of the study physicians, alter colonic function of inflammation

          -  Sustained blood pressure &gt; 150/95 mm Hg for three consecutive readings

          -  Total cholesterol greater than 240mg/dL, triglycerides &gt;600mg, LDL-C &gt; 175

          -  Subjects with a history of coronary artery disease, with EKG changes consistent with a
             past myocardial infarction

          -  HIV positive subjects

          -  Subjects taking antibiotics, anti-diabetes, hormone replacement therapy, oral,
             transplanted or injected contraceptives (thyroid hormone therapy is permitted as long
             as the subjects is euthyroid)

          -  Subjects consuming a vegetarian diet or a very &quot;prudent diet&quot;

        Withdrawal Criteria:

          -  If a subject is suspected of having taken illicit drugs, the subject will be asked to
             take a urine test. If positive, the subject will be withdrawn from the study

          -  The subject takes any medication prescribed without prior approval of the investigator

          -  Persistent noncompliance with the diets prescribed by the RUH nutritionists
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>72 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Holt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rockefeller University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rockefeller University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 11, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 3, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 15, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 15, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 17, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium, Dietary</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

