<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00932204</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4-2006-0318</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00932204</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Sequentially Applied Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation in Obsessive- Compulsive Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled Study of Sequentially Applied Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation in Obsessive- Compulsive Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Severance Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Severance Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the present study was to investigate possible therapeutic effects and safety
      of sequentially combined low-frequency repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) to
      the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) and supplementary motor area (SMA) in
      patients with treatment-resistant obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) is a relatively common psychiatric disorder characterized
      by repetitive, intrusive thoughts and time-consuming behavioral or mental acts. Many OCD
      patients who do not respond to conventional treatments experience severe distress and
      disruptions in their daily activities. Novel approaches including psychopharmacological
      therapy and surgical techniques for treatment-resistant OCD have been proposed. With recent
      advances in non-invasive technique for stimulating the cerebral cortex, repetitive
      transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) has been proposed as a potential therapeutic
      approach for various psychiatric illnesses including OCD.

      Because of contradictory findings and a lack of controlled trials in OCD, rTMS cannot be yet
      recommended as routine therapy for OCD. However, it may have a potential clinical effect as a
      putative add-on treatment for OCD and an alternative therapy for treatment-resistant OCD.

      For useful clinical applications, it is very important to develop methods to enhance the
      efficacy of rTMS. There are a number of putative ways to do this, and one of them is
      sequentially combining two forms of stimulation which are considered to have potential
      therapeutic effects. More recently, the sequential application of two stimulation regimens
      (high-frequency left-side rTMS and low-frequency right-side rTMS to the prefrontal cortex)
      has been found to have a substantial therapeutic effect in patients with treatment-resistant
      major depression. Therefore, the investigation for a sequentially combining effect of both
      the right prefrontal and the SMA stimulation would be worthwhile in OCD patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome measure for the study was score on the Y-BOCS. The responder on Y-BOCS is defined as a Y-BOCS decrease at least 25% from the baseline at post-treatment (at 4 weeks)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 1, week 2, and week 4</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary outcome measures were the scores of MADRS and HARS, to examine the effects on cognitive functions of rTMS, a computerized Stroop task was conducted and side effect checklist.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 1, week 2, and week 4</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the active group, rTMS over the right prefrontal cortex and the SMA was sequentially performed. The rTMS of the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex was conducted at a point 5 cm anterior to the point at which the MT was determined, and it was administered at an intensity of 110% of the RMT, a frequency of 1 Hz, for 10 minutes, and with an inter-train interval of 2 minutes (1200 stimuli/d).
The vertex (Cz) was measured for each patient, and the SMA was defined at 15% of the distance between the inion and nasion anterior to Cz on the sagittal midline, according to the international 10-20 EEG system. The rTMS over the SMA was administered at an intensity of 100% of the RMT, a frequency of 1 Hz, for 10 minutes and with an inter-train interval of 2 minutes (1200 stimuli/d).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the sham group, the sham stimulation was applied with the coil angled at 45° from the scalp using the same parameters as the active stimulation group over the same area.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (Magstim rapid magnetic stimulator)</intervention_name>
    <description>For the active group, rTMS over the right prefrontal cortex and the SMA was sequentially performed. The rTMS of the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex was conducted at a point 5 cm anterior to the point at which the MT was determined, and it was administered at an intensity of 110% of the RMT, a frequency of 1 Hz, for 10 minutes, and with an inter-train interval of 2 minutes (1200 stimuli/d).
The vertex (Cz) was measured for each patient, and the SMA was defined at 15% of the distance between the inion and nasion anterior to Cz on the sagittal midline, according to the international 10-20 EEG system. The rTMS over the SMA was administered at an intensity of 100% of the RMT, a frequency of 1 Hz, for 10 minutes and with an inter-train interval of 2 minutes (1200 stimuli/d).
For the sham group, the sham stimulation was applied with the coil angled at 45° from the scalp using the same parameters as the active stimulation group over the same area.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>A Magstim rapid magnetic stimulator with a 70-mm figure-of-eight coil (Magstim Company Ltd, Whitland, UK) was used for treatment.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  OCD patients who had failed adequate trials (a lack of at least a 25% reduction in the
             Yale-Brown Obsessive-Compulsive Scale (Y-BOCS) 15 after at least eight weeks of
             treatment) of at least two serotonin re-uptake inhibitors (SRI) and behavioral
             therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects were excluded if:

               -  they presented with a movement disorder other than a tic

               -  any psychotic symptoms

               -  other anxiety disorders

               -  mental retardation

               -  alcohol or other substance abuse within the last six months

               -  a history of psychosurgery, encephalitis or significant head trauma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Se Joo Kim, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yonsei Univ. College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yonsei Univ. Health System Severance Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>120-752</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mantovani A, Lisanby SH, Pieraccini F, Ulivelli M, Castrogiovanni P, Rossi S. Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) in the treatment of obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) and Tourette's syndrome (TS). Int J Neuropsychopharmacol. 2006 Feb;9(1):95-100. Epub 2005 Jun 28.</citation>
    <PMID>15982444</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sachdev PS, McBride R, Loo CK, Mitchell PB, Malhi GS, Croker VM. Right versus left prefrontal transcranial magnetic stimulation for obsessive-compulsive disorder: a preliminary investigation. J Clin Psychiatry. 2001 Dec;62(12):981-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11780880</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 1, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 2, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 3, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 2, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 2, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 3, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Se Joo Kim</name_title>
    <organization>Department of Psychiatry, Yonsei Univ. College of Medicine</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>obsessive-compulsive disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex</keyword>
  <keyword>supplementary motor area (SMA)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Compulsive Personality Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

