<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00931892</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2007P000280</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00931892</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Serum Markers in Gluten Challenge</brief_title>
  <official_title>Circulating Markers of Celiac Disease Activity During Gluten Challenge - a Pilot Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. The purpose of this research study is to evaluate non-invasive markers of celiac disease
           activity in subjects that are on a gluten-free diet, in remission from celiac disease
           who undergo gluten challenge.

        2. The secondary aims of this protocol are to identify novel mediators important in the
           pathophysiology of celiac disease and to evaluate changes in metabolism with gluten
           exposure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The diagnosis of celiac disease carries with it important ramifications. Celiac disease is a
      systemic immunologic disorder in which the sentinel lesion is an enteropathy triggered by
      polypeptides derived primarily from the gliadin proteins found in wheat, rye and barley.
      Ingestion of the offending proteins leads to inflammation and intestinal mucosal damage,
      which results in a spectrum of abdominal symptoms, increased intestinal permeability,
      malabsorption, occult gastrointestinal bleeding and diarrhea. Systemic manifestations of
      celiac disease include a myriad of conditions including malignancy and autoimmune disease.

      The only accepted treatment for celiac disease is lifelong adherence to a gluten free diet.
      Adherence to this diet, simply put avoiding all foods containing even small amounts of wheat,
      rye and barley, has been shown to lead to improvement in the majority of related problems and
      normalization of all standard diagnostic tests. Because of this many individuals who present
      for evaluation of possible celiac disease but who are already on a gluten free diet cannot be
      tested accurately as there is currently no way of differentiating between healthy individuals
      and individuals with well treated celiac disease. The standard practice in such cases is to
      perform a 'Gluten Challenge' whereby the patient eats the equivalent of 2 slices of bread per
      day for six to eight weeks before returning for evaluation with serologic testing and
      endoscopy with duodenal biopsy. The use of the gluten challenge in clinical practice is
      limited by patient symptoms and resistance to such a long test period, after which it may
      take a number of weeks for the intestine to heal and the symptoms to resolve. Autoantibodies
      to tissue transglutaminase or antibodies to deamidated gliadin, while being excellent tools
      to predict celiac disease in patients who have been on a long-term gluten containing diet,
      display low sensitivities to detect short-term and/or recent gluten exposure. For this
      reason, it would be very useful if novel circulating markers could be identified that
      indicate the presence of celiac disease and in particular would provide an early and less
      invasive marker of a positive response to gluten challenge.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Histological evaluation of duodenal biopsy samples to evaluate crypt depth to villous height ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -7 to -14), Day 3, Day 14</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Histological evaluation of duodenal biopsy samples to determine the number of intraepithelial lymphocytes per 100 enterocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -7 to -14), Day 3, Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measures of intestinal permeability (urinary lactulose to mannitol ratio) and malabsorption (plasma prealbumin)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -7 to -14), Day 0, Day 3, Day 7, Day 14, Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measures of immune activation (tTG, cytokines)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -7 to -14), Day 0, Day 3, Day 7, Day 14, Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of protein expression in intestinal biopsies</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -7 to -14), Day 3, Day 14</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic response to gluten exposure determined by questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (Day -7 to -14), Day 0, Day 3, Day 7, Day 14, Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Celiac Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low gluten group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will eat 3g of gluten per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High gluten group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will eat 10g of gluten per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gluten</intervention_name>
    <description>3g</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low gluten group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gluten</intervention_name>
    <description>10g</description>
    <arm_group_label>High gluten group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age between 17 and 72 years, inclusive.

          2. Subject must have been diagnosed with celiac disease by duodenal / jejunal biopsy at
             least 6 months prior to entrance into the study.

          3. Subject has Anti-Tissue Transglutaminase (anti-tTG) ≤ 20 EU as measured by serology.

          4. Subject must be on a gluten-free diet for at least the past 6 months.

          5. Female subjects should be either post-menopausal (amenorrhea for at least 24
             consecutive months), surgically sterile, or women of child-bearing potential (WOCP)
             with a negative urine beta human chorionic gonadotropin (HCG) pregnancy test prior to
             entering the study and who are using or agree to use acceptable methods of
             contraception. Abstinence is an acceptable means of avoiding pregnancy as long as the
             subject agrees to use contraception if they become sexually active. Acceptable
             contraceptives include intrauterine devices (IUDs), hormonal contraceptives (oral,
             depo, patch or injectable) in use for one month prior to screening and double barrier
             methods such as condoms or diaphragms with spermicidal gel or foam.

          6. Subject must sign an Institutional Review Board approved informed consent and agree to
             complete required clinic visits.

          7. BMI between 18.5 and 38, inclusive.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject has Anti-Tissue Transglutaminase (anti-tTG) &gt; 20 EU as measured by serology.

          2. Subject has other food intolerances or food allergies (other than celiac disease) that
             would interfere with the conduct of the study).

          3. Subject has a history of severe acute symptomatic reactions to sporadic gluten
             ingestion

          4. Subject has any chronic active GI disease other than celiac disease (e.g. Crohn's
             disease, IBS).

          5. Subjects with symptomatic neurological or psychiatric disease(s) that would interfere
             with the conduct of the study.

          6. Subject has clinically significant abnormal laboratory test results at the screening
             visit or as determined by the Principal Investigator

          7. Subject is pregnant or breast feeding.

          8. Subject (premenopausal females) is sexually active without contraception.

          9. Subject should not have been on steroids in the past 3 months.

         10. Subject is deemed inappropriate by the Principal Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>17 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>72 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ciaran P Kelly, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel A Leffler, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bidmc.org/CentersandDepartments/Departments/DigestiveDiseaseCenter/CeliacDiseaseCenter/ResearchStudies.aspx</url>
    <description>BIDMC Celiac Center Research website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 30, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 30, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 2, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ciaran Kelly</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>celiac disease</keyword>
  <keyword>gluten challenge</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Celiac Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

