<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01722812</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LP0075-34</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01722812</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cromoglicate in Psoriasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Exploratory Study Evaluating the Efficacy of Cromoglicate Cream Compared to Cream Vehicle in the Treatment of Itch in Psoriasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>LEO Pharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>LEO Pharma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this exploratory study is to investigate the clinical efficacy of cromoglicate
      cream compared to cream vehicle in the treatment of itch in psoriasis
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of change in visual analogue scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 2</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of change in 4-point itch scale, 7-point itch scale, duration of itch and comparison of treated areas</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to week 2</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (left) / Cromoglicate (right)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo (on a lesion on left bodyside), Cromoglicate (on a lesion on right bodyside)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (right) / Cromoglicate (left)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo (on a lesion on right bodyside), Cromoglicate (on a lesion on left bodyside)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cromoglicate</intervention_name>
    <description>Twice daily topical treatment for 14 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (right) / Cromoglicate (left)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Twice daily topical treatment for 14 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (left) / Cromoglicate (right)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed informed consent has been obtained

          -  Age 18 years or above

          -  Either sex

          -  Any race or ethnicity

          -  Attending hospital outpatient clinic or the private practice of a dermatologist

          -  Clinical diagnosis of stable plaque psoriasis of at least 6 months with a symmetric
             distribution

          -  Two treatment areas with a symmetrical distribution each corresponding to 2-3% BSA and
             each including at least one itchy psoriasis plaque

          -  Itchy psoriasis on both intended treatment areas of at least 40mm on the Visual
             Analogue Scale (VAS) with a maximum difference of 10mm on the visual analogue scale
             between each of the two treatment areas

          -  Disease severity graded mild, moderate or severe according to the Physician's global
             assessment (PGA) of disease severity on psoriasis plaques on each of the two treatment
             areas. The disease severity must be the same for both treatment areas

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Systemic treatment with biological therapies, whether marketed or not, with a possible
             effect on psoriasis vulgaris within the following time periods prior to randomisation:

               -  etanercept - within 4 weeks prior to randomisation

               -  adalimumab, infliximab - within 8 weeks prior to randomisation

               -  ustekinumab - within 16 weeks prior to randomisation

               -  other products - 4 weeks/5 half-lives (whichever is longer)

          -  Systemic treatment with all other therapies with a possible effect on psoriasis
             vulgaris (e.g., corticosteroids, retinoids, methotrexate, ciclosporin, fumaric acid
             derivatives, and other immunosuppressants) within 4 weeks prior to randomization

          -  Any topical treatment of the treatment areas (except for emollients) within 2 weeks
             prior to randomisation.

          -  Treatment with therapies, whether marketed or not, with a possible effect on itch
             within the following time periods prior to randomisation:

               -  antihistamins - within 1 week prior to randomisation

               -  gabapentin - within 4 weeks prior to randomisation

          -  Subjects who have received treatment with any non-marketed drug substance (i.e. a drug
             which has not yet been made available for clinical use following registration) within
             the 4-week period prior to randomisation or longer, if the class of substance required
             a longer treatment free period as defined in exclusion criterion 1 for biological
             treatments

          -  PUVA or Grenz ray therapy within 4 weeks prior to randomisation.

          -  UVB therapy within 2 weeks prior to randomisation

          -  Planned initiation of, or changes to concomitant medication that could affect
             psoriasis vulgaris (e.g., beta blockers, ACE inhibitors, anti-malaria drugs, lithium)
             within 2 weeks prior to randomisation

          -  Subjects with current participation in any other interventional clinical trial

          -  Subjects with any of the following conditions present on the treatment areas: viral
             (e.g. herpes or varicella) lesions of the skin, fungal and bacterial skin infections,
             parasitic infections, skin manifestations in relation to syphilis or tuberculosis,
             acne vulgaris, atrophic skin, striae atrophicae, fragility of skin veins, icthyosis,
             ulcers and wounds

          -  Other inflammatory skin disorders (e.g. seborrhoeic dermatitis or contact dermatitis)
             on the treatment area that may confound the evaluation of psoriasis

          -  Subjects with a history of serious allergy, allergic skin rash or sensitivity to any
             component of the investigational products or formulations being tested

          -  Known or suspected severe renal insufficiency or severe hepatic disorders

          -  Current diagnosis of erythrodermic, exfoliative, guttate or pustular psoriasis

          -  Planned exposure to the sun during the study that may affect psoriasis vulgaris (i.e.,
             normal lifestyle outdoor activities are permitted but deliberate exposure to sunlight
             or artificial ultraviolet light should be avoided)

          -  Subjects previously randomised into this trial

          -  Not all of the exclusion criteria listed due to limited space
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Allergie-Centrum-Charité, Department of Dermatology and Allergy, Charité - Universitätsmedizin Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>D-10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 5, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 5, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 7, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cromolyn Sodium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

