<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01721278</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12/LO/0768</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01721278</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Furlong Evolution® Hip Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Multicentre Clinical Surveillance Study To Evaluate The Stability, Efficacy And Safety Of The Furlong Evolution® Hip Stem In Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Joint Replacement Instrumented Orthopaedics Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Total hip replacement (THR) is a highly effective procedure in relieving pain and restoring
      function. Many different implants can be used in artificial hip joints. Hydroxyapatiteceramic
      (HAC) coating has become a well established The JRI Furlong® HAC femoral stem is one such
      implant with good long term survivorship. The femoral implant has been used since 1985 and
      published findings have shown a 97.4% survivorship at a mean of 17 years follow up in
      patients. The Furlong Evolution® design is based on the tried and tested Furlong HAC but with
      some modifications.

      This is a 10 year multicentre clinical surveillance study, which aims to assess the clinical,
      functional and radiological performance of the Furlong Evolution® Hip stem in human patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose and Design:

      The Furlong Evolution® design is based on the tried and tested Furlong H.A.C implant but with
      some modifications. It still retains its full H.A.C coating and is much shorter in length.
      This potentially makes it easier to introduce into the femoral canal, which may result in
      less soft tissue damage and lower rate of femoral fracture. This would be very beneficial,
      should revision (implant replacement) be required at a later date. This potential
      characteristic has been highlighted as an important component of determining the clinical
      effectiveness of a total hip replacement.

      As per the National Institute of Clinical Excellence (NICE) guidelines the best prostheses
      demonstrates a revision rate (the rate at which they need to be replaced) of 10% or less at
      10 years. This should be regarded as the current benchmark in the selection of prostheses for
      primary Total Hip Replacement (THR). It is also considered reasonable to recommend a
      prostheses with a maximum of 3% revision rate at 3 years which would indicate performance
      would then be subjected to annual review (up to 10 years) to ensure that the revision rate
      remains consistent with the 10year benchmark. The Orthopaedic Data Evaluation Panel (ODEP)
      was established to evaluate data on the outcomes of prostheses provided by manufactures and
      to inform the NHS which products are compliant with the benchmarks set by NICE. Therefore
      this study will be a ODEP compliant multicentre prospective surveillance study of the Furlong
      Evolution® Hip Stem that will assess the clinical, functional and radiographical performance
      over a 10 year period in compliance with the NICE guidelines.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The performance of the Furlong Evolution Hip Stem will be assessed clinically and radiographically of all participants. Number of participants who have reported complications, adverse events &amp; serious adverse events will act as a measure of safety.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Questionnaires (Oxford Hip,EQ5D &amp; Harris Hip Score) will be obtained from participating subjects to evaluate patient function &amp; satisfaction &amp; quality of life at each follow up visit.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">700</enrollment>
  <condition>Focus: A Multicentre Prospective Clinical Surveillance Study Aims to Assess the Clinical, Functional and Radiological Outcome of the Furlong Evolution® Hip Stem</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        As per ODEP guidelines, a minimum of 500 cohort size is required for benchmark validation
        of the clinical performance of a new orthopaedic implant. We will be using a total sample
        size of 700 patients over 10 centres to ensure we meet the benchmark validation criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. All patients consenting to total hip replacement

          2. All patients deemed suitable for total hip replacement

          3. All patients passing pre-assessment deeming them medically fit enough for total hip
             replacement.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients deemed unsuitable for Total Hip Replacement

          2. Patients who refuse to have surgery opting for other modes of treatment

          3. Patients who are unable to consent due to a lack of capacity

          4. Patients unable to understand English

          5. Any patient under the age of 18 years.

          6. Patients who are pregnant or breast feeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Professor Justin Cobb, MCh FRCS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Justin Cobb, MCh FRCS</last_name>
    <phone>02033117687</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hardeep Johal, BSc (Hons)</last_name>
    <phone>020 33115216</phone>
    <email>h.johal@imperial.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charing Cross hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>w6 8rf</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hardeep Johal, BSc (Hons)</last_name>
      <phone>020 33115216</phone>
      <email>h.johal@imperial.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 1, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 5, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 13, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

