<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01726166</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2011813-01H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01726166</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Suprapubic Aspiration Versus Urinary Catheterization In Neonates.</brief_title>
  <acronym>SPA</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial: Suprapubic Aspiration Versus Urinary Catheterization in the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Physicians' Services Incorporated Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Urinary tract infection (UTI) is relatively common in infants, with an occurence rate of up
      to 10%. It is more frequent in male and preterm newborn infants and can lead to significant
      problems in infants including blood infections, kidney infections, and kidney scarring which
      can affect how the kidneys work later in life.

      Analysis of collected urine for the presence of bacteria or fungus is the only way to make a
      certain UTI diagnosis. Urine culture results may take 24 to 48 hours to become available.
      Sterile collection of urine can be achieved in newborn infants by urinary catheterization
      (UC) where a catheter is passed through the urethra into the bladder, suprapubic aspiration
      (SPA) where a needle is inserted into the bladder through the abdominal wall, or 'clean
      catch' where urine is collected into a sterile bottle as the baby urinates during preparation
      for UC. The main advantage of SPA is that it bypasses the bacteria that normally resides in
      the urethral opening, thus minimizing the risk of contamination. Some studies have suggested
      that SPA is better than UC for collecting urine in a sterile fashion in the neonate due to
      the difficulty of doing sterile UC in small infants resulting in more contaminated samples
      (also called a false-positive urine culture); there are some problems with the way these
      studies were done so there is still no clear best choice. UC is commonly used in many
      Neonatal Intensive Care Units (NICU) as it is considered less invasive, can be done by the
      nursing staff, and generally has a higher chance of obtaining urine. SPA is a simple and safe
      alternative and, although some studies suggest that it is more painful than UC, it it
      performed more quickly. The reported success rate for SPA is variable, but is greatly
      increased when an ultrasound confirms urine in the bladder before doing the SPA. The question
      remains: what is the best method for sterile collection of urine in newborns and young
      infants? In this study, the investigators will try to answer this question by collecting
      urine from infants admitted to our NICU using either ultrasound guided SPA or UC and then
      comparing the contamination rates between these two methods.

      The investigators hypothesize that SPA will result in less contamination of urine samples.

      The investigators also hypothesize that there will be more success in obtaining an adequate
      urine sample (0.5 ml) by SPA, SPA will be quicker to perform, and that there will be no
      difference in associated complication rates between SPA and UC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Slow recruitment over 3 yrs (n=47). No chance to reach sample size (n=~160).
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of contaminated urine samples per SPA and UC</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>For SPA samples, urine contamination will be defined as the growth of two or more micro-organisms (any number of colonies per each microorganism) or the growth of Candida species plus growth of any other microorganism.
For UC samples, urine contamination will be defined as the growth of two or more micro-organisms (any number of colonies per each microorganism) or any growth &lt;10^4 colony forming unit(CFU)/ml or the growth of Candida species plus growth of any other microorganism.
The different cut-off used for contamination between UC and SPA samples stems from the fact that the UC procedure is not sterile in the neonatal population.
Note that a bacterial load of &lt;10^3 CFU/mL (e.g. 10^1 or 10^2 CFU/mL) does not grow in the media of either laboratory where our study samples are being cultured.
Further sensitivity analyses will be performed on this outcome measure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Success rates of obtaining urine by SPA versus UC</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Successful withdrawal of urine is defined as obtaining 0.5ml of urine during an attempt at SPA or UC. This is the quantity required by our laboratory for urine culture.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to perform the respective procedures</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Start time will be recorded as initiation of sterile preparation of the skin. Finish time will be recorded as removal of SPA needle or UC catheter. In the event that the catheter is to remain indwelling, finish time will be recorded as the cessation of sample collection for culture</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complication rates of SPA versus UC</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>UC complications
macroscopic hematuria within 48 hours after the procedure including the first void.
urinary retention (completely dry diaper with the presence of a distended bladder based on palpation and/or percussion) within the first 4 hours after the procedure.
SPA complications
macroscopic hematuria within 48 hours after the procedure including the first void after the procedure.
bowel perforation defined as the aspiration of stool contents or clinical and radiographic signs present within 4-6 hrs after the procedure.
suprapubic hematoma or abscess occurring within 1 week after the procedure
clinical peritonitis based on the new presence of some or all of the following: fever, tachycardia, absent bowel sounds, abdominal distension, guarding, rigidity or tenderness, and vomiting occuring within 72 hours after the procedure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Contamination rates of SPA versus UC (excluding clean catch urine)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Since the investigators will collect a clean catch urine sample if the randomly assigned infant passes urine spontaneously during a UC attempt but not during SPA attempt, the investigators will compare the contamination rates per UC versus SPA with the exclusion of clean catch samples to ensure pure comparison between the two procedures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of attempts per procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>For UC: each time a urinary catheter is introduced through the foreskin or the urethral meatus, this will be considered one attempt.
For SPA: each time the skin is punctured by the needle, this will be considered one attempt. This allows for an attempt to include redirection of the needle as long as it remains beneath the skin.
We will be assessing for a procedural learning curve through this outcome measure and the data recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">49</enrollment>
  <condition>Neonatal Urinary Tract Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Suprapubic Aspiration</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A trained physician or neonatal nurse practitioner utilizing U/S guidance at the bedside will perform the SPA. An U/S machine is readily available for use in each NICU.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Urinary Catheterization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The infants will have the procedure done by NICU nurses who have been trained in performing this procedure.
If the randomly assigned infant passes urine spontaneously during a UC attempt after complete perineal cleansing and the urine is collected as a &quot;clean catch&quot; sample, then this infant will be analysed in the assigned group (intention to treat).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Suprapubic Aspiration</intervention_name>
    <description>Pain management will be performed as per our NICU protocols by administering 24% sucrose prior to both procedures to ensure adequate pain control. Additional or different analgesia may be used depending on the patient's specific clinical situation. We will use a chlorhexidine 0.05% with no cetrimide solution as the cleaning solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Suprapubic Aspiration</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Urinary Catheterization</intervention_name>
    <description>Pain management will be performed as per our NICU protocols by administering 24% sucrose prior to both procedures to ensure adequate pain control. Additional or different analgesia may be used depending on the patient's specific clinical situation. We will use a chlorhexidine 0.05% with no cetrimide solution as the cleaning solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Urinary Catheterization</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria (to be approached for consent):

        -All infants who are admitted to the NICU and are not known to have the exclusion criteria
        listed below at the time of admission

        Exclusion criteria (to be approached for consent):

          -  Antenatal detection or suspicion of genitourinary anomaly including: ambiguous
             genitalia, hypospadias, posterior urethral valve, anal atresia, exstrophy-epispadias
             complex, and oligohydramnios secondary to probable genitourinary anomaly(e.g. renal
             agenesis, multicystic kidney disease)

          -  Antenatal hydrops

          -  Antenatally detected abdominal wall defect or abdominal masses

          -  Antenatally detected grossly dilated bowel loops

          -  Congenital abdominal skin lesion over the SPA puncture site

        Inclusion criteria (prior to randomization):

        -All infants who are greater than 72 hours of age, who are being investigated for a
        possible UTI, and have been consented will be eligible for randomization

        Exclusion criteria (prior to randomization):

          -  Oliguria (&lt;0.5 cc/kg/hr) or anuria over the 8 hours prior to attempted urine
             collection

          -  Skin infection over the SPA puncture site

          -  Distension or enlargement of abdominal viscera (e.g. grossly dilated loops of bowel or
             massive organomegaly)

          -  Active Necrotizing enterocolitis (Bell stage II or more)

          -  Uncorrected thrombocytopenia (platelets &lt; 50 x 10 6) or bleeding diathesis

          -  Post-abdominal surgery

          -  Large inguinal hernia

          -  Current pre-existing indwelling catheter
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gregory P Moore, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario; The Ottawa Hospital; The University of Ottawa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H 8L1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ottawa Hospital - General campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H 8L6, K1H 8L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 9, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 14, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Gregory Moore</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Neonatologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Infant</keyword>
  <keyword>contamination rates</keyword>
  <keyword>urinary catheterization</keyword>
  <keyword>suprapubic aspiration</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Tract Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

