<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01725685</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>116524</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01725685</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Investigate the Pharmacokinetics and Safety of Fluticasone Furoate (FF)/ Umeclidinium (UMEC) Combination Compared With FF and UMEC Monotherapies in Adult Healthy Volunteers Using a Dry Powder Inhaler (DPI)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double Blind, Single-dose, Three-period, Crossover Study to Investigate Pharmacokinetic, Safety and Tolerability of Fluticasone Furoate With Umeclidinium When Administered in Combination and as Monotherapies in Adult Healthy Volunteer Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Parexel</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This will be a randomized, double-blind, single-dose, three-period balanced crossover study
      in adult healthy subjects. Each of the 18 subjects will be randomized to receive a treatment
      sequence consisting of each of the three treatments (FF 400 microgram (mcg), UMEC 500 mcg and
      FF 400 mcg/UMEC 500 mcg), in three consecutive periods, with a wash-out period of 7 to 10
      days between the periods.

      The study will include a Screening period (28 days prior to first dose), Treatment period (3
      single dose periods separated by two 7 to 10 days washout periods) and Follow-up period (7 to
      14 days post last dose).

      The pharmacokinetic (PK) and safety assessments will be performed during the study at fixed
      timepoints.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 8, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2, 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2, 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) in plasma for FF and UMEC</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 5 minutes [mins], 15 mins, 30 mins, 45 mins, 1 hour (h), 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 12 h, and 16 h) and Day 2 (24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The PK parameter Cmax will be calculated for FF/UMEC in combination and as monotherapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration-time curve (AUC(0-t)), where t is time of last measurable concentration in plasma for FF and UMEC</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 5 mins, 15 mins, 30 mins, 45 mins, 1 h, 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 12 h, and 16 h) and Day 2 (24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The PK parameter AUC(0-t) will be calculated for will be calculated for FF/UMEC in combination and as monotherapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration-time curve from time zero (pre-dose) extrapolated to infinite time [AUC(0-inf)] in plasma for FF and UMEC, if data permits</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 5 mins, 15 mins, 30 mins, 45 mins, 1 h, 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 12 h, and 16 h) and Day 2 (24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The PK parameter AUC(0-inf) will be calculated for will be calculated for FF/UMEC in combination and as monotherapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of maximum observed concentration (tmax) in plasma for FF and UMEC</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 5 mins, 15 mins, 30 mins, 45 mins, 1 h, 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 12 h, and 16 h) and Day 2 (24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The FF and UMEC PK parameter in plasma will be calculated to compare the PK of FF/UMEC in combination with FF and UMEC monotherapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of last measurable concentration (tlast) in plasma for FF and UMEC</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 5 mins, 15 mins, 30 mins, 45 mins, 1 h, 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 12 h, and 16 h) and Day 2 (24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The FF and UMEC PK parameter in plasma will be calculated to compare the PK of FF/UMEC in combination with FF and UMEC monotherapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma elimination half life (t½) in plasma for FF and UMEC, if data permits</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 5 mins, 15 mins, 30 mins, 45 mins, 1 h, 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 12 h, and 16 h) and Day 2 (24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The FF and UMEC PK parameter in plasma will be calculated to compare the PK of FF/UMEC in combination with FF and UMEC monotherapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Elimination rate constant (Lambda z) in plasma for FF and UMEC, if data permits</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 5 mins, 15 mins, 30 mins, 45 mins, 1 h, 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 12 h, and 16 h) and Day 2 (24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The FF and UMEC PK parameter in plasma will be calculated to compare the PK of FF/UMEC in combination with FF and UMEC monotherapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent clearance (CL/F) in plasma for FF and UMEC, if data permits</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 5 mins, 15 mins, 30 mins, 45 mins, 1 h, 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 12 h, and 16 h) and Day 2 (24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The FF and UMEC PK parameter in plasma will be calculated to compare the PK of FF/UMEC in combination with FF and UMEC monotherapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent volume of distribution (V/F) in plasma for FF and UMEC, if data permits</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 5 mins, 15 mins, 30 mins, 45 mins, 1 h, 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 12 h, and 16 h) and Day 2 (24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The FF and UMEC PK parameter in plasma will be calculated to compare the PK of FF/UMEC in combination with FF and UMEC monotherapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative amount excreted drug in urine (Ae) for UMEC</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 0-6 h, 0-8 h, 0-12 h, 0-16 h) and Day 2(0-24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The UMEC PK parameter in urine will be calculated to compare the PK of UMEC when co-administered with FF; with UMEC as a monotherapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of dose excreted (% Fe) in urine for UMEC</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 0-6 h, 0-8 h, 0-12 h, 0-16 h) and Day 2 (0-24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The UMEC PK parameter in urine will be calculated to compare the PK of UMEC when co-administered with FF; with UMEC as a monotherapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine half life (urine t½) for UMEC, if data permits</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 0-6 h, 0-8 h, 0-12 h, 0-16 h) and Day 2 (0-24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The UMEC PK parameter in urine will be calculated to compare the PK of UMEC when co-administered with FF; with UMEC as a monotherapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal clearance (CLr) in urine for UMEC, if data permits</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 0-6 h, 6-8 h, 8-12 h, 12-16 h) and Day 2(16-24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The UMEC PK parameter in urine will be calculated to compare the PK of UMEC when co-administered with FF; with UMEC as a monotherapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration-time curve from time zero (pre-dose) to the time at which AUC is calculable for all subjects (AUC(0-t')), where t' is the time at which AUC is calculable for all the subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Day 1 (pre-dose, 5 mins, 15 mins, 30 mins, 45 mins, 1 h, 1.5 h, 2 h, 3 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 12 h, and 16 h) and Day 2 (24 h)</time_frame>
    <description>The PK parameter AUC(0-t') will be calculated for will be calculated for FF/UMEC in combination and as monotherapies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Safety data assessed as number of adverse events (AE) in each treatment group</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1 Day 1 dose to Follow up visit</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability will be assessed by recording of AEs for subjects receiving FF/UMEC in combination compared with FF and UMEC monotherapies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical laboratory measurements for each treatment group</measure>
    <time_frame>Period 1, 2 and 3: Baseline (Day -1) and Day 2</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability will be assessed by measuring the clinical laboratory parameters which include hematology, clinical chemistry, routine urinalysis and additional parameters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic and diastolic blood pressure for each treatment group</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Day 1 pre-dose) and Day 2 of each treatment period; and Follow-up Visit</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability will be assessed by measuring vital signs which include systolic and diastolic blood pressure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart rate for each treatment group</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Day 1 pre-dose) and Day 2 of each treatment period; and Follow-up Visit</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability will be assessed by measuring vital signs which include heart rate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) for each treatment group</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Day 1 pre-dose) and Day 2 of each treatment period; and Follow-up Visit</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability will be assessed by measuring ECG using an ECG machine that automatically calculates the heart rate and measures PR, QRS, QT and QTc intervals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment A - FF 400 microgram (mcg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be randomized to single dose of FF 400 mcg in either of the three treatment period, which is separated by a wash-out period of 7 to 10 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment B - UMEC 500 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be randomized to single dose of UMEC 125 mcg in either of the three treatment period, which is separated by a wash-out period of 7 to 10 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment C - FF/UMEC 400/500 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be randomized to single dose of FF/UMEC 100/125 mcg in either of the three treatment period, which is separated by a wash-out period of 7 to 10 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FF 400 mcg</intervention_name>
    <description>FF will be available as 100 mcg strength administered as 4 inhalations from a DPI</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment A - FF 400 microgram (mcg)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>UMEC 500 mcg</intervention_name>
    <description>UMEC will be available as 125 mcg strength administered as 4 inhalations from a DPI</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment B - UMEC 500 mcg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FF/UMEC 400/500 mcg</intervention_name>
    <description>FF/UMEC will be available as 100/125 mcg strength administered as 4 inhalations from a DPI</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment C - FF/UMEC 400/500 mcg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy as determined by a responsible and experienced physician, based on a medical
             evaluation including medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests, and
             cardiac monitoring.

          -  A subject with a clinical abnormality or laboratory parameters outside the reference
             range for the population being studied may be included only if the Investigator and
             the GlaxoSmithKline (GSK) Medical Monitor agree that the finding is unlikely to
             introduce additional risk factors and will not interfere with the study procedures.

          -  Male or female between 18 and 65 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the
             informed consent.

          -  A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of: Child-bearing potential and
             is abstinent or agrees to use the contraception methods listed in Protocol for an
             appropriate period of time (as determined by the product label or investigator) prior
             to the start of dosing to sufficiently minimize the risk of pregnancy at that point.
             Female subjects must agree to use contraception until the follow up visit (i.e. until
             after the follow up visit is complete; Non-childbearing potential defined as
             pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal ligation or hysterectomy; or
             postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous amenorrhea [in questionable cases a
             blood sample with simultaneous follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) &gt; 40 million
             international units (MlU)/milliliter (ml) and estradiol &lt;40 picograms (pg)/ml (&lt;147
             pmol/L) is confirmatory] Females on hormone replacement therapy (HRT) and whose
             menopausal status is in doubt will be required to use the contraception methods listed
             in Protocol if they wish to continue their HRT during the study. Otherwise, they must
             discontinue HRT to allow confirmation of postmenopausal status prior to study
             enrollment. For most forms of HRT, at least 2 to 4 weeks should elapse between the
             cessation of therapy and the blood draw; this interval depends on the type and dosage
             of HRT. Following confirmation of their post-menopausal status, they can resume use of
             HRT during the study without use of a contraceptive method.

          -  Women who are confirmed postmenopausal or permanently sterilized (e.g. tubal
             occlusion, tubal ligation, hysterectomy, bilateral salpingectomy).

          -  Male subjects with female partners of child-bearing potential must agree to use one of
             the contraception methods listed in Protocol. This criterion must be followed from the
             time of the first dose of study medication until the follow up visit.

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin &lt;=1.5xupper limit
             of normal (ULN) (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5xULN is acceptable if bilirubin is
             fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  Average QT duration corrected for heart rate by Fridericia's formula (QTcF) &lt; 450
             miliseconds (msec).

          -  Body mass index (BMI) within the range 19 to 33 kilogram (kg)/meter square (m2)
             (inclusive).

          -  Subjects who are current non-smokers who have not used any tobacco products in the
             6-month period preceding the screening visit and have a pack history of ≤10 pack
             years.[number of pack years = (number of cigarettes per day /20) x number of years
             smoked]

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of screening.

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary
             abnormalities.

          -  A positive pre-study drug/alcohol screen.

          -  A positive test for human Immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study defined as: an
             average weekly intake of &gt;14 drinks for males or &gt;7 drinks for females. One drink is
             equivalent to 12 g of alcohol: 12 ounces (360 mililitre [mL]) of beer, 5 ounces (150
             mL) of wine or 1.5 ounces (45 mL) of 80 proof distilled spirits.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.

          -  Unable to refrain from the use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, including
             vitamins, herbal and dietary supplements (including St John's Wort) within 7 days (or
             14 days if the drug is a potential enzyme inducer) or 5 half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to the first dose of study medication, unless in the opinion of the
             Investigator and GSK Medical Monitor the medication will not interfere with the study
             procedures or compromise subject safety.

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a
             history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or GSK
             Medical Monitor, contraindicates their participation.

          -  Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or blood products
             in excess of 500 mL within a 56 day period.

          -  Pregnant females as determined by positive serum or urine hCG test at screening or
             prior to dosing.

          -  Lactating females.

          -  Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures outlined in the protocol.

          -  Subject is mentally or legally incapacitated.

          -  History of sensitivity to heparin or heparin-induced thrombocytopenia.

          -  History of respiratory disease (i.e. history of asthmatic symptoms) in the last 10
             years.

          -  Urinary cotinine levels indicative of smoking or history or regular use of tobacco- or
             nicotine-containing products within 6 months prior to screening.

          -  Unable to refrain from consumption of red wine, seville oranges, grapefruit or
             grapefruit juice and pummelos, exotic citrus fruits, grapefruit hybrids or fruit
             juices from 7 days prior to the first dose of study medication.

          -  Known or suspected sensitivity to the constituents of the DPI or a history of severe
             milk protein allergy.

          -  A supine mean heart rate outside the range 40 to 90 beats per minute (bpm) at
             screening.

          -  Diseases preventing use of anticholinergics: Diagnosis of narrow-angle glaucoma, or
             bladder neck obstruction that in the opinion of the study investigator or GSK medical
             monitor would pose a safety risk with use of an inhaled anticholinergic.

          -  Other concurrent diseases/abnormalities: A subject must not have any clinically
             significant, uncontrolled condition or disease state that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would put the safety of the patient at risk through study participation
             if the condition/disease exacerbated during the study. The investigator is encouraged
             to contact the study medical monitor if further clarification is required.

          -  Affiliation with the investigators site
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21225</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</url>
    <description>Researchers can use this site to request access to anonymised patient level data and/or supporting documents from clinical studies to conduct further research.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://gsk-clinicalstudyregister.com/study/116524?search=study&amp;study_ids=116524#rs</url>
    <description>Results for study 116524 can be found on the GSK Clinical Study Register.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 14, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>healthy volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>Umeclidinium</keyword>
  <keyword>tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluticasone Furoate</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Patient-level data for this study will be made available through www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com following the timelines and process described on this site.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>116524</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Dataset Specification</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>116524</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Annotated Case Report Form</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>116524</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Study Protocol</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>116524</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>116524</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Individual Participant Data Set</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>116524</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Clinical Study Report</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>116524</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Informed Consent Form</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

