<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01723813</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LUC 10-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01723813</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Peptide Vaccinations Plus GM-CT-01 in Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Study of Peptide Vaccination Associated With GM-CT-01, a Galactomannan Oligomer That Inhibits Galectin-3, in Patients With Advanced Metastatic Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cliniques universitaires Saint-Luc- Université Catholique de Louvain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cliniques universitaires Saint-Luc- Université Catholique de Louvain</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the intravenous and/or GM-CT-01
      administration can correct Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocytes (TIL) anergy and induce a more
      efficient and long-lasting anti-tumoral immune response following peptide vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Human cancers express tumor antigens that can be targeted by cytolytic T lymphocytes (CTL).
      These antigens consist of a small peptide, derived from endogenous proteins, that is
      presented at the cancer cell's surface by an HLA class I molecule. Such antigenic peptides,
      including MAGE-3.A1 and NA17.A2, have been tested in experimental therapeutic vaccines to
      elicit CTL responses in cancer patients, mainly with metastatic melanoma. Up to now, only
      rare tumor responses have been observed.

      Tumor resistance to CTL killing is the most likely explanation for the poor effectiveness of
      cancer vaccines. This resistance is probably acquired by the tumor during its development and
      selected by its repetitive challenge with spontaneous anti-tumoral immune responses.
      Recently, we have identified a novel mechanism causing anergy of tumor-associated T
      lymphocytes, and established new approaches to correct this anergy in vitro. Galectin-3,
      secreted by tumor cells, appears to inhibit CTL function the co-localization of the T cell
      receptor and the cluster of differentiation 8 coreceptor. Importantly, this functional defect
      is restored when anergic T cells are incubated with galectin-3 inhibitors such as the
      disaccharides lactose and N-acetyllactosamine, and the polysaccharide GM-CT-01. GM-CT-01 is a
      vegetal galactomannan oligomer, currently under clinical investigation in several types of
      solid malignancies for its capacity to inhibit galectins and to synergize with chemotherapy
      drugs.

      Our observations suggest that treatment of cancer patients with GM-CT-01 could correct TIL
      anergy and induce a more efficient and long-lasting anti-tumoral immune response following
      peptide vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after last administration of Study drugs</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in adverse events will be recorded at each patient's visit and up to 30 days after last administration of study drugs. Measurements will use the Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Effects 4,0 scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate in both arms</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at week 7 and week 20</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy of the combination of a peptide vaccine and GM-CT-01 injections measures performed by CT-scan or MRI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate in group 2 versus group 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at week 7 and week 20</time_frame>
    <description>To determine whether addition of peri-tumoral injections of GM-CT-01 increase tumor response therefore response rate observed in group 1 will be compared with group 2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of inclusion until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, which ever came first, assessed up to 100 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>patients will be followed every three months at consultation and with radiological examination, they will be assessed up to 100 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From day of inclusion to date of death</time_frame>
    <description>patients will be followed every three months at consultation and with radiological examination, they will be assessed up to 100 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity of the treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at week 20</time_frame>
    <description>assessed at baseline and at week 20</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Translational research</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and at progression</time_frame>
    <description>anti-tumoral immunological events in tumor samples obtained before and at progression</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics of GM-CT-01</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at days 46 to 48</time_frame>
    <description>serum concentration of GM-CT-01</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 : peptides + GM-CT-01 IV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tumor specific peptides: MAGE-3.A1 and / or NA17.A2 plus Galectin-3 inhibitor: GM-CT-01 systemic injections</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 : peptides + GM-CT-01 IV+PT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tumor specific peptides: MAGE-3.A1 and / or NA17.A2 plus Galectin-3 inhibitor: GM-CT-01 systemic injections and Galectin-3 inhibitor: GM-CT-01 Peri-tumoral administration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tumor specific peptides: MAGE-3.A1 and / or NA17.A2</intervention_name>
    <description>Each peptide will be given at a dose of 300 µg in 1 ml of sodium chloride 0.9%, every 3 weeks on 6 occasions, and will be administered at one site in arm or thigh, 20% of the dose intradermally and 80% of the dose subcutaneously.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 : peptides + GM-CT-01 IV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 : peptides + GM-CT-01 IV+PT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Galectin-3 inhibitor: GM-CT-01 systemic injections</intervention_name>
    <description>Systemic injection of GM-CT-01: GM-CT-01 will be administered by slow intravenous infusions at a dose of 280 mg/m2, on days +3, +6, +9, +12, +15, +18 after each of the 3rd, 4th, 5th and 6th vaccination.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 : peptides + GM-CT-01 IV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 : peptides + GM-CT-01 IV+PT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Galectin-3 inhibitor: GM-CT-01 Peri-tumoral administration</intervention_name>
    <description>GM-CT-01 will be injected peri-tumoral at a dose of 100 µg per tumor injected, on days +3, +6, +9, +12, +15, +18 after each of the 3rd, 4th, 5th and 6th vaccination. If a patient has one or two superficial metastases at day 43 of the treatment, one of these lesions will be treated. If a patient has more than two superficial metastases at day 43, two of these lesions will be treated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 : peptides + GM-CT-01 IV+PT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histologically proven cutaneous melanoma at one of the following
             American Joint Committee on Cancer stages : Regional metastatic disease (any T; N2c or
             N3; M0), no amenable to curative treatment by surgery or isolated limb
             perfusion.Distant metastatic disease (any T; any N; M1a, M1b or M1c*).*except
             uncontrolled brain metastasis and except Lactate dehydrogenase &gt;1.5 upper normal value

          -  HLA-A1 or HLA-A2 (by serology or molecular biology)

          -  At least one of the two following conditions:

        MAGE-3 gene expression by the tumor if patient is HLA-A1 NA17 gene expression by the tumor
        if patient is HLA-A2 (determined by reverse transcription and polymerase chain reaction
        amplification).

          -  Measurable Disease. Patients must have at least 1 measurable metastasis at study entry
             for all patients. In addition, patients candidates for enrollment in Group 2 who will
             receive peri-tumoral injections of GM-CT-01 must have at least 1 superficial
             metastasis (cutaneous, subcutaneous or superficial lymph node metastasis, with its
             largest diameter equal to or greater than 5, 5, or 10 mm, respectively) at study
             entry.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years.

          -  Karnofsky Performance status ≥70 or WHO performance status of 0 or 1

          -  Expected survival of at least 6 months.

          -  Laboratory values :

        Platelet count ≥100x103/μL Leukocyte count ≥ 3x103/μL Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL Aspartate
        transaminase and Alanine transaminase ≤ 2 times upper normal value Serum creatinine ≤1.5
        times upper normal value Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times upper normal value Lactate
        dehydrogenase ≤ 1.5 times upper normal value

          -  Viral serology : negative antibodies for Hepatitis C Virus &amp; HIV; negative antigens
             for Hepatitis B Virus.

          -  Patient should agree to perform biopsies and blood collections for translational
             research.

          -  Signed informed consent from the patient must be obtained.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncontrolled brain or central nervous system metastasis.

          -  Previous treatment for the melanoma within 6 weeks from inclusion, with any reagent
             known to modulate the immune system such as a cancer vaccine, interferon-alpha,
             interleukins or anti-CTLA-4 antibodies.

          -  Previous chemotherapy, radiotherapy, corticotherapy, or other immune suppressive
             therapy within 4 weeks from inclusion.

          -  Clinically significant cardiovascular disease (including cardiac insufficiency New
             York Heart Association grade III and IV, unstable angina, arrythmia, myocardial
             infarction, symptomatic congestive heart failure) in the past 12 months before
             enrollment.

          -  Other serious acute or chronic illnesses, e.g. active infections requiring
             antibiotics, bleeding disorders or other conditions requiring concurrent medications
             not allowed during this study.

          -  Other malignancy within 3 years prior to entry in the study, except for treated
             non-melanoma skin cancer and in situ cervical carcinoma.

          -  Active immunodeficiency disease or autoimmune disease (vitiligo is not an exclusion
             criterion).

          -  Lack of availability for immunological and clinical follow-up assessments.

          -  Participation in any other clinical trial involving another investigational agent
             within 4 weeks prior to enrollment.

          -  Subject pregnant or breastfeeding, or planning to become pregnant within 6 months
             after the end of treatment.

          -  Subject (male or female) not willing to use highly effective methods of contraception
             (per institutional standard) during treatment and for 6 months after the end of
             treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-Francois BAURAIN, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cliniques univeristaires Saint-Luc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jean-François Baurain, MD / PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+32 2 764 54 71</phone>
    <email>jean-francois.baurain@uclouvain.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cliniques Universitaires Saint Luc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brussels</city>
        <zip>1200</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean-François Baurain, MD / PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+32 2 764 54 71</phone>
      <email>jean-francois.baurain@uclouvain.be</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-François Baurain, MD / PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 8, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 8, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Tumor-specific peptides</keyword>
  <keyword>GM-CT-01</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

