<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03281902</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC1634</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2017-01479</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MC1634</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015083</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03281902</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic Analysis in Blood and Tumor Samples From Patients With Advanced or Metastatic Estrogen Receptor Positive and HER2 Negative Breast Cancer Receiving Palbociclib and Endocrine Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Study to Evaluate the Role of Tumor Sequencing in Women Receiving Palbociclib for Advanced Hormone Receptor (HR)-Positive, Breast Cancer (PROMISE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research trial studies genetic profiles in blood and tumor samples from patients with
      estrogen receptor positive and HER2 negative breast cancer that has spread to other places in
      the body who are receiving palbociclib and endocrine therapy. Examine the genetic changes
      associated with the cancer and comparing the genetic material from the cancer tissue with the
      genetic material found in the blood may help doctors to develop customized treatment for
      breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Identify novel genomic variants and pathways associated with early progression
      (progression within 12 months) among women with advanced hormone positive breast cancer
      treated with palbociclib and endocrine therapy.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess whether time to progression differs with respect to SNAIL expression and other
      markers of EMT.

      II. To assess whether time to progression differs with respect to genetic alterations known
      to be associated with endocrine monotherapy resistance (e.g. ESR1 mutations/fusions, AKT,
      HER2, estrogen receptor [ER]alpha, etc.).

      III. To tabulate the number of patients who have targetable mutations found in the baseline
      tumor and assess their subsequent treatment regimen following progression on palbociclib and
      endocrine therapy.

      IV. To assess whether time to progression differs with respect to biomarkers associated with
      the CD44high/CD24/low/ERlow cancer stem cell-like phenotype, ERalpha downregulation and
      resistance to endocrine therapy and palbociclib [expression of total and phosphorylated
      AURKA, breast cancer stemness biomarkers (CD44, CD24, ALDH1) EMT transcription factors
      (SMAD5, SOX2), cyclin E, cyclin A and phosphorylated retinoblastoma (Rb)].

      V. To generate patient derived xenograft (PDX)s from the baseline tumor biopsy (Rochester
      only) test novel endocrine therapy combinations in PDXs generated from the baseline tumor
      biopsy.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To compare and contrast the spectrum of ESR1 mutations identified in tissue, circulating
      cell free deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) (cfDNA), and circulating tumor cell (CTC) derived DNA.

      II. To compare and contrast the actionable genomic alterations found in cfDNA or CTC derived
      DNA that are not found in tumor tissue.

      III. To assess whether genetic alterations known to be associated with endocrine monotherapy
      resistance is seen in cfDNA and CTC derived DNA.

      IV. To examine shifts in the populations of epithelial like CTCs and stem cell like CTCs
      during the course of endocrine therapy with palbociclib.

      V. To assess CTC expression of ER, HER2, and other markers of endocrine resistance.

      VI. To explore the proteomics of ER-positive breast cancer and identify biomarkers associated
      with early progression and neutropenia.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients undergo collection of blood at baseline and on day 1 of each treatment cycle.
      Patients also undergo tumor biopsy at baseline and 2 months. Biopsy samples are analyzed for
      genetic profile via next generation sequencing and ribonucleic acid (RNA) sequencing. Biopsy
      samples are also used for the generation of xenograft mice model.

      After completion of study, patients are followed up for 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 7, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 7, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bioinformatics analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Identify novel genomic variants and pathways associated with early progression (progression within 12 months) among women with advanced hormone positive breast cancer treated with palbociclib and endocrine therapy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Estrogen Receptor Positive</condition>
  <condition>HER2/Neu Negative</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Breast Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ancillary-Correlative (genetic profile analysis)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients undergo collection of blood at baseline and on day 1 of each treatment cycle. Patients also undergo tumor biopsy at baseline and 2 months. Biopsy samples are analyzed for genetic profile via next generation sequencing and RNA sequencing. Biopsy samples are also used for the generation of xenograft mice model. Patients are followed up for 3 years.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo tumor biopsy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ancillary-Correlative (genetic profile analysis)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bx</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biospecimen Collection</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo collection of blood</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ancillary-Correlative (genetic profile analysis)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ancillary-Correlative (genetic profile analysis)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      biopsy samples, DNA and RNA will be extracted and blood draws for collection of plasma,
      circulating tumor DNA, and circulating tumor cells.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women who have disease that is amenable to biopsy and agree to undergo a standard of care
        core biopsy of recurrent or metastatic breast cancer ,and to collect additional core
        samples for research purposes.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  PRE-REGISTRATION INCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  Women who have disease that is amenable to biopsy and agree to undergo a standard of
             care core biopsy of recurrent or metastatic breast cancer, and to collect additional
             core samples for research purposes

          -  Patients must satisfy one of the following criteria for prior therapy:

               -  First line setting: No prior endocrine therapy in the metastatic setting with no
                  more than one prior line of chemotherapy in the advanced/metastatic setting

               -  Second line setting: Progression on one prior line of endocrine based therapy
                  monotherapy either in the adjuvant or advanced/metastatic setting. Either one or
                  two prior lines of chemotherapy in the advanced setting are allowed

               -  Note: Patients receiving bisphosphonate or denosumab therapy prior to
                  registration may continue at the same intervals used prior to study registration

          -  First line therapy setting only: Palbociclib and letrozole is recommended for locally
             advanced or metastatic breast cancer

          -  Second line therapy setting only: Palbociclib and fulvestrant is recommended (after
             progression on first line endocrine therapy) for metastatic breast cancer

          -  Measurable disease as defined by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)
             criteria or bone only disease are eligible.

               -  Note: Those patients with both non-measurable disease and bone metastases are
                  eligible

               -  Note: Patients are not allowed to begin a new systemic anti-cancer therapy during
                  pre-registration with the exception of bisphosphonate or denosumab; palliative
                  radiation is allowed during pre-registration

          -  No current evidence of visceral crisis or lymphangitic spread

          -  History of central nervous system metastasis are allowed provided they have been
             treated (i.e., surgery, radiation, and/or radiosurgery) =&lt; 12 weeks prior to
             registration and have stable neurologic function, including no requirement for
             medication(s) to control symptoms for at least 2 weeks; Note: patients with known
             leptomeningeal disease are not eligible

          -  Women who are premenopausal must agree to begin or continue an LHRH agonist (goserelin
             preferred)

               -  NOTE: A woman is considered premenopausal if menses has occurred in the last 12
                  months prior to preregistration and both serum and follicle stimulating hormone
                  (FSH) levels are not in the laboratory?s reference range for postmenopausal
                  females

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status: 0, 1, or 2

          -  Able to swallow oral formulation of drugs

          -  Signed and dated informed consent document for study participation

          -  Willing to submit tissue for required correlative research

          -  REGISTRATION INCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  Histologic confirmation from the pre-registration biopsy of either locally advanced or
             metastatic breast cancer that is ER-positive and HER2 -negative

               -  Note: ER-positive disease is defined as &gt;= 10% nuclear staining; HER2-negative
                  disease per 2013 American Society of Clinical Oncology/College of American
                  Pathologists (ASCO/CAP) guidelines, one of the following must apply:

                    -  0 or 1+ by immunohistochemistry (IHC) and not amplified by in situ
                       hybridization (ISH)

                    -  0 or 1+ by IHC and ISH not done

                    -  2+ by IHC and not amplified by ISH or

                    -  IHC not done and not amplified by ISH

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1500/mm^3

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 100,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9.0 g/dL

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN), (=&lt; 3 x ULN if Gilbert?s
             disease)

          -  Aspartate transaminase (AST) =&lt; 3 x ULN (=&lt; 5 x ULN if liver metastases present)

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Willing to return to enrolling institution for follow-up (during the active monitoring
             phase of the study)

          -  Recovered from all toxicities from all prior anticancer therapies

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  PRE-REGISTRATION EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  History of metastatic ER negative or HER2 positive breast cancer

          -  Prior treatment in the metastatic setting with everolimus, or any agent whose
             mechanism of action is to inhibit the PI3K-mTOR pathway

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to:

               -  Ongoing or active infection

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure

               -  Unstable angina pectoris

               -  Uncontrolled symptomatic cardiac arrhythmia

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension (defined as blood pressure &gt; 160/90)

          -  Other active second malignancy other than non-melanoma skin cancers =&lt; 3 years of
             pre-registration; Note: a second malignancy is not considered active if all treatment
             for that malignancy is completed and the patient has been disease-free for =&lt; 3 years
             prior to pre-registration

          -  Prior hematopoietic stem cell or bone marrow transplantation =&lt; 3 years of
             pre-registration

          -  Known hypersensitivity to palbociclib, letrozole, fulvestrant, goserelin (if
             applicable) or to any of their excipients

          -  Known to be pregnant and planning to continue nursing

          -  REGISTRATION EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          -  No tumor identified on biopsy or insufficient tumor cells to obtain ER or HER2 status

          -  Any of the following therapies prior to registration:

               -  Chemotherapy =&lt; 2 weeks

               -  Immunotherapy =&lt; 2 weeks

               -  Biologic therapy =&lt; 2 weeks

               -  Monoclonal antibodies =&lt; 2 weeks

               -  Radiation therapy =&lt; 2 weeks

               -  Anti HER2 or other ?targeted? therapy =&lt; 2 weeks

          -  The following patients are not eligible

               -  Pregnant women

               -  Nursing women

               -  Women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to employ adequate
                  contraception
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Female</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ciara O'Sullivan</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>855-776-0015</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Donald W. Northfelt</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32224-9980</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>855-776-0015</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alvaro Moreno-Aspitia</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinical Trials Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>855-776-0015</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ciara C. O'Sullivan</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Palbociclib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

