<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03288454</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PER977-02-011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03288454</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 2 Study of Apixaban Reversal by Ciraparantag as Measured by WBCT</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 2 Placebo-Controlled, Single-Site, Single-Blind Study of Apixaban Reversal by Ciraparantag as Measured by WBCT</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Perosphere, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Perosphere, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a randomized, single-blind, placebo-controlled study to assess the efficacy and
      safety of ciraparantag administered to healthy volunteers anticoagulated with apixaban
      measuring clotting times using Whole Blood Clotting Time (WBCT).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 10, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy of ciraparantag in the reversal of anticoagulation induced by apixaban measured by WBCT</measure>
    <time_frame>4 days</time_frame>
    <description>efficacy of ciraparantag in the reversal of anticoagulation induced by apixaban at steady state measured by WBCT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values and/or Adverse Events That Are Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants With Abnormal Laboratory Values and/or Adverse Events That Are Related to Treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Administer ciraparantag or placebo Dosing schedule 1</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Administer ciraparantag or placebo Dosing schedule 2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Administer ciraparantag or placebo Dosing schedule 3</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ciraparantag</intervention_name>
    <description>Reversal of riva apixaban-induced anticoagulation via dose of ciraparantag or placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PER977</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Reversal of riva apixaban-induced anticoagulation via dose of ciraparantag or placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adults age 50 to 75 years, inclusive

          2. Laboratory tests (chemistry, hematology and coagulation assessments) and urinalysis
             performed during screening up to 36 days prior to administration of study treatment
             deemed not clinically significant by the principal investigator.

          3. No clinically significant findings on 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) performed during
             screening

          4. Body mass index (BMI) 18 to ≤ 32 kg/m2, inclusive

          5. Male subjects agree to use appropriate contraception (i.e., latex condom with
             spermicide) in addition to their partner using an acceptable form of contraception
             (e.g., diaphragm, cervical cap, intrauterine device, hormonal contraceptives, surgical
             sterilization or post-menopausal), when engaging in sexual activity during the course
             of the study. Moreover, male subjects should not donate sperm or attempt to impregnate
             a partner during the course of the study and for a period of 12 weeks following
             discharge from the study.

          6. Female subjects must have a negative urine pregnancy test at screening AND: be
             surgically sterile (with documentation of hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy,
             bilateral salpingectomy, bilateral tubal ligation/tubal occlusion) OR post-menopausal
             (no menstruation for a minimum of 12 months and confirmed by follicle stimulating
             hormone [FSH] of ≥ 40 mIU/ml) OR, if of child-bearing potential, must be using an
             acceptable method of contraception such as an IUD, implant or contraceptive injection,
             or two forms of the following (e.g., diaphragm, cervical cap, oral, patch or vaginal
             hormonal contraceptive, condom, spermicide, or sponge) for the last three months, OR
             in a monogamous relation with a male partner who has undergone a documented vasectomy
             a minimum of 6 months prior to study commencement. All females must agree to continue
             to use their method of birth control for the duration of the study and for a minimum
             of one complete menstrual cycle or 28 days following discharge from the study
             Ciraparantag Perosphere Inc. Clinical Trial Protocol: PER977-02-011 9 August 2017
             Confidential Page 10 of 85

          7. Subjects who have participated in a prior study of ciraparantag must have been
             discharged from the study a minimum of 1 month prior to the planned treatment.

          8. Subjects must understand and agree to comply with the requirements of the study and
             they must be willing to sign the informed consent form indicating voluntary consent to
             participate in the study prior to initiation of screening or study-related activities
             -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History or current evidence of clinically significant cardiac, hepatic, renal,
             pulmonary, endocrine, neurologic, infectious, gastrointestinal (including gallbladder
             disease or surgery), hematologic, or oncologic disease as determined by screening
             history, physical examination, laboratory test results or 12-lead ECG assessment.
             History or current evidence of liver function tests greater than 50% of the upper
             limit of normal (ULN) or renal function tests (serum creatinine) greater than 1.5
             mg/dl and based on PI discretion. History or current evidence of QTc (QTcF) greater
             than normal (450 msec for males or 470 msec for females).

          2. History of unexplained syncope

          3. History of major bleeding, trauma, or surgical procedure of any type,

          4. Vaginal delivery within six months prior to screening

          5. History of peptic ulcer, gastrointestinal bleeding (including hematemesis, melena,
             rectal bleeding) within one year prior to screening

          6. Long standing history of bleeding episodes such as epistaxis, bruising or gingival
             bleeding or if not long standing, within 1 month prior to screening

          7. Personal or family history of clotting disorder or abnormality, excessive bleeding,
             joint hematoma, thrombovascular disease or any hematologic disorder involving
             platelets or clotting abnormalities or any condition requiring treatment with
             transfusions, or history of thrombocytopenia

          8. Females with a history of dysfunctional uterine bleeding who have not undergone
             hysterectomy, including history of menorrhagia (heavy menstrual bleeding),
             menometrorrhagia or polymenorrhea

          9. Smokers or use of tobacco and/or nicotine containing products within 3 months prior to
             dosing as determined by the subject's verbal history

         10. Pregnant or breast-feeding

         11. Males with a history of hormone therapy within 3 months prior to screening

         12. Taking any type of chronic medication (including vitamin, nutritional and herbal
             supplements) for more than 14 consecutive days within the 4 weeks prior to study entry
             (use of hormonal contraceptives is acceptable except for oral contraceptives)

         13. Positive serologic test for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), Hepatitis C virus
             antibody (HCV-Ab), or Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg)

         14. Donation of blood or blood products within 56 days prior to screening

         15. Participation in any study with an investigational compound or device within 30 days
             prior to signing informed consent

         16. Active drug or alcohol dependence within the prior 12 months or any condition that, in
             the opinion of the Investigator, would interfere with adherence to study protocol

         17. Allergic to apixaban
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Solomon S Steiner, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>203 885 1116</phone>
    <email>s.steiner@perosphere.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Barry H Ginsberg, MD, PhE</last_name>
    <phone>203 885 1111</phone>
    <email>b.ginsberg@perosphere.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Frontage Clinical Services Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Secaucus</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07094</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexander N. Prezioso, MD</last_name>
      <phone>201-416-7747</phone>
      <email>aprezioso@frontaglab.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexander N Prezioso, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 18, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ciraparantag</keyword>
  <keyword>PER977</keyword>
  <keyword>Apixaban</keyword>
  <keyword>Whole Blood Clotting Time (WBCT)</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Apixaban</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

