<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03285113</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CTC1601</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03285113</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Confirm the Safety of High Frequency DRG Stimulator in Patients With Chronic Lower Limb Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-arm, Open Label, Single Center Pilot Study to Confirm the Safety of Dorsal Root Ganglia (DRG) and Ultrahigh Frequency Spinal Cord Stimulator in Patients With Chronic Lower Limb Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GiMer Medical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>China Medical University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GiMer Medical</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective, single-arm, open label, single center pilot study to confirm the
      safety of a ultrahigh frequency DRG stimulator in patients with chronic lower limb pain. The
      actual trial length is 5 days. Pts will be given ultrahigh frequency pulse stimulation, and
      VAS will be obtained after 3-4 hours of each stimulation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective, single-arm, open label, single center pilot study to confirm the
      safety of a ultrahigh frequency DRG stimulator in patients with chronic lower limb pain. The
      actual trial length is 5 days. An initial eligibility screening within Day -14. Pt admitted
      to hospital on Day 1. The lead implantation is conducted on Day 2, and the 1st treatment
      starts after anesthesia recovery (Day 2 T1). If VAS &gt;4 at 4 hours after the 1st treatment,
      the 2nd treatment will be conducted. VAS will be acquired 4 hours after the 2nd treatment. On
      Day 3, physical examination and vital signs will be collected. If VAS &gt;4, the 3rd treatment
      will be provided. One hour after the 3rd treatment, the device will be removed and an X-ray
      will be taken. Three hours after the removal, VAS will be collected and then the patient will
      be discharged. VAS will be estimated by phone call on Day 4, and the patient will return to
      OPD for follow up examination on Day 5. The trial is completed on Day 5 visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 5, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 5, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of ultrahigh frequency treatment: Adverse event (AE) and serious AE (SAE) incidence rates during the trial</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse event (AE) and serious AE (SAE) incidence rates during the trial</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain reduction measured by VAS score</measure>
    <time_frame>4 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pain reduction as a result of ultrahigh frequency DRG stimulation, as measured by VAS score compare to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Paresthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <description>If patients feel tingling during stimulation?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain medication consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pain medication consumption, including Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs) and weak opioids, compared to baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Failed Back Surgery Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Complex Regional Pain Syndrome (CRPS)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ultrahigh Frequency Stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with chronic lower limb pain will be treated with ultrahigh frequency stimulation via lead around DRG.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GiMer Medical MN 1000 External Stimulator</intervention_name>
    <description>Trial stimulator to generate pulsed ultrahigh frequency (&gt;200KHz) electrical stimulation, delivered via lead around DRG, in treating pain. Similar with current market available Spinal Cord Stimulators but with a higher stimulation frequency (hundred KHz) range.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ultrahigh Frequency Stimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≧20 and ≦75

          2. Have a symptom of complex regional pain syndrome (CRPS), failed back surgery syndrome
             (FBSS), lower limb pain with or without lower back pain with a diagnosis related to
             spinal lesion and pain history of &gt;6 months.

          3. Have an average pain score &gt;5 by Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) on inclusion.

          4. Has failed to achieve adequate pain relief from prior pharmacologic treatments.

          5. In the judgement of the investigator, the subject is an appropriate candidate for the
             trial procedure

          6. The subject is willing and able to comply with the procedure and requirements of this
             trial.

          7. The participant is able to understand and provide informed consent, and has signed
             their written informed consent in accordance with IRB requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Have evidence of a mental or psychological condition that affects pain perception and
             has difficulty/disability performing objective pain assessment, or have previously
             failed mental or psychological assessments administered by a psychiatrist that may be
             deemed to indicate the subject's lack of suitability for participation in this study.

          2. Subject has exhibited escalating or changing pain condition within the past 30 days as
             evidenced by Investigator examination.

          3. Be on anticoagulant medication with INR &gt;1.5 or platelet count less than 100,000/μL,
             peripheral vascular diseases (PVDs), visceral pain or uncontrolled Diabetes mellitus
             (DM).

          4. Has had corticosteroid therapy at an intended site of stimulation within the past 30
             days.

          5. Pain medication(s) dosages(s) are not stable for at least 30 days.

          6. Has previously failed spinal cord stimulation therapy.

          7. Currently has an active implantable device including ICD, pacemaker, spinal cord
             stimulator or intrathecal drug pump or subject requires magnetic resonance imaging
             (MRIs) or diathermy.

          8. Has pain only within a cervical or thoracic distribution.

          9. Have a current diagnosis of cancer with active symptoms

         10. Have a known terminal illness with life expectancy less than one year

         11. Have a systematic or local infection

         12. Currently has an indwelling device that may pose an increased risk of infection.

         13. Be pregnant or breast feeding

         14. Have a medical history of drug or alcohol addiction within the past 2 years.

         15. Participation in any investigational study in the last 30 days or current enrollment
             in any trial.

         16. Be currently involved in an injury claim law suit or medically related litigation,
             including workers compensation.

         17. Be a prisoner.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>China Medical University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taichung</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 15, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Complex Regional Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Reflex Sympathetic Dystrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Failed Back Surgery Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

