<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03283241</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ADD-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03283241</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zolidd One ExHex Dental Implant Compared to Uncoated One ExHex Dental Implant in Subjects With Partial Edentulism</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Multicentre, Double Blind, Parallel Study to Evaluate the Performance and Safety of the Zolidd One ExHex Dental Implant Compared to Uncoated One ExHex Dental Implant in Subjects With Partial Edentulism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Addbio AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Addbio AB</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomised, multicentre, double blind, parallel group comparative investigation where
      subjects will be randomised to receive coated or uncoated implants
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will consist of two parts. Part I, is the main study ending when all subjects have
      reached visit 5. The study will be evaluated and Clinical Study Report (CSR) will be written
      for this part.

      Part II, of the study is a post-follow up study starting when the first subject has completed
      visit 5. There will be a separate CSR written for Study Part II.

      The study Part I will begin with a baseline visit, visit 1, Informed consent procedure will
      take place. Provided the subject will give informed consent for both Study Part I and Study
      Part II the screening procedure starts. Subjects will undergo all screening and baseline
      assessment procedures including assessments of dental status to determine number of implants
      needed. Subjects who meet all the inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria will
      be given a date for implant surgery within three weeks. The required number of implants will
      be ordered from the Study Distributor.

      At the implantation day, visit 2, eligibility will be re-checked before the surgery
      procedures starts. The subjects who still are eligible will enter the treatment and the
      implantation surgery is conducted. The first follow-up visit after implantation will take
      place week 2 post-surgery and the last follow-up visit in Study Part I will be at week 12.
      Any post-surgical complications and adverse events will be collected and recorded in the
      eCRF. On demand, depending on the outcome of the surgery, additional visits might occur.

      Study Part II, the Post Follow-up Study, consist of two visits, one at month 12 and another
      visit at month 24 post-surgery. Post-surgical complications and adverse events from Study
      Part I will be followed-up if not resolved previously. Safety, survival rate and marginal
      bone loss will be assessed and outcome recorded in the eCRF. Additional visits might occur
      depending on the status of the subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel groups ration 1;1</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>The devices are delivered single packed and sterile to distributor. The distributor performs blinding, randomization and distribution. The labels are, after blinding of lot number, identical for both the Active and the placebo device.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in stability from day 1 to 12 weeks after implantation of the &quot;index implant&quot; comparing coated and uncoated implants</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective is to compare the change in stability from day 1 (implantation) to 12 weeks after surgery of the &quot;index implant&quot; between coated and uncoated implants.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute ISQ highest value</measure>
    <time_frame>week 8 and week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare absolute ISQ highest values between coated and uncoated &quot;index implants&quot; at week 8 and week 12 after implantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of post-surgery complications and adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day1 to week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare safety as assessed by complications post-surgery and any other adverse event up to week 12 between all coated and all uncoated implants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ISQ highest value for the &quot;index implant&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to week 8</time_frame>
    <description>To compare change in stability from day 1 to week 8 between the coated and the uncoated &quot;index implants&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ISQ highest value for all other implants</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, week 8 and week 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare change in stability day 1 to week 8 and 12 between all other coated and all other uncoated implants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute ISQ highest value for all other implants</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 8 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare absolute ISQ highest value at week 8 and 12 between all other coated and all other uncoated implants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in marginal bone height for all other implants</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 to week 8 and 12</time_frame>
    <description>To compare change in marginal bone height between all coated and all uncoated implants from day 1 to week 8 and 12</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-surgical complications and other adverse events for all implants</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12 to month 24</time_frame>
    <description>To compare safety as assessed by complications post-surgery and other adverse events up to month 24 post-implantation visit between all coated and all uncoated implants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival rate for all implants</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare survival rate of implants up to 24 months between all coated and all uncoated implants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in marginal bone height for all implants</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1, month 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>To compare change in marginal bone height from day 1 to month 12 and 24 between all coated and all uncoated implants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of signs associated with peri-implantitis for all implants</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 12 and 24</time_frame>
    <description>To compare peri-implantitis frequency at 12 and 24 months between all coated and all uncoated implants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">71</enrollment>
  <condition>Partial Edentulism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Zolidd One ExHex</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Coated titanium implant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>One ExHex</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Uncoated titanium implant</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zolidd One ExHex</intervention_name>
    <description>Subject will be treated/implanted at visit 2, one of the implants will be chosen as the &quot;index implant&quot;and will be followed together with other implants (maximum 6 implant per subject) at week 8,12 and month 12 and 24.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zolidd One ExHex</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>One ExHex</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>One ExHex</intervention_name>
    <description>Subject will be treated/implanted at visit 2, one of the implants will be chosen as the &quot;index implant&quot;and will be followed together with other implants (maximum 6 implant per subject) at week 8,12 and month 12 and 24.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zolidd One ExHex</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>One ExHex</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female subjects aged &gt;18 years

          -  Subjects should be willing to take part, able to understand the information given to
             them, and give written consent

          -  Subject diagnosed with partial edentulism and who needs at least one dental implant in
             the posterior upper jaw i.e. premolars to first molar. The same subject may also need
             implants in the posterior mandible (premolars to first molar region)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Suspected to be immunocompromised or are taking immunosuppressant

          -  Current participation in another clinical investigation or participation within the
             last 6 months

          -  Known sensitivity/allergies to any of the test materials or any of their ingredients,
             such as bisphosphonate, titanium or human fibrinogen

          -  Significant current or past medical history of hepatic, renal, cardiac, pulmonary,
             digestive, haematological, neurological, or psychiatric disease, hypercalcaemia,
             previous or ongoing malignancy in the head and neck region or uncontrolled diabetes
             type I which in the opinion of the Investigator, would compromise the safety of the
             subject or affect the outcome of the investigation

          -  Pregnant and lactating females or those actively seeking to become pregnant in the
             next 3 months

          -  Previous (last 5 years) or on-going Bisphosphonate or Denosumab treatment

          -  Significant marginal bone loss prior to implant insertion requiring bone grafting or
             bone graft substitute

          -  Subject with extraction(s) performed in the position of implant placement within the
             last 2 months

          -  Subject with need of &gt;6 implants or a full bridge

          -  The final prosthetic construction in need of support from neighbouring teeth

          -  Known drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Subjects only needed implant(s) in the posterior mandible region
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christer Dahlin, DDS, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Käk kirurgiska kliniken NÄL, Trollhättan, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dingletandläkarna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dingle</city>
        <zip>45561</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Praktikertjänst AB Holmgatans Tandläkarmottagning</name>
      <address>
        <city>Falun</city>
        <zip>79171</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Käk-kirurgiska Kliniken, Näl</name>
      <address>
        <city>Trollhättan</city>
        <zip>46185</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Not planned at the moment</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

