<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03287765</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IND 123119, Protocol F</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03287765</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Relationship Between Tau PET Imaging and CSF Biomarkers of AD (Alzheimer Disease) in Humans</brief_title>
  <acronym>ADRC proj 1</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluating the Relationship Between Tau PET Imaging and CSF Biomarkers of AD in Humans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to evaluate a new radioactive compound used in positron
      emission tomography (PET) scans in identifying tau tangles (a certain protein that might be
      associated with Alzheimer's disease) in the brain, and if the amount of tau tangles in the
      brain has a relationship to cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) biomarkers and cognitive status.

      This study involves a PET scans using the radioactive compound, F 18 T807 for measurement of
      tau deposition. This radioactive compound is not approved by the United States Food and Drug
      Administration (FDA). An MRI will be conducted if one has not been completed completed within
      the past 12 months under a related research study. Participants will be asked about their
      medical history, family history, surgical history, and current medications. We will evaluate
      history of traumatic brain injury (TBI) using the Ohio State University Traumatic Brain
      Injury Identification (OSU TBI-ID) Method. This will take approximately 10 minutes.
      Participants will be asked to undergo a Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE), which will last
      approximately 5-10 minutes.

      Additionally, participants may be invited to undergo optional brain PET imaging with
      2-deoxy-2-[18F]fluoro-D-glucose fludeoxyglucose (18F-FDG), for measurement of the cerebral
      metabolic rate of glucose consumption. At the time of the initial T807-PET study,
      participants will be asked if they are willing to undergo repeat T807-PET imaging at least 2
      years after the initial study. This follow up study is optional, and participation in the
      study and initial T807-PET imaging will not be contingent on agreeing to the 2-year follow up
      study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine the association among T807-PET measures of PHF-tau.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize the amount and spatial distribution of T807-PET measures in healthy aging. preclinical AD, and early symptomatic AD.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize the amount and spatial distribution of T807-PET measures in preclinical AD.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize the amount and spatial distribution of T807-PET measures in early symptomatic AD.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine the association among T807-PET measures of concentrations of CSF biomarkers. and cognitive performance.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine the association among T807-PET measures of cognitive performance.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the change in T807-PET measures over time in asymptomatic amyloid-positive individuals and its association with changes in concentrations of CSF biomarkers.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental 18F-AV-1451</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>18F-AV-1451</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive a single intravenous bolus injection of approximately 6.5-10mCi (240-370MBq) of F 18 T807. For those who cannot tolerate the full exam, participants will receive single intravenous bolus injection of approximately 6.5-10mCi (240-370MBq) of F 18 T807.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental 18F-AV-1451</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Flortauapir</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female participants, at least 65 years of age.

          2. Participant is willing to undergo a lumbar puncture (LP) or has previously undergone
             LP. LP will be conducted under IRB ID 201109100 (PI: Anne Fagan).

          3. Participant is able and willing to undergo positron emission tomography (PET) and
             magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain.

          4. Pre-menopausal women must have a negative urine pregnancy test within 24 hours
             preceding T807 drug administration.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has any condition that, in the Investigator's opinion, could increase risk to the
             participant, limit the participant's ability to tolerate the experimental procedures,
             or interfere with the collection/analysis of the data (for example, participants with
             severe chronic back pain might not be able to lie still during the scanning
             procedures).

          2. Is deemed likely unable to perform the imaging procedures for any reason.

          3. Has a history of Torsades de Pointes or is taking medications known to prolong or may
             prolong QT interval (refer to study's list of restricted medications).

          4. Has known hypersensitivity to T807 or any of its excipients.

          5. Contraindications to PET, PET-CT or MR (e.g. electronic medical devices, inability to
             lie still for long periods) that make it unsafe for the individual to participate.

          6. Severe claustrophobia.

          7. Currently pregnant or breast-feeding. -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tammie Benzinger, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kelley Jackson, BA</last_name>
    <phone>314 362 6737</phone>
    <email>jacksonk@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Theresa Butler, RN</last_name>
    <phone>314-362-3613</phone>
    <email>butlert@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kelley Jackson</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-6737</phone>
      <email>jacksonk@wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 31, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 14, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tammie Benzinger</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Radiology &amp; Neurological Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Tauopathies</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>CNS Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>neurodegenerative disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The Investigators may share the participant's data with other researchers that may be doing research in areas similar to this research or in other unrelated areas. These researchers may be at Washington University, at other research centers and institutions, or industry sponsors of research. The Investigators may also share the research data with large data repositories (a repository is a database of information) for broad sharing with the research community. If the individual research data is placed in one of these repositories only qualified researchers will be able to look at the information.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

