<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03289819</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IFG-NIB-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-003102-14</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1188-3915</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03289819</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neoadjuvant Pembrolizumab(Pbr)/Nab-Paclitaxel Followed by Pbr/Epirubicin/Cyclophosphamide in TNBC</brief_title>
  <acronym>NIB</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II One-arm Open-label Neoadjuvant Study of Pembrolizumab in Combination With Nab-paclitaxel Followed by Pembrolizumab in Combination With Epirubicin and Cyclophosphamide in Patients With Triple Negative Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut fuer Frauengesundheit</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut fuer Frauengesundheit</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite its aggressiveness and high incidence, to date, no targeted therapies exist for the
      treatment of triple negative breast cancer (TNBC). Emerging evidence suggests a crucial role
      of tumor immunology on outcome for this entity. Checkpoint inhibitors like pembrolizumab,
      which target immune cells within the tumor, might therefore have an important impact on
      therapy response and outcome in these high risk patients. We propose a phase II study
      exploring pathological complete response and the safety of the combination of pembrolizumab
      and nab-paclitaxel as well as the combination of pembrolizumab with epirubicin and
      cyclophosphamide in the neoadjuvant setting for women with early TNBC. After completion of
      this study an extension will be determined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, phase II, one-arm, open-label neoadjuvant study of pembrolizumab in
      combination with nab-paclitaxel followed by pembrolizumab in combination with epirubicin and
      cyclophosphamide (E/C) in patients with TNBC. Pathological complete response rate at the time
      of surgery is the primary objective of this study.

      In approximately six large breast cancer centers in Germany 50 patients are planned to be
      enrolled. All patients will undergo state of the art staging and tumor assessments prior to
      study entry to assess eligibility for the present trial. Eligible and consented patients will
      receive 12 cycles of weekly nab-paclitaxel i.v. 125 mg/m² BSA q1w in combination with 4
      cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg q3w; followed by 4 cycles of epirubicin i.v. 90 mg/m² BSA
      and cyclophosphamide i.v. 600 mg/m² BSA, q3w in combination with 4 cycles pembrolizumab i.v.
      200 mg q3w. Clinical and bioptic tumor assessment will be performed after each treatment
      phase. Additional imaging, preferably with sonography, will be performed 6 weeks after
      initiation of taxane and anthracycline therapy to allow for early progress and response
      monitoring.

      Study treatment will be applied until state of the art surgery, onset of unacceptable
      toxicities, progression or withdrawal of consent. No follow-up is planned after definite
      surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathological Complete Response (pCR) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Pathological complete response will be assessed at final surgery for patients who received at least two cycles of Pembrolizumab. The rate will be assessed from 30 days until 120 days after last application of medication.</time_frame>
    <description>Pathological complete response (pCR) rate, defined as the complete absence of all tumor cells (ypT0/ypN0), absence of invasive tumor (ypT0/is ypN0) and regression grades after study treatment. Pathological complete response is the primary endpoint of this trial and correlates especially well with disease-free survival and overall survival in patients with TNBC. Pathological complete response also serves as a surrogate marker for prognosis in TNBC</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>The adverse events will be assessed from first infusion until 120 days after last application of medication.</time_frame>
    <description>The safety endpoints for the study will include rate of AE/SAEs and fatal SAEs, causality and outcome of AE/SAEs, rate of treatment discontinuations and reasons, changes in vital signs, laboratory values etc. Grading of AE/SAEs will be based on NCI CTCAE v4.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 weeks from date of first medication administration until the date of first documented progression, surgery or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 120 days after last dose.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of the treatment as measured by clinical response (objective response rate by 30 %) 6 weeks after the start of each sequential chemotherapy (nab-paclitaxel and E/C) and at the time of the surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EORTC QLQ-BR23</measure>
    <time_frame>Every two weeks from first administration of trial medication through study completion, up to 120 days after administration of last medication.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate changes in health related quality of life (QoL) assessments from baseline in all subjects using the EORTC Breast Cancer-Specific Quality of Life Questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-BR23)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EORTC QLQ-C30</measure>
    <time_frame>Every two weeks from first administration of trial medication through study completion, up to 120 days after administration of last medication.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate changes in health related quality of life (QoL) assessments from baseline in all subjects using Quality of Life Questionnaire Core 30 (EORTC QLQ-C30)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor infiltrating lymphocytes (TILs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from biomaterial collected at baseline, 12 weeks after treatment initiation and at surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor microenvironment prior to and during study treatment. TILs (stroma and intratumoral) in percent as assessed in Denkert et al. 2015, JCO.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Immunohistochemistry</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from biomaterial collected at baseline, 12 weeks after treatment initiation and at surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>PD1 (Programmed cell death protein 1), PD-L1 (Programmed death-ligand 1), SPARC (Secreted protein acidic and rich in cysteine), Caveolin-1, TIM-3 (T-cell immunoglobulin mucin-3), Lag-3 (Lymphocyte-activation gene 3) will be assessed via immunohistochemistry in percentage of stained cells to total cell count and assesment of immunoreactive score (IRS) for each marker.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from biomaterial collected at baseline, 12 weeks after treatment initiation and at surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor immunogenicity characteristic measured via FACS of the following markers (CD45, CD3, CD4, CD8, CD14, CD19, CD25, CD56, CD127, CD197, HLA-DR, CD45RA, Ki67) in percent of positive cells to total cell count.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mutational load</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from biomaterial collected at baseline, 12 weeks after treatment initiation and at surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Mutational load assessed by Next Generation Sequencing of Germline- and Tumor-DNA in mutations per megabases</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Neoepitope Detection</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from biomaterial collected at baseline, 12 weeks after treatment initiation and at surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Amount of tumor neoepitopes assessed by Next Generation Sequencing comparing Germline- and Tumor-DNA. Neoepitopes are defined as mutations that lead to aminoacid changes and are found in tumor DNA only.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cell-free RNA (cfRNA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from biomaterial collected at baseline, 12 weeks after treatment initiation and at surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Expression levels of specific tumor- and immune-related analytes in cfRNA will be measured by qPCR and possibly other methods and analyzed for correlations with subject outcomes.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Neoplasm of Breast</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab/Nab-Paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is a phase II, one-arm, open label neoadjuvant study of pembrolizumab in combination with nab-paclitaxel followed by pembrolizumab in combination with epirubicin and cyclophosphamide in patients with triple negative breast cancer.
All patients will receive 12 cycles of weekly nab-paclitaxel intravenous (i.v.) 125 mg/m² body surface area (BSA) in combination with 4 cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg q3w; followed by 4 cycles of epirubicin i.v. 90 mg/m² BSA and cyclophosphamide i.v. 600 mg/m² BSA, q3w in combination with 4 cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg/kg q3w.
Clinical and bioptic tumor assessment will be performed after each treatment phase. Study treatment will be applied until state of the art surgery, onset of unacceptable toxicities, progression or withdrawal of consent.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will receive 12 cycles of weekly nab-paclitaxel intravenous (i.v.) 125 mg/m² body surface area (BSA) in combination with 4 cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg q3w; followed by 4 cycles of epirubicin i.v. 90 mg/m² BSA and cyclophosphamide i.v. 600 mg/m² BSA, q3w in combination with 4 cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg/kg q3w.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab/Nab-Paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Keytruda</other_name>
    <other_name>MK-3475</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nab-paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will receive 12 cycles of weekly nab-paclitaxel intravenous (i.v.) 125 mg/m² body surface area (BSA) in combination with 4 cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg q3w; followed by 4 cycles of epirubicin i.v. 90 mg/m² BSA and cyclophosphamide i.v. 600 mg/m² BSA, q3w in combination with 4 cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg/kg q3w.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab/Nab-Paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>nano-particle albumin bound (NAB) paclitaxel</other_name>
    <other_name>Abraxane</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epirubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will receive 12 cycles of weekly nab-paclitaxel intravenous (i.v.) 125 mg/m² body surface area (BSA) in combination with 4 cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg q3w; followed by 4 cycles of epirubicin i.v. 90 mg/m² BSA and cyclophosphamide i.v. 600 mg/m² BSA, q3w in combination with 4 cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg/kg q3w.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab/Nab-Paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients will receive 12 cycles of weekly nab-paclitaxel intravenous (i.v.) 125 mg/m² body surface area (BSA) in combination with 4 cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg q3w; followed by 4 cycles of epirubicin i.v. 90 mg/m² BSA and cyclophosphamide i.v. 600 mg/m² BSA, q3w in combination with 4 cycles of pembrolizumab i.v. 200 mg/kg q3w.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab/Nab-Paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent prior to beginning of trial specific procedures.

          2. Subject must be female and aged ≥ 18 years on day of signing informed consent.

          3. ECOG(Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group) 0-1

          4. Histologically confirmed, early TNBC determined by core biopsy of breast tumor lesion.
             ER and PR negativity are defined as ≤ 1% of cells expressing hormonal receptors via
             IHC (immuno-histochemistry) analysis. HER2(human epidermal growth factor receptor 2)
             negativity is defined as either of the following by local laboratory assessment: In
             situ hybridization (ISH) non-amplified (ratio ≤ 2.2), or IHC 0 or IHC 1+.

          5. Measurable tumor lesion with a size of ≥ 1 cm assessed by sonography or magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI) within ≤ 21 days prior to entry. In case of inflammatory
             disease the extent of inflammation will be measured.

          6. Indication for chemotherapy.

          7. Multicentric and/or multifocal disease, as well as synchronous bilateral breast
             cancer, is eligible as long as one measurable lesion meets all inclusion criteria. The
             investigator has to determine which lesion will be used for tumor evaluation before
             initiation of treatment.

          8. Complete staging work up within 8 weeks prior to entry with no evidence of distant
             disease, including bilateral mammography, breast ultrasound, chest-X-ray (or chest
             CT-scan), liver ultrasound (or liver CT-scan or liver MRI) and bone scan.

          9. Subjects must provide a core biopsy from tumor lesion at 3 time points (before, after
             first phase of treatment and at surgery) for central confirmation of TNBC status and
             biomarker analyses.

         10. Adequate organ function, defined as:

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Concurrent participation in a study with an investigational agent/device or within 14
             days of study entry.

          2. Prior chemotherapy, radiation therapy or small molecule therapy for any reason.

          3. Previous malignant disease being disease-free for less than 3 years (except in situ
             carcinoma of the cervix and basal cell carcinoma of the skin).

          4. Pregnancy or lactation.

          5. Prior therapy with an anti-PD1, anti-PD L1, anti-PD-L2 agent or with an agent directed
             to another co-inhibitory T-cell receptor (e.g. CTLA-4, OX-40, CD137).

          6. Active infection requiring systemic therapy.

          7. History of (non-infectious) pneumonitis that required steroids or current pneumonitis.

          8. Active autoimmune disease or other diseases that requires systemic treatment with
             corticosteroids or immunosuppressive drugs (physiologic corticosteroid replacement
             therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency is allowed).

          9. History of primary or acquired immunodeficiency (including allogenic organ
             transplant).

         10. Active or prior documented inflammatory bowel disease (e.g., Crohn's disease,
             ulcerative colitis).

         11. Known history of following infections:

               1. Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

               2. History of acute or chronic Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C

               3. Has received a live-virus vaccination within 30 days of planned treatment start.
                  Seasonal flu vaccines that do not contain live virus are permitted

         12. Known congestive heart failure &gt;NYHA I (New York Heart Association) and/or coronary
             heart disease, angina pectoris, previous history of myocardial infarction,
             uncontrolled or poorly controlled arterial hypertension (e.g. blood pressure &gt;160/90
             mmHg under treatment with two or more antihypertensive drugs), rhythm disorders with
             clinically significant valvular heart disease.

         13. Preexisting motor or sensory neuropathy of a severity grade ≥2 by NCI CTCAE v4.0.

         14. Known, pathogenic BRCA (breast cancer susceptibility gene) mutation. Note: testing is
             not mandatory for trial participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter A Fasching, MD, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics, Erlangen University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Peter A Fasching, MD, Prof.</last_name>
    <phone>+49 9131 85</phone>
    <phone_ext>33508</phone_ext>
    <email>peter.fasching@uk-erlangen.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alexander Hein, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 9131 85</phone>
    <phone_ext>33553</phone_ext>
    <email>alexander.hein@uk-erlangen.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics, Erlangen University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Erlangen</city>
        <state>Bavaria</state>
        <zip>91054</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter A Fasching, MD, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+49 9131 85</phone>
      <phone_ext>33508</phone_ext>
      <email>peter.fasching@uk-erlangen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alexander Hein, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 9131 85</phone>
      <phone_ext>33553</phone_ext>
      <email>alexander.hein@uk-erlangen.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 21, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TNBC</keyword>
  <keyword>neoadjuvant chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>triple negative breast cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Triple Negative Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epirubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

