<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00775216</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>080811</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00775216</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Project Diabetes: Prescription for Healthy Living</brief_title>
  <official_title>Project Diabetes: Prescription for Healthy Living</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vanderbilt University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Health disparities related to obesity, pre-diabetes and Type 2 diabetes in the United States
      represent public health concerns. Given the benefit of exercise in disease prevention and
      management, evidence-based, cost-effective, brief interventions are needed to improve patient
      outcomes related to Type 2 diabetes and associated conditions. This novel behavioral
      intervention study connects individuals with resources within their community to affect
      change in their health and wellness. The aim is to connect disparate individuals to health
      and wellness resources to prevent the onset of diabetes. This will be accomplished through a
      collaborative effort with Vanderbilt Diabetes Center, Nashville Metro Parks and Recreation,
      and the Metro Public Health Department.

      A time series design will be used to assess the efficacy of physical activity counseling
      delivered by a health care professional, plus continued contact intervention delivered via a
      proactive and reactive health promotion counseling hotline that will leverage our partnership
      with Metro Parks versus counseling advice alone. In order to refine this intervention (Phase
      II) before it is executed, focus groups will first be conducted in Phase I with members of
      the target population in order to obtain feedback on the proposed intervention activities and
      materials. Qualitative findings and feasibility testing will be the basis for modifying the
      intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lifestyle changes, such as moderate physical activity (e.g. brisk walking) have been shown to
      delay or prevent the development of Type 2 diabetes in patients with obesity and
      pre-diabetes. Given the clear benefit of exercise in disease prevention and management,
      evidence-based cost-effective brief interventions are needed to improve patient outcomes
      related to Type 2 diabetes and associated health disparities.

      In America over the last two decades, adult obesity rates have doubled from 15% to 30%. In
      1990, no state had an obesity rate over 14%. In 2003, thirty-five states posted obesity rates
      of over 20%. Tennessee currently ranks fifth in the U.S. for highest rate of adult obesity.
      In 2003, direct medical costs associated with obesity totaled an estimated $1.84 billion in
      Tennessee. Medicare ($433 million) and Medicaid ($488 million) absorbed approximately 50% of
      these medical costs. Obesity is closely linked with such diseases as heart disease, stroke,
      diabetes, and certain cancers. In both East and South Nashville, cancer, heart disease, and
      stroke are listed as three of the top five causes of death with significant racial,
      educational, and economic disparities.

      Reducing socioeconomic and racial/ethnic disparities in Type 2 diabetes among adults will
      require multiple interventions society-wide in order to provide cumulative and synergistic
      effects that can result in sustained health practices and improved patient outcomes. One step
      in this approach is to encourage health care providers to deliver health promotion advice and
      counseling to their patients during routine office visits. Another is to link advice with
      readily available resources wherein an individual might be able to implement counsel.
      Therefore, the specific aim of this proposal is to evaluate the relative contribution of a
      multi-component, behavioral counseling intervention delivered by health care professionals
      versus the same behavioral counseling intervention when augmented by an interactive health
      promotion &quot;telephone helpline&quot; that will, among other things offer guidance on the
      availability of physical activity resources at Metro Parks facilities. In order to refine
      this intervention (Phase II) before it is executed, focus groups will first be conducted in
      Phase I with members of the target population in order to obtain feedback on the proposed
      intervention activities and materials. Qualitative findings and feasibility testing will be
      the basis for modifying the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    grant funding ended and lack of sufficient participants to complete trial
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome will be assessed by the short version of the International Physical Activity Questionnaire and the 6-minute Walk Test.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Questions regarding readiness to change, self-efficacy, knowledge of and access to physical activity centers, basic demographics, height/weight, and blood pressure will be assessed.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Exercise</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Behavioral Research</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard behavioral counseling</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Behavioral counseling intervention augmented with an interactive health promotion &quot;telephone helpline&quot;</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral counseling plus &quot;telephone helpline&quot;</intervention_name>
    <description>A trained behavioral counselor will place phone calls to Phase 2 intervention participants. These calls will be used to provide tailored physical activity advice and to extend our partnership with the Metro Nashville Parks and Recreation Department, directing participants to community centers close to their homes or workplaces where they can access a variety of physical activities (e.g., indoor pools, walking tracks, fitness centers, greenways, etc) using a newly developed electronic database. Following an orientation to the Metro Parks services which will be held at either Hadley Regional Park or Coleman Regional Park, participants will be directed to the Metro Parks facility most convenient to them.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18-75 years old

          -  Overweight (BMI greater than or equal to 25)

          -  Sedentary (self-report less than 30 minutes of moderate physical activity most days of
             the week)

          -  Has a family member (parent, grandparent, or sibling) with diabetes or pre-diabetes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants unable to engage in physical activity (oxygen dependent, wheel chair
             bound, amputations, Class 3 or 4 NY Heart Association classification for Congestive
             Heart Failure)

          -  Non-English speaking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bettina M. Beech, DrPH, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 7, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 17, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 20, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 25, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Bettina M. Beech, DrPH, MPH</name_title>
    <organization>Vanderbilt University</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

