<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00777296</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TR02-105</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00777296</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multidose Safety and Tolerability Study of Dose Escalation of Liposomal Amikacin for Inhalation (ARIKAYCE™)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1b/2a Multidose Safety and Tolerability Study of Dose Escalation of Liposomal Amikacin for Inhalation (ARIKAYCE™) In Cystic Fibrosis Patients With Chronic Infections Due To Pseudomonas Aeruginosa.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Insmed Incorporated</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Insmed Incorporated</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A major factor in the respiratory health of CF subjects is acquisition of chronic Pseudomonas
      aeruginosa infections. The infection rate with P. aeruginosa increases with age and by age 18
      years, 80% of CF subjects in the U.S. are infected. Liposomal Amikacin for Inhalation
      (Arikayce™) is a sterile aqueous liposomal suspension consisting of amikacin sulfate
      encapsulated in liposomes. This formulation of amikacin maximizes the achievable dose and
      delivery to the lungs of subjects infected via a nebulizer. Because liposome particles are
      small enough to penetrate and diffuse through sputum into the bacterial biofilm, they deposit
      drug in close proximity to the bacterial colonies (Meers, et al., 2008) (Clancy, et al.,
      2013), thus improving the bioavailability of amikacin at the infection site. The clinically
      achievable doses of amikacin in the LAI formulation can effectively increase the half-life of
      the drug in the lungs, and decrease the potential for systemic toxicity. LAI offers several
      advantages over current therapies in treating CF subjects with chronic infection caused by P.
      aeruginosa.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cystic fibrosis (CF) is a genetic disease resulting from mutations in a 230 kb gene on
      chromosome 7 known as the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR). Study
      subjects with CF manifest pathological changes in a variety of organs that express CFTR. The
      lungs are frequently affected, the sequelae being chronic infections and airway inflammation.
      The principal goal of treatment of subjects with CF is to slow the chronic deterioration of
      lung function.

      This is a Phase 2a study of safety, and tolerability of 28 days of daily dosing of two dose
      (280mg, and 560 mg) cohorts of Arikayce™ versus placebo. Study subjects will be randomized to
      receive either study drug or placebo (1.5% NaCl) by inhalation via a PARI eFlow nebulizer.
      Cohort 1 (280mg) will complete 28 days of daily dosing with Arikayce™ and 14 day post dosing
      safety evaluation by the Safety Committee (DSMB) before initiation of enrollment in Cohort 2
      (560mg). Cohort 2 will complete 28 days of daily dosing, and a 14 day post dosing safety
      assessment by the DSMB to evaluate safety data. All study patients will be followed for
      safety, pharmacokinetics, clinical and microbiologic activity for 28 days post completion of
      study treatment.

      The total study period will be up to 56 days, with screening visit occurring within the
      preceding 14 days prior to randomization. Patients will be clinically evaluated during the
      first 48 hours post-randomization, and weekly for the 28 days treatment period, and during
      the follow up visits at study days 35, 42, 49 and 56 days to determine safety, tolerability,
      pharmacokinetics (PK), and clinical, and microbiologic activity.

      Clinical laboratory parameters, audiology testing, clinical adverse events and pulmonary
      function will be evaluated for all study subjects in order to determine the qualitative and
      quantitative safety and tolerability of Arikayce™ compared to Placebo. Serum, urine, and
      sputum specimens will be collected at periodic intervals to assess PK. Additionally; sputum
      samples will be collected to determine changes in bacterial density. Pulmonary function
      testing and CFQ-R measurements will be assessed at selected time points throughout the study.

      DSMB has recommended the amendment of the main study to evaluate safety and efficacy of
      additional cycles of treatment with Arikayce™. All patients who were randomized in the main
      study, were compliant with the study protocol, and continue meeting study eligibility
      criteria can be consented to participate in the open-label extension to evaluate the safety,
      tolerability and efficacy of 560 mg once daily dose of Arikayce™ administered for six cycles
      over eighteen months. Each cycle will comprise of 28 days of treatment followed by 56 days
      off treatment. The total extension period will be up to 518 days (74 weeks, about 18 months).

      Clinical laboratory parameters, audiology testing, clinical adverse events and pulmonary
      function will be evaluated for all study subjects in order to determine the longer term
      safety, tolerability, and efficacy of Arikayce™. Serum specimens will be collected at
      periodic intervals to assess PK for safety. Additionally, sputum samples will be collected to
      determine changes in bacterial density. Pulmonary function testing and CFQ-R measurements
      will be assessed at selected time points throughout the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of nebulized Arikace™. Safety will be evaluated by changes in FEV1, SaO2, chemistry and hematology lab tests, vital signs, and clinical exam, assess treatment-emergent AEs.</measure>
    <time_frame>28 Days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess pharmacokinetics (PK) of Arikace™ in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>28 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess pharmacokinetics (PK) of Arikace™ in urine</measure>
    <time_frame>28 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate sputum amikacin levels</measure>
    <time_frame>28 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate change in Pulmonary function</measure>
    <time_frame>28 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate change in density of Pseudomonas aeruginosa in sputum</measure>
    <time_frame>28 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate time to and duration of systemic antipseudomonal rescue therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>28 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate change in CFQ-R measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>28 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 - 280 mg Arikayce</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this cohort will receive 280 mg of Arikayce</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 - Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm of cohort 1 will receive matching placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - 560 mg Arikayce</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this cohort will receive 560 mg of Arikayce</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this arm of cohort 2 will receive matching placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Arikayce™</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 - 280 mg Arikayce</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - 560 mg Arikayce</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 - Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent obtained from patient or designated legal guardian prior to
             the performance of any study related procedures.

          -  Male or female study subjects ≥6 years of age or older

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of CF

          -  History of chronic infection with P. aeruginosa

          -  Study subjects must produce a screening specimen that is positive for growth of P.
             aeruginosa

          -  FEV1 ≥ 40% predicted at Screening

          -  SaO2 ≥ 90% at Screening while breathing room air

          -  Ability to comply with study medication use, study visits and study procedures as
             judged by the investigator

          -  Ability to produce sputum or be willing to undergo an induction to produce sputum for
             clinical evaluation

          -  Clinically stable with no evidence of acute upper or lower respiratory tract infection
             of history of pulmonary exacerbation within 4 weeks prior to screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Administration of any investigational drug within 8 weeks prior to Screening

          -  Emergency room visit or hospitalization for CF or respiratory-related illness within 4
             weeks prior to screening

          -  History of alcohol, medication or illicit drug abuse within the 1 year prior to
             screening

          -  History of lung transplant

          -  Female of childbearing potential who is lactating or is not practicing an acceptable
             method of birth control (e.g., abstinence, hormonal or barrier methods, partner
             sterilization, or IUD)

          -  Positive pregnancy test

          -  Use of any anti-pseudomonal anitbiotics (IV antibiotics, all inhalation antibiotics,
             oral fluoroquinolones)within the 28 days prior to screening

          -  Initiation of chronic therapy (i.e. TOBI®, high-dose ibuprofen, rhDNase, macrolide
             antibiotics) within 28 days prior to screening

          -  History of sputum or throat swab culture yielding Burkholderia cepacia within 2 years
             of Screening

          -  History of mycobacterial or Aspergillus infection

          -  History of biliary cirrhosis with portal hypertension, or splenomegaly

          -  History of daily, continuous oxygen supplementation or requirement for more than 2
             L/min at night Change in chest x-ray at screening (or within the 3 months prior to
             screening)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gina Eagle, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Insmed Incorporated</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kaposvar</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Skopje</city>
        <country>Macedonia, The Former Yugoslav Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Rabka</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Warsaw</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Belgrade</city>
        <country>Serbia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Bratislava</city>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kosice</city>
        <country>Slovakia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Keiv</city>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kharkiv</city>
        <country>Ukraine</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Macedonia, The Former Yugoslav Republic of</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Serbia</country>
    <country>Slovakia</country>
    <country>Ukraine</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Bulgaria</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 15, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 21, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 22, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>November 17, 2016</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2016</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Estimate">November 18, 2016</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 17, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 17, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cystic Fibrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory Infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Cystic Fibrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>CFTR</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amikacin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

