<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00632398</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000587451</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>COLLINGE-06-200</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00632398</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multimedia Training for Family Caregivers in Use of Touch and Massage in Supportive Cancer Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Couples and Cancer: Building Partner Efficacy in Caring</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Collinge and Associates, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Collinge and Associates, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: A multimedia education program for family caregivers that teaches simple methods
      of touch and massage for the comfort of cancer patients at home may be effective in lowering
      stress, reducing symptoms, and improving quality of life for patients; and may improve
      caregiver satisfaction and self-efficacy.

      PURPOSE: This randomized phase II trial is studying how well multimedia instruction of
      caregivers in use of touch and massage works for cancer patients and their care partners.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  Produce a multimedia program to deliver instructional content in massage for cancer
           patients and their lay care partners.

        -  Determine the effects of the multimedia program on care partner esteem and stress and on
           the frequency and duration of the care partner's provision of their assigned form of
           support to the patient.

        -  Determine the effects of the multimedia program on patient symptom levels, functional
           quality of life, perceived stress, and physiologic indices of stress.

      Secondary

        -  Examine the impact of the multimedia program on care partner concerns about use of touch
           as a form of support, and on self-efficacy in massage.

      OUTLINE:

        -  Multimedia program production and screening (year 1): Patient/care partner dyads
           representative of a broad spectrum of relationships participate in filming a multimedia
           program about massage, acupressure, light touch, and massage safety precautions. The
           multimedia program is titled, &quot;Massage for People with Cancer: Simple Instruction for
           Family and Friends.&quot; The program comprises a menu-driven DVD which allows the viewer to
           select English or Spanish as well as individual chapters of content, and a manual keyed
           to the DVD content. A different set of diverse patient/care partner dyads screen and
           critique the multimedia program.

        -  Randomized controlled study of program's efficacy (year 2): Patient/care partner dyads
           who reside in the same home are recruited. Dyads within each race/ethnic group are
           stratified by patient total scores on the baseline FACT-G assessment. Dyads are then
           randomized to 1 of 2 arms.

             -  Arm I (experimental intervention): Dyads attend an orientation meeting with other
                dyads of their language group in order to meet the Oncology Massage Therapist (OMT)
                and research assistant (RA) assigned to them during the study; watch the DVD
                together and discuss it afterward; receive instructions for weekly data collection;
                and receive explanation about the safety monitoring home visit and the bi-weekly
                phone monitoring. Instructions for data collection include instructions for the
                care partner to fill out a sample of the weekly Study Report card. Dyads are given
                the DVD and manual to take home, and those who do not have a DVD player are
                provided one. Dyads complete at least one massage over at least 20 minutes once a
                week for 20 weeks in which they provide the techniques demonstrated in the film. An
                OMT makes a home visit to each dyad during the first 2 weeks, and then as needed,
                to monitor for understanding of and adherence to the relevant safety precautions
                for the given patient. Dyads receive bi-weekly telephone monitoring from an RA in
                order to encourage compliance with the weekly activity and monitor for any adverse
                events or safety concerns that warrant another home visit by the dyad's OMT (e.g.,
                changes in medical treatment that call for changes in precautions).

             -  Arm II (control intervention): For 4 weeks, care partners spend at least 20 minutes
                a week alone with the patient, reading to the patient from literature of interest
                to the patient. The literature may be fiction, non-fiction, or poetry that does not
                contain news or stressful subject matter. Dyads receive telephone monitoring from
                their RA within the first week and then every 2 weeks thereafter to encourage
                compliance, monitor for any adverse events or concerns, and respond to questions
                about the project. At the end of the 4 weeks, dyads attend an orientation meeting
                with the Principal Investigator, OMTs, and RAs. At this meeting, dyads view the
                multimedia program and discuss precautions and any other issues that may affect
                their utilization of the instruction. Dyads are then given the multimedia program
                to take home, and a DVD player if they need one. A home visit by an OMT is
                scheduled to assure the dyad understands and implements relevant safety
                precautions. The dyads then participate in the use of the intervention for the
                remaining 16 weeks of the study.

      All participants in the study complete quality of life, perceived stress, and other
      questionnaires at baseline and then at 4, 12, and 20 weeks. Demographic and patient medical
      information is also collected. Saliva samples are collected from patients at baseline and
      then at 4, 12, and 20 weeks to monitor cortisol and DHEA levels.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute effects of massage on patient symptoms as assessed by the weekly Study Report card</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Longitudinal effects of massage on patient symptoms as assessed by the weekly Study Report card</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency and duration of care partner providing the assigned form of support as assessed by the weekly Study Report card</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Care partner esteem as assessed by a 7-item esteem subscale of the Caregiver Reaction Assessment at baseline and then at 12 and 24 weeks</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient physiological stress measures as assessed by measuring diurnal variation in cortisol and DHEA at baseline and then at 12 and 24 weeks</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient and care partner perceived stress as assessed by the Perceived Stress Scale at baseline and then at 12 and 24 weeks</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient functional quality of life as assessed by FACT-G at baseline and then at 12 and 24 weeks</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Care partner self-efficacy and concerns about using touch as support as assessed by an investigator-generated survey at baseline and then at 12 and 24 weeks</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Care partner utilization of multimedia materials as assessed by the weekly Study Report card</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">228</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Attention control (reading)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Caregivers read to patients from literature of the patient's choice for recommended 20 minutes at least 3 times per week for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Touch, Caring and Cancer DVD program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Caregivers apply the instruction of the Touch, Caring and Cancer DVD program for patients for recommended 20 minutes at least 3 times per week for 4 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Attention control (reading)</intervention_name>
    <description>Caregivers read to the patient from literature of the patient's choice for recommended 20 minutes at least 3 times per week for 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Attention control (reading)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Touch, Caring and Cancer DVD program</intervention_name>
    <description>DVD- and manual-based instruction for caregivers and patients in the use of touch and massage techniques as supportive care in cancer, including: preparation for a session, safety precautions related to cancer and its treatments, communication about touch, centering to calm the mind; manual techniques for the head, neck, shoulders, back, feet and hands to promote relaxation; and acupressure for pain, nausea and anxiety.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Touch, Caring and Cancer DVD program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Cancer patient and their care partner with any of the following characteristics:

               -  African American

               -  Asian

               -  Hispanic or Latino

               -  Caucasian

               -  Intimate relationship

               -  Parent/adult child relationship

               -  Same-sex couple relationship

               -  Male or female

          -  Patient must have undergone conventional cancer treatment within the past 6 months

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Speaks, reads, and writes English, Spanish, or Chinese (care partner)

          -  Speaks, reads, and writes English, Spanish, or Chinese (patient)

          -  No contraindication, such as serious mental illness or physical inability, that would
             preclude study participation (patient or care partner)

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  See Disease Characteristics
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>120 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Collinge, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Collinge and Associates, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Collinge and Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kittery</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>03904</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Greater Boston Chinese Golden Age Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Latin American Health Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02116</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.collinge.org/COUPLES.html</url>
    <description>Web site for additional information</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collinge W, MacDonald G, Walton T. Massage in supportive cancer care. Semin Oncol Nurs. 2012 Feb;28(1):45-54. doi: 10.1016/j.soncn.2011.11.005. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22281309</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Collinge W, Kahn J, Walton T, Kozak L, Bauer-Wu S, Fletcher K, Yarnold P, Soltysik R. Touch, Caring, and Cancer: randomized controlled trial of a multimedia caregiver education program. Support Care Cancer. 2013 May;21(5):1405-14. doi: 10.1007/s00520-012-1682-6. Epub 2012 Dec 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23262808</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 7, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 10, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 12, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 12, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Collinge and Associates, Inc.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>William Collinge, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>President</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>massage</keyword>
  <keyword>oncology massage</keyword>
  <keyword>palliative care</keyword>
  <keyword>supportive care</keyword>
  <keyword>integrative oncology</keyword>
  <keyword>informal caregiving</keyword>
  <keyword>spouse caregiving</keyword>
  <keyword>family caregiving</keyword>
  <keyword>caregiver education</keyword>
  <keyword>psychosocial oncology</keyword>
  <keyword>caregiver stress</keyword>
  <keyword>coping with cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>end of life care</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

