<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00631332</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NO1-AG-9-2115</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00631332</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging</brief_title>
  <acronym>WHISCA</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Hormone Replacement Therapy on Cognitive Aging: Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging (WHISCA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging (WHISCA) is a two-armed, randomized,
      placebo controlled, clinical trial designed to assess the efficacy of postmenopausal hormone
      therapy (HT) on age related changes in specific cognitive functions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      WHISCA is an ancillary study to the Women's Health Initiative (WHI) and the WHI Memory Study
      (WHIMS) and has enrolled 2303 women aged 66 to 84 years who did not meet the criteria for
      dementia. WHISCA is investigating the effects of hormone therapy on rates of change over time
      in memory, other aspects of cognition (language, attention, spatial ability), motor function,
      and mood.

      Objectives

        -  Does HT protect against age-associated memory and cognitive longitudinal decline in
           women age 65 and older?

        -  What is the rate of change in memory and other cognitive abilities in women receiving HT
           compared to women receiving placebo?

        -  Does the addition of progesterone to HT modify the effects of estrogen on memory and
           other cognitive abilities?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine if HT protect against age-associated memory and cognitive longitudinal decline in women age 65 and older as measured over time by a series of cognitive tests administered annually.</measure>
    <time_frame>Annual assessment done annually.</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measures are the changes in scores from a standardized neuropsychological assessment will be conducted annually. The battery is comprised primarily of tests of memory, and includes the following tests in specified order: the Prospective Memory Tests, Primary Mental Abilities Vocabulary Test, the California Verbal Learning Test, the Benton Visual Retention Test, Card Rotations Test, the Finger Tapping Test, the Letter and Semantic Fluency Test and the Digit Span Test. In addition, the Positive and Negative Affect Scale and Geriatric Depression Scale will be administered.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the long-term effects of HT on changes in memory, other cognitive functions, and affect; and to investigate predictors of the transitions between normal aging and mild cognitive impairment and mild cognitive impairment and dementia.</measure>
    <time_frame>measured over life of the study</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary outcome measures will examine relative differences in measures between enrollment in WHIMS and the termination of the WHIMS E+P trial and E-Alone trial and also examine the relative differences in measures comparing periods of time for each woman when she reported taking HT versus times she reported not taking HT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2303</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A subset of women who were enrolled in the Women's Health Initiative Memory Study (WHIMS),
        who are at least 65 years old and not diagnosed with any type of dementia.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrolled in WHIMS

          -  At least 65 years old

          -  Not diagnosed with dementia

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women younger than 65 years of age

          -  Have dementia

          -  not enrolled in WHIMS
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sally Shumaker, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ammann EM, Pottala JV, Harris WS, Espeland MA, Wallace R, Denburg NL, Carnahan RM, Robinson JG. ω-3 fatty acids and domain-specific cognitive aging: secondary analyses of data from WHISCA. Neurology. 2013 Oct 22;81(17):1484-91. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3182a9584c. Epub 2013 Sep 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24068783</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goveas JS, Espeland MA, Hogan PE, Tindle HA, Shih RA, Kotchen JM, Robinson JG, Barnes DE, Resnick SM. Depressive Symptoms and Longitudinal Changes in Cognition: Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging. J Geriatr Psychiatry Neurol. 2014 Jun;27(2):94-102. doi: 10.1177/0891988714522697. Epub 2014 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>24584465</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Driscoll I, Espeland MA, Wassertheil-Smoller S, Gaussoin SA, Ding J, Granek IA, Ockene JK, Phillips LS, Yaffe K, Resnick SM; Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging. Weight change and cognitive function: findings from the Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2011 Aug;19(8):1595-600. doi: 10.1038/oby.2011.23. Epub 2011 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21394095</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Resnick SM, Coker LH, Maki PM, Rapp SR, Espeland MA, Shumaker SA. The Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging (WHISCA): a randomized clinical trial of the effects of hormone therapy on age-associated cognitive decline. Clin Trials. 2004;1(5):440-50.</citation>
    <PMID>16279282</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Espeland MA, Coker LH, Wallace R, Rapp SR, Resnick SM, Limacher M, Powell LH, Messina CR; Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging. Association between alcohol intake and domain-specific cognitive function in older women. Neuroepidemiology. 2006;27(1):1-12. Epub 2006 May 24.</citation>
    <PMID>16717476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Resnick SM, Maki PM, Rapp SR, Espeland MA, Brunner R, Coker LH, Granek IA, Hogan P, Ockene JK, Shumaker SA; Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging Investigators. Effects of combination estrogen plus progestin hormone treatment on cognition and affect. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2006 May;91(5):1802-10. Epub 2006 Mar 7.</citation>
    <PMID>16522699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Resnick SM, Espeland MA, An Y, Maki PM, Coker LH, Jackson R, Stefanick ML, Wallace R, Rapp SR; Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging Investigators. Effects of conjugated equine estrogens on cognition and affect in postmenopausal women with prior hysterectomy. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2009 Nov;94(11):4152-61. doi: 10.1210/jc.2009-1340. Epub 2009 Oct 22.</citation>
    <PMID>19850684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Espeland MA, Miller ME, Goveas JS, Hogan PE, Coker LH, Williamson J, Naughton M, Resnick SM; Whisca Study Group. Cognitive function and fine motor speed in older women with diabetes mellitus: results from the women's health initiative study of cognitive aging. J Womens Health (Larchmt). 2011 Oct;20(10):1435-43. doi: 10.1089/jwh.2011.2812. Epub 2011 Aug 5.</citation>
    <PMID>21819251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Espeland MA, Brunner RL, Hogan PE, Rapp SR, Coker LH, Legault C, Granek I, Resnick SM; Women's Health Initiative Study of Cognitive Aging Study Group. Long-term effects of conjugated equine estrogen therapies on domain-specific cognitive function: results from the Women's Health Initiative study of cognitive aging extension. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2010 Jul;58(7):1263-71. doi: 10.1111/j.1532-5415.2010.02953.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20649689</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 7, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>women, dementia, cognition.</keyword>
  <keyword>non-demented women at least age 65</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>WHISCA will follow guidelines, methods and processes as set forth in the WHI 2015-2020 Data Sharing Plan. Accompanying the limited data sets, substantial electronic documentation will be provided in a standard format that is readable on a variety of platforms. Documentation will include data collection forms, a description of study protocol and procedures, description of all variable re-coding and a list of major study publications. These data will be available to users only under a data-sharing agreement that provides for: a commitment to using the data only for research purposes and not to identify any individual participant; a commitment to securing the data using appropriate computer technology; and a commitment to destroying or returning the data after analyses are completed. Data will be made available for timely release no later than the acceptance for publication of the main findings from the final dataset.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

