<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00639210</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Protocol number FBCSG-01-2004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00639210</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BREAST CANCER AND EXERCISE</brief_title>
  <acronym>BREX</acronym>
  <official_title>BREAST CANCER AND EXERCISE BREX: A Multicenter Phase III Open Randomised Trial of the Efficacy of Exercise in the Prevention of Long-Term Adverse Effects of Adjuvant Treatments and Breast Cancer Recurrences in Women With Primary Breast Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Finnish Breast Cancer Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Finnish Breast Cancer Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Finnish Breast Cancer Group Study (BREX 01-2004). A multicenter phase III open randomised
      trial of the efficacy of exercise in the prevention of long-term adverse effects of adjuvant
      treatments and breast cancer recurrences in women with primary breast cancer. The aim of the
      study is to investigate whether regular exercise training could reduce the long-term side
      effects of adjuvant treatments of primary breast cancer and improve quality of life and well
      being.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A multicenter phase III open randomised trial of the efficacy of exercise in the prevention
      of long-term adverse effects of adjuvant treatments and breast cancer recurrences in women
      with primary breast cancer. The aim of the study is to investigate whether regular exercise
      training could reduce the long-term side effects of adjuvant treatments of primary breast
      cancer and improve quality of life and well being. Large controlled prospective studies are
      needed to confirm the preliminary findings of exercises benefits in cancer patients, and to
      investigate the type, the frequency, intensity and tolerability of exercise training in
      cancer patients, before any clinical recommendations can be given. Prevention of
      osteoporosis, improvement of weight control, and muscular and cardiovascular fitness is been
      waited. The second aim of the study is to investigate, whether regular exercise training
      reduces the risk of breast cancer recurrence, prevents other diseases and reduce all-cause
      mortality and is cost effective in women with primary breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The aim of the study is to investigate whether regular exercise after adjuvant treatments of breast cancer could prevent osteoporosis and improve quality of life.</measure>
    <time_frame>1-10 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fitness and weight control, number of falls and fractures, breast cancer recurrence.</measure>
    <time_frame>1-10 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">573</enrollment>
  <condition>Prevent Osteoporosis and Osteoporotic Fractures</condition>
  <condition>Improve Quality of Life</condition>
  <condition>Improve Weight Control, and Muscular and Cardiovascular Fitness</condition>
  <condition>Help the Patients to Return to Working Life</condition>
  <condition>Reduce the Risk of Breast Cancer Recurrence</condition>
  <condition>Prevent Other Diseases and Reduce All-Cause Mortality in Patients With Primary Breast Cancer.</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Supervised training is organised for the exercise group once a week in groups of 10 to 15 subjects. The training is guided by an experienced physical therapist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>supervised training</intervention_name>
    <description>Design: supervised training is organised for the exercise group once a week in groups of 10 to 15 subjects. The training is guided by an experienced physical therapist.Content: The supervised training of the exercise group consists of two different classes alternating at four week periods; step aerobics class and circuit training class. The 60-minute aerobics and circuit training classes also include warming-up and cooling-down periods both lasting 10-15 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: Histologically proven invasive breast cancer T1-4N0-3M0, pre- or
        postmenopausal breast cancer patient treated with adjuvant chemotherapy or radiotherapy
        within 4 months or patient who has started adjuvant endocrine therapy (antiestrogens,
        aromatase inhibitors, LHRH agonists, or combinations) no later than 4 months earlier,age
        from 35 to 68 years,signed informed consent prior to beginning protocol specific procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior malignancy except basal cell carcinoma or in situ cervix carcinoma

          -  Male gender

          -  Haematogenous metastases (M1)

          -  No systemic adjuvant therapy

          -  Postmenopausal women treated with antiestrogens, tamoxifen or toremifene, adjuvant
             treatment only (+/- radiotherapy)

          -  Pregnancy or recent lactation (&lt; 1 year)

          -  Severe cardiac disease (New York Heart Association class III or greater), myocardial
             infarction within 12 months, uncontrolled hypertension

          -  Verified osteoporosis (proximal femur or lumbar spine t-score &lt; -2.5 or fracture
             without trauma)

          -  Concomitant medications affecting calcium and bone metabolism such as bisphosphonates,
             calcitonin, PTH, SERMs, oral corticosteroids (over 6 months), anticonvulsants
             (fenytoin, carbamazepine) and prolonged heparin therapy

          -  Other diseases affecting calcium and bone metabolism such as hyperthyroidism, newly
             diagnosed hypothyroidism, primary hyperparathyroidism, renal failure, chronic hepatic
             diseases, organ transplant, Cushing's syndrome, rheumatoid arthritis, chronic bowel
             diseases such as celiac disease, Chron disease or history of total ventricular
             resection

          -  Other serious illness or medical condition, which could be contraindication for
             exercise

          -  Patients not capable of training (severe knee arthrosis, severe ligamental or
             cartilage injuries at lower extremities)

          -  Residence more than one hour from the exercise centre

          -  Competitive athlete
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>68 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tiina Saarto, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Helsinki University Central Hospital, Department of Oncology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Helsinki University Central Hospital, Department of Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <zip>00029</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 20, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 20, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Riikka Huovinen</name_title>
    <organization>Finnish Brest Cancer Group</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>osteoporosis</keyword>
  <keyword>fracture</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Recurrence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoporotic Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

