<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00634556</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>05-0832</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01MH073856-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00634556</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dopaminergic Effects on Cortical Function in Tourette's (Levodopa Protocol)</brief_title>
  <acronym>TSfMRI</acronym>
  <official_title>Dopaminergic Effects on Cortical Function in Tourette's (Levodopa Protocol)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dr. Kevin J. Black at Washington University is conducting a study to learn whether we can use
      MRI scans to test dopamine function in the brain and to determine whether the brain performs
      memory tasks differently in Tourette Syndrome (TS). TS is a movement disorder characterized
      by vocal tics (sounds) and motor tics (movements). We will measure how and where brain
      activity changes using magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans during memory tasks and after
      taking levodopa. Levodopa is a drug commonly used for the treatment of Parkinson's disease
      (PD), a very different movement disorder.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Clinical observations suggest that in TS there is abnormal function in the brain's motor
      system that can be modified by manipulating dopamine. My colleagues and I have hypothesized
      that nonmotor brain systems may also show dopamine-sensitive functional abnormalities.
      Recently we tested this hypothesis using functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). A
      cognitive task involving working memory (WM) produced excessive activation of several brain
      regions in TS subjects compared to controls, but this excessive activation normalized after
      administering the dopamine precursor levodopa (Hershey et al, 2004).

      We can state the following focused hypotheses and corresponding specific aims:

      (1) In TS, normal performance during a working memory (WM) task requires greater activation
      of specific brain regions (parietal cortex, medial frontal cortex and thalamus) than in
      control subjects, and this excess fMRI response is reduced (improved) by exogenous levodopa.
      (2) These fMRI results in TS relate specifically to WM, to TS, and to dopamine receptor
      activation, rather than to non-WM components of the cognitive task, comorbidity, placebo
      effects, or other confounds.

      Specific Aim 1. Test whether the preliminary fMRI results generalize to a larger and more
      representative sample of adults with TS.

      Specific Aim 2. Clarify the variables that interact to produce the differential fMRI
      responses to a WM task and levodopa observed in TS subjects vs controls.

      2a. Task components. Control for non-WM components of the task and delineate a
      &quot;dose-response&quot; curve for effects of WM load on fMRI responses.

      2b. Clinical variables. Test whether the fMRI results in our preliminary data are associated
      with TS itself rather than with comorbid conditions, treatment history, demographic
      variables, or state variables such as current tic severity / tic suppression.

      2c. Pharmacology. Test whether the post-levodopa changes in WM-related fMRI signal relate
      specifically to levodopa plasma concentration (rather than practice effects, placebo effects,
      or passage of time) and are replicated by a nonselective dopamine receptor agonist or by a
      dopamine D2/D3/D4 agonist.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>BOLD (blood oxygen-level dependent) fMRI (functional magnetic resonance imaging) response to a working memory task</measure>
    <time_frame>From about 30 to 120 minutes after infusion begins</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>serum prolactin concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>approximately 2 hours after infusion begins</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">49</enrollment>
  <condition>Tourette Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>levodopa solution 2mg/ml for i.v. use</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>levodopa solution in saline, given intravenously, dosed as per &quot;final protocol&quot; in Black et al 2003.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>normal saline i.v.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>levodopa solution 2mg/ml for i.v. use</intervention_name>
    <description>2mg/mL in normal saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>levodopa solution 2mg/ml for i.v. use</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>L-DOPA</other_name>
    <other_name>L-3,4-dihydroxyphenylalanine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>normal saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NaCl 0.9% in water</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-55.

          -  Tic subjects must meet DSM-IV-TR criteria for a chronic tic disorder.

          -  Controls are matched for age (within 4 years), sex, handedness (right-handed,
             non-right-handed), and education (within 2 years), and if possible for race and
             ethnicity

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to give competent informed consent.

          -  Lactation, pregnancy or possibility of pregnancy.

          -  Contraindication to MRI (pacemaker; nontrivial metallic foreign bodies; significant
             claustrophobia).

          -  Contraindication to levodopa or carbidopa (known allergy).

          -  Significant neurological disease (not counting the tic disorder).

          -  Current renal, cardiac or hepatic disease that would make study participation less
             safe.

          -  Head injury with loss of consciousness for more than 5 minutes or with neurological
             sequelae.

          -  Lifetime history of serious lifetime psychopathology or substance abuse. (Specific
             exclusions are: lifetime diagnosis of mental retardation, autism, psychosis, mania,
             somatization disorder, panic disorder, social phobia [excludes symptoms present only
             when treated with a neuroleptic], anorexia nervosa or bulimia, drug or alcohol
             dependence, antisocial personality disorder, or dementia, or current major
             depression.)

          -  Depot neuroleptics in the past 6 months.

          -  Other antipsychotics within the past 2 weeks.

          -  Behavioral therapy for Tics of OCD sx in the past 2 weeks.

          -  For one half of the subjects in each diagnostic group: any brain-active medications
             within the past 2 weeks. For the remaining subjects: neuroactive medications in the
             past 2 weeks other than SSRIs, alpha-2 agonists, norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors,
             or clonazepam.

          -  Additional exclusions for controls: No history of tic disorder, OCD or ADHD. If under
             age 25, no first-degree relative with a tic disorder. No exposure to neuroleptics in
             the past year and none ever for a period exceeding a week.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin J Black, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington Universisty School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington Universisty School of Medicine,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nil.wustl.edu/labs/kevin/studies/TS-dopa-fMRI-NIMH.htm</url>
    <description>study description</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nil.wustl.edu/labs/kevin/move/ts.htm</url>
    <description>Tourette syndrome resources</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hershey T, Black KJ, Hartlein JM, Barch DM, Braver TS, Carl JL, Perlmutter JS. Cognitive-pharmacologic functional magnetic resonance imaging in tourette syndrome: a pilot study. Biol Psychiatry. 2004 May 1;55(9):916-25.</citation>
    <PMID>15110735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Black KJ, Carl JL, Hartlein JM, Warren SL, Hershey T, Perlmutter JS. Rapid intravenous loading of levodopa for human research: clinical results. J Neurosci Methods. 2003 Jul 15;127(1):19-29.</citation>
    <PMID>12865145</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Campbell M, Koller J, Shipley E, Creech M, Hershey T, Black K. Dopaminergic modulation of working memory in Tourette's syndrome [abstract]. J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci 20(2):232, 2008. http://neuro.psychiatryonline.org/article.aspx?articleid=103362</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Black KJ, Campbell MC, Koller JM, Schneider B, Hershey T. Dopaminergic modulation of working-memory-related cortical activity in Tourette syndrome. Annual meeting, Society for Neuroscience, Chicago, 20 Oct 2009. http://www.sfn.org/</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Siddiqi SH, Creech ML, Black KJ. Orthostatic stability with intravenous levodopa. PeerJ. 2015 Aug 27;3:e1198. doi: 10.7717/peerj.1198. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26336641</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 13, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tourette Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <keyword>levodopa</keyword>
  <keyword>working memory</keyword>
  <keyword>dopamine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tourette Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levodopa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dopamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dopamine Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dihydroxyphenylalanine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dopamine Agonists</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Vital signs IPD are shared at: Siddiqi SH, Creech ML, Black KJ. Orthostatic stability with intravenous levodopa. PeerJ. 2015 Aug 27;3:e1198. doi: 10.7717/peerj.1198. eCollection 2015. PubMed ID: 26336641 There is no plan to share other IPD.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

