<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00631176</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2006-8-4931</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5U18HS016678-02</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00631176</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>&quot;Just-In-Time Training&quot; in Pediatric Airway Management</brief_title>
  <acronym>JIT</acronym>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of &quot;Just-In-Time&quot; Training With/Without a High Fidelity Simulation on Patient Safety in Airway Management in Pediatric Intensive Care Unit</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective interventional study to test the hypothesis that just-in-time training
      for pediatric airway management may improve patient safety and operational performance of
      orotracheal intubation and decreases intubation associated events in pediatric residents in
      the PICU. To test the hypothesis that high fidelity simulation may enhance the training
      efficacy and patient safety in simulation settings.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Appropriate airway management is the most critical point in pediatric resuscitation and
      pediatric critical care. It remains, however, a challenge for pediatric residents to learn
      and retain this critical skill. Recent report from our PICU showed pediatric residents
      participated only 28% of initial orotracheal intubation, and the rate of the first successful
      endotracheal tube placement was only 38% of all orotracheal intubation attempt. Repetitive
      poor-skilled intubation attempts may be associated with complication such as dental or
      laryngeal contusion, and prolonged intubation attempt may be associated with hypoxia and
      hemodynamic instability. In order to improve the operational performance in the efficacy
      (first attempt success rate) and safety (minimizing the associated events which could
      potentially lead to adverse events), a better training method is warranted.

      Objectives:

      To test the hypothesis that just-in-time training for pediatric airway management may improve
      patient safety and operational performance of orotracheal intubation and decreases intubation
      associated events in pediatric residents in the PICU. To test the hypothesis that high
      fidelity simulation may enhance the training efficacy and patient safety in simulation
      settings.

      Study Design:

      This is a prospective interventional study. During the eighteen months of study period, one
      of two on-call pediatric residents from 7 south PICU (24 beds) will receive 20 minutes of
      just-in-time pediatric airway management training. This training will occur before their
      shift starts before the morning round. This training will cover direct laryngoscopy
      technique, orotracheal intubation technique, confirmation of the tube placement and
      recognition of associated events. This training will be done with or without high fidelity
      simulation function. We will use SimBaby (Laerdal, Norway). The assignment will be
      randomized. The clinical data of orotracheal intubation are collected through NEAR-4 KIDS
      registry. Primary outcome is a change in a first attempt success rate by the residents in an
      overtrained group (7 South PICU) compared to standard training group (7 East PICU). The
      secondary outcome is the rate of resident participation in orotracheal intubation attempt,
      the number of intubation attempt before successful intubation by residents and the number of
      intubation associated events. The videotaped performance during the training is analyzed with
      Healthcare Failure Mode and Effect Analysis (HFMEA) and will be compared between high
      fidelity simulation training group and low fidelity simulation training group. The evaluation
      system developed by HFMEA will be validated by a performance of experienced and
      non-experienced intubators. Furthermore, the real orotracheal intubation team performance in
      both PICUs will be evaluated with scale by a research assistant. The demographic and training
      data of participants of real PICU intubations will be collected. No patient identifiable
      information will be collected. This data will also be kept in a password-protected research
      computer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoint will be the success of first intubation attempts by a resident.</measure>
    <time_frame>per case</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Orotracheal Intubation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Just-In-Time Training</intervention_name>
    <description>On-call pediatric residents from 7 south PICU (24 beds) will receive 20 minutes of just-in-time pediatric airway management training. This training will occur before their shift starts before the morning round. This training will cover direct laryngoscopy technique, orotracheal intubation technique, confirmation of the tube placement and recognition of associated events. This training will be done with or without high fidelity simulation function.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Over training</other_name>
    <other_name>Intubation training</other_name>
    <other_name>Rapid Refresher</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pediatric or Emergency Medicine Residents rotating through PICU in CHOP.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Anesthesiology residents

          2. Residents who had formal US training (ACGME accredited) in Neonatology or Pediatric
             Critical Care Medicine, Critical Care Medicine or Anesthesiology.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vinay Nadkarni, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 7, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 8, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Vinay Nadkarni, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>oral intubation</keyword>
  <keyword>just in time</keyword>
  <keyword>simulation education</keyword>
  <keyword>high fidelity training</keyword>
  <keyword>intubation training</keyword>
  <keyword>intubation success</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

