<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00639548</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KIM-NMP4</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00639548</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ERPS, BIS and Entropy for Neuromonitoring in ICU Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Auditory Event-Related Potentials, BIS-Index and Entropy for the Discrimination of Different Levels of Sedation in the ICU Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GE Healthcare</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Most critically ill patients receive sedative and analgesic drugs to attenuate discomfort and
      pain. The excessive use of sedatives and analgesics has undesirable effects for patients.
      Whereas undersedation is mostly easy to identify, oversedation with its associated problems
      is more difficult to recognize. Stopping sedation daily helps to avoid gross oversedation,
      but this is not always possible. Monitoring the depth of sedation is difficult and is
      currently based on clinical assessment and the use of clinical scoring systems. These scoring
      systems cannot be applied continuously, they are subjective and the level of consciousness
      can be altered when sedation is assessed.

      Several methods based on the electroencephalogram have been tested to avoid these problems,
      but the results have been disappointing so far, so the BIS Monitor an dthe Entropy monitor.We
      have previously shown that the time-locked cortical response to standard external stimuli
      (long-latency auditory evoked potentials or event-related potentials; ERPs) can discriminate
      between clinically relevant light to moderate and deep sedation levels in healthy volunteers,
      when sedation is induced with a combination of propofol or midazolam with remifentanil.

      We therefore hypothesized that ERPs may be used to monitor the depth of sedation in ICU
      patients as well. As the first step to test this hypothesis, we evaluated the use of ERPs to
      assess the level of sedation in patients undergoing elective major surgery and admitted to
      the ICU for short term postoperative mechanical ventilation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Most critically ill patients receive sedative and analgesic drugs to attenuate discomfort and
      pain. The excessive use of sedatives and analgesics prolongs time on mechanical ventilation,
      the incidence of nosocomial pneumonia, time spent in the intensive care unit, and increases
      costs. Strategies to reduce the use of sedatives and analgesics may improve the outcome.
      Whereas undersedation is mostly easy to identify, oversedation with its associated problems
      is more difficult to recognize, but should be avoided. While stopping sedation daily helps to
      avoid gross oversedation, this is not always possible, e.g. due to unstable condition of the
      patient. Also, accumulation of sedatives and analgesics may occur rapidly, especially in
      patients with renal and/or liver dysfunction. Monitoring the depth of sedation is difficult
      and is currently based on clinical assessment and the use of clinical scoring systems. These
      scoring systems cannot be applied continuously, they are subjective and the level of
      consciousness can be altered when sedation is assessed.

      Several methods based on the electroencephalogram have been tested to avoid these problems,
      but the results have been disappointing so far. A relatively new method of processed EEG is
      Entropy®. Entropy is a non-linear statistic parameter which describes the order of random
      repetitive signals. In patients it translates the anesthesia-induced &quot;calmer&quot;, more
      synchronized EEG into a single parameter. Spectral entropy can reproducibly indicate the
      hypnotic effects of propofol, thiopental and different anesthetic gases. The most popular
      method of processed EEG for assessment of sedation is the bispectral index (BIS-Index®).
      While BIS has been tested and validated for the use in the operation room with different
      anesthetics, data on its use in the ICU setting at less deep levels of sedation are
      controversial. The multiple concomitant medications and heterogeneity of underlying
      pathologies present a further challenge to the use of neuromonitoring in the ICU.

      We have previously shown that the time-locked cortical response to standard external stimuli
      (long-latency auditory evoked potentials or event-related potentials; ERPs) can discriminate
      between clinically relevant light to moderate and deep sedation levels in healthy volunteers,
      when sedation is induced with a combination of propofol or midazolam with remifentanil.

      We therefore hypothesized that ERPs may be used to monitor the depth of sedation in ICU
      patients as well. As the first step to test this hypothesis, we evaluated the use of ERPs to
      assess the level of sedation in patients undergoing elective major surgery and admitted to
      the ICU for short term postoperative mechanical ventilation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Event related Potentials (Amplitudes, latencies) at different clinically relevant sedation levels</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative awakening</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BIS-Index at different clinically relevant sedation levels</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative awaakening</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Entropy at different clinically relevant sedation levels</measure>
    <time_frame>postoperative awakening</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Deep Sedation</condition>
  <condition>Electroencephalography</condition>
  <condition>Event-Related Potentials</condition>
  <condition>Evoked Potentials, Auditory</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients required an elective thoracic surgical intervention under general anesthesia and
        who were scheduled to the ICU for postoperative care
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 Years or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  ASA class III or higher history of adverse events during former surgery or anesthesia,
             neurological impairment in the medical history hearing abnormalities.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Departement of Intensive Care Medicine - University Hospital Bern - Inselspital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haenggi M, Ypparila H, Hauser K, Caviezel C, Korhonen I, Takala J, Jakob SM. The effects of dexmedetomidine/remifentanil and midazolam/remifentanil on auditory-evoked potentials and electroencephalogram at light-to-moderate sedation levels in healthy subjects. Anesth Analg. 2006 Nov;103(5):1163-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17056949</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haenggi M, Ypparila H, Takala J, Korhonen I, Luginbühl M, Petersen-Felix S, Jakob SM. Measuring depth of sedation with auditory evoked potentials during controlled infusion of propofol and remifentanil in healthy volunteers. Anesth Analg. 2004 Dec;99(6):1728-36, table of contents.</citation>
    <PMID>15562062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 20, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 20, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Haenggi Matthias</name_title>
    <organization>Department of Intensive Care Medicine - Inselspital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Deep Sedation</keyword>
  <keyword>EEG</keyword>
  <keyword>Event-Related Potentials</keyword>
  <keyword>Evoked potentials, auditory</keyword>
  <keyword>BIS-Index</keyword>
  <keyword>Entropy</keyword>
  <keyword>ICU</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

