<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00633958</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DFCI 05-303</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00633958</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Study of 18F-FLT in Pediatric Patients With Central Nervous System (CNS) Tumors</brief_title>
  <acronym>FLT</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pilot, Non-Therapeutic NeuroImaging Study of 18F-FLT in Pediatric Patients With Newly Diagnosed Central Nervous System Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In spite of numerous advances in neuroimaging techniques, the diagnosis of pediatric brain
      tumors relies on the pathologic evaluation of material obtained at the time of the initial
      operation. While 18F-FDG-positron emission tomography (PET) helps identify higher-grade
      lesions due to their increased glucose metabolism, the high tracer uptake of the normal
      adjacent brains makes this modality of limited value. Fluorine-18 fluorothymidine (FLT) is a
      new imaging agent that has two significant advantages in the imaging of CNS tumors. First,
      this agent detects cellular proliferation directly, and second, the normal brain does not
      take up the agent, making a positive area(s) easy to identify. Before embarking on a large
      pediatric disease stratified assessment of FLT imaging in pediatric neurooncology patients,
      the investigators are proposing a limited patient pilot study to evaluate the
      biodistribution, dosimetry and specificity of this compound when compared to
      immunohistochemical assessment of mitotic activity in newly diagnosed patients undergoing
      surgical resection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients will undergo standard pre-diagnostic imaging of the sites of disease using standard
      MRI techniques. If disease is suspected in both the brain and spine, then both imaging
      modalities should be obtained. This imaging should be obtained no more than 21 days before
      surgical resection. As close as possible to the completion of the MRI scans, patients will
      undergo 18F-FLT imaging using a single administration of tracer, and PET image acquisition at
      four different time points (baseline, 1 hr post injection, 2 hrs post injection and 4-6 hours
      post injection). A whole body PET scan (top of the head to mid thigh) will be performed
      immediately after injection (PET acquisition #1). These data will be acquired with a 2 minute
      emission and a 2 minute transmission scan at each bed position. Following this acquisition,
      the subject will empty his or her bladder. At 45 minutes post-injection, a brain and/or spine
      (body) PET scan will be acquired with a 10 min emission scan and a 5 min transmission scan
      (PET acquisition #2). This scan will include all areas of suspected tumor (brain, spine, or
      brain and spine). Following PET acquisition #2, a whole body PET scan will be acquired
      according to the same protocol as above (PET acquisition #3). If possible, a final whole body
      scan will be acquired 4-6 h post-injection (PET acquisition #4). All PET acquisitions will be
      acquired in 3D mode and reconstructed with the FORE re-binned OSEM algorithm with measured
      attenuation correction. Blood samples will be obtained at the completion of each whole body
      scan. Patients will receive the dose of 18F-FLT through a fresh intravenous catheter as per
      standard PET procedures. Patients will then undergo maximal surgical resection. Pieces from
      different areas of the tumor will be marked for correlation to imaging studies when possible.
      Tumor samples will undergo standard immunohistochemical analysis for cellular activation
      including mitotic index and MIB-1 proliferation staining.

      Serial blood draws will also be obtained at four different time points (baseline, 1 hr post
      injection, 2 hrs post injection, and 4-6 hours post injection) to evaluate clearance of
      18F-FLT from the blood.

      For the biodistribution, the 3D regions of interest (ROIs) will be drawn about each major
      organ that is identified on the whole body scans. This will be performed on each of the whole
      body scans and a time activity curve will be generated. The residence time for each organ
      will be determined. The blood data will be pipetted and counted for estimates of activity in
      the blood and bone marrow. For the brain and/or spine images, the PET data will be registered
      to the subjects' MRI. The PET scan will be graded on a subjective 4-point scale. 3D ROIs will
      be drawn around the tumor. In addition, an analogous ROI will be drawn in normal brain
      background and about the whole brain for comparison. For the tumor, tumor-to-background,
      tumor-to-whole brain ratios will be determined. In addition, standard uptake values (SUVs)
      will be determined for the tumor and background.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Large phase II opened to accue same patients
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>March 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the distribution, localization and kinetics of localization of 18F-FLT in pediatric patients with central nervous system tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed shortly after subjects undergo neuroimaging</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To correlate the activity of administering 18F-FLT in newly diagnosed pediatric brain tumor patients to standard immunohistochemical markers of cellular activation and MRI imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed shortly after subjects undergo neuroimaging</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Tumors of the Central Nervous System</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>18F-FLT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects will receive 18F-FLT prior to PET imaging.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[18F]-Fluorothymidine</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive a dose of 18F-FLT through a fresh intravenous catheter as per standard PET procedures. Dosing will be based on age.</description>
    <arm_group_label>18F-FLT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pediatric patients with newly diagnosed central nervous system tumors undergoing
             planned surgical resection within 21 days.

          -  Patients should be &lt; 21 years of age at the time of diagnosis.

          -  Patients should be capable of achieving imaging without the need for sedation or
             anesthesia.

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status ≥ 50. For infants, the Lansky play scale ≥ 50% can be
             substituted.

          -  Patients must not be pregnant or nursing.

          -  Signed Informed Consent.

          -  Patients receiving steroids and/or anti-seizure medications are eligible for this
             study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior radiation therapy and/or chemotherapy are not permitted.

          -  Active infection

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding

          -  Serious concurrent medical illness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark W Kieran, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute/Children's Hospital Boston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Boston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 12, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark W. Kieran, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>18F-FLT</keyword>
  <keyword>FLT</keyword>
  <keyword>PET</keyword>
  <keyword>CNS tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Newly</keyword>
  <keyword>diagnosed</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Central Nervous System Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alovudine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

