<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00169468</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R-CHOP VELCADE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00169468</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Association of Velcade to R-CHOP in the Treatment of B Cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of the Association of Velcade to R-CHOP in the Treatment of B Cell Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lymphoma Study Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Association pour le Développement de la Recherche Clinique et Informatique en Onco-Hématologie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lymphoma Study Association</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the response rate and toxicity of the
      association R-CHOP with two schedules of administration of Velcade, in B-cell CD 20 +
      lymphoma patients, aged from 18 to 80 years

      The goal is to get a response rate at least at what observed with R-CHOP alone and will be
      evaluates with a sequential test.

      The other objective is to evaluate the toxicity
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The association of the monoclonal antibody Rituximab to chemotherapy regimen of B-cell
      lymphoma is associated with an increase response rate and event free survival when compared
      to chemotherapy alone (Coiffier et al NEJM 2002). It has been observed in almost all
      histological type of B-cell lymphomas. No significant increase of toxicity was observed
      especially in the most used regimen CHOP and the association R-CHOP is a standard for most
      B-cell malignancies CD20 positive.

      However, in patients with diffuse large cell lymphoma progress should be made as the complete
      response rate is below 75% in most situation and in low grade lymphoma, although patients
      respond well to chemotherapy complete remission rate averaged generally 50% (Marcus et al
      2003), Czuczman et al 1999) .

      There is a need to improve this association with new innovative agent. Before running
      randomized study it is important to evaluate the like hood of getting improvement by phase 2
      study testing tolerance and efficacy on a well established regimen.

      Bortezomib (Velcade formerly PS 341) is a proteasome inhibitor which has shown promising
      activity in the treatment of refractory myeloma. As single agent in indolent lymphomas,
      administered twice per weeks for 2 weeks followed by one week rest period it has already
      showed activity in phase 2 study. It is well tolerated and main toxicity was neuropathy and
      thrombocytopenia.

      Proteasome inhibitors can act through multiple mechanisms to arrest tumor growth, tumor
      spread, and angiogenesis. In vitro studies have shown a synergistic effect of the association
      of Velcade and doxorubicin on myeloma cell lines resistant to chemotherapy.

      Association of Velcade to standard chemotherapy regimen is under study with the aim of
      improving on the results.

      Association of Velcade to one of the most efficient treatment of B-cell lymphoma, R-CHOP,
      might increase the response rate.

      However, different schedules should be explored in order to better appreciate efficacy and
      toxicity.

      This randomized phase 2 study is designed to evaluate the response rate and the toxicity of
      two schedules of administration of Velcade in association with R-CHOP. The aim of the study
      is to establish a well tolerated regimen giving a response rate in the limit upper/lower of
      what is observed with conventional R-CHOP used in all the different histological subtypes of
      B cell lymphomas patients requiring treatment.

      The heterogeneity of the population will preclude any meaningful subgroup analysis.

      It is important to evaluate tolerability before exploring the efficacy of this new regimen in
      large randomized studies or in specific phases II study which will need 50 patients for each
      subgroup of patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2011</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of complete remission</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>48</enrollment>
  <condition>B Cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab -CHOP plus Velcade</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        • Patients with one of the following B-cell Lymphoma CD 20 positive : Mantle cell, Marginal
        zone, lymphocytic, follicular requiring treatment, Histological transformation from low
        grade to high grade, diffuse large cell without adverse prognostic factors defined by the
        international prognostic index (IPI)

          -  Aged from 18 to 80 years

          -  Untreated with chemotherapy except with Chlorambucil or Cyclophosphamide per os alone
             less than 6 months

          -  Previous radiotherapy except if localized

          -  Performance status &lt; 3

          -  Signed inform consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other type of lymphomas: Burkitt, T cell, CD 20 negative

          -  Central nervous system or meningeal involvement

          -  Contraindication to any drug contained in the chemotherapy regimen

          -  HIV disease, active hepatitis B or C

          -  Treatment with polychemotherapy before except with Chlorambucil or Cyclophosphamide
             per os less than 6 months

          -  Prior extended radiotherapy

          -  Any serious active disease or co-morbid medical condition (according to investigator's
             decision )

          -  Renal deficiency (clearance &lt; 30 ml/mn), liver deficiency (bilirubin &gt; 30 mmol/l)
             unless related to lymphoma

          -  Neuropathy&gt; grade 2 within 14 days before enrollment

          -  Platelets &lt; 30.109/l within 14 days before enrollment

          -  Neutrophils &lt; 1.0 109/l within 14 days before enrollment

          -  Women with pregnancy or without adequate method of contraception

          -  Any history of active cancer during the last two years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>christian Gisselbrecht, MD PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lymphoma Study Association</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Saint-Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <state>Paris 10</state>
        <zip>75475</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Gustave Roussy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villejuif</city>
        <state>Villejuif Cedex</state>
        <zip>94805</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Henri Mondor</name>
      <address>
        <city>Créteil</city>
        <zip>94010</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Lyon Sud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pierre Bénite</city>
        <zip>69310</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Czuczman MS, Grillo-López AJ, White CA, Saleh M, Gordon L, LoBuglio AF, Jonas C, Klippenstein D, Dallaire B, Varns C. Treatment of patients with low-grade B-cell lymphoma with the combination of chimeric anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody and CHOP chemotherapy. J Clin Oncol. 1999 Jan;17(1):268-76.</citation>
    <PMID>10458242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coiffier B, Lepage E, Briere J, Herbrecht R, Tilly H, Bouabdallah R, Morel P, Van Den Neste E, Salles G, Gaulard P, Reyes F, Lederlin P, Gisselbrecht C. CHOP chemotherapy plus rituximab compared with CHOP alone in elderly patients with diffuse large-B-cell lymphoma. N Engl J Med. 2002 Jan 24;346(4):235-42.</citation>
    <PMID>11807147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>44. Marcus R, et al. (2003). An International Multi-Centre, Randomized, Open-Label, Phase III Trial Comparing Rituximab Added to CVP Chemotherapy to CVP Chemotherapy Alone in Untreated Stage III/IV Follicular Non-Hodgkins Lymphoma. Blood, 102, issue 11, (abstract 87).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Connor O, Wright J, Moskowitz CH et al. Promising Activity of the Proteasome Inhibitor Bortezomib (Velcade) in the Treatment of Indolent Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma and Mantle Cell Lymphoma. Session Type: Poster Session 517-II. Blood, Volume 102, issue 11, November 16, 2003 (abstract 2346)</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 26, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 26, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 27, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>B Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Velcade</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

