<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00160914</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11408B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00160914</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Childhood Obesity: Variations in Management</brief_title>
  <official_title>Childhood Obesity: Variations in Management</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Nathan Cummings Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Childhood obesity has been described as a growing national epidemic. Between 1980 and 1994
      the prevalence of childhood obesity doubled with 10% to 15% of children and adolescents being
      obese. Childhood obesity has both immediate and long-term detrimental consequences for health
      and well-being. Obese children are at increased risk for coronary heart disease, type 2
      diabetes, and hypertension. Obese children are more likely to be at risk for psychological
      stress and disturbed body image. Moreover, obese children are more likely to become obese
      adults, especially if weight reduction has not occurred by the end of adolescence.

      The pediatrician is in an ideal position to assess and manage childhood obesity. Recently,
      guidelines have been established for the assessment and treatment of childhood obesity. These
      &quot;best practice&quot; guidelines include recommended diagnostic criteria, assessment of
      contributing factors such as diet and lifestyle, family history, and treatment choices.
      Although these guidelines have been introduced little is known about pediatricians' actual
      practice patterns and their beliefs concerning childhood obesity.

      Project Description I plan to conduct a national survey of pediatricians to assess common
      strategies for the identification and management of childhood obesity, along with
      pediatricians' attitudes and beliefs about childhood obesity. In consultation with a panel of
      practicing general pediatricians and survey research experts, I plan to develop a survey that
      measures pediatricians' beliefs about the causes and consequences of childhood obesity, its
      prevalence in their practice settings, their approaches to diagnosis and management, and
      resources available for treatment. The survey will be administered to a randomly selected
      national sample of approximately 600 practicing general pediatricians. The response rate is
      expected to be approximately 60% or 360 pediatricians. The survey results will help to assess
      the degree to which recommended practice guidelines are being implemented, identify
      pediatricians' beliefs and attitudes that might serve as barriers to optimal care, and
      suggest areas for continuing medical education. The proposed time frame for the study is two
      years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Project Goals

      Year One

        -  Develop and Pilot Test Survey. The Pediatrician Survey will be designed to assess both
           practice patterns and attitudes/beliefs pertaining to childhood and adolescent obesity.
           From a review of the literature and the recently published guidelines, along with
           interviews with practicing pediatricians, we will generate items that assess relevant
           diagnostic and therapeutic approaches to childhood obesity, including patient and
           physician demographic data. We will also thoroughly review the literature to identify
           attitudes and beliefs that may impact pediatricians approaches to obesity management.
           The survey will be pilot tested with a small sample of practicing pediatricians, and
           appropriate modifications in the survey will be made.

        -  Select Sample. We will use the American Academy of Pediatrics Fellowship Directory to
           identify a national pool of practicing pediatricians. To allow us to assess any regional
           differences in practice patterns, we will stratify the pool of practicing pediatricians
           by geographic region and randomly select 150 pediatricians from within each of four
           geographic regions. This will allow us to survey a total of 600 practicing
           pediatricians.

        -  Mail Surveys. Using addresses provided by the Directory, we will send surveys via mail
           to selected pediatricians. All mailings will be coded and entered into a computerized
           master list that will facilitate tracking of surveys received and follow-up. Surveys
           sent and received will be tracked. Based on prior research experience, we expect an
           initial response rate of approximately 50%. One month after the initial mailing, we will
           conduct a second mailing to non--responders, sending a reminder postcard requesting the
           completion and return of the survey. Two months after the initial mailing, a second
           letter and survey will be sent to those who still have not responded. With this method,
           we expect a final response rate of 60%

      Year Two

      • Data Entry and Analysis. Data from returned surveys, including respondent demographic
      characteristics, practice structure and setting, practice patterns, and attitudes/beliefs
      will be entered into a database for subsequent analysis. Data will be double-entered and
      checked for accuracy. Data analysis will consist of establishing psychometric properties of
      attitude and belief measures, examining frequencies of responses to, individual items,
      looking for trends across geographic regions, and assessing common approaches to the
      diagnosis and management of childhood obesity. Moreover, we will analyze the data to
      determine the relationship of attitudes/beliefs and practice patterns. We anticipate that we
      will identify a number of important variations in the diagnosis and management of childhood
      obesity. We also expect to identify a number of personal and systems-related barriers to
      treatment of childhood obesity. For example, we expect that pediatricians with more recent
      training will have more optimistic attitudes toward successful management of childhood
      obesity. We also expect to find variations in reimbursement and clinic resources, and that
      these will impact pediatricians' approaches.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Identification/management of childhood obesity (behavior)</intervention_name>
    <description>In this project, we plan to conduct a national survey of pediatricians to assess common strategies for identification and management of childhood obesity, along with pediatricians' attitudes and beliefs about childhood obesity.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Practicing general pediatricians
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Practicing general pediatricians

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non practicing general pediatricians
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janis Mendelsohn, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flegal KM, Carroll MD, Kuczmarski RJ, Johnson CL. Overweight and obesity in the United States: prevalence and trends, 1960-1994. Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord. 1998 Jan;22(1):39-47.</citation>
    <PMID>9481598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lauer RM, Connor WE, Leaverton PE, Reiter MA, Clarke WR. Coronary heart disease risk factors in school children: the Muscatine study. J Pediatr. 1975 May;86(5):697-706.</citation>
    <PMID>1133650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drash A. Relationship between diabetes mellitus and obesity in the child. Metabolism. 1973 Feb;22(2):337-44.</citation>
    <PMID>4687958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Londe S, Bourgoignie JJ, Robson AM, Goldring D. Hypertension in apparently normal children. J Pediatr. 1971 Apr;78(4):569-77.</citation>
    <PMID>5555589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>French SA, Story M, Perry CL. Self-esteem and obesity in children and adolescents: a literature review. Obes Res. 1995 Sep;3(5):479-90. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8521169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serdula MK, Ivery D, Coates RJ, Freedman DS, Williamson DF, Byers T. Do obese children become obese adults? A review of the literature. Prev Med. 1993 Mar;22(2):167-77. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8483856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barlow SE, Dietz WH. Obesity evaluation and treatment: Expert Committee recommendations. The Maternal and Child Health Bureau, Health Resources and Services Administration and the Department of Health and Human Services. Pediatrics. 1998 Sep;102(3):E29.</citation>
    <PMID>9724677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Academy of Pediatrics. Fellowship Directory. Elk Grove Village, IL: American Academy of Pediatrics., 2001.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dietz WH, Nelson A. Barriers to the treatment of childhood obesity: a call to action. J Pediatr. 1999 May;134(5):535-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10228284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 8, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 12, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Childhood obesity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pediatric Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

