<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00166465</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC0248</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MC0248</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1126-03</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00166465</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stage IV Colorectal CA ALIMTA</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Dose-Finding Study and a Randomized Phase II Study of ALIMTA Plus Oxaliplatin Versus Oxaliplatin Plus 5-Fluorouracil and Leucovorin (FOLFOX 4 Regimen) in the First-Line Treatment of Patients With Locally Advanced Unresectable or Stage IV Colorectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase I: The primary objective of the Phase 1 portion of this study is to determine the
      Maximum tolerated dose and the recommended Phase 2 dose of ALIMTA plus oxaliplatin when given
      with folate and vitamin B-12 supplementation in the treatment of patients with unresectable,
      locally advanced or metastatic colorectal cancer. The Phase I component of the study will be
      activated for enrollment of Mayo Clinic patients only.

      Phase II: The primary objective of the Phase 2 portion of this study is to determine the
      tumor response rates to ALIMTA plus oxaliplatin and oxaliplatin plus 5-fluorouracil and
      leucovorin in patients with locally advanced unresectable or Stage IV colorectal cancer that
      have not received prior chemotherapy for advanced disease. Patients will be randomly assigned
      to receive either ALIMTA plus oxaliplatin (Arm A) or Oxaliplatin plus 5-Fluorouracil and
      Leucovorin (Arm B). The Phase II component of the study will be activated for enrollment of
      patients via the Mayo Clinic Cancer Research Consortium mechanism. A comparison will be made
      of the side effects between regimens.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ALIMTA, oxaliplatin, and 5-fluorouracil (alone or with leucovorin) have shown activity as
      single agents in the treatment of colorectal cancer. Their different mechanisms of action
      make the combination of ALIMTA with oxaliplatin attractive as potential first-line therapies
      in terms of improving response rates and overall survival in patients with metastatic
      colorectal cancer. Current reports of the combination of oxaliplatin and 5-FU as first-line
      therapies suggest that there may be advantages in combining oxaliplatin with other
      antifolates in the treatment of colorectal cancer. ALIMTA is an attractive candidate to
      replace other drugs such as 5-FU in the combinations with oxaliplatin in the treatment of
      locally advanced and metastatic colorectal cancer. ALIMTA has potential advantages over 5-FU
      when combined with oxaliplatin because it requires a single short injection and inhibits
      multiple targets in the folate pathway. Therefore, we propose to conduct a trial reporting
      the clinical effectiveness and side effects of ALIMTA plus oxaliplatin and one of the current
      standards of care, the FOLFOX 4 regimen (Oxaliplatin plus 5-Fluorouracil and Leucovorin).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2006</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of successes will be estimated by the number of successes divided by the total number of evaluable patients. Confidence intervals for the true success proportion will be calculated using the exact binomial distribution.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment>200</enrollment>
  <condition>Locally Advanced Unresectable or Stage IV Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ALIMTA plus Oxaliplatin versus Oxaliplatin plus 5-Fluorouracil and Leucovorin (FOLFOX 4 Regimen)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

        3.11 Phase I and II Required Characteristics

        3.111 Pathologic or cytologic diagnosis of adenocarcinoma of the colon or rectum. Patients
        must have locally advanced unresectable or Stage IV colorectal cancer that is not amenable
        to curative therapy. See Protocol Appendix VI, American Joint Committee on Cancer Staging
        Criteria for Colorectal Cancer.

        3.112 Measurable disease as defined by RECIST criteria (see Section 11.0). Patients who do
        not have measurable disease, but who do have evaluable disease, may be enrolled in the Ph I
        portion of the study only.

        3.113 Prior radiation therapy allowed to &lt;25% of the bone marrow (see Protocol Appendix
        VII, Distribution of Active Bone Marrow in the Adult), and patients must have recovered
        from the toxic effects of the treatment prior to study enrollment (except for alopecia).
        Patients are allowed to have received standard postoperative adjuvant radiation therapy for
        rectal cancer. Prior radiotherapy must be completed &lt; 30 days before study entry. Lesions
        that have been radiated in the advanced setting cannot be included as sites of measurable
        disease unless clear tumor progression has been documented in these lesions since the end
        of radiation therapy.

        3.114 ECOG performance status (PS) of 0, 1or 2 (see Protocol Appendix IV).

        3.115 Estimated life expectancy of greater than or equal to 12 weeks.

        3.116 Ability and willingness to comply with adequate follow-up.

        3.117 Adequate organ function including the following less than or equal to 7 days prior to
        study entry:

          -  Adequate bone marrow reserve:

          -  ANC greater than or equal to 1500

          -  PLT greater than or equal to 100,000

          -  Hgb greater than or equal to 9 g/dL.

          -  Hepatic:

          -  Total bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN

          -  Alk Phos (AP), AST less than or equal to 3.0 x ULN (AP and AST less than or equal to 5
             ULN is acceptable if liver has tumor involvement).

          -  Renal: calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) &gt;= 45 mL/min based on the standard
             Cockcroft and Gault formula (see table below) or on measured glomerular filtration
             rate (GFR) using the appropriate radiolabeled method (51-CrEDTA or Tc99m-DTPA).
             Enrollment and dosing decisions based on creatinine clearance may be made using local
             lab values (calculated using the standard Cockcroft and Gault formula [see below]) The
             serum creatinine must be assayed at the same local lab each time for that patient.

               -  Cockcroft and Gault Equation Creatinine clearance for males = (140 - age)(weight
                  in kg) (72)(serum creatinine in mg/dL) Creatinine clearance for females = 140 -
                  age)(weight in kg)(0.85) (72)(serum creatinine in mg/dL) Moderate renal
                  impairment is calculated creatinine clearance 30-50 mL/min (32). Mild renal
                  impairment is calculated creatinine clearance 51-80 mL/min (32).

        3.118 Ability to sign informed consent.

        3.119 Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

        Exclusion criteria

        3.12 Phase I and II Contraindications

        3.121 Evidence of peripheral neuropathy &gt;CTCAE v3.0 Grade 1 (for example, diabetic
        neuropathy).

        3.122 Prior chemotherapy for advanced disease. Only one prior adjuvant therapy including
        CPT-11, or 5-fluorouracil-leucovorin, Capecitabine but not oxaliplatin is allowed if it has
        been &gt;= 6 months since the last treatment. Patients enrolling in the Phase I portion of the
        trial may have received one advanced disease regimen that does not include either ALIMTA or
        oxaliplatin.

        3.123 Treatment less than or equal to 30 days with any chemotherapy as well as
        non-cytotoxic cancer therapy such as immunotherapy.

        3.124 Serious concomitant systemic disorders (including active infections or
        uncontrolled/brittle diabetes) that would compromise the safety of the patient or
        compromise the patients ability to complete the study.

        3.125 Second primary malignancy (except in situ carcinoma of the cervix or adequately
        treated nonmelanomatous carcinoma of the skin or other malignancy treated &gt;= 5 years
        previously with no evidence of recurrence; prior low grade [Gleason score £ 6] localized
        prostate cancer is allowed).

        3.126 Inability to interrupt aspirin or other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents 2 days
        before, the day of, and 2 days after each dose of ALIMTA (5 days prior for long-acting
        agents such as piroxicam). (See Appendix VIII for list of NSAIDs.)

        3.127 Clinically symptomatic central nervous system metastases. Metastases that have been
        previously treated and are stable are allowed as judged by the investigator.

        3.128 Any of the following as this regimen may be harmful to a developing fetus or nursing
        child:

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Nursing women

          -  Women of childbearing potential or their sexual partners who are unwilling to employ
             adequate contraception (condoms, diaphragm, birth control pills, injections,
             intrauterine device (IUD), surgical sterilization, subcutaneous implants, or
             abstinence, etc.)

        3.129a Presence of clinically relevant third-space fluid collections. Fluid collections may
        be drained to allow the patient to enroll in the study.

        3.129b Weight loss ³10% - 6 weeks prior to study entry.

        3.129c Inability or unwillingness to take folic acid or vitamin B12.

        3.129d Previous completion or withdrawal from this study or any other study investigating
        ALIMTA.

        3.129e Prior treatment with oxaliplatin.

        3.129f Concurrent therapy or treatment - 30 days with another experimental agent for cancer
        or other diseases.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven R. Alberts, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 12, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 14, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 11, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 11, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Steven R. Alberts, M.D.</name_title>
    <organization>Mayo Clinic Cancer Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

