<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02015559</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TRIO-US B10</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-02384</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>13-001676</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>TRIO-US B10</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016042</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02015559</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mucoadhesive Oral Wound Rinse in Preventing and Treating Stomatitis in Patients With ER- or PR-Positive Metastatic or Locally Recurrent Breast Cancer That Cannot be Removed by Surgery Receiving Everolimus</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Randomized Trial of Mugard Compared With Best Supportive Care for Prevention and Treatment of Stomatitis in Women With Hormone Receptor Positive Breast Cancer Initiating Treatment With Everolimus-based Endocrine Therapy.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Translational Research in Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase II trial studies how well mucoadhesive oral wound rinse works in
      preventing and treating stomatitis in patients with estrogen receptor (ER)- or progesterone
      receptor (PR)-positive metastatic or locally recurrent breast cancer that cannot be removed
      by surgery receiving everolimus. Mucoadhesive oral wound rinse may help prevent symptoms of
      stomatitis, or mouth sores, in patients receiving everolimus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Evaluate whether use of prophylactic MuGard (mucoadhesive oral wound rinse) in
      participants being treated with everolimus will reduce the rate of stomatitis.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Compare symptoms from mouth sores in patients receiving MuGard compared with those
      receiving best supportive care.

      II. Evaluate the rate of everolimus dose adjustment or therapy discontinuation as a result of
      stomatitis in participants treated with MuGard prophylaxis versus best supportive care.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 arms.

      ARM I: Patients receive mucoadhesive oral wound rinse orally (PO) as a gentle swish for 30-60
      seconds 3-6 times daily beginning on day 1 of everolimus therapy and continuing for up to 6
      months in the absence of unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM II: Patients receive no intervention.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up within 7 days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 8, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 26, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 26, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of grades 1-4 stomatitis assessed using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days after completion of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated and the 95% confidence interval (CI) will also be obtained. Chi-square test will be used to compare the stomatitis rates between the two study arms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of grade 3/4 stomatitis assessed using CTCAE version 4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days after completion of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated and the 95% CI will also be obtained. Chi-square test will be used to compare the stomatitis rates between the two study arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of everolimus dose adjustment or discontinuation related to stomatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 days after completion of treatment</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">61</enrollment>
  <condition>Estrogen Receptor-positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>HER2-negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Oral Complications</condition>
  <condition>Progesterone Receptor-positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (mucoadhesive oral wound rinse)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive mucoadhesive oral wound rinse PO as a gentle swish for 30-60 seconds 3-6 times daily beginning on day 1 of everolimus therapy and continuing for up to 6 months in the absence of unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (no intervention)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive no intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mucoadhesive oral wound rinse</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (mucoadhesive oral wound rinse)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MuGard</other_name>
    <other_name>oral mucoadhesive protectant rinse</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (mucoadhesive oral wound rinse)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Metastatic or locally recurrent unresectable breast cancer

          -  Histological or cytological confirmed ER and/or PR positivity

          -  Progression through at least one prior line of endocrine therapy

          -  Participant is scheduled to initiate treatment with everolimus combined with
             exemestane or another form of endocrine therapy

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.5 x 10^9/L

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100 x 10^9/L

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) ≥&gt;= 8.0 g/dL

          -  International normalized ratio (INR) =&lt; 2

          -  Serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 X
             upper limit of normal (ULN) (or =&lt; 5 X ULN if hepatic metastases are present)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)-overexpressing breast cancer by local
             laboratory testing (immunohistochemistry [IHC] 3+ staining or fluorescent in situ
             hybridization [FISH] positive)

          -  Baseline presence of oral ulcers

          -  Prior treatment with everolimus or another mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR)
             inhibitor (temsirolimus)

          -  Patients on warfarin (patients on injectable blood thinners, such as Lovenox, are able
             to continue those)

          -  Patients currently receiving chemotherapy or who have received chemotherapy less than
             4 weeks of the start of everolimus (including chemotherapy, radiation therapy,
             antibody based therapy, etc.)

          -  Known impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of oral everolimus

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus as defined by hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) &gt; 8% despite
             adequate therapy; patients with a known history of impaired fasting glucose or
             diabetes mellitus (DM) may be included, however blood glucose and antidiabetic
             treatment must be monitored closely throughout the trial and adjusted as necessary

          -  Patients who have any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions such as:

               -  Unstable angina pectoris, symptomatic congestive heart failure, myocardial
                  infarction =&lt; 6 months prior to start of everolimus, serious uncontrolled cardiac
                  arrhythmia, or any other clinically significant cardiac disease

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure of New York heart Association class III or
                  IV

               -  Active (acute or chronic) or uncontrolled severe infection, liver disease such as
                  cirrhosis, decompensated liver disease, and chronic hepatitis (i.e. quantifiable
                  hepatitis B virus [HBV]-deoxyribonucleic acid [DNA] and/or positive hepatitis B
                  virus surface antigen [HbsAg], quantifiable hepatitis C virus [HCV]-ribonucleic
                  acid [RNA])

               -  Known severely impaired lung function (spirometry and diffusing capacity of the
                  lung for carbon monoxide [DLCO] 50% or less of normal and oxygen [O2] saturation
                  88% or less at rest on room air)

               -  Active, bleeding diathesis

          -  Chronic treatment with corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive agents; topical or
             inhaled corticosteroids are allowed

          -  Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositivity

          -  Patients who have received live attenuated vaccines within 1 week of start of
             everolimus and during the study; patient should also avoid close contact with others
             who have received live attenuated vaccines; examples of live attenuated vaccines
             include intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral polio, Bacillus
             Calmette-Guérin (BCG), yellow fever, varicella and TY21a typhoid vaccines

          -  Patients with a history of non-compliance to medical regimens or who are considered
             potentially unreliable or will not be able to complete the entire study

          -  Patients who are currently part of or have participated in any clinical investigation
             with an investigational drug within 1 month prior to dosing

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women

          -  Women of child-bearing potential (WOCBP), defined as all women physiologically capable
             of becoming pregnant, must use highly effective methods of contraception during the
             study and 8 weeks after; highly effective contraception methods include combination of
             any two of the following:

               -  Use of oral, injected or implanted hormonal methods of contraception or

               -  Placement of an intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS)

               -  Barrier methods of contraception: condom or occlusive cap (diaphragm or
                  cervical/vault caps) with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/ vaginal suppository

               -  Total abstinence or

               -  Male/female sterilization Women are considered post-menopausal and not of
                  child-bearing potential if they have had 12 months of natural (spontaneous)
                  amenorrhea with an appropriate clinical profile (e.g. age appropriate, history of
                  vasomotor symptoms) or have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy (with or without
                  hysterectomy) or tubal ligation at least six weeks prior to randomization; in the
                  case of oophorectomy alone, only when the reproductive status of the woman has
                  been confirmed by follow up hormone level assessment is she considered not of
                  child-bearing potential
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Parvin Peddi</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 13, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 13, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 19, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

