<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02014246</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999903329</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-AG-N329</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02014246</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic Characterization of Movement Disorders and Dementias</brief_title>
  <official_title>Genetic Characterization of Movement Disorders and Dementias</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      There are two basic types of movement disorders. Some cause excessive movement, some cause
      slowness or lack of movement. Some of these are caused by mutations in genes. On the other
      hand, dementia is a condition of declining mental abilities, especially memory. Dementia can
      occur at any age but becomes more frequent with age. Researchers want to study the genes of
      families with a history of movement disorders or dementia. They hope to find a genetic cause
      of these disorders. This can help them better understand and treat the diseases. This study
      will not be limited to a particular disorder, but will study all movement disorders or
      dementias in general. This study will perform genetic testing to identify the genetic causes
      of movement disorders and dementia. Today, genetic testing can be done to analyze multiple
      genes at the same time. This increases the chances of finding the genetic cause of movement
      disorders and dementias.

      Objectives:

      To learn more about movement disorders and dementia, their causes, and treatments.

      Eligibility:

      Adults and children with a movement disorder or dementia, and their family members.

      Healthy volunteers.

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with medical history and blood tests. Some will have physical
      exam.

      Participants will give a blood sample by a needle in the arm. This can be done at the clinic,
      by their own doctor, or at home. Alternatively, a saliva sample may be provided if a blood
      sample cannot be obtained.

      Participants can opt to send an extra blood sample to a repository for future study. Genetic
      test will be done on these samples. The samples will be coded. The key to the code will
      remain at NIA. Only NIA investigators will have access to the code key. Participants can
      request to receive results of the tests.

      Participation is generally a single visit. Participants may be called back for extra
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective

      The objective of this study is to ascertain individuals with a clinical diagnosis of a
      movement disorder or dementia, their affected and unaffected family members, and unrelated,
      healthy individuals (to provide control samples); to characterize their phenotypes; and to
      identify and further characterize genetic contributions to etiology by collecting blood
      samples, and/or saliva samples on these individuals for DNA and induced Pluripotent stem
      (iPs) cell line preparation.

      Study population

      Up to 10,000 persons with a diagnosis of a movement disorder or dementia, 1,000 asymptomatic
      persons who are family members/related to individuals with a diagnosis of movement disorder
      or dementia, and 1,000 unrelated, healthy control individuals.

      Design

      This study usually requires one outpatient visit to the NIH Clinical Center. Participant
      visits may also take place when they are an inpatient at the NIH Clinical Center. Those who
      are unable to travel to NIH may have study procedures performed at a site near their

      home, such as hospital facilities, private physician offices, nursing homes, assisted living
      facilities, local community centers, or participant homes. Participants will undergo medical
      record review, a physical examination and biospecimen collection including

      blood draw and/or saliva collection at the enrollment visit.

      Additional visits may be scheduled to collect additional phenotype information or to collect
      additional biospecimens.

      Outcome measures

      The primary outcome measure of this study is the identification of pathogenic genetic
      variants that are causative for the movement disorder or dementia that the patient has been
      diagnosed with. These disease-causing variants are often inherited.

      The secondary outcome measure of this study is the identification of genetic variants that
      alter susceptibility/risk for the movement disorder or dementia that the patient has been
      diagnosed with. These genetic risk factors are associated with disease that can be apparently
      sporadic in nature.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 12, 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify and characterize genetic contributions to etiology for movement disorders, such as dystonia, Parkinson's disease, and dementias, such as Alzheimer's disease, Lewy Body Dementia, frontotemporal dementia.</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12000</enrollment>
  <condition>Ataxia</condition>
  <condition>Dystonia</condition>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Corticobasal Degeneration</condition>
  <condition>Multiple System Atrophy</condition>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Lewy Body Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease-Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Dentatorubral-pallidoluysian Atrophy</condition>
  <condition>Creutzfeldt-Jakob Disease and Fatal Familial Insomnia</condition>
  <condition>Fragile X-associated Tremor/Ataxia Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Krabbe's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Niemann-Pick Disease, Type C</condition>
  <condition>Neuronal Ceroid Lipofuscinosis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

        For Patients:

          -  Diagnosis of a movement disorder or dementia by a neurologist or other qualified
             professional and accompanied by sufficient clinical and/or laboratory evidence to
             support the diagnosis

          -  Confirmation of a movement disorder or dementia by study investigators or a qualified
             clinician by physical examination and/or review of medical records

          -  Ages 18 and above

          -  Able to provide consent or, in the case of minors, or cognitive impairment, have a
             legally-authorized representative to provide consent

          -  Able to understand and participate in study procedures or for those without consent
             capacity, able to participate in study procedures AND has a legally authorized
             representative that understands the study procedures and can consent on their behalf.

        For unaffected family members of patients:

          -  Unaffected relative of a patient diagnosed with a movement disorder or dementia
             enrolled in this protocol. For these purposes, we define a family member as an
             individual for which there is a demonstrable relationship with the proband in the
             pedigree. This is a standard approach used in family-based studies. Furthermore, the
             related patient (defined as a family member diagnosed with the disease of interest)
             must be enrolled in the study.

          -  Ages 18 and above

          -  Able to provide consent

          -  Able to understand and participate in study procedures

        For unrelated healthy control individuals:

          -  Be in good general health

          -  Have no known movement disorder or dementia, or family member with a movement disorder
             or dementia

          -  Age 18 and above

          -  Able to provide consent

          -  Able to understand and participate in study procedures

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

        For patients:

        -An identifiable, non-genetic etiology for the movement disorder or dementia, such as a
        specific environmental exposure, birth injury, metabolic disorder, or brain infection such
        as encephalitis

        For all participants:

          -  Clinically significant anemia that would make phlebotomy unsafe, and participant
             unwilling to provide saliva sample.

          -  Clinically significant bleeding that would make phlebotomy unsafe, and participant
             unwilling to provide saliva sample.

          -  Any medical condition that would make phlebotomy unsafe or undesirable, such as a
             serious medical illness like unstable heart disease, or unstable chronic obstructive
             pulmonary disease, and participant unwilling to provide saliva sample.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bryan J Traynor, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cynthia D Crews</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-3826</phone>
    <email>cc100h@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Bryan J Traynor, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-7606</phone>
    <email>traynorb@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Aging, Clinical Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>NIA Studies Recruitment</last_name>
      <phone>410-350-3941</phone>
      <email>niastudiesrecruitment@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 3, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 12, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Movement Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Polymorphisms</keyword>
  <keyword>DNA</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoblast Cell Lines</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Motor Neuron Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ataxia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebellar Ataxia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Movement Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple System Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shy-Drager Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pick Disease of the Brain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aphasia, Primary Progressive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Frontotemporal Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niemann-Pick Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niemann-Pick Disease, Type A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niemann-Pick Disease, Type C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuronal Ceroid-Lipofuscinoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lewy Body Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukodystrophy, Globoid Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Creutzfeldt-Jakob Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insomnia, Fatal Familial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myoclonic Epilepsies, Progressive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

