<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02014025</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SWHZSG004</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Zhengshuguo</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02014025</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Laparoscopic Hepatectomy Versus Open Hepatectomy for PHC</brief_title>
  <official_title>Laparoscopic Hepatectomy Versus Open Hepatectomy for PHC With a Tumor Size of 5-10cm:a Prospective Case-control Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shuguo Zheng, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Southwest Hospital, China</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare short-term and long-term efficacy of laparoscope
      hepatectomy and open hepatectomy, evaluate the safety and efficacy of laparoscope hepatectomy
      the PHC with a tumor size of 5～10㎝,and provide class B evidence based medicine for
      laparoscope hepatectomy for PHC with a tumor size of 5～10㎝.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:primary hepatic carcinoma( PHC) is the world's most common and one of the most
      malignant tumors, the incidence of malignant tumors in the top five in the world, second only
      to mortality in gastric cancer, ranked No. 3. surgery and comprehensive treatment is
      recognized by the medical profession Surgical approach, surgical methods include open and
      laparoscopic liver resection .The safety and efficacy of laparoscopic resection small PHC has
      been recognized, but the safety and efficacy of laparoscopy PHC resection is still a dispute,
      that with a tumor size of 5～10㎝, the clinical evidence is a C or D grade level from the
      standard definition of evidence-based medicine literature which has been published , for
      laparoscopic liver resection versus open liver resection for these hepatocellular carcinoma
      prospective case-control study has not been reported.

      Intervention:We will let the 90 patients who meet the inclusion criteria .Patients in
      hepatobiliary surgery A, D district is undergo traditional open liver resection,
      hepatobiliary surgery E district is undergo laparoscopic liver resection. In addition to the
      surgery way is different, the rest treatments are same.

      Results:

        1. Clinical data include:operation time, intraoperative blood loss, volume of blood
           transfusion, Rate of blood transfusion, complications and mortality, postoperative liver
           function, resection margin, long-term curative effect and survival time were collected
           and analysed.

        2. Statistical method:groups t-test ，univariate/multivariate analysis, logistic regression
           analysis, mixed linear regression, Cox survival analysis ，Kaplan-Meier survival
           analysis，Log-rank curves were used.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3-year</time_frame>
    <description>follow-up after the surgery every 3months, to understand relapse, death, statistics 1-year, 3-year overall survival rates，disease-free survival rates , recurrence and metastasis rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>intraoperative parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>during the operation</time_frame>
    <description>operation time, intraoperative blood loss, rate of blood transfusion, tumor resection margin.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration hospitalization(an expected average of 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>ascites, pleural effusion,cardiopulmonary insufficiency,mortality, postoperative liver function failure.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">335</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Liver Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>laparoscope hepatectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>We let the 45 patients who are meet the inclusion criteria .Hospital in hepatobiliary surgery E district is Group B ,they will accept laparoscopic hepatectomy: tumors are totally resected through laparoscopic.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>open hepatectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>We let the 45 patients who are meet the inclusion criteria .Hospital in hepatobiliary surgery A and D district is Group A ,they will accept Open Hepatectomy: tumors are totally resected by conventional laparotomy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Open hepatectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>We let the 45 patients who are meet the inclusion criteria .Hospital in hepatobiliary surgery A and D district is Group A ,they will accept Open Hepatectomy: tumors are totally resected by conventional laparotomy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>open hepatectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laparoscope hepatectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>We let the 45 patients who are meet the inclusion criteria .Hospital in hepatobiliary surgery E district is Group B ,they will accept Laparoscopic Hepatectomy: tumors are totally resected through laparoscopic.</description>
    <arm_group_label>laparoscope hepatectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion criteria for the Laparoscope hepatectomy group are:

               1. both male and female, aged 18 to 70;

               2. PHC diagnosis is clear preoperative;

               3. No active hepatitis and decompensated cirrhosis

               4. tumor size of 5-10 cm,no intrahepatic or distant metastasis,no tumor thrombus in
                  the portal vein, hepatic vein, vena cava, or bile duct; and no invasion of the
                  diaphragm or surrounding tissues;

               5. no rupture or bleeding of the tumor;

               6. Child-Pugh class A or B liver function;

               7. indocyanine green retention rate at 15 min of &lt;15%, and a remnant liver
                  volume/standard liver volume ratio of &gt;50% in patients with liver cirrhosis and
                  &gt;35% in patients without liver cirrhosis;

               8. upper abdominal surgery, radiofrequency ablation, Transhepatic Arterial
                  Chemotherapy And Embolization treatment, radiotherapy and chemotherapy have not
                  been implemented and no previous surgery that absolutely contraindicated
                  Laparoscope hepatectomy.

               9. General condition of patients and cardiopulmonary function enough to tolerate
                  surgery

              10. voluntary participation in the study, and informed consent.

          -  Inclusion criteria for the Open hepatectomy group are:

        meet the criteria for Laparoscope hepatectomy group;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  (1) age &lt;18 years or&gt; 70 years , pregnant or lactating women; (2) tumor size ≥10 cm,
             or tumor location that would interfere with intraoperative exposure and isolation of
             the hepatic hilum; (3) tumor encroaching on the hepatic hilum , the portal vein,
             primary bile duct or tumor adjacent to the major vascular structures ; (4) unable to
             tolerate a pneumoperitoneum or can't tolerate surgery duo to cardiopulmonary
             dysfunction; (5) severe upper abdominal adhesions; (6)Pathologically confirmed
             positive margins
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shuguo Zheng</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Shuguo Zheng, MD Study Director Institute of Hepatobiliary Surgery ,Southwest Hospital ,Third Military Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southwest Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chongqing</city>
        <state>Chongqing</state>
        <zip>400038</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parkin DM, Bray F, Ferlay J, Pisani P. Global cancer statistics, 2002. CA Cancer J Clin. 2005 Mar-Apr;55(2):74-108.</citation>
    <PMID>15761078</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhou XD, Tang ZY, Ma ZC, Wu ZQ, Fan J, Qin LX, Zhang BH. Surgery for large primary liver cancer more than 10 cm in diameter. J Cancer Res Clin Oncol. 2003 Sep;129(9):543-8. Epub 2003 Jul 30.</citation>
    <PMID>12898232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jingli C, Rong C, Rubai X. Influence of colorectal laparoscopic surgery on dissemination and seeding of tumor cells. Surg Endosc. 2006 Nov;20(11):1759-61. Epub 2006 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>17024537</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fu C, Li GY, Liu FY, Lin QH, Fang XL. [Effect of carbon dioxide pneumoperitoneum-laparoscopic surgery on tumor seeding and metastases in endometrial cancer]. Zhong Nan Da Xue Xue Bao Yi Xue Ban. 2008 Feb;33(2):130-7. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>18326907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Agostini A, Robin F, Jais JP, Aggerbeck M, Vildé F, Blanc B, Lécuru F. Impact of different gases and pneumoperitoneum pressures on tumor growth during laparoscopy in a rat model. Surg Endosc. 2002 Mar;16(3):529-32. Epub 2001 Nov 16.</citation>
    <PMID>11928042</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Metzelder M, Kuebler JF, Shimotakahara A, Chang DH, Vieten G, Ure B. CO2 pneumoperitoneum increases survival in mice with polymicrobial peritonitis. Eur J Pediatr Surg. 2008 Jun;18(3):171-5. doi: 10.1055/s-2008-1038365.</citation>
    <PMID>18493892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yin Z, Fan X, Ye H, Yin D, Wang J. Short- and long-term outcomes after laparoscopic and open hepatectomy for hepatocellular carcinoma: a global systematic review and meta-analysis. Ann Surg Oncol. 2013 Apr;20(4):1203-15. doi: 10.1245/s10434-012-2705-8. Epub 2012 Oct 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23099728</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rao A, Rao G, Ahmed I. Laparoscopic vs. open liver resection for malignant liver disease. A systematic review. Surgeon. 2012 Aug;10(4):194-201. doi: 10.1016/j.surge.2011.06.007. Epub 2011 Jul 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22818276</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toyosaka A, Okamoto E, Mitsunobu M, Oriyama T, Nakao N, Miura K. Intrahepatic metastases in hepatocellular carcinoma: evidence for spread via the portal vein as an efferent vessel. Am J Gastroenterol. 1996 Aug;91(8):1610-5. Retraction in: Am J Gastroenterol. 1998 Mar;93(3):492.</citation>
    <PMID>8759671</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poon RT, Fan ST, Lo CM, Ng IO, Liu CL, Lam CM, Wong J. Improving survival results after resection of hepatocellular carcinoma: a prospective study of 377 patients over 10 years. Ann Surg. 2001 Jul;234(1):63-70.</citation>
    <PMID>11420484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhou XD. Recurrence and metastasis of hepatocellular carcinoma: progress and prospects. Hepatobiliary Pancreat Dis Int. 2002 Feb;1(1):35-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14607620</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hanazaki K, Kajikawa S, Shimozawa N, Matsushita A, Machida T, Shimada K, Yazawa K, Koide N, Adachi W, Amano J. Perioperative blood transfusion and survival following curative hepatic resection for hepatocellular carcinoma. Hepatogastroenterology. 2005 Mar-Apr;52(62):524-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15816471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yeh CN, Lee WC, Jeng LB, Chen MF. Hepatic resection for hepatocellular carcinoma in Taiwan. Eur J Surg Oncol. 2002 Sep;28(6):652-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12359203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Makino Y, Yamanoi A, Kimoto T, El-Assal ON, Kohno H, Nagasue N. The influence of perioperative blood transfusion on intrahepatic recurrence after curative resection of hepatocellular carcinoma. Am J Gastroenterol. 2000 May;95(5):1294-300.</citation>
    <PMID>10811342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kwon AH, Matsui Y, Kamiyama Y. Perioperative blood transfusion in hepatocellular carcinomas: influence of immunologic profile and recurrence free survival. Cancer. 2001 Feb 15;91(4):771-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11241245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 8, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 11, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 17, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 8, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 8, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Southwest Hospital, China</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Shuguo Zheng, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Hepatobiliary Surgery Institute; Chief Physician; Administrator of laparoscopic department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Laparoscope hepatectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Open hepatectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>large PHC</keyword>
  <keyword>safety and sensibility</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

