<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02645071</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UW15-743</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02645071</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brief Program in Reducing Sedentary Behavior and Promoting Physical Exercise</brief_title>
  <official_title>FAMILY Project: Brief Program in Reducing Sedentary Behavior and Promoting Physical Exercise</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hong Kong Department of Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hong Kong Jockey Club Charities Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Lack of physical activity was found to be a local and worldwide issue. Most Hong Kong people
      are having sedentary lifestyle. Researchers show that the increase of physical activity
      reduces the risk of chronic diseases, and improve cardio-pulmonary functions; whereas
      sedentary behaviors increase the risks.

      For many people, the targets of the WHO physical activity guidelines are too high to be
      achieved. Some people are not even willing to try, despite the evidence for the protective
      benefits to their long term health. In response, a recent focus has been placed upon
      reduction of sedentary behavior. Sedentary behavior is defined as 'those activities that do
      not increase energy expenditure substantially above the resting level, such as sitting, lying
      down, or viewing TV, or simply as &quot;too much sitting&quot;. The primary determinants of sedentary
      behavior are behavioral and context-based, such as TV and screen-focused behaviors in home
      and work environments, sitting at work, and sitting during transport. The public health
      leaders have called for reducing the time spent in sedentary behaviors as a possible public
      health priority. This study will focus on reduction of sedentary behavior and increasing
      physical activity in daily life. We hypothesize that the training programs would promote the
      health awareness of the participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Physical activity is believed to contribute to physical and mental health, as well as social
      well-being. World Health organization (WHO) proposed that tobacco use, alcohol abuse, poor
      diets and physical inactivity are the common risk factors for non-communicable diseases (NCD)
      (WHO, 2014). The health benefits of regular physical activity (PA) are well established,
      including positive associations with psychological well-being and an inverse relationship
      with various illnesses.

      Lack of physical activity was found to be a local and worldwide issue and most Hong Kong
      people are having a sedentary lifestyle. Studies show that the increase of physical activity
      reduces the risk of chronic diseases, and improve cardio-pulmonary functions; whereas
      sedentary behaviors increase the risks. In response, a recent focus has been placed upon
      reduction of sedentary behavior. The primary determinants of sedentary behavior are
      behavioral and context-based, such as TV and screen-focused behaviors in home and work
      environments, sitting at work, and sitting during transport. As a result, public health
      leaders have called for reducing the time spent in sedentary behaviors as a possible public
      health priority.

      This study will focus on reduction of sedentary behavior and increasing physical activity in
      daily life. The intervention will promote activities that can be done without using extra
      time (Zero-time exercise). These exercises will encourage participants to use larger muscle
      groups than they would simply sitting or standing, but are designed to be done by all ages
      and all fitness levels. For example, while standing, participants will be encouraged to
      balance on one leg, which will engage stomach and leg muscles. There is evidence that these
      types of movements create cardiovascular and skeletal muscle changes.

      The intervention is a 15- to 20- minute interactive session program, which aims to reduce
      participants' sedentary behavior and increase physical activity by increasing their
      motivation, self-efficacy and knowledge of different types of easy movements (Zero-time
      exercises). We hypothesize that the training programs would promote the health awareness of
      the participants.

      The primary objective is to promote the health awareness on reducing sedentary behavior
      and/or increasing physical exercise. The secondary objectives are to enhance intention and
      confidence of participants to encourage their family members to reduce sedentary and/or
      increasing physical exercise.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in intention on performing physical activity in relation to reduce sedentary behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, immediately following the training session, 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Intention on performing physical activity in relation to reduce sedentary behavior, will be assessed by outcome-based physical activity questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in confidence on performing physical activity in relation to reduce sedentary behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, immediately following training, 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Confidence on performing physical activity in relation to reduce sedentary behavior, will be assessed by outcome-based physical activity questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in perceived knowledge on performing physical activity in relation to reduce sedentary behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, immediately following training, 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Perceived knowledge on performing physical activity in relation to reduce sedentary behavior, will be assessed by outcome-based physical activity questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in behaviour on performing physical activity in relation to reduce sedentary behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Behaviour on performing physical activity in relation to reduce sedentary behavior, will be assessed by outcome-based physical activity questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participants' own health and happiness</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Personal health and happiness will be assessed by personal health and happiness scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participants' family well-being</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Family well-being will be assessed by family well-being scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in intention to motivate participants' family members to reduce sedatry behvaiour</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, immediately following training, 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Intention to motivate participants' family members on reducing sedentary behaviour, will be assessed by outcome-based physical activity questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical activity</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The experimental arm is a 15-20 min interactive session, which aims to reduce participants' sedentary behavior and increase physical activity by increasing their motivation, self-efficacy, and knowledge of different types of easy exercises.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Activity</intervention_name>
    <description>A brief education program in reducing sedentary behavior and promoting physical exercise with family would be conducted. Assessments will be conducted in two different time points, before training session (T1), immediately following training (T2) and two weeks after training (T3) to evaluate the effectiveness of training program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Physical activity</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chinese speaking

          -  Able to complete the questionnaire

          -  Aged 18 or above

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - People with serious health condition that might prevent them from participating in
        physical activity
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Agnes YK LAI, DN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Agnes YK Lai, DN</last_name>
    <phone>852-3917-6779</phone>
    <email>agneslai@hku.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tai-Hing Lam, MD</last_name>
    <phone>852-3917-9287</phone>
    <email>hrmrlth@hku.hk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <zip>852</zip>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Grace Lau, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>39176555</phone>
      <email>gclau@hku.hk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs385/en/</url>
    <description>World Health Organization (2015). Physical activity : Fact sheet</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.chp.gov.hk/en/behavioural/10/280.html</url>
    <description>Department of Health (2014). Behavioral Risk Factor Survey</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bellicha A, Kieusseian A, Fontvieille AM, Tataranni A, Charreire H, Oppert JM. Stair-use interventions in worksites and public settings - a systematic review of effectiveness and external validity. Prev Med. 2015 Jan;70:3-13. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2014.11.001. Epub 2014 Nov 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25449692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gardiner PA, Eakin EG, Healy GN, Owen N. Feasibility of reducing older adults' sedentary time. Am J Prev Med. 2011 Aug;41(2):174-7. doi: 10.1016/j.amepre.2011.03.020.</citation>
    <PMID>21767725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kamani CH, Gencer B, Montecucco F, Courvoisier D, Vuilleumier N, Meyer P, Mach F. Stairs instead of elevators at the workplace decreases PCSK9 levels in a healthy population. Eur J Clin Invest. 2015 Oct;45(10):1017-24. doi: 10.1111/eci.12480. Epub 2015 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>26081791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Torbeyns T, Bailey S, Bos I, Meeusen R. Active workstations to fight sedentary behaviour. Sports Med. 2014 Sep;44(9):1261-73. doi: 10.1007/s40279-014-0202-x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24842828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 29, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 30, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 30, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 30, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Agnes Yuen-Kwan Lai</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Officer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>family well being,</keyword>
  <keyword>health</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

