<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02641782</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Uni-Koeln-1694</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02641782</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>NB2013-HR German (GPOH) / Dutch (DCOG) Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>NB2013-HR</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Phase 2 Trial Comparing Experimental Immunotherapy in Recurrent High Risk Neuroblastoma Patients With Standard Immunotherapy in Patients With Recurrent and Newly Diagnosed High Risk Neuroblastoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cologne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cologne</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Although the five year survival rate of children with high risk neuroblastoma have increased
      over the last three decades from 4 to 44 % (1), neuroblastoma is the second most frequent
      cause for cancer related death in childhood (11 %). Most patients show good initial response
      rates (complete (CR) and partial remission (PR) rate 95 %), but 55 % experience a largely
      treatment-resistant tumor progression.

      Recently, a breakthrough with immunotherapy was reported by US investigators from the
      Children's Oncology Group (2) using the anti-ganglioside D2 (GD2) monoclonal antibody ch14.18
      for tumor cell destruction and granulocyte macrophage-colony stimulating factor (GM-CSF) plus
      interleukin 2 (IL-2) for immunostimulation. This immune therapy resulted in an increase of 20
      % Event free survival (EFS) at 2 year from randomization. However, this was associated with a
      high toxicity rate (pain, capillary leak syndrome).

      The proposed trial compares the Childrens' Oncology Group (COG) &quot;standard of care&quot; arm
      (anti-GD2 + GM-CSF + IL-2 i.v. + retinoic acid oral) with an experimental arm (anti-GD2 +
      GM-CSF + IL-2 s.c. + retinoic acid oral) designed to reduce toxicity.

      The potential benefit from this trial consists of the confirmation that the American trial
      design is feasible in an independent set of patients with different preceding therapy, at a
      different time point regarding to immune reconstitution after autologous stem cell
      transplantation (ASCT), the feasibility of a newly designed immunotherapy (which is hopefully
      less toxic) and the investigation of immune response parameters. This pilot study is the
      prerequisite for a consecutive randomized clinical trial comparing two immunotherapeutic
      approaches in a larger set of patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Neuroblastoma is the second most frequent solid tumour (7.6%) and the second cause of cancer
      related death (11%) in childhood. In particular the large high risk (HR) group has remained a
      challenge to Paediatric Oncologists. Although the 5 year survival rates of children with HR
      disease have increased over the last 3 decades from 4 to 44.4%, the vast majority of those
      children will finally succumb to disease [1]. Most patients show good initial responses to
      chemotherapy (CR + PR-rate 95 %), but a majority experiences a highly treatment resistant
      tumour progression (55%). Therefore new therapeutic modalities are urgently needed.

      Recently, a randomized trial demonstrated that an immunotherapeutic concept using the
      anti-GD2 antibody ch14.18 together with interleukin 2, GM-CSF and retinoic acid improved the
      outcome of neuroblastoma patients which achieved CR or very good partial remission (VGPR)
      response to the preceding therapy. This treatment was associated with a high rate of toxic
      effects (neuropathic pain 52% of patients, capillary leak syndrome 23%). An earlier study
      using the antibody ch14.18 alone made comparable observations: pain despite of analgesia was
      seen in 33% of patients and severe capillary leak syndromes in 3 of 151 children. Differences
      of the reported frequencies are due to the different definitions of side effects.

      The investigators therefore propose a randomized clinical trial comparing the COG
      immunotherapy concept with newly designed hopefully equally effective but less toxic concept.
      This modifies the application route of IL-2 from i.v. to s.c. and increases the IL-2 dose to
      6.0 mio/m²xd (from 3.0 first week and 4.5 mio second week i.v.). Oral retinoic acid is used
      in both arms. The proposed randomized trial will answer the following questions:

      (i) Confirmation of the feasibility to apply the COG immunotherapy as consolidation treatment
      after a different remission induction therapy in patients with recurrent and de novo high
      risk neuroblastoma (ii) Investigation of the feasibility to apply the new immunotherapy
      concept in patients with recurrent high risk neuroblastoma (iii) Comparison of the toxicity
      of both immunotherapy regimens with the aim to reduce grade 2 - 4 toxicities in the
      experimental arm.

      (iv) Comparison of the immune response (antiidiotype antibodies, immune cell phenotypes,
      immune mediators, functional assays as antibody dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC) and
      complement dependent cytotoxicity (CDC) between treatment cycles (intraindividual), treatment
      arms (interindividual) and between recurrent and newly diagnosed patients (v) Comparison of
      pharmacokinetics of antibody ch14.18 in both arms (12.10.) (vi) Comparison of therapeutic
      efficacy by response evaluation at the end of the 25 week treatment (descriptive).

      (vii) Comparison of patients´ QoL experienced in both immunotherapy regimens as indicated by
      parents rating in appropriate questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Antibody supply was discontinued by United Therapeutics Corporation.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 30, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 23, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>toxic death or relevant grade 4 toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 7 months</time_frame>
    <description>Relevant grade 4 toxicities are defined as ascites, adult respiratory distress syndrome, capillary leak syndrome, cytokine release syndrome, dyspnea, hypotension, motor neuropathy, sensory neuropathy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of key side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 7 months</time_frame>
    <description>Key side effects are defined as capillary leak syndrome and cytokine release syndrome. Reduction is defined by at least 1 grade or score point or day less.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum of antibody-related pain</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 months</time_frame>
    <description>Neuralgia (with assessment of pain duration by days requiring morphine and maximum grade of pain scores during first 2 antibody cycles) will compared between both arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparative pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum plasma concentration of the antibody assessed during the first 2 months of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuroblastoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard IL-2 i.v. together with antibody ch14.18, GM-CSF and retinoic acid</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>IL-2 s.c. together with antibody ch14.18, GM-CSF and retinoic acid</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>antibody ch14.18</intervention_name>
    <description>17.5mg/m²d 10-20h i.v, d4-7 in cycles 1,3,5 and d8-11 in cycles 2,4.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Unituxin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GM-CSF</intervention_name>
    <description>250µg/m²xd, d1-14 s.c. or i.v (2h) in cycles 1,3,5</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sargramostim</other_name>
    <other_name>Leukine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IL-2 i.v.</intervention_name>
    <description>3.0 mio U/m²xd d1-4 continuous infusion i.v. and 4.5 mio U/m²xd d8-11 continuous infusion i.v. in cycles 2,4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Proleukin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IL-2 s.c.</intervention_name>
    <description>0.06 mio U/m² i.v. test dosis for 30min. i.v. at least 2h before first subcutaneous (s.c.) application. 6 mio U/m²xd d1-5 and 8-12 s.c. in cycles 2,4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Proleukin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Retinoic acid</intervention_name>
    <description>160mg/m²xd b.i.d.oral d 11-24 in cycles 1,3,5,6 and d15-28 in cycles 2,4</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>isotretinoin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Established diagnosis of neuroblastoma according to the international criteria (INSS)

          -  High risk (HR): stage 4 over 18 months of age and oncogen MYCN (MYCN) amplified
             neuroblastoma of any stage and any age until 25 years (recurrent disease (Germany and
             The Netherlands) after re-induction chemotherapy (+/- other modalities) or newly
             diagnosed disease (only The Netherlands):

          -  Complete front-line treatment including induction chemotherapy, radioisotope (mIBG)
             treatment, appropriate local therapy such as surgical removal and/ or local
             irradiation of the primary tumor and myeloablative chemotherapy with autologous stem
             cell reinfusion according to the actual guidelines of the GPOH/DCOG

          -  achieved response status: stable disease or better (CR, VGPR, PR, SD).

          -  Written informed consent of parents or guardian and - if appropriate - of the patient.

          -  For at least two weeks prior to start of trial medication off any standard or
             experimental treatment no tumour surgery no immediate requirements for palliative
             chemotherapy, radiotherapy or surgery

          -  The patient may have had prior central nervous system (CNS) metastases provided the
             following criteria are all met:

        The patient's CNS disease has been previously treated The patient's CNS disease has been
        clinically stable for four weeks prior to starting this study (assessed clinically and by
        MRI or CT) The patient is off steroids for four weeks prior to starting the study and will
        not require them during the course of the study A patient with seizure disorders may be
        enrolled if well controlled on anticonvulsants and if no seizures have occurred within a 6
        week period prior to starting trial treatment

          -  HIV sero-negative and neither active nor chronic-replicative hepatitis B infection

          -  Laboratory testing: The patients should have adequate functions of the cor, lung, bone
             marrow, liver, kidney

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frank Berthold, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cologne</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cologne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cologne</city>
        <zip>50924</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yu AL, Gilman AL, Ozkaynak MF, London WB, Kreissman SG, Chen HX, Smith M, Anderson B, Villablanca JG, Matthay KK, Shimada H, Grupp SA, Seeger R, Reynolds CP, Buxton A, Reisfeld RA, Gillies SD, Cohn SL, Maris JM, Sondel PM; Children's Oncology Group. Anti-GD2 antibody with GM-CSF, interleukin-2, and isotretinoin for neuroblastoma. N Engl J Med. 2010 Sep 30;363(14):1324-34. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0911123.</citation>
    <PMID>20879881</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Simon T, Hero B, Faldum A, Handgretinger R, Schrappe M, Niethammer D, Berthold F. Consolidation treatment with chimeric anti-GD2-antibody ch14.18 in children older than 1 year with metastatic neuroblastoma. J Clin Oncol. 2004 Sep 1;22(17):3549-57.</citation>
    <PMID>15337804</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Simon T, Hero B, Faldum A, Handgretinger R, Schrappe M, Klingebiel T, Berthold F. Long term outcome of high-risk neuroblastoma patients after immunotherapy with antibody ch14.18 or oral metronomic chemotherapy. BMC Cancer. 2011 Jan 18;11:21. doi: 10.1186/1471-2407-11-21.</citation>
    <PMID>21244693</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 12, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 29, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Cologne</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Frank Berthold</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>High Risk Neuroblastoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuroblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunoglobulins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tretinoin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isotretinoin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

