<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02643654</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HIDRA04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02643654</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MABp1 IN HIDRADENITIS SUPPURATIVA REFRACTORY TO ADALIMUMAB</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-blind, Randomised, Placebo-controlled Clinical Trial of the Efficacy of MABp1, a- First-in-class True Human Antibody Targeting Interleukin-1alpha, in Patients With Hidradenitis Suppurativa Not Eligible for antiTNF Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Evangelos J. Giamarellos-Bourboulis, M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hellenic Institute for the Study of Sepsis</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Athens</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hidradenitis suppurativa (HS) is a chronic inflammatory skin disorder. Although adalimumab is
      recently licensed for moderate to severe HS, many cases fail to respond or relapse during
      treatment. Favorable outcomes from a recently conducted double-blind randomized clinical
      study on the efficacy of anakinra, one interleukin(IL)-1alpha blocker, in hidradenitis
      suppurativa (HS), led to validate the efficacy of MABp1, a true human antiIL-1α antibody in
      these cases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hidradenitis suppurativa (HS) is a chronic devastating skin disorder affecting areas rich in
      apocrine glands. Nodules appear in the affected areas; they progressively become swollen and
      rupture with the release of pus. This process occurs repeatedly leading to sinus tract
      formation and scars. This disease course creates a frustrating situation not only for the
      patients but also for physicians. Traditional treatments comprise short-courses of
      antibiotics and surgical excision. However, relapse is the rule so that HS leads to severe
      impairment of the quality of life. The Dermatology Quality Life Index (DQLI) for HS is 8.9,
      being higher than any other skin disorder.

      This devastating disorder has often been neglected and considered a rare situation. However,
      HS seems to indiscriminately affect the global population. A large epidemiological survey in
      France reports 0.97% disease prevalence.

      The exact pathophysiology of HS is unknown. Both familial and non-familial cases of HS exist.
      Familial HS is less than 5% of cases and it is usually inherited through the dominant
      autosomal mode. Mutations in genes encoding for the gene complex of nicastrin-γ-secretase are
      predominant in hereditary HS. However, little is known on the genetic predisposition of
      non-familial HS that comprises the great majority of cases. Two studies by the investigators
      have been conducted to explore the predisposition of HS among patients who carry single
      nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) of gene encoding for pro-inflammatory cytokines namely TNF
      and IL-12RB1. Results have shown that carriage of haplotypes comprising minor frequency SNP
      alleles at the promoter region of TNF increases the likelihood for HS; furthermore these
      patients are less likely to respond to treatment with anti-TNF agents. In parallel,
      haplotyping for gene SNPs of exon 7 and exon 10 of IL-12RB1 comprising seven constitutive
      SNPs has shown that carriage of the h2 haplotype composed by four minor frequency SNP alleles
      is associated with more severe disease phenotypes. These results indicate a strong component
      of the implication of the innate immune responses in the pathogenesis of HS. In conjunction
      with this and following a successful phase II trial, the two phase III PIONEER studies ended
      up with significant improvement of patients after 12 weeks of treatment with adalimumab. A
      novel score, HS clinical response (HiSCR) score, was introduced in these trials and it is now
      suggested for the evaluation of the efficacy of any new formulation in HS. Using this score,
      it was found that the success rate of adalimumab to achieve a positive HiSCR after 12 weeks
      of treatment ranged between 40 and 60%. This means that several patients do not respond to
      adalimumab treatment whereas others may relapse after some initial response.

      The investigators have recently concluded a phase 2, double-blind, randomized study of the
      efficacy of anakinra treatment administered 100mg subcutaneously daily for 12 consecutive
      weeks compared to placebo in 19 patients; 10 were allocated to the placebo arm and nine to
      the anakinra arm (EudraCT2011-005145-12, www.clinicaltrials.gov NCT01558375). Results were
      favorable for the clinical efficacy of anakinra. The primary endpoint defined to be disease
      activity was marginally achieved in the modified intent-to-treat population. Regarding the
      secondary endpoints, treatment with anakinra was very effective in: a) prolonging the time to
      new exacerbation compared to the placebo arm; and b) modulating cytokine stimulation from
      peripheral blood mononuclear cells. More precisely, the production of interferon-γ was
      significantly decreased and the production of IL-22 was increased compared to the placebo
      arm. HiSCR score was not initially included as a study endpoint because this score has not
      been developed when the trial was submitted to the authorities. Retrospective validation of
      the HiSCR score showed significant reduction at week 12 in 7 patients (77.8%) treated with
      anakinra compared to three patients (30%) treated with placebo (p: 0.039).

      The considerable efficacy of anakinra that blocks interleukin (IL)-1alpha (IL-1α) leads to
      consider a significant role of IL-1α in the pathogenesis of HS. MABp1 is a first-in-class
      true human monoclonal antibody cloned directly from a human B lymphocyte and specifically
      targets IL-1α. Results from a first-in-man trial were recently published, in which fifty-two
      patients with metastatic cancer were enrolled in an open-label phase 1 study. The drug was
      well-tolerated, tumor responses were observed, and interestingly, treatment was accompanied
      by an increase of lean body weight.

      The purpose of this clinical study is to evaluate the safety and the efficacy of MABp1
      compared to placebo in patients with moderate to severe HS who either failed previous
      treatment with antiTNF regimens or who relapsed under antiTNF regimens or who are treatment
      naïve and they are unwilling to receive subcutaneous adalimumab treatment. The rationale
      behind the promising success of MABp1 relies on recent findings showing heterogeneity of
      cytokines in skin lesions with several patients expressing huge concentrations of TNFα the
      lesions and other who express low concentrations of TNFα but huge concentrations of IL-1α.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The efficacy of MABp1 in patients with moderate to severe HS</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by the difference of achievement of positive HiSCR score between the treatment group and the comparator placebo group at week 12.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The long-term efficacy of MABp1 in patients with moderate to severe HS</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by the difference of achievement of positive HiSCR score between the treatment group and the comparator placebo group at week 24. Analysis will also be done separately for patients with previous failure or relapse under antiTNF and for patients without previous antiTNF treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The short-and long-term efficacy of MABp1 in the quality of life of patients with moderate to severe HS</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by the comparisons of dermatology life quality index on all study visits taking also into account the visual analogue scale. Analysis will also be done separately for patients with previous failure or relapse under antiTNF and for patients without previous antiTNF treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The short-and long-term efficacy of MABp1 in individual lesions of patients with moderate to severe HS</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by the comparisons of modified Sartorius score on all study visits. Analysis will also be done separately for patients with previous failure or relapse under antiTNF and for patients without previous antiTNF treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of MAbp1 on the time to new exacerbation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by comparing the time to new exacerbation from week 0 between the two groups of treatment. Analysis will also be done separately for patients with previous failure or relapse under antiTNF and for patients without previous antiTNF treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of MAbp1 on the ultrasonographic findings of the skin lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by comparing the changes of skin lesions at week 12 between the two groups of treatment. Analysis will also be done separately for patients with previous failure or relapse under antiTNF and for patients without previous antiTNF treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Hidradenitis Suppurativa</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The placebo product is manufactured following the same procedures and batch records used to manufacture the MABp1 drug product. The placebo dosage form is a sterile isotonic formulation buffer at pH 6.2-6.5. Each 10-ml Type I borosilicate glass serum vial contains 6mL of the formulation buffer, and is sealed with a 20-mm Daikyo Flurotec butyl rubber stopper and flip-off aluminum seal.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MABp1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>MABp1 is a recombinant human IgG1 monoclonal antibody specific for human interleukin-1α (IL-1α). The entire MABp1 heavy and light chain sequences are identical to those found in naturally-occurring human IgG1κ, with the light and heavy chain variable regions being identical to those originally expressed by a peripheral blood B lymphocyte that was obtained from a healthy individual. It is a sterile injectable liquid formulation of 50 mg/mL MABp1 in a stabilizing isotonic buffer (pH 6.4). Each 10-mL serum vial contains 6 ml of the formulation, and is sealed with a 20-mm grey bromobutyl stopper and flip-off aluminum seal</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MABp1</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a sterile injectable liquid formulation of 50 mg/mL MABp1 in a stabilizing isotonic buffer (pH 6.4). Each 10-mL serum vial contains 6 ml of the formulation, and is sealed with a 20-mm grey bromobutyl stopper and flip-off aluminum seal</description>
    <arm_group_label>MABp1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo dosage form is a sterile isotonic formulation buffer at pH 6.2-6.5. Each 10-ml Type I borosilicate glass serum vial contains 6mL of the formulation buffer, and is sealed with a 20-mm Daikyo Flurotec butyl rubber stopper and flip-off aluminum seal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent provided by the patient

          -  Age equal to or more than 18 years

          -  Diagnosis of hidradenitis suppurativa (HS)

          -  HS of Hurley II or III stage disease or rapidly progressive HS of Hurley I stage

          -  Presence of at least 3 inflamed nodules consistent with HS in the body

          -  At least one of the following: a) previous failure of treatment with any anti-TNF
             regimen; b) previous relapse under treatment with any anti-TNF regimen; c)
             unwillingness to receive subcutaneous adalimumab treatment

        Note: Since rapidly progressive HS of Hurley I stage as defined below is not a licensed
        indication for adalimumab, these patients can be enrolled irrespective or not of a history
        of previous adalimumab treatment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of systemic lupus erythematosus

          -  Treatment with any biologicals or investigational agents within the last 4 weeks (or 5
             half-lives, whichever is longer).

          -  History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions to human, humanized, chimeric, or
             murine monoclonal antibodies.

          -  Administration of any live (attenuated) vaccine over the last 4 weeks

          -  History of recurrent vein thrombosis or embolism compatible with anti-cardiolipin
             syndrome

          -  Any present serious bacterial infection namely pneumonia, endocarditis, acute
             pyelonephritis and intrabdominal infection. These patients can be enrolled once the
             attending physicians confirm cure by the infection

          -  Hepatic dysfunction defined as any value of transaminases, of γ-glutamyl
             transpeptidase or of bilirubin&gt; 2 x upper normal limit

          -  History of haematological or solid tumor malignancy, arterial hypertension, liver
             cirrhosis, HIV infection, and hepatitis virus B or C infection

          -  History of episodes mimicking demyelinating disorders or a definite diagnosis of
             multiple sclerosis

          -  Any creatinine value above 1.5 mg/dl

          -  Intake of corticosteroids defined as daily intake of prednisone or equivalent more
             than 1mg/kg for the last three weeks

          -  Neutropenia defined as &lt;1000 neutrophils/mm3

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  History of tuberculosis (latent or active). This will be excluded according to the
             procedure defined in the screening of patients (see below)

          -  Major surgery within 28 days prior to Day 0

          -  It is explicitly stated that intake of antimicrobials for HS is not an exclusion
             criterion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Evangelos Giamarellos-Bourboulis, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Hellenic Institute for the Study of Sepsis</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dimitrios Boumpas, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Athens</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>4th Department of Internal Medicine, ATTIKON University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <zip>12462</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tzanetakou V, Kanni T, Giatrakou S, Katoulis A, Papadavid E, Netea MG, Dinarello CA, van der Meer JWM, Rigopoulos D, Giamarellos-Bourboulis EJ. Safety and Efficacy of Anakinra in Severe Hidradenitis Suppurativa: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Dermatol. 2016 Jan;152(1):52-59. doi: 10.1001/jamadermatol.2015.3903.</citation>
    <PMID>26579854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kimball AB, Jemec GB, Yang M, Kageleiry A, Signorovitch JE, Okun MM, Gu Y, Wang K, Mulani P, Sundaram M. Assessing the validity, responsiveness and meaningfulness of the Hidradenitis Suppurativa Clinical Response (HiSCR) as the clinical endpoint for hidradenitis suppurativa treatment. Br J Dermatol. 2014 Dec;171(6):1434-42. doi: 10.1111/bjd.13270. Epub 2014 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25040429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kanni T, Tzanetakou V, Savva A, Kersten B, Pistiki A, van de Veerdonk FL, Netea MG, van der Meer JW, Giamarellos-Bourboulis EJ. Compartmentalized Cytokine Responses in Hidradenitis Suppurativa. PLoS One. 2015 Jun 19;10(6):e0130522. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0130522. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26091259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelekis NL, Efstathopoulos E, Balanika A, Spyridopoulos TN, Pelekanou A, Kanni T, Savva A, Brountzos E, Giamarellos-Bourboulis EJ. Ultrasound aids in diagnosis and severity assessment of hidradenitis suppurativa. Br J Dermatol. 2010 Jun;162(6):1400-2. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2133.2010.09710.x. Epub 2010 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>20184586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 29, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 31, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Athens</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Evangelos J. Giamarellos-Bourboulis, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Internal Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>interleukin-1alpha</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hidradenitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hidradenitis Suppurativa</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

