<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02644044</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0166-15-TLV</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02644044</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intrathecal Methotrexate for Progressive Multiple Sclerosis: An Open Label Single Arm Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>ITMTXPMS</acronym>
  <official_title>Intrathecal Methotrexate for Progressive Multiple Sclerosis: An Open Label Single Arm Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple sclerosis (MS) is characterized pathologically by demyelination, axonal loss, and
      glial scar formation. Clinically, most patients have a relapsing-remitting course of MS
      (RRMS) that over time may become progressive without remissions - a secondary progressive MS
      (SPMS). About 15% of patients have a progressive course from onset which is called primary
      progressive (PP).

      Currently, there is no approved treatment for PPMS and for SPMS only therapy with
      mitoxantrone showed mild effect. Thus, more effective therapies need to be developed for
      treatment of SPMS and PPMS.

      Methotrexate (MTX), an anti-metabolite, has been in clinical use since 1948 when it was found
      to produce temporary remission of acute childhood leukemia.

      There are accumulating evidences that in progressive MS patients there are follicular
      lymphoid structures in the meninges and in the Virchow-Robin spaces. Therefore, intrathecal
      therapy may target the pathological follicular lymphoid activity.

      The safety of intrathecal MTX (ITMTX) has been demonstrated by its widespread use in treating
      lymphoproliferative diseases and leptomeningeal metastases. Sadik et. Al. reported about the
      feasibility and safety of using intrathecal methotrexate (ITMTX) as a treatment for
      unresponsive patients with progressive forms of MS. In their open label study they found that
      ITMTX may have a beneficial effect in progressive forms of MS and that it was well tolerated
      with no serious adverse events.

      The investigators aim is to evaluate the efficacy , safety and tolerability of intrathecal
      methotrexate administration every 3 months in progressive 30 patients with progressive MS.
      The investigators will evaluate clinical, laboratory evaluation of the blood and
      cerebrospinal fluid as well as the MRI scans of the participants. Each patient will be
      treated 4 times for 1 year with the option to continue for another 1 more year with the same
      protocol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Protocol Intrathecal Methotrexate for Progressive Multiple Sclerosis: An Open Label Single
      Arm Study

      Introduction Multiple sclerosis (MS) is characterized pathologically by demyelination, axonal
      loss, and glial scar formation. Clinically, most patients have a relapsing-remitting course
      of MS (RRMS) that over time may become progressive without remissions - a secondary
      progressive MS (SPMS). About 15% of patients have a progressive course from onset which is
      called primary progressive (PP) (1). In the past decades, several treatments have been
      approved mainly for the use in RRMS.

      Treatments for SPMS may be still effective for the early phase of this course, but it become
      ineffective for the later phase of SPMS (2,3) For PPMS, there is currently no approved
      treatment. Thus, more effective therapies need to be developed for treatment of SPMS and
      PPMS.

      Methotrexate (MTX), an anti-metabolite, has been in clinical use since 1948 when it was found
      to produce temporary remission of acute childhood leukemia. Methotrexate irreversibly binds
      to and inhibits dihydrofolate reductase, inhibiting the formation of reduced folate, and
      thymidylate synthetase, resulting in inhibition of purine and thymidylic acid synthesis, thus
      interfering with DNA synthesis, repair, and cellular replication.

      Because of its indirect immunosuppressive effects, MTX is used in treating autoimmune
      conditions such as rheumatoid arthritis and psoriasis (4). Low dose oral MTX (7.5 mg weekly)
      was found to be mildly effective, in slowing the deterioration in patients with SPMS (5).

      There are accumulating evidences that in progressive MS patients there are follicular
      lymphoid structures in the meninges and in the Virchow-Robin spaces (8). These follicles are
      enriched in lymphocytes and dendritic cells which may drive the CNS inflammatory responses in
      the disease. This CNS restricted immune response may be unaffected by systemic
      immunomodulation and immunosuppressive therapies. Therefore, intrathecal therapy may target
      the pathological follicular lymphoid activity.

      The safety of intrathecal MTX (ITMTX) has been demonstrated by its widespread use in treating
      lymphoproliferative diseases and leptomeningeal metastases (9). Sadik et. Al. reported about
      the feasibility and safety of using intrathecal methotrexate (ITMTX) as a treatment for
      unresponsive patients with progressive forms of MS (10). In their open label study they found
      that ITMTX may have a beneficial effect in progressive forms of MS and that it was well
      tolerated with no serious adverse events.

      In the Last year the investigators have treated 8 patients with IT MTX according to the
      proposed protocol. Until now these patients receive 1-3 therapies of IT MTX without
      significance adverse event. The adverse event was were reported were: fatigue for several
      days post therapy and mild headache.

      Objective The investigators aim is to evaluate the efficacy , safety and tolerability of
      intrathecal methotrexate administration in progressive MS patients.

      Methods Study Population 30 progressive MS patients Inclusion Criteria

        -  Age 18-750 years

        -  Clinically definite diagnosis of MS according to McDonald criteria 2010.

        -  Progressive disease form defined by confirmed expanded disability status scale (EDSS)
           progression without relapse by at least 0.5 point or greater in the six months prior to
           enrollment.

      Exclusion criteria

        -  Pregnancy

        -  Active infection

        -  Significant associated medical condition such as malignancy, heart disease or concurrent
           other autoimmune condition.

        -  Known allergy to MTX.

        -  WBC&lt;4000 cells/µL

        -  Lym&lt;800 cells/µL

        -  Treated with fingolimod or natalizumab 3 months prior to enrollment

      Treatment The physician will administer 12.5 mg of MTX diluted to a concentration of up to 4
      mg/mL in 0.9 percent sodium chloride with 4 mg Dexamethasone via lumbar puncture needle.
      These doses are standard doses of IT treatment with MTX.

      Treatments will be scheduled 3 months apart for 1 year .A tota of 4 treatments in a 1 year.

      A CBC with differential will be obtained before each treatment to assess the level of
      hematological suppression.

      Evaluation A. Patients will be evaluated every 3 months by a physician other then their
      treating physician with the following: Kurtzke Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS). 25 FW
      , 9 PHT, Symbol Digit Modalities Test (SDMT), fatigue scale (FSS) and depression scale (BDI).
      In each of the visits the patient will be asked about adverse events (AE) and will be
      instructed to report us every AE/ medical complain he will experience between visits.

      AEs will be followed until resolution or through completion of the study, whichever comes
      first. All Serious adverse events (SAEs) will be followed until event resolution, until the
      condition stabilizes, until the event is otherwise explained, or until the subject is lost to
      follow-up. The investigator is responsible for ensuring that follow-up includes any
      supplemental investigations as may be reasonably indicated to elucidate the nature and/or
      causality of the SAE. Any follow-up information regarding SAEs must be reported to the
      Helsinki committee within 24 hours.

      Treatment The physician will administer 12.5 mg of MTX diluted to a concentration of up to 4
      mg/mL in 0.9 percent sodium chloride with 4 mg Dexamethasone via lumbar puncture needle.
      These doses are standard doses of IT treatment with MTX.

      Treatments will be scheduled 3 months apart for 1 year .A tota of 4 treatments in a 1 year.

      A CBC with differential will be obtained before each treatment to assess the level of
      hematological suppression.

      Laboratory test After obtaining informed consent to perform the procedure, a physician will
      perform a lumbar puncture with a 25 gauge needle and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) sample will be
      obtained and analyze for parameters including cell count and differential, protein and
      glucose concentration, oligoclonal bands, IgG concentration, cellular analysis by flow
      cytometry for CD3+, CD20+, CD14+ cell subsets, and measurement of several soluble mediators
      such as: CXCL13, CD23, light chains, TNFa, IFNg, IL-17, IL-2, IL-10, BDNF and Neurofilaments
      will be studied by ELISA

      MRI scan Brain MRI scan will be done within 1 week before each treatment. The MRI protocol
      includes the following sequences: T1, T2, FLAIR, T1 will gadolinium, DTI.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in disability ( Multiple Sclerosis Functional Composite (MSFC)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Disability will be measured every visit by the Multiple Sclerosis Functional Composite (MSFC)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability (adverse events)</measure>
    <time_frame>each adverse event will be followed up until resolution</time_frame>
    <description>adverse events will be followed until resolution. Serious adverse events will be reported to the IRB within 24 hours of noticed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in brain MRI measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>(Composite measure) We will measure new gd+ enhancing lesions, number of lesions, brain and upper spinal cord atrophy and cortical thickness and compare these measure between the time before and after treatment along. Overall each participant will undergo 5 scans , the first before treatment installation and then before each treatment . one scan will be done 3 month after the last treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>(Composite measure) Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) sample will be obtained and analyze for parameters including cell count and differential, protein and glucose concentration, oligoclonal bands, IgG concentration, cellular analysis by flow cytometry for CD3+, CD20+, CD14+ cell subsets, and measurement of several soluble mediators such as: CXCL13, CD23, light chains, TNFa, IFNg, IL-17, IL-2, IL-10, BDNF and Neurofilaments will be studied by ELISA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>To Evaluate the Effect of Therapy With IT MTX on the Disease Course of Patients With Progressive MS</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment with IT methotrexate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intrathecal methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>12.5 mg of methotrexate diluted to a concentration of up to 4 mg/mL in 0.9 percent sodium chloride with 4 mg Dexamethasone via lumbar puncture needle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-75 years

          -  Clinically definite diagnosis of MS according to McDonald criteria 2010.

          -  Progressive disease form defined by confirmed expanded disability status scale (EDSS)
             progression without relapse by at least 0.5 point or greater in the six months prior
             to enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Active infection

          -  Significant associated medical condition such as malignancy, heart disease or
             concurrent other autoimmune condition.

          -  Known allergy to MTX.

          -  WBC&lt;4000 cells/µL

          -  Lym&lt;800 cells/µL

          -  Treated with fingolimod or natalizumab 3 months prior to enrollment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Arnon Karni, MD</last_name>
    <phone>052-4266733</phone>
    <email>arnonk@tlvmc.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Oren Weintraub, MPHA</last_name>
    <phone>03-6915138</phone>
    <email>orenw@tlvmc.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sadiq SA (2005) Multiple sclerosis. In: Rowland LP (ed) Merritt's neurology, 11th edn. Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, Philadelphia, pp 941-963</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goodkin DE, Rudick RA, VanderBrug Medendorp S, Daughtry MM, Schwetz KM, Fischer J, Van Dyke C. Low-dose (7.5 mg) oral methotrexate reduces the rate of progression in chronic progressive multiple sclerosis. Ann Neurol. 1995 Jan;37(1):30-40.</citation>
    <PMID>7818255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hartung HP, Gonsette R, König N, Kwiecinski H, Guseo A, Morrissey SP, Krapf H, Zwingers T; Mitoxantrone in Multiple Sclerosis Study Group (MIMS). Mitoxantrone in progressive multiple sclerosis: a placebo-controlled, double-blind, randomised, multicentre trial. Lancet. 2002 Dec 21-28;360(9350):2018-25.</citation>
    <PMID>12504397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American College of Rheumatology Subcommittee on Rheumatoid Arthritis Guidelines. Guidelines for the management of rheumatoid arthritis: 2002 Update. Arthritis Rheum. 2002 Feb;46(2):328-46.</citation>
    <PMID>11840435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashtari F, Savoj MR. Effects of low dose methotrexate on relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis in comparison to Interferon β-1α: A randomized controlled trial. J Res Med Sci. 2011 Apr;16(4):457-62.</citation>
    <PMID>22091259</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Currier RD, Haerer AF, Meydrech EF. Low dose oral methotrexate treatment of multiple sclerosis: a pilot study. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 1993 Nov;56(11):1217-8. Erratum in: J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry 1994 Apr;57(4):528.</citation>
    <PMID>8229034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Magliozzi R, Howell O, Vora A, Serafini B, Nicholas R, Puopolo M, Reynolds R, Aloisi F. Meningeal B-cell follicles in secondary progressive multiple sclerosis associate with early onset of disease and severe cortical pathology. Brain. 2007 Apr;130(Pt 4):1089-104.</citation>
    <PMID>17438020</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siegal T, Lossos A, Pfeffer MR. Leptomeningeal metastases: analysis of 31 patients with sustained off-therapy response following combined-modality therapy. Neurology. 1994 Aug;44(8):1463-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8058150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sadiq SA, Simon EV, Puccio LM. Intrathecal methotrexate treatment in multiple sclerosis. J Neurol. 2010 Nov;257(11):1806-11. doi: 10.1007/s00415-010-5614-4. Epub 2010 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>20532907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 28, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 31, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 28, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 28, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 31, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>michal roll</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director R&amp;D Division</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Progressive multiple sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>methotrexate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease Progression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

