<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02649790</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KCP-8602-801</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02649790</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of KPT-8602 in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Cancer Indications</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1/2 Open-Label Study of the Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of the Selective Inhibitor of Nuclear Export (SINE) Compound KPT-8602 in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Cancer Indications</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karyopharm Therapeutics Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karyopharm Therapeutics Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a first-in-human, multi-center, open-label clinical study with separate dose
      escalation (Phase 1) and expansion (Phase 2) stages to assess preliminary safety,
      tolerability, and efficacy of the second generation oral XPO1 inhibitor KPT-8602 in patients
      with relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma (MM), colorectal cancer (CRC), metastatic
      castration resistant prostate cancer (mCRPC), and higher risk myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS).

      Dose escalation and dose expansion may be included for all parts of the study as determined
      by ongoing study results.

      This study is currently closed for enrollment for patients with relapsed/refractory multiple
      myeloma (MM) or colorectal cancer (CRC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate dose limiting toxicities of KPT-8602</measure>
    <time_frame>From first dose through Cycle 1- 28 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">103</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma (MM)</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer (CRC)</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Castration Resistant Prostate Cancer (mCRPC)</condition>
  <condition>Higher Risk Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>KPT-8602</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Multiple myeloma 5-60mg monotherapy, 20mg KPT-8602 + low dose dexamethasone, 30mg KPT-8602 + low dose dexamethasone
starting dose for CRC,mCRPC, MDS is 20 mg KPT-8602</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>KPT-8602</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>KPT-8602</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA

          1. Written informed consent obtained prior to any screening procedures and in accordance
             with federal, local, and institutional guidelines.

          2. Age ≥ 18 years.

          3. Adequate hepatic function:

             a. total bilirubin ≤ 2 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) (except patients with
             Gilbert's syndrome [hereditary indirect hyperbilirubinemia] who must have a total
             bilirubin of ≤ 3 times ULN), b. aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 times ULN (except patients with known liver involvement
             of their tumor who must have their AST and ALT ≤ 5.0 times ULN).

          4. Adequate renal function: estimated creatinine clearance of ≥ 30 mL/min, calculated
             using the formula of Cockcroft and Gault (140-Age) • Mass (kg)/(72 • creatinine
             mg/dL); multiply by 0.85 if female.

          5. Contraception:

               1. RRMM, CRC, and higher risk MDS patients: Female patients of child-bearing
                  potential must agree to use dual methods of contraception (including one highly
                  effective and one effective method of contraception) and have a negative serum
                  pregnancy test at Screening, and male patients must use an effective barrier
                  method of contraception if sexually active with a female of child-bearing
                  potential. For both male and female patients, effective methods of contraception
                  must be used throughout the study and for 3 months following the last dose.

               2. RR mCRPC patients: Patients must use an effective barrier method of contraception
                  if sexually active with a female of child-bearing potential. Effective methods of
                  contraception must be used throughout the study and for 3 months following the
                  last dose.

             INDICATION-SPECIFIC INCLUSION CRITERIA

             Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma (Parts A1, A2, and B):

          6. Symptomatic, histologically confirmed MM and evidence of disease progression, based on
             IMWG guidelines.

          7. Patients must have measurable disease as defined by at least one of the following:

               -  Serum M-protein ≥ 0.5 g/dL by serum protein electrophoresis (SPEP) or for
                  immunoglobulin (Ig) A myeloma, by quantitative IgA. If SPEP is felt to be
                  unreliable for routine M-protein measurement (e.g., for patients with IgA MM),
                  then quantitative Ig levels by nephelometry; or

               -  Urinary M-protein excretion at least 200 mg/24 hours; or

               -  Serum free light chain (FLC) whereby the involved light chain measures ≥10 mg/dL
                  and with an abnormal ratio.

          8. Previously treated with ≥ 3 prior regimens (lines of therapy) that included at least
             one of each of the following: an immunomodulatory drug, a proteasome inhibitor, and a
             steroid.

          9. MM refractory to the patient's most recent anti-MM regimen.

         10. Patients receiving hematopoietic growth factor support including erythropoietin,
             darbepoetin, granulocyte-colony stimulating factor, granulocyte macrophage-colony
             stimulating factor, and platelet stimulators can continue to do so, but must be
             transfusion independent for at least one (1) week prior to Cycle 1 Day 1 (C1D1) in the
             study.

         11. Adequate hematopoietic function: total white blood cell (WBC) count ≥ 1500/mm3,
             absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 800/mm3, hemoglobin (Hb) ≥ 8.0 g/dL, and platelet
             count ≥ 75,000/mm3.

         12. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of ≤ 1.

         13. Life expectancy of ≥ 4 months.

             Relapsed/Refractory Colorectal Cancer (Part C):

         14. Histological or cytological documentation of adenocarcinoma of the colon or rectum.

         15. Measurable disease by RECIST v1.1.

         16. Metastatic disease not suitable for upfront curative-intent surgery.

         17. Patients with site-defined KRAS status (wild-type or mutant) from a fresh or archival
             tumor biopsy prior to enrollment.

               1. All patients must be willing to have fresh biopsies to obtain tumor tissue for
                  biomarker analysis.

         18. Documented evidence of progressive disease according to RECIST v1.1.

         19. Prior treatment (with completion of a course of therapy, or to disease progression or
             intolerability) with each of the following:

               1. Fluoropyrimidine-, oxaliplatin-, irinotecan-based chemotherapies (e.g., FOLFOX
                  and FOLFIRI)

               2. An anti-EGFR therapy, if KRAS wild-type

               3. Prior third line treatment with regorafenib or TAS‑102; will be assessed on an
                  individual basis

                  • Note: The requirement for prior third line regorafenib will be assessed on an
                  individual basis by the Investigator in consultation with the Karyopharm Medical
                  Monitor

               4. Radiation and surgery are not considered as prior anticancer regimens

         20. Patients should not be transfusion dependent.

         21. Adequate hematopoietic function: ANC ≥ 1000/mm3, hemoglobin (Hb) ≥ 9.0 g/dL, and
             platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm3.

         22. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of ≤ 1.

         23. Life expectancy of ≥ 4 months.

             Relapsed/Refractory Metastatic Castration Resistant Prostate Cancer (Parts D and E):

         24. Histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate with archival tumor tissue
             available for molecular analyses. If the patient does not have a prior histological
             diagnosis, then a fresh biopsy at screening may be used for this purpose.

             a. Optional: All patients will be asked to have fresh biopsies to obtain tumor tissue
             for biomarker analysis.

         25. Surgically or medically castrated, with testosterone levels of &lt;50 ng/dL (&lt;2.0 nM). If
             the patient is being treated with luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone (LHRH)
             agonists (patient who have not undergone orchiectomy), and patients must have shown to
             progress on this per inclusion criterion 26.

         26. Documented mCRPC progression as assessed by the Investigator with one of the
             following:

               1. Prostate specific antigen (PSA) progression defined by a minimum of 3 rising PSA
                  levels (at approximately Day -30 and approximately Day -45) with an interval of
                  &gt;1 week between each determination. The PSA values at the Screening visit should
                  be &gt;2 μg/L (&gt;2 ng/mL); patients on systemic glucocorticoids for control of
                  symptoms must have documented PSA progression by Prostate Cancer Working Group 3
                  (PCWG3) while on systemic glucocorticoids prior to commencing C1D1 of treatment.

               2. Radiographic progression of soft tissue disease by modified RECIST criteria 1.1
                  or of bone metastasis with 2 or more documented new bone lesions on a bone scan
                  with or without PSA progression.

         27. Initial response (per modified PCWG3 Guidelines) to second generation anti-hormonal
             therapy (examples: abiraterone, enzalutamide, TAK 700), but later relapsed. Disease
             relapse would be defined as progressive disease at the time of entry per inclusion
             criterion 26.

         28. Zero to 2 previous taxane-based chemotherapy regimens. If docetaxel chemotherapy is
             used more than once, this will be considered as one regimen. Patients may have had
             prior exposure to cabazitaxel treatment. Patients may be taxane naïve.

         29. At least 2 weeks from completion of any radiotherapy including a single fraction of
             radiotherapy for the purposes of palliation (confined to one field) is permitted.

         30. Patients should not be transfusion dependent.

         31. Albumin &gt;2.5 g/dL.

         32. Adequate hematopoietic function: ANC ≥ 1000/mm3, hemoglobin (Hb) ≥ 9.0 g/dL, and
             platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm3.

         33. Part E only: Patients currently receiving treatment with abiraterone and appropriate
             to continue in the opinion of the Investigator. Patients must also have been on and
             continue on a stable dose of corticosteroids (prednisone or dexamethasone) for 30 days
             prior to C1D1.

         34. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of ≤ 1.

         35. Life expectancy of ≥ 4 months.

             Higher Risk Myelodysplastic Syndrome (Part F):

         36. Documented diagnosis of MDS with 5-19% myeloblasts, (MDS-EB-2 by the 2016 WHO
             classification).

               -  The marrow histopathology must be documented by recent bone marrow biopsy

               -  Patients should be intermediate-2 or high-risk MDS by International Prognostic
                  Scoring System (IPSS)

         37. Patients believed to be IPSS high risk, without clearly meeting IPSS categories above
             should be discussed with the Medical Monitor prior to enrolling. This includes
             patients with unusual cytogenetic patterns, or those who would normally be high risk
             by International Prognostic Scoring System-Revised (IPSS-R).

         38. Documented evidence of progressive disease as defined by the 2006 International
             Working Group (IWG) Response Criteria for MDS. This includes hypomethylating agent
             failures (HMA).

         39. HMA refractory patients including:

               1. ≥2 cycles of azacitidine and/or decitabine or experimental agents (such as
                  SGI-110 or ASTX727 or similar) with clear progressive disease (PD) (no count
                  recovery with ≥50% increase in bone marrow blasts)

                  OR

               2. ≥4 cycles of azacitidine and/or decitabine (or other hypomethylating therapy)
                  with lack of improvement (no CR/CRi/PR/HI).

         40. Patients receiving a stable dose of erythropoiesis-stimulating agent (ESA) for at
             least 1 month at the time of study entry may continue to receive ESA, but changes in
             dosing of ESA or new start of ESA in less than 30 days are not permitted.

         41. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of ≤ 2.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

        Patients in All Parts of the Study:

          1. Female patients who are pregnant or lactating.

          2. Major surgery within 4 weeks before C1D1.

          3. Impaired cardiac function or clinically significant cardiac diseases, including any of
             the following:

               1. Unstable angina or acute myocardial infarction ≤ 3 months prior to C1D1;

               2. Clinically significant heart disease (e.g., symptomatic congestive heart failure
                  [e.g., &gt;NYHA Class 2]; uncontrolled arrhythmia, or hypertension; history of
                  labile hypertension or poor compliance with an antihypertensive regimen).

          4. Uncontrolled active severe systemic infection requiring parenteral antibiotics,
             antivirals, or antifungals within one week prior to C1D1.

          5. Patients with known symptomatic brain metastasis are not suitable for enrollment.
             Patients with asymptomatic, stable, treated brain metastases are eligible for study
             entry.

          6. Patients with a known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV); HIV testing is
             not required as part of this study.

          7. Known, active hepatitis A, B, or C infection; or known to be positive for HCV RNA or
             HBsAg (HBV surface antigen).

          8. Prior malignancies:

               1. Patients in All Parts of the Study: Patients with adequately resected basal or
                  squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or adequately resected carcinoma in situ
                  (i.e. cervix) may enroll irrespective of the time of diagnosis.

               2. Patients with Relapsed/refractory MM, CRC, and mCRPC only: Prior malignancies
                  which may interfere with the interpretation of the study. Cancer treated with
                  curative intent &lt; 5 years previously will not be allowed unless approved by the
                  Sponsor. Cancer treated with curative intent &gt; 5 years previously and without
                  evidence of recurrence will be allowed.

               3. Patients with Higher Risk MDS only: Concomitant malignancies or previous
                  malignancies with less than a 1-year disease free interval at the time of
                  enrollment.

          9. Patients with active central nervous system (CNS) malignancy. Patients who have only
             had prophylactic intrathecal or intravenous chemotherapy against CNS disease are
             eligible.

         10. Patients with gastrointestinal tract disease (or uncontrolled vomiting or diarrhea)
             that could interfere with the absorption of KPT-8602.

         11. Serious psychiatric or medical conditions that, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             could interfere with treatment, compliance, or the ability to give consent.

         12. Patients unwilling to comply with the protocol including required biopsies and sample
             collections required to measure disease.

        INDICATION-SPECIFIC EXCLUSION CRITERIA

        Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma (Parts A1, A2, and B):

        13. Time since the last prior therapy for treatment of RRMM:

          1. Radiation, chemotherapy, immunotherapy or any other anticancer therapy, including
             investigational anticancer therapy ≤ 2 weeks prior to C1D1.

          2. Palliative steroids for disease related symptoms are allowed up to 3 days prior to
             C1D1.

          3. Patients must have recovered or stabilized (≤ Grade 1 or to their baseline) from
             toxicities related to their previous treatment except for alopecia.

             14. Patients with active graft versus host disease after allogeneic stem cell
             transplantation. At least 3 months must have elapsed since completion of allogeneic
             stem cell transplantation 15. Grade &gt; 2 peripheral neuropathy or Grade 2 peripheral
             neuropathy with pain within 2 weeks prior to C1D1.

             Relapsed/Refractory Colorectal Cancer (Part C):

             16. Radiotherapy, chemotherapy, or any other anticancer therapy, including
             investigational anticancer therapy, within 2 weeks prior to Screening. Patients must
             have recovered from clinically significant toxicities. The site of irradiation should
             have evidence of progressive disease (new lesions or increase in lesion size) if this
             is the only site of disease.

             17. Patients who have been treated with their most recent chemotherapy or
             investigational drugs ≤21 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the
             first dose of study treatment, and/or have any acute toxicities due to prior
             chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy that have not resolved to a NCI-CTCAE v4.03 Grade 0
             or Grade 1 with the exception of chemotherapy induced alopecia and Grade 2 peripheral
             neuropathy.

             Relapsed/Refractory Metastatic Castration Resistant Prostate Cancer (Parts D and E):

             17. Patients who have been treated with their most recent chemotherapy or
             investigational drugs ≤21 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the
             first dose of study treatment, and/or have any acute toxicities due to prior
             chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy that have not resolved to a NCI-CTCAE v4.03 Grade 0
             or Grade 1 with the exception of chemotherapy induced alopecia and Grade 2 peripheral
             neuropathy.

             18. Initiating bisphosphonate therapy or adjusting bisphosphonate dose/regimen within
             30 days prior to C1D1. Patients on a stable bisphosphonate or denosumab regimen are
             eligible and may continue.

             Higher risk Myelodysplastic Syndrome (Part F):

             19. IPSS low or intermediate-1 risk MDS. 20. Evidence of transformation to AML by
             World Health Organization (WHO) (≥20% blasts in bone marrow or peripheral blood).

             21. Patients receiving granulocyte-colony stimulating factor (G-CSF) or granulocyte
             macrophage-colony stimulating factor (GM-CSF) within the 3 weeks prior to C1D1.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Kauffman, MD, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Karyopharm Therapeutics Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Kauffman, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <email>mkauffman@karyopharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sharon Shacham, PhD</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moffitt Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachid Baz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>813-745-8212</phone>
      <email>Rachid.Baz@Moffit.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rachid Baz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John Theurer Cancer Center at Hackensack UMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Josh Richter, MD</last_name>
      <phone>551-996-8704</phone>
      <email>JRicter@HackensackUMC.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Josh Richter, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sangmin Lee, MD</last_name>
      <phone>646-962-7200</phone>
      <email>sal9053@med.cornell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sangmin Lee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University, The James Cancer Hospital and Solove Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John Hays, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>John.Hays@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Hays, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania Abramson Cancer Center Clinical Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dan Vogl, MD</last_name>
      <phone>215-614-0037</phone>
      <email>Dan.Vogl@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dan Vogl, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert Cornell, MD,MS</last_name>
      <phone>615-936-8422</phone>
      <email>robert.f.cornell@vanderbilt.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Cornell, MD,MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Margaret Cancer Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MUHC GLEN Site Cedars - Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 6, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 7, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>Karyopharm</keyword>
  <keyword>KPT-8602</keyword>
  <keyword>MM</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase 1</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapsed/ Refractory Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>MDS</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Castration Resistant Prostate Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>mCRPC</keyword>
  <keyword>CRC</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

