<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02644122</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140904</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02644122</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SF1126 in Recurrent or Progressive SCCHN and Mutations in PIK3CA Gene and/or PI-3 Kinase Pathway Genes</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Open Label Study of the PI3 Kinase (PI-3) Inhibitor, SF1126, in Patients With Recurrent or Progressive SCCHN and Mutations in PIK3CA Gene and/or PI-3 Kinase Pathway Genes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ezra Cohen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>SignalRX Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test the good and bad effects of an experimental drug called
      SF1126. This drug is being tested in patients whose cancer has not been controlled by
      available standard therapies and who have certain genes in their tumor.

      SF1126 is a drug that inhibits a cell protein called phosphatidyl inositol 3 kinase (PI3K).
      PI3K is part of signaling pathway that tells cancer cells to grow, survive, invade and
      metastasize. PI3K also has an important role in the development of blood vessels that are
      required to support tumor growth. SF1126 is being developed by SignalRx Pharmaceuticals, Inc.
      It is considered an experimental drug because it is not approved by the FDA for any disease
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SignalRx Pharmaceuticals has developed a pan isoform specific PI-3 inhibitor called SF1126 to
      treat patients with advanced or metastatic cancer. SF1126 is a conjugate that contains two
      components: SF1101 (the active drug) and SF1174 (an inactive tetrapeptide RGD targeting
      moiety)

      Both components of SF1126 play key roles in the activity of the drug. SF1101 is a selective
      inhibitor of certain members of the phosphatidyl inositol 3-kinase (PI-3) family and SF1174
      binds selectively to receptors known to be present on neovasculature supporting tumors and on
      some tumor cells themselves. These components result in a drug designed to be both selective
      in its activity and targeted in its delivery.

      This is an open label Phase II study of SF1126 in adult patients with recurrent or refractory
      advanced SCCHN with PIK3CA mutation. Treatment cycles (28 days) will consist of SF1126 1110
      mg/m2 administered intravenously (IV) twice per week (separated by at least three days) for
      the first four cycles and then once weekly for subsequent cycles.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Slow enrollment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine ORR</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>best response of PR or CR observed within 6 months of enrollment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the effect of SF1126 on time to progression.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the effect of SF1126 on overall survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess disease-related patient-reported outcomes using the EORTC-QLQ-</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Squamous Neck Cancer With Occult Primary Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SF1126</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SF1126 1110 mg/m2 administered intravenously (IV) twice per week (separated by at least three days) for the first four treatment cycles (28 days) and then once weekly for subsequent cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SF1126</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SF1126</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of recurrent or metastatic SCCHN or any site except lip, thyroid, salivary
             gland, or nasopharynx.

          -  No known FDA-approved therapy available that's expected to prolong survival by greater
             than 3 months.

          -  Tumors with at least one of the following known mutations in the PI-3K signaling
             pathway, via assays performed in a CLIA-approved setting (Foundation Medicine
             FoundationOne test will be used. This assay uses a cut-off of 5% allele fraction for
             mutations. Allele fraction will be requested on each sample):

               1. PIK3CA,

               2. PIK3CG,

               3. PIK3R1, PIK3R5 and PIK3AP1 (regulatory subunits),

               4. AKT and mTOR, or

               5. PTEN Note: PIK3CA amplification is not eligible.

          -  Prior receipt of platinum-containing chemotherapy for recurrent/metastatic disease or
             a history of progression of disease within 6 months of receiving platinum as part of
             concurrent chemoradiation.

          -  Disease must not be amenable to potentially curative treatment..

          -  Has recovered from the acute toxic effects of all prior chemotherapy, immunotherapy,
             or radiotherapy.

               -  Myelosuppressive chemotherapy: At least 3 weeks since completion (6 weeks for
                  nitrosourea)

               -  Biologic (anti-neoplastic agent): At least 14 days since completion of therapy
                  with a biologic agent.

               -  Radiation (XRT):1 week must have elapsed from prior palliative XRT to non-target
                  lesions.

          -  Adequate Bone Marrow Function Defined for all subjects (including status post SCT):

               -  Peripheral absolute neutrophil count (ANC) 1000/mm3; Note: must be &gt;7 days from
                  use of hematopoietic growth factor or 21 days from pegfilgastrim

               -  Platelet count 75,000/ mm3 (transfusion independent for &gt;7 days)

               -  Hemoglobin 8.0 g/dL (may receive transfusions)

          -  Adequate Renal Function Defined As:

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x institution's ULN (upper limit of normal), or

               -  Creatinine clearance 50 ml/min

          -  Adequate Liver and Pancreatic Function Defined As:

               -  Total bilirubin 1.5 x upper limit of normal, and

               -  ALT or AST 5 x upper limit of normal, and

               -  Albumin 2 g/dL

          -  Adequate Central Nervous System Function Defined As:

               -  Subjects with seizure disorder may be enrolled if on anticonvulsants and seizures
                  are well controlled.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Brain metastases or spinal cord compression, unless treatment was completed at least 4
             weeks before study entry, and stable without steroid treatment for at least 4 weeks.

          -  Evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic diseases (e.g., unstable or uncompensated
             respiratory, cardiac [including life threatening arrhythmias], hepatic, or renal
             disease).

          -  Unresolved toxicity ≥ CTCAE Grade 2 from previous anti-cancer therapy except alopecia
             or long-term radiation toxicity (radiation related toxicity 3 months or greater after
             radiation exposure).

          -  Presence of cardiac impairment defined as:

               -  Prior history of cardiovascular disease including heart failure that meets New
                  York Hearth Association (NYHA) class III and IV definitions; OR

               -  History of myocardial infarction/active ischemic heart disease within one year of
                  study entry; OR

               -  Uncontrolled dysrhythmias; OR

               -  Poorly controlled angina.

          -  Participation in a trial of an investigational agent within the prior 30 days.

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding females.

          -  History of other malignancies except curatively excised carcinoma in situ of the
             cervix, non-melanomatous skin carcinoma or superficial bladder cancer or other solid
             tumors curatively treated with no evidence of disease for 3 years. Other cases will be
             reviewed and possibly allowed if discussed with and approved by the Principal
             Investigator.

          -  Patients receiving therapeutic doses of warfarin.

          -  Blood pressure greater than 170/90 or two standard deviations from normal based on age
             and weight nomogram on three separate measurements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ezra Cohen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC San Diego Moores Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 28, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 31, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ezra Cohen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>advanced cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>metastatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</keyword>
  <keyword>SCCHN</keyword>
  <keyword>gene mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>PIK3R1, PIK3R5 and PIK3AP1</keyword>
  <keyword>PIK3CG</keyword>
  <keyword>AKT and mTOR</keyword>
  <keyword>PIK3CA gene</keyword>
  <keyword>PI-3 kinase inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>PI-3 kinase pathway genes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Unknown Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>May 11, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

