<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02648139</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Eugenia Dentifrice</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02648139</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized, Controlled, Double-blind Clinical Trial of Surinam Cherry Dentifrice With Anti-gingivitis Properties</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled, Double-blind Clinical Trial of a Eugenia Uniflora Linn. (Surinam Cherry) Dentifrice With Anti-gingivitis Properties</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federal University of Paraíba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal University of Paraíba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the present randomized, controlled, double-blind clinical trial, we investigated the short
      term clinical efficacy of a dentifrice containing Eugenia uniflora L. ripe fruit extract in
      preventing gingivitis in children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This was a randomized, controlled, double-blind clinical trial investigating the short term
      clinical efficacy of a dentifrice containing Eugenia uniflora L. ripe fruit extract in
      preventing gingivitis in children. The study consisted of a sample of 50 male and female
      subjects between the ages of 10 and 12 years old, who had clinical signs of gingivitis. The
      subjects were randomly assigned to one of two groups. The intervention group comprised 25
      subjects who used the dentifrice with E. uniflora L. ripe fruit hydroalcoholic extract, three
      times per day, for seven consecutive days. The control group comprised 25 subjects who used
      the control dentifrice (fluoride, 1500 ppm and triclosan, 0.3%) for seven consecutive days.

      The sample size was estimated using Fleming's single-stage procedure for phase II trials.
      With regard to the primary outcome, a response proportion of at least 50% was defined as
      being clinically significant. The type I error was set as 0.05, and the type II error was set
      at 0.1. Based on these values, a sample size of 20 individuals per trial arm would provide
      90% power (1-β) to detect any clinically relevant treatment difference of 50% or greater
      compared to baseline. Taking into consideration an attrition rate of approximately 20%, the
      final sample size per trial arm comprised 25 individuals.

      Clinical examinations were performed at baseline and after seven days of dentifrice use. The
      examination was performed by a single examiner who was adequately calibrated with a Kappa
      statistic of 0.8, which is considered to be satisfactory agreement according to Landis &amp;
      Koch. The examination data were recorded in a specific clinical chart. The diagnosis of
      gingivitis (primary outcome) was assessed using the Gingival Bleeding Index (GBI) proposed by
      Ainamo and Bay. The accumulation of biofilm (secondary outcome) was assessed with the
      Simplified Oral Hygiene Index (OHI-S) described by Greene and Vermilion. Prior to the study,
      all of the subjects were instructed on correct tooth brushing techniques and received a kit
      that contained a toothbrush and one of the dentifrices (without the identification of its
      contents). The dentifrices were also masked with regard to flavor and color so that they
      could not be identified. In addition, the examiner had no knowledge of the subject
      allocation. Thus, the study was double-blind.

      The sample included only subjects who had not used an antimicrobial in the last two months,
      including topical fluoride.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in gingivitis levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and seven days</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome of interest was the reduction in the levels of gingivitis (bleeding on probing) assessed by the Gingival Bleeding Index (GBI) proposed by Ainamo and Bay.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in the amount of plaque</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and seven days</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary outcome of interest was the reduction in the amount of plaque assessed by the Simplified Oral Hygiene Index (OHI-S) described by Greene and Vermilion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Gingivitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental dentifrice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dentifrice containing the extract of Eugenia uniflora rip fruit. Each 10 ml of E. uniflora L. dentifrice comprises the following components: Hydroalcoholic extract of the ripe fruit of E. uniflora L. (3.0%), preservatives (parabens; 0.02 g), and dentifrice base (silicon dioxide, sodium lauryl sulfate, white dye, aromatic compounds, sodium saccharin, and Gangrez sodium salt; q.s.p.). Intervention protocol: three times per day (pea-like amount), for seven consecutive days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Dentifrice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control dentifrice - Colgate total 12 (fluoride, 1500 ppm and triclosan, 0.3%)
Intervention protocol: three times per day (pea-like amount), for seven consecutive days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dentifrice</intervention_name>
    <description>3x/day for 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental dentifrice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control Dentifrice</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surrinam cherry dentifrice, Colgate total 12</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children aged 10 to 12 years old with clinical signs of gingivitis (bleeding on
             probing);

          -  Presence of at least 20 dental elements

          -  Not using orthodontic fixed appliances

          -  Susceptibility to form biofilm and gingival inflammation

          -  Absence of systemic disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - Subjects who had used an antimicrobial in the last two months, including topical
        fluoride.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ricardo D Castro, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of Paraíba</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 5, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 5, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 5, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal University of Paraíba</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Irlan de Almeida Freires</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gingivitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

