<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02643732</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>170-11-15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02643732</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fatigue in Sarcoidosis - Treatment With Methylphenidate</brief_title>
  <acronym>FaST-MP</acronym>
  <official_title>Fatigue in Sarcoidosis - A Feasibility Study Investigating the Treatment of Fatigue in Stable Sarcoidosis Patients Using Methylphenidate</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of East Anglia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clinical Research and Trials Unit (Norfolk &amp; Norwich University Hospital, UK)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of East Anglia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a small randomised-controlled trial (RCT) using methylphenidate as a treatment for
      clinically-significant fatigue in sarcoidosis patients with stable disease. The primary
      outcomes are feasibility, aimed at determining factors that will influence the design a
      future, larger RCT, which will be powered to look at clinical efficacy of the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sarcoidosis and fatigue

      Sarcoidosis is a systemic granulomatous disease that affects all ethnic groups and ages. In
      the United Kingdom the incidence of the disease is 5.0 cases per 100,000 patient years, with
      a mean age at diagnosis of 47 years, frequently affecting patients of working age(Gribbin et
      al). The cause is unknown and there is no cure(Iannuzzi et al). Many patients suffer from
      debilitating fatigue for which there is presently no treatment.

      Fatigue has been described as a &quot;core symptom&quot; of sarcoidosis, and is present in up to 80% of
      patients(Marcellis et al). A &quot;post-sarcoidosis chronic-fatigue syndrome&quot; has been
      described(James), denoting the presence of fatigue where there is no evidence of active
      disease. The presence of this symptom has been shown to adversely affect quality of
      life(Michielsen et al). Although there increased risk of obstructive sleep apnoea and
      sleep-disordered breathing occurring in sarcoidosis patients(Michielsen et al; Drent et al)
      the majority of patients have no identifiable cause for fatigue other than their sarcoidosis.

      Both the British Thoracic Society(Bradley et al) and American Thoracic Society(Costabel et
      al) produce guidelines for physicians treating people with sarcoidosis. Neither guideline
      gives any advice on treatment of fatigue. Fatigue is a common problem in sarcoidosis. In a
      study of 76 patients with sarcoidosis, 50.7% reported pathological levels of fatigue, defined
      as a Fatigue Assessment Scale (FAS) score of greater than 21 units, compared with 8.6% of
      controls. People reporting fatigue scores above 21, had poorer EuroQoL Visual Analogue Scale
      (EQVAS) scores compared with people reporting fatigue scores of 21 or below (mean scores
      0.561 vs 0.792 , p&lt;0.001) (Unpublished data, Norfolk and Norwich University Hospital). This
      shows that fatigue impacts upon quality of life in sarcoidosis.

      Methylphenidate - a treatment for fatigue

      Methylphenidate (and its isomer dexmethylphenidate), which is used to treat attention deficit
      hyperactivity disorder(Keating et al), is an amphetamine-derivative which works by amplifying
      dopamine signals through inhibition of dopamine reuptake and enhancement of extracellular
      dopamine in the basal ganglia(Volkow et al). It has been used to treat fatigue in other
      settings with good effect. In a placebo-controlled, double-blind trial in post-chemotherapy
      participants with fatigue, methylphenidate exhibited a clinically significant reduction in
      fatigue(Lower et al). Prior to the results from this trial, a Cochrane review of treatments
      for cancer-related fatigue from 5 RCTs had shown an improvement in fatigue through
      methylphenidate treatment, leading them to conclude &quot;the current evidence supports the use of
      psychostimulants in cancer-related fatigue&quot;(Minton et al). Another trial investigated
      methylphenidate for the treatment of fatigue in 109 HIV-positive patients over a 6-week
      period. Methylphenidate improved fatigue on a visual analogue scale, with a 26.2 point
      increase (maximum of 100) from baseline, with 41% of participants receiving the drug
      demonstrating a greater than 50% improvement in visual analogue scale score(Breitbart et al).
      In contrast, no difference between methylphenidate and placebo was seen in a cohort of 68
      fatigued patients who had received radiotherapy for brain tumours followed over a 12 week
      period(Butler et al).

      In the case of sarcoidosis, so far only one small study has investigated the use of
      dexmethylphenidate for fatigue(Lower et al). Ten patients were included in this double blind
      crossover trial. Participants reported clinically and statistically significant improvements
      in fatigue measured by both the FAS and the Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness
      Therapy-Fatigue (FACIT-F) score after 8 weeks of treatment, although no statistically
      significant improvement was seen in six minute walk distance (6MWD) compared with placebo.
      The drug was well tolerated; all participants completed the study and no significant increase
      in side effects was noted between the patients receiving placebo and dexmethylphenidate.

      Rationale for current study

      Prior to designing a definitive study, issues about the feasibility of undertaking a
      sufficiently large trial require to be resolved. Completed trials have only used
      methylphenidate for 8-12 weeks, so sustainability of effect, tolerability of medications over
      a long period and retention of participants within the trial are unknown. Whilst the use of
      medications such as methylphenidate may not be used on a continuous basis in the clinical
      setting, their use on a 6-12 month basis may not be unreasonable, hence the need to review
      the effect of the medication over a longer period. Furthermore, it is unclear how many people
      would be willing to participate in a longer trial , and how many potential participants would
      be suitable for enrolment using our present inclusion and exclusion criteria. For this
      reason, a feasibility trial is necessary before committing to a larger trial.

      In addition, this trial will evaluate exercise and activity through both a modified shuttle
      walk test (MSWT) and accelerometer-measured change in activity levels. Although
      methylphenidate has not been shown to significantly improve 6MWD(Lower et al), a larger study
      using a more responsive test may be required to evaluate exercise capacity in this setting.
      This could be because as a self-paced test it is a sub-maximal exercise test - this has been
      shown to be the case in a study of interstitial lung disease (ILD) patients (including
      sarcoidosis) where peak oxygen uptake, carbon dioxide uptake and ventilation were all lower
      during 6MWD than on cardiopulmonary exercise testing(Holland et al). By not reaching their
      maximum exercise level this may make the test less responsive to change. This is particularly
      relevant given that the ILD cohort who did not reach maximal exercise or oxygen uptake during
      their 6MWD were likely to be much more limited in cardiopulmonary function than the cohort
      anticipated to be enrolled in a study of treatment of fatigue and therefore much more likely
      to get closer to their peak oxygen uptake during a 6MWD. Given that activity levels measured
      by accelerometers in people with sarcoidosis is related to fatigue (Korenromp et al), this
      trial will evaluate the feasibility of using them as an outcome measure in a clinical trial,
      including whether participants will wear the devices for long enough (i.e. 4 days out of 7,
      at least 10 hours per day) to get valid data for estimating daily activity levels.

      Study Design

      This is a parallel-arm RCT including 30 participants, randomised on a 1.5:1 basis in favour
      of the active treatment arm (18 participants will receive methylphenidate, 12 will receive
      placebo). The rationale of this trial is to determine the feasibility of designing and
      performing a sufficiently large RCT in the future looking for proof of clinical effect of
      methylphenidate in the treatment of sarcoidosis-associated fatigue. As a result, this study
      is not powered to detect a clinical difference in a clinical outcome, although these will be
      measured and analysed (the estimate of effect size will be used for future power
      calculations). Therefore the primary outcomes regard feasibility and safety, not treatment
      effect (see Outcome Measures section).

      Participants will receive either methylphenidate or placebo for 24 weeks, with a further
      assessment performed 6 weeks after completion of the trial. They will be carefully monitored
      over the initial 6 weeks to ensure that they are stable on the drug - during this time they
      will be seen every 2 weeks (at 0,2,4 and 6 weeks). Following this period they will be seen
      less frequently (at 12 and 24 weeks, with postal questionnaires performed at 18 weeks) to
      detect sustainability of effect. Determining if treatment effect is sustained over the second
      half of the trial period will help to establish how long any future trial will need to be.
      Although each participant is required to attend frequent visits to the hospital, this trial
      has been designed in conjunction with sarcoidosis patients and ensures that participant
      safety is paramount.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment rate (Feasibility outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months (recruitment period duration)</time_frame>
    <description>How quickly the 30 participants are recruited to the study (relates to feasibility criteria regarding number of centres that are likely to be needed in a future, larger randomised controlled trial). Up to 18 months is allowed for recruitment, based on 2 years for trial to be run and 24 weeks for final patient to complete study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of potential participants excluded (Feasibility outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months (recruitment period duration)</time_frame>
    <description>A record of the number of participants screened for inclusion will be kept, including whether they entered the trial or not, and if they were excluded, for what reason(s) they were excluded. This relates to number of centres likely to be required for a future trial. Up to 18 months is allowed for recruitment, based on 2 years for trial to be run and 24 weeks for final patient to complete study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants dropping out/Participant retention rate (Feasibility outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks (trial duration)</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants withdrawing/dropping out of the study, including reasons where able; enables estimation of drop-out rates so that future studies can be appropriately sized, and also whether there are safety issues (side-effects necessitating withdrawals or patients not tolerating medications) that would suggest a future study is unnecessary.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Side-effect rate (Feasibility and Safety outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks (trial duration)</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants reporting side effects; what they are, severity and need for discontinuation of study drug all required.
A likert scale measuring specific symptoms (palpitations, insomnia, headaches and chest pains) is also administered and these results will be recorded and presented to see if there are differences between the two groups.
Participants also have an ECG at all study visits; any change in ECG will be recorded and the number of participants required to discontinue medications will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of missed or unfilled assessments (Feasibility outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks (trial duration)</time_frame>
    <description>Identifies whether appropriate data is being collected within the trial.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of accelerometers returned with valid data (Feasibility outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks (trial duration)</time_frame>
    <description>Accelerometers are a novel outcome in this study. Their use in a trial of this nature has not been performed before. We wish to see how many participants return the accelerometer devices at the three time points in the trial, and how many of these have valid data on them; this is defined as 4 or more days of use with 10 or more hours or data. It is designed to see if it is feasible to use these devices as an outcome measure in future trials.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue Assessment Scale (FAS) (Clinical outcome)</measure>
    <time_frame>0,2,4,6,12,18,14 and 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in FAS after 24 weeks, including sustainability of effect between 12 and 24 weeks (does clinical effect wane? would a future trial need to be as long?). The trial is not powered for looking for clinical difference (30 patients chosen to answer the primary feasibility questions), hence this is the secondary outcome. However, the estimate of effect size will enable power calculations for future studies to be more accurate.
The FAS is measured at weeks 0,2,4,6,12,18,24 and 30 (6 weeks post-trial completion)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy - Fatigue (FACIT-F)</measure>
    <time_frame>0,2,4,6,12,18,14 and 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in FACIT-F after 24 weeks, including sustainability of effect - this question is co-administered with the FAS questionnaire, as performed in a small previous study (Lower EE et al, 2008).
The FACIT-F is measured at weeks 0,2,4,6,12,18,24 and 30 (6 weeks post-trial completion)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kings Sarcoidosis Questionnaire (KSQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12,18,14 and 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The KSQ is a disease-specific, health-related quality of life score used in sarcoidosis and validated in sarcoidosis cohorts within the United Kingdom. It consists of 31 questions which require rating of health problems on a scale.
The KSQ is assessed at weeks 0,6,12,18, 24 and 30 (6 weeks post-trial completion)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EuroQoL-5D (EQ5D) Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12,18,14 and 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This generic quality of life/health status questionnaire is used both to assess health status and also for exploratory health economic analysis.
The EQ5D is performed at weeks 0,6,12,18,24 and 30 (6 weeks post-trial completion)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short-form 36 (SF-36) Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12,18,14 and 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-36 is a generic quality of life/health status questionnaire, which can also be used for health economic modelling. Both EQ5D and SF-36 are used here as the SF-36 has a vitality domain which can reflect changes in fatigue; the two questionnaires are therefore being compared to see which would be better to use in a future trial for both assessment of health status and health economic modelling.
The SF-36 is performed at weeks 0,6,12,18,24 and 30 (6 weeks post-trial completion)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Anxiety and Depressions Score (HADS)</measure>
    <time_frame>0,6,12,18,14 and 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Depression has been suggested as a possible cause for fatigue in sarcoidosis, but it has also been suggested that the depression stems from the fatigue. Therefore a questionnaire identifying depressive and anxiety symptoms is administered.
The HADS is performed at weeks 0,6,12,18,24 and 30 (6 weeks post-trial completion).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accelerometer Use (wrist-worn accelerometer)</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 12, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A wrist-worn accelerometer can measure daily activity levels over a 7 day period. This will be performed before commencing medication (between screening and baseline visit), at the mid-point (12 weeks) and in the 2 weeks prior to medication completion (22-24 weeks). This will enable assessment in change of activity levels between the groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Shuttle Walk Test (MSWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 12, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This incremental physical exercise test will enable an assessment in change in physical capacity/ability to be made. Like the accelerometer outcome, it is assessed at 0,12 and 24 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Health Economic/Utility Use</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 12, 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A custom questionnaire based on existing tools will be administered at weeks 0,12 and 24 to look for changes in use of health and social facilities/services, as well as time off work/change in working patterns.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcoidosis</condition>
  <condition>Fatigue</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Methylphenidate 10mg (one tablet) twice daily, increasing to 20mg (two tablets) twice daily following assessment 2 weeks into trial.
24 weeks duration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Identical, over-encapsulated placebo tablets manufactured to be identical to the experimental tablets. One tablet twice daily, increased to two tablets twice daily following assessment 2 weeks into trial.
24 weeks duration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylphenidate (overencapsulated)</intervention_name>
    <description>10mg (1 capsule) methylphenidate (standard release) twice daily, increased to 20mg (2 capsules) twice daily after 2 weeks. The drug can be down-titrated in the event of side effects, although re-uptitration is not allowed even if the side effects resolve on the lower dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tranquilyn</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo (Over-encapsulated tablet)</intervention_name>
    <description>Identical capsules (over-encapsulated placebo tablets), administered initially one capsule twice daily, increased to 2 capsules after 2 weeks. As with the methylphenidate arm, the dose can be down-titrated in the event of side effects, although re-uptitration is not allowed even if the side effects resolve on the lower dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Biopsy-proven diagnosis of sarcoidosis or diagnosis of sarcoidosis from interstitial
             lung disease multidisciplinary team meeting after review of radiological and clinical
             information

          2. Stable disease (treatment unchanged for 6 weeks, without anticipation of treatment
             change during trial period)

          3. FAS score greater than 21 units

          4. Able to give informed consent

          5. In patients on warfarin therapy - Willing to consent to increased frequency of
             monitoring

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Evidence of co-existing obstructive sleep apnoea. Patients screened with a &quot;STOP-Bang&quot;
             questionnaire (acronym taken from individual questions within the questionnaire
             itself) score of greater than 4 must undertake overnight oximetry; they are excluded
             if this shows a desaturation index of more than 15 events per hour on overnight
             oximetry.

          2. Documented history of significant cardiac disease (including cardiac sarcoid) OR
             associated disease which would increase risk of underlying coronary artery disease
             (cerebrovascular disease, previous stroke or peripheral vascular disease).
             Definitively treated cardiac disease e.g. previous myocardial infarction treated with
             stents or coronary artery bypass grafting with no ongoing symptoms is permitted.

          3. Hyperthyroidism evidenced by abnormal screening thyroid function tests (Thyroid
             stimulating hormone level outside normal range of 0.35 - 3.50 milliunits/litre (mU/L)
             or thyroxine (T4) outside normal range of 8 - 21 picomoles per litre (pmol/L)).

          4. History of seizures, excluding febrile convulsions whilst an infant.

          5. Abnormal electrocardiogram (ECG) with evidence of arrhythmia (except first degree
             heart block which has been stable for 3 months).

          6. Concomitant therapy with the following drugs:

               -  Tricyclic antidepressants

               -  Monoamine oxidase inhibitors

               -  Tramadol or buprenorphine

               -  Levodopa

               -  Haloperidol and atypical antipsychotics

          7. Glaucoma or raised intra-ocular pressure for any reason.

          8. Patients with established liver disease defined as Child-Pugh class B or C.

          9. Documented medical history of psychiatric disorders (excluding depression)

         10. History of drug-dependence or addiction at any time

         11. Female participant who is pregnant, lactating or planning pregnancy during the course
             of the trial

         12. Female patient of childbearing potential unable or unwilling to take two acceptable
             forms of contraception (see exclusions section)

         13. Receiving an investigational drug or biological agent within 6 weeks (or 5 times the
             half-life if this is longer) prior to study entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew M Wilson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of East Anglia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chris Atkins, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>01603 591594</phone>
    <email>c.atkins@uea.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Andrew M Wilson, MD</last_name>
    <phone>01603 591257</phone>
    <email>a.m.wilson@uea.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Norfolk and Norwich University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norwich</city>
        <state>Norfolk</state>
        <zip>NR4 7UY</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marcus Flather, MB/BS</last_name>
      <email>marcus.flather@nnuh.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lisa Chalkley</last_name>
      <email>lisa.chlakley@nnuh.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chris Atkins, MB/BS</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gribbin J, Hubbard RB, Le Jeune I, Smith CJ, West J, Tata LJ. Incidence and mortality of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis and sarcoidosis in the UK. Thorax. 2006 Nov;61(11):980-5. Epub 2006 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>16844727</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iannuzzi MC, Rybicki BA, Teirstein AS. Sarcoidosis. N Engl J Med. 2007 Nov 22;357(21):2153-65. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18032765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marcellis RG, Lenssen AF, Elfferich MD, De Vries J, Kassim S, Foerster K, Drent M. Exercise capacity, muscle strength and fatigue in sarcoidosis. Eur Respir J. 2011 Sep;38(3):628-34. doi: 10.1183/09031936.00117710. Epub 2011 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21436356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>James DG. Complications of sarcoidosis. Chronic fatigue syndrome. Sarcoidosis. 1993 Mar;10(1):1-3.</citation>
    <PMID>8134708</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Michielsen HJ, Drent M, Peros-Golubicic T, De Vries J. Fatigue is associated with quality of life in sarcoidosis patients. Chest. 2006 Oct;130(4):989-94.</citation>
    <PMID>17035429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turner GA, Lower EE, Corser BC, Gunther KL, Baughman RP. Sleep apnea in sarcoidosis. Sarcoidosis Vasc Diffuse Lung Dis. 1997 Mar;14(1):61-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9186990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drent M, Verbraecken J, van der Grinten C, Wouters E. Fatigue associated with obstructive sleep apnea in a patient with sarcoidosis. Respiration. 2000;67(3):337-40.</citation>
    <PMID>10867608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bradley B, Branley HM, Egan JJ, Greaves MS, Hansell DM, Harrison NK, Hirani N, Hubbard R, Lake F, Millar AB, Wallace WA, Wells AU, Whyte MK, Wilsher ML; British Thoracic Society Interstitial Lung Disease Guideline Group, British Thoracic Society Standards of Care Committee; Thoracic Society of Australia; New Zealand Thoracic Society; Irish Thoracic Society. Interstitial lung disease guideline: the British Thoracic Society in collaboration with the Thoracic Society of Australia and New Zealand and the Irish Thoracic Society. Thorax. 2008 Sep;63 Suppl 5:v1-58. doi: 10.1136/thx.2008.101691. Erratum in: Thorax. 2008 Nov;63(11):1029. multiple author names added.</citation>
    <PMID>18757459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Costabel U, Hunninghake GW. ATS/ERS/WASOG statement on sarcoidosis. Sarcoidosis Statement Committee. American Thoracic Society. European Respiratory Society. World Association for Sarcoidosis and Other Granulomatous Disorders. Eur Respir J. 1999 Oct;14(4):735-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10573213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keating GM, Figgitt DP. Dexmethylphenidate. Drugs. 2002;62(13):1899-904; discussion 1905-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12215063</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Volkow ND, Fowler JS, Wang G, Ding Y, Gatley SJ. Mechanism of action of methylphenidate: insights from PET imaging studies. J Atten Disord. 2002;6 Suppl 1:S31-43.</citation>
    <PMID>12685517</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lower EE, Fleishman S, Cooper A, Zeldis J, Faleck H, Yu Z, Manning D. Efficacy of dexmethylphenidate for the treatment of fatigue after cancer chemotherapy: a randomized clinical trial. J Pain Symptom Manage. 2009 Nov;38(5):650-62. doi: 10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2009.03.011.</citation>
    <PMID>19896571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Minton O, Richardson A, Sharpe M, Hotopf M, Stone P. Drug therapy for the management of cancer-related fatigue. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2010 Jul 7;(7):CD006704. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD006704.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20614448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Breitbart W, Rosenfeld B, Kaim M, Funesti-Esch J. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of psychostimulants for the treatment of fatigue in ambulatory patients with human immunodeficiency virus disease. Arch Intern Med. 2001 Feb 12;161(3):411-20.</citation>
    <PMID>11176767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Butler JM Jr, Case LD, Atkins J, Frizzell B, Sanders G, Griffin P, Lesser G, McMullen K, McQuellon R, Naughton M, Rapp S, Stieber V, Shaw EG. A phase III, double-blind, placebo-controlled prospective randomized clinical trial of d-threo-methylphenidate HCl in brain tumor patients receiving radiation therapy. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2007 Dec 1;69(5):1496-501. Epub 2007 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>17869448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lower EE, Harman S, Baughman RP. Double-blind, randomized trial of dexmethylphenidate hydrochloride for the treatment of sarcoidosis-associated fatigue. Chest. 2008 May;133(5):1189-95. doi: 10.1378/chest.07-2952. Epub 2008 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>18263672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holland AE, Dowman L, Fiore J Jr, Brazzale D, Hill CJ, McDonald CF. Cardiorespiratory responses to 6-minute walk test in interstitial lung disease: not always a submaximal test. BMC Pulm Med. 2014 Aug 11;14:136. doi: 10.1186/1471-2466-14-136.</citation>
    <PMID>25113781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Korenromp IHE, Heijnen CJ, Vogels OJM, van den Bosch JMM, Grutters JC. Characterization of chronic fatigue in patients with sarcoidosis in clinical remission. Chest. 2011 Aug;140(2):441-447. doi: 10.1378/chest.10-2629. Epub 2011 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21330380</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 30, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 31, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Activity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methylphenidate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Plan for anonymised data to be available through data repository for analysis by other researchers with permission of team.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

