<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02648971</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB30774 (Z61894)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02648971</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Controlled Trial to Compare Single Versus Two Portal Knee Arthroscopy Techniques</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial to Compare Single Portal Versus Two Portal Knee Arthroscopy Techniques in Patients With Meniscal Injuries and Articular Cartilage Pathology</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized, controlled clinical trial will compare the outcomes of single portal versus
      two portal techniques in patients who have meniscus or articular cartilage pathology. The
      study hypothesis is that patients who undergo single portal arthroscopy will have less pain
      post-operatively, use less pain medication, and have a higher International Knee
      Documentation Committee (IKDC) score at six months and one year compared to patients who
      undergo traditional two portal knee arthroscopy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background, Rationale and Context

      Knee arthroscopy procedures provide a minimally invasive method to assess the status of the
      knee joint in order to repair injuries of the meniscus and articular cartilage. In the past,
      two or more small openings in the skin (portals) were required in order to allow the passage
      of both an arthroscope to provide visualization of the knee joint and the instrument used to
      complete the surgical repair process. However, recent innovations in arthroscopy
      instrumentation have resulted in the ability to use one portal for knee arthroscopy
      procedures with both the arthroscope and the instruments passed into the knee joint through
      the same portal. Both uniportal and two portal arthroscopic techniques are used currently for
      knee arthroscopy procedures in the Department of Orthopaedic Surgery at Wake Forest Baptist
      Health.

      Objectives

      This randomized, controlled clinical trial will compare the outcomes of single portal versus
      two portal techniques in patients who have meniscus or articular cartilage pathology. The
      study hypothesis is that patients who undergo single portal arthroscopy will have less pain
      post-operatively, use less pain medication, and have a higher International Knee
      Documentation Committee (IKDC) score at six months and one year compared to patients who
      undergo traditional two portal knee arthroscopy.

      Methods and Measures

      Design: A randomized, controlled trial

      Setting: Academic Medical Center: single study site at Wake Forest Baptist Health
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 3, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 3, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in the IKDC Subjective Knee Evaluation Form Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 30 days, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The IKDC subjective knee form contains 19 questions and requires approximately five minutes to complete. All except one of the items is converted to a score; a maximum score of 100 indicates that the patient has no restrictions in their daily activities or sports and does not have any knee symptoms. The change in the IKDC score is being followed before surgery until one year after surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Levels and Use of Pain Medication</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day postop through one year postop</time_frame>
    <description>Pain levels and the use of pain medication will be monitored by study participants using a daily pain diary. The pain diary will be used for the first two weeks after surgery. Pain levels will also be collected at the 1 and 4 day telephone calls. A pain rating will also be collected at the one week, 30 day, three months, six months, and one year visit. The use of pain medications and the pain levels will be monitored over time to determine each study participant's post-surgical course.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Injuries, Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Portal Knee Arthroscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After randomization for each patient is complete, the website will document the name of the person who logged on to perform the randomization, the date and time of the log in, and the surgical group assignment for each patient. This randomization information will be forwarded to the operating room staff so that they can prepare for each study participant's surgical procedure. Patients in Group 1 will undergo knee arthroscopy using a single portal. The details of the surgical procedure for each study participant will be documented on the IKDC Surgical Documentation Form. Study participants in each group will return for standard post-operative follow-up visits at one week, 30 days, and three months. They will return to the clinic at six months and one year for study visits.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Two Portal Knee Arthroscopy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in Group 2 will undergo knee arthroscopy using two portals. The details of the surgical procedure for each study participant will be documented on the IKDC Surgical Documentation Form. Study participants in each group will return for standard post-operative follow-up visits at one week, 30 days, and three months. They will return to the clinic at six months and one year for study visits.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Single Portal Knee Arthroscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in Group 1 will undergo knee arthroscopy using a single portal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Portal Knee Arthroscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Two Portal Knee Arthroscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in Group 2 will undergo knee arthroscopy using two portals.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Two Portal Knee Arthroscopy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women between 21 and 65 years of age, who agree to comply with the protocol

          -  Patients undergoing a primary knee arthroscopy procedure for meniscus or articular
             cartilage pathology

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a history of long term pain medication use and/or chronic pain
             conditions unrelated to the surgery.

          -  Subjects with severe renal disease, allergies to pain medication, and subjects that
             will have adverse drug-drug reactions from prescribed pain medication.

          -  Patients with previous reconstructive procedures, lateral retinacular release, or
             microfracture

          -  Active knee infection or sepsis at the time of surgery

          -  Meniscal injuries requiring repair

          -  Ligamentous instability

          -  Advanced degenerative or inflammatory arthritis

          -  Known cancer at the time of surgery

          -  Conditions that might interfere with recovery from knee arthroscopy (i.e. conditions
             or diseases of the nervous and/or muscular system, vascular disease, uncontrolled
             diabetes)

          -  Malignant tumor history or treatment of malignant tumor of the knee

          -  Lower extremity condition causing abnormal ambulation (e.g. ankle fusion, ankle
             arthroplasty, previous hip fracture, knee arthrofibrosis)

          -  Pregnant, breast feeding, or planning on becoming pregnant during the time frame of
             the study, (if a woman of child-bearing age)

          -  Emotional or neurological conditions that affect the subject's ability or willingness
             to participate in the study including mental illness or drug and/or alcohol abuse

          -  Severely overweight (BMI &gt;40) at study enrollment or surgery

          -  Currently participating in another research study

          -  Prisoner or impending imprisonment

          -  Workers' Compensation claims
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beth P. Smith, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Hubbard</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest Baptist Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irrgang JJ, Anderson AF, Boland AL, Harner CD, Kurosaka M, Neyret P, Richmond JC, Shelborne KD. Development and validation of the international knee documentation committee subjective knee form. Am J Sports Med. 2001 Sep-Oct;29(5):600-13.</citation>
    <PMID>11573919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van de Graaf VA, Wolterbeek N, Scholtes VA, Mutsaerts EL, Poolman RW. Reliability and Validity of the IKDC, KOOS, and WOMAC for Patients With Meniscal Injuries. Am J Sports Med. 2014 Jun;42(6):1408-16. doi: 10.1177/0363546514524698. Epub 2014 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24618098</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cooper DE, Fouts B. Single-portal arthroscopy: report of a new technique. Arthrosc Tech. 2013 Jul 19;2(3):e265-9. doi: 10.1016/j.eats.2013.02.017. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>24265996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crawford K, Briggs KK, Rodkey WG, Steadman JR. Reliability, validity, and responsiveness of the IKDC score for meniscus injuries of the knee. Arthroscopy. 2007 Aug;23(8):839-44.</citation>
    <PMID>17681205</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 15, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 5, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 7, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>knee</keyword>
  <keyword>arthroscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>portal</keyword>
  <keyword>meniscus</keyword>
  <keyword>cartilage injury</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Knee Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

