<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02643966</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO14100275</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA187593-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02643966</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Periodic Screening of Women With Denser Breast Using WBUS and DBT</brief_title>
  <acronym>DBTUST</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessment of Periodic Screening of Women With Denser Breast Using WBUS and DBT (Also Known as &quot;DBTUST-Dense Breast Tomosynthesis / Ultrasound Screening Trial&quot;)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wendie Berg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the role of technologist-performed whole breast
      ultrasound for detecting breast cancer in the screening population of women with dense
      breasts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective study designed to evaluate the role of whole breast ultrasound (WBUS)
      in screening for breast cancer. In particular, there is interest in investigating the value
      of using WBUS as an adjunct (supplementary imaging) to Digital Breast Tomosynthesis (DBT)
      based screening of women with dense (heterogeneously or extremely dense) breasts or as a
      primary screening examination in this group of women. Women scheduled for their routine
      mammography that includes a DBT exam who agree to participate in the study and sign informed
      consent will undergo (at the same visit) DBT imaging as part of their clinical exam and whole
      breast ultrasound (WBUS) each year for three rounds of screening plus one year of follow-up.
      The DBT images and WBUS will be interpreted independently by two experienced radiologists
      under standard clinical screening procedures. One radiologist will interpret the DBT and the
      other radiologist will interpret the WBUS. Using a modified &quot;LOGICAL OR&quot; approach
      women/subjects may be recalled for further diagnostic work-up (examinations). If a subject is
      recalled, she will then follow the standard/routine clinical procedures for follow-up and the
      investigators will verify outcomes. If neither radiologist recalls the subject, then the
      subject will follow conventional management and the investigators will verify outcome. The
      findings from the DBT and WBUS examinations, as well as any resulting follow-up, will be
      collected, recorded and analyzed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>True positive and false positive findings of whole breast ultrasound and digital breast tomosynthesis confirmed by routine follow-up or pathology outcome.</measure>
    <time_frame>three years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of women recalled for additional testing, short-interval follow-up, or biopsy based on whole breast ultrasound or digital breast tomosynthesis (3D mammography)</measure>
    <time_frame>within 2 weeks after screening</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of abnormalities detected by whole breast ultrasound and digital breast tomosynthesis.</measure>
    <time_frame>three years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6356</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Whole breast ultrasound</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All women will receive both 3D mammography and whole breast ultrasound for breast cancer screening; the order of interpretation will vary for each of two radiologists</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Whole breast ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>Breast cancer screening with whole breast ultrasound</description>
    <arm_group_label>Whole breast ultrasound</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women aged 40 to 75 years of age with heterogeneously dense or extremely dense
             parenchyma by prior digital mammography report (i.e., &quot;dense breasts&quot;), presenting for
             routine annual mammography with digital breast tomosynthesis.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known to be at high risk for breast cancer due to known or suspected pathologic BRCA
             mutation (i.e. first-degree relative with known mutation) or prior chest radiation
             therapy before age 30;

          -  No mammogram within the prior 3 years;

          -  Signs or symptoms of breast disease including lump, bloody or spontaneous clear nipple
             discharge, eczema of the nipple;

          -  Pregnancy or lactation within the prior 6 months;

          -  Plan to become pregnant in the next two years, as mammography is not typically
             performed for screening pregnant women;

          -  Breast implants, as assessment of breast density may be problematic;

          -  Recent prior breast surgery or breast biopsy or cyst aspiration within the prior 12
             months;

          -  Prior or current malignancy other than the following: a) Breast cancer at least one
             year earlier (12 full months have elapsed since the last treatment surgery) with no
             known distant metastases and no known residual tumor; or b) Basal or squamous cell
             skin cancer or in situ cervical cancer or stage I thyroid cancer; or c) Other cancer
             for which the patient has been disease free for ≥ 5 years, with no recurrence of
             cancer in the last five years and no residual disease detected in the last five years.

          -  Screening contrast-enhanced MRI or 99mTc-sestamibi based imaging of the breast(s)
             within the prior 12 months or planned within the next two years, to avoid
             contamination of results;

          -  Unwilling or unable to provide consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wendie Berg, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weinstein Imaging Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Magee-Womens Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 30, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 31, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Wendie Berg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Radiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>whole breast ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>digital breast tomosynthesis</keyword>
  <keyword>breast density</keyword>
  <keyword>breast cancer screening</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

