<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02973113</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-39090 PREVALE</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PREVALE</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02973113</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nivolumab With Epstein Barr Virus Specific T Cells (EBVSTS), Relapsed/Refractory EBV Positive Lymphoma (PREVALE)</brief_title>
  <acronym>PREVALE</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase I Study Combining Nivolumab With Epstein Barr Virus Specific T Cells (EBVSTS) in Relapsed/Refractory EBV Positive Lymphoma Patients (PREVALE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Methodist Hospital System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Texas Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Center for Cell and Gene Therapy, Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Subjects have a type of a lymph node cancer called Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma (NHL) or
      lymphoproliferative disease (LPD), which affects their immunity, blood production, and can
      involve multiple other organs in the body. Their disease has come back or has not gone away
      after treatment. The experimental treatment plan consists of an antibody therapy called
      &quot;Nivolumab&quot; that helps the subjects' T-cells control the tumor, and special immune system
      cells called EBV-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes, also a new therapy whose side effects are
      well studied.

      Some patients with NHL or LPD are infected with the virus that causes infectious
      mononucleosis (called Epstein-Barr virus, or EBV) before or at the time of their diagnosis.
      The cancer cells that are infected by EBV are able to hide from the body's immune system and
      escape destruction. Investigators want to see if special white blood cells, called T cells,
      that have been trained to kill cells infected by EBV can survive in the blood and affect the
      tumor.

      Investigators have used this sort of therapy to treat a different type of cancer that occurs
      after bone marrow or solid organ transplant called post-transplant lymphoma with good
      success. These cells are called EBV-specific cytotoxic T-lymphocytes (EBVSTs), and are
      effective in treating these diseases. These EBVSTs are experimental and not yet approved by
      the Food and Drug Administration (FDA).

      Sometimes it is not possible to grow these cells; or they may not last very long in the body
      after being given into the vein thereby having only limited time to fight the tumor. With
      this study, investigators aim to increase the duration of time that the T cells can last in
      the body and can effectively fight the cancer by using nivolumab. Nivolumab is FDA approved
      for treatment of other kinds of cancer like lung cancer and a skin cancer called Melanoma.

      The purpose of this study is to find out if EBVST cells in combination with nivolumab are
      safe, to learn what the side effects are, and to see whether this therapy may help patients
      with EBV related lymphoma or LPD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will draw blood from the subject to make EBV-specific cytotoxic
      T-lymphocytes (EBVSTs) in the lab. Investigators will make the cells by first growing a
      special type of cells called dendritic cells (DCs) or monocytes to stimulate the T cells.
      Then they will add specially produced mixtures of proteins that included the LMP, EBNA1, and
      BARF proteins. These are used to stimulate T cells. As the T cells grow, investigators add
      some of the subject's cells expressing these proteins to stimulate them. They also add a cell
      called K562 that has had new genes put inside it so it expresses proteins that stimulate the
      immune system to encourage the T cells to grow. This stimulation trains the EBVSTs to kill
      cells with EBV proteins on their surface. These cells will be grown and frozen.

      The cells grown in the lab will be thawed and injected into the subject's vein over 2-10
      minutes. Initially, one dose of the drug nivolumab is given one day before the EBVST cells
      are infused (on day 0) and then every 2 weeks for a total of four doses of nivolumab.
      Subjects will receive two infusions of the EBVST cells. The first infusion will be given on
      Day 1 and a second infusion of T cells on Day 15.

      If eligible, subjects may receive up to three additional doses of the T cells 6-12 weeks
      apart and each additional T cell infusion would be preceded by one dose of nivolumab a day
      prior.

      Subjects will have medical and blood tests at predetermined time points. Investigators will
      follow subjects closely after treatment for any side effects for at least for 1 year after
      the subject's last infusion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 16, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 16, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 16, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Dose-Limiting Toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>For the purpose of this study, dose limiting toxicity will be defined as any of the below listed items considered to be primarily related to the EBVST infusion or Nivolumab:
CTCAE grade 3-4 diarrhea needing steroids for more than 1 week or needing hospitalization for more than 1 week,
Pancreatitis of any grade needing hospitalization,
Pneumonitis needing hospitalization for more than a week or needing home oxygen despite appropriate treatment for 1 week.
Hepatitis grade 3 or more not resolving in 2 weeks after discontinuation of therapy,
Stomatitis/mucositis needing TPN.
Musculoskeletal symptoms affecting activities of daily living for more than 2 weeks after discontinuation of therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Overall Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of overall response is measured from the time measurement criteria are met for complete response or partial response (whichever is first recorded) until the first date that recurrent or progressive disease is objectively documented.
The duration of overall CR is measured from the time measurement criteria are first met for CR until the first date that recurrent disease is objectively documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>NonHodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoproliferative Disorders</condition>
  <condition>EBV Related Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>EBV-Related PTLD</condition>
  <condition>Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>EBV Related Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>EBV Related Hodgkin's Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EBVST Cells + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PD1 inhibitor - nivolumab 3 mg/kg (max dose: 240 mg) Q 2 weeks for total 4 doses and repeat a day prior to each EBVST infusion.
EBVST- 1 x 10^8/m2 at days +1 and +15. PD1 inhibitor - nivolumab 3 mg/kg (max dose: 240 mg) Q 2 weeks for total 4 doses and repeat a day prior to each EBVST infusion.
Can receive up to 3 additional infusions of EBVSTs with a single dose of nivolumab at 6-12 week intervals starting at least 6 weeks after the second infusion if stable disease or a partial response at Week 8 evaluation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EBVST Cells</intervention_name>
    <description>EBVST cells in an expected volume of 10-20cc will be given by intravenous injection over 2-10 minutes through either a peripheral or a central line.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EBVST Cells + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EBV-specific T Cells</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nivolumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Nivolumab 3mg/kg (max dose: 240 mg) will be administered as an intravenous infusion over 60 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EBVST Cells + Nivolumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Opdivo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        PROCUREMENT Inclusion

          -  Any patient, regardless of age* or sex, with measurable EBV-positive Hodgkin's or
             non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma, (regardless of the histological subtype)^ or EBV (associated)-
             T/NK- or B cell lymphoproliferative disease

             * The first 3 patients enrolled will be adults. Patients &lt;18 years of age are eligible
             if those first 3 patients do not experience dose limiting toxicity considered to be
             primarily related to the EBVST or Nivolumab.

             ^ Patients with relapsed or refractory lymphoma who failed or are ineligible for an
             autologous hematopoietic cell transplantation are also eligible for this study.

          -  EBV positive tumor (can be pending)

          -  Weighs at least 12kg

          -  Informed consent explained to, understood by and signed by patient/guardian.
             Patient/guardian given a copy of informed consent.

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 6 weeks.

        TREATMENT Inclusion

        - Any patient, regardless of age* or sex, with measurable EBV-positive Hodgkin's or
        non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma, (regardless of the histological subtype)^ or EBV (associated)-T/NK-
        or B cell lymphoproliferative disease

        * The first 3 patients enrolled will be adults. Patients &lt;18 years of age are eligible if
        those first 3 patients do not experience dose limiting toxicity considered to be primarily
        related to the EBVST or Nivolumab.

        ^ Patients with relapsed or refractory lymphoma who failed or are ineligible for an
        autologous hematopoietic cell transplantation are also eligible for this study.

        And

          -  Hodgkin's lymphoma patients in second relapse or first relapse and refractory to at
             least two lines of salvage chemotherapy including Brentuximab Vedotin or primary
             refractory disease after at least two lines therapy or

          -  Non- Hodgkin's lymphoma patients in first relapse and/or refractory to at least one
             salvage chemotherapy or with primary refractory disease after at least two lines of
             therapy or in second or subsequent relapse or

          -  T/NK- or B lymphoproliferative disease in first relapse and/or refractory to at least
             one salvage chemotherapy or with primary refractory disease after at least two lines
             of therapy or in second or subsequent relapse

          -  EBV positive tumor

          -  Patients with life expectancy &gt;/= 6 weeks.

          -  Patients with bilirubin less than or equal to 3x upper limit of normal

          -  AST less than or equal to 5x upper limit of normal

          -  Hgb more than 8.0 (may be a transfused value).

          -  Patients with a creatinine less than or equal to 2x upper limit of normal for age

          -  Pulse oximetry of more than 90% on room air

          -  Patients should have been off other investigational therapy for 4 weeks prior to entry
             in this study.

          -  Patients with a Karnofsky/Lansky score of &gt;/= 60

          -  Recovered from acute toxic effects of prior chemotherapy at least one week before
             entering the study.

          -  Sexually active patients must be willing to utilize one of the more effective birth
             control methods during the study and for 6 months after the study is concluded. The
             male partner should use a condom.

          -  Informed consent explained to, understood and signed by patient/guardian.
             Patient/guardian given a copy of informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        PROCUREMENT Exclusion

          -  Active infection with HIV, HTLV, HBV, HCV (can be pending at this time)

          -  History of solid organ transplant

        TREATMENT Exclusion

          -  Pregnant or lactating due to unknown effects of this therapy on a fetus or lactation

          -  Severe active intercurrent infection.

          -  Current use of systemic corticosteroids &gt;0.5 mg/kg/day

          -  Currently receiving any investigational agents or radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to
             entering the study.

          -  Patients with central nervous system involvement.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to nivolumab or any other checkpoint
             inhibitors.

          -  Uncontrolled autoimmune disease needing systemic steroids or steroid sparing agents
             except for hypothyroidism or type I diabetes.

          -  History of solid organ transplant

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Lipase more than 70U/ml
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ravi Pingali, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ravi Pingali, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-441-6220</phone>
    <email>spingali@houstonmethodist.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Vicky Torrano, RN</last_name>
    <phone>832-824-7821</phone>
    <email>vtorrano@bcm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Houston Methodist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ravi Pingali, MD</last_name>
      <phone>713-441-6220</phone>
      <email>spingali@houstonmethodist.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rayne Rouce, MD</last_name>
      <phone>832-824-4647</phone>
      <email>rouce@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 22, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 22, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Helen Heslop</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director CAGT</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nivolumab</keyword>
  <keyword>Hodgkin Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoproliferative Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>EBV-specific T Cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoproliferative Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nivolumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

