<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02979925</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B2366-P</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1192133</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02979925</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Functions in Veterans With Post-traumatic Peripheral Neuropathic Pain</brief_title>
  <acronym>PTP-NP</acronym>
  <official_title>Improving Functions in Veterans With Post-Traumatic Peripheral Neuropathic Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study will set the foundation for future multi-center studies. To validate tMS
      as a non-contact and non-invasive pain treatment option for reducing pain in Veterans with
      PTP-NP and improving their overall functions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will only be conducted at the VA hospital in San Diego.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Spontaneous Pain Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed during each of the subject's 7 visits, time course of 2 months per subject</time_frame>
    <description>Spontaneous pain rating: Spontaneous pain level will be measured by using a sliding algometer, known as the Mechanical Visual Analog Scale (M-VAS). The device has been well validated, and is anchored at the left by &quot;no pain sensation&quot; and at the right by &quot;the most intense pain sensation imaginable.&quot; The corresponding length of the red bar with a scale from 0 to 100, which can be read on the back by the tester, represents the subject's intensity of pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Evoked Pain Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed during each of the subject's 7 visits, time course of 2 months per subject</time_frame>
    <description>Evoked Pain M-VAS rating: Stroking evoked pain will be assessed by gently moving a paintbrush over the site of PTNP. Punctate evoked pain will be conducted by gently pressing a 5.18 von Frey monofilament against the site of PTNP. The patients will be asked if pain is felt. If so, the intensity of pain will be rated in the M-VAS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuropathic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active transcutaneous magnetic stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active transcutaneous magnetic stimulation (TMS) at the target site of nerve damage/injury.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham transcutaneous magnetic stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham TMS will consist of the same parameters as active, however, the subject will be shielded from the magnetic field of the coil.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active Transcutaneous Magnetic Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Active transcutaneous magnetic stimulation (TMS) at the target site of nerve damage/injury.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active transcutaneous magnetic stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TMS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Transcutaneous Magnetic Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Sham TMS will consist of the same parameters as active, however, the subject will be shielded from the magnetic field of the coil.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham transcutaneous magnetic stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TMS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence of a personally signed and dated informed consent document indicating that
             the subject has been informed of all pertinent aspects of the study

          -  Subject is willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan, daily
             pain, sleep and all study related assessments and procedures

          -  Subjects must be literate in the language used in the assessments and pain diary

          -  Veterans (men or women) of any race or ethnicity who are at least 18 years of age

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential must agree to use a highly effective method
             of contraception throughout the study and for at least 7 days after the last session
             of the assigned treatment

               -  A subject is of childbearing potential if, in the opinion of the investigator,
                  he/she is biologically capable of having children and is sexually active

          -  Subject must have chronic peripheral neuropathic pain present for more than 4 months
             after a traumatic or surgical event per medical history, this may include, for
             example:

               -  motor vehicle accident

               -  fall

               -  sports injury

               -  knee or hip replacement

               -  hernia repair

               -  thoracotomy

               -  mastectomy

               -  focal/localized burns or crush injury

          -  In addition, to be eligible for inclusion in the study, all subjects must:

               -  have an average daily Numerical Pain Rating Scale (NPRS) score &gt;3 during B1; and

               -  have a spontaneous pain intensity &gt;30 on 0-100 Mechanical Visual Analogue Scale
                  (M-VAS) to be eligible for randomization

          -  Must have their implicated peripheral nerve(s) identified

          -  Must meet criteria for neuropathic pain assessment to meet eligibility for the study
             [46]. Pain distribution across a nerve territory and history indicates relevant lesion
             or disease plus criteria listed in a and/or b

          -  (A): At least one negative or positive sensory sign or symptom confined to innervation
             territory of the lesioned nervous structure. Examples of negative or positive signs or
             symptoms include:

               -  Burning, stabbing or tingling sensation/pain

               -  Numbness/paresthesia

               -  Cold, heat or pressure

               -  Hyperalgesia or allodynia

               -  Hypoesthesia

               -  Increased or decreased sharp sensation (e.g., pinprick testing)

               -  Decreased vibration/vibratory sensation

          -  (B): Prior diagnostic tests confirming lesion or disease explaining neuropathic pain
             (Nerve conduction studies, EMG, skin or nerve biopsy). Documentation of affected
             nerve(s) indicating that the subject's pain is of neuropathic origin and is a result
             of injury/trauma to the affected/implicated nerve(s).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects presenting with ANY of the following will NOT be included in the study:

          -  Subjects with neuropathic pain due to:

               -  diabetic peripheral neuropathy

               -  post herpetic neuralgia

               -  Human Immunodeficiency Virus

               -  chemo/anti-viral therapy

               -  trigeminal neuralgia

               -  carpal tunnel syndrome

               -  subjects whose post-traumatic neuropathic pain is categorized as central (e.g.,
                  spinal cord injury) rather than peripheral

          -  Subjects with pain due to Complex Regional Pain Syndrome (CRPS, Type I or Type II)

          -  Phantom limb pain after amputation. However, subjects with stump pain and phantom
             sensation but no phantom pain will not be excluded

          -  Subjects with skin conditions in the affected dermatome that in the judgment of the
             investigator can interfere with evaluation of the neuropathic pain condition

          -  Subjects with other pain such as lumbar or cervical radiculopathy that may confound
             assessment or self-evaluation of the peripheral neuropathic pain

               -  subjects with significant somatic pain at the site of their trauma that may
                  confound assessment or self-evaluation of their neuropathic pain

          -  Any subject considered at risk of suicide or self-harm based on investigator judgment
             and/or the details of a risk assessment

          -  Use of prohibited medications in the absence of appropriate washout periods

          -  Participation in any other clinical trial within the 30 days prior to screening and/or
             during participation in this study

          -  Subjects with a history of a cardiac arrhythmia that has led to the placement of a
             cardiac pacer or defibrillator will be excluded from the study

          -  Pregnant females and females of childbearing potential not using highly effective
             contraception or not agreeing to continue highly effective contraception during the
             study

          -  Subjects with a current diagnosis of DSM-IV-TR Axis I disorder, including, for
             example:

               -  schizophrenia

               -  bipolar disorder

               -  other psychotic disorders such as schizoaffective disorder and delusion disorder

               -  somatoform disorders or factitious disorders

               -  bipolar disorders, even if controlled or stable

               -  alcohol or substance related disorders in the past 2 years

               -  however, diagnoses of Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD) or major depression
                  (MDD) that is clinically stable are allowed

          -  Subjects with pending Worker's Compensation, Worker's Compensation, civil litigation
             or disability claims pertinent to the subject based upon trauma

               -  current involvement in out-of-court settlements for claims pertinent to subject's
                  trauma

               -  subjects with fully resolved litigation and compensation claims can participate

          -  Subjects who have previously received either transcranial or transcutaneous magnetic
             stimulation therapy in the past
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Albert Yick Leung, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA San Diego Healthcare System, San Diego, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Valerie Metzger Smith, BS AA</last_name>
    <phone>(858) 750-0274</phone>
    <email>valerie.metzgersmith@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA San Diego Healthcare System, San Diego, CA</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92161</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Valerie Metzger Smith, BS AA</last_name>
      <phone>(858) 750-0274</phone>
      <email>valerie.metzgersmith@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Albert Yick Leung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 29, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>neuropathic pain</keyword>
  <keyword>TMS</keyword>
  <keyword>nerve injury</keyword>
  <keyword>transcutaneous magnetic stimulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neuralgia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

