<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02979392</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H1604-140-758</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02979392</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I Study of TENPA in Advanced Solid Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Open-label, Dose Escalation (Part A), Cohort Expansion (Part B) Phase I Study to Investigate the Safety and to Determine Maximum Tolerated Dose and Recommended Phase 2 Dose of TENPA (Targeting-Enhancing Nanoparticles of Paclitaxel) in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumor</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yung-Jue Bang</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Seoul National University Hospital</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate the safety and to determine maximum tolerated
      dose and recommended phase 2 dose of TENPA (Targeting-Enhancing Nanoparticles of Paclitaxel)
      in patients with advanced solid tumor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose limiting toxicity (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>at least one cycle of treatment (3 weeks)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D)</measure>
    <time_frame>at least one cycle of treatment (3 weeks)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Plasma Concentration [Cmax]</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area Under the Curve [AUC]</measure>
    <time_frame>3 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate (RR)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Part A, Dose escalation TENPA (Targeting-Enhancing Nanoparticles of Paclitaxel) IV once every 3 weeks (Phase I starting dose 75 mg/m2) Part B, Expansion TENPA (Targeting-Enhancing Nanoparticles of Paclitaxel) IV once every 3 weeks (RP2D dose determined in part A)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TENPA (Targeting-Enhancing Nanoparticles of Paclitaxel)</intervention_name>
    <description>TENPA IV once every 3 weeks (Phase I starting dose 75 mg/m2)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Phase I</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Willing and able to provide written informed consent for voluntary participation in
             the trial

          2. Twenty years of age or older on the day of signing informed consent

          3. Advanced solid tumors with no standard treatment available

          4. Evaluable disease or have measurable lesion

          5. ECOG performance score of 0 or 1

          6. Life expectancy ≥ 12 weeks

          7. Adequate organ and marrow function as defined below:

             A. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 109/L (&gt; 1500 per mm3) B. Haemoglobin ≥ 8.0
             g/dL C. Platelet count ≥ 100 x 109/L (&gt;100,000 per mm3) D. AST (SGOT)/ALT (SGPT) ≤ 2.5
             x institutional ULN E. Serum bilirubin ≤ 2 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)
             F. Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg/dL

          8. Adequate heart function A. QT interval corrected for heart rate (QTc) ≤ 480 ms

          9. In the opinion of the investigator likely to have the willingness to comply with the
             study protocol during and after the study period and capable of complying with it

         10. Negative serum pregnancy test (β HCG) upon study entry and agree to use contraception

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Uncontrolled CNS metastatic disease (radiographically unstable and symptomatic
             disease). (note) Subjects with previously treated CNS metastases (surgery or
             stereotactic brain radiation therapy) that are radiographically stable for at least 4
             weeks are permitted to enroll. Subjects should not receive corticosteroids within 3
             weeks prior to study enrollment.

          2. History of leptomeningeal carcinomatosis; brain metastasis with seizure not controlled
             with standard medical management.

          3. Major surgery within 4 weeks: patient must have recovered from any effects of any
             major surgery.

          4. History of hematopoietic stem cell transplantation or solid organ transplantation

          5. History of Gilbert's syndrome

          6. Prior malignancy except:

             Basal cell carcinoma and squamous cell carcinoma of the skin that has undergone
             potentially curative surgery, in situ cervical cancer that has undergone potentially
             curative surgery and had no evidence of recurrence at least in past 3 years, other
             malignancy that has undergone curative surgery and had no evidence of disease at least
             in past 5 years.

          7. Significant cardiovascular disease, such as: history of myocardial infarction, acute
             coronary syndrome or coronary angioplasty/stenting/bypass grafting within the last 6
             months; History or current evidence of clinically significant arrhythmia or conduction
             disorder, except symptomatic congestive heart failure (CHR), atrial fibrillation, and
             paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia (PSVT)

          8. Sustained uncontrolled hypertension

          9. Test results indicating active infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIR) or
             hepatitis B or C, defined by positive serology testing (note) inactive hepatitis B
             carrier on antiviral agents are permitted to enroll.

         10. Neuromuscular disorder associated with CK elevation (eg. Inflammatory myopathies,
             muscular dystrophy, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, and spinobulbar muscular atrophy)

         11. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness or symptoms including, but not limited to, ongoing
             or active infection, bowel obstruction, psychiatric illness/social situations that
             would limit compliance with study requirement.

         12. Radiation therapy within 2 weeks of the first dose of study drug: patient must have
             recovered from any effects of radiation therapy

         13. Pregnant or breast feeding.

         14. Female subjects of childbearing potential within the projected duration of the study,
             starting with the screening visit through 30 days after the last dose of study drug.

             Female of childbearing potential are defined as those who are not surgically sterile
             (i.3., bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral oophorectomy, or complete hysterectomy) or
             who are not postmenopausal (defined as 12 months with no menses without an alternative
             medical cause). Periodic abstinence, the rhythm method, and the withdrawal method are
             not acceptable methods of birth control.

         15. Non-sterilized males who are sexually active with a female partner of child bearing
             potential from screening through 30 days after receipt of the final dose of study
             drug.

         16. Any medical, psychiatric or cognitive disorder that compromise the ability of the
             subject to give informed consent, comply with the study protocol, and complete the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 27, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 29, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 29, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Seoul National University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yung-Jue Bang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

