<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02973191</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JCAR015-ALL-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02973191</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Determine Safety, Feasibility and Efficacy of JCAR015 in Adult Subjects With B-Cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <acronym>ORBIT</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Open-label, Multiple Cohort, Single-arm, Multi-center Trial to Determine the Safety, Feasibility and Efficacy of JCAR015 in Adult Subjects With B-cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Celgene</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Juno</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Celgene</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-arm, multi-center, open-label, Phase 2 study to determine the efficacy and
      safety of JCAR015 in adult subjects with B-cell ALL. The study is divided into two sequential
      parts, Part A and Part B; subjects will be screened and will provide informed consent before
      initiating any study procedures in Part A of the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Development of JCAR015 has been discontinued. No subjects were enrolled/treated under protocol
    JCAR015-ALL-001
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 20, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 24, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 25, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary efficacy endpoint (for Cohorts 1-4) is ORR as determined by an Independent Review Committee (IRC). The ORR is, defined as proportion of subjects with a best overall response of Complete response (CR) or Complete response with incomplete peripheral blood count recovery (CRi) from 28 days through 6 months after the final infusion of JCAR015 or the start of receiving another anti-cancer therapy whichever comes first.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimal residual disease (MRD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the proportion of subjects who achieve a MRD negative complete response (CR) and the duration of MRD negative status, if achieved, after JCAR015 administration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number participants with adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Minimal residual disease (MRD) response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time from Minimal Residual Disease (MRD) response until MRD recurrence, morphologic relapse, or death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse-free survival (RFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Relapse-free survival (RFS) is defined as the interval from the first documentation of complete response (CR) or Complete response with incomplete peripheral blood count recovery (CRi) to the earlier date of relapse or death due to any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival (EFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Is defined as the time from the date of the first JCAR015 infusion to death from any cause, relapse, or treatment failure, whichever occurs first</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Is defined as the time from the date of the first JCAR015 infusion to date of death due to any reason</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Minimal residual disease (MRD) negative</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of subjects who achieve CR or CRi with an MRD-negative bone marrow, as assessed by IgH gene sequencing (or BCR-ABL qPCR or flow cytometry for Ph(+) ALL subjects)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depth of Minimal residual disease (MRD) response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement of response in patients with MRD+ ALLL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of remission (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Is defined as the interval from the first documentation of CR or CRi to the earlier date of relapse or death due to ALL. The first documentation of CR or CRi is defined as the latest of all dates of required measurements to establish the response. Duration of remission (DOR) will be evaluated based on the IRC evaluations for subjects who achieve a CR or CRi.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed concentration in plasma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics- Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time to reach maximum observed concentration in plasma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics - AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration‐time curve</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>JCAR015 administration</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Single dose of 1.0-3.0 mg/m^2 IV cyclophosphamide, JCAR015 Dose 1 1x10^6 Tcells/kg, JCAR015 Dose 2 3x10^6 Tcells/kg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>JCAR015</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>JCAR015 administration</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥18 years at the time of signing the informed consent form

          2. Subject must understand and voluntarily sign an Informed consent form (ICF) prior to
             any study-related assessments/procedures being conducted

          3. Subject is willing and able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol
             requirements

          4. Diagnosis of B-cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL)

          5. Evidence of CD19 expression via flow cytometry (peripheral blood or bone marrow) or
             immunohistochemistry (bone marrow biopsy)

          6. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤ 2

          7. No contraindications to cyclophosphamide. This includes subjects with:

               -  hypersensitivity to cyclophosphamide, any of its metabolites

               -  acute infections

               -  bone marrow aplasia or bone marrow depression prior to treatment

               -  urinary tract infection

               -  acute urothelial toxicity from cytotoxic chemotherapy or radiation therapy

               -  urinary outflow obstruction

               -  obstruction

          8. Adequate organ function, defined as:

             a. Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 × age-adjusted upper limit of normal (ULN) OR calculated
             creatinine clearance (Cockcroft and Gault) &gt; 30 mL/min/1.73 m2 b. Alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 5 × ULN and direct bilirubin &lt; 2.0 mg/dL (or &lt; 3.0 mg/dL for
             subjects with leukemic infiltration of the liver) c. Adequate pulmonary function,
             defined as ≤ Grade 1 dyspnea and oxygen saturation (SaO2) ≥ 92% on room air d.
             Adequate cardiac function, defined as left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) ≥ 40%
             as assessed by echocardiogram (ECHO) or multiple uptake gated acquisition (MUGA)
             performed within 1 month of signing the informed consent form

          9. Adequate central or peripheral vascular access for leukapheresis procedure. For
             subjects requiring central venous catheter (CVC) placement, a surgical consultation
             indicating subject eligibility for CVC placement is sufficient for enrollment.

         10. Subjects must agree to not donate blood, organs, sperm or semen, and egg cells for
             usage in other individuals without recipient knowledge about exposure to a genetically
             modified organ by the donor and having been informed about the potential risks
             associated with it at any point after receiving JCAR015 infusion.

         11. Females of childbearing potential (FCBP1) must:

             a. Have two negative pregnancy tests as verified by the Investigator (one negative
             serum beta human chorionic gonadotropin (ß-hCG) pregnancy test result within 7 days
             prior to the first dose of cytoreductive chemotherapy (Part A screening evaluation),
             and one negative serum or urine pregnancy test at the Part B screening evaluation
             prior to first JCAR015 infusion). She must agree to have another pregnancy test 90
             days post final JCAR015 dose. This applies even if the subject practices true
             abstinence2 from heterosexual contact.

             b. Either commit to true abstinence2 from heterosexual contact (which must be reviewed
             on a monthly basis and source documented) or agree to use, and be able to comply with,
             effective contraception without interruption. Contraception methods must include 1
             highly effective and 1 additional effective (barrier) method of contraception from at
             least 28 days prior to JCAR015 initial infusion and during the study therapy including
             dose interruptions. Cessation of contraception after this point should be discussed
             with a responsible physician. Note: Highly effective methods are defined as those that
             result in a low failure rate (ie, less than 1% per year) when used consistently and
             correctly. The following are examples of highly effective and additional effective
             methods of contraception:

             - Intrauterine device (IUD)

             - Hormonal (birth control pill, injections, implants)

             - Tubal ligation

             - Partner's vasectomy

             - Male Condom (additional effective method)

             - Diaphragm (additional effective method)

             - Cervical Cap (additional effective method) c. Agree to abstain from breastfeeding
             during study participation and for at least 90 days after the last dose of JCAR015.

             d. Agree to use highly effective methods of contraception during the entire study
             period (Part A through 12 months after the final JCAR015 infusion).

         12. Males who have partners of childbearing potential must agree to use an effective
             barrier contraceptive method during the entire study period (Part A through 12 months
             after the final JCAR015 infusion).

        Additional Cohort Specific Inclusion Criteria

        Inclusion Criteria (Cohorts 1-4) 1. Relapsed or refractory disease, defined as:

          1. First bone marrow relapse (prior Complete response (CR) duration &lt; 18 months) or any
             subsequent bone marrow relapse from Complete response (CR), OR

          2. Any bone marrow relapse after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT);
             subjects must be at least 2 months from HSCT at the time of signing the informed
             consent form and off immunosuppressant medication for at least 1 month at the time of
             signing the informed consent form (with the exception of low-dose steroids (≤ 20 mg
             prednisone or equivalent), and have no Graft versus host disease (GVHD), OR

          3. Refractory Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL), defined by not having achieved a
             Complete response (CR) or Complete response with incomplete peripheral blood count
             recovery (CRi) after two attempts at remission induction using standard chemotherapy
             regimens, OR

          4. Philadelphia chromosome positive (Ph+) B-cell ALL if subjects are intolerant to, or
             ineligible for, Tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) therapy, or have progressed after at
             least one line of TKI therapy.

             2. Bone marrow with morphological evidence of disease (≥ 5% blasts by morphology).

             Inclusion Criteria [Ph(+) (Cohort 3)] All subjects must meet Inclusion criteria
             described for Cohort 1.

             Inclusion Criteria (Cohort 4 only) 1. Eligible for Cohorts 1-3 but investigator has
             decided to administer blinatumomab as standard ALL therapy rather than other
             alternatives listed after leukapheresis but prior to part B of therapy Inclusion
             Criteria (MRD Positive+ [Cohort 5])

             Inclusion criteria as for Cohorts 1 and 2, with the exception of:

             1. Bone marrow without morphological evidence of disease characterized as ≤ 5% blasts
             by morphology, but with MRD detected by flow cytometry, or qPCR at a frequency of ≥ 1
             x 10-4 following standard of care induction and consolidation therapy in CR1 or in any
             subsequent CR

               -  For subjects in whom MRD has been followed only by flow cytometry, a nucleic acid
                  sample of the leukemia blasts of sufficient quality must be available to generate
                  realtime quantitative PCR (RQ-PCR) primers.

             4.2.2. Inclusion Criteria (Part B)

             1. Completion of Part A and successful generation of a JCAR015 cell product 2. Results
             from bone marrow examination following Part A:

          1. Group 1: Morphological evidence of disease (≥ 5% blasts by morphology)

          2. Group 2: Morphologic complete remission (bone marrow with &lt; 5% blasts) with or without
             blood count recovery (CR or CRi) or a hypoplastic, aplastic, or &quot;recovery&quot; marrow at
             Day 42 of Part A 3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status
             between 0 and 2 4. Adequate organ function, defined as:

          1. Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 × age-adjusted ULN OR calculated creatinine clearance

          2. (Cockcroft and Gault) &gt; 30 mL/min/1.73 m2

          3. ALT ≤ 5 × ULN (or ≤ 8 × ULN for subjects with leukemic infiltration of the liver) and
             direct bilirubin &lt; 2.0 mg/dL (or &lt; 3.0 mg/dL for subjects with leukemic infiltration
             of the liver)

          4. Adequate pulmonary function, defined as ≤ Grade 1 dyspnea and SaO2 ≥ 92% on room air
             5. Females of childbearing potential and males who have partners of childbearing
             potential follow the same inclusion criteria as Part A.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Isolated extramedullary disease relapse

          2. Concomitant genetic syndrome such as Fanconi anemia, Kostmann syndrome, Shwachman
             syndrome, or any other known bone marrow failure syndrome

          3. Burkitt's lymphoma/leukemia or chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML) lymphoid blast
             crisis (p210 BCR-ABL+)

          4. Prior malignancy, unless treated with curative intent and with no evidence of active
             disease present for &gt; 5 years before signing the informed consent form, with the
             following exceptions:

             a. Subjects with Stage I breast cancer that has been completely and successfully
             treated, requiring no therapy or only anti-hormonal therapy b. Subjects with T1N0M0 or
             T2N0M0 colorectal cancer who have been completely and successfully resected and who
             are disease-free for &gt; 2 years prior to screening c. Subjects with indolent prostate
             cancer, defined as clinical stage T1 or T2a, Gleason score ≤ 6, and prostate-specific
             antigen (PSA) &lt; 10 ng/mL, requiring no therapy or only anti- hormonal therapy d.
             Subjects with a history of basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix, fully resected, and with no evidence of active
             disease

          5. Treatment with any prior gene therapy product

          6. Active hepatitis B, active hepatitis C, or any human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)
             infection at the time of signing the informed consent form

          7. Systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or other infection that is not controlled (defined
             as exhibiting ongoing signs/symptoms related to the infection and without improvement,
             despite appropriate antibiotics or other treatment) at the time of signing the
             informed consent form

          8. Presence of Grade II-IV (Glucksberg) or B-D (IBMTR) acute or extensive chronic GVHD at
             the time of signing the informed consent form

          9. Active C S involvement by malignancy, defined as CNS-3 per NCCN guidelines. Subjects
             with a history of Central nervous system (CNS) disease that has been effectively
             treated (defined as one documented negative CSF evaluation within 1 month prior to
             signing the informed consent form) will be eligible

         10. History of any one of the following cardiovascular conditions within the past 6 months
             of signing the informed consent form: Class III or IV heart failure as defined by the
             New York Heart Association (NYHA), cardiac angioplasty or stenting, myocardial
             infarction, unstable angina, or other clinically significant cardiac disease

         11. History or presence of clinically relevant CNS pathology such as epilepsy, generalized
             seizure disorder, paresis, aphasia, stroke, severe brain injuries, dementia,
             Parkinson's disease, cerebellar disease, organic brain syndrome, or psychosis

         12. Participation in an investigational research study using an investigational agent
             within 30 days of signing the informed consent form, with the exception of
             investigational antiinfective agents (eg, antibacterial, antifungal, antiviral)

         13. History of treatment with a murine-derived biological product (unless subject has been
             shown to be negative for human anti-mouse antibodies [HAMA] prior to or during
             screening). Prior use of blinatumomab is permitted (provided there is evidence of CD19
             expression per Part A Inclusion Criterion #4). Chimeric biological products (eg,
             rituximab) are not considered murine for the purpose of this protocol.

         14. Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women

         15. Use of prohibited medications:

             a. Steroids: Therapeutic doses of corticosteroids (defined as &gt; 20 mg/day prednisone
             or equivalent) are prohibited within 7 days prior to leukapheresis. Physiologic
             replacement dosing of steroids (≤ 12 mg/m2/day hydrocortisone or equivalent [≤ 3
             mg/m2/day prednisone or ≤ 0.45 mg/m2/day dexamethasone]) is allowed. Topical steroids
             and intrathecal steroids for CNS relapse prophylaxis are permitted.

             b. Allogeneic cellular therapy: Donor lymphocyte infusions (DLI) are prohibited within
             4 weeks prior to leukapheresis c. GVHD therapies: Any drug used for GVHD within 4
             weeks prior to leukapheresis, eg, calcineurin inhibitors, methotrexate or other
             chemotherapeutics, mycophenolate mofetil, rapamycin, thalidomide, immunosuppressive
             antibodies (such as anti-CD20 [rituximab], anti-TNFα, anti-IL-6, or anti-IL-6R) d.
             Chemotherapies: Salvage chemotherapy (eg, cytosine arabinoside &gt; 100 mg/m2/day,
             anthracyclines, and cyclophosphamide) must be stopped at least 1 week prior to
             leukapheresis

         16. Treatment with alemtuzumab within 6 months prior to leukapheresis, or treatment with
             clofarabine or cladribine within 3 months prior to leukapheresis

         17. Uncontrolled medical, psychological, familial, sociological, or geographical
             conditions that do not permit compliance with the protocol, as judged by the
             Investigator; or subject unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures required
             in the protocol 4.3.2. Exclusion Criteria (Part B)

        Subjects must not meet any of the following criteria prior to Part B to be considered
        eligible:

          1. Systemic fungal, bacterial, viral, or other infection that is not controlled (defined
             as exhibiting ongoing signs/symptoms related to the infection and without improvement,
             despite appropriate antibiotics or other treatment)

          2. Active CNS involvement by malignancy, defined as CNS-3 per NCCN guidelines. Subjects
             with a history of CNS disease that has been effectively treated (defined as one
             documented negative CSF evaluation within 1 month prior to signing the informed
             consent form) will be eligible

          3. Presence of clinically relevant CNS pathology such as epilepsy, generalized seizure
             disorder, paresis, aphasia, stroke, severe brain injuries, dementia, Parkinson's
             disease, cerebellar disease, organic brain syndrome, or psychosis

          4. Presence of Grade II-IV (Glucksberg) or B-D (IBMTR) acute or extensive chronic GVHD

          5. Use of prohibited medications

          6. Female subjects that have a positive serum or urine pregnancy test, or are pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jens Hasskarl, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Celgene Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitair Ziekenhuis Gent</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gent</city>
        <zip>9000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University de Lille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <zip>59037</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Saint Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75010</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitaetsklinikum Carl Gustav Carus an der Technischen Universitaet Dresden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dresden</city>
        <zip>1307</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitatsklinikum Frankfurt</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt</city>
        <zip>60590</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Munich Grosshadern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grosshadern Campus</city>
        <zip>D-81377</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cologne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Köln</city>
        <zip>50924</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Leipzig</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leipzig</city>
        <zip>4103</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitaetsklinikum Ulm</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ulm</city>
        <zip>89081</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>USC Ematologia, Azienda Ospedaliera Papa Giovanni XXIII</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bergamo</city>
        <zip>24127</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istituto Clinico Humanitas - Istituti di Ricovero E Cura A Carattere Scientifico (IRCSS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <zip>20089</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universita La Sapienza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00168</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Citta della Salute e della Scienza di Torino</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <zip>10126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICO-Hospital Germans Trias i Pujol</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08916</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Salamanca</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salamanca</city>
        <zip>37007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chuv Bh-04</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lausanne</city>
        <zip>1011</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bristol Royal Infirmary, University of Bristol Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bristol</city>
        <zip>BS2 8BJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCL Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1E 6BT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 22, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 22, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>B-Cell Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>JCAR015</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Burkitt Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

