<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00850551</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>35243-E/A</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00850551</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Intervention in Pulmonary Exacerbation in Cystic Fibrosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early Intervention in Pulmonary Exacerbation in Cystic Fibrosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cystic Fibrosis Foundation Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will be performed at the University of Washington. Forty subjects with Cystic
      Fibrosis will be enrolled, with 20 randomized into the usual care arm and 20 randomized into
      the intervention arm. All subjects will be enrolled for 6 months and have 3 study visits. One
      at baseline, midpoint, and final. The intervention arm subjects may have more study visits
      depending on their respiratory symptoms.

      The intervention arm subjects will perform home spirometry twice a week with a PiKo-6 hand
      held spirometer. They will also have a home-based telemonitoring system connected to their
      phone line. They will be prompted twice a week to answer questions regarding their health via
      the telemonitor.

      Subjects who are not able to utilize the home-based telemonitoring system will answer the
      questions regarding their health via the internet from their home computer.

      If the subject's spirometry falls by greater than 10% from baseline or the CF respiratory
      symptoms change in 3 or more of the 8 respiratory symptoms captured by the telemonitor
      questionnaire, the subject will be called by the research staff and clinically evaluated by
      the study PIs within three days.

      The usual care subjects will continue with their routine care at the University of Washington
      CF Clinic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study design is a single center, randomized non-blinded controlled clinical trial
      comparing usual care to a program of early identification and treatment of pulmonary
      exacerbation in adults with CF. Forty subjects will be enrolled a at the University of
      Washington with 20 subjects randomized into the usual care arm, and 20 randomized into the
      intervention arm.

      Usual care is defined as the regular quarterly CF visits with acute visits triggered by calls
      from the patient to the clinic. Neither home assessment of spirometry or standardized home
      symptom assessment are a component of usual care. Treatment of a pulmonary exacerbation will
      be based on a standard protocol employing a standard definition and treatment regimen. This
      study will employ current standardized CF pulmonary exacerbation orders used at the
      University of Washington. Usual care arm subjects will have 3 study visits at baseline,
      midpoint, and final, over a period of 6 months.

      The early intervention protocol will employ twice a week assessment of home spirometry and CF
      respiratory symptoms; we will employ a home based monitoring system from Philips called the
      Philips Remote Patient Monitoring system (TeleStation). The home monitoring system is
      connected to the patient's phone line; this system is currently used in clinical practice in
      the care of patients with diabetes and heart failure.

      Subjects who do not have a home phone line will answer the CF respiratory questions via the
      internet from their home computer.

      The home spirometry will be done using a PiKo-6 hand held spirometer up to 84 spirometry
      values. If the subject's spirometry falls by greater than 10% from baseline or the CF
      respiratory symptoms change in 3 or more of the 8 respiratory symptoms captured in the
      questionnaire, the subject will be called by the research staff and clinically evaluated by
      the study PIs within three days. This evaluation will include a history and physical exam
      along with repeat spirometry at the clinic. The intervention arm subjects will have 3 study
      visits at baseline, midpoint, and final, over a period of 6 months. They may have additional
      study visits depending on their respiratory symptoms or exacerbations during the 6 month
      study period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the feasibility of the use of home spirometry and home symptom assessment on the diagnosis of acute pulmonary exacerbation in adult patients with mild to moderate CF lung disease</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the impact of the use of home spirometry, home symptom assessment and a protocolized approach to treatment of acute pulmonary exacerbation compared to usual care.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual Care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Twice weekly home spirometry and symptom assessment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Early Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Twice a week home spirometry and symptom assessment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Piko-6</other_name>
    <other_name>Philips Telemonitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female at least 18 years old

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of cystic fibrosis

          -  Chronically colonization wtih Pseudomonas defined by positive sputum or lower airway
             cultures on 2 or more occasions in any 12 month period

          -  Ability to participate in an interview and administration of questionnaire lasting 60
             minutes

          -  Clinically stable without IV antibiotic treatment for a pulmonary exacerbation in the
             prior 2 weeks

          -  Ability to perform spirometry

          -  Have a home telephone line or home computer with internet connection

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Colonization with burkholderia cepacia complex

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis as defined by the CFF
             guidance document

          -  Currently receiving antimicrobial therapy to treat non-tuberculous mycobacterium

          -  History of prior solid organ transplant

          -  Inability to speak and read the English language well enough to complete questionnaire
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher H Goss, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 24, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 25, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 30, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 30, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Washington</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chris Goss</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Early Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Exacerbation</keyword>
  <keyword>Cystic Fibrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung Function</keyword>
  <keyword>Spirometry</keyword>
  <keyword>Phillips Telemonitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Home Spirometry</keyword>
  <keyword>PiKo-6</keyword>
  <keyword>Home Monitoring</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no IPD</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

