<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00859495</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAB9658 (A6)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00859495</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trimodal Lung-Sparing Treatment of Pleural Mesothelioma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II, A Study of Lung-Sparing Combined Modality Protocol for the Treatment for Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma: The Columbia Protocol</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study is to determine the feasibility (as determined by lack of
      serious adverse events) and tolerability (as determined by patient's ability to complete the
      study) of a multimodal lung sparing regimen of surgery, interpleural and intravenous
      chemotherapy, and local P-32 irradiation for malignant pleural mesothelioma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Current surgical and/or chemotherapeutic approaches for malignant pleural mesothelioma are
      unsatisfactory and have not been shown to significantly prolong survival, and often lead to
      worsened pulmonary function and quality of life. We will investigate whether a prospective
      trial of trimodal (surgery, pleural chemotherapy, and pleural radiation) therapy can improve
      the overall 1 year survival in patients with malignant pleural mesothelioma. The proposed
      treatment will include exploratory thoracoscopy, placement of Mediport catheters into the
      pleural space, intraoperative chemotherapy, repeated intraperitoneal chemotherapy, and
      intrapleural instillation of radioactive P32 to radiate the pleural surfaces. In addition,
      because this study is randomized, half the patients will receive an additional three
      intravenous systemic chemotherapy treatments of cisplatin and pemetrexed (Alimta) in tandem
      with their intrapleural chemotherapy (weeks 3, 6, and 9 only).

      The potential significance of this research is that such treatment may render it less
      necessary to surgically remove the affected lungs in whole or in part, in order to achieve
      significant disease cytoreduction. We hope to alter the currently accepted paradigm that
      major lung surgery is an inescapable component of such treatment, and advance the concept
      that a combination of judicious preparative surgery, systemic chemotherapy, and locoregional
      drug treatment of the pleural surfaces may offer the best hope for prolongation of survival
      with intact lung function.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the feasibility of multimodal lung sparing regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Intrapleural chemotherapy (12 weeks) will be administered within two weeks after surgery. Approximately 30 days post last dose of chemotherapy (+/- 14 days), the patient should be reassessed for resolution of any treatment-related toxicity which may have occurred during the course of study participation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Pleural Mesothelioma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multimodal lung sparing regimen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intrapleural chemotherapy plus systemic chemotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Doxorubicin and cisplatin (intrapleural) + cisplatin and pemetrexed (systemic)</intervention_name>
    <description>Thoracoscopy to implant two intrapleural catheters followed by intrapleural chemotherapy with doxorubicin and cisplatin (weeks 1, 2, 4, 5, 7, and 8). Systemic chemotherapy treatments with cisplatin and pemetrexed during weeks 3, 6, and 9. Intrapleural radiotherapy with P-32 will be given 3 weeks after last dose of chemotherapy and 11 to 12 weeks after initial thoracoscopy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Multimodal lung sparing regimen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed malignant mesothelioma, &lt; 20% sarcomatoid type

          -  No radiographic or other imaging evidence of Stage IV (cardiac, mediastinal,
             peritoneal, other distant) disease.

          -  Ineligible for other high priority national or institutional study.

          -  Age &gt;18 years [to physiologic 75 years].

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 3 months.

          -  Performance status, PS 0-2 [Karnofsky Performance Status, KPS=70-100 %].

          -  Prior therapy allowed (one prior systemic regimen) meeting the following parameters.

          -  No prior chest radiation therapy within 6 weeks of treatment

          -  No prior chemotherapy regimens within four weeks of treatment

          -  Non pregnant, non-lactating. (serum HCG test will be performed in patients in whom
             there is a possibility of pregnancy.)

          -  Required initial laboratory data/clinical parameters (see also Sec. 8.0) White cell
             count: &gt;3000/ul. Platelet count: &gt;100,000/ul. Creatinine clearance: ≥ 45 ml/min
             Bilirubin: &lt; 2 x ULN SGOT or SGPT: &lt; 2 x ULN

          -  Informed Consent: Each patient must be completely aware of the nature of his/her
             disease process and must willingly give consent after being informed of the procedure
             to be followed, the experimental nature of the therapy, alternatives, potential
             benefits, side-effects, risks, and discomforts.

          -  No other coexistent malignancy. However, curatively treated or fully controlled solid
             tumors (other than mesothelioma) may be eligible if in the judgement of the PI, the
             benefit of treatment outweighs the risk.

          -  No serious medical or psychiatric illness preventing informed consent or intensive
             treatment (e.g., serious infection, congestive heart failure, angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia(s), or uncontrolled hypertension). HIV status or other severe illnesses
             will be assessed using medical records.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert N Taub, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center Clinical Research Management Office</last_name>
    <phone>212-305-8615</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 10, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 11, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 28, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 28, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mesothelioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liposomal doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

