<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00853853</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2048-08</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00853853</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>EnSeal Device Versus Ferguson Technique in Hemorrhoidectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Trial Comparing Standard Ferguson Technique With the EnSeal Device During Hemorrhoidectomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Steven Schechter, M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ethicon, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Miriam Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will compare hemorrhoid surgery by comparing a sutureless heating device with the
      old standard hemorrhoid surgery. Patients will be followed closely for wound healing and
      satisfaction.

      Hypothesis: The sutureless device will be less painful for the patient and easier for the
      surgeon to perform.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The EnSeal Device is approved for laparoscopic surgery in ligating and dividing vascular
      tissue during abdominal surgery. Electrical energy is converted into heat energy and
      resultant simultaneous division of tissues. This allows surgery to be bloodless and
      sutureless. This device is being used in the current study in the treatment of hemorrhoidal
      disease where vascular tissue is excised in bloodless and sutureless fashion. The device is
      FDA-approved for laparoscopic surgery. This is currently being used in institutions
      throughout the United States and Europe.

      This study is looking at the EnSeal device and comparing it to a gold standard hemorrhoidal
      procedure to see if the OR procedure can be simplified and the postoperative course improved.

      The trial is a randomized, controlled, prospective study. Patients will be informed of the
      two techniques being studied and will be randomized in the operating room by opening up an
      envelope with the procedure to be employed inside. The envelopes will be numbered 1 through
      100, with 50 envelopes containing a slip of paper stating that the surgery will be done using
      the Ferguson technique and 50 envelopes containing a slip of paper stating the that the
      surgery will be done using the EnSeal device. These slips of paper will be placed in the
      envelopes and sealed. The envelopes will be mixed up by someone not involved in the study and
      then numbered 1 through 100. No one will know which surgical technique will be used on the
      patient until the surgeon opens the envelope on the day of surgery.

      Patients will be followed postoperatively in the office during week 1, week 4, and week 12.
      At this time, they will be assessed for postoperative complications including but not limited
      to: bleeding, urinary retention, infection, fecal impaction, hospital re-admission and pain.
      Delayed complications will also be followed including urinary retention, impaired healing,
      constipation, abscess, fistula formation, fissure, stenosis, fecal incontinence, and flatus
      incontinence. The patient's pain score will be assessed using the Universal Pain Assessment
      Tool, allowing the patient to describe their pain level on a scale between 1 and 10.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>to examine the advantage and disadvantages of the EnSeal device as it applies to hemorrhoidal surgery and document outcomes as compared to the traditional closed Ferguson hemorrhoidectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week, 4 weeks and 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemorrhoids</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1. EnSeal Device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The EnSeal device cuts and seals with heat energy leaving a sutureless wound, which heals with security against bleeding. The device is able to seal blood vessels up to 7mm and hemorrhoidal vessels are much smaller than this size.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2. Ferguson Hemorrhoidectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The closed Ferguson hemorrhoidectomy technique is a gold standard operation that has been in existence for 50 years. This operation is done under general or intravenous sedation, and the operating surgeon uses a special clamp to go across the hemorrhoidal complex followed by excision of the hemorrhoid. Sutures that dissolve are then placed at the root of the hemorrhoid, securely tied, and then run about the clamp. The clamp is removed and then the suture tightened, then the suture line is reinforced.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EnSeal Device</intervention_name>
    <description>Hemorrhoidectomy using the EnSeal Device, which is an instrument cuts and seals with heat energy leaving a sutureless wound, which heals with security against bleeding.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1. EnSeal Device</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ferguson Hemorrhoidectomy technique</intervention_name>
    <description>The closed Ferguson hemorrhoidectomy technique is a gold standard operation that has been in existence for 50 years. This operation is done under general or intravenous sedation, and the operating surgeon uses a special clamp to go across the hemorrhoidal complex followed by excision of the hemorrhoid. Sutures that dissolve (such as 3.0 vicryl) are then placed at the root of the hemorrhoid, securely tied, and then run about the clamp. The clamp is removed and then the suture tightened, then the suture line is reinforced. This can be done from 1-3 hemorrhoidal groups at a single time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2. Ferguson Hemorrhoidectomy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Men &amp; woman between ages 18-80.

          2. ASA level I, II, and III.

          3. External hemorrhoids may or may not be present.

          4. Internal hemorrhoids at least Grade II, III, and IV.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age less than 18, or greater than 80.

          2. ASA level IV.

          3. Grade I internal hemorrhoids.

          4. Patients on Coumadin, Plavix, or other anticoagulant.

          5. Associated procedure such as sphincterotomy, drainage of abscess, fistulotomy, or the
             like.

          6. Pregnancy - Women who have a positive urine pregnancy test pre-op will be excluded
             from the study.

          7. Inflammatory bowel disease.

          8. History of chronic active hepatitis B, C, or HIV infection.

          9. Lactating women.

         10. Inability to follow up with surgeon in office at 1 week, 4 weeks, and 3 months
             postoperatively.

         11. Prior chronic narcotic use (&gt; 30 days)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven Schechter, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Miriam Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Miriam Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02906</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 2, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 19, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 19, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Miriam Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Steven Schechter, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Site Director of Colorectal Fellowship program for The Miriam Hospital affiliated with Brown University Program in Colorectal Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hemorrhoidectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemorrhoids</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhoids</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

