<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00855634</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TUM-Chir-001/2009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00855634</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Resection in Pancreatic Cancer With Minimal Metastatic Disease or Venous Infiltration Trial at Technische Universität München</brief_title>
  <acronym>PaMeViTUM</acronym>
  <official_title>Extended Versus Standard Resection in Two Cohorts of Patients With Adenocarcinoma of the Pancreas: Minimal Metastatic Disease or Venous Infiltration - a Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Technische Universität München</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Technische Universität München</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      PaMeViTUM is a mono-centric prospective randomized controlled trial that compares different
      operating procedures in patients with pancreatic cancer and minimal metastatic disease or
      venous infiltration.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PaMeViTUM is a mono-centric prospective randomized controlled trial comparing different
      operating procedures in patients with pancreatic cancer and minimal metastatic disease or
      venous infiltration. Patients will be randomized intraoperatively after fulfilling all
      inclusion criteria (in particular: suspicion of cancer of the pancreas and an intraoperative
      histologically proven diagnosis of pancreatic adenocarcinoma; intraoperative assessment of
      tumor as potentially locally respectable). If no metastases and no infiltration of the portal
      vein are detected during the operation, the standard resection will be performed (for tumors
      of the pancreatic head: (pylorus-preserving) pancreaticoduodenectomy; for tumors of the
      pancreatic body/tail: distal (left) pancreatic resections; for tumors of the head and
      body/tail: total pancreatectomy). In the case of tumor infiltration of the pyloric region or
      the distal stomach, a classical pancreaticoduodenectomy will be performed.

      If the patient has pancreatic cancer with minimal metastatic disease (COHORT 1) and fulfills
      all inclusion criteria, she/he will be randomized into one of the following arms:

        -  Arm 1 (intervention): resection of the primary tumor, followed by resection of the liver
           metastasis/metastases

        -  Arm 2 (control): exploration and/or gastroenterostomy and/or
           hepaticojejunostomy/choledochojejunostomy

      If there are no liver metastases, following mobilization (and potentially also the dissection
      of the pancreas at the pancreatic head), the extension of the tumor towards the superior
      mesenteric/splenic/portal vein is examined. If there is venous infiltration (COHORT 2) and
      the patient fulfills the inclusion criteria, she/he will be randomized into one of the
      following arms:

        -  Arm 1 (intervention): resection of the primary tumor with resection of the portal vein
           (and/or superior mesenteric vein/splenic vein (SMV/SV)

        -  Arm 2 (control): resection of the primary tumor with dissection of the portal vein
           (and/or superior mesenteric vein/splenic vein (SMV/SV) plus tumor masses adjacent to
           these veins; no venous resection The aim of this study is to demonstrate that an
           extension of the resectability criteria in patients with pancreatic cancer and 1)
           minimal metastatic disease OR 2) venous infiltration improves overall survival. A
           secondary aim of the study is to prove that resection in these patient cohorts improves
           quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Protocol planned interim analysis after two years showed very low recruitment in cohort 1 and
    low recruitment in cohort 2.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>August 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life Perioperative morbidity and mortality 1-year survival and 2-year survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Additional 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">355</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>COHORT 1 (minimal metastatic disease):
Arm 1 (intervention): resection of the primary tumor, followed by resection of the liver metastasis/metastases
Arm 2 (control): exploration and/or gastroenterostomy and/or hepaticojejunostomy/choledochojejunostomy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>COHORT 2 (venous infiltration):
Arm 1 (intervention): resection of the primary tumor with resection of the portal vein (and/or superior mesenteric vein/splenic vein (SMV/SV)
Arm 2 (control): resection of the primary tumor with dissection of the portal vein (and/or superior mesenteric vein/splenic vein (SMV/SV) plus tumor masses adjacent to these veins; no venous resection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resection of metastases</intervention_name>
    <description>resection of the primary tumor, followed by resection of the liver metastasis/metastases</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resection of infiltrated veins</intervention_name>
    <description>resection of the primary tumor with resection of the portal vein (and/or superior mesenteric vein/splenic</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  suspicion of cancer of the pancreas and an intraoperative histologically proven
             diagnosis of pancreatic adenocarcinoma.

          -  intraoperative assessment of tumor as potentially locally resectable

          -  COHORT 1: Minimal metastatic disease

          -  COHORT 2: Venous infiltration

          -  ability to sign the informed consent.

          -  Karnofsky performance status &gt; 70.

          -  Life-expectancy of more than 3 months.

          -  able to attend follow-up.

          -  no previous or concurrent malignancy diagnoses, except non-melanoma skin cancer and in
             situ carcinoma of the cervix.

          -  no serious medical, psychological, familial, sociological or geographical conditions
             potentially hampering compliance with the study protocol and follow-up.

          -  patients older than 18 years.

          -  no pregnant or lactating women.

          -  preoperative evaluation by thin-sliced CT scans with:

          -  No evidence of substantial extra-pancreatic disease, i.e. no evidence of malignant
             ascites, extended liver metastasis (&gt;5 metastatic lesions), spread to other distant
             abdominal organs, peritoneal metastasis, spread to extra-abdominal organs.

          -  No evidence of extension of the tumor into the celiac axis or superior mesenteric
             artery (T4 disease).

          -  intraoperative findings with:

          -  tumor assessed as potentially locally resectable.

          -  no signs of peritoneal metastasis or tumor manifestations outside of the pancreas and
             the liver.

          -  frozen section: adenocarcinoma

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  extrapancreatic disease (except minimal metastatic disease of the liver, see above)

          -  concomitant venous infiltration and minimal metastatic disease

          -  extension of the tumor into the celiac axis or superior mesenteric artery

          -  life expectancy of less than 3 months

          -  previous or concurrent malignancy diagnosis, except non-melanoma skin cancer and in
             situ carcinoma of the cervix

          -  conditions potentially hampering compliance (also inclusion criteria)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Surgery and Institute of Statistics Klinikum rechts der Isar der Technischen Universität München Ismaningerstrasse 22 81675 München, Germany</name>
      <address>
        <city>München</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 3, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 3, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 5, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 5, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 6, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>metastasis</keyword>
  <keyword>venous infiltration</keyword>
  <keyword>Pancreatic cancer with minimal metastatic disease or venous infiltration</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

