<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00396461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HC-G-H-0510</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2005-003542-33</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00396461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ICULIP, Influence of Two Lipid Emulsions in the Nosocomial Infection in Critical Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>ICULIP</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase IV-IV. ICULIP,a Prospective,Multi-centre,Randomised,Comparative,Double-blind Study to Evaluate Two Different Types of Lipid Emulsions Used for Total Parenteral Nutrition in Critical Patients and Their Influence on Nosocomial Infection.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>B. Braun Medical SA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>B. Braun Medical SA</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to analyse the effect of two total parenteral nutrition diets with lipid
      emulsions of different compositions on the incidence of nosocomial infection in critical
      patients. One diet will contain an MCT/LCT emulsion concentrated to 20% (50:50 ratio) and the
      other will comprise an MCT/LCT/fish oil emulsion (50:40:10 ratio). The secondary objective of
      this study is to analyse mortality in hospital and up to 6 months of discharge.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During the last years the most widely used lipid emulsion for parenteral nutrition has been
      based on soybean oil. This first generation of lipid emulsions used in TPN contained w-6
      series polyunsaturated long-chain fatty acids (LCT) from soy, maize, sunflower and safflower
      oil. LCT contain an excess of linoleic acid which, when metabolised, produce large quantities
      of arachidonic acid and its metabolites. Although the generally used doses seem safe (1-2
      g/kg/day by continuous perfusion), alterations in pulmonary function in patients with acute
      adult respiratory distress syndrome have been described, as have alterations in platelet
      function, hepatic function and haemodynamics, which are attributed to the excess of said
      metabolites. However, the most important side effect of the LCT lipid infusions is its
      influence on the immune response. Experimental and clinical studies show that LCT can
      interfere with various stages of the immune response such as the production of antibodies,
      complement synthesis, granulocytic and lymphocytic activity and the reticuloendothelial
      system. Various hypotheses have been formulated to explain the modulator effect of the
      polyunsaturated fatty acids on immune function: changes in the permeability of the cellular
      membrane, modifications in the synthesis of eicosanoids and the presence of peroxides derived
      from the oxidation of polyunsaturated fatty acids.

      In summary, although linoleic acid as a dietary essential fatty acid is important, its
      excessive intake is associated with undesirable immunological and inflammatory events. Thus
      it is recommended that soybean oil should be partly replaced by other lipids.

      To avoid these side effects the second generation lipid emulsions were developed. These
      contain a combination of medium- and long-chain fatty acids (MCT/LCT) with lower w-6 fatty
      acid content. MCT/LCT lipid emulsions are safe and do not produce biochemical or metabolic
      alterations or gaseous exchange in patients with ARDS. MCT/LCT combinations seem to reduce
      the generation of eicosanoids and do not alter the immune response in in-vitro and
      experimental studies. The impact of these differences on the nosocomial infection and the
      clinical prognosis of the patients has not been studied sufficiently despite the fact that
      some studies show reduced mortality and morbidity using MCT/LCT emulsions when compared with
      the use of pure LCT emulsions. MCT/LCT emulsions are normally used in clinical practice on
      patients that have required parenteral nutrition for 20 years.

      Recently, the clinical use in artificial nutrition of omega-3 series polyunsaturated fatty
      acids, eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) present in many fish oils
      has been significant. EPA is a precursor to certain eicosanoid series that compensate the
      proinflammatory effects of the eicosanoids in arachidonic acid (omega-6 series). The
      objective is immunomodulation to attenuate the inflammatory response of patients without
      negatively impacting on the immune function. The use of enteral diets enriched with omega-3
      series fatty acids (fish oil) in post-operation cancer patients showed a reduction in the
      number of days in hospital and infectious complications.

      The use of fish oil or fat emulsions enriched with fish oil (omega-3) in parenteral nutrition
      has already been the subject of various studies: where modulation of the inflammatory
      response markers has been shown, reduces the stay in hospital and the need for mechanical
      ventilation in patients undergoing major abdominal surgery, reduces the stay in hospital in
      patients undergoing digestive surgery… So, w-3 lipids exhibit strong immunologic properties.
      They offer the possibility to counterbalance the negative effects of conventional w-6 fatty
      acids. Recent studies exhibit positive effects of intravenous use of fish oil on immunologic
      functions and clinical parameters in surgical and septic patients

      The purpose of this study is to analyse the effect of two total parenteral nutrition diets
      with lipid emulsions of different compositions on the incidence of nosocomial infection in
      critical patients. One diet will contain an MCT/LCT emulsion concentrated to 20% (50:50
      ratio) (w3:w6 is 1:7) and the other will comprise an MCT/LCT/fish oil emulsion (50:40:10
      ratio) (w3:w6 is 1:2,7). The secondary objective of this study is to analyse mortality in
      hospital and up to 6 months after discharge.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The analyses will particularly focus on: Pneumonia associated with mechanical ventilation, Catheter infection, Bacteraemia not associated with catheter, Urinary infection, Infection of surgical wounds and Intra-abdominal abscess and peritonitis.</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will receive at least 5 days of PN. Clinical condition and nosocomial infection will be monitored daily until the first phase of the study is completed on day 28 or the patient is discharged from the unit.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the incidence of nosocomial infection associated with the administration of two different lipid solutions in total parenteral nutrition of patients in an Intensive Care Unit.</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will receive at least 5 days of PN. Clinical condition and nosocomial infection will be monitored daily until the first phase of the study is completed on day 28 or the patient is discharged from the unit.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Study mortality at the end of the study and 6 months after discharge from ICU; Hospital stay and/or in Intensive Care Unit; Mechanical ventilation days; Assessment of hepatic function; Assessment of nutritional efficacy.</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of the study and 6 months after discharge from ICU.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">212</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Illness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TPN A (Group I)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Emulsion based on 20% MCT/LCT (50:50 ratio)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TPN B (Group II)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Emulsion based on 20% MCT/LCT/w3 (50:40:10 ratio), medium- and long-chain triglycerides and fish oil triglycerides</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MCT/LCT (1:1)</intervention_name>
    <description>Emulsion based on 20% MCT/LCT (50:50 ratio)</description>
    <arm_group_label>TPN A (Group I)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LIPOFUNDINA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MCT/LCT/omega-3 (5:4:1)</intervention_name>
    <description>Emulsion based on 20% MCT/LCT/w3 (50:40:10 ratio), medium- and long-chain triglycerides and fish oil triglycerides.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TPN B (Group II)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LIPOPLUS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients of both sexes, prospective admission to Intensive Care Units (ICUs), over 18
        years, where TPN is required as a nutritional metabolic support for a minimum period of 5
        days and where said patients have signed the informed consent form.

        The indications for administration of parenteral nutrition shall be those recommended by
        the American Society of Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition (ASPEN), and in particular:

          -  Severe malnutrition

          -  Major intra-abdominal surgery

          -  Peritonitis

          -  Intestinal ischaemia

          -  Intestinal occlusion

          -  Gastrointestinal fistulas

          -  Small intestine

        Patients of both sexes, over 18 years, that commencing nutritional support with enteral
        diets in the first 3 days of admission to ICU require parenteral nutrition as:

          -  75% of the calculated energy requirements have not been reached after three days
             receiving enteral nutrition.

          -  Gastrointestinal complications have been suffered as a result of enteral nutrition
             that cannot be treated or are persistent in the first 3 days of admission.

        In this case EN will be suspended and the patient will be included in the protocol
        receiving PN.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  APACHE II &lt; 13

          -  Morbid obesity (BMI ≥ 39)

          -  Hepatic disease defined within the following set of parameters:

               1. Portal hypertension with gastrointestinal bleeding on admission

               2. Clinically apparent hepatocellular ascites

               3. Hepatocellular bilirubin higher than 3 mg/dL

               4. Serum albumin less than 30 g/L with portal hypertension

               5. Grade II or higher encephalopathy

               6. Clinical diagnosis of alcoholic hepatitis

          -  Chronic renal insufficiency defined by one of the following criteria:

               1. Plasmatic creatinine greater than 4 mg/dL

               2. Chronic peritoneal dialysis or haemodialysis

          -  Patients with severe acquired or familial hyperlipidaemias (&gt; 400 mg/day) of any kind

          -  Serious chronic neurological disease defined by one of the following criteria:

               1. Cerebrovascular accident with persistent neurological deficit in the past six
                  months

               2. Neurological deficit that necessitates chronic confinement

          -  Neoplastic patients with metastasis and a life expectancy of less than six months

          -  Patients that underwent chemotherapy or radiotherapy during the month prior to the
             study

          -  Patients that received chronic treatment with corticoids in the month preceding
             admission to ICU. Patients receiving treatment with corticoids since admission to ICU
             for septic shock should not be excluded.

          -  Continuous infusion treatment for more than 24 hours with propofol or with other
             pharmaceuticals where lipid emulsions are used as the vehicle

          -  Infectious diseases transmitted through the blood, products derived from blood or
             urine: hepatitis B, C and HIV

          -  Inclusion in another clinical trial

          -  Having received TPN in the month prior to inclusion in the study

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Refusal to participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Abelardo García de Lorenzo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Universitario La Paz, Madrid</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alfonso Bonet Saris, MD_Study Coordinator</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Universitari de Girona Doctor Josep Trueta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Teodoro Grau Carmona, MD_Study Coordinator</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Severo Ochoa Leganés (Madrid)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Son Dureta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palma de Mallorca</city>
        <state>Baleares</state>
        <zip>07014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Bellvitge (H.U.B.)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hospitalet de Llobregat</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08097</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Cruces</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barakaldo</city>
        <state>Bizcaya</state>
        <zip>48903</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Marqués de Valdecilla</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santander</city>
        <state>Cantabria</state>
        <zip>39008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Gran Canaria Dr. Negrín</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Palmas de Gran Canaria</city>
        <state>Gran Canaria</state>
        <zip>35010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo Hospitalario Materno Insular de Gran Canaria</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Palmas de Gran Canaria</city>
        <state>Gran Canaria</state>
        <zip>35016</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Severo Ochoa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leganés</city>
        <state>Madrid</state>
        <zip>28911</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario &quot;Virgen de la Arrixaca&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Palmar</city>
        <state>Murcia</state>
        <zip>30120</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario de Alicante</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alicante</city>
        <zip>03010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital del Mar (Institut Municipal d'Assistència Sanitària, IMAS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari Vall d'Hebrón</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario &quot;Puerta del Mar&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cádiz</city>
        <zip>11009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari de Girona Doctor Josep Trueta</name>
      <address>
        <city>Girona</city>
        <zip>17007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Virgen de las Nieves</name>
      <address>
        <city>Granada</city>
        <zip>18014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Arnau de Vilanova</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lleida</city>
        <zip>25198</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fundación Jiménez Díaz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28040</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario &quot;Reina Sofía&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Murcia</city>
        <zip>30003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Regional Universitario Carlos Haya</name>
      <address>
        <city>Málaga</city>
        <zip>29010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Valme</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valencia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Del Río Hortega</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valladolid</city>
        <zip>47010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Miguel Servet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zaragoza</city>
        <zip>50009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.senpe.com</url>
    <description>Spanish Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.nutritioncare.org/</url>
    <description>ASPEN, American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition --&gt; Nutrition-related Links</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.semicyuc.org/</url>
    <description>Spanish Society for Intensive Medicine, Critical and Coronary Units</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cerra FB. Hypermetabolism, organ failure, and metabolic support. Surgery. 1987 Jan;101(1):1-14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3541266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>García-de-Lorenzo A. Lipid emulsions with different phospholipid/triglyceride ratio in critically ill septic and traumatic patients. Crit Care Med. 1998 Dec;26(12):2094-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9875927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bach AC, Frey A, Lutz O. Clinical and experimental effects of medium-chain-triglyceride-based fat emulsions--a review. Clin Nutr. 1989 Oct;8(5):223-35.</citation>
    <PMID>16837294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mathru M, Dries DJ, Zecca A, Fareed J, Rooney MW, Rao TL. Effect of fast vs slow intralipid infusion on gas exchange, pulmonary hemodynamics, and prostaglandin metabolism. Chest. 1991 Feb;99(2):426-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1989806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gogos CA, Kalfarentzos F. Total parenteral nutrition and immune system activity: a review. Nutrition. 1995 Jul-Aug;11(4):339-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8580573</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calder PC, Sherrington EJ, Askanazi J, Newsholme EA. Inhibition of lymphocyte proliferation in vitro by two lipid emulsions with different fatty acid compositions. Clin Nutr. 1994 Apr;13(2):69-74.</citation>
    <PMID>16843362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clarke PJ, Ball MJ, Hands LJ, Dennison AR, Tunbridge A, White K, Kettlewell MG. Use of a lipid containing medium chain triglycerides in patients receiving TPN: a randomized prospective trial. Br J Surg. 1987 Aug;74(8):701-4.</citation>
    <PMID>3115354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barton RG. Nutrition support in critical illness. Nutr Clin Pract. 1994 Aug;9(4):127-39. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8078451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suchner U, Katz DP, Fürst P, Beck K, Felbinger TW, Senftleben U, Thiel M, Goetz AE, Peter K. Effects of intravenous fat emulsions on lung function in patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome or sepsis. Crit Care Med. 2001 Aug;29(8):1569-74.</citation>
    <PMID>11505129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gogos CA, Kalfarentzos FE, Zoumbos NC. Effect of different types of total parenteral nutrition on T-lymphocyte subpopulations and NK cells. Am J Clin Nutr. 1990 Jan;51(1):119-22.</citation>
    <PMID>2136970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen GL, Mascioli EA, Seidner DL, Istfan NW, Domnitch AM, Selleck K, Babayan VK, Blackburn GL, Bistrian BR. Parenteral infusion of long- and medium-chain triglycerides and reticuloendothelial system function in man. JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 1990 Sep-Oct;14(5):467-71.</citation>
    <PMID>2122019</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suchner U, Senftleben U. Immune modulation by polyunsaturated fatty acids during nutritional therapy: interactions with synthesis and effects of eicosanoids. Infusionsther Transfusionsmed. 1994 Jun;21(3):167-82. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7919904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calder PC. Long-chain n-3 fatty acids and inflammation: potential application in surgical and trauma patients. Braz J Med Biol Res. 2003 Apr;36(4):433-46. Epub 2003 Apr 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12700820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gadek JE, DeMichele SJ, Karlstad MD, Pacht ER, Donahoe M, Albertson TE, Van Hoozen C, Wennberg AK, Nelson JL, Noursalehi M. Effect of enteral feeding with eicosapentaenoic acid, gamma-linolenic acid, and antioxidants in patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome. Enteral Nutrition in ARDS Study Group. Crit Care Med. 1999 Aug;27(8):1409-20.</citation>
    <PMID>10470743</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weiss G, Meyer F, Matthies B, Pross M, Koenig W, Lippert H. Immunomodulation by perioperative administration of n-3 fatty acids. Br J Nutr. 2002 Jan;87 Suppl 1:S89-94.</citation>
    <PMID>11895158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Köller M, Senkal M, Kemen M, König W, Zumtobel V, Muhr G. Impact of omega-3 fatty acid enriched TPN on leukotriene synthesis by leukocytes after major surgery. Clin Nutr. 2003 Feb;22(1):59-64.</citation>
    <PMID>12553951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsekos E, Reuter C, Stehle P, Boeden G. Perioperative administration of parenteral fish oil supplements in a routine clinical setting improves patient outcome after major abdominal surgery. Clin Nutr. 2004 Jun;23(3):325-30. Erratum in: Clin Nutr. 2004 Aug;23(4):755-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15158295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>ASPEN Board of Directors and the Clinical Guidelines Task Force. Guidelines for the use of parenteral and enteral nutrition in adult and pediatric patients. JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 2002 Jan-Feb;26(1 Suppl):1SA-138SA. Erratum in: JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr 2002 Mar-Apr;26(2):144.</citation>
    <PMID>11841046</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carpentier YA, Van Gossum A, Dubois D, Deckeibaum R. Lipid Metabolism in Parenteral Nutrition. In: Wilmore DW, Carpentier YA (Eds). Metabolic Support of the Critically III Patient. Berlin, Springer-Veriag 1993, pp 35-74</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Driscoll DF, Adolph M, Bistrian BR. Lipid emulsions in parenteral nutrition. In: Rombeau JL, Rolandelli R, eds. Parenteral nutrition. Philadelphia: W. B. Saunders Company; 2000:35-39.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Santoli D, Zurier RB. Prostaglandin E precursor fatty acids inhibit human IL-2 production by a prostaglandin E-independent mechanism. J Immunol. 1989 Aug 15;143(4):1303-9. Erratum in: J Immunol 1990 Jan 15;144(2):774.</citation>
    <PMID>2545787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kinsella JE, Lokesh B. Dietary lipids, eicosanoids, and the immune system. Crit Care Med. 1990 Feb;18(2 Suppl):S94-113. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2105185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumar SG, Das UN, Kumar KV, Madhavi N, Das NP, Tan BKH. Effect of n-6 and n-3 fatty acids on the proliferation of human lymphocyes and their secretion of TN F-alpha and IL-2 in vitro. Nutr Res 1992; 12: 815-823.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grau T, Ruiz de Adana JC, Zubillaga S, Fuerte S, Girón C. [Randomized study of two different fat emulsions in total parenteral nutrition of malnourished surgical patients;effect of infectious morbidity and mortality]. Nutr Hosp. 2003 May-Jun;18(3):159-66. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>12875092</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grimminger F, Seeger W, Mayer K. Use of n-3 fatty acid-containing lipid emulsions in the intensive care unit environment: the clinician's view. Clinical Nutrition 2002, 21, Supplement 2: 23-29.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wichmann MW, Morlion B, Czarnetzki H-D, Thul P, Jauch K-W. Reduction of length of postoperative stay by fish oil containing lipid emulsion - data from a multicenter trial. Clinical Nutrition 2004, 23: 1471</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 6, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 7, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 19, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Critical Illness</keyword>
  <keyword>Fat Emulsions, Intravenous</keyword>
  <keyword>Superinfection</keyword>
  <keyword>Parenteral Nutrition</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cross Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

