<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00395668</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2103-05-0005</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Project nr. 0501- (Dept. ID)</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00395668</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TETRA (Terrestrial Trunked Radio)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Acute Changes in Cognitive Performance Arising From Exposure to TETRA Handset.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aarhus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aalborg University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aarhus University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aarhus</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate if electromagnetic radiation from TETRA handset
      can influence cognitive function and the well-being of healthy adults. Furthermore, the
      purpose is to provide any special information about the subjects which can cause the possible
      reactions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      TETRA is the term used to describe the technology known as Terrestrial Trunked Radio. It is
      the European standard digital mobile radio communication system. TETRA has primarily been
      developed to enable the deployment of secure, digital PMR (Professional Mobile Radio)
      services required by the public safety and emergency services (police, fire and paramedics).
      The TETRA system is specified to work within the VHF and UHF bands (150 MHz to 900 MHz)
      [Chadwick, 2003], and operates most often at frequencies around 400 MHz. The lower frequency
      means that TETRA is less vulnerable to interference, which is a vital aspect of
      communications for the emergency services. The system makes it possible to offer complete
      coverage for the emergency services. One of the TETRA features is that the signal is
      transmitted in bursts that repeat. The result is a power modulation of some of the RF signal
      at a frequency of 17,6 Hz (times pr. second) [NRPB, 2001]. This pulsing has led to concerns
      about its effect on health. Since this pulsing only occurs for transmission from TETRA
      handset and not from the base stations, most concerns is related to the health effect on the
      users of TETRA handset.

      The aim is to asses whether exposure to TETRA handset can affect cognitive functions and high
      level brain functions such as learning and problem solving the volunteers will be tested by
      comparing performance with and without exposure. Sham exposure (no radiation from the
      handset) vs. TETRA signal (at the lowest carrier frequency, standard TDMA pulsing at 17,6 Hz
      and a selection of lengths of exposures at the realistic SAR value).

      56 healthy males aged 25-50 year working within public safety and emergency services (police,
      fire and paramedics), is planned to be used in this study. Subjects must be identified as
      potential users of the TETRA system.

      A climatic chamber at the Department of Environmental and Occupational Medicine, Aarhus
      University, is modified with absorbing lining to dampen reflections from the walls. The
      climatic chamber is modified to make it a screened room to prevent external RF fields, and to
      some extent low frequency fields, to enter the chamber. Except for cables to the keyboard and
      screen there are no other electromagnetic radiators in the chamber. The study will be double
      blinded as any noise (acoustic and electric) related to exposure will be the same and the
      person responsible for exposure and exposure assessment will not be able to see each other.
      The only investigator knowledgeable about the exposure will have no contact with subjects and
      staff doing measurement. This double blinding will continue until the basic statistical
      analyses have been conducted.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2007</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary analysis is the comparison</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>of the placebo exposure (no radiation) and the TETRA signal</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome for this analysis is the Trail Making B (time in seconds).</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reaction Time (RTI), complex reaction and movement time</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Digit Span forward and backward</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>'Headache' and 'concentration difficulties' (VAS-scale)</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Cognitive Performance</condition>
  <condition>Well-Being</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TETRA (at lowest carrier freq, std TDMA pulse at 17,6 Hz).</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy subjects

          -  Age 25-50

          -  Males

          -  Right-handers

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with current or previous cardiovascular disease

          -  Subjects with current or previous fractured scull

          -  Subjects with diseases, which could involve a risk for the subject or possible
             influence the outcome measurements
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Søren K. Kjærgaard, Ass.Prof.PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Public Health, University of Aarhus, Vennelyst Boulevard 6, Build. 1260</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dept. of Environmental and Occupational Medicine, Institute of Public Health, University of Aarhus, Vennelyst Boulevard 6, Build. 1260</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus C</city>
        <zip>8000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 3, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 6, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 6, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 10, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>TETRA</keyword>
  <keyword>EMF</keyword>
  <keyword>Human exposure study</keyword>
  <keyword>Symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Well-being</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive function</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tetracycline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

