<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00395226</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-05-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00395226</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zinc Sulfate in the Treatment of Rosacea: A Randomized, Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>&quot;Zinc Sulfate in the Treatment of Rosacea: A Randomized, Controlled Trial.&quot; Prospective, Double Blind, Randomized, Controlled Trial Comparing the Effects of Supplemental Zinc Sulfate and Placebo on the Severity of Rosacea.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Essentia Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Essentia Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rosacea is a common chronic dermatological condition, characterized by recurrent or
      persistent redness, permanent dilation of small blood vessel causing small red lesions, and
      papules/pustules. The signs of rosacea are usually confined to the face, but may appear on
      the neck, scalp or trunk. Opthalmologic findings are also common. Rosacea is usually
      described as being most common in fair skinned women over 40. The purpose of the study is to
      determine whether oral Zinc Sulfate treatment is an effective treatment for facial rosacea.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rosacea is a common chronic dermatological condition. The epidemiology of rosacea has not
      been determined extensively, due to part in problems with case definition. Rosacea is usually
      described as being most common in fair skinned women over the age of 40. However it occurs in
      most adult populations, including both men and women of all ages, and in people of many
      complexion types, including African Americans and Asians.

      Although rosacea is encountered frequently in primary care and dermatology practices, its
      precise incidence and prevalence are not known. The etiology and pathogenesis of rosacea are
      unknown. Both genetic and environmental factors are thought to be important. A wide range of
      medical and surgical interventions have been used in the management of rosacea, including
      dietary management, topical and systemic antibiotics, azelaic acid, low dose isotretinoin,
      and laser treatments for telangiectasia and rhinophyma. No single regimen has been found to
      be entirely satisfactory.

      Zinc has been found to be effective in managing several dermatological conditions, especially
      acne. It has also been found to be of benefit in dermatological conditions such as viral
      warts and cutaneous leishmaniasis.

      No studies have been published on the use of Zinc in the treatment of rosacea. This will be a
      prospective, double blind, randomized, controlled trial, comparing the effects of
      supplemental and placebo on the severity of rosacea. Enrolled subjects will be assigned to
      one of two study arms.

      Subjects and investigators will be blinded regarding treatment. After evaluation, meeting the
      study criteria,obtaining informed consent, and initiating study related procedures, the
      subject will take oral study drug or placebo, bid, for 90 days.

      Subjects are followed via phone call at one week and 6 weeks after enrollment into the study.
      At the conclusion of the 90 day study, subjects will be re-examined.

      The primary endpoint of this study will be the severity of rosacea at the end of the 90 day
      intervention period.

      The efficacy of Zinc vs. placebo will be assessed by a comparison of the change in the
      severity of rosacea.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Difficulty recruiting subjects
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Facial Rosacea After 90 Days of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Modified Rosacea Severity Scoring System evaluating four signs of rosacea, flushing (transient erythema or redness), erythema (redness), papules and pustules and telangiectasia (spider-veins) ranges from 0 (best, absent) to 12 (worst, severe on all items)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Rosacea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Zinc sulfate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>220 mg of zinc sulfate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lactose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>270 mg lactose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>zinc sulfate</intervention_name>
    <description>zinc sulfate 220 mg bis for 90 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zinc sulfate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>placebo bid for 90 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lactose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of facial rosacea made or confirmed by one of the investigators.

          -  Severity of signs of rosacea &quot;greater than mild&quot; at the time of enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Treatment for rosacea during the 3 months prior to enrollment.

          -  Use of zinc dietary supplement &gt; 25 mg per day during the 3 months prior to enrollment
             ( Most patients taking multivitamins with Zinc, often 15 mg per day, will not be
             excluded, whereas most patients taking additional Zinc supplements, often 25-50 mg per
             day or more will be excluded.)

          -  Diagnosis of rosacea fulminancy.

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joel Bamford, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Essentia Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Mary's Duluth Clinic Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duluth</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55805</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berg M, Lidén S. An epidemiological study of rosacea. Acta Derm Venereol. 1989;69(5):419-23.</citation>
    <PMID>2572109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bamford JT. Rosacea: current thoughts on origin. Semin Cutan Med Surg. 2001 Sep;20(3):199-206. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11594675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Millikan L. The proposed inflammatory pathophysiology of rosacea: implications for treatment. Skinmed. 2003 Jan-Feb;2(1):43-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14673323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilkin JK. Rosacea. Pathophysiology and treatment. Arch Dermatol. 1994 Mar;130(3):359-62. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8129416</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thiboutot DM. Acne and rosacea. New and emerging therapies. Dermatol Clin. 2000 Jan;18(1):63-71, viii. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10626112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bikowski JB.Del Rosso JQ, Goldberg DJ, Margolis DJ, Van Zuuren EJ, Wolf JE. Future Trends in the Treatment of Rosacea. Cutis. 2005;75(Suppl 3):33-36</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tuleya S. Research Highlights: Acne and Rosacea Treatments. Skin and Agining.2003;11(8):70-72.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fraker PJ, King LE. Reprogramming of the immune system during zinc deficiency. Annu Rev Nutr. 2004;24:277-98. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15189122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fraker PJ, King LE, Laakko T, Vollmer TL. The dynamic link between the integrity of the immune system and zinc status. J Nutr. 2000 May;130(5S Suppl):1399S-406S. doi: 10.1093/jn/130.5.1399S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10801951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walker CF, Black RE. Zinc and the Risk for Infectious Disease. ann Intern Med. 1996;125(2):81-88.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mossad SB, Macknin ML, Medendorp SV, Mason P. Zinc gluconate lozenges for treating the common cold. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Ann Intern Med. 1996 Jul 15;125(2):81-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8678384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>___.What's New about Zinc. UC Berkeley Wellness Letter. 2004:130:1344S-1349S.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hambridge M. Human Zinc Deficiency. J Nutrition. 2000;130:1344S-1349S.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoffman HN 2nd, Phyliky RL, Fleming CR. Zinc-induced copper deficiency. Gastroenterology. 1988 Feb;94(2):508-12.</citation>
    <PMID>3335323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Salzman MB, Smith EM, Koo C. Excessive oral zinc supplementation. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2002 Oct;24(7):582-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12368702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irving JA, Mattman A, Lockitch G, Farrell K, Wadsworth LD. Element of caution: a case of reversible cytopenias associated with excessive zinc supplementation. CMAJ. 2003 Jul 22;169(2):129-31.</citation>
    <PMID>12874162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chandra RK. Excessive intake of zinc impairs immune responses. JAMA. 1984 Sep 21;252(11):1443-6.</citation>
    <PMID>6471270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barceloux DG. Zinc. J Toxicol Clin Toxicol. 1999;37(2):279-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10382562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schosinsky KH, Lehmann HP, Beeler MF. Measurement of ceruloplasmin from its oxidase activity in serum by use of o-dianisidine dihydrochloride. Clin Chem. 1974 Dec;20(12):1556-63.</citation>
    <PMID>4214636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>West EC, Prohaska JR. Cu,Zn-superoxide dismutase is lower and copper chaperone CCS is higher in erythrocytes of copper-deficient rats and mice. Exp Biol Med (Maywood). 2004 Sep;229(8):756-64.</citation>
    <PMID>15337829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dreno B, Amblard P, Agache P, Sirot S, Litoux P. Low doses of zinc gluconate for inflammatory acne. Acta Derm Venereol. 1989;69(6):541-3.</citation>
    <PMID>2575335</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dreno B, Moyse D, Alirezai M, Amblard P, Auffret N, Beylot C, Bodokh I, Chivot M, Daniel F, Humbert P, Meynadier J, Poli F; Acne Research and Study Group. Multicenter randomized comparative double-blind controlled clinical trial of the safety and efficacy of zinc gluconate versus minocycline hydrochloride in the treatment of inflammatory acne vulgaris. Dermatology. 2001;203(2):135-40.</citation>
    <PMID>11586012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chu A, Huber FJ, Plott RT. The comparative efficacy of benzoyl peroxide 5%/erythromycin 3% gel and erythromycin 4%/zinc 1.2% solution in the treatment of acne vulgaris. Br J Dermatol. 1997 Feb;136(2):235-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9068739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meynadier J. Efficacy and safety study of two zinc gluconate regimens in the treatment of inflammatory acne. Eur J Dermatol. 2000 Jun;10(4):269-73.</citation>
    <PMID>10846252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schachner L, Eaglstein W, Kittles C, Mertz P. Topical erythromycin and zinc therapy for acne. J Am Acad Dermatol. 1990 Feb;22(2 Pt 1):253-60.</citation>
    <PMID>2138176</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Verma KC, Saini AS, Dhamija SK. Oral zinc sulphate therapy in acne vulgaris: a double-blind trial. Acta Derm Venereol. 1980;60(4):337-40.</citation>
    <PMID>6163281</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Gurairi FT, Al-Waiz M, Sharquie KE. Oral zinc sulphate in the treatment of recalcitrant viral warts: randomized placebo-controlled clinical trial. Br J Dermatol. 2002 Mar;146(3):423-31.</citation>
    <PMID>11952542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharquie KE, Najim RA, Farjou IB, Al-Timimi DJ. Oral zinc sulphate in the treatment of acute cutaneous leishmaniasis. Clin Exp Dermatol. 2001 Jan;26(1):21-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11260171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berne B, Venge P, Ohman S. Perifolliculitis capitis abscedens et suffodiens (Hoffman). Complete healing associated with oral zinc therapy. Arch Dermatol. 1985 Aug;121(8):1028-30.</citation>
    <PMID>4026339</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rostan EF, DeBuys HV, Madey DL, Pinnell SR. Evidence supporting zinc as an important antioxidant for skin. Int J Dermatol. 2002 Sep;41(9):606-11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12358835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dreno B, Trossaert M, Boiteau HL, Litoux P. Zinc salts effects on granulocyte zinc concentration and chemotaxis in acne patients. Acta Derm Venereol. 1992 Aug;72(4):250-2.</citation>
    <PMID>1357876</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilkin J, Dahl M, Detmar M, Drake L, Liang MH, Odom R, Powell F; National Rosacea Society Expert Committee. Standard grading system for rosacea: report of the National Rosacea Society Expert Committee on the classification and staging of rosacea. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2004 Jun;50(6):907-12.</citation>
    <PMID>15153893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 31, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 1, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 2, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>June 3, 2011</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>June 3, 2011</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">June 30, 2011</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 3, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 3, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 30, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Joel Bamford, MD</name_title>
    <organization>St. Mary's duluth Clinic Health System</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rosacea</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rosacea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Zinc</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Zinc Sulfate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>65 participants were recruited between August 2006 and April 2008</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>65 participants were assessed for eligibility. 12 did not meet inclusion criteria (severity of facial rosacea “greater than mild” at the time of enrollment, at least 5 of 12 on the Modified Rosacea Severity Scoring System).</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Placebo (Lactose)</title>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Zinc Sulfate</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="26"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="27"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="22"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="22"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="4"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="5"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Adverse Event</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="4"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lost to Follow-up</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Placebo (Lactose)</title>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Zinc Sulfate</title>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="26"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="27"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="53"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="47.3" spread="13.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="52.8" spread="10.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="50.1" spread="12.2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="39"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race/Ethnicity, Customized</title>
          <units>participant</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Caucasian</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="26"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="50"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Non-Caucasian</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="26"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="27"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="53"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Length of Rosacea</title>
          <units>participant</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt; 1 year</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>1-2 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>2-5 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="16"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>5-10 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt; 10 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Rosacea Severity Score</title>
          <description>Modified Rosacea Severity Scoring System evaluating four signs of rosacea, flushing (transient erythema or redness), erythema (redness), papules and pustules and telangiectasia (spider-veins) ranges from 0 (best, absent) to 12 (worst, severe on all items)</description>
          <units>units on scale 0 to 12</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6.8" spread="1.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6.3" spread="1.2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="6.5" spread="1.3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Severity of Facial Rosacea After 90 Days of Treatment</title>
        <description>Modified Rosacea Severity Scoring System evaluating four signs of rosacea, flushing (transient erythema or redness), erythema (redness), papules and pustules and telangiectasia (spider-veins) ranges from 0 (best, absent) to 12 (worst, severe on all items)</description>
        <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Placebo (Lactose)</title>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Zinc Sulfate</title>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Severity of Facial Rosacea After 90 Days of Treatment</title>
          <description>Modified Rosacea Severity Scoring System evaluating four signs of rosacea, flushing (transient erythema or redness), erythema (redness), papules and pustules and telangiectasia (spider-veins) ranges from 0 (best, absent) to 12 (worst, severe on all items)</description>
          <units>units on scale 0 to 12</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="22"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="22"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="4.9" lower_limit="4.1" upper_limit="5.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5.1" lower_limit="4.2" upper_limit="6.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>The null hypothesis was “no group differences.” The alternative hypothesis was that the zinc sulfate arm is superior to placebo arm.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.2840</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>The a priori significance threshold level was 0.05 (two-sided)</p_value_desc>
            <method>ANCOVA</method>
            <method_desc>The ANCOVA used group as a factor and baseline rosacea severity score as a covariate.</method_desc>
            <param_type>Mean Difference (Final Values)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.57</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>-0.47</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>1.62</ci_upper_limit>
            <estimate_desc>The effect of zinc sulfate treatment on rosacea severity score was estimated with baseline rosacea severity score included in the regression model</estimate_desc>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Placebo (Lactose)</title>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Zinc Sulfate</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="27"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Allergic reaction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="27"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="15" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="15" subjects_at_risk="27"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>gastrointestinal disorders</sub_title>
                <description>stomach upset, including nausea, discomfort, gas, diarrhea, constipation, and increased bowel movements</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="12" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="15" subjects_at_risk="27"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>rosacea outbreak</sub_title>
                <description>including redness and itching</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="25"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="27"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Brian Johnson</name_or_title>
      <organization>Essentia Institute of Rural Health</organization>
      <phone>218-786-8856</phone>
      <email>bjohnson3@eirh.org</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

