<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00989963</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BPS-MR-PAH-203</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00989963</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose-response Study of the Safety and Efficacy of Beraprost Sodium Modified Release (BPS-MR) in Patients With Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension (PAH)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A 12-week, Double-blind, International, Multicenter, Dose-response Study of the Safety and Efficacy of Beraprost Sodium Modified Release (BPS-MR) in Patients With Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension (PAH)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lung Biotechnology PBC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lung Biotechnology PBC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 12-week, international, multicenter, double-blind, three-group, dose-response study
      to assess the safety and efficacy of BPS-MR in patients with PAH. Eligible patients will have
      been previously diagnosed with PAH and will be on a stable course of an ERA and/or PDE-5
      inhibitor for at least 60 days prior to Baseline.

      Patients will be randomized to 1 of 3 treatment groups in a 1:1:1 ratio and will be
      stratified by PAH background therapy (Endothelium Receptor Antagonist (ERA),
      Phosphodiesterase-5 (PDE-5), and both). The treatment groups consist of one Maximum Tolerated
      Dose (MTD) and two Fixed Dose (FD) groups. Following randomization, patients will begin
      taking active drug (60µg) orally twice daily. Patients will visit their investigational site
      at Week 6 and Week 12 for study evaluations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a 12-week, international, multicenter, double-blind, three-group, dose-response study
      to assess the safety and efficacy of BPS-MR in patients with PAH. Eligible patients will have
      been previously diagnosed with PAH and will be on a stable course of an ERA and/or PDE-5
      inhibitor for at least 60 days prior to Baseline.

      A total of approximately 36 patients will be randomized to 1 of 3 treatment groups (12 per
      group) in a 1:1:1 ratio and will be stratified by PAH background therapy (ERA, PDE-5, and
      both). The treatment groups consist of one MTD and two FD groups. Following randomization,
      patients will begin taking active drug (60µg) orally twice daily. Patients will visit their
      investigational site at Week 6 and Week 12 for study evaluations. Between visits, clinical
      site personnel will contact patients by phone each week to assess tolerability, provide
      instructions for a change in dosage, record changes in concomitant medications, and record
      adverse events. Patients who complete the study will be offered the opportunity to continue
      taking study medication in a separate open-label continuation protocol. Patients who withdraw
      early from the study or who otherwise do not elect to enroll into the open-label continuation
      protocol will be down-titrated off of BPS-MR at the discretion of the Investigator, at a
      maximum decrement not to exceed one tablet (60µg) b.i.d. per day and a minimum decrement of
      one tablet (60µg) b.i.d. per week.

      Patients in the iMTD treatment group will dose escalate weekly by 60µg b.i.d. until they
      reach the maximum dose of 600µg b.i.d. or they reach an intolerable dose which requires them
      to down-titrate by 60µg b.i.d. In these instances and at the Investigator's discretion,
      further attempts at dose escalation may be made.

      The FD treatment groups will consist of a low dose group receiving 60µg b.i.d. and a high
      dose group receiving 240µg b.i.d. Patients in the high dose group will dose escalate weekly
      by 60µg b.i.d. until they reach the fixed dose of 240µg b.i.d. Once patients in these
      treatment groups have reached their assigned maximum dose of active drug, weekly increases in
      the number of placebo tablets administered will continue in order to maintain the blind.

      Patients will be requested to maintain a daily diary of symptoms and study drug
      administration for evaluation by clinical site personnel. Also, patients will be given the
      option to contribute blood for pharmacokinetic assessment of BPS/BPS-314d plasma
      concentrations at the Week 12 visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Right Heart Catheterization</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after randomization</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise Capacity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 &amp; 12 weeks after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>World Health Organization(WHO)Functional Class.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 &amp;12 weeks after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Laboratory Parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>6 &amp;12 Weeks after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Electrocardiogram (ECG) Findings</measure>
    <time_frame>6 &amp; 12 weeks after randomization</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the MTD treatment group will dose escalate weekly by 60µg b.i.d. until they reach the maximum dose of 600µg b.i.d. or they reach an intolerable dose which requires them to down-titrate by 60µg b.i.d. In these instances and at the Investigator's discretion, further attempts at dose escalation may be made.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Fixed Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The low dose group will receive 60µg twice a day(b.i.d.)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Fixed Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the high dose group will dose escalate weekly by 60µg twice a day (b.i.d.) until they reach the fixed dose of 240µg b.i.d. Once patients in these treatment groups have reached their assigned maximum dose of active drug,</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Beraprost Sodium Modified Release</intervention_name>
    <description>60µg Tablets, twice a day for 12 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low Fixed Dose</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>High Fixed Dose</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. IRB approved written informed consent has been obtained.

          2. Male or female, age 18 to 75 years (inclusive).

          3. Established diagnosis of pulmonary arterial hypertension that is either idiopathic or
             familial PAH, collagen vascular disease associated PAH, PAH induced by anorexigens, or
             PAH associated with repaired congenital systemic-to-pulmonary shunts (repaired ≥5
             years).

          4. Clinically stable PAH as determined by the Investigator.

          5. Able to walk unassisted.

          6. Has a complete, unencouraged 6MWT distance of 150 to 450 meters (inclusive) at
             Screening.

          7. Previous (at any time) right heart cardiac catheterization with findings consistent
             with PAH, specifically mean Pulmonary Arterial Pressure (PAPm) ≥25 mmHg (at rest),
             Pulmonary Capillary Wedge Pressure (PCWP) (or left ventricular end diastolic pressure)
             ≤15 mmHg, and Pulmonary Vascular Resistance (PVR) &gt;3 mmHg/L/min.

          8. Previous (at any time) chest radiograph consistent with the diagnosis of PAH.

          9. Has been on a stable course of an ERA or/and PDE-5 inhibitor for a minimum of 60 days
             prior to Baseline.

         10. Women of child-bearing potential (defined as less than 1 year post-menopausal or not
             surgically sterile) must be using an acceptable method of birth control or practicing
             abstinence. If sexually active, female patients must use a double barrier method of
             birth control, such as a condom and spermicidal. Patient must have a negative
             pregnancy test at the Screening and Baseline visits.

         11. Willing and able to comply with study requirements and restrictions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has pulmonary venous hypertension, pulmonary veno-occlusive disease, pulmonary
             capillary hemangiomatosis, or chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension.

          2. Has a history of interstitial lung disease, unless:

               -  Pulmonary Function Testing conducted within 6 months of the Baseline visit
                  demonstrates a Total Lung Capacity ≥ 70 % of predicted.

          3. Has a history of obstructive lung disease, unless:

               -  Pulmonary Function Testing conducted within 6 months of the Baseline visit
                  demonstrates a forced expiratory volume in 1 second/forced vital capacity
                  (FEV1/FVC) ratio of ≥ 50%.

          4. Is pregnant and/or lactating.

          5. Changed or discontinued any PAH medication within 60 days prior to the Baseline visit
             including, but not limited to, an ERA, PDE-5 inhibitor, or calcium channel blocker
             (with the exception of anticoagulants).

          6. Has an ongoing hemorrhagic condition (e.g. upper digestive tract hemorrhage,
             hemoptysis, etc), or has a pre-existing condition that, in the Investigator's judgment
             may increase the risk for developing hemorrhage during the study (e.g. hemophilia).
             Transient hemorrhage (e.g. epistaxis, normal menstrual bleeding, gingival bleeding,
             hemorrhoidal hemorrhage, etc.) will not preclude enrollment.

          7. Has donated blood or plasma, or has lost a volume of blood &gt;450mL within 6-weeks of
             the Baseline visit.

          8. Has received any investigational medication, device or therapy within 30 days prior to
             the Baseline visit or is scheduled to receive another investigational drug, device or
             therapy during the course of the study.

          9. Has received any prostanoid therapy at any time.

         10. Has any preexisting disease known to cause pulmonary hypertension other than collagen
             vascular disease.

         11. Has any musculoskeletal disease or any other disease that would limit ambulation.

         12. Has any form of unrepaired or recently repaired (&lt; 5 years) congenital
             systemic-to-pulmonary shunt other than patent foramen ovale.

         13. History of pulmonary embolism or deep venous thrombosis.

         14. History of ischemic heart disease, including previous myocardial infarction, or
             symptomatic coronary artery disease, or history of left sided myocardial disease as
             evidenced by a mean PCWP (or a left ventricular end diastolic pressure) &gt; 15 mmHg or
             left ventricular ejection fraction &lt; 40% as assessed by either multigated angiogram,
             angiography or echocardiography, or left ventricular shortening fraction &lt; 22% as
             assessed by echocardiography. Note that patients in whom abnormal left ventricular
             function is attributed entirely to impaired left ventricular filling due to the
             effects of right ventricular overload (i.e. right ventricular hypertrophy and/or
             dilatation) will not be excluded.

         15. Presence of atrial fibrillation (determined from 12-lead ECG at Screening).

         16. Any other clinically significant illness that, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             might put the patient at risk of harm during the study or might adversely affect the
             interpretation of the study data.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harbor-UCLA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torrance</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90502</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Edward Heart Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Naperville</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60566</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albert Einstein College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10461</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Allegheny General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universite Libre de Bruxelles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxellas</city>
        <zip>1070</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Catholic University of Leuven</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General Teaching Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha</city>
        <zip>2, 128 08</zip>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum der Universitat zu Koln</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cologne</city>
        <zip>50937</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medizinische Klinik und Poliklinik</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dresden</city>
        <zip>01307</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Abt. Innere Medizin III, Medizinische Universitatsklinik</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <zip>69120</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitatsklinik Leipzig Abteilung Pulmologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leipzig</city>
        <zip>04103</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mater Misericordiae University Hospital Ltd.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dublin</city>
        <zip>7</zip>
        <country>Ireland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institutul de Urgenta pentru Boli</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucuresti</city>
        <zip>022322</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institutul National de Pneumologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bucuresti</city>
        <zip>050159</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institutul de Boli Cardiovasculare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lasi</city>
        <zip>700503</zip>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Ireland</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>April 16, 2013</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>April 16, 2013</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Estimate">April 24, 2013</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 24, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PAH</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Familial Primary Pulmonary Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Beraprost</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epoprostenol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

