<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00984243</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>281-92</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PulmMed 649</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00984243</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Photodynamic Therapy (PDT) in Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>PDT</acronym>
  <official_title>An Evaluation of the Effectiveness of Photodynamic Therapy (PDT) Compared to Surgical Resection in Early Stage Roentgenographically Occult Lung Cancer.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being done to determine whether a substance called hematoporphyrin can be used
      to treat tumors in various locations in the body when used in association with a laser.
      Hematoporphyrin is a substance that is taken up by cancerous cells. When these cells are
      exposed to the energy emitted by a laser source, chemical reactions occur in the cell and
      cause the cells to die. It is hoped that this treatment method may be able to selectively
      destroy malignant cells without damaging surrounding healthy tissue.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lung cancer is currently the leading cause of death in both women and men in the United
      States and continues to be a major problem in several other countries in the world.
      Detection, localization, and surgical treatment at an early stage, provides the best
      opportunity for long-term survival for patients with non-sma11 cell lung cancer at this time.
      Studies examining the utility of screening patients at high risk for lung cancer with sputum
      cytology and chest roentgenograms showed that, despite a higher frequency of detecting and
      resecting early cancers in the screened group, there was no difference between the screened
      group and the control group in overall cancer mortality.

      The purpose of this study is to determine if photodynamic therapy (PDT) is an alternative to
      surgical resection in patients with early stage) roentgenographically occult squamous cell
      carcinoma of the lung who are candidates for surgery. If PDT is successful, it would remove
      the indication for surgery and eliminate the need for an operation. The specific goals are to
      evaluate the impact of PDT on these patients by determining the percentage of patients who
      are spared surgery as wel1 as the following: morbidity, overall mortality, lung cancer
      mortality, the rate of subsequent lung cancer, the relative cost of PDT and surgery, the
      change in pulmonary function over time, the effect on quality of life, and the patient
      preferences for PDT and surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 1994</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2006</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the impact of PDT on these patients by determining the percentage of patients who are spared surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Morbidity,overall mortality and lung cancer mortality.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of subsequent lung cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relative cost of PDT and surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pulmonary function over time.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect on quality of life.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient preferences for PDT and surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Photodynamic Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PHOTODYNAMIC THERAPY (PDT)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PHOTODYNAMIC THERAPY (PDT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Photodynamic Procedure:
Photofrin II will be injected at a dosage of 2 mm/Kg intravenously. Laser treatment will take place 40-50 hours later. An argon-dye or an excimer-dye laser tuned to 620-630 nm will be used.
It is anticipated that a microlens fiber will be used in almost all cases, but a cylinder-diffusing fiber can be used to treat lesions in segmental bronchi if needed.
Argon-dye laser: Power settings 200 milliwatt (mW) microlens and 400 mW for cylinder Excimer laser: 4 milliJoules (mJoules)/pulse at 30 hertz for the microlens
Energy density:
Argon-dye laser: 200-300 Joules/cm^2 Excimer-dye laser: 100-200 Joules/cm^2</description>
    <arm_group_label>Photodynamic Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient less than 75 years of age.

          -  Squamous cell lung cancer proven by biopsy or repeated Brushings obtained from the
             same location at separate bronchoscopies.

          -  Occult lung cancer by chest roentgenogram and CT scan If CT scan is abnormal,
             mediastinoscopy is negative.

          -  Cancer is bronchoscopically superficial as defined in section IV, E.

          -  Estimated size less than 1 cm diameter on the surface of the bronchus with the surface
             area of 0.7 to 1.0 cm2.

          -  Location in the trachea, main stem bronChi, lobar bronchi, segmental bronchi, or
             subsegmental bronchi.

          -  Medical condition permits surgery: cardiovascular status is satisfactory for operation
             and postoperative FEVl is predicted to be greater than 0.75 liter.

          -  Patients will complete quality of life questionnaire and a spirometry which will
             include forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEVl) and forced vital capacity (FVC).

          -  On bronchoscopic biopsy, the carcinoma is entirely in situ or shows no more than 2 mm
             of microinvasion.

          -  The characteristics of the mucosa. may include paleness, opacity, loss of luster,
             roughness, micro-granularity.

          -  The mucosal folds may demonstrate lack of clarity. thickening, disappearance.

          -  There may be small nodular protrusion of tumor into the lumen

          -  The peripheral extent of tumor invasion can be confirmed endoscopically.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A medical disease which excludes surgery as an option

          -  A postoperative FEVl predicted to be less than 0.75 liter

          -  A previous carcinoma or other malignancy not curatively treated

          -  The presence of simultaneous lung cancers

          -  CT scan of the chest shows thickening of the bronchial wall or extension beyond the
             bronchial wall in the area of the cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric S. Edell, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.mayo.edu</url>
    <description>Mayo Clinic Clinical Trials</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 24, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 23, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 25, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 13, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 13, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 15, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Eric S. Edell, M.D.</name_title>
    <organization>Mayo Clinic</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>lung cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

