<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02809443</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Zika-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02809443</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of GLS-5700 in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I, Open-label, Dose-Ranging Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, and Immunogenicity of GLS-5700 Administered ID Followed by EP in Dengue Virus-Naïve Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GeneOne Life Science, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Inovio Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GeneOne Life Science, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The clinical trial will assess the safety, tolerability, and immunogenicity of GLS-5700.
      GLS-5700 is a synthetic DNA plasmid vaccine against the Zika virus. ZIKA-001 is the first in
      man clinical trial of this vaccine which encodes for the premembrane-membrane and envelope
      regions of Zika virus.

      Zika virus, first discovered in the Zika forest in 1947, has caused a large epidemic in South
      America, Central America, and the Caribbean islands commencing in late 2014 or early 2015.
      Zika virus can cause significant neurologic disease to include Guillain Barre Syndrome in
      adults and microcephaly and other birth defects among children born to mothers who are
      infected during pregnancy. At present no vaccines or treatments have been approved for Zika
      virus infection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      GLS-5700 contains a single plasmid containing DNA encoding for pre-membrane and envelope
      (prME) proteins of the Zika virus.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in safety laboratory measures</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Week 60</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of solicited adverse events after vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Week 60</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of unsolicited adverse events after vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Week 60</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Week 60</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Binding antibody titers to Zika envelope</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Week 60 following first dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neutralizing antibody response against Zika virus</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Week 60 following first dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T cell response</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through Week 60 following first dose</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GLS-5700 at 1 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>DNA/dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GLS-5700 at 2 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>DNA/dose</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GLS-5700</intervention_name>
    <description>GLS-5700 contains a single plasmid containing DNA encoding for pre-membrane and envelope (prME) proteins of the Zika virus</description>
    <arm_group_label>GLS-5700 at 1 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>GLS-5700 at 2 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18-65 years;

          2. Able to provide consent to participate and having signed an Informed Consent Form
             (ICF);

          3. Able and willing to comply with all study procedures;

          4. Women of child-bearing potential agree to use medically effective contraception (oral
             contraception, barrier methods, spermicide, etc.) or have a partner who is sterile
             from enrollment to 3 months following the last injection, or have a partner who is
             medically unable to induce pregnancy.

          5. Sexually active men who are considered sexually fertile must agree to use either a
             barrier method of contraception during the study, and agree to continue the use for at
             least 3 months following the last injection, or have a partner who is permanently
             sterile or is medically unable to become pregnant;

          6. Normal screening ECG or screening ECG with no clinically significant findings;

          7. Screening laboratory must be within normal limits or have only Grade 0-1 findings;

          8. No history of clinically significant immunosuppressive or autoimmune disease.

          9. No history of dengue virus vaccination or illness; no history of yellow fever
             vaccination.

         10. Dengue seronegative at baseline by screening laboratory evaluation

         11. Not currently or within the previous 4 weeks taking immunosuppressive agents
             (excluding inhaled, topical skin and/or eye drop-containing corticosteroids, low-dose
             methotrexate, or corticosteroids at a dose less than 20 mg/day).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Administration of an investigational compound either currently or within 30 days of
             first dose;

          2. Previous receipt of an investigational product for the treatment or prevention of Zika
             virus except if participant is verified to have received placebo;

          3. Administration of any vaccine within 4 weeks of first dose;

          4. Administration of any monoclonal or polyclonal antibody product within 4 weeks of the
             first dose

          5. Administration of any blood product within 3 months of first dose;

          6. Pregnancy or breast feeding or plans to become pregnant during the course of the
             study;

          7. Positive serologic result for dengue virus (any serotype) or history of receipt of
             either dengue virus or yellow fever virus vaccination at any time in the past;

          8. Positive serologic test for HIV, hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg); or any
             potentially communicable infectious disease as determined by the Principal
             Investigator or Medical Monitor;

          9. Positive serologic test for hepatitis C (exception: successful treatment with
             confirmation of sustained virologic response);

         10. Baseline evidence of kidney disease as measured by creatinine greater than 1.5 (CKD
             Stage II or greater);

         11. Baseline screening lab(s) with Grade 2 or higher abnormality, except for Grade 2
             creatinine;

         12. Chronic liver disease or cirrhosis;

         13. Immunosuppressive illness including hematologic malignancy, history of solid organ or
             bone marrow transplantation;

         14. Current or anticipated concomitant immunosuppressive therapy (excluding inhaled,
             topical skin and/or eye drop-containing corticosteroids, low-dose methotrexate, or
             corticosteroids at a dose less than 20 mg/day);

         15. Current or anticipated treatment with TNF-α inhibitors such as infliximab, adalimumab,
             etanercept;

         16. Prior major surgery or any radiation therapy within 4 weeks of group assignment;

         17. Any pre-excitation syndromes, e.g., Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome;

         18. Presence of a cardiac pacemaker or automatic implantable cardioverter defibrillator
             (AICD)

         19. Metal implants within 20 cm of the planned site(s) of injection;

         20. Presence of keloid scar formation or hypertrophic scar as a clinically significant
             medical condition at the planned site(s) of injection.

         21. Prisoner or participants who are compulsorily detained (involuntary incarceration) for
             treatment of either a physical or psychiatric illness;

         22. Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the investigator,
             would interfere with adherence to study requirements or assessment of immunologic
             endpoints; or

         23. Not willing to allow storage and future use of samples for Zika virus related research

         24. Any illness or condition that in the opinion of the investigator may affect the safety
             of the participant or the evaluation of any study endpoint.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joel Maslow, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>GeneOne Life Science</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Miami Research Associate</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennslyvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Québec -Université Laval hopital CHUL Centre de Recherche en infectiologie</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quebec</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 20, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Zika</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>DNA</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

