<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02809963</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-002519-14</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02809963</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mineralocorticoid Receptor Antagonists in Type 2 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Study of the Effect of Mineralocorticoid Receptor Antagonists in Type 2 Diabetes Patients on Myocardial Function, Glucose and Fat Metabolism (The MIRAD-study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Herlev Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Herlev Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to investigate the effect of selective blocking of the
      mineralocorticoid receptor in patients with type 2 diabetes on insulin resistance, lipid
      metabolism and myocardial function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study we want to investigate the effect
      of mineralocorticoid receptor antagonists in type 2 diabetes patients on myocardial function,
      glucose and fat metabolism.

      Background The mortality rate in T2 DM is still increased by almost a factor 2 although poly
      pharmacological therapy of risk factors has been recommended for years. Treatment with MR
      antagonists in patients with primary hyperaldosteronism and systolic heart failure improves
      insulin resistance, myocardial function and prognosis. Further, recent evidence has suggested
      that aldosterone participates in the regulation of glucose and lipid metabolism, as MR
      expression has been identified in adipocytes and beneficial metabolic effects of selective MR
      blockade has been demonstrated in several animal models. Notably, there is no available data
      in humans with T2DM.

      A key feature of T2 DM is altered body composition characterized by increased metabolic
      active visceral adipose tissue (VAT) and increased fat content of the liver, which has been
      associated with cardiac dysfunction and outcome. Gold standard for measurement of VAT is
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), and proton MRI spectroscopy can quantitatively measure fat
      content in the liver with high precision. The pathogenesis of myocardial dysfunction in T2DM
      is linked with insulin resistance (IR) of adipose tissue mediating increased supply of free
      fatty acids and intra myocardial lipid accumulation. Thus, beneficial effects of lipid
      metabolism could in theory indirectly improve myocardial function in type 2 diabetics.

      Global longitudinal strain (GLS) is a validated method for evaluating regional and global
      function of the left ventricle, which is a strong predictor of incident HF in patients with
      myocardial infarction and closely related with plasma NT-proBNP concentrations.

      Hypothesis Selective blocking of the MR receptor in patients with T2 DM improves insulin
      resistance, lipid metabolism and myocardial function.

      Objectives To investigate the effect of Eplerenone 100-200 mg once daily compared to placebo
      in patients with type 2 diabetes with regard to glucose and lipid metabolism, myocardial
      function and structure, and vascular function.

      The primary objective is to investigate the effect of Eplerenone 100-200 mg once daily
      compared to placebo on changes in liver fat content.

      Design A single center, randomized, double blinded placebo controlled trial. Patients with T2
      DM and high risk of cardiovascular disease will be randomized to either Eplerenone 100-200 mg
      or placebo daily for 26 weeks. Patients will be investigated at baseline and after 26 weeks.

      A total of 130 patients with type 2 diabetes will be included.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver fat content</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in liver fat content by proton MR spectroscopy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fat mass distribution</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in body fat distribution (total body fat, visceral fat, subcutaneous fat)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>insulin resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in insulin resistance by HOMA and Matsuda index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary albumin/creatinine ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in Urinary albumin/creatinine ratio</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarkers of adipocyte function</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in biomarkers of adipocyte function (adiponectin, leptin, FGF-21, TNF-alfa, FFA, IL-6, MCP-1, MAC-1)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>24 Hour blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in 24 Hour blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global longitudinal strain (GLS)</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in global longitudinal strain by echocardiography</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>systolic and diastolic function og left ventricule</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in systolic and diastolic function of left ventricule by echocardiography</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Regional and global fibrosis by cardiac magnetic resonance</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in regional and global fibrosis using Late gadolineum enhancement cardiac magnetic resonance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>biomarkers of myocardial stress and fibrosis</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in biomarkers of myocardial stress and fibrosis (NT-proBNP, MR-proANP, galectin-3, GDF-15, MR-proADM)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pulse wave analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in pulse wave analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in quality of life using WHO-5</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>changes in quality of life using W-BQ12</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Eplerenone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eplerenone 50 mg tablets. 2-4 tablets once daily for 26 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>sugar pill manufactured to mimic Eplerenone 50 mg tablet. 2-4 tablets once daily for 26 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eplerenone</intervention_name>
    <description>50 mg tablets, oral use.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Eplerenone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>50 mg tablets, oral use</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Able to understand the written patient information and to give informed consent

          -  Type 2 diabetes mellitus (WHO criteria), diagnosed at least 3 months prior to baseline

          -  Blood pressure treatment according to standard guidelines

          -  Negative pregnancy test (fertile women)

          -  Be willing to change/pause potassium sparing medication

          -  Age 18-85 years

          -  Patients must have high cardiovascular risk factors, defined as one of the following:

        NT-proBNP ≥ 70 pg/ml (taken within the last 6 months prior to baseline) Albuminuria (
        albumin/creatinine ratio ≥ 30 mg/g Confirmed history of myocardial infarction (≥ 3 months
        prior to baseline) Or patient discharged from hospital with a documented diagnosis of
        unstable angina within 24 months prior to baseline Evidence of coronary artery disease by
        CAG in 1 or more major coronary arteries OR at least one of the following: a positive
        noninvasive stress test, OR a positive stress echocardiography showing regional systolic
        wall motion abnormalities, OR a positive scintigraphy test showing stress-induced ischemia
        History of ischemic or hemorrhagic stroke (≥ 3 months prior to informed consent) Presence
        of peripheral artery disease (symptomatic or not ) documented by either: previous limb
        angioplasty, stenting or bypass surgery; or previous limb or foot amputation due to
        circulatory insufficiency; or angiographic evidence of significant (≥ 50%) peripheral
        artery stenosis in at least one limb; or evidence from a non-invasive measurement of
        significant (≥50% or as reported as hemodynamically significant) peripheral artery stenosis
        in at least one limb; or ankle brachial index of ≤ 0.9

        Left ventricle hypertrophy:

        Documented at echocardiography ECG: R-spike in V5/V6 ≥ 25 mm or S-spike in V1 + R-spike in
        V5/V6 ≥ 35 mm Patients both with and without a cardiovascular risk factor can be randomized
        to the fat biopsy sub study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergic to the study medication

          -  Systolic HF (LVEF ≤ 40%)

          -  Impaired kidney function, eGFR ≤ 40 ml/min

          -  Severe liver insufficiency (Child-Pugh class C)

          -  Treatment with MR antagonist within 3 months prior to baseline

          -  Treatment with both ACE inhibitors and Angiotensin II Receptor blockers.

          -  Serum-potassium ≥ 5.0 mmol/l

          -  Serum-sodium ≤ 135 mmol/l

          -  Myocardial infarction, unstable angina pectoris or bypass graft surgery within 3
             months prior to baseline

          -  Persistant atrial fibrillation (except for the fat biopsy sub population)

          -  ECG showing malign ventricular arrhythmia or prolonged QT-interval (&gt; 500ms)

          -  Untreated heart valve disease

          -  ICD-unit/pacemaker

          -  Pregnancy or desire hereof or breastfeeding

          -  Women in the fertile age not using safe contraceptives (spiral, hormonal
             contraceptives)

          -  Cancer unless complete remission ≥ 5 year

          -  Alcohol-/drug-abuse

          -  Inflammatory bowel disease

          -  Other concomitant disease or treatment that according to the investigator's assessment
             makes the patient unsuitable to participate in the study

          -  Simultaneous participation in another clinical study

          -  Treatment with CYP3A4-inhibitors (e.g. itraconazol, etoconazol, ritonavir, nelfinavir,
             clarithromycin, telithromycin and nefazodon)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Herlev Hospital, department of internal medicine, endocrine research unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Herlev</city>
        <zip>2730</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 16, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Herlev Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marie Louise Johansen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Eplerenone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spironolactone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mineralocorticoid Receptor Antagonists</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mineralocorticoids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

