<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02801578</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-0226</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2016-01091</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02801578</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Different Doses of Ibrutinib in Participants With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Different Doses of Ibrutinib in Participants With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Ibrutinib is currently FDA approved and commercially available for the treatment of CLL.
      However, some researchers think the approved dose may be unnecessarily high.

      The goal of this clinical research study is to compare 3 different daily doses of ibrutinib
      to learn how these doses affect the disease and your body. Researchers think that if a lower
      dose of ibrutinib can be found to be as effective as the currently approved dose this may
      help to lower the risk of side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Drug Administration:

      Each study cycle is 28 days.

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will take ibrutinib capsules
      by mouth every day for 3 cycles. Each dose of ibrutinib should be taken at about the same
      time, either with or without food.

      During Cycle 1, you will receive the highest dose of ibrutinib (the dose that is currently
      FDA approved). You will take 3 capsules each day during Cycle 1. During Cycle 2, you will
      receive the second-highest dose and you will take 2 capsules each day. During Cycle 3, you
      will take the lowest dose of ibrutinib and you will take 1 capsule each day.

      You must swallow the ibrutinib capsules whole without opening, breaking, or chewing them.

      You will be given a study drug diary to keep track of each dose of ibrutinib taken, including
      the time the dose was taken, any missed or vomited doses and the reason for missing the dose,
      and any doses that you vomited.

      Study Visits:

      On Days 1, 8 and 28 of each cycle blood (about 1-2 tablespoons total) will be drawn before
      your dose of ibrutinib and then at 4 and 24 hours after your dose for pharmacodynamic (PD)
      and pharmacokinetic (PK) testing, to help researchers understand how ibrutinib works in the
      body, and to learn if the dose you are taking is as effective as other doses (Exception:
      there will be no 4-hour blood draw on day 28). PK testing measures the amount of study drug
      in the body at different time points. PD testing measures how the level of study drug in your
      body may affect the disease. You will need to return to the clinic on the following day (Days
      2, 9 and 29 of each cycle [Day 1 of the next cycle]) for the last blood draw.

      On Day 28 of each cycle:

        -  You will have a physical exam

        -  Blood (about 1-2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will have an EKG.

      Length of Study:

      You may receive ibrutinib on this study for up to 3 cycles. After this time, you will
      continue treatment for CLL as directed by your doctor. This may or may not include ibrutinib.
      If you do continue to take ibrutinib after the study is over, your doctor will determine the
      best dose for you to be taking.

      You will no longer be able to take the study drug if the disease gets worse, if intolerable
      side effects occur, or if you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation in this study will be over after your last dose of ibrutinib (after the
      end of Cycle 3).

      This is an investigational study. Ibrutinib is FDA approved and commercially available for
      the treatment of CLL. It is considered investigational to compare 3 different doses of
      ibrutinib. The study doctor can explain how the study drug is designed to work.

      Up to 12 participants will be enrolled in this study. All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 6, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Bruton's Tyrosine Kinase (BTK) Occupancy in Different Daily Doses of Ibrutinib in Participants with Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Just before dosing and at 4 and 24 hours post-dosing on Days 1, 8, and 28 (but before the first dose of the next cycle) of each cycle</time_frame>
    <description>Participants receive three 28 day cycles with decreasing dose levels.
BTK occupancy level measured by fluorescent affinity probe just before dosing and at 4 and 24 hours post-dosing on days 1, 8, and 28 (but before the first dose of the next cycle) of each cycle.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ibrutinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants take Ibrutinib capsules by mouth every day for 3, 28 day cycles.
During Cycle 1, participants receive the highest dose of Ibrutinib by taking 3 capsules each day. During Cycle 2, participants receive the second-highest dose and will take 2 capsules each day. During Cycle 3, participant takes the lowest dose of Ibrutinib and takes 1 capsule each day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ibrutinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Cycle 1 daily dose of ibrutinib is 420 mg (3 capsules), in the second cycle 280 mg (2 capsules), and in the third cycle 140 mg (1 capsule).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ibrutinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PCI-32765</other_name>
    <other_name>Imbruvica</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with a diagnosis of CLL (any stage) with ALC &gt;/= 20 x 109/l, requiring
             therapy.

          2. Able to receive ibrutinib through commercial supply, i.e., insured patients meeting
             FDA-approved indications.

          3. Age &gt;/=18 years.

          4. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-2.

          5. Adequate end organ function, defined as the following: total bilirubin &lt;/= 1.5 x upper
             limit of normal (ULN, unless due to Gilbert syndrome, in which case it should be &lt;/=
             3.0 x ULN), ALT and AST &lt;/= 2.5 x ULN, CrCL &gt;/= 25 ml/min.

          6. Able to understand and sign the IRB-approved informed consent document for this trial.

          7. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must practice 2 effective methods of birth
             control during the course of the study. Male patients who are partners of WOCBP should
             also practice an effective method of contraception. Effective methods of birth control
             include diaphragm or condoms with spermicidal foam or jelly, birth control pills
             (BCPs), injections or patches, intra-uterine devices (IUDs) and surgical
             sterilization. Postmenopausal women must be amenorrheic for &gt;/= 12 months to be
             considered of non-childbearing potential, Women and men must continue birth control
             for the duration of the trial and &gt;/= 3 months after the last dose of study drug, All
             WOCBP MUST have a negative pregnancy test prior to beginning ibrutinib on study.

          8. Patients should have discontinued any and all other therapy for CLL &gt;/= 48 hours prior
             to start of study therapy and recovered from any toxicity due to these therapies to
             grade &lt;/= 1.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous treatment with ibrutinib.

          2. Current therapy with warfarin or other anticoagulants at therapeutic doses, e.g., low
             molecular weight heparin, fondaparinux, dabigatran, rivaroxaban, apixaban or edoxaban
             that are unable to be discontinued.

          3. Active gastrointestinal conditions that are expected to impair absorption of orally
             administered medications.

          4. Active, uncontrolled infection.

          5. History of hypersensitivity to ibrutinib.

          6. Pregnancy or lactation.

          7. Patients with leukemic involvement of the central nervous system.

          8. Patients who currently have or have a history of the following within 6 months
             preceding study entry are not eligible: Unstable angina (UA) or myocardial infarction
             (MI), Clinically significant atrial or ventricular arrhythmias (e.g., AF, atrial
             flutter, ventricular tachycardia, ventricular fibrillation, or torsades de pointes),
             New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III or IV heart failure.

          9. Patients on strong CYP3A inducers or inhibitors that are unable to be discontinued.
             The list of drugs that interact with cytochrome P450 enzymes can be found online at:
             http://medicine.iupui.edu/clinpharm/DDIs/ClinicalTable.aspx
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prithviraj Bose, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 16, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>CLL</keyword>
  <keyword>Malignant neoplasms stated as primary lymphoid haematopoietic</keyword>
  <keyword>Ibrutinib</keyword>
  <keyword>PCI-32765</keyword>
  <keyword>Imbruvica</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacodynamics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

