<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02809391</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KR_POG</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02809391</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Orthotics and Parkinson's Disease: The Acute and Long-term Effects of Increased Somatosensory Feedback</brief_title>
  <official_title>Orthotics and Parkinson's Disease: The Acute and Long-term Effects of Increased Somatosensory Feedback</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wilfrid Laurier University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wilfrid Laurier University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to increase clinical knowledge of the relationship between
      increased plantar sensory information and orthotics in a Parkinsonian gait. The objectives of
      this study are to determine if orthotics, with and without a textured top cover, can alter
      muscle activation, gait parameters, balance, functional mobility, and decrease fall risks in
      Parkinson's participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to increase clinical knowledge of the relationship between
      increased plantar sensory information and orthotics in a Parkinsonian gait. Observing gait
      parameters and muscle activation changes, in orthotics with and without a textured top cover,
      provides an increased understanding of conservative treatment options available to the
      Parkinson's population. It is hypothesized that balance and functional mobility in
      Parkinson's Disease (PD) patients will increase, while decreasing fall risks, when wearing
      both types of orthotics. Larger improvements are expected with the orthotics with a textured
      top cover, thus increasing plantar sensory feedback. Male and female participants, aged
      55-75, with a diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's disease can participate in the study. Two
      types of orthotic design will be examined: 1) Customizable over-the-counter orthotics and 2)
      Customizable over-the-counter orthotics with a textured top cover. Five different assessments
      will be performed during three different testing sessions: 1) baseline testing; 2) 6-weeks
      post-baseline; and 3) 12-weeks post-baseline. The administered assessments include: 1) Static
      balance, double limb stance; 2) The Berg Balance Scale (BBS); 3) Timed Up and Go (TUG), 4)
      Functional Gait Assessment (FGA); and 5) Walking task.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Postural Sway during Static Stance</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 12 weeks post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Static balance will be measured by the amount of postural sway in both the medio-lateral (ML) and antero-posterior (AP) directions. Participants will be asked to stand, without movement, on the pressure platform for 2 minutes. The force platform will measure the amount of spatio-temporal firing patterns from the sensory afferents in the plantar surface of participant's feet. Secondly, the IRED markers placed on participants clothing, will measure the center of mass (COM) changes in relation to the base of support (BOS). An improvement in the location of the COM in relation to the BOS suggests an improvement in balance, resulting from increased cutaneous sensation from the textured material.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Dynamic Balance, using the Berg Balance Scale, Timed Up and Go, and the Functional Gait Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 12 weeks post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Improvements in dynamic balance and postural stability will be defined by score improvements on the BBS, TUG, and FGA assessments. Furthermore, plantar pressure changes will be recorded during the walking task to determine if simple changes in top cover design can alter the cutaneous information from the plantar surface of the foot. Observations will be made of the plantar pressure distribution changes between the orthotic, with and without a textured top cover, in comparison to participants walking patterns with footwear alone.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Plantar Pressure Distribution</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 12 weeks post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Force platform data will detail participant's plantar pressure distribution. Changes in plantar pressures will be recorded at 6-weeks and 12-weeks post-baseline. Pressure patterns can visually demonstrate the precise location of pressure changes on the plantar sole of the foot. Secondly, peak forces and increased load can be isolated to specific areas of the plantar sole of the foot, in relation to the total stance phase of the gait cycle (heel strike, midstance, forefoot load, and toe-off).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Stride Length</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 12 weeks post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Force platform data will be recorded for each participant. The anterior-posterior displacement of the ankle markers will be used to determine stride length, defined as the distance between heel strikes of the same limb.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Stride Width</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 12 weeks post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Force platform data will be recorded for each participant. Platform data and marker placement on participants will determine stride width, also known as base of gait, which is defined as the lateral distance between midlines of each foot.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Single Limb Support Time</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 12 weeks post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Force platform data will be recorded for each participant. Single limb support time is the duration of weight bearing, when only 1 limb is on contact with the ground. The force platform will record the duration of time a participant spends weight bearing on each limb.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Walking Velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 12 weeks post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Walking velocity, or speed of gait, will be recoded by the force platform data.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Electromyography (EMG) Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks and 12 weeks post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Muscle activity will be measured through EMG recordings of the tibialis anterior, peroneus longus, and gastrochnemius musculature. Secondly, changes in muscle activity will be observed in the orthotics alone compared to the textured top cover condition. The study will evaluate if the length, timing, and magnitude of the tibialis anterior, peroneus longus, and gastrochnemius properties altered with the use of orthotics, with and without a textured top cover, compared to footwear alone.
EMG data analysis will be isolated to the stance phase of gait for each of the three muscles. The time of muscle onset and offset will be recorded within the stance phase. This will determine the location and total percentage of the stance phase each muscle activity occupied. The length of activation, the muscle's specific start and stop time of activation, and magnitude of activation will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Orthotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recruited participants will be asked to wear the customizable foot orthotic, from baseline testing to a follow-up at 6 weeks post-baseline. Outcome measures at 6 weeks will be compared to those at baseline.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Orthotic+Textured Top Cover</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>At 6 weeks post-baseline, participants will received a different orthotic which has a textured material used as its top cover. Testing at 6 weeks post-baseline will determine if acute changes occur as a result of wearing the orthotic with textured top cover. Testing at 12 weeks post-baseline will determine if long-term changes occur as a result of the orthotic with textured top cover.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Orthotics alone</intervention_name>
    <description>The sole thin sport orthotic will be heat moulded to participants footwear. A top cover will be used of similar cushioning thickness and durometer properties as the orthotics+texture intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Orthotic</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sole thin sport orthotic</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Orthotics+textured top cover</intervention_name>
    <description>The sole thin sport orthotic will be heat moulded to participants footwear. A textured material will be used as the orthotic top cover in this intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Orthotic+Textured Top Cover</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sole thin sport orthotics with textured top cover</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosed with idiopathic Parkinson' disease

        Exclusion Criteria: A pre-screening questionnaire will assess the following:

          -  peripheral neuropathy, vestibular concerns, cognitive impairment, severe arthritic
             conditions, or other conflicting medical conditions

          -  deep brain stimulation

          -  currently wearing orthotics, or previously worn in the last two years

          -  decreased plantar sole sensation

          -  requires the ability to walk 10m unassisted
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kelly Robb, B.A.Kin, C Ped. (C)</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wilfrid Laurier University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kelly Robb, B.A.Kin, C Ped. (C)</last_name>
    <phone>(519) 884-1970</phone>
    <phone_ext>3298</phone_ext>
    <email>robb8660@mylaurier.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stephen Perry, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>519-884-0710</phone>
    <phone_ext>4215</phone_ext>
    <email>sperry@wlu.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wilfrid Laurier University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waterloo</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N2L 3C5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jenkins ME, Almeida QJ, Spaulding SJ, van Oostveen RB, Holmes JD, Johnson AM, Perry SD. Plantar cutaneous sensory stimulation improves single-limb support time, and EMG activation patterns among individuals with Parkinson's disease. Parkinsonism Relat Disord. 2009 Nov;15(9):697-702. doi: 10.1016/j.parkreldis.2009.04.004. Epub 2009 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>19467910</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gross MT, Mercer VS, Lin FC. Effects of foot orthoses on balance in older adults. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2012 Jul;42(7):649-57. doi: 10.2519/jospt.2012.3944. Epub 2012 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22282317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 18, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 18, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wilfrid Laurier University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kelly Robb</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>master's student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Postural Balance</keyword>
  <keyword>Gait</keyword>
  <keyword>Foot Orthotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Proprioception</keyword>
  <keyword>Somatosensory</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

