<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02800330</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EMC16-165</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02800330</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of the Proton Pump Inhibitor Esomeprazole on the Bioavailability of Regorafenib</brief_title>
  <acronym>REGORA</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effects of the Proton Pump Inhibitor Esomeprazole on the Bioavailability of Regorafenib in Patients With Metastatic Colorectal Cancer (mCRC) or Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumour (GIST)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Erasmus Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Erasmus Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Regorafenib is a novel oral multi-kinase inhibitor which targets angiogenic, stromal and
      oncogenic receptor tyrosine kinases. It is currently registered for GIST and mCRC. When
      regorafenib is co-administered with an acid suppressive agent, the intra-gastric pH
      increases, and as a result the equilibrium of ionized/non-ionized regorafenib may shift to
      the less soluble non-ionized form which reduces regorafenib bioavailability and exposure.
      Since proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) are often used during regorafenib therapy, this drug-drug
      interaction (DDI) confronts pharmacists and oncologists with challenges in clinical practice.
      In this study the investigators will therefore evaluate the impact of PPI-induced
      intra-gastric pH elevation on regorafenib pharmacokinetics in patients with GIST and mCRC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients will start with regorafenib in a loading phase of 21 days and will be admitted for
      24 hours to the hospital for pharmacokinetic blood sampling on day 21, 49 and 77 (± 1-2
      days). Patients will be randomized into 2 sequence groups (respectively sequences phase A-B-C
      or phase C-B-A). The patient will use regorafenib alone (phase A) or with esomeprazole for
      five days (phases B and C). To (completely) rule out a pH-dependent DDI between regorafenib
      and esomeprazole, during phase B of the study regorafenib is given concomitantly for five
      days, while during phase C regorafenib is given 3 hours after esomeprazole intake for five
      days (when the intragastric pH is maximally elevated by esomeprazole).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>As primary endpoint, AUC of regorafenib alone and AUC of regorafenib with esomeprazole (concomitantly and 3 hours before regorafenib intake, respectively) will be related.</measure>
    <time_frame>T=0, 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 3.5h, 4h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h at day 21, day 49 and day 77</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC of regorafenib will be determined by multiple blood samples at T=0, 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 3.5h, 4h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h at day 21, day 49 and day 77</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Cmax of regorafenib alone and regorafenib with esomeprazole (concomitantly and 3 hours before regorafenib intake respectively) will be related</measure>
    <time_frame>T=0, 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 3.5h, 4h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h at day 21, day 49 and day 77</time_frame>
    <description>The Cmax of regorafenib will be determined by multiple blood samples at T=0, 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 3.5h, 4h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h at day 21, day 49 and day 77</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0 in absence and presence of esomeprazole</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, approximately 0.5 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Tmax of regorafenib alone and regorafenib with esomeprazole (concomitantly and 3 hours before regorafenib intake respectively) will be related</measure>
    <time_frame>T=0, 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 3.5h, 4h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h at day 21, day 49 and day 77</time_frame>
    <description>The Tmax of regorafenib will be determined by multiple blood samples at T=0, 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 3.5h, 4h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h at day 21, day 49 and day 77</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The clearance of regorafenib alone and regorafenib with esomeprazole (concomitantly and 3 hours before regorafenib intake respectively) will be related</measure>
    <time_frame>T=0, 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 3.5h, 4h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h at day 21, day 49 and day 77</time_frame>
    <description>The clearance of regorafenib will be determined by multiple blood samples at T=0, 0.5h, 1h, 1.5h, 2h, 2.5h, 3h, 3.5h, 4h, 6h, 8h, 12h, 24h at day 21, day 49 and day 77</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (e.g. sequence phase A-B-C)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this arm patients will use regorafenib alone in the first cycle (treatment A), then regorafenib with esomeprazole concomitantly in the second cycle (treatment B) and at last they will use regorafenib with esomeprazole 3 hours before (treatment C)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (e.q. sequence phase C-B-A)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this arm patients will use regorafenib with esomeprazole 3 hours before (treatment C), then regorafenib with esomeprazole concomitantly in the second cycle (treatment B) and at last they will use regorafenib alone (treatment A),</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Esomeprazole 40mg concomitantly</intervention_name>
    <description>During phase B the patients will use esomeprazole 40mg concomitantly with regorafenib for 5 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (e.g. sequence phase A-B-C)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (e.q. sequence phase C-B-A)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>phase B</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Esomeprazole 40mg before</intervention_name>
    <description>During phase C the patients will use esomeprazole 40mg 3 hours before regorafenib for 5 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (e.g. sequence phase A-B-C)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (e.q. sequence phase C-B-A)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>phase C</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Regorafenib 160mg or 120mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will use regorafenib 160mg or 120mg during all phases (A, B, C)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (e.g. sequence phase A-B-C)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B (e.q. sequence phase C-B-A)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 years

          2. Histological or cytological confirmed diagnosis of mCRC or GIST and prior treatment
             specific:

               1. mCRC-patients who have been previously treated with, or are not considered
                  candidates for, available therapies according to common practice.

               2. Irresectable or metastatic GIST who progressed on or are intolerant to prior
                  treatment with imatinib and sunitinib.

          3. ECOG Performance Status ≤ 1

          4. Able and willing to sign the Informed Consent Form

          5. No concurrent (over the counter) use of other acid reducing drugs (PPIs, H2As and/or
             antacids), other than esomeprazole 40mg once daily during the study.

          6. No concurrent medication or supplements which can interact with esomeprazole or
             regorafenib during the study period.

          7. Abstain from grapefruit, grapefruit juice, herbal dietary supplements, and herbal tea
             during the study period.

          8. Adequate baseline patient characteristics (complete blood count, and serum
             biochemistry which involves sodium, potassium, creatinin, calculation of creatinin
             clearance (MDRD), AST, ALT, gamma glutamyl transpeptidase, lipase, lactate
             dehydrogenase, ALP, total bilirubin, albumin, glucose, INR, thyroid function tests,
             and PTT or APTT within two weeks prior to the study).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or lactating patients.

          2. Patients with known impaired drug absorption (e.g. gastrectomy and achlorhydria).

          3. Known serious illness or medical unstable conditions that could interfere with this
             study; requiring treatment (e.g. infection, bleedings, uncontrolled hypertension
             despite optimal medical management, HIV, hepatitis, organ transplants, kidney, cardiac
             and respiratory diseases).

          4. Non-healing wound, non-healing ulcer, or non-healing bone fracture

          5. Major surgical procedure or significant traumatic injury within 28 days before start
             of study medication.

          6. Patients with evidence or history of any bleeding diathesis, irrespective of severity

          7. Any hemorrhage or bleeding event ≥ CTCAE Grade 3 within 4 weeks prior to the start of
             study medication.

          8. Arterial or venous thrombotic or embolic events such as cerebrovascular accident
             (including transient ischemic attacks), deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism
             within 6 month before the start of study medication (except for adequately treated
             catheter-related venous thrombosis occurring more than one month before the start of
             study medication)

          9. Unstable angina (angina symptoms at rest), new-onset angina (begun within the last 3
             months)

         10. Myocardial infarction less than 6 months before start of study drug.

         11. Uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmias

         12. Symptomatic CNS metastases or history of psychiatric disorder that would prohibit the
             understanding and giving of informed consent.

         13. Interstitial lung disease with ongoing signs and symptoms at the time of informed
             consent

         14. Known hypersensitivity to any of the study drugs, study drug classes, or excipients in
             the formulation.

         15. Known history of HIV infection, active hepatitis B or C, or chronic hepatitis B or C
             requiring treatment with antiviral therapy.

         16. Patients on strong CYP3A4 inhibitors or inducers are not eligible for the study (see
             appendix B).

         17. The use of BCRP or P-glycoprotein substrates which leads to a clinically relevant
             drug-drug interaction concerning the pharmacokinetics of regorafenib.

         18. Unwillingness to abstain from grapefruit (juice), (herbal) dietary supplements,
             herbals, over-the-counter medication (except for paracetamol and ibuprofen) and other
             drugs known to seriously interact with esomeprazole and regorafenib during the study
             period.

         19. Unwillingness to abstain from acid beverages such as orange juice and other acidic
             beverages (e.g. Coca-Cola, 7-UP etc.) in the morning (between 06.00-14.00u AM) during
             regorafenib treatment in this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>R.H.J. Mathijssen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>EMC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>F.M. de Man, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+31 (0)10 7042451</phone>
    <email>f.deman@erasmusmc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>R.H.J. Mathijssen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>Prof. R.H.J. Mathijssen</phone>
    <email>a.mathijssen@erasmusmc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Erasmus Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rotterdam</city>
        <state>South Holland</state>
        <zip>3015 CE</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>F.M. de Man, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+31 (0)10 7042451</phone>
      <email>f.deman@erasmusmc.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>R.H.J. Mathijssen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+31 (0)10 7034897</phone>
      <email>a.mathijssen@erasmusmc.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 10, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Erasmus Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. R.H.J. Mathijssen, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof, MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumors</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esomeprazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Proton Pump Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

