<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02803658</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PHRCIR09-DR-DEVAUX-MME</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02803658</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Male Smoking on the Couple's Infertility</brief_title>
  <acronym>TABAFERTIMASC</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Male Smoking on the Couple's Infertility: Two-centre Case-control Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire, Amiens</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire, Amiens</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      About 15% of couples consult for difficulties achieving pregnancy. In about two-thirds of
      cases, a male component is identified, but is not always sufficient to explain infertility.
      In the majority of cases, the cause cannot be clearly identified and multiple abnormalities
      may be detected in both partners.

      Many factors concerning lifestyle and environment (medications, alcohol, smoking, pollution,
      exposure to heat, toxins, xenobiotic oestrogens, etc.) may impact on fertility. These factors
      may also impact on the fertility of the children conceived, which is described as an
      intergenerational effect (alteration of the fertility of boys exposed to smoking in utero).

      Few scientific studies with a high level of proof have been published on the impact of
      smoking on the couple's fertility. Gonadal functioning and the quality of gametes can be
      altered by these environmental factors, which may trigger a process of apoptosis or
      alteration of the DNA of gametes (sperm DNA fragmentation). Other modifications include DNA
      methylation and histone acetylation, which control gene expression and are grouped under the
      term epigenetic modifications. More recently, oestrogens has been shown to be involved in
      male reproductive function by acting on spermatogenesis, spermiogenesis and epididymal
      maturation. Demonstration of an active aromatase (Arom) (mRNA, protein and activity) in
      ejaculated human spermatozoa suggests the synthesis of small quantities of oestrogens in
      spermatozoa. The study of transcript profiles could provide information about the quality of
      spermatogenesis and/or spermiogenesis and during the first steps of embryonic development.
      Confocal microscopy has colocalized the aromatase on the head, midpiece and tail and can be
      used to assess the quality of the acrosome with anti-CD-46 monoclonal antibody. Even low
      concentrations of xenobiotic oestrogens can exert biological effects on certain functions of
      murine or human spermatozoa, accelerating capacitation and the acrosome reaction. These
      factors are all the more effective when they act in combination, as human gametes appear to
      be more sensitive to their action than murine gametes All studies conducted to date have
      investigated the impact of toxins either on one of the partners or in the children born to
      the couple. No detailed and high-level scientific study has studied both partners and the
      quality of their embryos.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Amiens University Hospital Cytogenetic, CECOS Reproduction Biology, and the assisted
      reproductive technology departments in collaboration with Caen University Hospital (members
      of G4) want to conduct this type of routine clinical practice follow-up study in the context
      of an inter-regional research grant (PHRC). These 2 University Hospitals are situated in
      agricultural regions with potential polluting industries. The recruitment of these centres
      comprises younger couples presenting with infertility for which a cause cannot always be
      demonstrated and in which the percentage of ART by ICSI is higher than the national average
      (close to 75% vs 60%). This population also presents a higher cancer risk than in other
      regions.

      This research project concerns evaluation of the impact of male smoking on the couple's
      fertility and will consist of a two-centre case-control study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Carbon monoxide in expired air using CO-tester®</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cotinine rate (micromol/L)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">154</enrollment>
  <condition>Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>infertile couples</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>smoking behavior</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fertile couples</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>smoking behavior</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>smoking behavior</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>infertile couples</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fertile couples</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sperm collection</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>infertile couples</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Fertile couples = control cases (with spontaneously conceived a child with a time
             required to design less than 12 months) and whose wife gives birth in one of the two
             maternity hospitals participating in the study

          -  All couples candidates for AMP: reproductive age couples (Female age &lt;35 years of age
             men &lt;40 years), infertility (primary infertility, inability to conceive after 12
             months of no sex protected). 1st or 2nd attempt at in vitro fertilization

          -  For infertile couples, couples in which we note

               1. spouses have sperm characteristics compatible with a natural pregnancy: an
                  normospermie (&gt; 20 million / ml) or moderate oligozoospermia (5-20 million sperm
                  per ml) idiopathic (or exclusion criteria)

               2. where the partner does not exhibit anovulation or tubal pathology-proven utero,
                  whose ovarian reserve is normal (FSH and estradiol rate J2 / 3 of cycle) ,.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female age &gt; 35 years Women&gt; 45 years

          -  Co- infections of one of the two members of the couple (or 2) by HIV, HBV and / or HCV

          -  Severe Oligospermia humans ( &lt;5000 000 sperm) or azzoospermie

          -  A normospermie or moderate oligozoospermia (5-20 million sperm per ml) nonidiopathic

          -  Will also be excluded couples where the partner has anovulation or uterotubal proven
             pathology , impaired ovarian reserve or chronic viral disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aviva DEVAUX, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU Amiens</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Amiens</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amiens</city>
        <zip>80054</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Caen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caen</city>
        <zip>14033</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 16, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 17, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 17, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>smoking</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

