<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02809326</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UCFlorida</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02809326</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trauma Management Therapy for OEF and OIF Combat Veterans</brief_title>
  <acronym>TMT</acronym>
  <official_title>Trauma Management Therapy for OEF and OIF Combat Veterans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Central Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Central Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial will evaluate the efficacy and efficiency of Trauma Management Therapy (TMT;
      Frueh, Turner, Beidel, 1996; Beidel, Frueh, Uhde, under preparation), which combines
      individual virtual reality (VR) assisted exposure therapy with group social and emotional
      rehabilitation skills training (will be superior to a treatment consisting of the same VR-
      exposure and group psychoeducational group therapy. TMT will be conducted in traditional
      17-week format, and a 3-week intensive treatment format. Outcome will be assessed using
      relevant clinical, process, and cost outcomes. Additionally, investigators will assess the
      potential of olfactory stimulation as a trigger for PTSD symptoms of intrusive thoughts and
      re-experiencing. Therefore, this proposal will integrate clinical and neurobiological
      assessment studies designed to understand the role of these factors in the etiology,
      maintenance, and treatment of PTSD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Troop deployment for OIF/OEF has been extensive for the past five years Among
      returning veterans, up to 18.5% are diagnosed with posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD). In
      addition to its positive symptoms (intrusive thoughts, reexperiencing, hyperarousal, and
      avoidance), PTSD is associated with social maladjustment, poor quality of life, medical
      comorbidity, and general symptom severity. Social and emotional problems include social
      avoidance, guilt, anger, and unemployment, impulsive or violent behavior, and family discord.
      A majority (&gt; 90%) of veterans seeking treatment for PTSD also seek disability compensation
      for debilitating occupational impairment and there are virtually no administrative or
      research data to indicate veterans are recovering from PTSD. Exposure therapy, which operates
      on long-established and fundamental principles of behavior therapy, offers hope for acute
      symptom alleviation, but may not address severe social impairment.

      Objectives/Hypothesis: To test the hypothesis that Trauma Management Therapy (TMT), which
      combines individual virtual reality (VR) assisted exposure therapy with group social and
      emotional rehabilitation skills training (will be superior to a treatment consisting of the
      same VR- exposure and group psychoeducational group therapy. Outcome will be assessed using
      relevant clinical, process, and cost outcomes. Additionally, we will assess the potential of
      olfactory stimulation as a trigger for PTSD symptoms of intrusive thoughts and
      re-experiencing. Therefore, this proposal will integrate clinical and neurobiological
      assessment studies designed to understand the role of these factors in the etiology,
      maintenance, and treatment of PTSD.

      Specific Aims: There are three specific aims: First, we will evaluate the efficacy of Trauma
      Management Therapy (TMT) for the treatment of PTSD in OIF/OEF and determine if TMT (which
      combines exposure and social/emotional rehabilitation) improves social/emotional functioning
      compared to our comparison group (exposure plus psychoeducational group therapy). Second, we
      will explore olfactory activation patterns that may aid understanding of brain mechanisms in
      PTSD. Third, we will determine TMT's cost efficacy using treatment expenses and resource
      utilization measures.

      Study Design: In a prospective randomized clinical trial we will test the superiority of TMT
      for OIF/OEF veterans with PTSD compared to exposure therapy plus psychoeducational group
      therapy. TMT combines VR assisted exposure therapy (VR-EXP) with social and emotional
      rehabilitation (SER). In addition to clinical, process, and cost outcomes relevant to PTSD
      for this population, we will include fMRI assessment of the central olfactory system in order
      to document its hypothesized role in fear acquisition and maintenance. Relevant outcome
      domains will be reassessed at mid-treatment, post-treatment, and 3- and 6-month follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale (CAPS; Blake et al., 1990; Weathers &amp; Litz, 1994; Weathers et al., 1999)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 17 weeks for two study arms; after three weeks for the third study arm</time_frame>
    <description>PTSD Symptom Severity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life Questionnaire (QLQ; Evans &amp; Cope, 1989)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 17 weeks for two study arms; after three weeks for the third study arm</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale (Selected items)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 17 weeks for two study arms; after three weeks for the third study arm</time_frame>
    <description>We will examine a subset of the CAPS separately, using frequency and intensity ratings on 4 items (interest in activities, social detachment, range of affect, anger control). These items were independently rated by 3 of the study investigators as being representative of social/emotional functioning</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Functional Indicators</measure>
    <time_frame>after 17 weeks for two study arms; after three weeks for the third study arm</time_frame>
    <description>Data will be collected via a clinician-administered rating form regarding objective indicators of social functioning, such as changes in marital status, employment status, residential status, legal involvement, psychiatric hospitalization, and utilization of medical care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impressions Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>after 17 weeks for two study arms; after three weeks for the third study arm</time_frame>
    <description>The Severity and Global Improvement Subscales are each 7-point scales which are part of the ECDEU Assessment Manual for Psychopharmacology. They will be used to assess overall severity and improvement. The CGI severity rating is a frequently used measure in pharmacological treatment studies and could be useful in making comparisons of rates of improvement from this study and those of drug studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-Related Functioning: Medical Outcome Study Short Form-36 Health Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>after 17 weeks for two study arms; after three weeks for the third study arm</time_frame>
    <description>The SF-36 is a 36-item questionnaire that measures health status and functioning over the past four weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Ratings</measure>
    <time_frame>after 17 weeks for two study arms; after three weeks for the third study arm</time_frame>
    <description>For a one-week period at each assessment point, patients will keep a log of daily symptoms, such as nightmares, flashbacks, total hours of sleep, and exaggerated startle responses behavioral ratings to monitor the frequency and severity (on a 10-point scale) of PTSD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The PTSD Checklist (PCL-M; Weathers et al., 1993)</measure>
    <time_frame>after 17 weeks for two study arms; after three weeks for the third study arm</time_frame>
    <description>PTSD Symptom Severity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Credibility</measure>
    <time_frame>after week 3 for 17 week arms; after third day for 3 week arm</time_frame>
    <description>To assess for differences in outcome expectancy, treatment credibility scales developed by Borkovec and Nau (1972) will be used. Four of the questions will be used for this study, with 10-point Likert scales. These include questions regarding how logical the treatment seems, how confident participants are about treatment, and their expectancy of success.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Charleston Psychiatric Outpatient Satisfaction Scale (CPOSS-VA; Frueh et al., 2002):</measure>
    <time_frame>after 17 weeks for two study arms; after three weeks for the third study arm</time_frame>
    <description>The CPOSS-VA is 16-item measure, with a Likert scale response format, based on a general measure of patient satisfaction (Pellegrin et al., 2001).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Combat Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>17 week Trauma Management Therapy (TMT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TMTconsists of 29 treatment sessions administered over a period of 3 weeks. Individual VR-assisted exposure sessions (14 sessions) are followed by Social and Emotional Regulation (SER) sessions conducted in small groups. Individual exposure therapy includes virtual reality to assist in augmenting exposure therapy. Group therapy includes anger management, social skills training, problem solving and behavioral activation for depression. The treatment program as a whole results in approximately 43.5 hours of therapist contact for each patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3 week Trauma Management Therapy (TMT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intensive 3-Week Trauma Management Therapy consists of 29 treatment sessions administered over a period of 3 weeks. Individual VR-assisted exposure sessions and group sessions are conducted Monday-Friday with individual sessions conducted in the morning and Social and Emotional Regulation (SER) sessions conducted in the afternoon. Education and exposure are implemented individually while SER is administered in small group sessions (3-5 people). All exposure treatment sessions will terminate after a decline of 50% in the highest rating recorded. SER sessions will be 90 minutes. The treatment program as a whole results in approximately 43.5 hours of therapist contact for each patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>17 week Exposure Therapy Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Control Arm of the study contains 15 individual VR-assisted exposure therapy sessions and 14 psychoeducational group sessions conducted over a period of 17 weeks. After the Education session, treatment occurs three times a week during the Virtual Reality (VR) assisted Exposure phase, and then once a week during the Psychoeducational phase.The psychoeducational group therapy, will include topics such as: DSM-IV criteria of PTSD, prevalence of PTSD, risk factors for PTSD, biological and conditioning models of PTSD, PTSD comorbidity, pharmacological treatment of PTSD, the impact of substance abuse, impairment in interpersonal functioning among veterans with PTSD, and issues related to anger control problems and suggested coping strategies</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>17 week Exposure Therapy Control Arm</intervention_name>
    <description>15 individual VR-assisted exposure therapy sessions and 14 psychoeducational group sessions conducted over a period of 17 weeks. After the Education session, treatment occurs three times a week during the Virtual Reality (VR) assisted Exposure phase, and then once a week during the Psychoeducational phase.The psychoeducational group therapy, will include topics such as: DSM-IV criteria of PTSD, prevalence of PTSD, risk factors for PTSD, biological and conditioning models of PTSD, PTSD comorbidity, pharmacological treatment of PTSD, the impact of substance abuse, impairment in interpersonal functioning among veterans with PTSD, and issues related to anger control problems and suggested coping strategies</description>
    <arm_group_label>17 week Exposure Therapy Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Exposure Therapy, Psychoeducation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trauma Management Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>TMT consists of 29 treatment sessions administered over a period of 17 weeks. After the Education session, treatment occurs three times a week during the Virtual Reality (VR) assisted Exposure phase, and then once a week during Social and Emotional Regulation (SER). Education and exposure are implemented individually while SER is administered in small group sessions (3-5 people). All exposure treatment sessions will terminate after a decline of 50% in the highest rating recorded. SER sessions will be 90 minutes. The treatment program as a whole results in approximately 43.5 hours of therapist contact for each patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>17 week Trauma Management Therapy (TMT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TMT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intensive 3-Week Trauma Management Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Intensive 3-Week Trauma Management Therapy consists of 29 treatment sessions administered over a period of 3 weeks. Individual VR-assisted exposure sessions and group sessions are conducted Monday-Friday with individual sessions conducted in the morning and Social and Emotional Regulation (SER) sessions conducted in the afternoon. Education and exposure are implemented individually while SER is administered in small group sessions (3-5 people). All exposure treatment sessions will terminate after a decline of 50% in the highest rating recorded. SER sessions will be 90 minutes. The treatment program as a whole results in approximately 43.5 hours of therapist contact for each patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>3 week Trauma Management Therapy (TMT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Intensive TMT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        Veterans or active duty military personnel with combat-related PTSD as a result of
        deployment to Iraq or Afghanistan.

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. Personnel with acute cardiac difficulties (angina, myocardial infarction, and severe
             hypertension) will initially be excluded from the study due to concern that intensive
             EXP, often accompanied by temporary increases in heart rate and blood pressure, may
             pose risks of exacerbating cardiac status. They will be included once they are cleared
             by the cardiologist.

          2. Veterans with comorbid Axis I psychotic disorders or acute substance abuse disorders
             initially will be excluded from the study but will be eligible once their substance
             abuse is under control for at least two weeks. Additionally, an Axis II diagnosis of
             antisocial personality disorder will be reason for exclusion.

          3. Because PTSD typically is accompanied by high rates of comorbid psychiatric disorders
             (Keane &amp; Wolfe, 1990), patients with comorbid depressive disorders, anxiety disorders,
             and personality disorders other than Antisocial Personality Disorder will be included.
             Also, veterans who have a diagnosis of mild Traumatic Brain Injury will be included,
             in order that our sample is as representative of OIF/OEF veterans as possible. We will
             address the issue of comorbid mTBI in the data analysis. In all cases included, PTSD
             must be considered the primary disorder.

          4. Patients must have a symptom duration of at least 6 months.

          5. Patients on benzodiazepines will be given an opportunity to discontinue and will be
             off benzodiazepines for at least two weeks prior to beginning the study. This
             exclusion is based on the empirical evidence to suggest that the efficacy of EXP for
             other anxiety disorders may be attenuated by benzodiazepines (Gray, 1987; Wardle,
             1990). Patients on SSRI antidepressant medication for PTSD (Ballenger et al., 2000;
             Brady et al., 2000) will be included once their medication regimen has stabilized for
             at least 2 weeks. SSRI medication dosage must remain stable throughout the course of
             the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Deborah C Beidel, Ph.D., ABPP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Central Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Central Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32816</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 29, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 29, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 31, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Central Florida</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Deborah Beidel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Pegasus Professor of Psychology and Medical Education Associate Chair for Research Director, UCF RESTORES</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>efficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>exposure therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <keyword>combat</keyword>
  <keyword>veterans</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Combat Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

