<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02801409</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013[653]</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ChiCTR-TRC-14004136</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02801409</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epidural Anesthesia/Analgesia and Outcome of Patients After Lung Cancer Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Epidural Anesthesia/Analgesia on Recurrence and Metastasis in Patients After Lung Cancer Surgery: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking University First Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University First Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Some studies suggest that regional anesthesia/analgesia may decrease the rate of
      recurrence/metastasis in patients after cancer surgery. However, evidences from prospective
      studies are still lacking. The purpose of this randomized controlled trial is to investigate
      the effect of epidural anesthesia/analgesia on the rate of recurrence/metastasis in patients
      undergoing lung cancer surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lung cancer is rapidly increasing and is a primary cause of cancer deaths. Surgical resection
      is the first line of treatment for lung cancer. However, it is unavoidable that some tumor
      cells will be disseminated into the blood or the lymphatic systems during surgery. The
      outcome depends on the balance between tumor-promoting factors and immune function of the
      body during the perioperative period.

      Studies showed that stress response induced by surgery inhibits the cell-mediated immunity.
      In addition, anesthesia management during perioperative period can all affect the immune
      function of patients; for example, volatile anesthetics and opioids might aggravate the
      immunosuppression and potentially worsen long-term outcome, whereas regional anesthesia might
      attenuate the immunosuppression and exert protective effects. However, existing evidences are
      insufficient to draw conclusion in this topic.

      The investigators hypothesize that regional anesthesia might improve long-term outcome in
      patients after lung cancer surgery, possibly by preserving postoperative immune function. The
      purpose of this randomized controlled trial is to investigate the effect of epidural
      anesthesia/analgesia on the rate of recurrence/metastasis in patients undergoing lung cancer
      surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>2-year recurrence-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Till 2 years after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Recurrence-free survival within 2 years after surgery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>During the first 3 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed with numeric rating score where 0 = no pain and 10 = the most severe pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of 30-day postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>During the first 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative complications that occurred within 30 days after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay in hospital after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>From end of surgery to 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay in hospital after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause 30-day mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>During the first 30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>All-cause 30-day mortality after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1-year tumor-free survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end 1 year after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor-free survival rate at 1 year after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2-year tumor-free survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 2 years after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor-free survival rate at 2 years after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1-year survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 1 year after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Survival rate at 1 year after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2-year survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of 2 years after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Survival rate at 2 years after surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of CD8+ and FOXP3+ T cells per mm2 tumor area</measure>
    <time_frame>After resection of lung adenocarcinoma specimens</time_frame>
    <description>Immunohistochemical staining of CD8 and FOXP3 molecules in excised lung adenocarcinoma specimens. Performed in part of enrolled patients.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of NK-cells and T-cell subgroups in peripheral blood</measure>
    <time_frame>Peripheral blood samples collected before induction, at the end of surgery and at 24 hours after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by flow cytometry. Performed in part of enrolled patients.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The chronic pain at 3 month and 6 month after surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 months and 6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by Brief Pain Inventory (BPI), neuropathic pain screening questionnaire (ID pain), and McGill Pain Questionnair (MPQ)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">396</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Thoracic Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Anesthesia, Epidural</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasm Metastasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Epi-GA/PCEA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combined epidural-general anesthesia (combined Epi-GA) will be performed during surgery and patient-controlled epidural analgesia (PCEA) will be provided after surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GA/PCIA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>General anesthesia (GA) will be performed during surgery and patient-controlled intravenous analgesia (PCIA) will be provided after surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combined Epi-GA</intervention_name>
    <description>Thoracic epidural catheterization will be performed according the surgical incision site. General anesthesia will be induced and maintained as in the control group, combined with epidural anesthesia which will be maintained with 0.5% ropivacaine during surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Epi-GA/PCEA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Combined epidural-general anesthesia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PCEA</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient-controlled epidural analgesia (0.12% ropivacaine and 0.5 ug/ml sufentanil) will be provided after surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Epi-GA/PCEA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Patient-controlled epidural analgesia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GA</intervention_name>
    <description>General anesthesia will be induced with midazolam, propofol, sufentanil and rocuronium. Anesthesia will be maintained with intravenous (propofol), inhalational (sevoflurane), or combined intravenous-inhalational anesthetics. Opioids and muscle relaxants will be administered when considered necessary.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GA/PCIA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>General anesthesia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PCIA</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient-controlled intravenous analgesia (0.5 mg/ml morphine) will be provided after surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GA/PCIA</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Patient-controlled intravenous analgesia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. age of 18 years or older, but less than 80 years;

          2. clinical diagnosis of primary non-small cell lung cancer (stage IA-IIIA), and plan to
             undergo radical surgery;

          3. agree to receive postoperative patient-controlled analgesia;

          4. agree to participate in the study and have signed written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. clinical evidence of metastasis, complicated with primary malignant tumor in other
             place, or received chemotherapy or radiotherapy before surgery;

          2. complicated with mental illness, severe heart disease (NYHA classification &gt;3), renal
             insufficience (serum creatinine &gt; 442 umol/L or receiving renal replacement therapy),
             or severe hepatic disease (Child-Pugh classification = C) before surgery;

          3. complicated with autoimmune diseases, or receiving glucocorticoids or other
             immunosuppressants before surgery;

          4. contradictions of epidural anesthesia;

          5. received surgery and/or anesthesia within one year;

          6. allergic to any drugs used during the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dong-Xin Wang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University First Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peking University First Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100034</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelsey CR, Marks LB, Hollis D, Hubbs JL, Ready NE, D'Amico TA, Boyd JA. Local recurrence after surgery for early stage lung cancer: an 11-year experience with 975 patients. Cancer. 2009 Nov 15;115(22):5218-27. doi: 10.1002/cncr.24625.</citation>
    <PMID>19672942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sawyer TE, Bonner JA, Gould PM, Foote RL, Deschamps C, Lange CM, Li H. Factors predicting patterns of recurrence after resection of N1 non-small cell lung carcinoma. Ann Thorac Surg. 1999 Oct;68(4):1171-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10543475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snyder GL, Greenberg S. Effect of anaesthetic technique and other perioperative factors on cancer recurrence. Br J Anaesth. 2010 Aug;105(2):106-15. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeq164. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20627881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koebel CM, Vermi W, Swann JB, Zerafa N, Rodig SJ, Old LJ, Smyth MJ, Schreiber RD. Adaptive immunity maintains occult cancer in an equilibrium state. Nature. 2007 Dec 6;450(7171):903-7. Epub 2007 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>18026089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shakhar G, Ben-Eliyahu S. Potential prophylactic measures against postoperative immunosuppression: could they reduce recurrence rates in oncological patients? Ann Surg Oncol. 2003 Oct;10(8):972-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14527919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamaguchi K, Takagi Y, Aoki S, Futamura M, Saji S. Significant detection of circulating cancer cells in the blood by reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction during colorectal cancer resection. Ann Surg. 2000 Jul;232(1):58-65.</citation>
    <PMID>10862196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hofer SO, Molema G, Hermens RA, Wanebo HJ, Reichner JS, Hoekstra HJ. The effect of surgical wounding on tumour development. Eur J Surg Oncol. 1999 Jun;25(3):231-43. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10336800</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lennard TW, Shenton BK, Borzotta A, Donnelly PK, White M, Gerrie LM, Proud G, Taylor RM. The influence of surgical operations on components of the human immune system. Br J Surg. 1985 Oct;72(10):771-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2412626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carter JJ, Whelan RL. The immunologic consequences of laparoscopy in oncology. Surg Oncol Clin N Am. 2001 Jul;10(3):655-77. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11685934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tashiro T, Yamamori H, Takagi K, Hayashi N, Furukawa K, Nitta H, Toyoda Y, Sano W, Itabashi T, Nishiya K, Hirano J, Nakajima N. Changes in immune function following surgery for esophageal carcinoma. Nutrition. 1999 Oct;15(10):760-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10501289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Downing JE, Miyan JA. Neural immunoregulation: emerging roles for nerves in immune homeostasis and disease. Immunol Today. 2000 Jun;21(6):281-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10825740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elenkov IJ, Wilder RL, Chrousos GP, Vizi ES. The sympathetic nerve--an integrative interface between two supersystems: the brain and the immune system. Pharmacol Rev. 2000 Dec;52(4):595-638. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11121511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Page GG, Blakely WP, Ben-Eliyahu S. Evidence that postoperative pain is a mediator of the tumor-promoting effects of surgery in rats. Pain. 2001 Feb 1;90(1-2):191-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11166986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Afsharimani B, Cabot PJ, Parat MO. Morphine use in cancer surgery. Front Pharmacol. 2011 Aug 8;2:46. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2011.00046. eCollection 2011.</citation>
    <PMID>21852973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu YX, Ayala A, Chaudry IH. Prolonged immunodepression after trauma and hemorrhagic shock. J Trauma. 1998 Feb;44(2):335-41.</citation>
    <PMID>9498507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein HG. Immunomodulatory aspects of transfusion: a once and future risk? Anesthesiology. 1999 Sep;91(3):861-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10485799</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gottschalk A, Sharma S, Ford J, Durieux ME, Tiouririne M. Review article: the role of the perioperative period in recurrence after cancer surgery. Anesth Analg. 2010 Jun 1;110(6):1636-43. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e3181de0ab6. Epub 2010 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>20435944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ishihara Y, Matsunaga K, Iijima H, Fujii T, Oguchi Y, Kagawa J. Time-dependent effects of stressor application on metastasis of tumor cells in the lung and its regulation by an immunomodulator in mice. Psychoneuroendocrinology. 1999 Oct;24(7):713-26.</citation>
    <PMID>10451907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freire-Garabal M, Núñez MJ, Balboa JL, Fernández-Rial JC, Vallejo LG, González-Bahillo J, Rey-Méndez M. Effects of alprazolam on cellular immune response to surgical stress in mice. Cancer Lett. 1993 Sep 30;73(2-3):155-60.</citation>
    <PMID>8221628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andersen BL, Farrar WB, Golden-Kreutz D, Kutz LA, MacCallum R, Courtney ME, Glaser R. Stress and immune responses after surgical treatment for regional breast cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst. 1998 Jan 7;90(1):30-6.</citation>
    <PMID>9428780</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heaney A, Buggy DJ. Can anaesthetic and analgesic techniques affect cancer recurrence or metastasis? Br J Anaesth. 2012 Dec;109 Suppl 1:i17-i28. doi: 10.1093/bja/aes421. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23242747</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Conrick-Martin I, Buggy DJ. The effects of anesthetic and analgesic techniques on immune function. J Clin Anesth. 2013 Jun;25(4):253-4. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinane.2013.04.003. Epub 2013 Apr 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23624071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahlers O, Nachtigall I, Lenze J, Goldmann A, Schulte E, Höhne C, Fritz G, Keh D. Intraoperative thoracic epidural anaesthesia attenuates stress-induced immunosuppression in patients undergoing major abdominal surgery. Br J Anaesth. 2008 Dec;101(6):781-7. doi: 10.1093/bja/aen287. Epub 2008 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>18922851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piegeler T, Votta-Velis EG, Liu G, Place AT, Schwartz DE, Beck-Schimmer B, Minshall RD, Borgeat A. Antimetastatic potential of amide-linked local anesthetics: inhibition of lung adenocarcinoma cell migration and inflammatory Src signaling independent of sodium channel blockade. Anesthesiology. 2012 Sep;117(3):548-59.</citation>
    <PMID>22846676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waurick R, Van Aken H. Update in thoracic epidural anaesthesia. Best Pract Res Clin Anaesthesiol. 2005 Jun;19(2):201-13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15966493</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Biki B, Mascha E, Moriarty DC, Fitzpatrick JM, Sessler DI, Buggy DJ. Anesthetic technique for radical prostatectomy surgery affects cancer recurrence: a retrospective analysis. Anesthesiology. 2008 Aug;109(2):180-7. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e31817f5b73.</citation>
    <PMID>18648226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Exadaktylos AK, Buggy DJ, Moriarty DC, Mascha E, Sessler DI. Can anesthetic technique for primary breast cancer surgery affect recurrence or metastasis? Anesthesiology. 2006 Oct;105(4):660-4.</citation>
    <PMID>17006061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsui BC, Rashiq S, Schopflocher D, Murtha A, Broemling S, Pillay J, Finucane BT. Epidural anesthesia and cancer recurrence rates after radical prostatectomy. Can J Anaesth. 2010 Feb;57(2):107-12. doi: 10.1007/s12630-009-9214-7.</citation>
    <PMID>19911247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin L, Liu C, Tan H, Ouyang H, Zhang Y, Zeng W. Anaesthetic technique may affect prognosis for ovarian serous adenocarcinoma: a retrospective analysis. Br J Anaesth. 2011 Jun;106(6):814-22. doi: 10.1093/bja/aer055. Epub 2011 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21436156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cummings KC 3rd, Xu F, Cummings LC, Cooper GS. A comparison of epidural analgesia and traditional pain management effects on survival and cancer recurrence after colectomy: a population-based study. Anesthesiology. 2012 Apr;116(4):797-806. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e31824674f6.</citation>
    <PMID>22273991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ismail H, Ho KM, Narayan K, Kondalsamy-Chennakesavan S. Effect of neuraxial anaesthesia on tumour progression in cervical cancer patients treated with brachytherapy: a retrospective cohort study. Br J Anaesth. 2010 Aug;105(2):145-9. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeq156. Epub 2010 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20573631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lai R, Peng Z, Chen D, Wang X, Xing W, Zeng W, Chen M. The effects of anesthetic technique on cancer recurrence in percutaneous radiofrequency ablation of small hepatocellular carcinoma. Anesth Analg. 2012 Feb;114(2):290-6. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e318239c2e3. Epub 2011 Nov 21. Erratum in: Anesth Analg. 2013 Jan;116(1):266.</citation>
    <PMID>22104077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gupta A, Björnsson A, Fredriksson M, Hallböök O, Eintrei C. Reduction in mortality after epidural anaesthesia and analgesia in patients undergoing rectal but not colonic cancer surgery: a retrospective analysis of data from 655 patients in central Sweden. Br J Anaesth. 2011 Aug;107(2):164-70. doi: 10.1093/bja/aer100. Epub 2011 May 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21586443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Christopherson R, James KE, Tableman M, Marshall P, Johnson FE. Long-term survival after colon cancer surgery: a variation associated with choice of anesthesia. Anesth Analg. 2008 Jul;107(1):325-32. doi: 10.1213/ane.0b013e3181770f55.</citation>
    <PMID>18635504</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gottschalk A, Ford JG, Regelin CC, You J, Mascha EJ, Sessler DI, Durieux ME, Nemergut EC. Association between epidural analgesia and cancer recurrence after colorectal cancer surgery. Anesthesiology. 2010 Jul;113(1):27-34. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181de6d0d.</citation>
    <PMID>20508494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wuethrich PY, Hsu Schmitz SF, Kessler TM, Thalmann GN, Studer UE, Stueber F, Burkhard FC. Potential influence of the anesthetic technique used during open radical prostatectomy on prostate cancer-related outcome: a retrospective study. Anesthesiology. 2010 Sep;113(3):570-6. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181e4f6ec.</citation>
    <PMID>20683253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myles PS, Peyton P, Silbert B, Hunt J, Rigg JR, Sessler DI; ANZCA Trials Group Investigators. Perioperative epidural analgesia for major abdominal surgery for cancer and recurrence-free survival: randomised trial. BMJ. 2011 Mar 29;342:d1491. doi: 10.1136/bmj.d1491.</citation>
    <PMID>21447587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor MD, Nagji AS, Bhamidipati CM, Theodosakis N, Kozower BD, Lau CL, Jones DR. Tumor recurrence after complete resection for non-small cell lung cancer. Ann Thorac Surg. 2012 Jun;93(6):1813-20; discussion 1820-1. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2012.03.031. Epub 2012 Apr 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22542070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alberts WM. Follow up and surveillance of the patient with lung cancer: what do you do after surgery? Respirology. 2007 Jan;12(1):16-21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17207020</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Colt HG, Murgu SD, Korst RJ, Slatore CG, Unger M, Quadrelli S. Follow-up and surveillance of the patient with lung cancer after curative-intent therapy: Diagnosis and management of lung cancer, 3rd ed: American College of Chest Physicians evidence-based clinical practice guidelines. Chest. 2013 May;143(5 Suppl):e437S-e454S. doi: 10.1378/chest.12-2365.</citation>
    <PMID>23649451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bruzzi JF, Munden RF. PET/CT imaging of lung cancer. J Thorac Imaging. 2006 May;21(2):123-36. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16770229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pei L, Tan G, Wang L, Guo W, Xiao B, Gao X, Wang L, Li H, Xu Z, Zhang X, Zhao J, Yi J, Huang Y. Comparison of combined general-epidural anesthesia with general anesthesia effects on survival and cancer recurrence: a meta-analysis of retrospective and prospective studies. PLoS One. 2014 Dec 30;9(12):e114667. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0114667. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25548913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 14, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking University First Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dong-Xin Wang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgical Resection</keyword>
  <keyword>Epidural Anesthesia and Analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Long-Term Outcome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Recurrence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Recurrence, Local</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

