<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00956852</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UW 08-249</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00956852</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study on Systemic and Airway Cytokines and Oxidative Stress in Lung Cancer Patients Undergoing Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study on Systemic and Airway Cytokines and Oxidative Stress in Patients With Non-small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC) Undergoing Surgical Lung Resections</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Lung cancer has remained as the top cancer killer in Hong Kong. Even for early resectable
      stage of lung cancer, only around 60-70% of patients can survive for 5 years after operation,
      mostly related to disease recurrence. Therefore there is urgent need for predictive
      biomarkers that can potentially help in monitoring patients for risk of disease recurrence
      after operation. Recent studies have suggested an important role of oxidative stress in the
      development of lung cancer and our preliminary data have suggested that some of the oxidative
      stress markers in blood could be predictive of response to systemic chemotherapy for lung
      cancer. Apart from potential biomarkers from blood, ongoing study has also been conducted to
      investigate the predictive role of biomarkers in exhaled breath condensate in lung cancer
      patients undergoing chemotherapy. Exhaled breath condensate can be collected simply with a
      disposable commercially available device that allows trapping of breath condensate via a
      cooling column during normal breathing for 20 minutes. Therefore this study aims at
      investigating the role of blood and exhaled breath condensate oxidative stress biomarkers
      before and after surgical lung resection for lung cancer in predicting subsequent clinical
      outcome, i.e., timing of disease recurrence. Recruited subjects will undergo interval
      sampling of blood and exhaled breath condensate, without any additional invasive
      interventions. The study subjects will be followed up for 5 years for subsequent disease
      recurrence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lung cancer is the major cause of cancer deaths among both genders in Hong Kong. In 2005,
      primary lung cancer accounted for 33% and 25% of all cancer deaths in men and women
      respectively. On average, there are around 4,000 new cases of lung cancer each year.
      Non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) accounts for about 80% of all primary lung cancers. About
      60% of cases present as advanced stages IIIB and IV disease. The currently available
      treatment modalities include surgery, radiotherapy and systemic chemotherapy. However, the
      overall prognosis remains dismal with 5-year survival rate less than 15%. Among those with
      early stage lung cancer, the 5-year survival rate is still suboptimal at around 60-70%.
      Therefore, there has been immense interest in the development of novel biomarkers to
      delineate the high risk group for subsequent tumour recurrence after curative lung
      resections. It has long been found that cellular prooxidant states promote cells to
      neoplastic growth, in part due to DNA damage caused by reactive oxygen species (ROS), i.e.
      superoxide anion and hydroxyl radical. The potential therapeutic role of antioxidants in the
      chemoprevention of lung cancer has therefore been brought to major clinical trials in recent
      years. Disappointingly, the major landmark chemoprevention trials including the
      Alpha-Tocopherol, Beta Carotene Cancer Prevention (ATBC) study and the Beta-Carotene and
      Retinol Efficacy Trial (CARET) have failed to demonstrate therapeutic benefits of vitamins A
      and E in lung cancer. Apart from the criticism about the dosages being used in the trials,
      these results may reflect the lack of understanding of the exact role of antioxidants in lung
      carcinogenesis. The simple use of general antioxidants, vitamins A and E, may not be able to
      target specifically the peculiar alterations in antioxidant profiles that lead to the
      development of lung cancer. In fact, our recent study has demonstrated specific changes in
      antioxidant expressions in surgically resected non-small cell lung cancer. In the resected
      lung cancer tissues, there were increased manganese superoxide dismutase (Mn SOD) and
      decreased catalase expressions at the transcriptional levels as compared with adjacent normal
      lung tissues. It has been hypothesized that this alteration in local antioxidant levels may
      result in anti-apoptosis and accumulation of genetic damages thus perpetuating
      carcinogenesis. However the exact clinical implications are still under investigation. Our
      previous case-control study on the systemic (erythrocyte) antioxidant activities in patients
      with NSCLC has shown an increased glutathione peroxidase (GPx), but decreased SOD activities
      compared with healthy controls. The erythrocyte SOD activity was associated with disease
      staging. In addition, our recent study on longitudinal profile of erythrocyte antioxidants
      during chemotherapy for advanced NSCLC has identified total glutathione as an independent
      predictor to treatment response, which may reflect tumour load (submitted, unpublished data).

      Exhaled breath condensate (EBC) has recently emerged as a non-invasive sampling method for
      real-time analysis and evaluation of oxidative stress biomarkers in the lower respiratory
      tract airways, especially in various lung diseases including asthma, chronic obstructive
      pulmonary disease, and lung cancer. In particular, endothelin-1 and interleukin-6 have been
      found to be elevated in the EBC from patients with lung cancer. Therefore, the current study
      aims to evaluate the temporal changes of various oxidative stress biomarkers and cytokines in
      EBC and blood in patients with NSCLC who are undergoing surgical lung resections and the
      potential role of these parameters in predicting subsequent tumour recurrence. Also, the
      correlation of biomarkers in blood or EBC with lung tumour tissue will be looked into.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Poor subject recruitment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>September 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to disease recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lung cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-small cell lung cancer patients undergoing surgical lung resections</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Plasma, buffy coat, red blood cell and exhaled breath condensate samples.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with early stage NSCLC who undergo curative lung resections in the Division of
        Cardiothoracic Surgery, Department of Surgery, Queen Mary Hospital will be recruited.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed early-stage non-small cell lung cancer
             undergoing curative surgical lung resections.

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 12 weeks.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Respiratory failure requiring use of supplemental oxygen therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chung-man James Ho</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Mary Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 9, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 12, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James Chung-Man HO</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

