<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00953095</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>G09-02-016-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UA3MC11055</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00953095</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Social and Communication Outcomes for Young Children With Autism</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimizing Social and Communication Outcomes for Young Children With Autism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Health Resources and Services Administration (HRSA)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Florida State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Health Resources and Services Administration (HRSA)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this project is to test an intervention program for caregivers and their young
      children with autism that is focused on improving social communication. This study
      specifically targets underserved populations, specifically children from low SES and
      racial/ethnic minority families. Participants will include 40 children (aged 24 months to 60
      months) and their caregivers who will be randomized (as if by flipping a coin) to one of the
      two treatments: Parent education sessions for two hours a week for 12 weeks or parent-child
      intervention sessions with the child for one hour, twice a week for 12 weeks. Young children
      with autism have difficulty with engaging in joint attention with others (e.g. pointing,
      showing. Joint attention skills are important to later development of language. Therefore,
      targeting this problem in young children may result in better language outcomes for these
      children.

      In order to examine the effects of the interventions, all participants will be complete
      cognitive, language, communication and play-based assessments prior to treatment, at the end
      of the first 12 weeks of the intervention, and post-treatment immediately following the
      intervention (approximately 2.5 to 3 hours each).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Child/parent dyads will be randomized to one of two intervention conditions: (1) Parent-child
      model, also known as the Caregiver Education Model (CMM):focuses on joint
      attention/engagement intervention using an established evidence based treatment (Kasari et
      al., 2006). It involves individual interventionist meetings with the parents and their
      children in their homes for one hour, twice a week for 12 weeks. In this intervention, the
      parent-child pair meet with the interventionist (as opposed to the group training in the CEM
      condition). Parents will be specifically taught techniques for altering the home environment
      and ways to enhance children's language, social, and play development. Parents will given
      guided practice (input and coaching from the interventionist) as they implement these
      techniques with their child. (2)Parent-education intervention, also known as the Caregiver
      Education Model (CEM): focuses on teaching parents information about autism, behavior
      modification, and community services using a manualized approach (Brereton &amp; Tonge, 2005).
      Parents will receive information on child development each week, and will be able to ask
      questions and discuss the information vis-à-vis their own child. This intervention is
      manualized (Brereton &amp; Tonge 2005). In the CEM condition, parents meet in a group, without
      their children, in a community-based setting to receive the intervention. Intervention in
      both conditions occurs for 2 hours for 12 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Social Communication Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Before treatment, after treatment and 3 months after treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mullen Scales of Early Learning</measure>
    <time_frame>Before treatment, after treatment, and 3 months after treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">112</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Mediated Model (CMM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>focuses on joint attention/engagement intervention using an established evidence based treatment (Kasari et al., 2006). It involves meeting the parent and child in their home for one hour, twice a week for 12 weeks. In this intervention, the parent-child pair meet with the interventionist (as opposed to the group training in the CEM condition). Parents will be specifically taught techniques for altering the home environment and ways to enhance children's language, social, and play development. Parents will given guided practice (input and coaching from the interventionist) as they implement these techniques with their child.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Education Model (CEM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>focuses on teaching parents information about autism, behavior modification, and community services using a manualized approach (Brereton &amp; Tonge, 2005). Parents will receive information on child development each week, and will be able to ask questions and discuss the information vis-à-vis their own child. This intervention is manualized (Brereton &amp; Tonge 2005). In the CEM condition, parents meet in a group (without their children) in a community-based setting to receive the intervention. Intervention sessions occur once a week for 2 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Joint Attention Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention in both conditions occurs once a week for 2 hours. Participants will be randomized to 1 of 2 interventions : (1) Caregiver Mediated Model (CMM):focuses on joint attention/engagement and involves individual meetings with the parents and children at their homes. Parents will be specifically taught techniques for altering the home environment and ways to enhance children's language, social, and play development. Parents will given guided practice (input/ coaching from the interventionist) as they implement these techniques with their child. (2) Caregiver Education Model (CEM): focuses on teaching parents information about autism, behavior modification, and community services. Parents will receive information on child development each week, and will be able to ask questions and discuss the information. Parents meet in a group (without their children) in a community-based setting to receive the intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Mediated Model (CMM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Education Model (CEM)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children must be between 24 months and 60 months at entry into the study

          -  Children must have a clinical diagnosis of autism or PDD-NOS, and/or meet criteria on
             the ADOS for ASD or autism

          -  Children must have an age equivalent of 12 months or greater for non-verbal ability
             based on the Mullen Visual Reception and Fine Motor scales

          -  Caregiver and child must be available for all assessments

          -  Children must be able to walk independently

          -  Parents must be between the ages of 16 and 50 years old

          -  Family should be currently underserved (inability to obtain services for their child)
             and have limited family resources

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children must not have a seizure disorder

          -  Children must not have associated sensory (uncorrected hearing loss greater than 20 db
             or vision loss) or physical disorders that restrict mobility (e.g., cerebral palsy)

          -  Children must not have sustained a head injury

          -  Children's diagnosis of autism spectrum disorder must not be comorbid with other
             medical syndromes (e.g., Tuberose Sclerosis, Neurofibromatosis, Down syndrome, fragile
             X) or diseases

          -  Children must not be in foster care

          -  English must be the primary language spoken at home

          -  Parents must not have a psychiatric diagnosis or a diagnosis of mental retardation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>24 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Connie Kasari, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Los Angles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tallahassee</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32306</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kennedy Krieger Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rutter M. Diagnosis and definition of childhood autism. J Autism Child Schizophr. 1978 Jun;8(2):139-61.</citation>
    <PMID>670129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahoney, G., Kaiser, A., Girolametto, L., MacDonald, J., Robinson, C., Safford, P., &amp; Spiker, D. (1999). Parent education in early intervention: A call for a renewed focus. Topics in Early Childhood Special Education, 19(3), 131-140.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koegel RL, Bimbela A, Schreibman L. Collateral effects of parent training on family interactions. J Autism Dev Disord. 1996 Jun;26(3):347-59.</citation>
    <PMID>8792265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kasari C, Freeman S, Paparella T. Joint attention and symbolic play in young children with autism: a randomized controlled intervention study. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2006 Jun;47(6):611-20. Erratum in: J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2007 May;48(5):523.</citation>
    <PMID>16712638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whalen C, Schreibman L. Joint attention training for children with autism using behavior modification procedures. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2003 Mar;44(3):456-68.</citation>
    <PMID>12635974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adamson LB, Bakeman R, Deckner DF, Romski M. Joint engagement and the emergence of language in children with autism and Down syndrome. J Autism Dev Disord. 2009 Jan;39(1):84-96. doi: 10.1007/s10803-008-0601-7. Epub 2008 Jun 26.</citation>
    <PMID>18581223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tomasello M, Farrar MJ. Joint attention and early language. Child Dev. 1986 Dec;57(6):1454-63.</citation>
    <PMID>3802971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 5, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 6, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 22, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 22, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 25, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Health Resources and Services Administration (HRSA)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Connie Kasari, Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Psychological Studies in Education and Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Autism Spectrum Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>joint attention</keyword>
  <keyword>communication</keyword>
  <keyword>language</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

