<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00957229</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009-026</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>SHH-4685s</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00957229</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Determine The Efficacy and Safety of GDC-0449 in Patients With Basal Cell Nevus Syndrome (BCNS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>GDC-0449</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Phase II Multicenter Trial Evaluating the Efficacy and Safety of a Systemic Hedgehog Pathway Antagonist (GDC-0449) in Patients With Basal Cell Nevus Syndrome (BCNS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital &amp; Research Center Oakland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital &amp; Research Center Oakland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to reduce the number of new surgically eligible BCCs by 50%
      appearing during month 3-18 of medication ingestion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase II, 18 month, double blind, randomized placebo-controlled, two arm
      multicenter clinical study design. During the 18-month treatment period, the safety and
      chemopreventive efficacy of 150 mg/day GDC-0449 versus placebo will be assessed, and include
      evaluations of the skin at monthly intervals for the first three months and then every 3
      months for the next 15 months. Removal of new surgically eligible BCCs (SEBs) will be done by
      primary skin care physicians (PSCPs) or at Study Centers. A Data Safety Monitoring Board
      (DSMB) will review unblinded results for an interim analysis when 20 subjects have completed
      12 months of drug. This review will focus on adverse events and efficacy results. Subjects
      will be monitored for the development of new SEBs after they discontinue study treatment. At
      the end of the 18 months, given that the observed adverse events are minimal, patients on
      placebo will be offered the opportunity to take GDC-0449 for 18 months in an open label
      continuation, followed by six months observation, and patients on GDC449 will be monitored
      for the next 24 months for assessment of the duration of benefit after stopping the drug.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>OBJECTIVES Primary: - To evaluate the efficacy of GDC-0449 in reducing new surgically eligible BCCs in BCNS patients during month 3-18 of ingestion of 150 mg/day. - To evaluate the safety of this dose of GDC-0449 in these patients</measure>
    <time_frame>Monthly</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary: - To assess the effect of GDC-0449 in reducing the total number of BCCs of diameter 5mm or greater on the upper back. - To determine the duration of any anti-BCC effect of GDC-0449 after administration of the drug is stopped.</measure>
    <time_frame>Effacacy will assessed at 1 year and duration of anti-BCC effect will be assessed 6 months after study med is stopped.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">41</enrollment>
  <condition>Basal Cell Nevus Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Gorlin Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo pill by mouth once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GDC-0449</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>vismodegib 150MG by mouth once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GDC-0449</intervention_name>
    <description>capsule, 150 mg, one pill daily, 18 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>GDC-0449</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hedgehog Inhibitor</other_name>
    <other_name>Hedgehog Antagonist</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The subject:

          -  has had diagnosed at least 10 SEB (of diameter 3 mm diameter or greater on the nose or
             periorbital skin, 5 mm or greater elsewhere on the face, or 9 mm or greater on
             non-facial areas excluding the skin below the knees) during the two years before study
             entry, as documented histologically in physicians' records and/or diagnosed clinically
             by a Study Investigator at baseline.

          -  meet diagnostic criteria for basal cell nevus syndrome

          -  is willing to abstain from application of non-study topical medications to the skin
             for the duration of the study, including prescription and over the counter
             preparations. Subjects will be encouraged to use sunscreen (SPF 15) at least once
             daily on all exposed skin sites.

          -  is willing to forego treatment of BCCs unless the BCCs are documented by Study
             Investigators, preferably on two separate visits, except when the PSCP believes that
             delay in treatment potentially might compromise the health of the subject.

          -  has normal laboratory tests as defined by the following: Normal hematopoietic
             capacity, Normal hepatic function: AST and ALT greater than or equal to 2x the upper
             limit of normal (ULN) Total bilirubin within normal range 0.20 mg/dl to 1.50 mg/dl or
             within 3x ULN for patients with Gilbert's disease Normal renal function: normal serum
             creatinine or measured creatinine clearance less than 50 mL/minute. Fasting
             cholesterol greater than or equal to 220 untreated

          -  be willing to not donate blood or semen for three months following discontinuation of
             Study medications.

          -  is willing to avoid pregnancy in his partner as defined by the following: Male subject
             is willing to use a latex condom during the study and for 3 months after the last dose
             during sexual contact with a female of childbearing potential, even if he has had a
             successful vasectomy. His partner must also use a form of birth control

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The subject:

          -  has used topical or systemic therapies that might interfere with the evaluation of the
             study medication during the study. Specifically these include the use of: (i)
             glucocorticoids to more than 5% of the skin (ii) retinoids systemically or topically
             to more than 5% of the skin during the six months prior to study entry; (iii)
             alpha-hydroxy acids to more than 5% of the skin during the six months prior to study
             entry (iv) 5-fluorouracil or imiquimod systemically or topically to the skin above the
             knees during the six months prior to study entry. (v) treatment with systemic
             chemotherapy within one year prior to starting study medication.

          -  has a history of hypersensitivity to any of the ingredients in the study medication
             formulations.

          -  is unable to return for follow-up visits and tests.

          -  has uncontrolled systemic disease, including known HIV positive patients.

          -  has history of congestive heart failure.

          -  has uncontrolled hypocalcemia, hypomagnesemia, or hypokalemia

          -  has clinically important history of liver disease, including viral or hepatitis,
             current alcohol abuse, or cirrhosis.

          -  has any condition or situation which in the Investigator's opinion may put the subject
             at significant risk, could confound the study results, or could interfere
             significantly with the subject's participation in the study.

          -  has a history of invasive cancer within the past five years excluding non-melanoma
             skin cancer, Stage I cervical cancer, ductal carcinoma in situ of the breast, or CLL
             Stage 0.

          -  has current, recent (within 4 weeks of Day 1), or planned participation in an
             experimental drug study while enrolled in this study.

          -  is a female who is pregnant, plans to ever to become pregnant, capable of becoming
             pregnant or is breast feeding.

          -  is a male who is unwilling or unable to comply with pregnancy prevention measures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ervin Epstein, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital &amp; Research Center Oakland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Oakland Research Institiute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oakland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94609</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center at Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 11, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 12, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nevus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Basal Cell Nevus Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nevus, Pigmented</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

