<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00956722</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Immuron Travelan HCV</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00956722</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hyperimmune Bovine Colostrum - TRAVELAN™ for Patients With Chronic Hepatitis C Virus Infection Not Responding to Standard Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hyperimmune Bovine Colostrum - TRAVELAN™ for Patients With Chronic Hepatitis C Virus Infection Not Responding to Standard Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hadassah Medical Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hadassah Medical Organization</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an exploratory trial of Bovine Colostrum powder to decrease translocation of
      gut-derived microbial products and immune activation in HCV infection.

      The study is designed as a single-arm, open-label, before-and after exploratory trial of 10
      weeks of Bovine Colostrum Powder (BCP) to reduce translocation of intestinal microbial
      products and immune activation in patients suffering from chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV)
      infection.

      The study population will include HCV-infected (genotype 1) men and women, ≥ 18 years of age,
      not receiving anti-viral therapy at the time of enrollment and for at least the previous 3
      months. Having failed previous anti-viral therapy (non responders), HCV recurrence after 72
      weeks of therapy, developed side effects which mandated stopping anti viral therapy, or not
      considered eligible for initiation of such treatment, with a plasma HCV RNA level ≥ 1000 I.U.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine if the administration of BCP will reduce the levels of intestinal microbial products in the bloodstream of HCV-infected, untreated persons.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the safety of the administration of oral BCP to patients with chronic HCV</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether the administration of BCP will reduce HCV RNA levels or the frequency of T cells expressing markers of cellular immune activation in the peripheral blood of HCV-infected, untreated persons.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine whether the changes in levels of intestinal microbial products in plasma after administration of BCP are associated with changes in HCV RNA levels or the frequency of activated T cells in the peripheral blood</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Asymptomatic Chronic HCV Carriers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active treatment with Bovine colostrum</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bovine Colostrum Powder</intervention_name>
    <description>Bovine Colostrum Powder (Biogard)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic HCV infection (genotype 1), as documented by a positive anti HCV titer, and
             confirmed by positive HCV RNA.

          -  Non responder to previous antiviral therapy, HCV recurrence after 72 weeks of therapy,
             previous antiviral therapy stopped due to side effects, or not a candidate for
             treatment with interferon + ribavirin.

          -  No antiviral therapy for at least 3 months.

          -  HCV RNA ≥1,000 IU obtained within 30 days prior to study entry.

          -  Not currently listed for liver transplantation

          -  Female study subjects of reproductive potential (defined as girls who have reached
             menarche or women who have not been post-menopausal for at least 24 consecutive
             months, i.e., who have had menses within the preceding 24 months, or have not
             undergone a sterilization procedure (hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy) must have
             a negative serum or urine pregnancy test performed within 48 hours before initiating
             the protocol-specified medication(s) unless otherwise specified by product labeling.

          -  All study subjects must agree not to participate in a conception process (e.g., active
             attempt to become pregnant or to impregnate, sperm donation, in vitro fertilization).

          -  If participating in sexual activity that could lead to pregnancy, the study volunteer
             must agree that two reliable methods of contraception will be used simultaneously
             while receiving the protocol-specified medication and for 1 month after stopping the
             medication. NOTE: Hormonal-based methods alone are not sufficient. At least two of the
             following methods MUST be used appropriately unless documentation of menopause,
             sterilization, or azoospermia is present:

               -  Condoms (male or female) with or without a spermicidal agent. Condoms are
                  recommended because their appropriate use is the only contraception method
                  effective for preventing HIV transmission;

               -  Diaphragm or cervical cap with spermicide;

               -  IUD;

               -  Hormonal-based contraception.

          -  Study subjects who are not of reproductive potential (girls who have not reached
             menarche or women who have been post-menopausal for at least 24 consecutive months or
             have undergone hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy are eligible without
             requiring the use of contraceptives. Written or oral documentation communicated by
             clinician or clinician's staff is required by one of the following:

               -  Physician report/letter;

               -  Operative report or other source documentation in the patient record (a
                  laboratory report of azoospermia is required to document successful vasectomy);

               -  Discharge summary;

               -  Laboratory report of azoospermia;

               -  FSH measurement elevated into the menopausal range as established by the
                  reporting laboratory.

          -  Men and women age &gt; 18 years.

          -  Ability and willingness of subject or legal guardian/representative to provide
             informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy or Breast-Feeding

          -  Continuous use of the following medications for more than 3 days within 30 days of
             study entry:

               -  Immunosuppressives;

               -  Immune modulators;

               -  Systemic glucocorticoids;

               -  Anti-neoplastic agents;

               -  Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
                  investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements.

          -  Serious illness requiring systemic treatment and/or hospitalization within 30 days
             prior to entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gadi Lalazar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hadassah Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Liver Unit, Hadassah Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <zip>91120</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenchley JM, Price DA, Schacker TW, Asher TE, Silvestri G, Rao S, Kazzaz Z, Bornstein E, Lambotte O, Altmann D, Blazar BR, Rodriguez B, Teixeira-Johnson L, Landay A, Martin JN, Hecht FM, Picker LJ, Lederman MM, Deeks SG, Douek DC. Microbial translocation is a cause of systemic immune activation in chronic HIV infection. Nat Med. 2006 Dec;12(12):1365-71. Epub 2006 Nov 19.</citation>
    <PMID>17115046</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 10, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 27, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 27, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 28, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Grant Rawling</name_title>
    <organization>Immuron Ltd.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

