<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02878200</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCC1488</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02878200</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RHOST-cRCT, Reactive Household-based Self-administered Treatment Against Residual Malaria Transmission</brief_title>
  <acronym>RHOST</acronym>
  <official_title>Reactive Household-based Self-administered Treatment Against Residual Malaria Transmission: a Cluster Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institute of Tropical Medicine, Belgium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Sheffield</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Reactive treatment of household contacts of a confirmed malaria case has been shown to reduce
      infection prevalence since the former as they are at an increased risk of infection. However,
      implementing this on a programmatic scale poses significant pressure on the health system and
      may not be sustainable without the active involvement of the recipient community. This study
      investigates a novel approach to reducing residual malaria transmission that combines the
      elements of active community involvement in reactive treatment of household contacts of a
      clinical case reporting at a health facility. The investigators hypothesize that in areas of
      low transmission (prevalence of infection ≤10%), most asymptomatic carriers are clustered
      around clinical malaria cases in the same households. Also, targeting individuals sharing a
      sleeping area with diagnosed malaria case will reduce parasite carriage in the community.
      This is a cluster-randomized trial where villages in Central and Upper Baddibu, North Bank
      East Region of The Gambia, are randomized to receive either reactive treatment of household
      contacts following a confirmed case of malaria or standard care, i.e. treatment of index case
      only. Formative research into community perception and reaction to self-administered
      treatment will be used to generate, adapt and evaluate messages that encourage adherence and
      compliance to treatment. This will be tested in the first year of the implementation, and
      findings used to develop a final model of messages to be implemented in the second year of
      the study. The primary outcome is the prevalence of malaria infection, determined by
      molecular methods, in all age groups at the end of the second intervention year and the
      incidence of clinical malaria during the transmission season.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Achieving malaria elimination presents a challenge because of important gaps in the knowledge
      about the strategies and tools needed achieve this. While malaria control measures aim to
      reduce morbidity and mortality in vulnerable populations, interventions to reduce
      transmission are designed to interrupt transmission of malaria parasites from humans,
      especially asymptomatic parasite carriers [1], to mosquitoes.

      The importance of asymptomatic infections in transmission has grown with the awareness that
      the majority of the human reservoir of infection are asymptomatic carriers [2] and these are
      quite difficult to target [3]. Previous malaria elimination campaigns have applied a strategy
      of mass drug administration: extensive treatment of entire populations, irrespective of their
      infection status, in one or multiple rounds [4]. Although transmission was interrupted in
      some cases, albeit temporarily [5], there is a reluctance to apply this method because the
      evidence of its impact has been mixed. A Cochrane systematic review of MDAs showed that long
      term reductions were not possible within the current concept and highlighted the need for
      studies in low- and moderate-transmission settings and studies that could address potential
      barriers for community uptake, and contribution to the development of drug resistance [6].

      More conservative approaches involving screening for infection with a rapid malaria
      diagnostic test (RDT) and treating only positive individuals; mass screening and treatment,
      did not have a significant impact on the malaria incidence [7], largely due to low test's
      sensitivity that would miss a large proportion of infected individuals with low parasite
      densities. Implementing reactive screening on a programmatic scale puts significant pressure
      on the health system [8] and available field-based screening tests lack the required
      sensitivity for low-density parasitaemia seen with asymptomatic infections [9]. More
      importantly, understanding the local context and adapting intervention strategies may help
      improve coverage and participation by recipient communities [10].

      This study investigates a novel approach to reducing residual malaria transmission that
      combines the elements of reactive treatment of household contacts of a clinical case
      reporting at a health facility with the active involvement of both patients and their
      households. The approach to implementation will be developed through formative research that
      identifies the optimum means of community engagement that will result in the best possible
      compliance and adherence to the treatment in the household.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 4, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>prevalence of malaria infection</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>the prevalence of malaria infection (determined by molecular methods) in all age groups at the end of the second intervention year</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>prevalence of clinical (laboratory confirmed) malaria cases</measure>
    <time_frame>3-4 months</time_frame>
    <description>the incidence of clinical (laboratory confirmed) malaria cases as detected through the health system; health facilities and village health worker, in both intervention and control clusters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the prevalence of antimalarial drug resistance molecular markers</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months and 16 months</time_frame>
    <description>the prevalence of antimalarial drug resistance molecular markers as determined among malaria infected individuals detected at cross-sectional surveys;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>treatment coverage</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months and 16 months</time_frame>
    <description>treatment coverage as determined by percentage of household members having received and taken at least 80% of the prescribed dose.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8000</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>reactive treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Household members; defined as those sharing the same sleeping area, in the intervention villages, will be treated with a full course of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine (DHAP)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In control villages, no household treatment will be done</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine</intervention_name>
    <description>A treatment course of DHAP consists of three doses taken daily. Treatment doses for household members will be prepared based on measured weight</description>
    <arm_group_label>reactive treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>DHAP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Resident in the study area for at least two weeks

          -  Informed consent to participate in the trial

          -  willing to receive DHAP (intervention villages)

          -  Age ≥6 months and weight ≥5kg*

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy (first trimester only)†

          -  Known allergies to DHAP

          -  Known chronic cardiac disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Umberto D'Alessandro, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical Research Council Unit, The Gambia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joseph Okebe, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+220-4495443-6</phone>
    <phone_ext>4009</phone_ext>
    <email>jokebe@mrc.gm</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Health Centres in NBR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Farafenni, North Bank Region</city>
        <country>Gambia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Edgar Dabira, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+220-2040284</phone>
      <email>edabira@mrc.gm</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Joseph Okebe, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+2204495442-6</phone>
      <phone_ext>4009</phone_ext>
      <email>jokebe@mrc.gm</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Gambia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 24, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 25, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Piperaquine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dihydroartemisinin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemisinins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

