<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02873013</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A-CaP2015-2026</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02873013</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Asia Study Group of Prostate Cancer (A-CaP Study)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Research Concerning Background Factors at Time of Diagnosis and Initial Treatment and Treatment Progress Cancer Patients in Asia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Japan Study Group of Prostate Cancer</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Japan Study Group of Prostate Cancer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will target patients who have received a histopathological diagnosis of prostate
      cancer and who are undergoing treatment in various forms, including active PSA surveillance,
      surgical treatment, radiotherapy, endocrine therapy, and chemotherapy. The study will survey
      information about the patient at time of diagnosis, clinical staging, details of initial
      treatment, status of disease progression, and prognosis at the end point of the study. The
      purpose of the study is to clarify distribution of staging, the actual status of treatment
      choices and treatment outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The A-CaP will collect information in a linkable anonymized format from all medical
      institutions in Asian countries participating in the study and will engage in data analysis.
      J-CaP which has previous experience of engaging in a similar study in 2010 wll be a sponsor
      for A-CaP study, the aggregated results of which have been reported. The registration period
      for this study will be three years followed by 7 years of follow-up study, and research will
      be implemented across a wider range of Asian countries, with new institutions participating
      for the purposes of this study. As this study will be an observational study the acquisition
      of data will be relatively simple, and as the content of the study will be almost identical
      to the study conducted by J-CaP in 2010, a system for research implementation is already
      established at J-CaP.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients background at time of diagnosis of prostate cancer, treatment progress and prognosis with the reason for progression and subsequent treatment methods</measure>
    <time_frame>three years</time_frame>
    <description>The following items are examined for primary outcome measure.
Patient background which is represented by month and year of birth; height and weight; ethnicity and family history; medical history; and name of condition/disease for which currently receiving treatment at hospital.
Information pertaining to prostate cancer which is represented by PSA value at time of prostate cancer diagnosis and Gleason score.
Prognosis information which is survival or death at end point of the Study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient QOL measured by SF-36 during treatment by comparison with A-Cap data and data in the United States and Australia</measure>
    <time_frame>three years</time_frame>
    <description>The short form 36 (SF-36) is used for an evaluation indicator of patient QOL. SF-36 includes the following eight elements.
Physical functioning
Role functioning Physical
Bodily pain
General health
Vitality
Social functioning
Role functioning emotional
Mental health
More detailed questions are prepared under the above each eight element, which a score is produced for a quantitative outcome of the patients QOL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20000</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prostate Cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>About 20,000 patients who have received a histopathological diagnosis of prostate cancer from ten countries in Asia.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Prostate cancer patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have received a histopathological diagnosis of prostate cancer between
             January 1,2016,and December 31,2018.

          -  Patients who, having received a diagnosis within the abovementioned period, began
             initial treatment for prostate cancer(including active surveillance).

          -  Patients who are either hospitalized as outpatients.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • Patients for whom information about the time of diagnosis, including histopathological
        diagnosis, cannot be acquired.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hideyuki Akaza, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>J-CaP</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Tokyo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <state>Meguro-ku</state>
        <zip>153-8904</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Onozawa M, Hinotsu S, Tsukamoto T, Oya M, Ogawa O, Kitamura T, Suzuki K, Naito S, Namiki M, Nishimura K, Hirao Y, Akaza H. Recent trends in the initial therapy for newly diagnosed prostate cancer in Japan. Jpn J Clin Oncol. 2014 Oct;44(10):969-81. doi: 10.1093/jjco/hyu104. Epub 2014 Aug 6.</citation>
    <PMID>25098707</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cooperberg MR, Hinotsu S, Namiki M, Ito K, Broering J, Carroll PR, Akaza H. Risk assessment among prostate cancer patients receiving primary androgen deprivation therapy. J Clin Oncol. 2009 Sep 10;27(26):4306-13. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2008.21.5228. Epub 2009 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19667269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 16, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 16, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 16, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Japan Study Group of Prostate Cancer</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hideyuki Akaza</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>observational study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

