<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02875418</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>171-16-TLV</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02875418</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparing Two Methods of Contractions Monitoring for Clinical Decision Making Regarding Treatment Among Pregnant Women With Preterm Contractions.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study Aimed at Comparing Two Methods of Contractions Monitoring (Electrical Uterine Monitor - EUM vs. Tocodynamometer) for Clinical Decision Making Regarding Treatment Among Pregnant Women With Preterm Contractions.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Identification and measurement of uterine contractions throughout pregnancy and labor is
      crucial to the well being of both mother and fetus. Prematurity is one of the major causes
      for adverse pregnancy outcomes, and clinical decision-making often relies on uterine
      frequency as recorded by a tocodynamometer, as well as on other methods including sonographic
      cervical length, pelvic examination.

      Objective:

      To show that the use of the EUM in preterm labor is effective in establishing true preterm
      labor.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Methods:

      Currently, three methods of assessing uterine activity exist. The first, tocodynamometry, is
      based on mechanical measurement of abdominal wall stiffness by a strain gauge placed
      externally on the patient's abdomen. This method mainly displays the presence of a
      contraction, its duration and the frequency of contractions. Yet, it fails to reflect the
      actual quantity of baseline tone or contraction amplitude due to great variability in
      placement and the gravida's body habitus. It is also unable to distinguish between true
      contractions or maternal movements or maternal Valsalva maneuver such as in coughing,
      straining or sneezing. These are the main reasons this technology is known to be unreliable
      in many cases and shows high percentage of false positive and false negative results [1].

      Another method for monitoring uterine contractions is an internal measurement of uterine
      pressure via an Intra-Uterine Pressure Catheter (IUPC). While it is accurate in recording
      intensity, duration and frequency of contractions, as well as uterine basal tone, it has two
      principle limitations: the IUPC can only be used after rupture of the membranes, and the
      introduction of a foreign object in the uterine cavity may result in chorioamnionitis.

      The third method of evaluating uterine activity involves recording of the myometrial
      electrical activity [2]. Initially, this was assessed in animal models by means of invasive
      uterine EMG [3-6], followed by noninvasive EMG recordings from abdominal surface in humans
      [7-10]. Several studies have attempted to correlate between term and preterm labor to uterine
      EMG, with limited success [11-17]. However, although most traditional EMG devices use only 2
      electrodes, a multichannel, noninvasive EMG device have been used successfully in previous
      studies, both in preterm and term pregnancies, and were proved as both safe and accurate
      [18-25]. Recently, reliability studies were published, regarding the comparison to
      tocodynamomtery, IUPC and electrical uterine monitoring, using a multichannel EMG, and
      demonstrated the multichannel EMG is as good as the IUPC ('Gold Standard') and both
      multichannel EMG and IUPC are superior to tocodynamometry in recording uterine activity
      [26-27].

      Study rational Premature labor and delivery heralds great costs to the healthcare system,
      including admission costs, tocolytic treatment and side effects and neonatal treatment of the
      preterm neonate. Unfortunately, the accuracy of diagnosing preterm labor is poor, with less
      than 10% of women presenting with preterm labor symptoms actually delivering within 7 days of
      symptoms' onset [28], 30% with resolving symptoms and more than 50% delivering at term [29].
      Since IUPC cannot be used in women with intact membranes and tocodynamometry is unreliable,
      with previous reports concluding that multichannel EMG is superior to tocodynamomtery and
      comparable to IUPC, our objective is to evaluate the utility of the multichannel EMG in women
      with preterm contractions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of preterm deliveries</measure>
    <time_frame>4 month</time_frame>
    <description>Week of gestation will be documented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Fetal Heartbeat Tracings</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EUM and tocodynamometry</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pregnant women with gestational age 24+0/7 to 33+6/7 weeks of gestation and contractions, cramping, pelvic pressure or backache.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EUM</intervention_name>
    <description>STUDY DESIGN
Explanation regarding the study and assessing eligibility criteria.
Signing an informed consent.
Recording of uterine contractions by both EUM and tocodynamometry. A correlation between EUM and tocodynamometry will be calculated. For the purpose of this study, a positive EUM or tocodynamometry will be defined as 3 at least 3 contractions in 30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EUM and tocodynamometry</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tocodynamometry</intervention_name>
    <description>STUDY DESIGN
Explanation regarding the study and assessing eligibility criteria.
Signing an informed consent.
Recording of uterine contractions by both EUM and tocodynamometry. A correlation between EUM and tocodynamometry will be calculated. For the purpose of this study, a positive EUM or tocodynamometry will be defined as 3 at least 3 contractions in 30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>EUM and tocodynamometry</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Gestational age 24+0/7 to 33+6/7 weeks of gestation.

          2. Maternal age &gt; 18 years.

          3. Contractions, cramping, pelvic pressure or backache.

          4. Reactive fetal heart rate monitoring at enrollment.

          5. Subjects are willing and able to comply with the requirements of the protocol.

          6. Fully understand all elements of the study, and have signed and dated, the written
             informed consent form before initiation of protocol-specified procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Refusal to participate.

          2. Maternal age &lt; 18 years.

          3. Woman with implanted electronic device of any kind.

          4. Woman with allergy to silver.

          5. Irritated skin or open wound.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>yariv yogev, professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tel Aviv Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>yariv yogev, professor</last_name>
    <phone>97236925603</phone>
    <email>yarivy@tlvmc.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 18, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 23, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 18, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 18, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

