<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02871752</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU00105259</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA193331-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02871752</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reducing the Effects of Active Surveillance Stress, Uncertainty and Rumination Thru Engagement in Mindfulness Education</brief_title>
  <acronym>REASSUREME</acronym>
  <official_title>Reducing the Effects of Active Surveillance Stress, Uncertainty and Rumination Thru Engagement in Mindfulness Education</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fox Chase Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NorthShore University HealthSystem</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We propose to examine the efficacy of couples-based mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR)
      on positive and negative psychological responses to active surveillance (AS) and AS
      adherence, with a sample of men on AS and their spouses.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The current study proposes to examine the efficacy of couples-based mindfulness-based stress
      reduction (MBSR) on positive and negative psychological responses to active surveillance (AS)
      and AS adherence, with a larger, more geographically representative sample of men on AS and
      their spouses. We will compare the MBSR intervention condition (Group A) with a health
      promotion and wellness condition (Group B) in a sample of prostate cancer patients and their
      spouses. We will evaluate its efficacy on self-reported measures of positive and negative
      psychological responses to AS.

      PRIMARY AIM Examine longitudinal change in positive and negative psychological responses to
      AS between groups over time.

      SECONDARY AIM Observe the relation between positive and negative psychological responses to
      AS and AS adherence between groups over time.

      THIRD AIM Explore dyadic factors on positive and negative psychological responses to AS and
      AS adherence between groups over time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>longitudinal change in psychological responses as assessed through online survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 8, Month 6, Month 12</time_frame>
    <description>longitudinal change in psychological responses as assessed through online survey</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>relation between psychological responses to AS as assessed by online survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 8, Month 6, Month 12</time_frame>
    <description>relation between psychological responses to AS as assessed by online survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>dyadic factors on psychological responses as assessed by online survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 8, Month 6, Month 12</time_frame>
    <description>dyadic factors on psychological responses as assessed by online survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MBSR (Mindfulness condition)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MBSR (mindfulness-based stress reduction) is a group-based, 8-week program that was developed at the University of Massachusetts Stress Reduction Clinic under the direction of Jon Kabat-Zinn. MBSR is comprised of a structured, developmentally sequenced curriculum that uses a group format to experientially instruct participants in the practice of mindfulness meditation and mindful Hatha yoga. Each session includes different forms of meditation practice, such as cultivating awareness of thoughts, feelings and bodily sensations, and learning to incorporate this awareness during stressful emotional and/or physical life situations. Lesson activities include the following: (1) mindful meditation (e.g., awareness of breathing, body scan, sitting, walking); (2) yoga; and (3) group discussion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HealthPro (Control Matched Condition)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>HealthPro is a health promotion program designed by Dr. David Victorson of Northwestern University Medical Social Sciences Department and his research team to function as a matched control for the MBSR intervention in this research study. The program teaches and promotes healthy behaviors, skills, and lifestyles. Major learning themes include: (1) health behavioral change readiness and self-assessment; (2) physical activity, movement, and non-sedentary lifestyles; (3) dietary and nutritional considerations for optimal health; (4) emotional wellness and coping with difficulties; (5) social engagement, relationships intimacy, and health; (6) managing bodily pain; (7) weight management and weight loss strategies; (8) health behavior maintenance over the long-term.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health promotion</intervention_name>
    <description>mindfulness-based stress reduction</description>
    <arm_group_label>MBSR (Mindfulness condition)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>HealthPro (Control Matched Condition)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be diagnosed with prostate cancer and on active surveillance within the past 36
             months (or the spouse or significant other of someone with prostate cancer on active
             surveillance)

          -  Must be at least 18 years of age

          -  Must be able to read, write, speak and understand English

          -  Must be able to perform basic activities of daily living (as determined by referring
             physician)

          -  Must be cognitively intact and free of serious psychiatric illness (as determined by
             referring physician)

          -  Must have access to the internet and ability to locate the assessment URL and/or
             ability to use a touchscreen keypad on a tablet device

          -  Must be willing to commit to the 8-week MBSR or Health Promotion course, which
             includes attending weekly, 2.5 hours classes over an 8 week period, a half-day retreat
             between week 6 and 7 , and daily homework assignments

          -  Must be willing to complete study assessments

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to provide consent

          -  Bedridden, or physical debilitation such that study participation would not be
             feasible or would create undue hardship
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David E Victorson, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David E Victorson, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>847-467-3060</phone>
    <email>d-victorson@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Bruriah E Horowitz, M.Ed.</last_name>
    <phone>312-503-3465</phone>
    <email>bruriah.horowitz@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Scott Eggener, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>773-702-1860</phone>
      <email>seggener@surgery.bsd.uchicago.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NorthShore University HealthSystem</name>
      <address>
        <city>Evanston</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kristian Novakovic, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>224-364-7104</phone>
      <email>KNovakovic@northshore.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Todd Morgan, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>734-615-6662</phone>
      <email>tomorgan@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fox Chase Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexander Kutikov, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>215-728-2468</phone>
      <email>Alexander.Kutikov@fccc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Eton DT, Lepore SJ, Helgeson VS. Early quality of life in patients with localized prostate carcinoma: an examination of treatment-related, demographic, and psychosocial factors. Cancer. 2001 Sep 15;92(6):1451-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11745222</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Eton DT, Lepore SJ, Helgeson VS. Psychological distress in spouses of men treated for early-stage prostate carcinoma. Cancer. 2005 Jun 1;103(11):2412-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15858824</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Eton DT, Lepore SJ. Prostate cancer and health-related quality of life: a review of the literature. Psychooncology. 2002 Jul-Aug;11(4):307-26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12203744</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>American Cancer Society, Cancer Facts and Figures 2013. American Cancer Society, 2013.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Salminen EK, Portin RI, Koskinen AI, Helenius HY, Nurmi MJ. Estradiol and cognition during androgen deprivation in men with prostate carcinoma. Cancer. 2005 Apr 1;103(7):1381-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15717315</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Krupski TL, Smith MR, Lee WC, Pashos CL, Brandman J, Wang Q, Botteman M, Litwin MS. Natural history of bone complications in men with prostate carcinoma initiating androgen deprivation therapy. Cancer. 2004 Aug 1;101(3):541-9. Erratum in: Cancer. 2004 Nov 15;101(10):2370.</citation>
    <PMID>15274067</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Smith MR, McGovern FJ, Fallon MA, Schoenfeld D, Kantoff PW, Finkelstein JS. Low bone mineral density in hormone-naïve men with prostate carcinoma. Cancer. 2001 Jun 15;91(12):2238-45.</citation>
    <PMID>11413511</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Smith MR. Osteoporosis during androgen deprivation therapy for prostate cancer. Urology. 2002 Sep;60(3 Suppl 1):79-85; discussion 86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12231056</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pirl WF, Siegel GI, Goode MJ, Smith MR. Depression in men receiving androgen deprivation therapy for prostate cancer: a pilot study. Psychooncology. 2002 Nov-Dec;11(6):518-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12476433</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dale W, Bilir P, Han M, Meltzer D. The role of anxiety in prostate carcinoma: a structured review of the literature. Cancer. 2005 Aug 1;104(3):467-78. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15959911</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cooperberg MR, Broering JM, Litwin MS, Lubeck DP, Mehta SS, Henning JM, Carroll PR; CaPSURE Investigators. The contemporary management of prostate cancer in the United States: lessons from the cancer of the prostate strategic urologic research endeavor (CapSURE), a national disease registry. J Urol. 2004 Apr;171(4):1393-401. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15017184</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Roemeling S, Roobol MJ, Postma R, Gosselaar C, van der Kwast TH, Bangma CH, Schröder FH. Management and survival of screen-detected prostate cancer patients who might have been suitable for active surveillance. Eur Urol. 2006 Sep;50(3):475-82. Epub 2006 May 3.</citation>
    <PMID>16713065</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ganz PA, Barry JM, Burke W, Col NF, Corso PS, Dodson E, Hammond ME, Kogan BA, Lynch CF, Newcomer L, Seifter EJ, Tooze JA, Viswanath KV, Wessells H. NIH State-of-the-Science Conference Statement: Role of active surveillance in the management of men with localized prostate cancer. NIH Consens State Sci Statements. 2011 Dec 5-7;28(1):1-27.</citation>
    <PMID>23392076</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Parker C. Active surveillance: towards a new paradigm in the management of early prostate cancer. Lancet Oncol. 2004 Feb;5(2):101-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14761814</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Parker C. Active surveillance of early prostate cancer: rationale, initial results and future developments. Prostate Cancer Prostatic Dis. 2004;7(3):184-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15224088</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bergman J, Litwin MS. Quality of life in men undergoing active surveillance for localized prostate cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr. 2012 Dec;2012(45):242-9. doi: 10.1093/jncimonographs/lgs026.</citation>
    <PMID>23271780</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kazer MW, Psutka SP, Latini DM, Bailey DE Jr. Psychosocial aspects of active surveillance. Curr Opin Urol. 2013 May;23(3):273-7. doi: 10.1097/MOU.0b013e32835eff24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23422588</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carlson LE, Ursuliak Z, Goodey E, Angen M, Speca M. The effects of a mindfulness meditation-based stress reduction program on mood and symptoms of stress in cancer outpatients: 6-month follow-up. Support Care Cancer. 2001 Mar;9(2):112-23.</citation>
    <PMID>11305069</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Astin JA. Stress reduction through mindfulness meditation. Effects on psychological symptomatology, sense of control, and spiritual experiences. Psychother Psychosom. 1997;66(2):97-106.</citation>
    <PMID>9097338</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wong SY. Effect of mindfulness-based stress reduction programme on pain and quality of life in chronic pain patients: a randomised controlled clinical trial. Hong Kong Med J. 2009 Oct;15 Suppl 6:13-4.</citation>
    <PMID>19801710</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chiesa A, Serretti A. Mindfulness-based stress reduction for stress management in healthy people: a review and meta-analysis. J Altern Complement Med. 2009 May;15(5):593-600. doi: 10.1089/acm.2008.0495. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19432513</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ledesma D, Kumano H. Mindfulness-based stress reduction and cancer: a meta-analysis. Psychooncology. 2009 Jun;18(6):571-9. doi: 10.1002/pon.1400.</citation>
    <PMID>19023879</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bohlmeijer E, Prenger R, Taal E, Cuijpers P. The effects of mindfulness-based stress reduction therapy on mental health of adults with a chronic medical disease: a meta-analysis. J Psychosom Res. 2010 Jun;68(6):539-44. doi: 10.1016/j.jpsychores.2009.10.005. Epub 2009 Dec 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20488270</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kabat-Zinn, J., Full Catastrophe Living: Using the Wisdom of your Mind to Face Stress, Pain and Illness. 1990, New York: Dell Publishing.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kabat-Zinn J, Massion AO, Kristeller J, Peterson LG, Fletcher KE, Pbert L, Lenderking WR, Santorelli SF. Effectiveness of a meditation-based stress reduction program in the treatment of anxiety disorders. Am J Psychiatry. 1992 Jul;149(7):936-43.</citation>
    <PMID>1609875</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vøllestad J, Sivertsen B, Nielsen GH. Mindfulness-based stress reduction for patients with anxiety disorders: evaluation in a randomized controlled trial. Behav Res Ther. 2011 Apr;49(4):281-8. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2011.01.007. Epub 2011 Jan 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21320700</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gross CR, Kreitzer MJ, Thomas W, Reilly-Spong M, Cramer-Bornemann M, Nyman JA, Frazier P, Ibrahim HN. Mindfulness-based stress reduction for solid organ transplant recipients: a randomized controlled trial. Altern Ther Health Med. 2010 Sep-Oct;16(5):30-8.</citation>
    <PMID>20882729</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gross CR, Kreitzer MJ, Reilly-Spong M, Wall M, Winbush NY, Patterson R, Mahowald M, Cramer-Bornemann M. Mindfulness-based stress reduction versus pharmacotherapy for chronic primary insomnia: a randomized controlled clinical trial. Explore (NY). 2011 Mar-Apr;7(2):76-87. doi: 10.1016/j.explore.2010.12.003.</citation>
    <PMID>21397868</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carlson LE, Speca M, Patel KD, Goodey E. Mindfulness-based stress reduction in relation to quality of life, mood, symptoms of stress, and immune parameters in breast and prostate cancer outpatients. Psychosom Med. 2003 Jul-Aug;65(4):571-81.</citation>
    <PMID>12883107</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carlson LE, Garland SN. Impact of mindfulness-based stress reduction (MBSR) on sleep, mood, stress and fatigue symptoms in cancer outpatients. Int J Behav Med. 2005;12(4):278-85.</citation>
    <PMID>16262547</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Matousek RH, Dobkin PL, Pruessner J. Cortisol as a marker for improvement in mindfulness-based stress reduction. Complement Ther Clin Pract. 2010 Feb;16(1):13-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ctcp.2009.06.004. Epub 2009 Jul 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20129404</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Matousek RH, Pruessner JC, Dobkin PL. Changes in the cortisol awakening response (CAR) following participation in mindfulness-based stress reduction in women who completed treatment for breast cancer. Complement Ther Clin Pract. 2011 May;17(2):65-70. doi: 10.1016/j.ctcp.2010.10.005. Epub 2010 Nov 26.</citation>
    <PMID>21457893</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carlson LE, Speca M, Patel KD, Goodey E. Mindfulness-based stress reduction in relation to quality of life, mood, symptoms of stress and levels of cortisol, dehydroepiandrosterone sulfate (DHEAS) and melatonin in breast and prostate cancer outpatients. Psychoneuroendocrinology. 2004 May;29(4):448-74.</citation>
    <PMID>14749092</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lamanque P, Daneault S. [Does meditation improve the quality of life for patients living with cancer?]. Can Fam Physician. 2006 Apr;52:474-5. Review. French.</citation>
    <PMID>17327889</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Matchim Y, Armer JM. Measuring the psychological impact of mindfulness meditation on health among patients with cancer: a literature review. Oncol Nurs Forum. 2007 Sep;34(5):1059-66. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17878133</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Matchim Y, Armer JM, Stewart BR. Mindfulness-based stress reduction among breast cancer survivors: a literature review and discussion. Oncol Nurs Forum. 2011 Mar;38(2):E61-71. doi: 10.1188/11.ONF.E61-E71. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21356643</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ott MJ, Norris RL, Bauer-Wu SM. Mindfulness meditation for oncology patients: a discussion and critical review. Integr Cancer Ther. 2006 Jun;5(2):98-108. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16685074</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Smith JE, Richardson J, Hoffman C, Pilkington K. Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction as supportive therapy in cancer care: systematic review. J Adv Nurs. 2005 Nov;52(3):315-27. Review. Erratum in: J Adv Nurs. 2006 Mar;53(5):618.</citation>
    <PMID>16194185</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Saxe GA, Hébert JR, Carmody JF, Kabat-Zinn J, Rosenzweig PH, Jarzobski D, Reed GW, Blute RD. Can diet in conjunction with stress reduction affect the rate of increase in prostate specific antigen after biochemical recurrence of prostate cancer? J Urol. 2001 Dec;166(6):2202-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11696736</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pickles T, Ruether JD, Weir L, Carlson L, Jakulj F; SCRN Communication Team. Psychosocial barriers to active surveillance for the management of early prostate cancer and a strategy for increased acceptance. BJU Int. 2007 Sep;100(3):544-51. Epub 2007 May 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17532857</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Victorson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>active surveillance</keyword>
  <keyword>MBSR</keyword>
  <keyword>couples</keyword>
  <keyword>health promotion</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>mindfulness</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

