<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02876679</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P150955</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-002129-12</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02876679</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cyclophosphamide Versus Anti-thymocyte Globulin for GVHD Prophylaxis After RIC Allo-SCT</brief_title>
  <acronym>ATG-CyGVHD</acronym>
  <official_title>Cyclophosphamide Versus Anti-thymocyte Globulin for GVHD Prophylaxis After RIC Allo-SCT</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is designed as a two arm randomized Phase II, multicenter trial comparing
      cyclophosphamide to anti-thymocyte globulin for Graft-versus-Host Disease (GVHD) prophylaxis
      in patients with hematologic malignancies undergoing reduced intensity conditioning
      hematopoietic stem cell transplantation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Allogeneic stem cell transplantation (allo-SCT) is a well-established therapy for different
      hematologic malignancies. Reduced-intensity conditioning (RIC) regimens can decrease the rate
      of toxicity/mortality in elderly patients, or in patients with poor medical condition. GVHD
      prophylaxis remains a challenging task after allo-SCT. The Flu-ivBu combination is a widely
      used RIC regimen, endorsed by EMA since July 2014. ATG in combination with cyclosporine-A
      ±mycophenolate mofetil is the backbone for GVHD prophylaxis in this setting. ATG can prevent
      GVHD with a good efficacy, but at the cost of a higher toxicity and profound
      immunosuppression, calling for more effective therapies. The most widely used RIC regimen in
      France incorporates fludarabine (Flu), intermediate doses of IV-busulfan (Bu) and
      anti-thymocyte globulins (ATG). While the use of ATG can prevent severe acute and chronic
      GVHD after allogeneic peripheral blood stem cell (PBSC) transplantation from both
      HLA-identical sibling and unrelated donors, some data suggested that in-vivo T-cell depletion
      with ATG in the RIC setting may induce a higher risk of disease relapse. Also, ATG induces
      profound immune suppression and increase incidence of opportunistic infections, especially
      EBV-related complications (relative risk=4.9; 95% CI[ 1.1-21.0]; P=0.03).

      On the other hand, high-dose post-transplantation cyclophosphamide (PTCy) was developed to
      facilitate HLA-haploidentical allo-SCT using unmanipulated bone marrow (BM) cells. PTCy was
      effective in preventing both acute and chronic GVHD given its capacity to preferentially
      eliminate allo-reactive T cells and preserve regulatory T cells, both of which impact
      allogeneic immune reactions. Subsequently, the efficacy of PTCy as sole GVHD prophylaxis
      after myeloablative conditioning when using BM was also shown. However, BM is not the
      preferred source of stem cells after RIC allo-SCT, and the potential efficacy of PTCy on
      preventing GVHD when using PBSCs (which is the most frequently used source of allogeneic
      cells worldwide) is debated.

      The advent of PTCy therapy is nowadays on the cutting edge. Thus, the potential efficacy (and
      cost-effectiveness) of PTCy for GVHD prophylaxis may have a major ATG sparing potential. A
      recent single centre phase 2 study (n=49) suggested that PTCy alone may not be the preferred
      GVHD prophylaxis following a RIC transplant with PBSCs. Indeed, A matched cohort analysis
      compared outcomes to tacrolimus/methotrexate GVHD prophylaxis and indicated higher rates of
      acute GVHD grade II to IV (46% versus 19%; hazard ratio [HR], 2.8; P =0.02) and
      treatment-related mortality (HR, 3.3; P =0.035) and worse overall survival (HR, 1.9; P=0..04)
      with post-CY. Interpretation of the above non-randomized data is further complicated by
      heterogeneity (related and unrelated donors, BM and PBSC as stem cell source, different
      conditioning regimen), highlighting the need for a controlled randomized trial in a
      standardized setting.

      The ultimate goal of this Phase IIB study is to assess the feasibility and inform the design
      of a subsequent phase III study. The present randomized trial is designed to compare the
      efficacy of the addition of PTCy to current standard of care with ATG after a Flu-Bu-based
      RIC regimen on GVHD prophylaxis. The protocol will use a novel endpoint for benchmarking
      interventions based on a composite primary endpoint of GVHD-free, relapse-free survival which
      measures freedom from ongoing morbidity and represents an ideal outcome measure after
      allo-SCT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 6, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite endpoint of GVHD-free, relapse-free survival (GRFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Absence of grade 3-4 acute GVHD, chronic GVHD requiring systemic treatment, relapse, or death</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of grade 2-4 and grade 3-4 severe acute GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Acute GVHD grading should be performed by the revised Glucksberg criteria (Przepiorka et al., 1995). The time of onset of acute grades II-IV and III-IV acute GVHD will be recorded, as well as the maximum grade achieved</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of non-relapse mortality within the first 12 months after transplantation.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Death without evidence of disease recurrence. Disease recurrence will be considered a competing event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Relapse-free survival : time from date of transplant to death or relapse, whichever comes first. The event for this endpoint is relapse or death. Patients alive and free from disease relapse will be censored at last follow-up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival : time interval between date of transplant and death from any cause or for surviving patients, to last follow-up. The event for this endpoint is death from any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL) with EORTC QLQ-C30</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation by the questionnaire EORTC QLQ-C30 (European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire-Core 30)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL) with FACT-BMT</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation by the questionnaire FACT-BMT (Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Bone Marrow Transplant)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune recovery measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Immune recovery measurement: number of patients with complete immune recovery (T, B and dendritic cells subsets)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">88</enrollment>
  <condition>Graft vs Host Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>50mg/Kg/day cyclophosphamide (day +3 and +4)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-Thymocyte Globulin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>2.5 mg/Kg/day ATG (Thymoglobuline®) for 2 consecutive days (day -2 and -1)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>GVHD prophylaxis: All patients will receive post-transplant 50mg/Kg/day cyclophosphamide (day +3 and +4) AND cyclosporine-A alone in case of an HLA-sibling donor, or cyclosporine-A and mycophenolate-mofetil in case of an HLA-matched unrelated donor</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cyclophosphamide + cyclosporine-A +/-mycophenolate-mofetil</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti-Thymocyte Globulin</intervention_name>
    <description>GVHD prophylaxis: 2.5 mg/Kg/day ATG (Thymoglobuline®) for 2 consecutive days (day -2 and -1) All patients will receive cyclosporine-A alone in case of an HLA-sibling donor, or cyclosporine-A and mycophenolate-mofetil (MMF) in case of an HLA-matched unrelated donor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-Thymocyte Globulin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Anti-Thymocyte Globulin + cyclosporine-A +/-mycophenolate-mofetil</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conditioning regimen</intervention_name>
    <description>30 mg/m2/day fludarabine for 5 days (day-6 to day-2) 130 mg/m2/day IV busulfan once daily for 2 days (day -4 and -3)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cyclophosphamide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-Thymocyte Globulin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria :

          -  Patients aged between 18 and 65 years

          -  Presence of a hematologic malignancy for which a reduced-intensity conditioning
             allo-SCT is indicated (eligibility criteria for RIC allo-SCT include at least one of
             the following parameters: (i) patient age older than 50 years; (ii) heavily
             pre-treated patients who received an autologous hematopoietic SCT (auto-SCT) or with
             more than 2 lines of chemotherapy before allo-SCT; and (iii) patients with poor
             performance status because of significant medical comorbidities as described by Sorror
             et al.

          -  Karnofsky index ≥ 70%

          -  Availability of a sibling or unrelated stem-cell donor (10/10-HLA matched unrelated
             donor)

          -  Efficient contraceptive method within 1 month for women and 3 months for men after the
             last dose of treatment

          -  Written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Creatinine clearance less than 30 mL/min

          -  Bilirubin or amino-transferases above 3X upper normal limit

          -  Cardiac ejection fraction less than 40%

          -  Pulmonary impairment with &lt;50% lung carbon monoxide diffusing capacity (DLCO)

          -  Known hypersensitivity or contraindication to the use of post-transplant Cy and ATG

          -  Any circumstance that precludes the use of the drugs involved in the protocol

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohamad MOHTY, PU-PH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mohamad MOHTY, PU-PH</last_name>
    <phone>01.49.28.26.20</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>mohamad.mohty@inserm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Florent MALARD, CCU-AH</last_name>
    <phone>01.49.28.26.20</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>malardf@yahoo.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint Antoine Hospital - Hematology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75012</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mohamad MOHTY, PU-PH</last_name>
      <phone>01.49.28.26.20</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>mohamad.mohty@inserm.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Florent MALARD, CCU-AH</last_name>
      <phone>01.49.28.26.20</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>malardf@yahoo.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 18, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 24, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hematopoietic Stem Cell</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Graft vs Host Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Cyclophosphamide</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-Thymocyte Globulin</keyword>
  <keyword>GVHD prophylaxis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antilymphocyte Serum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

