<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02874833</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EXDEP_1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02874833</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exercise for Depression</brief_title>
  <acronym>EXDEP</acronym>
  <official_title>The Efficacy of Exercise in Depressive Episodes of Unipolar Depression and Bipolar Affective Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, University Medical Center, Mainz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomized single-blinded prospective study to evaluate the efficacy of an individualized
      supervised 8-week exercise program in subjects with moderate to severe depressive episodes
      compared to treatment-as-usual
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the efficacy of a supervised and indvidualized 8-week
      exercise program compared to treatment-as-usual in subjects with a moderate or severe
      depressive episode in the context of unipolar depression or bipolar affective disorders.
      Numerous previous studies suggest that exercise may help to improve the symptoms of
      depression. Moreover, exercise was shown to enhance neuroplasticity in adults whereas
      depression results in decreased neuroplasticity. Here, we aim at elucidating whether a newly
      developed supervised, Internet-based, individualized exercise program of the Institute of
      Sports Science and the Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy at the University Mainz is
      more effective in reducing depressive symptoms than treatment-as-usual. Furthermore, this
      study will clarify if severely depressed subjects are able to adhere to an internet-based
      exercise therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of depressive symptoms - Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology - clinical rating-16 (QIDS C-16)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change of Score on the QIDS C-16 after 8 weeks compared to baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of depressive symptoms - Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology - self-report-16 (QIDS SR-16)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change of Score on the QIDS SR-16 after 8 weeks compared to baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence of internet-based concept</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence of internet-based concept using an own questionnaire. Participants respond at the end of every week how they managed their individualized exercise schedule in terms of number of realised training sessions, average heart rate and subjective perceived exertion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Placebo effect of exercise (QIDS-SR16)</measure>
    <time_frame>8-10 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change of Score on the QIDS-SR16 after one week of training to determine placebo effect of exercise.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Placebo effect of exercise (QIDS-C16)</measure>
    <time_frame>8-10 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change of Score on the QIDS-C16 after one week of training to determine placebo effect of exercise.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak oxygen uptake (VO2peak)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change of VO2peak after 8 weeks compared to baseline. Participants will be subjected to a step-wise treadmill test at baseline and after 8 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lactate threshold</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change of lactate threshold using the baseline +1.5 mmol model after 8 weeks compared to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short form 36 (SF36) health survey questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change of score on the SF-36 after 8 weeks compared to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>General self efficacy questionnaire (GSE)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change of score on the GSE after 8 weeks compared to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Clinical Issues (GCI)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change of score on GCI after 8 weeks compared to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating, cell-free DNA (cfDNA)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change of cfDNA concentrations after 8 weeks compared to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression, Unipolar</condition>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experimental arm type will assess whether a newly developed, supervised 8-week individualized, internet-based exercise therapy is effective in reducing depressive symptoms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment as usual. Other form of therapy (e.g. antidepressive medication) will not be affected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>After performance diagnostics, participants will complete an 8-week supervised, individualized exercise program. Training will include up to 3 aerobic training sessions and up to two resistance training units per week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Ability to understand the purpose and risks of the study and provide signed and dated
             informed consent and authorization to use confidential health information in
             accordance with national and local subject privacy regulations.

          2. Aged 18 to 65 years old, inclusive, at the time of informed consent.

          3. Montral Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) &gt; 26 to exclude cognitive impairment.

          4. Apart from a clinical diagnosis of major depression or bipolar affective disorder, the
             subject must be in good health as determined by the Investigator, based on medical
             history and physical examination.

          5. QIDS scores &gt; 5

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Use of antidepressive medications or benzodiazepines at doses that have not been
             stable for at least 6 weeks prior to Screening

          2. Psychotherapy that started less than 8 weeks prior to Screening

          3. Any clinically significant psychiatric illness other than major depression or bipolar
             affective disorder

          4. Transient ischemic attack or stroke or any unexplained loss of consciousness within 1
             year prior to Screening

          5. Any uncontrolled medical or neurological/neurodegenerative condition that, in the
             opinion of the Investigator, might impair treatment compliance and adherence

          6. History of unstable angina, myocardial infarction, chronic heart failure (New York
             Heart Association Class III or IV), or clinically significant conduction abnormalities
             (e.g., unstable atrial fibrillation) within 1 year prior to Screening

          7. Clinically significant 12-lead ECG abnormalities, as determined by the Investigator

          8. Uncontrolled hypertension defined as: average of 3 systolic blood pressure
             [SBP]/diastolic blood pressure [DBP] readings &gt; 165/100 mmHg at Screening

          9. History of malignancy or carcinoma, with the following exceptions:

             i) Subjects with cancers in remission more than 5 years prior to Screening. ii)
             Subjects with a history of excised or treated basal cell or squamous carcinoma. iii)
             Subjects with prostate cancer in situ.

         10. History of seizure within 2 years prior to Screening.

         11. Recent history (within 1 year of Screening) of alcohol or substance abuse as
             determined by the Investigator, a positive urine drug (due to non-prescription drug)
             or alcohol test at Screening

         12. Clinically significant systemic illness or serious infection (e.g., pneumonia,
             septicemia) within 30 days prior to or during Screening

         13. History of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis C virus (HCV) or hepatitis B
             virus (HBV)

         14. Any other medical conditions (e.g., renal disease) that are not stable or controlled,
             or, which in the opinion of the Investigator, could affect the subject's safety or
             interfere with the study assessments

         15. Female subjects who are pregnant or currently breastfeeding

         16. Participation in another study

         17. Other unspecified reasons that, in the opinion of the Investigator or Biogen, make the
             subject unsuitable for enrollment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick Jung, PD Dr. habil.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, University Medical Center, Mainz</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, University Medical Center, Mainz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <state>Rhineland-Palatinate</state>
        <zip>55099</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Sports Medicine, Johannes Gutenberg University, Mainz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <state>Rhineland-Palatinate</state>
        <zip>55099</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cooney GM, Dwan K, Greig CA, Lawlor DA, Rimer J, Waugh FR, McMurdo M, Mead GE. Exercise for depression. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2013 Sep 12;(9):CD004366. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD004366.pub6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24026850</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malykhin NV, Coupland NJ. Hippocampal neuroplasticity in major depressive disorder. Neuroscience. 2015 Nov 19;309:200-13. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2015.04.047. Epub 2015 Apr 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25934030</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Praag H, Shubert T, Zhao C, Gage FH. Exercise enhances learning and hippocampal neurogenesis in aged mice. J Neurosci. 2005 Sep 21;25(38):8680-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16177036</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yau GS, Lee JW, Woo TT, Wong RL, Wong IY. Central Macular Thickness in Children with Myopia, Emmetropia, and Hyperopia: An Optical Coherence Tomography Study. Biomed Res Int. 2015;2015:847694. doi: 10.1155/2015/847694. Epub 2015 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>26167504</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Dr. Dr. Perikles Simon</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor for Sports Medicine MD PHD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Unipolar depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Bipolar affective disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Internet-based intervention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mood Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

