<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02871661</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>State University of Campinas</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02871661</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Physical Therapy as Adjuvant Treatment of Vulvodynia: a Randomized Controled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Physical Therapy as Adjuvant Treatment of Vulvodynia: a Randomized Controled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Campinas, Brazil</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Campinas, Brazil</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION: Vulvodynia (chronic vulvar pain in the absence of clinical findings) has a
      negative impact over quality of life in women with this diagnose. The existing treatments,
      however, are manifold but insufficient. This study aims to verify the effectiveness of
      kinesiotherapy and electrotherapy as adjuvant methods in the treatment of vulvodynia.
      METHODS: A single-blind randomized controlled trial will examine 58 women, divided into three
      treatment arms: use of tricyclic antidepressant alone (hydrochloride Amitriptyline),
      amitriptyline hydrochloride associated with pelvic floor muscle exercises and amitriptyline
      hydrochloride associated with electrotherapy (interferential current). Exclusion criteria
      are: presence of infections or genital cancers, chronic degenerative diseases; younger than
      18 years, neurological disease that jeopardizes the contraction of the muscles of the pelvic
      floor, taking antidepressant drugs that have interaction with amitriptyline hydrochloride and
      being pacemakers use. The parameters analyzed before and after treatment will be: muscle
      volume of the anus elevator and perfusion of the pudendal artery obtained with 3D ultrasound,
      subjective pain in vaginal intercourse (visual analog scale), monthly frequency of vaginal
      intercourse, pain referred within vulvar touch on physical examination (swab test from zero
      to 10) and female sexual function (Female Sexual Function questionnaire - FSFI). There will
      be a follow up of subjective pain in vaginal intercourse and monthly frequency of vaginal
      intercourse obtained by telephone contact with the voluntary on one, six and twelve months
      after the end of interventions. The data will be analyzed using Chi-square test of Pearson,
      Fisher exact and Mann-Whitney. The beginning and end of treatment will be compared using the
      Wilcoxon test (related samples) and McNemar (effect of the intervention), considering
      statistical significance level of 5%. The software used is the statistical analysis software
      (SAS) - Release 9.1, SAS Institute, Cary, North Carolina, USA, 2002-2003 and Statistical
      Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) -Release 17.0.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      GOALS

        1. General Check the effectiveness of physical therapy applied to the pelvic floor muscles
           used as an adjunct to standard treatment (amitriptyline hydrochloride) on the
           improvement of symptoms of vulvodynia.

        2. Specific

      Check and compare in women with vulvodynia before and after being randomly assigned to three
      treatment arms (drug only drug associated with therapeutic exercise or medication associated
      with electrotherapy with CI):

        -  Pain during intercourse and during the swab test obtained by Visual Analogue Scale
           (VAS);

        -  The scores obtained in the questionnaire Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI);

        -  The change in the volume of puborectal, pubococcygeus and iliococcygeal muscles accessed
           through Tridimensional Ultrasound (US3D);

        -  The variation of the perfusion of the pelvic floor muscles by pudendal artery obtained
           by 3D ultrasound;

        -  The effectiveness of therapeutic exercise in the improvement of vulvar pain to test swab
           and sexual intercourse by penetration in women diagnosed with vulvodynia;

        -  The effectiveness of electrical therapy with interferential current in the improvement
           of vulvar pain to test swab and sexual intercourse by penetration of women diagnosed
           with vulvodynia;

        -  Compare the effectiveness of electrical therapy and kinesiotherapy in the improvement of
           vulvar pain;

        -  Compare the effectiveness of physical therapy as an adjunct to standard against standard
           treatment alone.

      SUBJECTS AND METHODS:

        1. Study design:

           clinical trial randomized controlled single-blind. Designed according to the CONSORT
           standards, pending completion of the project after approval by Brazil Platform for final
           implementation, scheduled for July 2016.

        2. Sample size:

           To calculate the sample size, we sought in literature studies addressing the main
           variables to be analyzed in this study (FSFI score after physical therapy intervention
           and medication versus medication, change in visual analog pain scale before and after
           the intervention).

           The study whose design and statistical analysis were closer than we propose in this
           project was used to calculate the sample, and its purpose was to compare in women with
           vulvodynia, the improvement in pain using the VAS pain and sexual function index using
           the FSFI after undergoing sessions of transcutaneous electrical stimulation (TENS) (65).

           Assuming type II alpha error probability equal to 0.05 and study of power equal to 80%,
           and considering the average VAS score of 8 (± 3.4) and 2.2 (± 6.1), the sample size
           calculation estimated using the Small software Stata 13.1 was n = 16 for each group,
           totaling n = 48. However, as a study with follow-up two months and assuming loss of
           follow-up of 20% of the total number of the sample, we assume a sampling size n = 58.

        3. Variables and concepts:

      3.1 Independent Variables Vulvodynia Characterized by present or absent, it is diagnosed by
      the presence of vulvar pain sexual penetration or touch gynecological self-reported, burning
      to light touch in the lobby (swab test [13]) and erythema. It can be classified as localized
      or generalized.

      3.2 Dependent Variables Muscle thickness - Measure cross the levator ani muscle given in
      millimeters, obtained by 3D US in three situations: rest, maximum voluntary contraction and
      Valsalva; Perfusion pudendal artery - blood flow of the pudendal artery, given in millimeters
      per square centimeters (mm / cm2) obtained by 3D US.

      Pain referred to the swab test - referred pain to perform the swab test, playing with a swab
      certain points of the vulvar vestibule, pointed using the visual analog scale (VAS) ranging
      from zero to 10, where ten is the highest grade concerning the higher pain threshold.

      Pain said the vaginal penetration - mean referred pain during sexual intercourse with vaginal
      penetration, pointed using the visual analog scale (VAS) ranging from zero to 10, where ten
      is the maximum note to higher pain threshold.

      FSFI - female sexual function index, as measured by the score obtained by the
      self-administered questionnaire FSFI (Female Sexual Function Index), which proposes to
      evaluate women's sexual response in the areas: desire, arousal, vaginal lubrication, orgasm,
      sexual satisfaction and pain. Assesses the relative strength of each field of female sexual
      response and transform subjective measures in objective, quantifiable and analyzable data.
      Applied in therapeutic exercise before and after the program applied to the pelvic floor.

      3.3 Control variables BMI: body mass index, obtained by dividing weight in kilograms by
      height in meters squared. Categorized to assess the degree of obesity of an individual, it is
      considered underweight when BMI &lt;20; ideal weight BMI = 20 to 25; overweight BMI = 26 to 30;
      moderate obesity BMI = 31 to 35; severe obesity BMI = 36 to 40; Morbid obesity BMI = 41 to
      50; super obesity BMI&gt; 50.

      Gestation: number of times the respondent became pregnant, including abortions until the day
      of the interview (self reported); Delivery type: delivery route number taken by the
      respondent to the day of the interview, self reported, classified as: C-section; Forceps,
      vaginal; Frequency of sex: number of sexual contacts per month in the last six months (self
      reported); Number of sexual partners: number of partners in the last six months (self
      reported); Frequency of physical activity: number of times a week practicing physical
      activity on average in the last six months (self reported); Type of physical activity: type
      of physical activity carried out in the last six months (self reported) classified as: (I)
      strengthening (weight training, pilates class, functional training), (II) aerobic (walking,
      running, swimming, cycling, wrestling) and / or (III) stretching (stretching classes, yoga);
      (IV) sedentary.

      Symptoms or pelvic floor dysfunction signs: self reported complaint by the patient in
      relation to the perineum such as dyspareunia, dysuria, redness, cracking, itching, vaginal
      flatus, urinary incontinence, fecal incontinence.

      Treatment for vulvodynia used before kinesiotherapy: techniques and previously tested
      therapies to reduce the nuisance caused by vulvodynia.

      Drug name, time and amount of drugs administered during the period of participation in the
      survey.

      3.4 Descriptive Variables Age: elapsed time in years from the date of birth and date of the
      first interview, said the participant. Given in ordinal numbers; Education: number of years
      of study referred to by the subject. Given in ordinal numbers; Marital status: marital status
      of the subject at the time of the study. Categorized in (I) with a steady partner and (II)
      without a professional occupation; Skin color: skin color referred to by the subject.
      Categorized into (I) White and (II) not white; Smoking: current smoking habit, self reported
      by the interviewee, considering the options (I) yes or (II) not; Contraceptive methods that
      are used by women in order to prevent conception, informed by the participant, categorized
      into (I) male or female condom, (II) oral hormonal pill, (III) injectable hormonal
      contraceptive (IV) ligation of the fallopian tubes (V) or levonorgestrel copper intrauterine
      device (VI) rhythm, (VII) withdrawal, (VIII) and vasectomy (IX) other;

      Subject Selection

      Women who attend the outpatient genital infections and sexuality and are diagnosed with
      vulvodynia will be invited to participate in this study. Will also be distributed informative
      pamphlets on chronic vulvar pain and the methodology of this research in specialized clinics
      vulvodynia, vulvodynia groups on the Internet and clinics where researchers involved in this
      study attend. Women who agree to participate in the study aged over 18 years old will be
      interviewed in order to meet the criteria for inclusion in the study (Appendix I). The
      evaluation will be scheduled in the center of comprehensive care to women's health of Unicamp
      (CAISM) in physiotherapy clinic to perform the steps of the research participation.

      The volunteers will be randomized through a computer program in www.randomizer.org obtained
      in three treatment arms: only amitriptyline, amitriptyline combined with kinesiotherapy
      applied to the pelvic floor and electrical therapy associated with the amitriptyline.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Scale Measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Eight weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Effectiveness of the treatment for vulvodynia will be accessed through pain score scale from zero to ten, compared from day zero of treatment to day eight</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Female Sexual Index Function Improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>Eight weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Will be accessed through FSIF (Female Sexual Index Function questionnaire) score that goes from 2 to 36, compared from day zero of treatment to day eight, which indicates sexual disfunction pointed by scores below 26,55.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3D Ultrasound measurement of Pelvic Floor Muscle thickness and pudendal artery flow</measure>
    <time_frame>Eight weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A 3D Ultrassound will be used to access these outcomes and compare changes from day zero to day eight of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Interleukin 1-B Vaginal Inflammatory response</measure>
    <time_frame>Eight weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Vaginal fluid collected will be analysed in laboratory to access possible inflammatory response of vulva and vagina of women with vulvodynia obtained by comparing quantitatively interleukin 1-B presente before and after treatment</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">58</enrollment>
  <condition>Vulvodynia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amitriptyline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be treated with medication alone (amitriptyline hydrochloride, 25 mg) for chronic vulvar pain (vulvodynia).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amitriptyline plus kinesiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be treated with medication (amitriptyline hydrochloride, 25 mg) plus pelvic floor exercises such as Kegel contractions and stretching of pelvic floor muscles with patients own hands.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amitriptyline plus IC (Quark)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be treated with medication (amitriptyline hydrochloride, 25 mg) plus electrical stimulation with Interferential Current (manufacturer: Quark Medical; Model: Dualpex 961 - program number 42): two electrodes put into the perineal surface area emitting interferential current, once a week for twenty minutes each, for eight weeks long.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amitriptyline</intervention_name>
    <description>Volunteers will take 25 milligrams of this medication every day from their enrollment until completing eight weeks long.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amitriptyline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Amitriptyline plus kinesiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Amitriptyline plus IC (Quark)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Amitriptyline hydrochloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Kinesiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Volunteers will be taught to contract their pelvic floor muscles right before stretching it, following a home protocol, every day for eight weeks long.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amitriptyline plus kinesiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kegel exercises plus muscle stretch</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IC (Quark)</intervention_name>
    <description>Volunteers will visit physical therapy clinic once a week to receive twenty minutes of electrical stimulation with Interferential Current (Duapex 961 of Quark Medical manufacturer) in their perineal area, for eight weeks long.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amitriptyline plus IC (Quark)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>interferential current, Dualpex 961 - Quark</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Having had previous vaginal penetration

          -  Accept to perform kinesiotherapy sessions or electrical therapy once a week for two
             months

          -  Accept using medication (Amitriptyline hydrochloride) during the treatment period

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Being pregnant

          -  Using drugs that negatively interfere with the hydrochloride Amtriptilina (ANNEX II)

          -  Having cognitive or literacy difficulties that prevent the understanding of self
             answered questionnaires such Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI).

          -  Refusing to sign the Informed Consent

          -  Neuromuscular disorders that interfere on the proper contraction of the pelvic floor
             muscles

          -  Having decompensated chronic degenerative diseases (tuberculosis, AIDS, hepatitis,
             diabetes, etc.)

          -  Using pacemaker or having cardiac arrhythmia

          -  Taking antidepressant monoamine oxidase inhibitor (MAOI) or Ayahuasca tea
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paulo C Giraldo, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Campinas, Brazil</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcela G Bardin, PT, Master</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Campinas, Brazil</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marcela G Bardin, Master</last_name>
    <phone>5519981548688</phone>
    <email>mabardin@yahoo.com.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unicamp</name>
      <address>
        <city>Campinas</city>
        <state>Sao Paulo</state>
        <zip>13083-970</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marcela G Bardin, Master</last_name>
      <phone>5519981548688</phone>
      <email>mabardin@yahoo.co.br</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Paulo c Giraldo, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>5519996156466</phone>
      <email>paulocesargiraldo@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Goldstein AT, Pukall CF, Brown C, Bergeron S, Stein A, Kellogg-Spadt S. Vulvodynia: Assessment and Treatment. J Sex Med. 2016 Apr;13(4):572-90. doi: 10.1016/j.jsxm.2016.01.020. Epub 2016 Mar 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27045258</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Reed BD, Caron AM, Gorenflo DW, Haefner HK. Treatment of vulvodynia with tricyclic antidepressants: efficacy and associated factors. J Low Genit Tract Dis. 2006 Oct;10(4):245-51.</citation>
    <PMID>17012991</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Corrêa JB, Costa LO, Oliveira NT, Lima WP, Sluka KA, Liebano RE. Effects of the carrier frequency of interferential current on pain modulation and central hypersensitivity in people with chronic nonspecific low back pain: A randomized placebo-controlled trial. Eur J Pain. 2016 Nov;20(10):1653-1666. doi: 10.1002/ejp.889. Epub 2016 May 6.</citation>
    <PMID>27150263</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gentilcore-Saulnier E, McLean L, Goldfinger C, Pukall CF, Chamberlain S. Pelvic floor muscle assessment outcomes in women with and without provoked vestibulodynia and the impact of a physical therapy program. J Sex Med. 2010 Feb;7(2 Pt 2):1003-22. doi: 10.1111/j.1743-6109.2009.01642.x. Epub 2010 Jan 6.</citation>
    <PMID>20059663</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dionisi B, Anglana F, Inghirami P, Lippa P, Senatori R. [Use of transcutaneous electrical stimulation and biofeedback for the treatment of vulvodynia (vulvar vestibular syndrome): result of 3 years of experience]. Minerva Ginecol. 2008 Dec;60(6):485-91. Italian.</citation>
    <PMID>18981976</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 15, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 15, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 15, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Campinas, Brazil</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marcela Grigol Bardin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Master in Obstetrics and Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>vulvodynia</keyword>
  <keyword>pelvic floor muscles</keyword>
  <keyword>kinesiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>electrical therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>physical therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>amitriptyline</keyword>
  <keyword>female sexual dysfunction.</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vulvodynia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amitriptyline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amitriptyline, perphenazine drug combination</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

