<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02871791</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-177</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02871791</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Palbociclib With Everolimus + Exemestane In BC</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1b/2a Study Of Palbociclib In Combination With Everolimus And Exemestane In Postmenopausal Women With Estrogen Receptor Positive and HER2 Negative Metastatic Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is studying a combination of targeted therapy and hormonal therapy as a
      possible treatment for breast cancer that has spread to other places in the body and is
      hormone receptor positive (HR+) and HER2-negative.

      The names of the study interventions involved in this study are:

        -  Palbociclib

        -  Everolimus

        -  Exemestane
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I/II clinical trial. The Phase I portion of this clinical trial tests the
      safety of an investigational intervention and also tries to define the appropriate dose of
      the investigational intervention to use for further studies. The Phase II portion of the
      study tests the safety and effectiveness of an investigational intervention to learn whether
      the intervention works in treating a specific disease. &quot;Investigational&quot; means that the
      intervention is being studied.

      The FDA (the U.S. Food and Drug Administration) has not approved the combination of
      Palbociclib, Everolimus, and Exemestane as a treatment for any disease.

      This is the first time that the combination of Palbociclib, Everolimus, and Exemestane will
      be given to humans.

      Palbociclib is a drug that may stop cancer cells from growing. Palbociclib blocks activity of
      two closely related enzymes (proteins that help chemical reactions occur in the body), called
      Cyclin D Kinases 4 and 6 (CDK 4/6). These proteins are part of a pathway, or a sequence of
      steps, which is known to regulate cell growth. Laboratory testing has suggested Palbociclib
      may stop the growth of HR+ breast cancer.

      Everolimus is a type of drug called an mTORinhibitor that treats breast cancer by preventing
      the cells from multiplying by inhibiting the pathway, or a sequence of steps, known to
      regulate cell reproduction. Everolimus also may stop the growth of cancer cells by decreasing
      blood supply to the cancer cells.

      Exemestane is an anti-hormone therapy that prevents breast cancer cell growth by blocking
      estrogen receptor stimulation. Premenopausal women will also receive an injection drug called
      an LHRH (luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone) agonist to shut down ovary function. It is
      standard of care for people with breast cancer, specifically with HR+ breast cancer, to take
      anti-hormone therapy.

      The combination of everolimus and exemestane is FDA approved to treat this type of breast
      cancer.

      The purpose of the Phase I portion of this research study is to determine a safe and
      tolerable dose of the combination of Palbociclib, Everolimus, and Exemestane for participants
      with ER-positive, HER2-negative advanced breast cancer.

      The purpose of the Phase II portion of this research study is to determine whether the
      combination of Palbociclib, Everolimus, and Exemestane is an effective treatment for
      participants with ER-positive, HER2-negative advanced breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 24, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with Dose-Limiting Toxicities (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 28 Days (1 cycle)</time_frame>
    <description>first cycle DLTs in order to determine maximum tolerated dose of the combination of palbociclib, everolimus and exemestane.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Benefit Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Response will be assessed among participants eligible for the phase IIa part of the study who received at least one dose of the study drugs at the MTD/RP2D and have measurable disease at screening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Response will be assessed among participants eligible for the phase IIa part of the study who received at least one dose of the study drugs at the MTD/RP2D and have measurable disease at screening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Response will be assessed among participants eligible for the phase IIa part of the study who received at least one dose of the study drugs at the MTD/RP2D and have measurable disease at screening.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <description>PFS will be described using the method of Kaplan-Meier, and it will be presented with a 95% confidence interval. Participants alive without disease progression are censored at the date of last disease evaluation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Epidermal Growth Factor 2 Negative Carcinoma of Breast</condition>
  <condition>Hormone Receptor (HR)-Positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Palbociclib, Everolimus, Exemestane</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Palbociclib will be administered orally, once daily for 21 consecutive days followed by a 7-day rest (28-day cycle)
Everolimus will be administered orally, once daily on a 28 day schedule
Exemestane will be administered orally, once daily on a 28 day schedule
Participants will be treated with increasing/decreasing doses of palbociclib and everolimus to establish MTD(s)/RP2D for both drugs in the setting of the triple combination of palbociclib, everolimus and exemestane</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Palbociclib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Palbociclib, Everolimus, Exemestane</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Everolimus</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Palbociclib, Everolimus, Exemestane</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exemestane</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Palbociclib, Everolimus, Exemestane</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must meet the following criteria on screening examination to be eligible
             to participate in the study. Laboratory tests required for eligibility must be
             completed within 14 days prior to the date of registration. Diagnostic tests, such as
             MRIs and CT scans, must be performed within 30 days of registration and baseline
             measurements must be documented within 14 days of the date of registration.

          -  Participants with histologically or cytologically confirmed hormone receptor
             (HR)-positive, Her2-negative metastatic breast cancer. Central confirmation of HR
             positivity is not required

          -  Postmenopausal women as defined as:

               -  Age &gt;60 years

                  --- or

               -  Age &gt;45 with intact uterus and amenorrhea for ≥ 12 consecutive months or Follicle
                  stimulating hormone (FSH) levels within postmenopausal range according to the
                  ranges established by the testing facility

                  --- or

               -  Premenopausal women who have been on a GnRH agonist for at least 6 weeks prior to
                  study entry. Women in this group MUST remain on the GnRH agonist for the duration
                  of protocol treatment

                  --- or

               -  Status post bilateral oophorectomy, after adequate healing post surgery;

          -  Men are eligible, as long as on a GnRH agonist for at least 6 weeks prior to study
             entry. Men MUST remain on the GnRH agonist for the duration of protocol treatment.

          -  Participants must have measurable disease as per RECIST 1.1.

          -  Prior Treatment Specifics:

               -  Participants must have radiological or objective evidence of progression to a
                  CDK4/6 inhibitor regimen in the metastatic setting AND relapse/progression on an
                  NSAI (defined as either relapsed ≤ 12 months after completing adjuvant NSAI or
                  progressed through an NSAI for metastatic or locally advanced breast cancer)

               -  Participants may have received any number of previous endocrine/hormonal lines of
                  therapy in the metastatic setting, as long none of them were exemestane-based and
                  the last dose is ≥ 14 days prior to registration;

               -  Participants may have received up to one prior chemotherapy line for advanced
                  breast cancer as long as the last dose is ≥ 21 days prior to registration;

               -  Participants may have received prior biologic treatments or investigational drugs
                  as long as the last dose is ≥ 21 days prior to registration;

               -  Participants may have received radiotherapy for palliative purposes but must not
                  be experiencing &gt; grade 1 treatment related toxicities and have completed
                  treatment ≥ 14 days prior to registration

          -  Age ≥18 years. Age restriction applies given that no dosing or adverse event data are
             currently available on the use of palbociclib or exemestane in participants &lt;18 years
             of age.

          -  ECOG performance status ≤2 (Karnofsky ≥60%, see Appendix A)

          -  For participants enrolling the phase IIa part of the study, accessible tumor lesion(s)
             for the purpose of research biopsy and willingness to undergo a research biopsy before
             treatment initiation and at the time of disease progression, as well as a single
             research blood sample before initiation of therapy. Participants who undergo an
             attempted on-treatment research biopsy and in whom inadequate tissue is obtained are
             still eligible to receive protocol therapy. They will not be required to undergo a
             repeat research biopsy attempt.

          -  For participants enrolling the phase IIa part of the study, willingness to provide
             archival tumor samples when available.

          -  Participants must have normal organ and marrow function, as defined below:

               -  absolute neutrophil count ≥1,5x109/L

               -  platelets ≥100 x109/L

               -  total hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL (which may be post transfusion)

               -  total bilirubin ≤1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal

               -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) ≤2.5 × institutional upper limit of normal or ≤5 ×
                  institutional upper limit of normal for participants with liver metastization

               -  creatinine ≤1.5 x above institutional normal or ≥ 60 ml/min/1.73m2 for subjects
                  with creatinine levels above institutional normal.

               -  baseline QTc &lt; 500 ms

               -  fasting plasma glucose &lt;140 mg/dL / 7.8 mmol/L

          -  The effects of the combination of palbociclib, everolimus and exemestane on the
             developing human fetus are unknown. Given that women in this study will be
             post-menopausal by eligibility criteria (de facto or pharmacologically induced), it is
             expected that there will be no women of child-bearing potential in this study. If, for
             any reason, a woman should become pregnant or suspect that she is pregnant while
             participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately. Of
             note, premenopausal women and men are only eligible if they have been on a GnRH
             agonist for at least 6 weeks prior to study entry. These participants MUST remain on
             the GnRH agonist for the duration of protocol treatment. Such participants should be
             counseled prior to study entry that GnRH agonists alone may not be adequate
             contraception and that adequate contraception (barrier method of birth control;
             abstinence) should be employed for the duration of study participation.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who have demonstrated intolerance to 125mg of Palbociclib are ineligible
             for the Phase I portion.

          -  Participants who are receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Participants who have received previous treatment with an mTOR inhibitor or
             exemestane.

          -  Participants with a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition to palbociclib, everolimus or exemestane.

          -  Participants with known brain metastases may be enrolled in this study if radiation
             therapy and/or surgery have been completed with a minimum of 3 months of stable
             disease demonstrated on serial evaluation by CT (with contrast enhancement) or MRI.
             Such participants must no longer require treatment with corticosteroids or enzyme
             inducing anti-epileptic medications for their CNS disease.

          -  Participants with bilateral diffuse lymphangitic carcinomatosis.

          -  Participants with significant symptomatic deterioration of lung function. If
             clinically indicated, pulmonary function tests including measures of predicted lung
             volumes, DLco, O2 saturation at rest on room air should be considered to exclude
             restrictive pulmonary disease, pneumonitis or pulmonary infiltrates.

          -  Evidence of current pneumonitis

          -  Subjects with organ allograft requiring immunosuppression.

          -  Participants with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to:

               -  Ongoing or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable
                  angina pectoris, symptomatic cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social
                  situations that would limit compliance with study requirements. Ability to comply
                  with study requirements is to be assessed by each investigator at the time of
                  screening for study participation;

               -  Impairment of gastrointestinal function or who have gastrointestinal disease that
                  may significantly alter the absorption of study drugs (e.g., ulcerative disease,
                  uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhea or malabsorption syndrome).

          -  Participants receiving any medications or substances that are moderate or strong
             inhibitors or inducers of CYP3A within 7 days of registration. Lists including
             medications and substances known or with the potential to interact with the CYP3A
             isoenzymes are provided in Appendix B, and can also be found within Sections 2.4.1.2
             and 5.8. Because the lists of these agents are constantly changing, it is important to
             regularly consult a frequently-updated list such as:
             http://medicine.iupui.edu/clinpharm/ddis/table.aspx; medical reference texts such as
             the Physicians' Desk Reference may also provide this information. As part of the
             enrollment/informed consent procedures, the participant will be counseled on the risk
             of interactions with other agents, and what to do if new medications need to be
             prescribed or if the participant is considering a new over-the-counter medicine or
             herbal product.

          -  Proton pump inhibitors(PPI) may be taken while on study, however it is recommended
             that the PPI is taken 12 hours from the time of palbociclib administration. If needed,
             alternative antacid therapies may be used including H2-receptor antagonists and
             locally acting antacids. H2-receptor antagonists should be administered with a
             staggered dosing regimen (twice daily). The dosing of palbociclib should occur at
             least 10 hours after H2-receptor antagonist evening dose and 2 hours before the
             H2-receptor antagonist morning dose.

          -  Pregnant women are excluded.

          -  Individuals with a history of a different malignancy are ineligible except for the
             following circumstances: a) if they have been disease-free for at least 5 years and
             are deemed by the investigator to be at low risk for recurrence of that malignancy; b)
             if diagnosed with the following cancers and treated within the past 5 years: ductal
             carcinoma in situ of the breast, cervical cancer in situ, and basal cell or squamous
             cell carcinoma of the skin.

          -  Participants known to be HIV-positive on combination antiretroviral therapy are
             ineligible because of the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions with palbociclib
             and everolimus. In addition, these individuals are at increased risk of lethal
             infections when treated with marrow-suppressive therapy. Appropriate studies will be
             undertaken in participants receiving combination antiretroviral therapy when
             indicated. Screening for HIV infection at baseline is not required.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sara Tolaney, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sara Tolaney, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-632-2335</phone>
    <email>STOLANEY@PARTNERS.ORG</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sara Tolaney, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-2335</phone>
      <email>stolaney@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sara Tolaney, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 15, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sara Tolaney</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Her2-negative metastatic breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormone receptor (HR)-positive breast cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Palbociclib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Exemestane</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

