<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02878538</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P30AG044271</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HSC20160395H</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02878538</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot of the Feasibility of Using the Iron-Chelator Deferiprone on Mild Cognitive Impairment</brief_title>
  <official_title>An N of One Clinical Trial to Pilot the Feasibility of Using the Iron-Chelator Deferiprone on Mild Cognitive Impairment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators propose to conduct a series of N of One (No1) single blinded clinical
      trials to pilot the feasibility of using the iron-chelator deferiprone on Mild Cognitive
      Impairment (MCI). Chelation therapy has previously been reported to slow the rate of
      cognitive decline in Alzheimer's Disease (AD) by 50% in a single human randomized clinical
      trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Iron chelation's mechanism of action (MOA) in Alzheimer's disease (AD) is uncertain.
      Potential MOA include reversal of aluminum (AL) toxicity, the prevention of a-beta
      aggregation, β-amyloid disaggregation, and the obstruction of microbacterial and viral
      parasitism. The latter mechanism involves augmentation of innate immunity, and disruption of
      microbacterial iron metabolism. Infectious models of AD's pathophysiology have been recently
      proposed. Iron blocks toll-like receptor (TLR) initiated anti-microbial actions mediated via
      gamma-interferon (IFN-γ) tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-alpha), interleukin-6 (IL-6), and
      interleukin-10 (IL-10). These biomarkers are of interest because they have also been
      associated with our novel latent dementia phenotype (i.e., &quot;d&quot; for &quot;dementia&quot;) in the Texas
      Alzheimer's Research and Care Consortium (TARCC). &quot;d&quot; is a continuous measure of dementia
      severity that can be constructed from any cognitive battery that also includes a measure of
      Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (IADL). Serum biomarkers might &quot;trigger&quot; dementing
      processes without participating in their later stages. Thus, the investigators have
      indications as to who might benefit from iron-chelation and when the intervention might be
      best applied. This knowledge may help them detect an effect of deferiprone on prospective
      change in &quot;d&quot; and even on MCI conversion in TARCC NHW (Non Hispanic White) subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study was withdrawn before IRB approval
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of deferiprone therapy on &quot;d&quot; scores in Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using N of 1 trial design in small number of MCI cases to compare within subject response to placebo and deferiprone in a A1-A-A1 design</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Explore deferiprone's longitudinal effect on &quot;d&quot; and dementia conversion</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>We want to survey the effect of deferiprone on &quot;d&quot; to see If serum biomarkers trigger dementing processes in non Hispanic whites and if deferiprone exposure in MCI may terminate progression and conversion to dementia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>deferiprone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Deferiprone will be administered three times a day (25mg/kg). Total dose per day will depend on participants' body weight for one, three month block.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Phase</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo tablets with inactive substance will be used. Total number of placebo tablets will be equivalent to the active tablets administered depending on participants' body weight for two, three month blocks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deferiprone</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will then begin an experimental No1 design: placebo-deferiprone-placebo. Study drug will be administered in three 3 month blocks. All subjects will receive 30 days of active study drug. The placebo-deferiprone contrast compares placebo to active drug initiation. The deferiprone-placebo contrast tests active drug withdrawal. All will be given placebo in months 1-3, and 6-12. This will allow the investigators to examine active drug exposure on d score up to one year and prospective time to MCI conversion. Dosing: Participants will be treated 25 mg/kg po tid (75mg /kg /d total) The dose will be rounded by the prescriber to the nearest 250 mg (half-tablet).</description>
    <arm_group_label>deferiprone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ferriprox, ATC Code V03AC02</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo phase</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo tablets with inactive substance will be provided to subjects for two, 3 month blocks during the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Phase</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. MA (Mexican Americans) or NHW TARCC participants with competent informants;

          2. TARCC diagnosis of &quot;MCI&quot; (any subtype);

          3. Incident MCI or conversion to MCI from control in the two previous TARCC waves;

          4. 65-80 yrs of age;

          5. Non-institutionalized level of care;

          6. Capacity to give informed consent

          7. GDS (Geriatric Depression Screen) score (15 item) ≤ 6;

          8. TARCC MMSE (Mini-Mental State Examination) ≥ 26 /30;

          9. HIS (Hachinski Ischemic Scale) ≤ 05/15;

         10. Most recent TARCC dEQ-score = 0 ± 0.25.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. A clinical diagnosis of &quot;Diabetes Mellitus&quot; and current treatment with insulin;

          2. A self-reported diagnosis of &quot;Major Depression&quot; (treatment with &quot;antidepressants&quot; not
             exclusionary);

          3. A history of psychosis, including visual hallucinations;

          4. History or treatment for Parkinson's, or tremor, or Rapid Eye Movement (REM) behavior
             disorder;

          5. History or treatment for atrial fibrillation;

          6. Treatment for cancer in the last 5 years (exc. skin cancers);

          7. Major surgery in the last year;

          8. History of craniotomy;

          9. Serum Ferritin &lt; 500mcg/ml, Hgb &lt; 14g/dl♂ /12g/dl♀,, HCT &lt; 45%♂ /40%♀, recent blood
             transfusion (last 5 years), FeSO4 supplementation, erythromycin therapy;

         10. ANC (absolute neutrophil count) &lt; 500 cells/µL, platelet count &lt; 150 × 106 /ml;

         11. Treatment with anti-convulsants, mood stabilizers, neuroleptics, opiates, muscle
             relaxants, systemic steroids, or AD-indicated agents.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donald R Royall, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dean Kellogg, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Health Science Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Becerril-Ortega J, Bordji K, Fréret T, Rush T, Buisson A. Iron overload accelerates neuronal amyloid-β production and cognitive impairment in transgenic mice model of Alzheimer's disease. Neurobiol Aging. 2014 Oct;35(10):2288-301. doi: 10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2014.04.019. Epub 2014 May 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24863668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Chiara G, Marcocci ME, Sgarbanti R, Civitelli L, Ripoli C, Piacentini R, Garaci E, Grassi C, Palamara AT. Infectious agents and neurodegeneration. Mol Neurobiol. 2012 Dec;46(3):614-38. doi: 10.1007/s12035-012-8320-7. Epub 2012 Aug 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22899188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fine JM, Renner DB, Forsberg AC, Cameron RA, Galick BT, Le C, Conway PM, Stroebel BM, Frey WH 2nd, Hanson LR. Intranasal deferoxamine engages multiple pathways to decrease memory loss in the APP/PS1 model of amyloid accumulation. Neurosci Lett. 2015 Jan 1;584:362-7. doi: 10.1016/j.neulet.2014.11.013. Epub 2014 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25445365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gavett BE, Vudy V, Jeffrey M, John SE, Gurnani AS, Adams JW. The δ latent dementia phenotype in the uniform data set: Cross-validation and extension. Neuropsychology. 2015 May;29(3):344-52. doi: 10.1037/neu0000128. Epub 2014 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>25151112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hughes CP, Berg L, Danziger WL, Coben LA, Martin RL. A new clinical scale for the staging of dementia. Br J Psychiatry. 1982 Jun;140:566-72.</citation>
    <PMID>7104545</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nairz M, Schroll A, Sonnweber T, Weiss G. The struggle for iron - a metal at the host-pathogen interface. Cell Microbiol. 2010 Dec;12(12):1691-702. doi: 10.1111/j.1462-5822.2010.01529.x. Epub 2010 Oct 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20964797</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peters DG, Connor JR, Meadowcroft MD. The relationship between iron dyshomeostasis and amyloidogenesis in Alzheimer's disease: Two sides of the same coin. Neurobiol Dis. 2015 Sep;81:49-65. doi: 10.1016/j.nbd.2015.08.007. Epub 2015 Aug 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26303889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Royall DR, Palmer RF, Markides KS. Exportation and Validation of Latent Constructs for Dementia Case Finding in a Mexican American Population-based Cohort. J Gerontol B Psychol Sci Soc Sci. 2017 Oct 1;72(6):947-955. doi: 10.1093/geronb/gbw004.</citation>
    <PMID>26968639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Royall DR, Palmer RF; Texas Alzheimer’s Research and Care. Validation of a latent construct for dementia case-finding in Mexican-Americans. J Alzheimers Dis. 2013;37(1):89-97. doi: 10.3233/JAD-130353.</citation>
    <PMID>23800829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Royall DR, Palmer RF. Ethnicity moderates dementia's biomarkers. J Alzheimers Dis. 2015;43(1):275-87. doi: 10.3233/JAD-140264.</citation>
    <PMID>25079802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Royall DR, Palmer RF. Thrombopoietin is associated with δ's intercept, and only in Non-Hispanic Whites. Alzheimers Dement (Amst). 2016 Feb 26;3:35-42. doi: 10.1016/j.dadm.2016.02.003. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27239547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Royall DR, Palmer RF, O'Bryant SE; Texas Alzheimer’s Research and Care Consortium. Validation of a latent variable representing the dementing process. J Alzheimers Dis. 2012;30(3):639-49. doi: 10.3233/JAD-2012-120055.</citation>
    <PMID>22451315</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Salkovic-Petrisic M, Knezovic A, Osmanovic-Barilar J, Smailovic U, Trkulja V, Riederer P, Amit T, Mandel S, Youdim MB. Multi-target iron-chelators improve memory loss in a rat model of sporadic Alzheimer's disease. Life Sci. 2015 Sep 1;136:108-19. doi: 10.1016/j.lfs.2015.06.026. Epub 2015 Jul 6.</citation>
    <PMID>26159898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 25, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Deferiprone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chelating Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

