<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02870036</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GV-LP-102</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02870036</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Preliminary Efficacy and Pharmacokinetics of Simmitecan Monotherapy and Combination in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ShangHai HaiHe Pharmaceutical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ShangHai HaiHe Pharmaceutical</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the safety, tolerability, preliminary efficacy and pharmacokinetics of
      Simmitecan in patients with advanced solid tumors and Simmitecan, 5-fluorouracil and
      Leucovorin Calcium,thalidomide in patients with advanced solid tumor or advanced/metastatic
      colorectal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax (maximum plasma concentration)</measure>
    <time_frame>before administration (within 5 minutes before administration), 45 and 90 minutes after the start of the infusion of Simmitecan and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48 and 72 hours after the completion of infusion of Simmitecan</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax (time to maximum plasma concentration)</measure>
    <time_frame>before administration (within 5 minutes before administration), 45 and 90 minutes after the start of the infusion of Simmitecan and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48 and 72 hours after the completion of infusion of Simmitecan</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC (area under the plasma concentration-time curve)</measure>
    <time_frame>before administration (within 5 minutes before administration), 45 and 90 minutes after the start of the infusion of Simmitecan and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48 and 72 hours after the completion of infusion of Simmitecan</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>T½</measure>
    <time_frame>before administration (within 5 minutes before administration), 45 and 90 minutes after the start of the infusion of Simmitecan and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48 and 72 hours after the completion of infusion of Simmitecan</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CL (systemic clearance)</measure>
    <time_frame>before administration (within 5 minutes before administration), 45 and 90 minutes after the start of the infusion of Simmitecan and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48 and 72 hours after the completion of infusion of Simmitecan</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vz (apparent volume of distribution)</measure>
    <time_frame>before administration (within 5 minutes before administration), 45 and 90 minutes after the start of the infusion of Simmitecan and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48 and 72 hours after the completion of infusion of Simmitecan</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (AE)</measure>
    <time_frame>AEs will be classified by type, incidence, severity (graded per NCI-CTCAE [version 4.03]), time to onset, seriousness and relationship</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Imaging examination will be performed for tumor assessment every 6 weeks (±7 days) from the first dose of Simmitecan until PD, intolerable toxicity, withdrawal of consent or death.</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor will be evaluated according to RECIST-1.1. CT or MRI can be used for tumor imaging at the investigator's discretion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Imaging examination will be performed for tumor assessment every 6 weeks (±7 days) from the first dose of Simmitecan until PD, intolerable toxicity, withdrawal of consent or death.</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor will be evaluated according to RECIST-1.1. CT or MRI can be used for tumor imaging at the investigator's discretion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CBR (clinical benefit rate)</measure>
    <time_frame>Imaging examination will be performed for tumor assessment every 6 weeks (±7 days) from the first dose of Simmitecan until PD, intolerable toxicity, withdrawal of consent or death.</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor will be evaluated according to RECIST-1.1. CT or MRI can be used for tumor imaging at the investigator's discretion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DCR (disease control rate)</measure>
    <time_frame>Imaging examination will be performed for tumor assessment every 6 weeks (±7 days) from the first dose of Simmitecan until PD, intolerable toxicity, withdrawal of consent or death.</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor will be evaluated according to RECIST-1.1. CT or MRI can be used for tumor imaging at the investigator's discretion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OS (overall survival)</measure>
    <time_frame>Imaging examination will be performed for tumor assessment every 6 weeks (±7 days) from the first dose of Simmitecan until PD, intolerable toxicity, withdrawal of consent or death.</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor will be evaluated according to RECIST-1.1. CT or MRI can be used for tumor imaging at the investigator's discretion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>accumulative excretion rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Accumulative excretion rate within 0-72 h after the first administration of Simmitecan.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">243</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Advanced/Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pharmacokinetic data investigation of Simmitecan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To further determine the pharmacokinetic (PK) characteristics of Simmitecan monotherapy in patients with advanced solid tumors</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose escalation study of Simmitecan combined therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of Simmitecan combined with 5-fluorouracil/Leucovorin Calcium in patients with advanced solid tumor</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose extension study of Simmitecan monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To preliminarily evaluate the anti-tumor activity of Simmitecan monotherapy in patients with advanced solid tumors, and to determine the recommended phase II dose (RP2D)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose extension study of Simmitecan combined Thalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To preliminarily evaluate the anti-tumor activity of Simmitecan combined with 5-fluorouracil/Leucovorin Calcium in patients with advanced/metastatic colorectal cancer (CRC), and to determine RP2D</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose escalation&amp;extension Simmitecan combined Thalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To preliminarily evaluate the anti-tumor activity of Simmitecan combined with thalidomide in patients with gastrointestinal tumors, and to determine RP2D and MTD</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dose extension study of Simmitecan combined therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To preliminarily evaluate the anti-tumor activity of Simmitecan combined with thalidomide in patients with specific tumors</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Simmitecan</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Pharmacokinetic data investigation of Simmitecan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose escalation study of Simmitecan combined therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose extension study of Simmitecan monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose extension study of Simmitecan combined Thalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose escalation&amp;extension Simmitecan combined Thalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose extension study of Simmitecan combined therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5-fluorouracil and Leucovorin Calcium</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dose escalation study of Simmitecan combined therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose extension study of Simmitecan combined therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thalidomide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Dose extension study of Simmitecan combined Thalidomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Dose escalation&amp;extension Simmitecan combined Thalidomide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          1. Patients who have fully understood the study, and are willing to sign the informed
             consent (ICF);

          2. Patients with advanced solid tumor confirmed by histopathology and/or cytology were
             enrolled in Parts 1 and 2 of the study; Four groups of patients with advanced solid
             tumor confirmed by histopathology and/or cytology were enrolled in Part 3 of the
             study: Group 1 consisted of patients with rectal carcinoma, Group 2 consisted of
             patients with gastric carcinoma and esophageal carcinoma, Group 3 consisted of
             patients with biliary duct carcinoma and pancreatic carcinoma, and Group 4 consisted
             of patients with gastro-entero-pancreatic neuroendocrine carcinoma. Patients with
             advanced or metastatic CRC confirmed by histopathology and/or cytology were enrolled
             in Part 4 of the study; In Part 5 of the study, patients with advanced
             gastrointestinal tumor (including biliary tumor [gallbladder carcinoma, intra- or
             extra-hepatic biliary carcinoma], pancreatic carcinoma, hepatocellular carcinoma,
             esophageal carcinoma, gastric carcinoma, colorectal carcinoma, gastrointestinal
             stromal carcinoma, and gastro-entero-pancreatic neuroendocrine carcinoma) confirmed by
             histopathology were enrolled; In Part 6 of the study, patients with advanced
             gastrointestinal tumor (tentatively determined as biliary tumor, hepatocellular
             carcinoma, pancreatic carcinoma, and colorectal carcinoma); At least 5 unstained
             slices of tumor tissues must be obtained at baseline from patients participating in
             Parts 5 and 6 of the study: Primary lesion samples at the initial diagnosis or
             archived recently were acceptable. They were used to detect protein expression level
             of SOD1 and other related molecules to and tumor immunity related indicators.

             Note: patients being enrolled in part 2 of the study should be those with advanced
             solid tumor who are suitable for therapeutic regimen of Simmitecan combined with 5
             FU/LV as judged by the investigator;

          3. Patients who had failed standard treatments for advanced cancer, or are intolerant to
             the current standard treatments, or no suitable standard treatments available for
             advanced cancer;

          4. Patients who have at least one measurable lesion (according to RECIST, version 1.1);
             note: the lesions previously treated with radiotherapy cannot be regarded as the
             target lesion, unless the lesion showed clear progression after radiotherapy;

          5. Patients with Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score of 0
             or 1;

          6. Age≥ 18 years and ≤ 70 years, male or female is allowed;

          7. Patients with life expectancy of 12 weeks or more;

          8. Patients with appropriate organ function as documented by:

               1. absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.5 × 109/L;

               2. hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL (without RBC transfusion within 14 days);

               3. platelet count ≥ 100 × 109/L.

               4. serum total bilirubin ≤1.5 times of upper limit of normal (ULN) (for the patients
                  with Gilbert syndrome, total bilirubin is allowed to be ≤ 3 × ULN and direct
                  bilirubin is allowed to be 1.5 × ULN);

               5. aspertate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 × ULN, or
                  AST and ALT ≤ 5 × ULN for patients with liver metastasis;

               6. creatinine clearance ≥ 50 mL/min (calculated by MDRD equation, see appendix 7);

               7. international normalized ratio (INR) ≤1.5 × ULN, or activated partial
                  thromboplastin time (aPTT) ≤ 1.5 × ULN (INR only for patients who were not given
                  anticoagulant therapy).

          9. Patients with negative hepatitis b surface antigen; for patients with positive
             hepatitis b surface antigen, quantitative result of hepatitis b virus (HBV) DNA should
             be lower than 1000 cps/mL;

         10. Toxicity events caused by previous treatments, surgery or radiotherapy have recovered
             to CTCAE grade 0 or 1 (except for alopecia);

         11. Female patients are eligible for the study if the following conditions are met:

               1. Patients have no fertility (i.e., physiological infertility), including
                  postmenopausal period (complete menolipsis for more than 1 year) or documented
                  irreversible sterilization operation including hysterectomy, bilateral
                  ovariectomy, or bilateral salpingectomy (instead of tubal ligation);

               2. For patients of childbearing potential, the results of serum pregnancy test
                  screening should be negative (within 7 days before the first dose of
                  investigational drug), and breastfeeding is not allowed before the start of the
                  study and throughout the study. Moreover, the patients should agree to take
                  effective contraception measures during the study and within 90 days after the
                  last dose, and should always conduct strict birth control in accordance with the
                  label of drug/appliance and the investigator's instructions. Effective
                  contraception measure is defined as:

                    -  The sexual partner with removed deferens is the only sexual partner of
                       female patient;

                    -  Use of any intrauterine device with documented failure rate less than 1% per
                       year;

                    -  Double contraception, such as spermicide plus male condom, female condom,
                       diaphragm, cervical cap or intrauterine contraceptive device.

         12. Male patients should have undergone vasectomy, or agree to take effective
             contraception measures during the study and within 90 days after the last dose;

         13. Patients are able to follow the study procedures, restrictions and requirements at the
             investigator's discretion.

        Exclusion criteria

          1. Patients are still within 5 half-life of previous anticancer chemotherapy, biological
             agents or other investigational drugs (if 5 half-life exceeds 28 days, calculated as
             28 days) at the time of screening;

          2. Patients received systemic radiotherapy (including whole brain radiotherapy) within 28
             days before enrollment, or received small area radiotherapy (stereotactic radiotherapy
             of central nervous system (CNS)) within 7 days before enrollment, or have not yet
             recovered from the previous radiotherapy;

          3. Patients have not yet recovered from the toxic effects (except alopecia) caused by
             previous anti-tumor treatments (&gt; CTCAE grade 1);

          4. Patients underwent major surgery or have not yet been fully recovered from pervious
             surgery (major surgery is defined as grade 3 or 4 surgery specified in &quot;Management
             Measures for Clinical Application of Medical Technology&quot; implemented on May 1st,
             2009).

          5. Patients had CNS metastasis or cancer-related epilepsy requiring clinical
             intervention; however, patients with CNS metastasis who received treatments, or the
             asymptomatic patient can be enrolled;

          6. Patients with a history of allergy to 5-FU or LV;

          7. Patients with active HBV or HCV infection;

          8. Patients diagnosed as human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection, or are not willing
             to have HIV test;

          9. Patients with clinically significant active infection;

         10. Patients with previous or concurrent other malignant tumors (except effectively
             controlled non-melanoma skin basal cell carcinoma, breast/cervical carcinoma in situ,
             and other effectively controlled tumors in the past 5 years even without treatments);

         11. Patients with impaired cardiac function or clinically significant heart diseases,
             including grade 2 or higher congestive heart failure per New York Heart Association
             (NYHA) classification, arrhythmia, conduction abnormalities requiring treatment,
             cardiomyopathy, or uncontrolled hypertension;

         12. Patients with serious kidney damage requiring kidney dialysis;

         13. Patients with serious liver damage, grade B or C end-stage liver diseases per
             Child-Pugh classification (see appendix 8);

         14. Any other diseases or conditions with clinical significance that may affect the
             protocol compliance or patient's signature of ICF at the investigator's discretion
             (such as uncontrolled diabetes, etc.);

         15. Patients with disease of digestive tract such as duodenal ulcer, ulcerative colitis,
             intestinal obstruction or other conditions that may cause alimentary tract hemorrhage
             or perforation as judged by the investigator, or have past medical history of
             gastric-intestinal perforation or intestinal fistula;;

         16. Patient's physical condition cause the risk of investigational drug use, or render the
             toxicity or AE difficult to explain at the investigator's discretion.

         17. Patients who received Irinotecan therapy within 3 months prior to enrollment.

         18. Patients with arteriovenous thromboembolic events within the past 6 months, including
             myocardial infarction, cerebral stroke, deep vein thrombosis, or pulmonary embolism,
             etc.

         19. Patients who were sensitive to Thalidomide (in Parts 5 and 6).

         20. Peripheral neuropathy CTCAE ≥ Grade 2 (in Parts 5 and 6).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijin</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lin Shen, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>8610-88196561</phone>
      <email>lin100@medmail.com.cn</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lin Shen, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Harbin Medical University Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harbin</city>
        <state>Heilongjiang</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bai Yu Xian</last_name>
      <phone>13945095085</phone>
      <email>bai_yuxian@126.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tongji Hospital of Tongji Medical College,Huazhong University of Science and Technology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuhan</city>
        <state>Hubei</state>
        <zip>430030</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xianglin Yuan, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>8627-83662299</phone>
      <email>yxl@medmail.com.cn</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xianglin Yuan, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hunan Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changsha</city>
        <state>Hunan</state>
        <zip>410013</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nong Yang, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>13055193557</phone>
      <email>yangnong0217@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nong Yang, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jiangsu Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Feng Ji Feng, M.D</last_name>
      <phone>13901581264</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The first hospital of China Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenyang</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <zip>110001</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yunpeng Liu, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>13898865122</phone>
      <email>cmu_trial@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yunpeng Liu, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fudan University Shanghai Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Junning Cao, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>13651680209</phone>
      <email>cao_junning@126.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Junning Cao, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tianjin Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tianjin</city>
        <state>Tianjin</state>
        <zip>300060</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yi Ba, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>13752157916</phone>
      <email>bayi@tjmuch.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yi Ba, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Second Affiliated hospital of Zhejiang University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hangzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>50011</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yuan Ying, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>13858193601</phone>
      <email>yuanying1999@zju.edu.cn</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yuan Ying, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guimbaud R, Louvet C, Ries P, Ychou M, Maillard E, André T, Gornet JM, Aparicio T, Nguyen S, Azzedine A, Etienne PL, Boucher E, Rebischung C, Hammel P, Rougier P, Bedenne L, Bouché O. Prospective, randomized, multicenter, phase III study of fluorouracil, leucovorin, and irinotecan versus epirubicin, cisplatin, and capecitabine in advanced gastric adenocarcinoma: a French intergroup (Fédération Francophone de Cancérologie Digestive, Fédération Nationale des Centres de Lutte Contre le Cancer, and Groupe Coopérateur Multidisciplinaire en Oncologie) study. J Clin Oncol. 2014 Nov 1;32(31):3520-6. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2013.54.1011. Epub 2014 Oct 6. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2015 Apr 20;33(12):1416.</citation>
    <PMID>25287828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chen W, Zheng R, Baade PD, Zhang S, Zeng H, Bray F, Jemal A, Yu XQ, He J. Cancer statistics in China, 2015. CA Cancer J Clin. 2016 Mar-Apr;66(2):115-32. doi: 10.3322/caac.21338. Epub 2016 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>26808342</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 3, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 12, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 17, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium, Dietary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leucovorin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

