<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02962167</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PNOC 005</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>150812</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02962167</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Modified Measles Virus (MV-NIS) for Children and Young Adults With Recurrent Medulloblastoma or Recurrent ATRT</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study of Modified Measles Virus (MV-NIS) for the Treatment of Children and Young Adults With Recurrent Medulloblastoma or Recurrent Atypical Teratoid Rhabdoid Tumors (ATRT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>No More Kids With Cancer</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Matthew Larson Foundation for Pediatric Brain Tumors</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vyriad, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a two arm Phase I study within the Pacific Pediatric Neuro-Oncology Consortium
      (PNOC).

      This study will look to determine the safety and recommended phase 2 dose of the modified
      measles virus (MV-NIS) in children and young adults with recurrent medulloblastoma or
      atypical teratoid rhabdoid tumor (ATRT).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, multi-center, Phase I study to assess the safety of administering
      MV-NIS directly into the tumor bed (for locally recurrent medulloblastoma or ATRT patients)
      or into the subarachnoid space (for disseminated recurrent medulloblastoma or ATRT patients).

      For locally recurrent patients, MV-NIS will be directly administered into the tumor bed
      following a standard of care surgical resection. For patients with disseminated recurrence,
      MV-NIS will be injected via lumbar puncture (LP). This is a one-time administration for
      either locally or disseminated recurrence.

      Patients will be closely monitored for 30 days after injection, and then followed for
      evaluation of 6 month progressive free survival and overall response rate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as Assessed by CTCAE v4.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of the modified measles virus will be assessed by monitoring for adverse events. Subjects will be monitored for adverse events via scheduled laboratory assessments, vital sign measurements, and physical examinations. The severity of any toxicity will be graded according to the NCI CTCAE v4.0. We will aggregate this information into the number of subjects with adverse events that are related to study treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recommended Phase 2 Dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum tolerated dose (MTD)/recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D) will be the dose level at which 6 evaluable patients have been treated and at most 1 patient experienced a DLT and the next highest dose level is too toxic or we have reached the protocol defined highest dose level.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Any eligible patient that receives MV-NIS will be considered evaluable for clinical efficacy. The objective response criteria is that partial response (PR) and complete response (CR) must be confirmed at least 8 weeks after the initial PR or CR criteria is met.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>For patients who are still progression free at the time of analysis, PFS will be censored at the last contact date. PFS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The distribution of MV-NIS</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects who consent to this optional study will receive an injection of TC-99m (pertechnetate) and then undergo SPECT imaging to determine MV-NIS distribution after local injection or after administration into the subarachnoid space.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Medulloblastoma, Childhood, Recurrent</condition>
  <condition>Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Medulloblastoma Recurrent</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Locally Recurrent Medulloblastoma/ATRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients must have local recurrent disease (defined as negative spine MRI and negative cytology within 21 days prior to study registration) and undergo resection of local recurrence as part of their standard of care. Patients must have undergone what is considered the standard of care as upfront therapy including either surgery followed by high dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue or multi-modality therapy of surgery, radiation and chemotherapy. Patients will receive the modified measles virus, MV-NIS, directly into the tumor bed during standard of care resection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Disseminated Recurrent MB/ATRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients must have disseminated recurrent medulloblastoma (MB) or ATRT (defined as multifocal disease, positive spine MRI including leptomeningeal disease and/or positive cytology within 21 days prior to study registration) and have adequate CSF flow based on spine MRI with no evidence of bulky disease or if bulky disease is present based on a CSF flow study per institutional guidelines. Patients must have undergone what is considered the standard of care as upfront therapy including either surgery followed by high dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue or multi-modality therapy of surgery, radiation and chemotherapy. Patients will receive the modified measles virus, MV-NIS, via lumbar puncture (modified measles virus lumbar puncture).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Modified Measles Virus</intervention_name>
    <description>Administration of MV-NIS either into the tumor bed, if surgery to remove local tumor</description>
    <arm_group_label>Locally Recurrent Medulloblastoma/ATRT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MV-NIS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Modified Measles Virus Lumbar Puncture</intervention_name>
    <description>Administration of MV-NIS into the cerebrospinal fluid via lumbar puncture</description>
    <arm_group_label>Disseminated Recurrent MB/ATRT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MV-NIS LP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  For stratum A, patients must have local recurrent disease (defined as negative spine
             MRI and negative cytology within 21 days prior to study registration) and undergo
             resection of local recurrence as part of their standard of care. Children must have
             undergone what is considered the standard of care as upfront therapy including either
             surgery followed by high dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue or multi-modality
             therapy of surgery, radiation and chemotherapy.

          -  For stratum B, patients must have disseminated recurrent disease (defined as
             multifocal disease, positive spine MRI including leptomeningeal disease and/or
             positive cytology within 21 days prior to study registration) and have adequate
             cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) flow based on spine MRI with no evidence of bulky disease or
             if bulky disease is present based on a CSF flow study per institutional guidelines.
             Children must have undergone what is considered the standard of care as upfront
             therapy including either surgery followed by high dose chemotherapy with stem cell
             rescue or multi-modality therapy of surgery, radiation and chemotherapy.

        Prior Therapy:

          -  The patient must have failed at least one prior therapy - surgery followed by high
             dose chemotherapy with stem cell rescue or multi-modality therapy of surgery,
             radiation and chemotherapy - prior to study registration. Patients must have fully
             recovered from the acute toxic effects of all prior chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or
             radiotherapy prior to entering this study.

             o Myelosuppressive chemotherapy: Patients must have received their last dose of known
             myelosuppressive anticancer chemotherapy at least three weeks prior to study
             registration or at least six weeks prior if nitrosourea.

               -  Biologic agent: Patient must have recovered from any toxicity potentially related
                  to the agent and received their last dose of the biologic agent ≥ 7 days prior to
                  study registration.

          -  For agents that have known adverse events occurring beyond 7 days after
             administration, this period must be extended to beyond the time during which adverse
             events are known to occur. The duration of this interval should be discussed with the
             study chair.

          -  For biologic agents that have a prolonged half-life, the appropriate interval since
             last treatment should be discussed with the Study Chair prior to registration.

             o Monoclonal antibody treatment: At least three half-lives must have elapsed prior to
             registration. Such patients should be discussed with the study chair prior to
             registration. For bevacizumab, patients must have received last dose ≥ 32 days prior
             to study registration.

             o Bone Marrow Transplant: Patient must be:

          -  ≥ 6 months since allogeneic bone marrow transplant prior to registration

          -  ≥ 3 months since autologous bone marrow/stem cell prior to registration

          -  Radiation:

        Patients must have:

          -  Had their last fraction of local irradiation to primary tumor ≥12 weeks prior to
             registration

          -  Had their last fraction of craniospinal irradiation or total body irradiation ≥ 12
             weeks prior to registration

             • Age ≥ 12 months to less than or equal to 39 years of age

             • Karnofsky ≥ 50 for patients ≥ 16 years of age, and Lansky ≥ 50 for patients &lt; 16
             years of age (See Appendix A). Patients who are unable to walk because of paralysis,
             but who are up in a wheelchair, will be considered ambulatory for the purpose of
             assessing the performance score. Patients with pre-existing neurological deficits need
             to be stable prior to surgery or LP as determined by the investigator.

               -  Anti-measles virus immunity as demonstrated by IgG anti-measles antibody per
                  institutional guidelines (within 21 days prior to study registration).

               -  Organ Function Requirements (within 7 days prior to study registration)

          -  Adequate Bone Marrow Function Defined as:

             - Peripheral absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1000/mm3 and

             - Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm3 (transfusion independent, defined as not receiving
             platelet transfusions for at least 7 days prior to enrollment).

          -  Adequate Renal Function Defined as:

               -  Creatinine clearance or radioisotope glomerular filtration rate (GFR) greater
                  than or equal to 70mL/min/1.73 m2 or

               -  A serum creatinine based on age/gender as follows:

        Age

        Maximum Serum

        Creatinine (mg/dL)

        Male Female

          1. - 2 years 0.6 0.6

          2. to &lt; 6 years 0.8 0.8

        6 to &lt; 10 years 1 1

        10 to &lt; 13 years 1.2 1.2

        13 to &lt; 16 years 1.5 1.4

          -  16 years 1.7 1.4 The threshold creatinine values in this table were derived from the
             Schwartz formula for estimating GFR utilizing child length and stature data published
             by the CDC.

               -  Adequate Liver Function Defined as:

                  - Bilirubin (sum of conjugated + unconjugated) less than or equal to 1.5 x upper
                  limit of normal (ULN) for age and

                  - SGPT (ALT) less than or equal to 110 U/L. and

                  - Serum albumin less than or equal to 2 g/dL.

                  • The effects of MV-NIS on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this
                  reason, women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate
                  contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to
                  study entry, for the duration of study participation and 4 months after
                  completion of MV-NIS administration. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect
                  she is pregnant while she or her partner is participating in this study, she
                  should inform her treating physician immediately.

                  • Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent
                  document.

                  -Exclusion Criteria

                  -Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 3 weeks (6 weeks for
                  nitrosoureas or mitomycin C) prior to entering the study or those who have not
                  recovered from adverse events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks
                  earlier

                  -Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents

                  - History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or
                  biologic composition to measles virus vaccination

                  -Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or
                  active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris,
                  cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit
                  compliance with study requirements

                  -Female patients of childbearing potential must not be pregnant or
                  breast-feeding.

                  -Female patients of childbearing potential must have a negative serum or urine
                  pregnancy test (within 7 days prior to study registration)

                  -HIV-positive patients

                    -  Patients with very low CD4 counts (&lt;200/µL or 14% of total lymphocyte count)

                    -  Patients with inability to return for follow-up visits or obtain follow-up
                       studies required to assess toxicity to therapy

                    -  Exposure to household contact with known immunodeficiency

                    -  Allergy to measles vaccine or history of severe reaction to prior measles
                       vaccination

                    -  History of chronic hepatitis B or C infection

                    -  History of organ transplantation

                    -  Patients with evidence of extraneural disease

                    -  Patients on chronic steroid use or other immunosuppressive agents
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>39 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sabine Mueller, MD, PhD, MAS</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sabine Mueller, MD, PhD, MAS</last_name>
    <phone>(415) 476-3831</phone>
    <email>sabine.mueller@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lajhem Cambridge, MS</last_name>
    <phone>(415) 502-1600</phone>
    <email>lajhem.cambridge@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ashley Margol, MD</last_name>
      <phone>323-361-5642</phone>
      <email>amargol@chla.usc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Girish Dhall, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(323) 361-4629</phone>
      <email>gdhall@chla.usc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSF Helen Diller Family Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94158</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sabine Mueller, MD</last_name>
      <phone>415-476-3831</phone>
      <email>sabine.mueller@ucsf.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ann &amp; Robert H. Lurie Children's Hospital of Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stewart Goldman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>312-227-4873</phone>
      <email>sgoldman@luriechildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rishi Lulla, MD</last_name>
      <phone>312-227-4874</phone>
      <email>rlulla@luriechildrens.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215-5450</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Chi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-4386</phone>
      <email>Susan_Chi@dfci.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Daphne Haas-Kogan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-2291</phone>
      <email>Dhaas-kogan@lroc.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University in St. Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Gauvain, MD</last_name>
      <phone>314-454-2002</phone>
      <email>gauvain_k@kids.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Josh Rubin, MD</last_name>
      <phone>314-286-2790</phone>
      <email>rubin_j@kids.wustl.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jane Minturn, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>267-426-5026</phone>
      <email>MINTURN@email.chop.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Angela Waanders, MD</last_name>
      <phone>1-800-879-2467</phone>
      <email>waandersa@email.chop.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seattle Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Leary, MD</last_name>
      <phone>206-987-2106</phone>
      <email>sarah.leary@seattlechildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nicholas Vitanza, MD</last_name>
      <phone>206-987-2106</phone>
      <email>nicholas.vitanza@seattlechildrens.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>measles virus</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent medulloblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent ATRT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Medulloblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Measles</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhabdoid Tumor</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

