<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02969369</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SEP361-203</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02969369</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Efficacy, Safety and Tolerability of SEP-363856 in Subjects With Parkinson's Disease Psychosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Parallel-group, Multicenter Study to Evaluate the Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of SEP 363856 in Subjects With Parkinson's Disease Psychosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sunovion</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sunovion</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A study to evaluate the safety and tolerability of SEP363856 in subjects with Parkinson's
      Disease Psychosis
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, randomized, parallel-group, double-blind, placebo-controlled study
      evaluating the efficacy, safety, and tolerability of SEP-363856 flexibly dosed at 25, 50, or
      75 mg/day for 6 weeks in male and female subjects ≥ 55 years of age with a clinical diagnosis
      of PDP. The study will randomize approximately 36 subjects to 2 treatment groups in a 2:1
      ratio (approximately 24 subjects to SEP-363856 and 12 to placebo).

      The study will consist of 4 periods: Screening/washout Period (up to 14 days prior to
      Lead-in), Lead-in Period (2 weeks prior to Baseline), Double-blind treatment Period (6
      weeks), and Follow-up Period (1 week after last dose) as shown in the following figure. All
      post-Baseline clinic visits will have a window of ± 2 days relative to the date of the
      Baseline visit (Visit 3).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 31, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in total SAPS-PD Score at Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0-week 6</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the CGI S at Week 6.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0-week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in NPI at Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0-week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in MMSE at Week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0-week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of overall AEs, serious adverse events (SAEs), and AEs (or SAEs) leading to discontinuation.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes from Baseline in clinical laboratory tests (hematology)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute values from Baseline in clinical laboratory tests (hematology)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes from Baseline in clinical laboratory tests (serum chemistry)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute values from Baseline in clinical laboratory tests (serum chemistry)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes from Baseline in clinical laboratory tests (urinalysis)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>absolute values from Baseline in clinical laboratory tests (urinalysis)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes from Baseline in clinical evaluations (body weight)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>absolute values from Baseline in clinical evaluations (body weight)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes from Baseline in clinical evaluations (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>absolute values from Baseline in clinical evaluations (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes from Baseline in clinical evaluations (blood pressure , [supine and standing])</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>absolute values from Baseline in clinical evaluations (blood pressure , [supine and standing])</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes from Baseline in clinical evaluations (heart rate [supine and standing])</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>absolute values from Baseline in clinical evaluations (heart rate [supine and standing])</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>changes from Baseline in clinical evaluations ( 12-lead ECGs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>absolute values from Baseline in clinical evaluations ( 12-lead ECGs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of subjects With suicidal ideation or suicidal behavior using the C-SSRS</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0 - week 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease Psychosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SEP-363856</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SEP-363856 (25, 50, or 75mg/day), once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Capsule</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SEP-363856</intervention_name>
    <description>SEP-363856 (25, 50, or 75mg/day)</description>
    <arm_group_label>SEP-363856</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Capsule</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Subject, caregiver, and/or legally authorized representative understands and is
             willing to sign informed consent to participate in the study.

             2. Subject must be willing and able to comply with the study procedures and visit
             schedules and must be able to follow verbal and written instructions.

             3. Subject is male or postmenopausal female ≥ 55 years of age. 4. Subject meets
             established diagnostic criteria for Parkinson's disease of at least one year duration,
             consistent with the UK Brain Bank criteria 5. Subject has psychotic symptoms that
             began after the diagnosis of PD for at least one month, occurring at least weekly in
             the month prior to screening (according to subject or caregiver), and severe enough to
             warrant treatment with antipsychotics.

             6. Subject has a combined score of at least 6 or an individual score of at least 4 on
             the neuropsychiatric inventory (NPI) Item A (delusions) and/or Item B
             (hallucinations).This criterion must be met at visits 1 and 3.

             7. Subject has a Mini-mental status examination (MMSE) score &gt; 16 points out of 30.

             8. Subject has a caregiver (spouse or family member) who will be required to attend
             all visits and is able to provide study information on various scales such as the NPI
             and Zarit 22 scale.

             9. Subject is taking antiparkinsonian drugs or deep brain stimulation, with a stable
             dose/dose regimen and settings for 1 month before screening.

             10. Female subject must be postmenopausal defined as being amenorrheic for greater
             than two years with an appropriate clinical profile.

             11. Male subjects with female partner(s) of childbearing potential must agree to avoid
             fathering a child and use acceptable methods of birth control from screening until at
             least 30 days after the last study drug administration.

             12. Subject is, in the opinion of the Investigator, medically stable based on
             screening medical history, PE, neurological examination, vital signs, clinical
             laboratory values (hematology, serum chemistry, urinalysis, lipid panel, coagulation
             panel, thyroid panel, and serum prolactin).

             13. Subject has had a stable living arrangement at the time of screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Subject has psychosis secondary to other toxic or metabolic disorders. 2. Subject
             has atypical Parkinson's disease, Parkinsonism secondary to medication or other
             neurodegenerative disorders, such as progressive supranuclear palsy or multiple system
             atrophy.

             3. Subject has dementia diagnosed concurrent with or before Parkinson's disease, motor
             symptoms that began less than one year before the onset of dementia or symptoms
             consistent with the diagnosis of Lewy Body Dementia (LBD), or if the psychosis
             occurred after ablative stereotaxic surgery.

             4. Subject failed 2 or more antipsychotic agents given at adequate doses for at least
             4 weeks within 1 year before screening. Treatment failure is defined as a complete
             lack of efficacy. Subjects who had a partial response or who discontinued treatment
             for reasons of tolerability will be allowed.

             5. Subject has had a stroke or other uncontrolled serious medical or neurological
             illness within 6 months of baseline.

             6. Subject answers &quot;yes&quot; to &quot;Suicidal Ideation&quot; Item 4 (active suicidal ideation with
             some intent to act, without specific plan) or Item 5 (active suicidal ideation with
             specific plan and intent) on the C SSRS at Screening (ie, in the past one month), or
             baseline (ie, since last visit).

             7. Subject does not tolerate venipuncture or has poor venous access that would cause
             difficulty for collecting blood samples.

             8. Subject has participated in an investigational drug study and received
             investigational drug within 30 days (or longer if the half-life is known to be ≥ 150
             hours) prior to the screening visit, or who is currently participating in another
             interventional study. Observational studies are not exclusionary. Subject has
             previously received SEP 363856.9. Subject has any clinically significant unstable
             medical condition or any clinically significant chronic disease that in the opinion of
             the Investigator, would limit the subject's ability to complete and/or participate in
             the study: 10. Subject has hematological (including deep vein thrombosis) or bleeding
             disorder, renal, metabolic, endocrine, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, urological,
             cardiovascular, hepatic, neurologic, or allergic disease that is clinically
             significant or unstable as judged by the Investigator 11. Subject has a history of
             malignancy within 5 years prior to the Screening visit, except for adequately treated
             basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer or in situ cervical cancer. Pituitary tumors
             of any duration are excluded.

             12. Subject has, in the opinion of the investigator, a disorder or history of a
             condition such as a clinically significant abnormality of the hepatic or renal system
             or a history of malabsorption, or previous gastrointestinal surgery (eg,
             cholecystectomy, vagotomy, bowel resection, or any surgical procedure) that may
             interfere with drug absorption, distribution, metabolism, excretion.

             13. Subject has known or suspected Alcohol or Substance Use Disorder as defined by DSM
             5. The only exceptions are caffeine or nicotine.

             14. Subject has a clinically significant abnormal 12 lead ECG that may result in the
             subject's inability to complete the study, as judged by the Investigator.

             15. Subjects with known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositivity will be
             excluded.

             16. Female subject who is pregnant or lactating. 17. Subject has an active and
             unstable psychiatric disorder as judged by the investigator 18. Subject is at
             significant risk of harming him/herself or others according to the Investigator's
             judgment.

             19. Subject has attempted suicide within 3 months prior to screening. 20. Subject has
             a history of allergic reaction or suspected sensitivity to any substance that is
             contained in the study drug formulation.

             21. Subject has any clinically significant abnormal laboratory values (hematology,
             serum chemistry, urinalysis, lipid panel, coagulation panel, thyroid panel, serum
             prolactin, and urine drug screen(Note: abnormal findings that may be clinically
             significant or of questionable significance will be discussed with the Medical Monitor
             prior to including subject).

             22. Subjects with serum alanine transaminase (ALT) or aspartate transaminase (AST)
             levels ≥ 3 times, serum blood urea nitrogen (BUN) or creatine ≥ 1.5 X the upper limit
             of the reference ranges provided by the central laboratory require retesting. If on
             retesting, the laboratory value remains equal to or above the ULN, the subject will be
             excluded.

             23. Subjects with a random (non-fasting) blood glucose at screening ≥ 200 mg/dL (11.1
             mmol/L) or HbA1c ≥ 7% will be excluded.

             24. Subject has a prolactin concentration &gt; 100 ng/mL at screening or has a history of
             pituitary adenoma.

             25.. Subject has an abnormal BMI that may result in the subject's inability to
             complete the study, as judged by the Investigator.

             26. Subject has experienced significant blood loss (≥ 473 mL) or donated blood within
             60 days prior to first dose of study drug; has donated plasma within 72 hours prior to
             the first dose of study drug or intends to donate plasma or blood or undergo elective
             surgery during study participation or within 60 days after the last study visit.

             27. Subject consumes more than 300 mg of caffeine per day (5 cups of coffee or
             equivalent in caffeinated beverages).

             28. Subject has used disallowed prescription medications or anticipates the need for
             any disallowed medication during their participation in this study. Subject is a staff
             member or the relative of a staff member.

             29. Subject is in the opinion of the Investigator, unsuitable in any other way to
             participate in this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>105 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>CNS Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Sunovion</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>CNS Medical Director</last_name>
    <phone>1-866-503-6351</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neuuro-Pain Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fresno</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>93710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Perminder Bhatia, MD</last_name>
      <phone>559-437-9700</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Keck School of Medicine of USC/ University of Southern California</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Hui, MD</last_name>
      <phone>323-442-5710</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>JEM Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlantis</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33462</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mark Goldstein, MD</last_name>
      <phone>561-968-2933</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Parkinson's Disease and Movement Disorders Center of Boca Raton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boca Raton</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33486</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stuart Isaacson, MD</last_name>
      <phone>561-392-1818</phone>
      <phone_ext>6</phone_ext>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Compass Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32802</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ira Goodman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>407-426-9299</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neurology Associates of Ormond Beach</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ormond Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32174</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida Parkinson's Disease and Movement Disorder's Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33613</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert Hauser, MD</last_name>
      <phone>813-396-0751</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kansas Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66160</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rajesh Pahwa, MD</last_name>
      <phone>913-588-6782</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kevin Black, MD</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-5041</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>David Kreitzman</name>
      <address>
        <city>Commack</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11725</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Burton Scott, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>919-688-6477</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Movement Disorder Clinic of Oklahoma</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tulsa</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>74136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kevin Klos, MD</last_name>
      <phone>918-392-4530</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Ratliff, MD</last_name>
      <phone>215-503-2724</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 21, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parkinson's Disease Psychosis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

