<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02960334</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-076</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02960334</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Screening for Actionable Atrial Fibrillation During Preoperative Consultation With the MyDiagnostick</brief_title>
  <official_title>Screening for Actionable Atrial Fibrillation During Preoperative Consultation With the MyDiagnostick</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Martini Hospital Groningen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Martini Hospital Groningen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Atrial Fibrillation (AF) It is the most common arrhythmia in the world. It carries great
      public health significance because of its prevalence, additional morbidity and mortality. It
      provides a 4-5 times higher risk of developing a ischemic stroke or transient ischemic
      attack. In term, this risk can be 70% reduced by taking oral anticoagulants. Actionable AF is
      the overarching term for silent AF (asymptomatic AF) and undertreated AF (known AF, but not
      sufficiently protected against ischemic stroke). It is recommended that over the age of 65,
      patients should be screened with pulse palpation or rhythm strip for the presence of AF. The
      MyDiagnostick is a single-lead I, compact hand-held device that analyses heart rhythm during
      one minute. During preoperative consultation, this device will be used to value the yield of
      screening for actionable AF.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common arrhythmia in the world, with a prevalence
      ranging from 1.9 - 2.3% and rising. It is known that the disease occurs more often as age
      progresses: 70% of affected cases are aged between 65 and 85, over 80 years, one is 10-18%
      likely to be carrying the illness. Multiple risk factors for developing AF have been
      determined, like hypertension, myocardial infarction, heart failure, valvular heart disease,
      obesity, DM and hyperthyroidism.

      AF potentially leads to thrombus formation, resulting in a 4-5 times increased risk of
      getting a TIA or ischemic infarction.

      Taking a 12 lead electrocardiogram (ECG) remains the golden standard, with the absence of
      distinct P-waves and a RR interval that is irregularly irregular.

      AF is a risk factor and a risk marker for developing ischemic stroke, by providing a
      prothrombotic environment. This makes a patient with AF 4-5 times more susceptible for
      getting an ischemic stroke. Protection for this risk is done by prescribing oral
      anticoagulants (OAC) (according to an individuals CHA2DS2VASc-score) by either Vitamin-K
      antagonists (VKAs) or Novel Oral Anticoagulants (NOACs). This allows for a 70% stroke risk
      reduction.

      Not all AF is known to its carrier, it has been proven that 30% of all cases proceeds
      asymptomatic. These patients are unknowingly exposed to a higher stroke risk. Undertreated AF
      is when AF is known, but OAC is unrightfully withheld. In approximately 20% of all AF-related
      strokes, AF was known but undertreated.

      In view of the increasing prevalence of AF, it seems there is a need for screening for
      prevention of actionable AF-associated strokes. The European Society of Cardiology discloses
      in their most recent guideline that opportunistic screening appears feasible and
      cost-effective in patients older than 65 years, to be performed by either pulse taking or ECG
      rhythm strip. The MyDiagnostick, a compact hand-held, 1-lead ECG recorder was created to
      fulfil the need for better large scale screening devices. In one minute it distinguishes
      irregular rhythms from normal cardiac rhythms and it can store over 120 ECGs. In a study of
      192 patients the MyDiagnostick showed to be 100% sensitive for detecting AF and had a
      specificity of 95.9%. It provided in a study in which the prevalence of silent AF was
      examined during influenza vaccination in 10 general practices with more than 3000 patients.
      From a total of 3269 screened patients, 121 (3,7%) cases of AF were detected, whereof 37
      (1,1%) had not yet been diagnosed before.

      In this study, the yield of opportunistic screening will be tested of all patients aged 65 or
      older during preoperative consultation with the MyDiagnostick
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of AF</measure>
    <time_frame>Single time point (when the patient visits the preoperative consultation hour)</time_frame>
    <description>The MyDiagnostick shows regular or irregular RR-interval</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Usage of OAC</measure>
    <time_frame>Single time point (when the patient visits the preoperative consultation hour)</time_frame>
    <description>Usage of OAC</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">505</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MyDiagnostick</intervention_name>
    <description>The MyDiagnostick is a compact hand-held device that registers and stores I-lead ECG strips. In one minute, t analyses the rhythm for the presence of AF. It distinguishes AF from normal cardiac rhythms by measuring RR-irregularity.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Every patient &gt; 64 years can participate in the trial. Patients who visit the preoperative
        consultation (e.g. before surgery) will be asked to hold the MyDiagnostick for one minute.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  &gt;64 years of age, visiting preoperative consultation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt;64 years of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Martini Ziekenhuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Groningen</city>
        <zip>9700 RM Groningen</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 3, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 7, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 9, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 31, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Martini Hospital Groningen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eva Roseboom</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Silent Atrial Fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>Undertreated Atrial Fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>Actionable Atrial Fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>MyDiagnostick</keyword>
  <keyword>Opportunistic Screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Preoperative Consultation</keyword>
  <keyword>OAC</keyword>
  <keyword>VKA</keyword>
  <keyword>NOAC</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

