<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02966223</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RADY-BTG-TANN-HIDA/0603</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02966223</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Assess the Effect of Y-90 Therapy on Non-target/Background Liver</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Assess the Effect of Y-90 Therapy on Non-target/Background Liver</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BTG International Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary question of interest is quantifying the relationship between Y-90 liver therapy
      and liver damage. Little is known on this subject. Present assumptions and calculations of
      Y-90 administration are based on surgical lobar hepatectomies and external radiation beam
      therapies. The investigators hope that by using a functional model of the liver, the
      investigators can improve this important knowledge gap.

      The investigators will be enrolling patients planning to receive Y-90 therapy for the
      treatment of liver malignancies. The diagnosis of a primary liver cancer, hepatocellular
      carcinoma (HCC), is usually made by a combination of specific imaging findings and clinical
      criteria; only rarely is a confirmatory biopsy performed. This is due to the high accuracy of
      the present diagnostic model and the significant risk of biopsy and tumor seeding.

      Y-90 therapy involves administering radioactive particles to liver tumors by placing a
      catheter in a hepatic artery supplying the tumor using angiographic techniques and injection
      of these particles.

      Y-90 Positron Emission Tomography-Computed Tomography (PET/CT) imaging has been established
      as a method to validate and quantitate distribution of Yttrium after Y-90 administration. The
      post Y-90 therapy PET/CT images provide an imaging distribution of the Y-90, which is
      essential for validation of administered versus planned dose to the liver lesion and
      background liver.

      If the investigators can compare the Y-90 distribution to estimate background liver radiation
      distribution and dose (generated by the Y-90 PET/CT scan) combined with the global and
      regional function map (generated by the hepatobiliary [HIDA] scan performed before and after
      therapy), then the investigators will be assuming that the difference pre and post therapy in
      global and regional function can be ascribed to the Y-90 administration. The investigators
      will also analyze the Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) and CT sets performed before and after
      therapy and correlate the imaging results collected with clinical findings such as
      ascites/encephalopathy and routine serological markers (bilirubin, albumin, International
      normalized ratio [INR], etc.). With this information, the investigators will have the
      potential to establish whether there is a relationship between Y-90 distribution to
      non-tumoral (normal) hepatic parenchyma and the incidence and severity of
      Radioembolization-Induced Liver Disease (REILD). This would have the potential to improve
      selection criteria and outcomes in populations selected for Y-90 therapy in the future.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Little is known on the potential relationship between Y-90 liver therapy and liver damage
      this subject. Present assumptions and calculations of Y-90 administration are based on
      surgical lobar hepatectomies and external radiation beam therapies.

      As most participants that need Y90 based liver therapies have compromised livers, the
      importance of knowing what potential collateral liver damage could be induced by Y90 is key
      so as not induce liver failure. Successful treatment of a liver malignancy would not be
      important if the potential mortality/morbidity risk of the treatment is higher or equal to
      the existing malignancy.

      As apposed to anatomical imaging looking for changes in size/shape which are late changes,
      the investigators hope that by using a functional model of the liver, which can show early
      changes of liver damage, the investigators can improve the sensitivity for detection of liver
      damage and bridge this important knowledge gap. Additionally due to compensatory hypertrophy
      of the non treated liver, potential liver damage estimated by lab tests may be masked, again
      this emphasizes the importance of the measurement of the functional approach before and after
      therapy.

      The investigators will be enrolling participants planning to receive Y-90 therapy for the
      treatment of liver malignancies. The diagnosis of a primary liver cancer, hepatocellular
      carcinoma (HCC), is usually made by a combination of specific imaging findings and clinical
      criteria; only rarely is a confirmatory biopsy performed. This is due to the high accuracy of
      the present diagnostic model and the significant risk of biopsy and tumor seeding.

      Y-90 therapy involves administering radioactive particles to liver tumors by placing a
      catheter in a hepatic artery supplying the tumor using angiographic techniques and injection
      of these particles.

      Y-90 PET/CT imaging has been established as a method to validate and quantitate distribution
      of Yttrium after Y-90 administration. The post Y-90 therapy PET/CT images provide an imaging
      distribution of the Y-90, which is essential for validation of administered versus planned
      dose to the liver lesion and background liver.

      The investigators will be performing both specialized nuclear medicine HIDA and MRI scans
      aimed at constructing a functional map of the liver before and 3 months after therapy.

      The investigators will compare the Y-90 distribution to estimate background liver radiation
      distribution and dose (generated by the Y-90 PET/CT scan) combined with the global and
      regional function map (generated by the HIDA and MRI scans performed before and after
      therapy), then the investigators will be assuming that the difference pre and post therapy in
      global and regional function can be ascribed to the Y-90 administration.

      The investigators will also analyze the MRI and NM data sets performed before and after
      therapy and correlate the imaging results collected with clinical findings such as
      ascites/encephalopathy and routine serological markers (bilirubin, albumin, INR, etc.).

      With this information, the investigators will have the potential to establish whether there
      is a relationship between Y-90 distribution to non-tumoral (normal) hepatic parenchyma and
      the incidence and severity of REILD. This would have the potential to improve selection
      criteria and outcomes in populations selected for Y-90 therapy in the future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 17, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in regional liver function between pre and 3 months post Yttrium 90 delivery using the HIDA functional imaging scans.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in global liver function between pre and 3 months post Yttrium 90 delivery using the HIDA functional imaging scans.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between the differences in liver function (both regional and global) with the Y 90 dose provided.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>HCC</condition>
  <condition>Liver Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MRI and HIDA scan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI and HIDA scan</intervention_name>
    <description>Pre y90 therapy each subject will undergo a HIDA and MRI scan. 3 months post Y90 - Each subject will undergo a second HIDA scan and MRI scan</description>
    <arm_group_label>MRI and HIDA scan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written
             informed consent document.

          2. Subjects must be ≥ 18 years of age at the time of signing informed consent.

          3. Subjects must have a diagnosis of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) and a treatment plan
             to undergo radioembolization therapy with Y-90 at Indiana University Health Hospital.

          4. Subjects must be willing and able to comply with all procedures and visits required
             for this protocol (pre-treatment, during treatment, and post-treatment).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects who have contraindications for receiving Y-90 therapy and any routine
             procedures and imaging associated with Y-90 therapy, including subjects who are
             pregnant or are planning to become pregnant, will not be eligible to participate in
             this study. Female subjects who are of childbearing potential should inform her
             treating physician should she become pregnant at any time during the course of the
             study.

          2. Subjects with contraindications for receiving hepatobiliary scans (HIDA scans) and
             Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI scans) will not be eligible to participate in this
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Tann, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark Tann, MD</last_name>
    <phone>3179488782</phone>
    <email>matann@iupui.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah D Munson, RN</last_name>
      <phone>317-963-0305</phone>
      <email>sed@iu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Tann, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew S Johnson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 14, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 17, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Indiana University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark Tann</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Radiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plan to share</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

