<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02968056</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XH-16-027</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02968056</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>One Staged Hybrid Approach of Surgical/Catheter Ablation for Persistent Atrial Fibrillation</brief_title>
  <official_title>One Staged Hybrid Approach of Minimally Invasively Surgical/Catheter Ablation for Persistent Atrial Fibrillation: A Non-Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There are 10 million atrial fibrillation (AF) patients in China, and the patients are risk of
      stroke, heart failure and sudden death. Persistent AF is still a refractory disease, and
      single catheter ablation only has a success rate around 30-50%. Hybrid strategy consisting of
      thoracoscopic epicardial ablation and transvenous endocardial ablation seems to be an
      attractive procedure to improve the treatment of persistent AF. However, only a few centers
      reported their preliminary results, and the conclusions are controversial. The investigator
      previously reported a minimally invasive surgical ablation from left thoracoscope only and
      achieved good results. Recently, the investigator successfully explored a hybrid procedure
      combing this unique surgical technique and transvenous catheter ablation. Here, the
      investigator present a study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of this novel hybrid
      procedure. The hypothesis is that a hybrid approach is more efficient than surgical ablation
      alone in the treatment of persistent AF.

      This study is a non-randomized controlled study within a single institution. Isolated
      persistent AF patients admitted to the cardiovascular surgery department of Shanghai Xinhua
      Hospital will be screened for enrollment of this study. The study will recruit 180 patients
      in total. Based on their own willingness, the patients will be divided into hybrid group and
      minimally invasive (MIS) group. The MIS group patients only have surgical ablation surgery
      from left thoracoscope as the investigator reported before, while the hybrid group patients
      will have additional transvenous catheter ablation after the surgical ablation is done during
      the same operation. The ratio of hybrid to MIS group is expected to be 1:1, so that each
      group contains 90 patients. The perioperative data is collected, and the patients will be
      followed for 6 months. The primary outcome is the rate of sinus rhythm at 6 months post
      operation. The secondary outcomes include off antiarrhythmic drug rate, perioperative
      complications, major cardiovascular events, stroke, left ventricular systolic function,
      medical expense, serum brain natriuretic peptide level and quality of life. The aim is to
      evaluate the efficacy and safety of this novel hybrid procedure, therefore to provide more
      evidence of the hybrid strategy in the treatment of persistent AF.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sinus rhythm maintenance rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Based on ECG results from 3 months and 6 months after the surgery. Any non-sinus rhythm lasting &gt;30 seconds captured on ECG at any time will be considered failure to maintain sinus rhythm</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Off any antiarrhythmic drug rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The rate is counted at 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perioperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 1 month after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Emergent thoracotomy or exploration for bleeding, renal dysfunction requiring new dialysis treatment, respiratory dysfunction requiring prolonged mechanical ventilation with tracheotomy, new pacemaker implantation, and perioperative death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major cardiovascular events</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 6 months after discharge</time_frame>
    <description>Death, Nonfatal myocardial infarction, re-admission because of heart disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>New onset of stroke after the surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular systolic function</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by ejection fraction from echocardiogram</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Costs of treatment in Chinese Yuan</measure>
    <time_frame>From surgery to 6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>There are 3 parts. 1. Cost during the first hospitalization; 2. Cost of all the health care from first discharge to 6 months after the surgery, including seeing clinics, medication, re-hospitalization related to atrial fibrillation/surgical complications/new onset of stroke/other atrial fibrillation related complications. 3. Total cost: the combination of the abovementioned two parts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum brain natriuretic peptide level</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated by short form 36 questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Persistent Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hybrid group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Minimally invasive surgical radiofrequency ablation of atrial fibrillation followed by catheterized radiofrequency ablation within the same procedure</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MIS group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Minimally invasive surgical radiofrequency ablation of atrial fibrillation only</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiofrequency ablation</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiofrequency energy is used for ablation in both arms of this study (Hybrid group and MIS group)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hybrid group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MIS group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. Isolated atrial fibrillation, without structural heart disease.

          2. Persistent atrial fibrillation (Af last time &gt; 7 days, including persistent long
             standing atrial fibrillation)

          3. Patients with symptomatic AF that is refractory to at least one antiarrhythmic
             medication; symptomatic patients are those who have been aware of their AF at any time
             within the last 5 years before enrolment. Symptoms may include, but are not restricted
             to, palpitations, shortness of breath, chest pain, fatigue, left ventricular
             dysfunction, or other symptoms, or any combination of these.

          4. Patient admitted with intent to treat by either hybrid or surgical ablation

          5. Consent

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Previous surgical ablation of atrial fibrillation

          2. Concomitant other cardiac diseases which require surgery at the same procedure, such
             as heart valve disease, congenital heart disease, coronary disease, dilated
             cardiomyopathy etc.

          3. With other forms of severe arrhythmia

          4. Ejection fraction of left ventricle less than 30%

          5. Anteroposterior diameter of left atrial over 60mm

          6. Tumor, active infection, pregnancy.

          7. Previous surgeries with left thoracotomy, or expected left pleural adhesion, such as
             history of tuberculosis infection, pleural effusion, pneumothorax etc.

          8. Hyperthyroidism

          9. Thrombosis within left atrial appendage

         10. General conditions too weak to tolerate the surgeries

         11. Patient's circumstance that precludes completion of follow-up and/or obtaining
             information from the 1-year follow-up

         12. Other conditions not appropriate for this study based on the investigators' judgments
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xin Zhou, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ju Mei, MD and PhD</last_name>
    <phone>86-21-25078030</phone>
    <email>ju_mei63@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jiaquan Zhu, MD and PhD</last_name>
    <phone>86-21-25078051</phone>
    <email>somzjq@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ju Mei, MD and PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boersma LV, Castella M, van Boven W, Berruezo A, Yilmaz A, Nadal M, Sandoval E, Calvo N, Brugada J, Kelder J, Wijffels M, Mont L. Atrial fibrillation catheter ablation versus surgical ablation treatment (FAST): a 2-center randomized clinical trial. Circulation. 2012 Jan 3;125(1):23-30. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.074047. Epub 2011 Nov 14.</citation>
    <PMID>22082673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muneretto C, Bisleri G, Bontempi L, Cheema FH, Curnis A. Successful treatment of lone persistent atrial fibrillation by means of a hybrid thoracoscopic-transcatheter approach. Innovations (Phila). 2012 Jul-Aug;7(4):254-8. doi: 10.1097/IMI.0b013e31826f0462.</citation>
    <PMID>23123991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pison L, La Meir M, van Opstal J, Blaauw Y, Maessen J, Crijns HJ. Hybrid thoracoscopic surgical and transvenous catheter ablation of atrial fibrillation. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2012 Jul 3;60(1):54-61. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.12.055.</citation>
    <PMID>22742400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pokushalov E, Romanov A, Elesin D, Bogachev-Prokophiev A, Losik D, Bairamova S, Karaskov A, Steinberg JS. Catheter versus surgical ablation of atrial fibrillation after a failed initial pulmonary vein isolation procedure: a randomized controlled trial. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 2013 Dec;24(12):1338-43. doi: 10.1111/jce.12245. Epub 2013 Sep 9.</citation>
    <PMID>24016147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cox JL. A brief overview of surgery for atrial fibrillation. Ann Cardiothorac Surg. 2014 Jan;3(1):80-8. doi: 10.3978/j.issn.2225-319X.2014.01.05.</citation>
    <PMID>24516803</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gelsomino S, Van Breugel HN, Pison L, Parise O, Crijns HJ, Wellens F, Maessen JG, La Meir M. Hybrid thoracoscopic and transvenous catheter ablation of atrial fibrillation. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2014 Mar;45(3):401-7. doi: 10.1093/ejcts/ezt385. Epub 2013 Jul 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23904136</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mei J, Ma N, Ding F, Chen Y, Jiang Z, Hu F, Xiao H. Complete thoracoscopic ablation of the left atrium via the left chest for treatment of lone atrial fibrillation. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2014 Jan;147(1):242-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2012.10.005. Epub 2012 Nov 2.</citation>
    <PMID>23122696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pragliola C, Mastroroberto P, Gaudino M, Chello M, Covino E. Staged transthoracic approach to persistent atrial fibrillation (TOP-AF): study protocol for a randomized trial. Trials. 2014 May 26;15:190. doi: 10.1186/1745-6215-15-190.</citation>
    <PMID>24885377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bulava A, Mokracek A, Hanis J, Kurfirst V, Eisenberger M, Pesl L. Sequential hybrid procedure for persistent atrial fibrillation. J Am Heart Assoc. 2015 Mar 25;4(3):e001754. doi: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001754.</citation>
    <PMID>25809548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang PJ. Hybrid epicardial and endocardial ablation of atrial fibrillation: is ablation on two sides of the atrial wall better than one? J Am Heart Assoc. 2015 Mar 25;4(3):e001893. doi: 10.1161/JAHA.115.001893.</citation>
    <PMID>25809549</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beukema RJ, Adiyaman A, Smit JJ, Delnoy PP, Ramdat Misier AR, Elvan A. Catheter ablation of symptomatic postoperative atrial arrhythmias after epicardial surgical disconnection of the pulmonary veins and left atrial appendage ligation in patients with atrial fibrillation. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2016 Jan;49(1):265-71. doi: 10.1093/ejcts/ezv047. Epub 2015 Feb 26.</citation>
    <PMID>25721819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phan K, Phan S, Thiagalingam A, Medi C, Yan TD. Thoracoscopic surgical ablation versus catheter ablation for atrial fibrillation. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2016 Apr;49(4):1044-51. doi: 10.1093/ejcts/ezv180. Epub 2015 May 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26003961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richardson TD, Shoemaker MB, Whalen SP, Hoff SJ, Ellis CR. Staged versus Simultaneous Thoracoscopic Hybrid Ablation for Persistent Atrial Fibrillation Does Not Affect Time to Recurrence of Atrial Arrhythmia. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 2016 Apr;27(4):428-34. doi: 10.1111/jce.12906. Epub 2016 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26725742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calkins H, Kuck KH, Cappato R, Brugada J, Camm AJ, Chen SA, Crijns HJ, Damiano RJ Jr, Davies DW, DiMarco J, Edgerton J, Ellenbogen K, Ezekowitz MD, Haines DE, Haissaguerre M, Hindricks G, Iesaka Y, Jackman W, Jalife J, Jais P, Kalman J, Keane D, Kim YH, Kirchhof P, Klein G, Kottkamp H, Kumagai K, Lindsay BD, Mansour M, Marchlinski FE, McCarthy PM, Mont JL, Morady F, Nademanee K, Nakagawa H, Natale A, Nattel S, Packer DL, Pappone C, Prystowsky E, Raviele A, Reddy V, Ruskin JN, Shemin RJ, Tsao HM, Wilber D. 2012 HRS/EHRA/ECAS Expert Consensus Statement on Catheter and Surgical Ablation of Atrial Fibrillation: recommendations for patient selection, procedural techniques, patient management and follow-up, definitions, endpoints, and research trial design. Europace. 2012 Apr;14(4):528-606. doi: 10.1093/europace/eus027. Epub 2012 Mar 1.</citation>
    <PMID>22389422</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 16, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 18, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 16, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 16, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 18, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ju Mei</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>atrial fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>radiofrequency ablation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

