<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02361996</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RENE271242</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02361996</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Quantitative Measurement of Myocardial Perfusion by Cardiac CT in Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>CCT/MPERF</acronym>
  <official_title>Quantitative Measurement of Myocardial Perfusion by Cardiac CT in Patients Before and After Coronary-bypass-surgery, Before and After Dilating/Stenting and Before and After Aortic-valve-replacement.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bakulev Scientific Center of Cardiovascular Surgery</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of Graz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Health &amp; Life Sciences University, Tryol</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bakulev Scientific Center of Cardiovascular Surgery</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It is a common understanding that patients with coronary heart disease are suffering, among
      others, from reduced myocardial perfusion. In order to increase (normalize) the reduced
      perfusion, when conventional approach failed, coronary bypass surgery, coronary vessel
      dilatation/stenting are performed. The similar situation with reduced myocardial perfusion
      may be found in patients with stenosis of the aortic valve, where aortic valve replacement
      may increase myocardial perfusion by left-ventricular remodelling. However, there is
      presently no method established to measure myocardial perfusion quantitatively and
      noninvasively before and after a therapeutic intervention.

      Data of pre- and post-therapeutic myocardial perfusion, quantitatively measured in
      ml/100g/min would strengthen the indication for specific therapeutic approach and enable an
      objective control of effectiveness of the applied therapy.

      Hypothesis:

      There is a measureable difference in quantitative myocardial perfusion values before (lower)
      and after (higher) interventional or surgical procedure.

      The goal of the study is to measure myocardial perfusion by advanced CT technology (e.g. iCT
      256 Brilliance ) quantitatively in ml/100g/min in three groups of patients:

        1. Before and after coronary bypass surgery

        2. Before and after coronary vessel dilatation/stenting

        3. Before and after aortic valve replacement.

      The investigators will not assign specific interventions to the subjects of these three
      groups. Therefore, the research is strictly observational.

      Design:

      Prospective study to measure quantitatively myocardial perfusion in the above mentioned three
      groups of patients with simultaneous control and registration of all essential, physiological
      determinants of myocardial perfusion immediately prior to each CT study. The CT myocardial
      perfusion measurements will be performed directly after the indication for intervention or
      surgery and on the last day before discharge from hospital.

      All the collected data (determinants) inclusively the CT-studies will be anonymised and
      archived on a local server. The investigators of the University of Medical Computed Sciences
      and Technology, Innsbruck / Austria will perform the evaluation of the myocardial perfusion
      measurements and all statistical analysis independently of the CT-studies performing
      physicians.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Reliability of the hypothesis:

      On phantom studies simulating myocardial perfusion measurements and in animal studies we
      could confirm that using advanced CT technology (as e.g. &quot;iCT 256 Brilliance&quot;) it is possible
      to measure myocardial perfusion in absolute values - in ml/100g/min. These myocardial
      perfusion measurements did not differ from those received by EBCT (Electron Beam Computed
      Tomography) Based on these experimental results and based on the quantitative measurements of
      myocardial perfusion in 1500 patients studied by EBCT at the Medical University of Graz the
      hypothesis may be done that using the above mentioned iCT 256 technology, it should be
      possible to measure myocardial perfusion quantitatively in a daily clinical practice.

      Ethical aspects:

      The study will be performed according to the international regulations (ISO 14144:212-01) and
      in agreement with the &quot;Declaration of Helsinki&quot;. After oral and written explanation of the
      planned study and by signing the study agreement by patient and by responsible physician,
      patients participation is voluntary. The patients participating can leave the study any time
      without negative sequels for him or her. There is no financial restitution for the patients.

      Patients will be informed about (very rare) possible allergoid-toxic reactions during and
      after intravenous contrast agent application. For possible emergency well trained medical
      staff and equipment is present. About renal insufficiency: renal failure (creatinin clearance
      &lt;60ml/min [GFR (Glomerulo Filtration Rate)will be calculated according the
      Cockroft-Gault-Formula, GFR {ml/min}=((40-age)*weight{kg}*0,85{only for women}]/serum
      creatinin [mg/dl]*72) above.

      The applied X-ray dose (CT) may and will be reduced by:

      reduction of KV (kilovoltage) from 120 to 100 or 80 in dependance of patients weight,
      reduction of MA (milliamper)by using iterative image reconstruction allgorithm (iDOSE). These
      technical approaches represent the best possibility to reduce X-ray dose for the patient. As
      the coronary heart disease with stenotic lesions above 50% is a disease mainly of an elderly
      men (in female mostly after menopause and in male after 50 years of age) the risk for X-Ray
      dose related genetic defects is very low. The expected applied X-Ray doses by the above
      mentioned approach will be very low and therefore the risk of X-Ray induced malignancy may be
      regarded as very low too.

      Design:

      Prospective study to measure quantitatively myocardial perfusion in the above mentioned three
      groups of patients with simultaneous control and registration of all essential, physiological
      determinants of myocardial perfusion immediately before the CT study. The CT myocardial
      perfusion measurements will be performed directly after the indication for intervention or
      surgery and on the last day before discharge from hospital.

      All the collected data (determinants) inclusively the CT-studies will be anonymised and
      archived on a local server. These anonymised data may be approached only by the co-workers of
      UMIT, who will perform the evaluation of the myocardial perfusion measurements and the
      statistical analysis independently of the CT-studies performing physicians.

      Practical procedure:

        1. In supine position on CT table the blood pressure and the heart rate will be measured
           and registered.

        2. In all patients a standard native cardiac CT for evaluation of coronary calcification by
           Agatston score will be performed.

        3. In all patients myocardial perfusion will be measured in inspiration and contrast agent
           application where by the amount of contrast agent and the applied dose is related to
           patient weights as shown below:

           Patient Perfusion 210mg Iodine/ml Expected dose weight [kg] / [kV/mAs] / [ml] / per
           shoot [mSv](milli Sievert)

           &lt;60 80/80 40 0.21/ 60-70 80/100 50 0.25/ 70-90 80/120 60 0.30/ 90-100 100/90 70 0.40/
           &gt;100 100/100 80 0.43

        4. Standard cardiac CT will be performed to evaluate coronary arteries and left ventricular
           volumes.

        5. In supine position on CT table the blood pressure and the heart rate will be measured
           and registered.

      Quantitative evaluation:

      The calculation of the myocardial perfusion succeeds in all slices with visible left
      ventricular myocardium using a modification of the formula described by K.Miles.

      The calculation of the left ventricular volumes succeeds by use of the vendors software.

      Statistic:

      All personal and measured data will be anonymised, tested, analysed and evaluated in the
      Health &amp; Life Sciences University,Tryol.

      The numerical values will be expressed as mean +/- SD (min, max, 95% CI). P-values of 0.05
      will be regarded statistically significant. Paired test and or Wilcoxon signed-rank tests
      will be used. X² analyses will be used to compare categoric variables. Additionally
      correlation analyses (Pearson, Spearman) will be performed and method of classification (pre-
      vs. postoperative) will be applied. All calculation will be done by SPSS 21.0 (SPSS, Chicago,
      Il, USA) or by Matlab R2013b statistic Toolbox.

      The neccessary number of studied patients is based on the results of 64 patients studied
      before and after aortic valve replacement in whom the myocardial perfusion was measured
      before and four months after surgery.

      Pre-operative: Mean=74 (SD=21) ml/100g/min Post 4 Months: Mean=78 (SD=20) ml/100g/min.
      Difference= +4ml/100g/min. With 0.5 supposed correlation of the measured values the standard
      deviation of the differences may be estimated as 20ml/100g/min.

      By alpha=0.05, 1-beta=0.80, n=209 patients is needed.

      As a drop-out quote of 10% may be expected it is neccessary to study in each group of
      patients 230 patients. This means total 690 patients.

      All data will be registered in a EXCEL-data bank and tested for plausibility.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of myocardial perfusion (ml/100g/min) [MPerf]</measure>
    <time_frame>after indication for and before intervention or surgery and after intervention or surgery one day before discharge</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composition of parameters influencing the complexity of myocardial perfusion regulation: Heart-rate, blood-pressure, rate-pressure-product, left ventricular haemodynamic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>after indication for and before intervention or surgery and after intervention or surgery one day before discharge</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">690</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Aortic Valve Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Coronary Bypass Surgery</arm_group_label>
    <description>inclusion criteria:
presence of at least one coronary stenotic lesion above 50% with clinical indication for coronary bypass surgery.
list of medication timely related to the procedure
signed informed consent
exclusion criteria:
intolerance to contrast agent
multiple myeloma, pheochromocytoma, thyroid dysfunction, acute infection
renal failure
severe arrhythmia
pregnancy
reduction of cognitive capabilities to understand the purpose and the extent of the study
participation in a medical-scientific study using X-rays in the last ten years
lack of Russian knowledge to fill the forms
lack of signed study agreement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Coronary Stenting</arm_group_label>
    <description>inclusion criteria:
presence of at least one coronary stenotic lesion above 50% with clinical indication for coronary vessel dilatation/stenting.
list of medication timely related to the procedure
signed informed consent
exclusion criteria:
intolerance to contrast agent
multiple myeloma, pheochromocytoma, thyroid dysfunction, acute infection
renal failure
severe arrhythmia
pregnancy
reduction of cognitive capabilities to understand the purpose and the extant of the study
participation in a medical-scientific study using X-rays in the last ten years
lack of Russian knowledge to fill the forms
lack of signed study agreement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aortic Valve Replacement</arm_group_label>
    <description>inclusion criteria:
presence of aortic valve disease (stenosis) with clinical indication for aortic valve replacement without coronary vessel stenosis above 50%
list of medication timely related to the procedure
signed informed consent
exclusion criteria:
intolerance to contrast agent
multiple myeloma, pheochromocytoma, thyroid dysfunction, acute infection
renal failure
severe arrhythmia
pregnancy
reduction of cognitive capabilities to understand the purpose and the extent of the study
participation in a medical-scientific study using X-rays in the last ten years
lack of Russian knowledge to fill the forms
lack of signed study agreement</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients above 18 years of age, who are reffered with suspected or known coronary
        artery disease or aortic valve stenosis either to the Bakoulev Scientific Centre for
        Cardiovascular Surgery, Moscow / Russia or to the Republican Special Centre of Surgery,
        Tashkent / Uzbekistan and fulfill the eligibility criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        in cohort: Coronary Bypass Surgery:

        o presence of at least one coronary stenotic lesion above 50% with clinical indication for
        coronary bypass surgery

        in cohort: Coronary Stenting: o presence of at least one coronary stenotic lesion above 50%
        with indication for coronary vessel dilatation/stenting

        in cohort: Aortic Valve Replacement

        o presence of aortic valve disease (stenosis) with clinical indication for aortic valve
        replacement without coronary vessel stenosis above 50%

        for all three cohorts:

          -  list of medication timely related to the procedure

          -  signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        for all three cohorts:

          -  intolerance to contrast agent

          -  multiple myeloma, pheochromocytoma, thyroid dysfunction, acute infection

          -  renal failure

          -  severe arrhythmia

          -  pregnancy

          -  reduction of cognitive capabilities to understand the purpose and the extent of the
             study

          -  participation in a medical-scientific study using X-rays in the last ten years

          -  lack of Russian knowledge to fill the forms

          -  lack of signed study agreement -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rainer K Rienmueller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bakoulev Scientific Centre for Cardiovascular Surgery, Moscow / Russia; Medical University of Graz / Austria</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vladimir N Makarenko, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bakoulev Scientific Centre for Cardiovascular Surgery, Moscow / Russia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marat Khodjibekov, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Republican Special Center of Surgery, Tashkent / Uzbekistan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christian Baumgartner, Dr.techn.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University for Medical Computer Sciences and Technology, Innsbruck / Austria</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rainer K Rienmueller, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00436644225931</phone>
    <email>rainer@rienmueller.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bakoulev Scientific Center for Cardiovascular Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>121552</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rainer K Rienmueller, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043-664-4225931</phone>
      <email>rainer@rienmueller.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Vladimir N Makarenko, MD</last_name>
      <phone>007-495-7902352</phone>
      <email>vnmakarenko@bakulev.ru</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Inna Rychina, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Republican Specialized Center of Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tashkent</city>
        <zip>100115</zip>
        <country>Uzbekistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marat Khodjibekov, MD</last_name>
      <phone>00998-71-2772765</phone>
      <email>uzradsociety@fromru.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Muzaffar F Maksudov, MD</last_name>
      <phone>00998-98-361-69-64</phone>
      <email>drmfmaksudov@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Muzaffar F Maksudov, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Uzbekistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 15, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 12, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 12, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Bakulev Scientific Center of Cardiovascular Surgery</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rainer Rienmueller, M.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>em.Univ.Prof.Dr.med.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aortic Valve Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

