<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02360384</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WMC1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02360384</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Caecal pH as a Biomarker for Irritable Bowel Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised Controlled Trial to Validate the Use of Caecal pH Measurement as a Biomarker in Irritable Bowel Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wingate Institute of Neurogastroenterology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wingate Institute of Neurogastroenterology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Irritable bowel syndrome is common. Currently, it is a diagnosis of exclusion. There is
      increasing evidence of the importance of the microbiota in the pathophysiology of this
      disorder. However, it has been challenging to measure the &quot;activity&quot; of the microbiota in
      vivo as much of the GI tract is inaccessible. Fermentation by the microbiota occurs in the
      colon, a by product of which are short chain fatty acids. Measuring pH in the colon could
      potentially act as a surrogate marker of fermentation. The investigators are undertaking a
      randomised controlled trial in patients with IBS measuring the pH in the digestive tract
      using a wireless motility capsule at baseline and in response to dietary changes in patients
      with diarrhoea predominant IBS and in response to linaclotide in those with constipation
      predominant IBS to ascertain the effect of these interventions on the microbiota and clinical
      outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) is an extremely common condition. Between 1.9 and 3.6 million
      patients consult a healthcare professional for IBS each year in the UK (1). The total
      population prevalence is much higher as most IBS sufferers are non-consulters due to the
      perceived lack of effective treatments. IBS can be sub-classified based upon predominating
      bowel habit, i.e. constipation predominant (IBS-C), alternating bowel habit (IBS-A) or
      diarrhoea predominant (2). In recent years, several efficacious treatment approaches have
      been applied to IBS including dietary interventions (low fibre and low fermentable
      oligosaccharides, disaccha¬rides, monosaccharides and polyols (FODMAP)), probiotics (VSL#3)
      and pharmacological agents (linaclotide) (3). Whilst each of these treatment approaches have
      shown efficacy, it is clear that further refinement of the IBS diagnostic algorithm is
      required to better target therapies in order to overcome the inherent heterogeneity within
      the IBS population.

      Bloating and distension are both common and vexatious symptoms in a proportion of IBS
      patients. Bloating is largely regarded as a subjective sensation of abdominal swelling,
      whereas distension refers to an observable increase in abdominal girth. Bloating is
      associated with a reduction in quality of life, is a cause for healthcare seeking and
      represents a considerable challenge to manage effectively.

      The anaerobic breakdown of carbohydrates and protein by bacteria, largely occurring within
      the proximal colon, is through a process known as fermentation, the principal products of
      which are short chain fatty acids (SCFA). One of the proposed mechanisms of bloating and
      distension is colonic dysbiosis and subsequent mal-fermentation. This has been supported by
      data which show that a large proportion of IBS patients improve symptomatically when
      restricting their diet to an 'elemental' formula for 2-4 weeks thus reducing the amount of
      fermentable material in the intestinal lumen.

      The direct in vivo measurement of SCFA concentrations in the human proximal colon is
      technically difficult and invasive. Given that the degree of bacterial fermentation is
      directly proportional to the concentration of SCFA, the measurement of segmental
      intra-colonic pH is an inverse surrogate proxy of the degree of fermentation occurring within
      that territory. We have recently shown that measurement of caecal pH using the wireless
      motility capsule (WMC) in IBS and control patients is both technical feasible and able to
      differentiate between the two populations (4).

      Our study showed that caecal pH is significantly lower in IBS when compared to controls thus
      supporting the concept that mal-fermentation is contributing to IBS symptomatology.
      Importantly, we have also shown that caecal pH is correlated with inhibition of caecal
      contractility which has led us to propose the idea that 'caecoparesis' maybe the long sought
      after alteration in motor function which differentiates IBS patients from healthy
      participants and explains why IBS preferentially experience pain in the right colon and upper
      abdomen in response to balloon distension.

      TRIAL OBJECTIVES The primary aim of this study is to demonstrate that caecal pH is a
      sensitive and reliable biomarker of caecal fermentation in IBS and that normalisation of the
      caecal pH environment will correlate with symptomatic improvement in IBS patients. We
      hypothesise that normalisation of the caecal pH environment with either dietary intervention
      or linaclotide will correlate with symptomatic improvement in IBS patients. To achieve this
      we will recruit a cohort of Rome III defined IBS patients and sub-divide them into the
      appropriate IBS type based on symptoms. We will then characterise their phenotype in terms of
      gastro-intestinal physiology (WMC + lactulose hydrogen breath test) and psychological
      profile. They will then be allocated to one of (2 or 3) treatment arms (control diet, low
      FODMAP diet, control diet + linaclotide). Each treatment arm will last for 28 days after
      which WMC will be repeated and symptoms assessed. Secondary aims will include characterising
      motility and transit in IBS-sub groups, determining the effect of the interventions of
      motility and transit, comparison of ileal and caecal pH profiles with hydrogen / methane
      breath testing data and comparison of symptom change and physiological assessment outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the change in pH around the ileocaecal valve in response to dietary intervention or linaclotide.</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Change in pH around the ileocaecal valve using the wireless motility capsule in response to the dietary intervention and linaclotide</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in caecal pH and its association with the degree in symptomatic improvement using the IBS-symptom scale</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>The change in caecal pH association and it is association with the magnitude of improvement in symptoms using the validated IBS-SSS questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motility patterns and transit in subtype IBS patients, according to the Rome III criteria, using the wireless motility capsule</measure>
    <time_frame>1-2 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of the interventions on symptoms using the validated questionnaires of IBS-SSS</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of the interventions on quality of life measures using the validated Eq-5D</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The placebo intervention will be healthy eating advice in patients with irritable bowel syndrome of the alternating subtype for 28 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lincalotide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients with constipation predominant IBS will receive linaclotide 280mcg po od for 28 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FODMAP diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The FODMAP diet will be introduced in patients with irritable bowel syndrome of the alternating subtype for 28 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Linaclotide</intervention_name>
    <description>Linaclotide 290mcg po od in all patients with irritable bowel syndrome with constipation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Lincalotide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Constella</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FODMAP diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with irritable bowel syndrome with alternating bowel habit will be commenced on the either the low FODMAP diet or a control healthy eating diet.</description>
    <arm_group_label>FODMAP diet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to provide Informed written consent

          -  Age (18-65 years old)

          -  Male and female patients with irritable bowel syndrome of the alternating or
             constipation subtype.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any inclusion criteria not met

          -  Participants unable to provide informed consent.

          -  Participants on any medications that may influence gastrointestinal motility (e.g.
             beta-agonists).

          -  Pregnancy.

          -  Recent antibiotic use in the preceding 4 weeks.

          -  Recent probiotic use in the last 2 weeks, concurrent use of promotile medications.

          -  Participants with IBS-C who are already taking linaclotide or have known
             hypersensitivity to linaclotide.

          -  History of a systemic disorder with known gastrointestinal manifestations (such as
             diabetes mellitus, connective tissue disorders etc.) and previous gastrointestinal
             tract surgery will be treated as criteria for exclusion. Specific contraindications to
             WMC are dysphagia, recent abdominal surgery, Crohn's disease, planned MRI and
             diverticulitis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adam D Farmer, PhD MRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wingate Institute of Neurogastroenterology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wingate Institute of Neurogastroenterology</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>E1 @AJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farmer AD, Mohammed SD, Dukes GE, Scott SM, Hobson AR. Caecal pH is a biomarker of excessive colonic fermentation. World J Gastroenterol. 2014 May 7;20(17):5000-7. doi: 10.3748/wjg.v20.i17.5000.</citation>
    <PMID>24803812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 25, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 2, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 2, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 3, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wingate Institute of Neurogastroenterology</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adam Farmer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Consultant gastroenterologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>wireless motility capsule</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

