<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02367846</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00000464</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02367846</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessing the Impact of Contraceptives on Bone Health Using 41Ca</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Oral vs. Non-oral Contraceptive Therapy on Bone Turnover Using 41Ca Methodology</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Penn State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Purdue University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Penn State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This preclinical randomized crossover study will examine the effects of oral versus non-oral
      contraceptive therapy on bone turnover in young exercising women. In an effort to expose the
      route-dependent effects of oral versus non-oral contraceptive therapy on bone turnover, the
      investigators will examine 1) the effects of ethinyl estradiol on bone calcium balance using
      the 41Ca technology and 2) the underlying physiological mechanisms associated with the
      effects of oral versus non-oral contraceptive therapy on net bone calcium balance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a preclinical, multi-site study (Penn State University and Purdue University)
      that will determine whether the negative effects of combined oral contraceptive (COC) therapy
      on bone turnover are dependent on the route of administration such that an attenuation of
      these effects is observed when a comparable dose of non-oral contraceptive therapy, such as
      vaginal contraceptive (CVR) therapy is also tested. Millions of women use COC therapy for
      birth control purposes or regulation of menstrual cycles. CVR therapy is a relatively new
      FDA-approved contraceptive alternative to COC. The purpose of the proposed project is to
      investigate whether oral ethinyl estradiol (EE) may negatively impair bone turnover when
      compared to vaginally-administered EE in young physically-active women.

      A novel calcium tracer technology suitable to rapidly assess changes in net bone calcium
      balance in a small sample size will be applied to evaluate the effects of COC and CVR therapy
      on bone turnover. The radioisotope Calcium-41 (41Ca) demonstrates increased sensitivity when
      compared to dual x-ray absorptiometry (DXA) and increased specificity for bone mineralization
      and precision when compared to biochemical markers of bone turnover. This study will be the
      first study to examine how the route of estrogen administration affects bone turnover in
      young physically active women by assessing changes in net bone calcium balance with different
      forms of contraceptive therapy.

      The overall purpose of this study is to explore the effects of oral versus vaginal
      contraceptive therapy on bone turnover in young exercising women using 41Ca technology. In an
      effort to expose the route-dependent effects of oral versus non-oral contraceptive therapy on
      bone turnover, the investigators will examine 1) the effects of ethinyl estradiol on bone
      calcium balance using the 41Ca technology and 2) the underlying physiological mechanisms
      associated with the effects of oral versus vaginal contraceptive therapy on net bone calcium
      balance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in 41Ca:Ca ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>49 days of contraceptive therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the 41Ca:Ca ratio in 24-h urine samples measured every 10-14 days during and after oral and non-oral contraceptive therapy as determined by Accelerometer Mass Spectrometry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in serum concentrations of insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1), IGF-binding proteins (IGFBP-1, IGFBP-3), and acid labile subunit (ALS)</measure>
    <time_frame>49 days of contraceptive therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in fasting serum concentrations of IGF-1, IGFBP-1, IGFBP-3, and ALS after oral and non-oral contraceptive therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in serum concentrations of markers of bone formation and bone resorption</measure>
    <time_frame>49 days of contraceptive therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in fasting serum concentrations of markers of bone formation (osteocalcin, P1NP) and bone resorption (CTx) after oral and non-oral contraceptive therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Other Disorders of Bone Development and Growth</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Oral Contraceptive (COC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>We are testing the effects of a COC (Apri (Reclipsen); 30 µg EE, 150 µg desogestrel). On the first day of the intervention, the participants randomized to COC will begin taking the pill. One pill will be ingested orally at the same time each day for days 1-49 of the intervention. Pills ingested during days 1-21 and during days 29-49 will be active tablets. Pills ingested on days 22-28 will be tablets without active ingredients. Each participant in the COC group will ingest a pill from the first pack each day for the first 28 days then begin the second pack. If a participant is unable to collect a 24-h urine sample on day 49, she will take active tablets from the third pill pack until she has collected the 24-h urine sample.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Contraceptive Vaginal Ring (CVR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>We are testing the effects of the vaginal ring (Nuva Ring; 15 µg/d EE, 120 µg/d etonogestrel). When randomized to CVR, participants will insert the contraceptive ring into their vagina . The ring will be worn during weeks 1-3, and again during weeks 5-7. During week 4, no ring will be worn to allow for withdrawal bleeding. If a participant is unable to collect a 24-h urine sample on day 49, they will insert a third ring which will remain in the vagina until she has collected a 24-h urine sample.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combined Oral Contraceptive (COC)</intervention_name>
    <description>The proposed study is a preclinical, multi-site trial comparing the short-term effects of oral vs. non-oral ethinyl estradiol on net bone calcium balance. A prospective crossover study with repeated measures and a simple random assignment will be used to test the effects of 49 days of COC use on bone metabolism using 41Ca to determine net bone calcium balance. Subjects will be randomized to receive COC during either the first or second intervention period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Oral Contraceptive (COC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Apri (Reclipsen)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Contraceptive Vaginal Ring (CVR)</intervention_name>
    <description>The proposed study is a preclinical, multi-site trial comparing the short-term effects of oral vs. non-oral ethinyl estradiol on net bone calcium balance. A prospective crossover study with repeated measures and a simple random assignment will be used to test the effects of 49 days of CVR use on bone metabolism using 41Ca to determine net bone calcium balance. Subjects will be randomized to receive CVR during either the first or second intervention period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Contraceptive Vaginal Ring (CVR)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nuva Ring</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Female

          2. Age 18-25 yrs

          3. BMI 18-29 kg/m2

          4. Non-smoking

          5. Willing to refrain from using hormonal contraceptives for the equilibration + baseline
             period of the study (~150 days)

          6. Availability to frequently visit the laboratory in the next 12 months

          7. Not currently pregnant nor intending to become pregnant in the next 12 months

          8. Not lactating

          9. No apparent metabolic, endocrine, musculoskeletal, or severe psychiatric disease

         10. Willing to maintain consistent exercise (aerobic, weight-bearing) and dietary habits
             during pre-intervention and intervention periods

         11. Willing to refrain from supplements other than those provided by study staff in the
             next 12 months

         12. Variable physical activity acceptable, but mode must be primarily weight bearing

         13. At least 9 menses in the past 12 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Non-weight bearing exercise as primary mode of physical activity

          2. Resistance exercise training (≥ 2 times 30 minutes per week of resistance exercise)

          3. Complete seasonal change of impact mode of physical activity

          4. Known or suspected metabolic or endocrine disease

          5. Smoking

          6. Pregnant

          7. Currently consuming large amounts of soy products

          8. Current clinical eating disorder or other axis 1 psychiatric disorder or bipolar
             disorders

          9. Oral or hormonal contraceptive use in the last 6 months

         10. Hyperparathyroidism

         11. Liver or renal disease

         12. Evidence of malabsorption or skeletal disorder

         13. Thyroid abnormalities (controlled hypothyroidism acceptable)

         14. Chronic use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS)

         15. Taking medications known to have interactions with oral or vaginal contraceptive
             therapy

         16. Other Exclusion Criteria proposed by the World Health Organization COC
             Contraindications (Grossman et al., 2011).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary Jane De Souza, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Penn State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women's Health and Exercise Laboratories, The Pennsylvania State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>University Park</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>16802</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grossman D, White K, Hopkins K, Amastae J, Shedlin M, Potter JE. Contraindications to combined oral contraceptives among over-the-counter compared with prescription users. Obstet Gynecol. 2011 Mar;117(3):558-65. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e31820b0244.</citation>
    <PMID>21343758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee WH, Wastney ME, Jackson GS, Martin BR, Weaver CM. Interpretation of 41Ca data using compartmental modeling in post-menopausal women. Anal Bioanal Chem. 2011 Feb;399(4):1613-22. doi: 10.1007/s00216-010-4454-5. Epub 2010 Dec 9.</citation>
    <PMID>21152905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weaver CM, Martin BR, Jackson GS, McCabe GP, Nolan JR, McCabe LD, Barnes S, Reinwald S, Boris ME, Peacock M. Antiresorptive effects of phytoestrogen supplements compared with estradiol or risedronate in postmenopausal women using (41)Ca methodology. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2009 Oct;94(10):3798-805. doi: 10.1210/jc.2009-0332. Epub 2009 Jul 7.</citation>
    <PMID>19584189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Denk E, Hillegonds D, Vogel J, Synal A, Geppert C, Wendt K, Fattinger K, Hennessy C, Berglund M, Hurrell RF, Walczyk T. Labeling the human skeleton with 41Ca to assess changes in bone calcium metabolism. Anal Bioanal Chem. 2006 Nov;386(6):1587-602. Epub 2006 Oct 11.</citation>
    <PMID>17033771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 27, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Penn State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mary Jane DeSouza</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Kinesiology and Physiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Calcium Tracer</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Contraceptives</keyword>
  <keyword>Contraceptive Vaginal Ring</keyword>
  <keyword>Impact of contraceptives on bone health using 41Ca</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases, Developmental</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Contraceptive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Contraceptives, Oral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ethinyl Estradiol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Contraceptives, Oral, Combined</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

