<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02363322</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>150083</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>15-I-0083</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02363322</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Putative Investigational Therapeutics in the Treatment of Patients With Known Ebola Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter Randomized Safety and Efficacy Study of Putative Investigational Therapeutics in the Treatment of Patients With Known Ebola Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Ministry of Health and Social Welfare of the Republic of Liberia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Ministry of Health and Sanitation of the Republic of Sierra Leone</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Ministry of Health and Public Hygiene of the Republic of Guinea</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Ebola is a viral infection that can spread quickly and causes life-threatening disease.
      Right now there is an Ebola outbreak in many countries in West Africa. There are no approved
      treatments for Ebola. But possible treatments are being developed. Researchers need to study
      these treatments to see if they help people get better.

      Objective:

      - To identify possible Ebola treatments. Also, to learn if adding 1 or more experimental
      drugs to advanced Ebola care can reduce the risk of death.

      Eligibility:

      - People who have recently been diagnosed with Ebola, usually by a test called the Polymerase
      Chain Reaction (PCR), and have been hospitalized in an isolation unit for treatment.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be randomly assigned to Group A or B. Both groups will get advanced
           level care. One group will also get an experimental drug.

        -  Participants may have blood tests. They may have another PCR test.

        -  Researchers will try to learn how the participant got Ebola.

        -  Participants put in the experimental drug group may start taking medicine within 24
           hours of enrollment. It may be given by mouth or intravenously. Additional doses may be
           needed.

        -  Participants may have a series of timed blood tests over the first 24 to 48 hours after
           they take the medicine.

        -  Blood will be drawn frequently. Other body fluids (urine, stool, vaginal fluid, etc.)
           may also be collected.

        -  Participants will be followed for up to 60 days. They may be evaluated for any long-term
           effects of the experimental treatment(s). They may be asked to return for 1 or more
           outpatient visits.

        -  For consenting participants, follow-up will be extended for up to one full year past Day
           58 with contact/visits every 1-3 months to assess for a history of signs or symptoms
           potentially consistent with late onset of virologic relapse syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ebolaviruses (EBOV) are members of the Filoviridae and are known primarily as the underlying
      cause of severe viral hemorrhagic fevers with disturbingly high case fatality rates. Between
      1994 and the present, there have been many EBOV outbreaks affecting mostly central Africa,
      with 2 large outbreaks in 1995 in Kikwit, Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC), and in Gulu,
      Uganda in 2000-2001. However, the 2014 West African outbreak significantly exceeds all
      previous outbreaks in geographic range, number of patients affected, and in disruption of
      typical activities of civil society.

      There is strong consensus that the most important element necessary to improve survival from
      Ebola infection is the provision of full hemodynamic support in the form of aggressive fluid
      replacement, ability to diagnose and correct severe metabolic derangements, and other
      standards of modern medical care available in resource-rich environments. However, against
      this background, a small series of investigational agents or interventions have also been
      proposed as putative antiviral strategies of potential utility in treating this infection.
      Unfortunately, phase 1/2 data supporting the safety and efficacy of these agents is generally
      lacking, and thus there should be equipoise as to which, if any, of these interventions
      should be utilized in the treatment of severe infection.

      In this multicenter randomized trial, we propose a flexible trial design with frequent
      interim monitoring to facilitate early elimination of poorly performing treatments as well as
      the introduction of new candidate therapies. The trial allows for a series of pairwise
      comparisons of novel interventions against a background of optimized medical care, with the
      goal of determining whether one or more of these interventions can improve the mortality over
      that achievable through optimized standard-of- care (oSOC) alone. The primary endpoint of
      this trial will be comparative mortality at Day 28, with a number of secondary endpoints that
      hopefully will generate generalizable knowledge about the relative safety and antiviral
      activity of these adjunctive interventions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 13, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical and virology effects of experimental treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Viral Load</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Ebola Virus Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Optimized standard of care to include aggressive fluid resuscitation, hemodynamic support, and other interventions available in an optimized care setting</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ZMapp (Trademark) + Optimized standard of care to include aggressive fluid resuscitation, hemodynamic support, and other interventions available in an optimized care setting.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ZMApp</intervention_name>
    <description>Triple monoclonal cocktail of antibodies against Zaire species of Ebola virus</description>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment A</intervention_name>
    <description>Optimized standard of care for Ebola virus infection</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Males or females with documented positive PCR for Ebola virus infection within 10 days
             of enrollment

          -  Willingness of study participant to accept randomization to any assigned treatment arm

          -  Access to oSOC

          -  All males and females of childbearing potential, must be willing to use highly
             effective methods of contraception [e.g. absolute abstinence from potentially
             reproductive sexual activity, hormonal, surgical or multiple barrier/combined], from
             time of enrollment for the duration of study participation.

          -  Must agree not to enroll in another study of an investigational agent prior to
             completion of last required protocol visit (Day 58)

          -  Ability to provide informed consent personally, or by a legally-authorized [per
             applicable local laws and regulations] representative [LAR] if the patient is unable
             to do so.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Any medical condition that, in the opinion of the site investigator, would place the
             patient at an unreasonably increased risk through participation in this study,
             including any past or concurrent conditions that would preclude randomization to one
             or more of the assigned treatment arms.

          -  Prior treatment with any investigational antiviral drug therapy against Ebola
             infection other than experimental vaccines, within 5 half-lives or 30 days, whichever
             is longer, prior to enrollment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard T Davey, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CTE Forecariah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Forecariah</city>
        <country>Guinea</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Monrovia Medical Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monrovia</city>
        <country>Liberia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ELWA III Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paynesville</city>
        <country>Liberia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Police Training School 1 (PTS1), Western Rural District</name>
      <address>
        <city>Freetown</city>
        <country>Sierra Leone</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emergency Ebola Treatment Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Goderich</city>
        <country>Sierra Leone</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Police Training School 2</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hastings</city>
        <country>Sierra Leone</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chinese Friendship Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jui</city>
        <country>Sierra Leone</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>International Medical Corps (IMC) Kambia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kambia District</city>
        <country>Sierra Leone</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>International Medical Corps (IMC) Lunsar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port Loko District</city>
        <country>Sierra Leone</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adventist Development and Relief Ebola Treatment Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waterloo</city>
        <country>Sierra Leone</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Guinea</country>
    <country>Liberia</country>
    <country>Sierra Leone</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2015-I-0083.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Joffe S. Evaluating novel therapies during the Ebola epidemic. JAMA. 2014 Oct 1;312(13):1299-300. doi: 10.1001/jama.2014.12867.</citation>
    <PMID>25211645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kanapathipillai R. Ebola virus disease--current knowledge. N Engl J Med. 2014 Sep 25;371(13):e18. doi: 10.1056/NEJMp1410741.</citation>
    <PMID>25251632</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piot P, Muyembe JJ, Edmunds WJ. Ebola in west Africa: from disease outbreak to humanitarian crisis. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014 Nov;14(11):1034-1035. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(14)70956-9. Epub 2014 Oct 1.</citation>
    <PMID>25282665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 12, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 16, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Medical Countermeasures</keyword>
  <keyword>VHF</keyword>
  <keyword>EVD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhagic Fever, Ebola</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coal Tar</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

