<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02367222</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200405 (H2014:019)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02367222</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Database Study to Estimate the Risk of Multiple Sclerosis Following Vaccination With Arepanrix™ in Manitoba, Canada</brief_title>
  <acronym>H1N1-014VS</acronym>
  <official_title>An Observational Retrospective Database Analysis to Estimate the Risk of Multiple Sclerosis Following Vaccination With Arepanrix™ in Manitoba, Canada</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Manitoba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manitoba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this database study is to assess if Arepanrix™ vaccination during the 2009
      pandemic was associated with an increased risk of multiple sclerosis (MS) in Manitoba,
      Canada.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This observational, retrospective, propensity-score matched cohort study using the Manitoba
      Immunization Monitoring System (MIMS) and the hospital, physician, and prescription claims
      databases of the Manitoba Health (MH) Database System will assess if Arepanrix™ vaccination
      during the 2009 pandemic was associated with an increased risk of multiple sclerosis (MS) and
      other demyelinating conditions not ultimately leading to a multiple sclerosis diagnosis in
      Manitoba, Canada.

      The data will be collected form the following linked databases:

        -  Manitoba Health (MH) administrative databases

        -  Manitoba Immunization Monitoring System (MIMS)

        -  Manitoba Health Population Registry (MHPR)

        -  Drug Program Information Network (DPIN)

        -  Hospital Abstract Database

        -  The Medical Services database
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of MS</measure>
    <time_frame>15 September 2009 to 15 March 2010 (up to 6 months)</time_frame>
    <description>During the period of 1 year following administration of Arepanrix™ among an exposed cohort and during an equivalent time period in the unexposed cohort.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of MS</measure>
    <time_frame>15 September 2009 to 31 December 2012 (up to 39 months)</time_frame>
    <description>From administration of Arepanrix™ until 31 December 2012, among an exposed cohort and during an equivalent time period in the unexposed cohort.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of demyelinating events which do not ultimately lead to a diagnosis of MS</measure>
    <time_frame>15 September 2009 to 15 March 2010 (up to 3 months)</time_frame>
    <description>During the period of 1 year following administration of Arepanrix™ among an exposed cohort and during an equivalent time period in the unexposed cohort.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of demyelinating events which do not ultimately lead to a diagnosis of MS</measure>
    <time_frame>15 September 2009 to 31 December 2012 (up to 39 months)</time_frame>
    <description>From administration of Arepanrix™ until 31 December 2012, among an exposed cohort and during an equivalent time period in the unexposed cohort.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exposed to Arepanrix™ Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>All individuals with Manitoba Immunization Monitoring System (MIMS) record of H1N1 (Arepanrix™) and/or seasonal influenza vaccination during the influenza season 2009/2010 (15 September 2009 to 15 March 2010).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Unexposed to Arepanrix™ Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>All individuals registered with Manitoba Health (MH) during the study period but with no MIMS record for H1N1 (Arepanrix™) and seasonal influenza vaccination during the influenza season 2009/2010 (15 September 2009 to 15 March 2010).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exposed to Arepanrix™ Cohort</intervention_name>
    <description>Demographic characteristics such as age, sex, area of residence, socio-economic status; medical history such as comorbidities, immune status, vaccine indication, receipt of other vaccines or medications and frequency of healthcare contacts, as well as information on pregnancy status and pre-existing conditions will be collected..</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exposed to Arepanrix™ Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Database collection and analysis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Unexposed to Arepanrix™ Cohort</intervention_name>
    <description>Demographic characteristics such as age, sex, area of residence, socio-economic status; medical history such as comorbidities, immune status, vaccine indication, receipt of other vaccines or medications and frequency of healthcare contacts, as well as information on pregnancy status and pre-existing conditions will be collected.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Unexposed to Arepanrix™ Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Database collection and analysis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adults and children above 6 months of age (at the time of vaccination) who normally reside
        in Manitoba, Canada and who had been registered with MH during the study period.

        To ensure sufficient historical data, all participants will be required to have at least
        one year of insurance coverage before the study period (15 September 2009 to 15 March
        2010).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The entire population of Manitoba is considered for inclusion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals less than or equal to 6 months of age;

          -  Having less than one year of insurance coverage before the enrolment period;

          -  Not registered with MH during the enrolment period;

          -  Physician or hospitalization records indicating a diagnosis of any demyelinating
             condition between 1971 (earliest year for which information is available) and the
             index date.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Salah Mahmud, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Community Health Sciences, University of Manitoba</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ascherio A, Munger KL, Lünemann JD. The initiation and prevention of multiple sclerosis. Nat Rev Neurol. 2012 Nov 5;8(11):602-12. doi: 10.1038/nrneurol.2012.198. Epub 2012 Oct 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23045241</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ascherio A, Zhang SM, Hernán MA, Olek MJ, Coplan PM, Brodovicz K, Walker AM. Hepatitis B vaccination and the risk of multiple sclerosis. N Engl J Med. 2001 Feb 1;344(5):327-32.</citation>
    <PMID>11172163</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bansil S, Troiano R, Dowling PC, Cook SD. Measles vaccination does not prevent multiple sclerosis. Neuroepidemiology. 1990;9(5):248-54.</citation>
    <PMID>2087249</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bardage C, Persson I, Ortqvist A, Bergman U, Ludvigsson JF, Granath F. Neurological and autoimmune disorders after vaccination against pandemic influenza A (H1N1) with a monovalent adjuvanted vaccine: population based cohort study in Stockholm, Sweden. BMJ. 2011 Oct 12;343:d5956. doi: 10.1136/bmj.d5956.</citation>
    <PMID>21994316</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Beck CA, Metz LM, Svenson LW, Patten SB. Regional variation of multiple sclerosis prevalence in Canada. Mult Scler. 2005 Oct;11(5):516-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16193887</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Canadian Institute for Health Information (2006). Canadian Classification of Health Interventions (Ottawa, Ontario, Canada).</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Casetta I, Granieri E, Malagù S, Tola MR, Paolino E, Caniatti LM, Govoni V, Monetti VC, Fainardi E. Environmental risk factors and multiple sclerosis: a community-based, case-control study in the province of Ferrara, Italy. Neuroepidemiology. 1994;13(3):120-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8015665</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Confavreux C, Suissa S, Saddier P, Bourdès V, Vukusic S; Vaccines in Multiple Sclerosis Study Group. Vaccinations and the risk of relapse in multiple sclerosis. Vaccines in Multiple Sclerosis Study Group. N Engl J Med. 2001 Feb 1;344(5):319-26.</citation>
    <PMID>11172162</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cosby SL, McQuaid S, Taylor MJ, Bailey M, Rima BK, Martin SJ, Allen IV. Examination of eight cases of multiple sclerosis and 56 neurological and non-neurological controls for genomic sequences of measles virus, canine distemper virus, simian virus 5 and rubella virus. J Gen Virol. 1989 Aug;70 ( Pt 8):2027-36.</citation>
    <PMID>2769228</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cummings P, McKnight B, Greenland S. Matched cohort methods for injury research. Epidemiol Rev. 2003;25:43-50. Review. Erratum in: Epidemiol Rev. 2004 Aug 1;160(3):300.</citation>
    <PMID>12923989</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Currier RD, Meydrech EF, Currier MM. Measles vaccination has had no effect on the occurrence of multiple sclerosis. Arch Neurol. 1996 Dec;53(12):1216.</citation>
    <PMID>8970447</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dean G. How many people in the world have multiple sclerosis? Neuroepidemiology. 1994;13(1-2):1-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8190200</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>DeStefano F, Verstraeten T, Jackson LA, Okoro CA, Benson P, Black SB, Shinefield HR, Mullooly JP, Likosky W, Chen RT; Vaccine Safety Datalink Research Group, National Immunization Program, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Vaccinations and risk of central nervous system demyelinating diseases in adults. Arch Neurol. 2003 Apr;60(4):504-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12707063</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dublin S, Jackson ML, Nelson JC, Weiss NS, Larson EB, Jackson LA. Statin use and risk of community acquired pneumonia in older people: population based case-control study. BMJ. 2009 Jun 16;338:b2137. doi: 10.1136/bmj.b2137.</citation>
    <PMID>19531550</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Elixhauser A, Steiner C, Harris DR, Coffey RM. Comorbidity measures for use with administrative data. Med Care. 1998 Jan;36(1):8-27.</citation>
    <PMID>9431328</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Farez MF, Ysrraelit MC, Fiol M, Correale J. H1N1 vaccination does not increase risk of relapse in multiple sclerosis: a self-controlled case-series study. Mult Scler. 2012 Feb;18(2):254-6. doi: 10.1177/1352458511417253. Epub 2011 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>21828198</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fedson DS, Wajda A, Nicol JP, Hammond GW, Kaiser DL, Roos LL. Clinical effectiveness of influenza vaccination in Manitoba. JAMA. 1993 Oct 27;270(16):1956-61. Erratum in: JAMA 1994 May 25;271(20):1578.</citation>
    <PMID>8411553</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fleiss J L Levin B, Paik M C. (2003). Statistical Methods for Rates and Proportions (3rd ed.) (Formulas 3.18 &amp;3.19). New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Haase AT, Ventura P, Gibbs CJ Jr, Tourtellotte WW. Measles virus nucleotide sequences: detection by hybridization in situ. Science. 1981 May 8;212(4495):672-5.</citation>
    <PMID>7221554</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hammerschlag MR, Ke Z, Lu F, Roblin P, Boman J, Kalman B. Is Chlamydia pneumoniae present in brain lesions of patients with multiple sclerosis? J Clin Microbiol. 2000 Nov;38(11):4274-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11060110</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hardy JR, Holford TR, Hall GC, Bracken MB. Strategies for identifying pregnancies in the automated medical records of the General Practice Research Database. Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf. 2004 Nov;13(11):749-59.</citation>
    <PMID>15386720</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Humphries KH, Rankin JM, Carere RG, Buller CE, Kiely FM, Spinelli JJ. Co-morbidity data in outcomes research: are clinical data derived from administrative databases a reliable alternative to chart review? J Clin Epidemiol. 2000 Apr;53(4):343-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10785564</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kakalacheva K, Lünemann JD. Environmental triggers of multiple sclerosis. FEBS Lett. 2011 Dec 1;585(23):3724-9. doi: 10.1016/j.febslet.2011.04.006. Epub 2011 Apr 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21486562</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kelsey JL, Whittemore AS, Evans AS, Thompson WD (1996). Methods in Observational Epidemiology (2nd Edition) (Table 12-15) Oxford University Press.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kozyrskyj AL, Mustard CA. Validation of an electronic, population-based prescription database. Ann Pharmacother. 1998 Nov;32(11):1152-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9825079</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lix L, Yogendran M, Burchill C, et al., (2006). Defining and Validating Chronic Diseases: An Administrative Data Approach (Winnipeg, Manitoba Centre for Health Policy).</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mahmud S, Hammond G, Elliott L, Hilderman T, Kurbis C, Caetano P, Van Caeseele P, Kettner J, Dawood M. Effectiveness of the pandemic H1N1 influenza vaccines against laboratory-confirmed H1N1 infections: population-based case-control study. Vaccine. 2011 Oct 19;29(45):7975-81. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2011.08.068. Epub 2011 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21884747</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mahmud SM, Van Caeseele P, Hammond G, Kurbis C, Hilderman T, Elliott L. No association between 2008-09 influenza vaccine and influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 virus infection, Manitoba, Canada, 2009. Emerg Infect Dis. 2012 May;18(5):801-10. doi: 10.3201/eid1805.111596.</citation>
    <PMID>22516189</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Marrie RA, Yu N, Blanchard J, Leung S, Elliott L. The rising prevalence and changing age distribution of multiple sclerosis in Manitoba. Neurology. 2010 Feb 9;74(6):465-71. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3181cf6ec0. Epub 2010 Jan 13. Erratum in: Neurology. 2011 Sep 13;77(11):1105.</citation>
    <PMID>20071664</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Marrie RA. Environmental risk factors in multiple sclerosis aetiology. Lancet Neurol. 2004 Dec;3(12):709-18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15556803</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>MCHP Guidelines for Public and Private Sponsorship of Research Projects Accessing the Population Health Data Repository (2011); http://umanitoba.ca/faculties/medicine/units/community_health_sciences/departmental_units/mchp/protocol/media/Private_Sector_Sponsorship_Guidelines.pdf.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>McNicholas N, Chataway J. Relapse risk in patients with multiple sclerosis after H1N1 vaccination, with or without seasonal influenza vaccination. J Neurol. 2011 Aug;258(8):1545-7. doi: 10.1007/s00415-011-5944-x. Epub 2011 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21336784</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nortvedt MW, Riise T, Myhr KM, Nyland HI. Quality of life in multiple sclerosis: measuring the disease effects more broadly. Neurology. 1999 Sep 22;53(5):1098-103.</citation>
    <PMID>10496273</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>OpenEpi: Open Source Epidemiologic Statistics for Public Health, Version 3.01, Released April 4 and revised April 6, 2013, http://www.openepi.com/v37/SampleSize/SSPropor.htm.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Parsons L S (2001). Reducing bias in a propensity score matched-pair sample using greedy matching techniques. Paper presented at: Proceedings of the Twenty-sixth Annual SAS Users group international conference (SAS Institute, Inc.); pp. 214-26.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Persson I, Granath F, Askling J, Ludvigsson JF, Olsson T, Feltelius N. Risks of neurological and immune-related diseases, including narcolepsy, after vaccination with Pandemrix: a population- and registry-based cohort study with over 2 years of follow-up. J Intern Med. 2014 Feb;275(2):172-90. doi: 10.1111/joim.12150. Epub 2013 Nov 10. Erratum in: J Intern Med. 2017 Jan;281(1):102-104.</citation>
    <PMID>24134219</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rao SM, Leo GJ, Ellington L, Nauertz T, Bernardin L, Unverzagt F. Cognitive dysfunction in multiple sclerosis. II. Impact on employment and social functioning. Neurology. 1991 May;41(5):692-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1823781</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Roberts JD, Poffenroth LA, Roos LL, Bebchuk JD, Carter AO. Monitoring childhood immunizations: a Canadian approach. Am J Public Health. 1994 Oct;84(10):1666-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7943493</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Roberts JD, Roos LL, Poffenroth LA, Hassard TH, Bebchuk JD, Carter AO, Law B. Surveillance of vaccine-related adverse events in the first year of life: a Manitoba cohort study. J Clin Epidemiol. 1996 Jan;49(1):51-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8598511</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Roos LL, Mustard CA, Nicol JP, McLerran DF, Malenka DJ, Young TK, Cohen MM. Registries and administrative data: organization and accuracy. Med Care. 1993 Mar;31(3):201-12.</citation>
    <PMID>8450678</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rubin DB. Estimating causal effects from large data sets using propensity scores. Ann Intern Med. 1997 Oct 15;127(8 Pt 2):757-63. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9382394</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Singh H, Demers AA, Nugent Z, Mahmud SM, Kliewer EV, Bernstein CN. Risk of cervical abnormalities in women with inflammatory bowel disease: a population-based nested case-control study. Gastroenterology. 2009 Feb;136(2):451-8. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2008.10.021. Epub 2008 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>18996382</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Singh H, Mahmud SM, Turner D, Xue L, Demers AA, Bernstein CN. Long-term use of statins and risk of colorectal cancer: a population-based study. Am J Gastroenterol. 2009 Dec;104(12):3015-23. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2009.574. Epub 2009 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>19809413</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Skarsgard D, Tonita J. Prostate cancer in Saskatchewan Canada, before and during the PSA era. Cancer Causes Control. 2000 Jan;11(1):79-88.</citation>
    <PMID>10680732</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Therneau T M, Grambsch P M (2000). Modeling Survival Data: Extending the Cox Model (New York, Springer).</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Thompson LH, Mahmud SM, Keynan Y, Blanchard JF, Slater J, Dawood M, Fowke K, Van Caeseele P, Becker M. Serological survey of the novel influenza A H1N1 in inner city Winnipeg, Manitoba, 2009. Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol. 2012 Summer;23(2):65-70.</citation>
    <PMID>23730311</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vrethem M, Malmgren K, Lindh J. A patient with both narcolepsy and multiple sclerosis in association with Pandemrix vaccination. J Neurol Sci. 2012 Oct 15;321(1-2):89-91. doi: 10.1016/j.jns.2012.07.025. Epub 2012 Jul 28.</citation>
    <PMID>22841884</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>WHO Collaborating Centre for Drug Statistics Methodology (2002). ATC Index With DDDs (WHO, Oslo, Norway,).</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cochran SD, Drescher J, Kismödi E, Giami A, García-Moreno C, Atalla E, Marais A, Vieira EM, Reed GM. Proposed declassification of disease categories related to sexual orientation in the International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems (ICD-11). Bull World Health Organ. 2014 Sep 1;92(9):672-9. doi: 10.2471/BLT.14.135541. Epub 2014 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>25378758</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Robinson JR, Young TK, Roos LL, Gelskey DE. Estimating the burden of disease. Comparing administrative data and self-reports. Med Care. 1997 Sep;35(9):932-47.</citation>
    <PMID>9298082</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zarychanski R, Stuart TL, Kumar A, Doucette S, Elliott L, Kettner J, Plummer F. Correlates of severe disease in patients with 2009 pandemic influenza (H1N1) virus infection. CMAJ. 2010 Feb 23;182(3):257-64. doi: 10.1503/cmaj.091884. Epub 2010 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>20093297</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zorzon M, Zivadinov R, Nasuelli D, Dolfini P, Bosco A, Bratina A, Tommasi MA, Locatelli L, Cazzato G. Risk factors of multiple sclerosis: a case-control study. Neurol Sci. 2003 Nov;24(4):242-7.</citation>
    <PMID>14658040</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 12, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 12, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

