<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02367768</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201410060RINA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02367768</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Long-term Outcome Related Prognostic Factor and Biomarkers of Major Trauma Database Analysis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Long-term Outcome Related Prognostic Factor and Biomarkers of Major Trauma Database Analysis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Taiwan University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators were looking for resuscitation management, trauma mechanism, risk factors,
      and de novo biomarkers related to prognosis and long-term outcome for evaluating trauma
      patients besides injury severity score (ISS) guiding the traumatologist. The medicare
      resource could be utilized efficiently along with increasing in the survival and quality of
      lifer (QoL) in major trauma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Severe traumatic injury occupied the sixth leading cause of death in Taiwan, especially in
      young adults. In 2013, there were accidental deaths in every 76 minutes. Not compared with
      the malignancy, heart disease, cerebrovascular disease, diabetes mellitus, or pneumonia Since
      1995, Taiwan replaced a previous patchwork of separate social health insurance funds with one
      single-payer, National Health Insurance (NHI) scheme that is administered by an agency of the
      central government's Department of Health. NHI supported the cost of Critical Illness and
      Injury that numerous patients with major trauma were eligible for preference. However, the
      national medical cost of trauma care, especially in poly-trauma or major trauma were
      impressive: the adjusted national inpatient trauma yearly costs were estimated at
      $37,511,328,659 US dollars; the national insurance cost provided by Bureau of National Health
      Insurance, Department of Health for trauma was over $20,000,000,000 new Taiwan dollars till
      1999 with increasing yearly.

      Recently it flashed bulletins nationwide and overseas for catastrophes, such as aircraft
      accident, wrecks, or underground gas explosions. There was a stirring of interest in life
      support system for major trauma related rescue from dying. Death to trauma is caused by
      costly damages on scene, hemorrhage shock or trauma and massive transfusion related acute
      respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). Extra-Corporeal Membrane Oxygenation (ECMO) can rescue
      life from severe cardiopulmonary failure, but coexisting complication as bleeding and
      coagulopathy restricting the utilization the use in trauma patients. Besides, there were more
      portable ECMO sets making a debut, especially for air transportation. It act now the medical
      transferral for trauma patients under ECMO support. The portable ECMO sets launched with
      possibility, accessibility, and convenience. The issue of life support system utilization,
      long-term outcome, and medical cost-effectiveness for major trauma patients was worth
      discussing no matter in National Taiwan University Hospital (NTUH) trauma database or
      National Health Insurance Research Database (NHIRD).

      Immune system alteration was previously considered the mechanism of post-traumatic stress
      disorder (PTSD). Moreover, an externally experienced traumatic event induces downstream
      alterations in immune function by reducing methylation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Event related survival</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>since major trauma event till trauma related death</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Besides Rehabilitation Complexity Scale (RCS) and Functional Independence Measure (FIM) for traumatic brain injury patients, Glasgow Outcome Scale - Extended (GOS-E) and European Quality of Life Five Dimensions Questionnaire (EQ-5D) are used in concerning longer-term outcome indicators. There are currently no robust measures of patient experience for use in major trauma. Functional status after the major trauma event could be measured using non-clinical outcomes such as return to work, maintenance of education and societal dependency at post injury 3, 6, and 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>over all survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>since major trauma event till death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Wounds and Injuries</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      CRP, IL-6, cortisol / prolactin / growth hormone
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All major trauma (ISS&gt;=16 ) patients sent to NTUH and initiated the trauma team, except
        children younger than 20 years old, pregnancy woman, breast feeding woman, and those
        forbidden legally.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  age ≧ 20

          -  willing to join this study and sign the inform consent form by the patients or their
             contactable families

          -  ISS score ≧ 16, or meet trauma blue or trauma red criteria

          -  response to primary resuscitation

          -  without uncontrolled or major (&gt;1500mL) bleeding.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  active malignancy before the event of major trauma

          -  age &lt;20, pregnancy woman, breast-feeding woman, or mental illness

          -  uncontrolled bleeding with hemoglobin &lt;7g/dL after treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ting-Chun Kuo, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>No.7, Chung San South Road, Taipei City 100, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ying-Ru Chen, Master</last_name>
    <phone>886972651471</phone>
    <email>ronaldinhol@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ying-Ru Chen, Master</last_name>
    <phone>886972651471</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Taiwan University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei City</city>
        <zip>100</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ting-Chun Kuo</last_name>
      <phone>886-97265-3245</phone>
      <email>tina@ntuh.gov.tw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 17, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>trauma blue</keyword>
  <keyword>major trauma</keyword>
  <keyword>cohort study</keyword>
  <keyword>prognostic factor</keyword>
  <keyword>Healing Time</keyword>
  <keyword>Post Operative</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

