<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02362750</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IH-12-11-5255</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02362750</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating Cancer Survivorship Care Models</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluating Cancer Survivorship Care Models</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>George Washington University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>George Washington University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Evaluating Cancer Survivorship Care Models project is an innovative 3-year study that is
      collecting data to help understand how to best deliver follow-up care to cancer survivors.
      Cancer is a complex disease requiring complex treatments that can cause lasting impacts after
      treatment ends. Some patients face physical, psychosocial, spiritual and/or practical
      challenges as they adjust to life after cancer. Fortunately, health care providers have begun
      to focus on the consequences of cancer and its treatment and are more actively working with
      cancer survivors to manage post-treatment needs and care.

      Led by the George Washington University and funded by the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research
      Institute, this project brings together representatives from the Commission on Cancer, the
      Cancer Support Community, LIVESTRONG and the American Cancer Society as well as cancer
      survivors and healthcare professionals to better understand how different strategies or
      models of care impact outcomes that are most important to cancer survivors. The project will
      focus on survivors of breast, prostate and colorectal cancers and will be relevant for
      understanding the needs and preferences of survivors of other cancers as well. The emphasis
      is on patient-centered outcomes, which are outcomes that are most significant to patients,
      such as patient satisfaction and quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Evaluating Cancer Survivorship Care Models Study Overview and Research Design

      Cancer is a complex disease requiring complex treatments that can cause lasting impacts after
      treatment ends. Some patients face lasting physical, psychosocial, spiritual and/or practical
      challenges as they adjust to life after cancer. Fortunately, health care clinicians have
      begun to focus on the consequences of cancer and its treatment and are more actively working
      with cancer survivors to manage post-treatment needs and care.

      The Evaluating Cancer Survivorship Care Models project is a groundbreaking 3-year comparative
      effectiveness research (CER) study that examines how to best deliver follow-up care to cancer
      survivors. This project is led by the George Washington University and funded by the
      Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute. A key component of the project is the use of a
      stakeholder Advisory Board chaired by a cancer survivor who serves as a senior advisor to the
      research team. The Advisory Board includes survivors, survivor advocates, clinicians, health
      care professionals and advisors from stakeholders across myriad facets of cancer care,
      including the Cancer Support Community, LIVESTRONG, the Commission on Cancer, and the
      American Cancer Society. These organizations are critical to the success of the project.

      The study is innovative in its focus on patient-centered outcomes. The first phase of the
      project employed a mixed methods approach including a secondary analysis of existing data
      from 4 national surveys, focus groups with cancer survivors, an environmental scan of
      existing survivorship programs and a national survey of cancer survivors to develop an
      outcomes tool and a prospective observational CER study. Based on results from the first
      phase, the study team at the George Washington University (GW) developed a
      patient-prioritized index to identify services and components of care that patients equate
      with high quality survivorship care.

      Three models of survivorship care at Commission on Cancer-accredited institutions were
      identified through the environmental scan. In the CER phase of the study, each survivorship
      care model will serve as a comparator for the other two models. Patients in the CER study
      population will be adults who have been diagnosed with non-metastatic breast, prostate or
      colorectal cancer and completed active treatment. Patient-reported outcomes will be assessed
      at three points in the project: at baseline (immediately prior to and immediately following a
      post-treatment survivorship visit), 3 months post-visit and 6 months post-visit.
      Multivariable analyses including repeated measures and mixed-effect regression modeling will
      be used to control for systematic differences across the groups, which would further increase
      the validity of our results. Using the newly-developed index, the comparative effectiveness
      study will measure the quality of programs according to what patients have identified as most
      important to them.

      The investigators have launched the CER phase of the study and are enrolling high-performing
      survivorship programs. Our pool of invited participants consists of Commission on
      Cancer-accredited sites with clinical survivorship care programs that meet the following
      eligibility criteria:

        -  Provide services to survivors of breast, prostate or colorectal cancer

        -  Have demonstrated a high performance level on incorporating elements of survivorship
           care into clinical care delivery

        -  See at least 60 new survivors yearly

        -  Includes the most common characteristics related to delivery of survivorship care

      During the CER study, data will be gathered from survivorship program administrators,
      patients and survivorship care clinicians. Survivorship program administrators will complete
      an interview and survey to examine how survivorship programs are organized and identify key
      characteristics of programs to determine which factors are most influential in delivering
      high quality post-treatment survivorship care. Patients will complete surveys measuring
      patient-centered outcomes: health-related quality of life; self-efficacy; satisfaction;
      health care utilization and a newly developed measure of quality of survivorship care as
      prioritized by patients. Clinicians will complete surveys on the services offered during
      participating patients' initial post-treatment survivorship visit. Together, this data will
      allow the GW study team to understand successful strategies for transforming the care
      delivery system to be more responsive to patient needs.

      In the third and final phase, this project will generate critical data for a variety of
      decision-makers related to care for post-treatment cancer survivors and will result in
      evidence-based guidance for how to organize and deliver post-treatment care. The GW study
      team seeks to provide recommendations on survivorship care delivery best practices; develop
      tools for improving survivorship programs and care delivery from both clinician and patient
      perspectives; and to widely disseminate findings to a variety of stakeholders, including
      survivors and their families, clinicians, survivorship care program leaders, payers,
      policymakers and others.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-centered outcomes for cancer survivors</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be surveyed before their survivorship visit, within 1 week after survivorship visit, 3 months after survivorship visit and 6 months after survivorship visit</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will assess the following specific outcomes across different cancer survivorship care models for the comparative effectiveness evaluation: a Patient Index and patients' satisfaction, health-related quality of life, ability to manage their cancer post-treatment and appropriate health care utilization. Each cancer survivorship care model identified through the study will serve as a comparator for the other two models.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">992</enrollment>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participating Program Administrators</arm_group_label>
    <description>Eligible survivorship program administrators at selected Commission on Cancer-accredited institutions will complete an organizational interview and organizational survey.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participating Cancer Survivors</arm_group_label>
    <description>Survivors receiving follow-up care surveys at selected Commission on Cancer-accredited institutions will complete four surveys:
Survivor Survey (1): Pre-Visit Baseline Survivor Survey (2): 1 Week Post-Visit Survivor Survey (3): 3 Months Post-Visit Survivor Survey (4): 6 Months Post-Visit</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participating Clinicians</arm_group_label>
    <description>Survivorship clinicians from clinical survivorship programs at selected Commission on Cancer-accredited institutions will complete a clinician survey.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Organizational Interview</intervention_name>
    <description>Survivorship program leaders will participate in a phone-based organizational interview regarding the organization of the clinical survivorship care program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participating Program Administrators</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Organizational Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>Survivorship program leaders will participate in a brief web-based organizational survey regarding the organization of the clinical survivorship care program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participating Program Administrators</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survivor Survey (1): Pre-Visit Baseline</intervention_name>
    <description>Survivors will participate in a baseline survey regarding their satisfaction, health-related quality of life, ability to manage their cancer post-treatment and appropriate health care utilization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participating Cancer Survivors</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survivor Survey (2): Post-Visit</intervention_name>
    <description>Survivors will participate in a survey within one week after their survivorship visit regarding their satisfaction, health-related quality of life, ability to manage their cancer post-treatment and appropriate health care utilization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participating Cancer Survivors</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survivor Survey (3): 3 Month Post-Visit</intervention_name>
    <description>Survivors will participate in a survey three months after their survivorship visit regarding their satisfaction, health-related quality of life, ability to manage their cancer post-treatment and appropriate health care utilization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participating Cancer Survivors</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Survivor Survey (4): 6 Month Post-Visit</intervention_name>
    <description>Survivors will participate in a survey six months after their survivorship visit regarding their satisfaction, health-related quality of life, ability to manage their cancer post-treatment and appropriate health care utilization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participating Cancer Survivors</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinician Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>Survivorship program clinicians will complete a survey for each survivor who enrolls in the study indicating services provided through the survivorship visit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participating Clinicians</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Phase 1 of our study focused on developing instruments to conduct comparative effectiveness
        research. The investigators analyzed three large national studies of cancer survivors;
        conducted focus groups across the country with adult survivors of breast, prostate or
        colorectal cancer; surveyed Commission on Cancer accredited institutions regarding
        provision of survivorship care and surveyed a nationally representative sample of adult
        cancer survivors. In phase II, the investigators will conduct surveys with survivorship
        program leaders at eligible Commission on Cancer accredited institutions; adult survivors
        of breast, prostate or colorectal cancer; and the survivorship program clinicians providing
        their care.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria for the CER component:

        Survivorship program administrators oversee survivorship programs which:

          -  See at least 60 new survivors of non-metastatic breast, prostate or colorectal cancer
             or survivors of any type of cancer yearly

          -  Represent one of the clinical survivorship care models identified in our environmental
             scan

          -  Indicate a high performance level on incorporating elements of survivorship care into
             clinical care delivery.

        Survivors:

          -  English-speaking survivors of non-metastatic breast, prostate or colorectal cancers

          -  Completed planned active treatment (chemotherapy, radiation, and/or surgery) with the
             exception of hormonal medication, aromatase inhibitors or other maintenance therapy

          -  Diagnosed at 18 years old or older

          -  First appointment with the survivorship program is planned but has not yet been
             completed

        Survivorship program clinicians:

        • Must be providing services for eligible survivors who have completed their first visit
        with the survivorship program and are participating in the study.

        Exclusion criteria for the CER component:

        Survivorship program administrators:

          -  Programs with fewer than at least 60 new survivors yearly

          -  Do not provide services to adult survivors of non-metastatic breast, prostate or
             colorectal cancer or survivors of any type of cancer

          -  Do not represent one of the three models of clinical survivorship care as identified
             in our environmental scan

          -  Do not indicate a high performance level on incorporating elements of survivorship
             care into clinical care delivery

        Survivors:

          -  Received diagnosis for cancer that was not breast, prostate or colorectal cancer

          -  Not English-speaking

          -  Currently undergoing active treatment (defined as chemotherapy, radiation, and/or
             surgery)

          -  Cancer has metastasized

          -  Diagnosed at under 18 years old

          -  Have completed first appointment with the survivorship program

        Men will be excluded from the breast cancer arm of the study. Women will be excluded from
        the prostate cancer arm of the study.

        Survivorship program clinicians:

        • Not providing services for eligible survivors.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>K. Holly Mead, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The George Washington University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The George Washington University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20036</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://smhs.gwu.edu/gwci/research/evaluating-cancer-survivorship-care-models</url>
    <description>Evaluating Cancer Survivorship Care Models Project Website</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cancer.org/acs/groups/content/@epidemiologysurveilance/documents/document/acspc-033876.pdf</url>
    <description>American Cancer Society. Cancer Treatment and Survivorship Facts &amp; Figures 2012-2013. Atlanta: American Cancer Society; 2012.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.facs.org/cancer/coc/cocprogramstandards2012.pdf</url>
    <description>American College of Surgeons' Commission on Cancer. Cancer program standards 2012: ensuring patient-centered care. Accessed December 12, 2012.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK196214/</url>
    <description>Viswanathan M, Halpern M, Swinson Evans T, et al. Models of Cancer Survivorship Care [Internet]. Rockville (MD): Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (US); 2014 Mar. (Technical Briefs, No. 14.)</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 21, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 13, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 20, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 20, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 22, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>comparative effectiveness</keyword>
  <keyword>survivorship</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research</keyword>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 19, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

