<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02360020</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCTCM03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02360020</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The XLIMUS-DES in Very Complex Lesions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Performance of the XLIMUS Sirolimus-eluting Coronary Stent In Very Complex Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clinica Mediterranea</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Clinica Mediterranea</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stent delivery failure occurs in 4% of all percutaneous coronary interventions (PCI) and &gt;90%
      of these failures are due to vessel tortuosity and/or calcification. The XLIMUS eluting
      coronary stent (CARDIONOVUM GmbH, Bonn, Germany) is a new type of endovascular prostheses
      characterised by better mechanical properties than traditional DES. This is a prospective,
      non-randomized, single-center pilot study, aiming to evaluate the performance of the XLIMUS
      DES in severely complex coronary lesions in real-world clinical practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All consecutive patients who will undergo elective PCI in native coronary arteries at the
      Clinica Mediterranea (Naples, Italy) will be considered for eligility. Study participants
      wiil require to have symptomatic ischemic heart disease attributable to critical (that is,
      &gt;70% visual estimate) stenotic lesions of native coronary arteries. Inclusion criteria in
      this pilot study are 1) chronic total occlusion (CTO), 2) severe target vessel calcification,
      and 3) severe target vessel tortuosity. CTO is defined as the presence of TIMI 0 flow within
      the occluded segment and angiographic or clinical evidence or high likelihood of an occlusion
      duration of ≥3 months. Calcification is defined severe when larger than 3x vessel diameter,
      and comprising the vessel wall totally in two perpendicular views. Tortuosity is defined
      severe when it satisfies the following criteria: one or more bends of 90° or more, or three
      or more bends of 45-90° proximal to the diseased segment.

      200 patients will be enrolled into the study. Stents will be implanted according to current
      clinical practice. Techniques attempted for facilitating stent delivery in such a complex
      lesions are: maximize guide catheter support, optimize predilatation of the stenosis, use of
      a stiffer guidewire. Specific tricks include: a) buddy-wire; anchoring balloon; GuideLiner
      catheter. In case of severe calcification, rotational atherectomy will be electively
      performed with the Rotablator® system (Boston Scientific Corporation, Natick, MA, U.S.A.).
      Following stent implantation, postdilatation will be performed in all instances with a
      non-compliant balloon. All patients will receive aspirin 325 mg and clopidogrel (75 mg daily)
      before stent deployment, with a loading dose (600 mg of clopidogrel) given to patients not
      pretreated. All patients will receive 70 IU/Kg intra-arterial bolus of unfractionated heparin
      in order to achieve and activated clotting time &gt;250 seconds. Glycoprotein IIb/IIIa
      inhibitors will be administered according to operator preference. Estimated glomerular
      filtration rate (eGFR) will be calculated by applying the Levey Modification of Diet in Renal
      Disease (MDRD) formula. Chronic kidney disease was defined as a eGFR &lt;60 ml/min/1.73 m2 .

      XLIMUS eluting-stent is made of cobalt chromium L 605 and the stent is available in a 6-, 8-,
      or 10-cell structure design (closed cell architecture). The struts thickness is 73µm. The
      6-cell design is for stenting of coronary artery diameter of 2.25mm-2.50mm, 8-cell structure
      is used for stenting of 2.75-3.50 mm artery diameters, and the 10-cell is for larger artery
      diameter lesions (up to 5mm). The XLIMUS has an innovative hydrophilic-coated shaft and an
      extra-low tip profile (crossing profile = 0.90 mm) to access the most tortuous lesions. The
      highly biocompatible polylactid acid (PLLA) drug containing release matrix degrades smoothly
      and provides an optimal release kinetic profile. Within 30 days, about 70% of the
      anti-proliferative drug is distributed into the surrounding arterial tissue of the stent
      struts, ensuring a highly effective inhibition of smooth muscle cell migration and
      proliferation. Pharmacokinetic study result confirm sustained anti-proliferative drug
      efficacy up to 120 days.

      The primary objective of the study is the assessment of the clinical performance of the
      XLILMUS DES, using the following criteria 1) device success, defined as the ability to insert
      the stent into the target lesion and the attainment of &lt;20% residual stenosis (by visual
      estimate), 2) lesion success, defined as attainment of &lt;20% residual stenosis of the target
      lesion using any percutaneous method, and 3) procedural success, defined as lesion success
      without any in-hospital and MACE.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stent Performance</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective of the study was the assessment of the clinical performance of the XLIMUS DES, using the following criteria 1) device success, defined as the ability to insert the stent into the target lesion and the attainment of &lt;20% residual stenosis (by visual estimate), 2) lesion success, defined as attainment of &lt;20% residual stenosis of the target lesion using any percutaneous method, and 3) procedural success, defined as lesion success without any in-hospital Man 30-day MACE</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inhospital, 30-day and 1-year MACE</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Major adverse cardiac events included death of any cause, nonfatal myocardial infarction, and repeated revascularization by PCI or surgery occurring within 30-day and 1-year. Myocardial infarction was defined as the presence of pathological and new Q waves on an ECG or as an increase in creatine kinase-myocardial band level to &gt;3 times the upper limit of normal (ULN). Periprocedural myocardial infarction was defined as an increase of troponin I ≥5 times ULN. Target lesion revascularization was defined as a clinically-driven repeat percutaneous coronary angioplasty or coronary artery bypass surgery. Stent thrombosis was defined according to the Academic Research Consortium definitions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Atherosclerosis Due to Calcified Coronary Lesion</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Total Occlusion of Coronary Artery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>XLimus patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>participants must have symptomatic ischemic heart disease attributable to critical (that is, &gt;70% visual estimate) stenotic lesions of native coronary arteries. Inclusion criteria are 1) chronic total occlusion (CTO), 2) severe calcification, and 3) severe tortuosity. CTO is defined as the presence of TIMI 0 flow within the occluded segment and angiographic or clinical evidence of an occlusion duration of ≥3 months. Calcification is defined severe when larger than 3x vessel diameter, and comprising the vessel wall totally in two perpendicular views. Tortuosity is defined severe when: one or more bends &gt;= 90°, or three or more bends of 45-90° proximal to the diseased segment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>XLimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Techniques attempted for facilitating stent delivery in such a complex lesions are: maximize guide catheter support, optimize predilatation of the stenosis, use of a stiffer guidewire. Specific tricks include: a) buddy-wire; anchoring balloon; GuideLiner catheter. In case of severe calcification, rotational atherectomy was electively performed with the Rotablator® system (Boston Scientific Corporation, Natick, MA, U.S.A.). Following stent implantation, postdilatation is performed in all instances with a non-compliant balloon</description>
    <arm_group_label>XLimus patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  chronic total occlusion (CTO)

          -  severe calcification

          -  severe tortuosity

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • coronary artery lesions non satisfying the inclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlo Briguori, Md, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinica Mediterranea</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinica Mediterranea</name>
      <address>
        <city>Naples</city>
        <zip>80121</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nikolsky E, Gruberg L, Pechersky S, Kapeliovich M, Grenadier E, Amikam S, Boulos M, Suleiman M, Markiewicz W, Beyar R. Stent deployment failure: reasons, implications, and short- and long-term outcomes. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2003 Jul;59(3):324-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12822150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feldman T. Tricks for overcoming difficult stent delivery. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 1999 Nov;48(3):285-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10525229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernandes V, Kałuza GL, Godlewski B, Li G, Raizner AE. Novel technique for stent delivery in tortuous coronary arteries: report of three cases. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2002 Apr;55(4):485-90.</citation>
    <PMID>11948896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashikaga T, Sakurai K, Satoh Y. Tools &amp; Techniques: stent delivery in distal lesions. EuroIntervention. 2010 Nov;6(5):660-1. doi: 10.4244/EIJV6I5A109.</citation>
    <PMID>21044922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumar S, Gorog DA, Secco GG, Di Mario C, Kukreja N. The GuideLiner &quot;child&quot; catheter for percutaneous coronary intervention - early clinical experience. J Invasive Cardiol. 2010 Oct;22(10):495-8.</citation>
    <PMID>20944191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rieu R, Barragan P, Garitey V, Roquebert PO, Fuseri J, Commeau P, Sainsous J. Assessment of the trackability, flexibility, and conformability of coronary stents: a comparative analysis. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2003 Aug;59(4):496-503.</citation>
    <PMID>12891615</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt W, Lanzer P, Behrens P, Topoleski LD, Schmitz KP. A comparison of the mechanical performance characteristics of seven drug-eluting stent systems. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2009 Feb 15;73(3):350-60. doi: 10.1002/ccd.21832.</citation>
    <PMID>19085917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morice MC, Colombo A, Meier B, Serruys P, Tamburino C, Guagliumi G, Sousa E, Stoll HP; REALITY Trial Investigators. Sirolimus- vs paclitaxel-eluting stents in de novo coronary artery lesions: the REALITY trial: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2006 Feb 22;295(8):895-904.</citation>
    <PMID>16493102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lohavanichbutr K, Webb JG, Carere RG, Solankhi N, Jarochowski M, D'yachkova Y, Dodek A. Mechanisms, management, and outcome of failure of delivery of coronary stents. Am J Cardiol. 1999 Mar 1;83(5):779-81, A9.</citation>
    <PMID>10080438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cantor WJ, Lazzam C, Cohen EA, Bowman KA, Dolman S, Mackie K, Natarajan MK, Strauss BH. Failed coronary stent deployment. Am Heart J. 1998 Dec;136(6):1088-95.</citation>
    <PMID>9842025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mortier P, De Beule M, Segers P, Verdonck P, Verhegghe B. Virtual bench testing of new generation coronary stents. EuroIntervention. 2011 Jul;7(3):369-76. doi: 10.4244/EIJV7I3A62.</citation>
    <PMID>21729840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gyöngyösi M, Yang P, Khorsand A, Glogar D. Longitudinal straightening effect of stents is an additional predictor for major adverse cardiac events. Austrian Wiktor Stent Study Group and European Paragon Stent Investigators. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2000 May;35(6):1580-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10807464</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Briguori C, Visconti G, Focaccio A, Donahue M. Performance of the XLIMUS sirolimus-eluting coronary stent in very complex lesions. Minerva Cardioangiol. 2014 Feb;62(1):1-8.</citation>
    <PMID>24500212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Clinica Mediterranea</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carlo Briguori</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief of Invasive Cardiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>coronary stent</keyword>
  <keyword>outcome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We plan to present and publish the results in an international journal of interventional cardiology</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

