<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01120795</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HREC 2000.175</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01120795</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pegylated Interferon and Ribavirin in Hepatitis C Patients on Opioid Pharmacotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pegylated Interferon Alfa-2a Plus Ribavirin for Patients With Chronic Hepatitis c Virus on Opioid Pharmacotherapy: Virological and Psychological Outcomes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Melbourne Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The University of New South Wales</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Western Hospital, Australia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Monash University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hoffmann-La Roche</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Melbourne Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see if treatment of chronic hepatitis C in people who are on
      opiate replacement therapy such as methadone or buprenorphine (including patient who still
      inject drugs) is safe and effective.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It is estimated that in excess of 170 million people worldwide are infected with the
      hepatitis C virus (HCV) resulting in 1.4 million deaths annually. In developed countries HCV
      is most commonly transmitted through injecting drug use (IDU) with estimates suggesting up to
      80-90% of incident cases are due to unsafe injecting practices. Infection results in chronic
      infection in around 75% of cases and it is these patients who subsequently develop the
      life-threatening complications of liver failure and hepatocellular carcinoma due to
      progressive fibrosis.

      Current standard of care consists of a combination of pegylated interferon and ribavirin
      which results in sustained virological response rates (SVR, defined as undetectable HCV RNA
      24 weeks post treatment) in 54-63% of patients. This is strongly dependent on viral genotype
      with genotype 1 patients achieving lower SVR rates compared to genotype 2 and 3. These
      therapies are however associated with significant side effects, most notably psychiatric.
      Depression, anxiety and irritability are common and of concern is the attendant risk of
      suicidality in patients with a chronic illness in which depression is particularly common.
      Mood disorders have been reported to occur in up to 50% patients on therapy and can result in
      dose reductions and discontinuation in 40% and 20% patients respectively.

      While more effective therapies have become available for the treatment of chronic HCV, they
      have not been largely utilised in patients actively injecting. This is due to concerns about
      potential poor adherence to treatment regimens, reinfection due to ongoing IDU, increased
      incidence of concomitant alcohol abuse, potential for increased side effects (especially
      psychiatric), concerns about pregnancy with ribavirin use due to non-adherence to
      contraception as well as active discrimination by practitioners. There are however
      considerable potential advantages including: improvement in the health of the infected
      individual, potential for decreasing the burden of disease to the community with its
      attendant costs as well as the potential for impact on transmission and its inherent
      potential public health benefits.

      This multicentre study was conducted to determine the response rates as well as the AE
      profile and the psychiatric impact of therapy in a population with chronic hepatitis C (CHC)
      who were receiving opiate pharmacotherapy, many of who were still injecting.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2006</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sustained virological response</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks post cessation of HCV therapy</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">55</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Hepatitis C</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>pegylated interferon and ribavirin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Anti hepatitis C agents</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pegylated interferon and ribavirin</intervention_name>
    <description>Pegylated interferon 180 ug subcutaneous per week Ribavirin 1000-1200 mg /day for genotype 1 and 800 mg /day orally for genotype non 1 Duration: 48 weeks for genotype 1 and 24 weeks for gentoype non 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>pegylated interferon and ribavirin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pegasys and Copegus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pegylated interferon and ribavirin</intervention_name>
    <description>Pegylated interferon 180 ug/ week subcutaneously Ribavrin 1000-1200 mg /day for genotype 1 and 800 mg/day orally for genotype 2 and 3 Treatment duration 48 weeks for genotype 1 and 24 weeks for genotypes 2 and 3</description>
    <arm_group_label>pegylated interferon and ribavirin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pegasys and Copegus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18 years of age or older

          2. on opioid substitution therapy (methadone or buprenorphine)

          3. serologic evidence of chronic hepatitis C infection determined by a detectable
             anti-HCV antibody for 6 months or greater with evidence of detectable HCV RNA

          4. elevated ALT on at least two occasions at least one month apart within the past 6
             months, with at least one during the screening period preceding the initiation of
             study drug dosing.

          5. HCV treatment-naïve

          6. Liver biopsy findings consistent with the diagnosis of chronic hepatitis C infection
             (unless contraindicated due to a bleeding disorder)

          7. Compensated liver disease (Child-Pugh Grade A clinical classification).

          8. All fertile males and females receiving ribavirin were required to be using two forms
             of effective contraception during treatment and during the 6 months after treatment

          9. Women of child bearing potential were required to have a negative urine or blood
             pregnancy test documented within the 24-hour period prior to the first dose of study
             drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Women who were pregnant, breastfeeding or planning a pregnancy

          2. Male partners of women who were pregnant

          3. Patients who had previously received therapy with any systemic anti-neoplastic or
             immunomodulatory treatment (including supraphysiologic doses of steroids and
             radiation) 6 months prior to the first dose of study drug

          4. Recipients of any investigational drug 4 weeks or 5 half lives, whichever was longer,
             prior to the first dose of study drug

          5. A positive test at screening for anti-HAV IgM Ab, HBsAg, anti-HBc IgM Ab, anti-HIV Ab

          6. A history or other evidence of a medical condition associated with chronic liver
             disease other than HCV

          7. Haemoglobin &lt;12 g/dL in women or &lt;13 g/dL in men, a neutrophil count &lt;1500 cells/mm3
             or platelet count &lt;90,000 cells/mm3 at screening and serum creatinine level &gt;1.5 times
             the upper limit of normal at screening.)

          8. A history of a severe seizure disorder or current anticonvulsant use

          9. Patients with a history of immunologically-mediated disease, chronic pulmonary disease
             associated with functional limitation, severe cardiac disease, coronary artery
             disease, cerebrovascular disease, major organ transplantation or other evidence of
             severe illness, malignancy, or any other conditions which would make the patient, in
             the opinion of the investigator, unsuitable for the study

         10. Patients with a history of thyroid disease which is poorly controlled on prescribed
             medications

         11. Evidence of severe retinopathy

         12. Evidence of excessive substance abuse as judged by the investigator

         13. Patients with an increased baseline risk for anaemia (e.g. thalassaemia,
             spherocytosis, history of gastrointestinal bleeding, etc) or for whom anemia would be
             medically problematic.

         14. Patients with a history of severe psychiatric disease (defined as acute phase of
             schizophrenia or bipolar disorder manic, mixed or depressive phase, severe anorexia,
             history of severe multiple episodes of self harm, currently screening as high or
             moderate suicide risk, current major depressive episode or current psychosis of any
             cause at screening)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph J Sasadeusz, MBBS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Melbourne Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nepean Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sydney</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Vincents Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sydney</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Footscray</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3011</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Melbourne Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3050</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 11, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 27, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 27, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr Joe Sasadeusz</name_title>
    <organization>Victorian Infectious Diseases Service, Royal Melbourne Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Interferons</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ribavirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peginterferon alfa-2a</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

