<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01125228</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>880172</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>88-I-0172</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01125228</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Zidovudine vs. Zidovudine Plus Alpha Interferon vs. Interferon for Treatment of HIV</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase III Study With Long-Term Follow-Up of Zidovudine Versus Zidovudine and Alpha-Interferon Versus Alpha-Interferon in Patients With Early HIV Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will compare the effectiveness of zidovudine (AZT) alone vs. zidovudine plus
      interferon (IFN) vs. interferon alone in reducing HIV viral load, lessening immune system
      deterioration, and increasing the time to development of the first opportunistic infection in
      HIV-infected patients.

      HIV-infected persons 18 years of age and older with a T4 lymphocyte count of 500/mm3 or more
      and no current opportunistic infections may be eligible for this study. Candidates will be
      screened with a medical history, physical examination, blood tests, chest X-ray,
      electrocardiogram, urinalysis, and, for patients with Kaposi s sarcoma lesions, measurement,
      photographs, and biopsy of lesions.

      Patients will be assigned to receive treatment with either zidovudine alone, zidovudine plus
      interferon or interferon alone. They will continue treatment until one of the following
      occurs:

        -  Unacceptable side effects, despite dose modifications

        -  Development of an opportunistic infection

        -  Decrease in CD4 count by 20 percent or to an absolute count of less than 200/mm3

        -  Rapid progression of Kaposi s sarcoma lesions, requiring alternative therapy

        -  A decision is made to terminate the study

      Patients will be followed long term for viral load, immune function, development of
      opportunistic infections, disease progression, and survival.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Initial Study: THREE ARM (INTERVENTIONAL) STUDY

      This randomized, controlled phase III protocol, initiated in 1988, was the first study to
      examine intervention with antiretroviral therapy and alpha interferon in patients with HIV
      infection. It evaluated the relative efficacy of zidovudine (AZT) vs. AZT + alpha interferon
      (IFN) vs. IFN in increasing time to first opportunistic infection, reducing HIV viremia, and
      lessening immune system deterioration in HIV-infected persons.

      For the AZT alone arm, AZT dosing consisted ofthe standard regimen of 200 mg q4h. Persons on
      the AZT + IFN combination arm received AZT 100 mg q4h with IFN beginning at 1 million units
      qd, escalating up to 2.5 million units at 2 weeks, then in increments of 2.5 million units
      every 2 weeks. Patients on the IFN-alone arm began therapy at 5 million units qd and
      escalated in 2.5 million unit increments every 2 weeks, unless escalations were precluded by
      toxicity. Patients who had evidence of HIV infection and a CD4 countgreater than or equal to
      500 were randomized to one of the three treatment groups. Patients were treated with their
      assigned medication until intolerable toxicity, opportunistic infection, or progressive
      Kaposi's sarcoma developed, or CD4 count declined to less than 200/mm(3).

      Our statistically significant findings during this pre-HAART era study showed that
      interferon-alpha decreased HIV RNA viral load levels, both alone and in combination with AZT.

      Long-Term Follow-up: EXTENSION PHASE (NATURAL HISTORY STUDY)

      Once the intervention phase was completed, this protocol entered a long-term follow-up phase
      and evolved into a longitudinal natural history study. As of 2013 this work earned the
      distinction of following a cohort for 25 years or more. It continues to serve as an important
      source of data regarding the long-term outcomes of patients receiving anti-HIV treatment, and
      to provide information on the long-term consequences of therapy. In addition, stored blood
      and cells enable the study of cutting edge research questions, such as those related to
      immune activation, with new state-of-the-art laboratory assays.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 15, 1988</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalizations; AIDS events; Non AIDS events; CD4 and VL; Deaths</measure>
    <time_frame>Annually</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">180</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infection</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Over 18 years of age.

        T4 lymphocyte count greater than or equal to 500/mm3.

        Infection with HIV as documented by positive ELISA and Western blot and positive HIV
        culture or positive p24 antigen or positive polymerase chain reaction.

        Absence of current opportunistic infection (defined for purposes of this study as:
        candidiasis, cryptosporidiosis, mycobacterial infection, persistent herpes simplex
        infection, isosporiasis, cytomegalovirus infection, toxoplasmosis, pneumocystosis,
        salmonellosis, and cryptococcosis). Routine clinical methods and observations were
        performed to exclude such patients.

        Afebrile (Temperature less the 38 degrees Centigrade orally) without antipyretics for at
        least 72 hours prior to enrollment.

        Performance status 0, 1, or 2.

        Relatively stable clinical condition, with no deterioration of performance status in the
        month prior to enrollment.

        Ability to give informed consent and willing to comply with all procedures and visits
        scheduled.

        Suitability of I.V. access for the scheduled blood tests.

        Normal renal function as defined by BUN less than or equal to 30 and creatinine less than
        or equal to 1.5.

        Normal hepatic function with transaminases and alkaline phosphatase less than 5 times the
        upper limit of normal range.

        Hemoglobin greater than or equal to 10 gm/dl, total granulocyte count greater than or equal
        to 1250/mm(3), platelet count greater than or equal to 125,000/mm(3).

        No previous therapy for KS within the month prior to enrollment, and no prior exposure to
        investigational agents. Prior exposure to AZT did not disqualify a patient; however
        patients were stratified on this basis.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients with malignancy other than Kaposi's sarcoma were specifically excluded from this
        study.

        Pregnant women, nursing mothers, or women of childbearing potential who were not employing
        effective means of contraception or abstinence.

        Patients actively using illicit drugs.

        Patients receiving systemically and potentially myelosuppressive drugs (such as TMP/SMX,
        pyrimethamine-sulfa or DHPG), nephrotoxic agents (such as amphotericin B or
        aminoglycosides), or cytotoxic or experimental chemotherapy.

        Patients with a history of significant depressive disorder.

        Patients with a history of an AIDS-defining opportunistic infection.

        Subsequent Exclusion Criteria (Post Enrollment)

        After enrollment, a patient was excluded from further participation in the study for any of
        the following reasons:

        Serious infection not cleared by antibiotic therapy. The occurrence of a life-threatening
        infection, whether or not considered to be opportunistic, will prompt a discontinuation of
        therapy during the infection and for 2 weeks following its successful resolution. Therapy
        was re-initiated unless (1) in the investigator's judgment re-treatment with either or both
        of the study medications would be contraindicated for other reasons or (2) therapy had been
        held for more than 6 weeks.

        Decrease in percent CD4 to less than 20 percent or in absolute CD4 count to less than
        200/mm(3) on 3 consecutive blood tests.

        Systemic allergic reaction to either study medication, characterized by angioedema,
        bronchial constriction, or anaphylaxis.

        It was the principal investigator's judgment that the patient was too ill to continue in
        the trial.

        Toxicity necessitating withdrawal.

        Patient non-compliance: A patient not taking medication as directed or not keeping
        appointments was not allowed to continue on this study.

        Rapid or life-threatening progression of KS such that the principal investigator believed
        other therapies would be in the patient's best interest.

        Voluntary withdrawal: A patient could remove himself from study at any time. The patient
        was allowed to withdraw without prejudice.

        Termination of the study by the principal investigator, sponsor, or the FDA.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary E Wright, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_1988-I-0172.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tavel JA, Huang CY, Shen J, Metcalf JA, Dewar R, Shah A, Vasudevachari MB, Follmann DA, Herpin B, Davey RT, Polis MA, Kovacs J, Masur H, Lane HC. Interferon-alpha produces significant decreases in HIV load. J Interferon Cytokine Res. 2010 Jul;30(7):461-4. doi: 10.1089/jir.2009.0090.</citation>
    <PMID>20235638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 11, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 18, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>AIDS</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiretroviral</keyword>
  <keyword>Kaposi's Sarcoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Interferons</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Zidovudine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interferon-alpha</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

