<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01128842</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3144A1-1122</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>B1891018</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01128842</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Of Neratinib (HKI-272) And Capecitabine In Japanese With Solid Tumor</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-Label Study Of Neratinib (HKI-272) In Combination With Capecitabine In Japanese Subject With Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Puma Biotechnology, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Puma Biotechnology, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label, phase 1 study of ascending single cohort of neratinib (HKI-272)
      combination with capecitabine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary objectives are to assess the safety and tolerability of neratinib in combination with capecitabine in Japanese subjects with advanced solid tumors, and to confirm the recommended dose of the regimen.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary objectives of this study are to obtain preliminary antitumor activity for neratinib combined with capecitabine and to obtain Pharmacokinetic (PK) information</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">7</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Malignant Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neratinib + Capecitabine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Neratinib + Capecitabine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neratinib + Capecitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Neratinib: 240 mg, continuous daily OD Capecitabine: 1500 mg/m^2, BID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neratinib + Capecitabine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and female subjects 20 years and older

          -  Confirmed pathologic diagnosis of a solid tumor not curable with currently available
             therapies, for which neratinib plus capecitabine is a reasonable treatment option.

          -  At least 1 measurable lesion as defined by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid
             Tumors (RECIST) criteria (Please note: ascites, pleural or pericardial effusion,
             osteoblastic bone metastases, and carcinomatous lymphangitis of the lung will not be
             considered measurable lesions).

          -  Subjects with skin lesions that are measurable by computed tomography (CT) scans or
             magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) as the only site of measurable disease are allowed.

          -  Recovery from all clinically significant adverse events (AEs) related to prior
             therapies (excluding alopecia).

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) within institutional range of normal as
             measured by multi-gated acquisition (MUGA) or echocardiogram (ECHO).

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 2 (not declining
             within 2 weeks before signing the informed consent form [ICF]).

        Screening lab values within the following parameters: Absolute neutrophil count (ANC):
        1.5×109/L (1500/mm3) Platelet count: 100×109/L (100,000/mm3) Hemoglobin: 9.0 g/dL (90 g/L)
        Serum creatinine: 01.5×upper limit of normal (ULN) Total bilirubin: 1.5×ULN (&lt;3 ULN if
        Gilbert's disease) Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT):
        2.5×ULN (=5×ULN if liver metastases are present)

          -  For women of childbearing potential, a negative urine or serum pregnancy test result
             before study entry.

          -  All subjects who are biologically capable of having children must agree and commit to
             the use of a reliable method of birth control for the duration of the study and for 28
             days after the last dose of investigational product. A subject is biologically capable
             of having children if he or she is using contraceptives or if his or her sexual
             partner is sterile or using contraceptives.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior treatment with anthracyclines with a cumulative dose of doxorubicin &gt;400 mg/m²,
             or of epirubicin &gt;800 mg/m², or the equivalent dose for other anthracyclines or
             derivatives.

          -  Major surgery, chemotherapy, radiotherapy, any investigational agents, or other cancer
             therapy within at least 2 weeks before administration of the first dose of
             investigational product.

          -  Bone as the ONLY site of disease .

          -  Active central nervous system (CNS) metastases, as indicated by clinical symptoms,
             cerebral edema, and/or progressive growth (subjects with a history of CNS metastases
             or cord compression are permitted if they have been definitively treated and are off
             anticonvulsants and steroids for at least 4 weeks before cycle 1 day 1).

        QT (corrected QT (QTc)) interval &gt;0.47seconds or a known history of QTc prolongation or
        torsades de pointes.

          -  Presence of clinically significant or uncontrolled cardiac disease, including
             congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association [NYHA] functional classification
             of 02), angina requiring treatment, myocardial infarction within the past 12 months,
             or any clinically significant supraventricular arrhythmia or ventricular arrhythmia
             requiring treatment or intervention.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women.

          -  Significant chronic or recent acute gastrointestinal disorder with diarrhea as a major
             symptom (eg, Crohn's disease, malabsorption, or grade 2 or higher diarrhea of any
             etiology at baseline).

          -  Inability or unwillingness to swallow tablets (neratinib and capecitabine).

          -  Subjects with active or uncontrolled renal insufficiency, in whom medication dose
             adjustments are indicated.

          -  Subject known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositive and/or have acute
             or chronic hepatitis B infection (hepatitis B surface antigen [HBsAg] positive) or
             hepatitis C infection (anti-HCV positive).

          -  Known history of hypersensitivity to capecitabine or any of it components, including
             5-FU.

          -  Any other cancer within 5 years prior to screening with the exception of contralateral
             breast carcinoma, adequately treated cervical carcinoma in situ, or adequately treated
             basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin.

          -  Clinically significant ongoing or recent infection within 2 weeks before
             administration of the first dose of investigational product.

          -  Evidence of significant medical illness or abnormal laboratory findings that in the
             investigator's judgment will substantially increase the risk associated with the
             subject's participation in and completion of the study, or preclude the evaluation of
             the subject's response. Examples include, but are not limited to, serious active
             infection, (ie, requiring intravenous antibiotic or antiviral agent) or uncontrolled
             major seizure disorder, significant pulmonary disorder (eg, interstitial pneumonitis,
             pulmonary hypertension), or psychiatric disorder that would interfere with subject
             safety or informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Puma</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Biotechnology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shizuoka</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 24, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 14, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neratinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Capecitabine</keyword>
  <keyword>Combination</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid Tumor</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Capecitabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>August 10, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>February 15, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>April 24, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

