<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01122745</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-243-B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01122745</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single Shot vs Continuous Interscalene Block for Rotator Cuff Repair</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Pain Relief After Single Shot Interscalene Block With Continuous Interscalene Block for Arthroscopic Rotator Cuff Shoulder Surgery: A Randomized Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. Rotator cuff have painful post surgery recovery.

        2. Single shot interscalene with oral analgesics may or may not be enough

        3. Continuous nerve block may be too much for the surgery

        4. The idea is to compare two techniques to see if the two techniques can improve patient
           pain control and satisfaction.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      After consent patients will be randomized to one of the two groups: Control Group or the
      Experimental Group. Patients will be blinded to the group assignment.

      In the Control Group the patient will be given single shot interscalene block using
      ultrasound technique following established guidelines. The procedure will be done after
      starting intravenous access and placing standard anesthesia monitors (EKG, Blood Pressure
      Cuff and Pulse-Ox) on the patient. Following accepted aseptic guidelines the nerves will be
      visualized at the base of the neck using ultrasound machine. Once proper nerve roots or
      trunks visualized 3 mg/kg of 0.5 % bupivacaine will be injected in small blouses.

      In the Experimental Group, after placement of monitors, the nerves will be visualized using
      ultrasound machine. There after a catheter will be placed. They subjects will be dosed using
      0.5% bupivacaine 3 mg/kg for the surgery via the catheter.

      The extent of block before the surgery will be evaluated at 30 minutes post injection.
      Surgery will be done with sedation. Conversion of anesthetic technique to general anesthesia
      will be considered failure of the technique to provide adequate surgical anesthesia.

      At the end of the case the patient will be taken to recovery and will be evaluated for pain.
      If patient is having pain of 3 or more then they will be treated as follows.

      In single shot group will be offered to be blocked again or treated with oral narcotics.

      In the catheter group patient will be dosed with 10 ml 1% lidocaine. If it fails to provide
      any relief then the catheter will be pulled back and another 10 ml1% lidocaine will be given.
      If still not effective then it will be replaced. Refusal of patient to replace the catheter
      will result in patient dropping out of the study.

      Working catheter will be left in place for at least 48 hrs. Patients will be allowed to take
      oral pain medicines as prescribed by their surgeons. The patient will be sent home with pain
      pump to continuously give them 0.125% bupivacaine at 5 ml per hr with an option to get extra
      dose of 5 ml q hr if needed. The pain control will be monitored by phone daily till catheter
      comes out.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pain relief</measure>
    <time_frame>2-3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Patients having rotator cuff repair surgery will be randomized to either single shot or continuous catheter group. Pain score will be followed for 2 days to see which group gets better pain relief.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">88</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Rotator Cuff</condition>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Catheter Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patient will have continuous interscalene block for pain relief placed preoperatively. They will go home with the portable pump. Pain score will be tracked via phone and compared with the control or single short group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single shot group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patient will have single shot interscalene block and will go home. Pain will be tracked using phone. Pain will be compared with the catheter group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All pateint undergoing arthroscopic rotator cuff surgrey and agreed to have regional block
        for pain control
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adult

          -  rotator cuff surgery

          -  agreeing to regional block for pain control

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnancy

          -  neuropathy

          -  any allergies to local anesthetics

          -  any contraindication to nerve blocks
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 11, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 12, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 13, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 29, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 29, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 30, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>continuous block</keyword>
  <keyword>single shot</keyword>
  <keyword>interscalene</keyword>
  <keyword>rotator cuff surgery</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

