<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01128777</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34MH082164</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R34MH082164</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01128777</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Teens Coping With Parental Military Deployment</brief_title>
  <acronym>Helping Hand</acronym>
  <official_title>Mental Health Intervention for Teens Coping With Parental Military Deployment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brown University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brown University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The total number of military personnel is over 3.5 million and approximately 43% have
      children. The deployment cycle can be associated with depression, anxiety, and behavior
      problems in children as well as psychological distress in the military spouse. Further, the
      health of family members can affect the physical and psychological functioning of the
      military service member during the deployment and re-integration periods. While research and
      federal funding has been dedicated toward developing treatments for the returning service
      member, intervention protocols for mental health problems in the children of military
      families have not been tested. In collaboration with the Family Readiness Program of the
      Rhode Island National Guard &amp; Reserves, the purpose of this proposal is to develop a
      cognitive behavioral treatment protocol for adolescents experiencing depression, anxiety,
      and/or behavior problems associated with the deployment and re-integration phases of the
      military deployment cycle. This protocol will be created by modifying an NIH funded cognitive
      behavioral protocol for the treatment of adolescent mental health problems with initial
      demonstrated efficacy (PI, C. Esposito-Smythers). There are three primary aims in this
      project: 1) develop the manualized intervention protocol for adolescents experiencing mental
      health problems associated with the deployment cycle; 2) refine and pilot the intervention
      protocol with 12 families; and 3) test the intervention in a randomized pilot trial. To
      accomplish these aims, a two step sequence of treatment development is proposed. Stage Ia
      includes initial manual development, focus groups, therapist training, and an open pilot
      trial. Stage Ib includes a randomized pilot trial. Seventy-two adolescents and their
      caretakers will be enrolled through the Rhode Island Family Readiness program and randomly
      assigned to the experimental intervention or non-directive supportive therapy for their
      outpatient care. The experimental intervention includes 12 adolescent group sessions which
      address depression, anxiety, and behavior problems associated with the deployment cycle and
      12 parent group sessions that address stress management and parenting skills. The
      non-directive supportive therapy condition includes 12 adolescent and 12 parent group
      sessions which involve patient initiated discussions focused on issues surrounding military
      deployment and re-integration. Outcome will be assessed at post-treatment and 3 month
      follow-up. The long term objective of this research is to yield an effective outpatient
      intervention for teens of military service members experiencing mental health problems
      associated with the deployment and re-integration phases of the deployment cycle.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Terminated due to difficuly recruiting participants
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Depressed mood</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, posttreatment, 3 month follow-up</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavior problems</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, posttreatment, 3 month follow-up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Emotional Distress</condition>
  <condition>Behavior Problems</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive behavioral group therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cognitive behavioral group therapy for adolescents and a parallel group for parents</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nondirective supportive group therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nondirective supportive group therapy for adolescents and a parallel group for parents</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavioral Group Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The CBT group therapy protocol will teach adolescents coping, cognitive restructuring, and affect regulation skills to remediate skills deficits that underlie depression, anxiety, and behavior problems associated with the deployment cycle. Parents will also learn stress management and parenting skills in their own group therapy sessions that occur as the same time as the adolescent group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive behavioral group therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nondirective supportive group therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient initiated discussions form the basis for the intervention for both the adolescent group and the parent group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nondirective supportive group therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Adolescents must: 1) be 13-17 years old; 2) be English speaking; 3) provide adolescent
        assent; 4) have parental consent and a parent/legal guardian available to participate in
        the intervention protocol; 5) have a parent who is deployed or returned from a deployment
        within the last year; and 6) report current sub-clinical or clinical levels of depression,
        anxiety, or oppositional behavior. In order to meet the symptom criterion, adolescents must
        receive a T score of ≥ 65 on the affective problems, anxiety problems, and/or oppositional
        defiant problems on the Youth Self-Report or the Child Behavior Checklist.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Adolescents who : 1) are developmentally delayed such that the intervention materials will
        not be appropriate; 2) are actively suicidal or psychotic at intake; 3) are receiving
        pharmacotherapy or psychotherapy in the community for depression, anxiety, or disruptive
        behavior which are the primary targets of this intervention; or 4) meet current criteria
        for a DSM-IV diagnosis of bipolar disorder, conduct disorder, substance dependence, or
        obsessive-compulsive disorder.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anthony Spirito, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brown University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brown Univerity</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 21, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 24, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 3, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 3, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anthony Spirito</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>family conflict</keyword>
  <keyword>behavior problems</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Problem Behavior</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

