<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01812889</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-0077</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HHSN272200800024C</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>TOL-463</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01812889</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Intravaginal Gel and Ovule Formulations of TOL-463</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Two Part Randomized, Open-Label Phase I Safety and Pharmacokinetic Evaluation of Gel and Ovule Formulations of TOL-463 (Intravaginal Therapy) in 18-45 Year Old Healthy Female Subjects and Women With Vaginitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety, local tolerability and pharmacokinetic
      parameters of TOL-463 intravaginal dosage forms in both healthy, nonpregnant females
      following single dose administration (Part 1), and in nonpregnant women with vaginitis
      following multi-dose administration (Part 2).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety, local tolerability and pharmacokinetic
      parameters of TOL-463 intravaginal dosage forms in both healthy, nonpregnant females
      following single dose administration (Part 1), and in nonpregnant women with vaginitis
      following multi-dose administration (Part 2).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The local (vulvovaginal) and systemic safety and tolerability of TOL-463 gel and ovules following a single intravaginal administration in healthy female subjects and following daily dosing for 7 days in women with BV or VVC will be assessed.</measure>
    <time_frame>Following daily dosing for 1 or 7 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (AEs) will be monitored throughout the course of the study following administration of Investigational Product (IP).</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 16</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Standard PK parameters (half-life, Cmax, Tmax and AUC), will be assessed following single-dose administration of TOL-463 gel and ovule in healthy subjects and after single- and multiple-dose administration of TOL-463 gel or ovules in women with BV or VVC</measure>
    <time_frame>Once daily for 1 or 7 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Vaginal Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 women diagnosed with BV, 10 diagnosed with VVC will be randomized to receive either TOL-463 gel or TOL-463 ovules administered intravaginally once daily for 7 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 Healthy women randomized, two-way crossover design will receive a single dose of TOL-463 gel and ovule intravaginally, separated by a minimum of 7 day washout period between administrations</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TOL-463 Vaginal ovule</intervention_name>
    <description>TOL-463 Vaginal Ovule</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TOL-463 Vaginal gel</intervention_name>
    <description>TOL-463 Vaginal Gel</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult women of any race between 18 to 45 years of age (inclusive).

          -  Subjects must be able to give voluntary written informed consent before any study
             related procedure is performed.

          -  Subjects must have a negative serum pregnancy test at Screening and negative urine
             pregnancy test at all other clinical site visits, as applicable.

          -  Subjects either have no childbearing potential (as defined below) (Note 1) or agree to
             avoid becoming pregnant from the day of screening through one month after the last
             study Day using one of the following acceptable methods of birth control (Note 2) in
             addition to the use of non-lubricated condoms by the male partner (even if
             vasectomized).

               -  Hormonal contraceptives

               -  Abstinence

               -  Note 1: Non-childbearing potential is defined as being post-menopausal for at
                  least 2 years, status after bilateral tubal ligation for at least 1 year, status
                  after bilateral oophorectomy or status after hysterectomy.

               -  Note 2: Intravaginal or intra-uterine contraceptives and contraceptive devices
                  (IUDs) are not acceptable forms of birth control for this study.

          -  Subjects must agree to refrain from douching or using any intravaginal products (i.e.,
             contraceptive creams, gels, foams, sponges, lubricants, etc.) or IUDs during the study
             period.

          -  Subjects must agree not to donate blood during the study and up to 14 days after the
             end of the study.

          -  Subjects willing and able to comply with all study requirements.

        For Part 1 Only

          -  Subjects must be healthy as determined by medical history, physical examination, vital
             signs, pelvic examination and laboratory evaluations (hematology, clinical chemistry
             and urinalysis tests) within study-defined ranges at Screening.

          -  Subjects must be without current symptomatic or asymptomatic bacterial vaginosis,
             candida vulvovaginitis or any other form of vaginitis by clinical and microbiologic
             testing.

          -  Subjects must be willing to abstain from sexual intercourse for 24 hours prior to each
             site visit.

        For Part 2 Only

          -  Subjects with vaginitis must be otherwise healthy based on medical history, physical
             examination, vital signs, pelvic examination and laboratory evaluations (hematology,
             clinical chemistry and urinalysis tests) within study-defined ranges at Screening.

          -  Subjects with vaginitis must be willing to abstain from sexual intercourse 24 hours
             prior to the first dose of study medication and throughout the last visit of the
             study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A history of clinically significant acute illness (resolved within 4 weeks of
             screening) or any other condition which, in the opinion of the Site Principal
             Investigator (PI), would jeopardize the safety of the subject or impact the validity
             of the study results.

          -  Subjects with intrauterine devices.

          -  Subjects with renal dysfunction (serum creatinine &gt;/= 1.2 mg/dL).

          -  Subjects with underlying metabolic or endocrine dysfunction, such as diabetes
             mellitus, Cushing's disease, Addison's disease, or hypo- or hyperthyroidism.

          -  Subjects who test positive for HIV, hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), or hepatitis
             C antibody.

          -  Subjects who have diseases known to cause immunodeficiency, e.g., AIDS, advanced
             malignancy, anemia or severe vitamin deficiency.

          -  Subjects who test positive for Trichomonas vaginalis, Neisseria gonorrhea, or
             Chlamydia trachomatis at screening.

          -  Subjects with active genital lesions at screening, including syphilitic chancre,
             herpetic lesions, or genital warts (HPV).

          -  Subjects who have had major surgery within 4 weeks of screening.

          -  Subjects with an uncontrolled active illness (e.g., active infection) or fever (oral
             temperature &gt;/=100 degrees F or &gt;/= 37.7 degrees C) at screening.

          -  Subjects with a known sensitivity to any ingredient in TOL-463 vaginal gel or ovule.

          -  With the exception of oral contraceptives, use of a prescription medication, notably
             antimicrobial agents, corticosteroids or other immuno-suppressants, within 14 days
             prior to Day 1 of study treatment, unless in the opinion of the PI, the substance
             would not likely impact the conduct or results of this study.

          -  Subjects with any current unstable medical condition(s) requiring prescription
             medication(s) that would preclude accurate evaluation of subjects or otherwise impact
             the conduct or results of the study.

          -  Subjects who have received an investigational drug in a clinical trial within 30 days
             prior to screening.

          -  Women who are pregnant or breast feeding. Subject has a positive history for alcohol
             abuse or dependence and/or a positive urine screen test for alcohol and drugs of abuse
             [amphetamines, barbiturates, benzodiazepines, cocaine metabolites, marijuana, opiates,
             phencyclidine (PCP)] at screening or at any check-in prior to receiving study drug.

          -  Subjects who have donated blood within the past 30 days prior to Day 1 of treatment
             with study drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Quintiles Phase I Services - Overland Park</name>
      <address>
        <city>Overland Park</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66211-1553</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 14, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 18, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bacterial vaginosis, vulvovaginal candidiasis, TOL-463, intravaginal therapy, vaginitis, women, cross-over</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

