<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01819519</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RFA-DD-12-005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01819519</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial of Behavioral Modification to Prevent Congenital Cytomegalovirus</brief_title>
  <acronym>CDC/CMV</acronym>
  <official_title>Development and Evaluation of a Clinic-Based Screening and Brief Intervention for Changing Behaviors Related to Cytomegalovirus Transmission in Pregnant Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Women and Infants Hospital of Rhode Island</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Women and Infants Hospital of Rhode Island</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to develop a brief screening and behavioral intervention for the
      prevention of congenital cytomegalovirus (CMV) that will both be acceptable to clinic staff
      and feasible to implement as part of routine clinical prenatal care, and to test whether
      behavioral intervention for susceptible pregnant women can lead to a behavioral change that
      is likely to lead to decreased primary CMV infection. The study research assistants will
      enroll pregnant women who are less than 20 weeks' gestation, either English or
      Spanish-speaking and that do not have a primary CMV infection (never been infected or
      previously infected). Enrollment will occur during the woman's prenatal visit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a randomized single-masked clinical trial of behavioral intervention versus
      standard care of pregnant women lacking evidence of acute CMV infection that have consented
      to be screened as part of the Maternal Fetal Medicine Units Network multi-centered randomized
      clinical trial, in which pregnant women are screened with CMV serology for IgM, IgG, and IgG
      avidity.

      Eligible pregnant women will be randomized to one of two treatment groups:

        -  Control Group - no intervention

        -  Intervention Group - brief intervention and educational materials Written informed
           consent will be obtained from patients before they can be screened for the study by CMV
           testing (IgM, IgG, and IgG avidity) as per the protocol for screening in the MFMU study.

      All women presenting for prenatal care no later than 20 weeks gestational age without a known
      multifetal gestation are eligible for CMV screening Those with evidence of primary infection
      will be offered participation in the MFMU randomized trial of CMV hyperimmune globulin to
      prevent congenital infection. Women lacking evidence of acute infection will be eligible for
      randomization into this study. Patients must be randomized no later than 20 weeks gestation.

      If eligible and no more than 20 weeks gestation, the patient will be randomized. If the
      patient is randomized in the control group, she will continue her routine prenatal care
      inclusive of the CDC brochure that she received at the time of her venipuncture for serologic
      screening and assessment of hygiene behaviors. If the patient is randomized into the
      intervention group, we will deliver a face-face educational intervention during her next
      routine prenatal visit. In addition to the intervention, the patient will include educational
      material to take home.

      Both groups will be assessed for performance of hygiene behaviors as a baseline assessment at
      the time of consent. A second assessment will occur at least 12 weeks after enrollment during
      the third trimester between 28-36 weeks of gestation. The follow-up assessment will be
      completed by a different research assistant from the unblinded educator. A Kessler 10 (K10)
      survey will also be completed in addition to the baseline and follow-up assessment.

      The follow-up assessment will take place during the participant's third trimester between
      28-36 weeks of gestation, depending on duration of enrollment and likelihood of early
      delivery. The enrollment duration will vary from approximately 14-20 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hygiene Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed from enrollment (baseline) to 14-20 weeks after enrollment (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is defined as a change in the participant's hygiene behaviors determined by the differences between the baseline and follow-up behavioral assessment compliance scores. Each question in these assessments will be assigned a score from 0-5 (5 = desired preventative behavior).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavior Change based on Serostatus</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed from enrollment (baseline) to 14-20 weeks after enrollment (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Did knowing the serostatus affect hygiene behavior change, as defined by a change in compliance scores between baseline and follow-up visits?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in K10 after Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed from enrollment (baseline) to 14-20 weeks after enrollment (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Was there a change in stress and anxiety (measured by the K10 assessment scores) before and after the intervention?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavior Change based on Socioeconomics</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed from enrollment (baseline) to 14-20 weeks after enrollment (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Was behavior change influenced by socioeconomic status? Behavior change is defined by the difference in compliance scores between baseline and follow-up visits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Racial associations with hygiene behavior change</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed from enrollment (baseline) to 14-20 weeks after enrollment (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Was behavior change influenced by race? Behavior change is defined by the difference in compliance scores between baseline and follow-up visits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavior Change related to Children at home</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed from enrollment (baseline) to 14-20 weeks after enrollment (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Was behavior change influenced by the number of children living at home? Behavior change is defined by the difference in compliance scores between baseline and follow-up visits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavior Change and Occupation Association</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed from enrollment (baseline) to 14-20 weeks after enrollment (follow-up)</time_frame>
    <description>Was behavior change influenced by participants' occupation? Behavior change is defined by the difference in compliance scores between baseline and follow-up visits</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">223</enrollment>
  <condition>Cytomegalovirus Infections</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <condition>Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Prenatal Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive standard prenatal care from the time they are screened for CMV to delivery. This includes a CMV brochure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Educational Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be approached during a routine prenatal visit and will receive a 5-10 minute educational intervention (CMV prevention video, preventive information, weekly text messages/emails as reminders for hygiene behaviors, developmental calendar with hygiene reminders).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Educational Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The patient will told if previously infected or seronegative and what is the risk of the becoming infected. The research assistant will deliver a 5-10 minutes educational intervention, which will consist of a CMV video and some Q&amp;A.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Educational Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women lacking evidence of acute CMV infection is defined as one of the
             following: A negative IgM antibody (&lt;1.00 Index) and negative IgG antibody (&lt;6.0
             AU/ml) or A negative IgM antibody (&lt;1.00 Index) and positive IgG antibody (≥6.0 AU/ml)

          -  Gestational age during CMV screening will be no later than 20 weeks based on clinical
             information and evaluation of the earliest ultrasound.

          -  Enrollment will occur no later than 20 weeks' gestation.

          -  Singleton pregnancy. A twin pregnancy reduced to singleton (either spontaneously or
             therapeutically) before 20 weeks' by project gestational age is acceptable.

          -  English and Spanish-speaking women of any age will be offered enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Planned termination of pregnancy

          -  Women with a previous child with congenital CMV

          -  Intention of leaving the prenatal practice

          -  Known major fetal anomalies or demise

          -  Multiple gestation

          -  Known HIV infection

          -  Primary CMV infection, as determined by a positive IgM antibody, a positive IgG
             antibody and low IgG avidity or positive IgM antibody and negative IgG antibody

          -  An old and a recent CMV infection, as determined by a positive IgM antibody, positive
             IgG antibody and high IgG avidity.

          -  Non-Spanish or English speaking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brenna Anderson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Women &amp; Infants Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Women and Infants Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 21, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 27, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Women and Infants Hospital of Rhode Island</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brenna Hughes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intervention studies</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytomegalovirus Infections</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cytomegalovirus Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

