<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01817998</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-2-2012-048</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01817998</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Atrial Fibrillation (AF) and Physical Exercise</brief_title>
  <acronym>EXAF</acronym>
  <official_title>Role of Physical Exercise in Patients With Atrial Fibrillation.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hvidovre University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sygekassernes Helsefond</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eva og Henry Frænkels Mindefond</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Thorkild Steenbecks Legat</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Toyota-Fonden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Snedkermester Sophus Jacobsen and hustru Astrid Jacobsens Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hvidovre University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background and study concept:

      Atrial fibrillation is the new global epidemic in cardiology. With improved survival from
      other cardiovascular diseases and longer living in general, the incidence and prevalence of
      AF rise dramatically in all developed countries with an estimated life time risk of one in
      four for all people above the age of 40 years. Similarly in Denmark, the prevalence is
      estimated to almost double within 2020. It is a fatal arrhythmia with doubled mortality
      compared to patients with normal sinus rhythm; this primarily caused by an increased risk of
      stroke and heart failure. In particular stroke is a feared complication with a 70% risk of
      fatal outcome or lasting handicaps and immense costs for each patient as well as in terms of
      health costs.

      Moreover, many AF patients experience a variety of symptoms and have markedly reduced quality
      of life. Opposed to heart failure patients and patients who have suffered from a myocardial
      infarction, AF patients are not offered any sort of rehabilitation when diagnosed.

      Pharmacological treatment of the arrhythmia is challenging. Most often, individual and
      careful risk evaluation including ultrasound of the heart is obligatory to choose optimal
      treatment strategy and prophylactic anticoagulation. In case a new anti-arrhythmic drug is
      started to restore and maintain sinus rhythm, hospitalization for at least two days with
      heart rhythm monitoring is required to detect any possible potentially dangerous or even
      fatal arrhythmia as a side effect to the treatment. Additionally, the first new oral
      anti-arrhythmic AF drug introduced for more than twenty-five years proved to be hazardous in
      a high-risk AF population and is now only used with strict precautions.

      To explore the role of alternative treatment strategies and to renew handling of cardiac
      arrhythmia, we have therefore set out to study the role of physical exercise in AF patients.

      Our specific study aims are to examine:

        1. The effect of physical exercise on AF burden

        2. The effect of physical exercise on the risk of cardiovascular hospitalization

      Method:

      Our study is an interventional, randomized exercise study. 60 patients older than 18 years
      with ECG-documented AF will be included if written informed consent is obtained. They will be
      randomized 1:1 to moderate-severe (80-85% of max capacity) or low intensity (50% of max
      capacity) training. Exclusion criteria are language barrier, illness inherent with an
      expected survival shorter than a year, other reasons preventing the patient from training,
      revealed serious cardiac disease during pre-tests, AF ablation within one year, permanent AF.

      Both groups are first participating in a nurse-led educational and care program. The program
      is built on two individual consultations and one team consultation with focus on education in
      AF.

      The patients will be thoroughly examined before randomization and after ended training period
      with special ultrasound of the heart, ECG-monitored test of maximal oxygen uptake on
      ergometer bicycle, 24 hours measurement of blood pressure and pulse, and blood samples. They
      will all be taught to use home ECG recorders, a new handheld device. The patients will send
      ECG's twice daily and if the experience cardiac symptoms for 5 months (during exercise and
      two months after).

      When randomized the patients will be divided in teams of ten and trained on separate teams,
      so the physiotherapist closely can guide the patients in training at the correct intensity
      level.

      Measurements:

      During and after physical exercise the burden of atrial fibrillation is measured by tele-ECG
      i.e. number of ECGs with atrial fibrillation divided by total number of ECGs. ECG reporting
      begins after four weeks of physical exercise and continues 2 months after last training
      session.

      Recording of hospitalization begins after randomization and continues one year after last
      training session. All hospitalizations caused by AF or related to the AF disease (relapse of
      AF, heart failure, stroke, new anti-arrhythmic medication, elective electrical cardioversion,
      complications to anticoagulation, pacemaker implantation) are recorded. Also, total days in
      hospital are registered.

      The AF population is growing on a global scale and the disease attracts immense interest on
      all international cardiology congresses. New knowledge of the effect of training for the
      general population as well as the effect in the setting of established disease could have
      paramount effect for prognosis, quality of life, and health costs as pharmacological
      treatment is AF still holds challenges.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in burden of atrial fibrillation at 12 weeks measured by tele-ECG i.e. number og ECGs with atrial fibrillation divided by total number of ECGs</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-training (baseline) and after 12 weeks of training (primary endpoint)</time_frame>
    <description>Further assessments: 2 months after end of training.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in hospitalization related to atrial fibrillation at one year after end of training measured by number of admissions/contacts registered in the patients records.</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-training (baseline) and one year after end of training (primary endpoint)</time_frame>
    <description>Hospitalization or contact to emergency rooms registered in the patients records caused by atrial fibrillation, heart failure, stroke, atrial fibrillation, ablation, side effects to atrial fibrillation medication, and pacemaker implantation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">76</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Intensity Endurance Physical Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>High Intensity endurance physical exercise, intensity measured on Borg Scale with progression from Borg 10-13 (50% of maximum) to 17-18 (80 % of maximum). One hour of exercise twice weekly for 12 weeks supervised by physiotherapists.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Intensity Endurance Physical Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low Intensity endurance physical exercise, intensity measured on Borg Scale, Borg 10-13 (50% of maximum) with no progression in intensity. One hour of exercise twice weekly for 12 weeks supervised by physiotherapists.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>Comparison of high versus low intensity physical exercise in patients with atrial fibrillation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Intensity Endurance Physical Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low Intensity Endurance Physical Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  paroxysmal or persistent atrial fibrillation documented on ECG

          -  male and female of age 18 and above

          -  written concent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  established permanent atrial fibrillation

          -  language barrier

          -  severe health conditions making physical exercise impossible or life expectancy
             shorter than one year

          -  signs of severe cardiac disease during inclusion tests
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ulrik Dixen, Consultant</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Copenhagen University Hospital, Hvidovre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Cardiology, Copenhagen University Hospital, Hvidovre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hvidovre</city>
        <zip>2650</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 21, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 25, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Copenhagen University Hospital, Hvidovre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ane Katrine Skielboe</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

