<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01819831</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5120263</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01819831</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase II Trial of Preoperative Proton Therapy in Soft-tissue Sarcomas of the Extremities and Body Wall</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of Preoperative Proton Therapy in Soft-tissue Sarcomas of the Extremities and Body Wall</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Loma Linda University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Loma Linda University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      When treated with surgery alone, many soft-tissue sarcomas have a high chance of coming back.
      Radiation therapy is frequently used in addition to surgery to reduce the chances of the
      sarcoma coming back. However, radiation can have long-term side effects on the normal tissues
      surrounding the tumor, leading to problems such as swelling, scarring, and joint stiffness.

      Recently, there have been advances in the way that radiation therapy can be given. Proton
      radiation therapy is one of those advances. With proton radiation, it is possible to give
      radiation over a smaller area surrounding the tumor, resulting in less radiation to the
      surrounding normal tissues.

      The purpose of this study is to determine whether proton radiation decreases the long-term
      side effects of radiation on normal tissues and if smaller proton radiation fields reduce
      local recurrence compared to the larger radiation fields that have been used in prior
      studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Data support preoperative radiotherapy as one of the standard options in the management of
      large or high-grade extremity soft tissue sarcomas (STS). The advantages of preoperative
      radiotherapy are lower doses and smaller radiation volumes; these may be used to effect
      improvement of long-term side effects and extremity function. Another potential advantage is
      assisting surgery through tumor shrinkage and reduction of tumor cell seeding. The
      disadvantage of preoperative radiation is the higher likelihood of postoperative wound
      complications, but in a prospective phase III trial these complications were found to be
      generally temporary and without significant effect on long term function.

      Combined conservative surgery and radiotherapy has shown to achieve excellent local control
      in sarcoma patients following margin-negative surgery, but late radiation morbidity and
      reduced quality of life may result from adjuvant radiation. The dosimetric advantage of
      proton radiotherapy may translate into reduced acute and late effects due to improved
      normal-tissue sparing in the treatment of extremity and truncal STS. However, these potential
      advantages need to be validated in clinical trials. The investigators propose a phase II
      study to evaluate the effect of preoperative proton radiotherapy on the reduction of late
      radiation morbidity, patterns of failure, and impact of late radiation morbidity on general
      quality of life (QOL).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Late radiation toxicities (&gt;grade 2 lymphedema, subcutaneous fibrosis, and joint stiffness)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2 years from the start of radiation treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Grade 3-5 adverse events (CTCAE, v4.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite patterns of failure, including local failure (in-field, marginal, out-of-field), regional failure, distant failure, and death without disease progression</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite measures of local failure, including local-regional failure, distant failure, distant-disease-free survival, disease-free survival, overall survival rates, and second primary tumor</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound complication rates</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Infection, dehiscence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Degree of late radiation morbidity at 2 years with quality of life assessment (FACT-G)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Soft Tissue Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Preoperative proton radiation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive 50 Gray equivalents (GyE) in 25 fractions with proton therapy, followed by surgery 4-8 weeks after completion of radiation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>proton radiation</intervention_name>
    <description>proton radiation: 2 GyE/Day to isocenter, one treatment per day, 5 days per week for 25 treatments (=50 GyE to isocenter/25 fractions)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Preoperative proton radiation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Proton radiotherapy</other_name>
    <other_name>Proton treatment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>surgery (wide local excision; limb preservation surgery)</intervention_name>
    <description>In areas with ample soft tissue that can be removed without compromising future function or wound closure, wide margins is the goal of treatment; associated rates of local failure are low in such instances. Margins will be determined by the surgeon; the goal is to achieve at least a 2 mm negative margin resection. However, smaller margins can be acceptable if it allows for limb-sparing surgery with conserved functional outcomes. Every effort will be made to have limb preservation surgery unless there is documented evidence of tumor progression during or after the course of radiation that would require amputation for an appropriate margin resection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Preoperative proton radiation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>wide local excision</other_name>
    <other_name>limb preservation surgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically proven primary soft tissue sarcoma of the upper extremity (including
             shoulder), lower extremity (including hip) or body trunk (excluding retroperitoneum).

          -  No clinical evidence of distant metastatic disease

          -  Evaluation by surgeon, with documentation that the tumor is resectable

          -  ECOG performance status 0-1

          -  For females of childbearing potential, a serum pregnancy test within 4 weeks prior to
             registration

          -  Patient must practice adequate contraception

          -  Adequate bone marrow function

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with sarcoma of the head, neck, intra-abdominal or retroperitoneal region,
             hand or foot

          -  Histopathology demonstrating rhabdomyosarcoma, extraosseous primitive neuroectodermal
             tumor (PNET), soft tissue Ewing's sarcoma, osteosarcoma, Kaposi's sarcoma,
             angiosarcoma, aggressive fibromatosis, dermatofibrosarcoma protuberans or
             chondrosarcoma

          -  Clinical evidence of regional lymph node or distant metastatic disease

          -  Prior invasive malignancy (except non-melanomatous skin cancer or early stage prostate
             cancer) unless disease free for a minimum of 3 years

          -  Prior radiotherapy to the potential target anatomic region would result in overlap of
             radiation fields for current sarcoma

          -  Pregnancy or women of childbearing potential and men who are sexually active and not
             willing/able to used medically acceptable forms of contraception
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>98 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary Yang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>gyang@llu.edu</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bernadette Bautista, RN</last_name>
    <phone>800-496-4966 or 909-558-4000</phone>
    <phone_ext>88213</phone_ext>
    <email>bbautista@llu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gary Yang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>Back-up: Sandi Teichman, RN</phone>
    <phone_ext>909-558-8231</phone_ext>
    <email>scteichm@llu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Loma Linda University Medical Center / James M. Slater Proton Treatment Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loma Linda</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92354</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gary Y Yang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 25, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 28, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Loma Linda University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gary Yang, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>extremity soft tissue sarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>proton radiation</keyword>
  <keyword>preoperative radiation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

