<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01814111</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-SR-082</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01814111</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Renal Sympathetic Denervation in Patients With Hypertension and Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation</brief_title>
  <acronym>RSDforPAF</acronym>
  <official_title>Safety and Effectiveness Study of Percutaneous Catheter-based Sympathetic Denervation of the Renal Arteries in Patients With Hypertension and Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital with Nanjing Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The First Affiliated Hospital with Nanjing Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to demonstrate whether renal sympathetic denervation is safe and
      effective in patients with hypertension and paroxysmal atrial fibrillation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Atrial fibrillation (AF) is one of the most common cardiac arrhythmia, complications of AF
      such as stroke, thromboembolism and heart failure will bring high disable rate and mortality
      , which will be serious influence on people's health and aggrandize medical financial burden,
      however, treatment for AF is not ideal. The affection of traditional antiarrhythmia drugs is
      not enough good, due to extra-heart bad reaction and potential arrhythmogenic substrate
      function restricted; rate control strategy applied quite abroad, however, anticoagulated
      medicine were not applied enough, Radiofrequency catheter ablation of AF has developed
      rapidly in recent years, But it's station is also disputed and its success rate is low and
      recrudescence is very high. meanwhile, serious complications will be caused. So far,
      hypertension is the most risk factor of AF. Long-term hypertension will change left-ventricle
      structure, through variability of pressure loading and capacity loading, damage diastolic
      function of left-ventricle. Increase of diastolic pressure in left-ventricle and atrial
      pressure will gradually result in atrial enlargement and fibrosis, so it will cause atrial
      fibrillation, repeating paroxysm or slow maintaining. Investigation indicated
      anti-hypertension therapy can decrease occurrence ratio and reoccurrence ratio of AF.
      Recently, many clinical researches have verified that renal sympathetic denervation acquired
      exact and sustained hypotension effect, In addition, Renal sympathetic denervation can reduce
      left ventricular hypertrophy, improve glucose metabolization and obstructive sleep,
      meanwhile, it reduce the level of nonepinephrine for both partial and whole-body. While left
      ventricle hypertrophy, left atrium enlarge，epinephrine over release itself and breath sleep
      obstacle are the independent dangerous factors of emerging AF. So ,we design this randomized
      parallel control multi center clinical study to demonstrate that renal sympathetic
      denervation is a safe and effective treatment for patients with hypertension and paroxysmal
      atrial fibrillation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in atrial fibrillation burden</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint of this study is the Change in atrial fibrillation burden, atrial fibrillation burden was calculated as the median number of minutes in AF over a 24-hour period for each Holter recording</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>change in Office systolic and diastolic blood pressure,</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac function and structure</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>measure left ventricular ejection fractionleft，left ventricular end diastolic diameter, ventricular septal thickness, left atrium diameter by echocardiographic</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>heart-rate-variability</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>heart-rate-variability by Holter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pulse wave velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>life quality on SF-36 Health Survey Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood biochemical examination Blood biochemical examination Blood biochemical examination</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>include Fasting blood glucose, Glycated hemoglobin，Urinary protein</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>renal sympathetic denervation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Perform renal angiogram immediately prior to renal sympathetic denervation procedure to confirm anatomic eligibility，The treatment catheter was introduced into each renal artery using a guiding catheter. Up to six ablations at 10 W for 1 min each were performed in both renal arteries. Treatments were delivered from the first distal main renal artery bifurcation to the ostium proximally and were spaced longitudinally and rotationally under fluoroscopic guidance. Catheter tip impedance and temperature were constantly monitored, and radio frequency energy delivery was regulated according to a predetermined algorithm. Visceral pain at the time of energy delivery was managed with intravenous analgetics and sedatives.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>All the patients in this group will take their baseline antihypertensive medication at the original doses, without any changes except when medically required. AAD treatment is consistent in both arms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>renal sympathetic denervation</intervention_name>
    <description>The ablation catheter was maneuvered within the renal artery to allow energy delivery in a circumferential, longitudinally staggered manner to minimize the chance of renal artery stenosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>renal sympathetic denervation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Individual is ≥ 18 and ≤ 75 years of age.

          2. More than half a year for definite hypertension.

          3. AF is a common superventricular arrhythmia that is characterized by chaotic
             contraction of the atrium. An electrocardiogram (EGG) recording is necessary to
             diagnose AF. At least 30 seconds on a rhythm strip in an EGG record and at least 1 AF
             outbreak which was recorded by EGG and Holter in half a year.

          4. Paroxysmal AF Individual ,Paroxysmal AF is defined as recurrent AF (≧2 episodes) that
             terminates spontaneously within 7 days. Episodes of AF of ≤ 48 hours' duration that
             are terminated with electrical or pharmacologic cardioversion should also be
             classified as paroxysmal AF episodes.

          5. Individual eligible conditions through renal artery CTA inspection, such as undoubled
             renal artery on one side, renal artery length≧2cm, diameter≧4mm, and distortion at
             incept sect.

          6. Agree to attend clinic experiment and sign written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Persistent AF Individual, Persistent AF is defined as continuous AF that is sustained
             beyond seven days. Episodes of AF in which a decision is made to electrically or
             pharmacologically cardiovert the patient after _≧48 hours of AF, but prior to 7 days,
             should also be classified as persistent AF episodes.

          2. Individual with Severely enlarged left atria≥ 55 mm

          3. Individual who reversibility mostly generated AF, such as abnormal hypothyroid or
             structural heart diseases

          4. Individual has experienced renal artery stenosis ，or A history of prior renal artery
             intervention including balloon angioplasty or stenting. or ineligible conditions
             through renal artery CTA inspection, such as double renal artery on one side, renal
             artery length≤2cm, diameter≤4mm, and distortion at incept sect.

          5. Individual has experienced a definite acute coronary syndrome in recent 3 months, or a
             cerebrovascular accident and alimentary canal bleeding within 3 months

          6. Individual has experienced sick sinus syndrome

          7. Pregnant Women or planning to be Pregnant Women, psychopathy Individual, individual
             who is sensitive to visualization, individual who can not cooperate with follow-up
             visit, or individual who researcher think it unsuitable to be included in this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>qijun shan, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital with Nanjing Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>First Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanjing</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>210000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>qijun shan, professor</last_name>
      <phone>0086 025 68136407</phone>
      <email>qjshan@njmu.edu.cn</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>qijun shan, professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 13, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 15, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 15, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 15, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital with Nanjing Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Qijun Shan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor，protomedicus and tutor for doctor in cardiovascular department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Atrial Fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>Arrhythmias, Cardiac</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular Diseases</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

